<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - Job</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <editor role="editor">Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor role="editor">
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                  <!-- <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>-->
             <refState unit="chapter"/><refState unit="verse"/></refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>14-Oct-99</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <resp>markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial markup from flat ASCII text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>5/27/09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>RS</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: world.english.xml,v $
			Revision 1.2  2010-06-29 22:00:29  student
			fixing place tags - AD

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:10:56  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.3  2009/05/27 16:11:31  rsingh04
			added/fixed cvs log keyword
                </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="Job" type="book">
                <head>Job</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        There was a man in the land of Uz, whose name was Job. That
man was blameless and upright, and one who feared God, and turned away
from evil.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        There were born to him seven sons and three daughters.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        His possessions also were seven thousand sheep, three thousand
camels, five hundred yoke of oxen, five hundred she-donkeys, and a very
great household; so that this man was the greatest of all the children
of the east.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        His sons went and held a feast in the house of each
one on his birthday; and they sent and called for their three sisters
to eat and to drink with them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        It was so, when the days of their
feasting had run their course, that Job sent and sanctified them, and
rose up early in the morning, and offered burnt offerings according to
the number of them all. For Job said, "It may be that my sons have
sinned, and renounced God in their hearts." Thus did Job continually.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Now it happened on the day when the sons of God came to
present themselves before Yahweh, that Satan also came among them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Yahweh said to Satan, "Where have you come from?"

   Then Satan answered Yahweh, and said, "From going back and forth in
the earth, and from walking up and down in it."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Yahweh said to Satan, "Have you considered my servant, Job?
For there is none like him in the earth, a blameless and an upright
man, one who fears God, and turns away from evil."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Then Satan answered Yahweh, and said, "Does Job fear God for
nothing?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Haven't you made a hedge around him, and around his
house, and around all that he has, on every side? You have blessed the
work of his hands, and his substance is increased in the land.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        But put forth your hand now, and touch all that he has, and he will
renounce you to your face."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Yahweh said to Satan, "Behold, all that he has is in your
power. Only on himself don't put forth your hand."

   So Satan went forth from the presence of Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        It fell on a
day when his sons and his daughters were eating and drinking wine in
their eldest brother's house,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        that there came a messenger to
Job, and said, "The oxen were plowing, and the donkeys feeding beside
them,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        and the Sabeans attacked, and took them away. Yes, they
have killed the servants with the edge of the sword, and I alone have
escaped to tell you."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        While he was still speaking, there also came another, and
said, "The fire of God has fallen from the sky, and has burned up the
sheep and the servants, and consumed them, and I alone have escaped to
tell you."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        While he was still speaking, there came also another, and
said, "The Chaldeans made three bands, and swept down on the camels,
and have taken them away, yes, and killed the servants with the edge of
the sword; and I alone have escaped to tell you."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        While he was still speaking, there came also another, and
said, "Your sons and your daughters were eating and drinking wine in
their eldest brother's house,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        and, behold, there came a great
wind from the wilderness, and struck the four corners of the house, and
it fell on the young men, and they are dead. I alone have escaped to
tell you."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Then Job arose, and tore his robe, and shaved his head, and
fell down on the ground, and worshiped.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        He said, "Naked I came
out of my mother's womb, and naked shall I return there. Yahweh gave,
and Yahweh has taken away. Blessed be the name of Yahweh."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        In
all this, Job did not sin, nor charge God with wrongdoing.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Again it happened on the day when the sons of God came to
present themselves before Yahweh, that Satan came also among them to
present himself before Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Yahweh said to Satan, "Where have
you come from?"

   Satan answered Yahweh, and said, "From going back and forth in the
earth, and from walking up and down in it."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Yahweh said to Satan, "Have you considered my servant Job? For
there is none like him in the earth, a blameless and an upright man,
one who fears God, and turns away from evil. He still maintains his
integrity, although you incited me against him, to ruin him without
cause."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Satan answered Yahweh, and said, "Skin for skin. Yes, all that
a man has will he give for his life.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        But put forth your hand now,
and touch his bone and his flesh, and he will renounce you to your
face."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Yahweh said to Satan, "Behold, he is in your hand. Only spare
his life."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        So Satan went forth from the presence of Yahweh, and struck
Job with painful sores from the sole of his foot to his head.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        He
took for himself a potsherd to scrape himself with, and he sat among
the ashes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Then his wife said to him, "Do you still maintain your
integrity? Renounce God, and die."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        But he said to her, "You speak as one of the foolish women
would speak. What? Shall we receive good at the hand of God, and shall
we not receive evil?"

   In all this Job didn't sin with his lips.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Now when Job's
three friends heard of all this evil that had come on him, they each
came from his own place: Eliphaz the Temanite, Bildad the Shuhite, and
Zophar the Naamathite, and they made an appointment together to come to
sympathize with him and to comfort him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        When they lifted up
their eyes from a distance, and didn't recognize him, they raised their
voices, and wept; and they each tore his robe, and sprinkled dust on
their heads toward the sky.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        So they sat down with him on the
ground seven days and seven nights, and none spoke a word to him, for
they saw that his grief was very great.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        After this Job opened his mouth, and cursed the day of his
birth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Job answered:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        "Let the day perish in which I was born,
   The night which said, 'There is a man-child conceived.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Let that day be darkness;
   Don't let God from above seek for it,
   Neither let the light shine on it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Let darkness and the shadow of death claim it for their own.
   Let a cloud dwell on it.
   Let all that makes black the day terrify it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        As for that night, let thick darkness seize on it.
   Let it not rejoice among the days of the year.
   Let it not come into the number of the months.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Behold, let that night be barren.
   Let no joyful voice come therein.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Let them curse it who curse the day,
   Who are ready to rouse up leviathan.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Let the stars of the twilight of it be dark.
   Let it look for light, but have none,
   Neither let it see the eyelids of the morning,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Because it didn't shut up the doors of my mother's womb,
   Nor did it hide trouble from my eyes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        "Why didn't I die from the womb?
   Why didn't I give up the spirit when my mother bore me?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Why did the knees receive me?
   Or why the breast, that I should suck?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        For now should I have lain down and been quiet.
   I should have slept, then I would have been at rest,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        With kings and counselors of the earth,
   Who built up waste places for themselves;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Or with princes who had gold,
   Who filled their houses with silver:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Or as a hidden untimely birth I had not been,
   As infants who never saw light.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        There the wicked cease from troubling;
   There the weary are at rest.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        There the prisoners are at ease together.
   They don't hear the voice of the taskmaster.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        The small and the great are there.
   The servant is free from his master.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        "Why is light given to him who is in misery,
   Life to the bitter in soul,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Who long for death, but it doesn't come;
   Dig for it more than for hidden treasures,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Who rejoice exceedingly,
   Are glad, when they can find the grave?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        Why is light given to a man whose way is hid,
   Whom God has hedged in?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        For my sighing comes before I eat,
   My groanings are poured out like water.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        For the thing which I fear comes on me,
   That which I am afraid of comes to me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        I am not at ease, neither am I quiet, neither have I rest;
   But trouble comes."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "If someone ventures to talk with you, will you be grieved?
   But who can withhold himself from speaking?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Behold, you have instructed many,
   You have strengthened the weak hands.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Your words have supported him who was falling,
   You have made firm the feeble knees.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        But now it is come to you, and you faint;
   It touches you, and you are troubled.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Isn't your piety your confidence,
   The integrity of your ways your hope?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "Remember, now, whoever perished, being innocent?
   Or where were the upright cut off?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        According to what I have seen, those who plow iniquity,
   And sow trouble,
   Reap the same.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        By the breath of God they perish,
   By the blast of his anger are they consumed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        The roaring of the lion, and the voice of the fierce lion,
   The teeth of the young lions, are broken.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        The old lion perishes for lack of prey,
   The whelps of the lioness are scattered abroad.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        "Now a thing was secretly brought to me,
   My ear received a whisper of it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        In thoughts from the visions of the night,
   When deep sleep falls on men,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Fear came on me, and trembling,
   Which made all my bones shake.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Then a spirit passed before my face;
   The hair of my flesh stood up.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        It stood still, but I couldn't discern the appearance of it;
   A form was before my eyes.
   Silence, then I heard a voice, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        'Shall mortal man be more just than God?
   Shall a man be more pure than his Maker?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Behold, he puts no trust in his servants.
   He charges his angels with error.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        How much more, those who dwell in houses of clay,
   Whose foundation is in the dust,
   Who are crushed before the moth!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Between morning and evening they are destroyed.
   They perish forever without any regarding it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Isn't their tent-cord plucked up within them?
   They die, and that without wisdom.'
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Call now; is there any who will answer you?
   To which of the holy ones will you turn?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        For resentment kills the foolish man,
   And jealousy kills the simple.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        I have seen the foolish taking root,
   But suddenly I cursed his habitation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        His children are far from safety,
   They are crushed in the gate.
   Neither is there any to deliver them,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Whose harvest the hungry eats up,
   And take it even out of the thorns;
   The snare gapes for their substance.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        For affliction doesn't come forth from the dust,
   Neither does trouble spring out of the ground;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        But man is born to trouble,
   As the sparks fly upward.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        "But as for me, I would seek God,
   To God would I commit my cause;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Who does great things that can't be fathomed,
   Marvelous things without number;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Who gives rain on the earth,
   And sends waters on the fields;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        So that he sets up on high those who are low,
   Those who mourn are exalted to safety.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        He frustrates the devices of the crafty,
   So that their hands can't perform their enterprise.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        He takes the wise in their own craftiness;
   The counsel of the cunning is carried headlong.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        They meet with darkness in the day-time,
   And grope at noonday as in the night.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        But he saves from the sword of their mouth,
   Even the needy from the hand of the mighty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        So the poor has hope,
   And injustice shuts her mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        "Behold, happy is the man whom God corrects:
   Therefore do not despise the chastening of the Almighty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        For he wounds, and binds up;
   He injures, and his hands make whole.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        He will deliver you in six troubles;
   Yes, in seven there shall no evil touch you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        In famine he will redeem you from death;
   In war, from the power of the sword.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        You shall be hidden from the scourge of the tongue,
   Neither shall you be afraid of destruction when it comes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        At destruction and famine you shall laugh,
   Neither shall you be afraid of the animals of the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        For you shall be in league with the stones of the field.
   The animals of the field shall be at peace with you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        You shall know that your tent is in peace.
   You shall visit your fold, and shall miss nothing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        You shall know also that your seed shall be great,
   Your offspring as the grass of the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        You shall come to your grave in a full age,
   Like a shock of grain comes in its season.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        Look this, we have searched it, so it is;
   Hear it, and know it for your good."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Oh that my anguish were weighed,
   And all my calamity laid in the balances!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        For now it would be heavier than the sand of the seas,
   Therefore have my words been rash.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        For the arrows of the Almighty are within me,
   My spirit drinks up their poison.
The terrors of God set themselves in array against me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Does the wild donkey bray when he has grass?
Or does the ox low over his fodder?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Can that which has no flavor be eaten without salt?
Or is there any taste in the white of an egg?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        My soul refuses to touch them;
They are as loathsome food to me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        "Oh that I might have my request;
   That God would grant the thing that I long for!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Even that it would please God to crush me;
   That he would let loose his hand, and cut me off!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Be it still my consolation,
   Yes, let me exult in pain that doesn't spare,
   That I have not denied the words of the Holy One.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        What is my strength, that I should wait?
   What is my end, that I should be patient?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Is my strength the strength of stones?
   Or is my flesh of brass?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Isn't it that I have no help in me,
   That wisdom is driven quite from me?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        "To him who is ready to faint, kindness should be shown from his
      friend;
   Even to him who forsakes the fear of the Almighty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        My brothers have dealt deceitfully as a brook,
   As the channel of brooks that pass away;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Which are black by reason of the ice,
   in which the snow hides itself:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        In the dry season, they vanish.
   When it is hot, they are consumed out of their place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        The caravans that travel beside them turn aside;
   They go up into the waste, and perish.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        The caravans of Tema looked,
   The companies of Sheba waited for them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        They were put to shame because they had hoped;
   They came there, and were confounded.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        For now you are nothing.
   You see a terror, and are afraid.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Did I say, 'Give to me?'
   Or, 'Offer a present for me from your substance?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        Or, 'Deliver me from the adversary's hand?'
   Or, 'Redeem me from the hand of the oppressors?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        "Teach me, and I will hold my peace;
   Cause me to understand wherein I have erred.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        How forcible are words of uprightness!
   But your reproof, what does it reprove?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        Do you intend to reprove words,
   Seeing that the speeches of one who is desperate are as wind?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        Yes, you would even cast lots for the fatherless,
   And make merchandise of your friend.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        Now therefore be pleased to look at me,
   For surely I shall not lie to your face.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        Please return. Let there be no injustice;
   Yes, return again, my cause is righteous.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        Is there injustice on my tongue?
   Can't my taste discern mischievous things?
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Isn't a man forced to labor on earth?
   Aren't his days like the days of a hired hand?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        As a servant who earnestly desires the shadow,
   As a hireling who looks for his wages,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        So am I made to possess months of misery,
   Wearisome nights are appointed to me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        When I lie down, I say,
   'When shall I arise, and the night be gone?'
   I toss and turn until the dawning of the day.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        My flesh is clothed with worms and clods of dust.
   My skin closes up, and breaks out afresh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        My days are swifter than a weaver's shuttle,
   And are spent without hope.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Oh remember that my life is a breath.
   My eye shall no more see good.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        The eye of him who sees me shall see me no more.
   Your eyes shall be on me, but I shall not be.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        As the cloud is consumed and vanishes away,
   So he who goes down to Sheol shall come up no more.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        He shall return no more to his house,
   Neither shall his place know him any more.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        "Therefore I will not keep silent.
   I will speak in the anguish of my spirit.
   I will complain in the bitterness of my soul.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Am I a sea, or a sea-monster,
   That you put a guard over me?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        When I say, 'My bed shall comfort me,
   My couch shall ease my complaint;'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Then you scar me with dreams,
   And terrify me through visions:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        So that my soul chooses strangling,
   Death rather than my bones.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        I loathe my life. I don't want to live forever.
   Leave me alone; for my days are but a breath.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        What is man, that you should magnify him,
   That you should set your mind on him,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        That you should visit him every morning,
   And test him every moment?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        How long will you not look away from me,
   Nor leave me alone until I swallow down my spittle?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        If I have sinned, what do I do to you, you watcher of men?
   Why have you set me as a mark for you,
   So that I am a burden to myself?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Why do you not pardon my disobedience, and take away my iniquity?
   For now shall I lie down in the dust.
   You will seek me diligently, but I shall not be."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Bildad the Shuhite answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "How long will you speak these things?
   Shall the words of your mouth be a mighty wind?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Does God pervert justice?
   Or does the Almighty pervert righteousness?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        If your children have sinned against him,
   He has delivered them into the hand of their disobedience;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        If you want to seek God diligently,
   Make your supplication to the Almighty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        If you were pure and upright,
   Surely now he would awaken for you,
And make the habitation of your righteousness prosperous.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Though your beginning was small,
Yet your latter end would greatly increase.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        "Please inquire of past generations,
   Find out about the learning of their fathers.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        (For we are but of yesterday, and know nothing,
   Because our days on earth are a shadow.)
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Shall they not teach you, tell you,
   And utter words out of their heart?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        "Can the papyrus grow up without mire?
   Can the rushes grow without water?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        While it is yet in its greenness, not cut down,
   It withers before any other reed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        So are the paths of all who forget God.
   The hope of the godless man shall perish,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Whose confidence shall break apart,
   Whose trust is a spider's web.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        He shall lean on his house, but it shall not stand.
   He shall cling to it, but it shall not endure.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        He is green before the sun,
   His shoots go forth over his garden.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        His roots are wrapped around the rock pile,
   He sees the place of stones.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        If he is destroyed from his place,
   Then it shall deny him, saying, 'I have not seen you.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Behold, this is the joy of his way:
   Out of the earth shall others spring.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        "Behold, God will not cast away a blameless man,
   Neither will he uphold the evil-doers.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        He will still fill your mouth with laughter,
   Your lips with shouting.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Those who hate you shall be clothed with shame.
   The tent of the wicked shall be no more."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Truly I know that it is so,
   But how can man be just with God?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        If he is pleased to contend with him,
   He can't answer him one time in a thousand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        God who is wise in heart, and mighty in strength:
   Who has hardened himself against him, and prospered?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Who removes the mountains, and they don't know it,
   When he overturns them in his anger
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Who shakes the earth out of its place;
   The pillars of it tremble;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Who commands the sun, and it doesn't rise,
   And seals up the stars;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Who alone stretches out the heavens,
   Treads on the waves of the sea;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Who makes the Bear, Orion, and the Pleiades,
   And the chambers of the south;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Who does great things past finding out,
   Yes, marvelous things without number.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Behold, he goes by me, and I don't see him.
   He passes on also, but I don't perceive him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Behold, he snatches away; who can hinder him?
   Who will ask him, 'What are you doing?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "God will not withdraw his anger;
   The helpers of Rahab stoop under him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        How much less shall I answer him,
   Choose my words to argue with him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Whom, though I were righteous, yet would I not answer.
   I would make supplication to my judge.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        If I had called, and he had answered me,
   Yet would I not believe that he listened to my voice.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        For he breaks me with a tempest,
   Multiplies my wounds without cause.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        He will not allow me to take my breath,
   But fills me with bitterness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        If it is a matter of strength, behold, he is mighty!
   If of justice, 'Who,' says he, 'will summon me?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Though I am righteous, my own mouth shall condemn me.
   Though I am blameless, it shall prove me perverse.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        I am blameless. I don't regard myself.
   I despise my life.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        "It is all the same. Therefore I say,
   He destroys the blameless and the wicked.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        If the scourge kills suddenly,
   He will mock at the trial of the innocent.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        The earth is given into the hand of the wicked.
   He covers the faces of the judges of it.
   If not he, then who is it?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        "Now my days are swifter than a runner.
   They flee away, they see no good,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        They have passed away as the swift ships,
   As the eagle that swoops on the prey.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        If I say, 'I will forget my complaint,
   I will put off my sad face, and cheer up;'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        I am afraid of all my sorrows,
   I know that you will not hold me innocent.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        I shall be condemned;
   Why then do I labor in vain?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        If I wash myself with snow,
   And cleanse my hands with lye,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        Yet you will plunge me in the ditch.
   My own clothes shall abhor me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        For he is not a man, as I am, that I should answer him,
   That we should come together in judgment.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        There is no umpire between us,
   That might lay his hand on us both.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="34"/>
                        Let him take his rod away from me,
   Let his terror not make me afraid:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="35"/>
                        Then I would speak, and not fear him,
   For I am not so in myself.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "My soul is weary of my life;
   I will give free course to my complaint.
   I will speak in the bitterness of my soul.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        I will tell God, 'Do not condemn me,
   Show me why you contend with me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Is it good to you that you should oppress,
   That you should despise the work of your hands,
   And smile on the counsel of the wicked?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Do you have eyes of flesh?
   Or do you see as man sees?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Are your days as the days of mortals,
   Or your years as man's years,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        That you inquire after my iniquity,
   And search after my sin?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Although you know that I am not wicked,
   There is no one who can deliver out of your hand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        'Your hands have framed me and fashioned me altogether;
   Yet you destroy me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Remember, I beg you, that you have fashioned me as clay.
   Will you bring me into dust again?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Haven't you poured me out like milk,
   And curdled me like cheese?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        You have clothed me with skin and flesh,
   And knit me together with bones and sinews.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        You have granted me life and lovingkindness.
   Your visitation has preserved my spirit.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Yet you hid these things in your heart.
   I know that this is with you:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        If I sin, then you mark me.
   You will not acquit me from my iniquity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        If I am wicked, woe to me.
   If I am righteous, I still shall not lift up my head,
   Being filled with disgrace,
   And conscious of my affliction.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        If my head is held high, you hunt me like a lion.
   Again you show yourself powerful to me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        You renew your witnesses against me,
   And increase your indignation on me.
   Changes and warfare are with me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        "'Why, then, have you brought me forth out of the womb?
   I wish I had given up the spirit, and no eye had seen me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        I should have been as though I had not been.
   I should have been carried from the womb to the grave.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Aren't my days few? Cease then,
   Leave me alone, that I may find a little comfort,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Before I go where I shall not return from,
   To the land of darkness and of the shadow of death;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        The land dark as midnight,
   Of the shadow of death, without any order,
   Where the light is as midnight.'"
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Zophar, the Naamathite, answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Shouldn't the multitude of words be answered?
   Should a man full of talk be justified?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Should your boastings make men hold their peace?
   When you mock, shall no man make you ashamed?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        For you say, 'My doctrine is pure,
   I am clean in your eyes.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        But oh that God would speak,
   And open his lips against you,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        That he would show you the secrets of wisdom!
   For true wisdom has two sides.
   Know therefore that God exacts of you less than your iniquity
      deserves.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "Can you fathom the mystery of God?
   Or can you probe the limits of the Almighty?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        They are high as heaven. What can you do?
   Deeper than Sheol: what can you know?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        The measure of it is longer than the earth,
   And broader than the sea.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        If he passes by, or confines,
   Or convenes a court, then who can oppose him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        For he knows false men.
   He sees iniquity also, even though he doesn't consider it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        But vain man can become wise
   If a man can be born as a wild donkey's colt.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "If you set your heart aright,
   Stretch out your hands toward him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        If iniquity is in your hand, put it far away,
   Don't let unrighteousness dwell in your tents.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Surely then shall you lift up your face without spot;
   Yes, you shall be steadfast, and shall not fear:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        For you shall forget your misery;
   You shall remember it as waters that are passed away,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Life shall be clearer than the noonday;
   Though there is darkness, it shall be as the morning.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        You shall be secure, because there is hope;
   Yes, you shall search, and shall take your rest in safety.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Also you shall lie down, and none shall make you afraid;
   Yes, many shall court your favor.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        But the eyes of the wicked shall fail,
   They shall have no way to flee;
   Their hope shall be the giving up of the spirit."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "No doubt, but you are the people,
   And wisdom shall die with you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        But I have understanding as well as you;
   I am not inferior to you:
   Yes, who doesn't know such things as these?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        I am like one who is a joke to his neighbor,
   I, who called on God, and he answered.
   The just, the blameless man is a joke.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        In the thought of him who is at ease there is contempt for
      misfortune,
   It is ready for them whose foot slips.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        The tents of robbers prosper,
   Those who provoke God are secure;
   Who carry their God in their hands.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "But ask the animals, now, and they shall teach you;
   The birds of the sky, and they shall tell you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Or speak to the earth, and it shall teach you;
   The fish of the sea shall declare to you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Who doesn't know that in all these,
   The hand of Yahweh has done this,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        In whose hand is the life of every living thing,
   The breath of all mankind?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Doesn't the ear try words,
   Even as the palate tastes its food?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        With aged men is wisdom,
   In length of days understanding.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "With God is wisdom and might.
   He has counsel and understanding.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Behold, he breaks down, and it can't be built again;
   He imprisons a man, and there can be no release.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Behold, he withholds the waters, and they dry up;
   Again, he sends them out, and they overturn the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        With him is strength and wisdom;
   The deceived and the deceiver are his.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        He leads counselors away stripped.
   He makes judges fools.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        He loosens the bond of kings,
   He binds their loins with a belt.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        He leads priests away stripped,
   And overthrows the mighty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        He removes the speech of those who are trusted,
   And takes away the understanding of the elders.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        He pours contempt on princes,
   And loosens the belt of the strong.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        He uncovers deep things out of darkness,
   And brings out to light the shadow of death.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        He increases the nations, and he destroys them.
   He enlarges the nations, and he leads them captive.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        He takes away understanding from the chiefs of the people of
      the earth,
   And causes them to wander in a wilderness where there is no way.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        They grope in the dark without light.
   He makes them stagger like a drunken man.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="13" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Behold, my eye has seen all this,
   My ear has heard and understood it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        What you know, I know also.
   I am not inferior to you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        "Surely I would speak to the Almighty.
   I desire to reason with God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        But you are forgers of lies.
   You are all physicians of no value.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Oh that you would be completely silent!
   Then you would be wise.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Hear now my reasoning.
   Listen to the pleadings of my lips.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Will you speak unrighteously for God,
   And talk deceitfully for him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Will you show partiality to him?
   Will you contend for God?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Is it good that he should search you out?
   Or as one deceives a man, will you deceive him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        He will surely reprove you
   If you secretly show partiality.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Shall not his majesty make you afraid,
   And his dread fall on you?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Your memorable sayings are proverbs of ashes,
   Your defenses are defenses of clay.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "Be silent, leave me alone, that I may speak.
   Let come on me what will.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Why should I take my flesh in my teeth,
   And put my life in my hand?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Behold, he will kill me; I have no hope.
   Nevertheless, I will maintain my ways before him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        This also shall be my salvation,
   That a godless man shall not come before him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Hear diligently my speech.
   Let my declaration be in your ears.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        See now, I have set my cause in order.
   I know that I am righteous.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Who is he who will contend with me?
   For then would I hold my peace and give up the spirit.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        "Only don't do two things to me;
   Then I will not hide myself from your face:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Withdraw your hand far from me;
   And don't let your terror make me afraid.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Then call, and I will answer;
   Or let me speak, and you answer me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        How many are my iniquities and sins?
   Make me know my disobedience and my sin.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        Why hide you your face,
   And hold me for your enemy?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        Will you harass a driven leaf?
   Will you pursue the dry stubble?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        For you write bitter things against me,
   And make me inherit the iniquities of my youth:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        You also put my feet in the stocks,
   And mark all my paths.
   You set a bound to the soles of my feet:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        Though I am decaying like a rotten thing,
   Like a garment that is moth-eaten.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="14" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Man, who is born of a woman,
   Is of few days, and full of trouble.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        He comes forth like a flower, and is cut down.
   He also flees like a shadow, and doesn't continue.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Do you open your eyes on such a one,
   And bring me into judgment with you?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean?
   Not one.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Seeing his days are determined,
   The number of his months is with you,
   And you have appointed his bounds that he can't pass;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Look away from him, that he may rest,
   Until he shall accomplish, as a hireling, his day.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "For there is hope for a tree,
   If it is cut down, that it will sprout again,
   That the tender branch of it will not cease.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Though the root of it grows old in the earth,
   And the stock of it dies in the ground;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Yet through the scent of water it will bud,
   And put forth boughs like a plant.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        But man dies, and is laid low.
   Yes, man gives up the spirit, and where is he?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        As the waters fail from the sea,
   And the river wastes and dries up,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        So man lies down and doesn't rise;
   Until the heavens are no more, they shall not awake,
   Nor be roused out of their sleep.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "Oh that you would hide me in Sheol,
   That you would keep me secret, until your wrath is past,
   That you would appoint me a set time, and remember me!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        If a man dies, shall he live again?
   All the days of my warfare would I wait,
   Until my release should come.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        You would call, and I would answer you.
   You would have a desire to the work of your hands.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        But now you number my steps.
   Don't you watch over my sin?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        My disobedience is sealed up in a bag.
   You fasten up my iniquity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        "But the mountain falling comes to nothing;
   The rock is removed out of its place;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        The waters wear the stones;
   The torrents of it wash away the dust of the earth:
   So you destroy the hope of man.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        You forever prevail against him, and he passes;
   You change his face, and send him away.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        His sons come to honor, and he doesn't know it;
   They are brought low, but he doesn't perceive it of them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        But his flesh on him has pain;
   His soul within him mourns."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="15" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Should a wise man answer with vain knowledge,
   And fill himself with the east wind?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Should he reason with unprofitable talk,
   Or with speeches with which he can do no good?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Yes, you do away with fear,
   And hinder devotion before God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        For your iniquity teaches your mouth,
   And you choose the language of the crafty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Your own mouth condemns you, and not I;
   Yes, your own lips testify against you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "Are you the first man who was born?
   Or were you brought forth before the hills?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Have you heard the secret counsel of God?
   Do you limit wisdom to yourself?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        What do you know, that we don't know?
   What do you understand, which is not in us?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        With us are both the gray-headed and the very aged men,
   Much elder than your father.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Are the consolations of God too small for you,
   Even the word that is gentle toward you?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Why does your heart carry you away?
   Why do your eyes flash,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        That you turn your spirit against God,
   And let such words go out of your mouth?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        What is man, that he should be clean?
   He who is born of a woman, that he should be righteous?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Behold, he puts no trust in his holy ones;
   Yes, the heavens are not clean in his sight:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        How much less one who is abominable and corrupt,
   A man who drinks iniquity like water!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        "I will show you, listen to me;
   That which I have seen I will declare:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        (Which wise men have told
   From their fathers, and have not hidden it;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        To whom alone the land was given,
   And no stranger passed among them):
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        The wicked man travails with pain all his days,
   Even the number of years that are laid up for the oppressor.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        A sound of terrors is in his ears;
   In prosperity the destroyer shall come on him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        He doesn't believe that he shall return out of darkness,
   He is waited for by the sword.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        He wanders abroad for bread, saying, 'Where is it?'
   He knows that the day of darkness is ready at his hand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        Distress and anguish make him afraid;
   They prevail against him, as a king ready to the battle.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        Because he has stretched out his hand against God,
   And behaves himself proudly against the Almighty;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        He runs at him with a stiff neck,
   With the thick shields of his bucklers;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        Because he has covered his face with his fatness,
   And gathered fat on his loins.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        He has lived in desolate cities,
   In houses which no one inhabited,
   Which were ready to become heaps.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        He shall not be rich, neither shall his substance continue,
   Neither shall their possessions be extended on the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        He shall not depart out of darkness;
   The flame shall dry up his branches,
   By the breath of God's mouth shall he go away.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        Let him not trust in emptiness, deceiving himself;
   For emptiness shall be his reward.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        It shall be accomplished before his time.
   His branch shall not be green.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        He shall shake off his unripe grape as the vine,
   And shall cast off his flower as the olive tree.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="34"/>
                        For the company of the godless shall be barren,
   And fire shall consume the tents of bribery.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="35"/>
                        They conceive mischief, and bring forth iniquity.
   Their heart prepares deceit."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="16" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "I have heard many such things.
   Miserable comforters are you all!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Shall vain words have an end?
   Or what provokes you that you answer?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        I also could speak as you do.
   If your soul were in my soul's place,
   I could join words together against you,
   And shake my head at you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        But I would strengthen you with my mouth.
   The solace of my lips would relieve you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        "Though I speak, my grief is not subsided.
   Though I forbear, what am I eased?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        But now, God, you have surely worn me out.
   You have made desolate all my company.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        You have shriveled me up. This is a witness against me.
   My leanness rises up against me,
   It testifies to my face.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        He has torn me in his wrath, and persecuted me;
   He has gnashed on me with his teeth:
   My adversary sharpens his eyes on me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        They have gaped on me with their mouth;
   They have struck me on the cheek reproachfully.
   They gather themselves together against me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        God delivers me to the ungodly,
   And casts me into the hands of the wicked.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        I was at ease, and he broke me apart.
   Yes, he has taken me by the neck, and dashed me to pieces.
   He has also set me up for his target.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        His archers surround me.
   He splits my kidneys apart, and does not spare.
   He pours out my gall on the ground.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        He breaks me with breach on breach.
   He runs on me like a giant.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        I have sewed sackcloth on my skin,
   And have thrust my horn in the dust.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        My face is red with weeping.
   Deep darkness is on my eyelids.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Although there is no violence in my hands,
   And my prayer is pure.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        "Earth, don't cover my blood,
   Let my cry have no place to rest.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Even now, behold, my witness is in heaven.
   He who vouches for me is on high.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        My friends scoff at me.
   My eyes pour out tears to God,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        That he would maintain the right of a man with God,
   Of a son of man with his neighbor!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        For when a few years are come,
   I shall go the way from whence I shall not return.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="17" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "My spirit is consumed, my days are extinct,
   And the grave is ready for me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Surely there are mockers with me,
   My eye dwells on their provocation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        "Now give a pledge, be collateral for me with yourself.
   Who is there who will strike hands with me?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        For you have hidden their heart from understanding,
   Therefore shall you not exalt them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        He who denounces his friends for a prey,
   Even the eyes of his children shall fail.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        "But he has made me a byword of the people.
   They spit in my face.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        My eye also is dim by reason of sorrow.
   All my members are as a shadow.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Upright men shall be astonished at this.
   The innocent shall stir up himself against the godless.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Yet shall the righteous hold on his way.
   He who has clean hands shall grow stronger and stronger.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        But as for you all, come on now again;
   I shall not find a wise man among you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        My days are past, my plans are broken off,
   As are the thoughts of my heart.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        They change the night into day,
   Saying 'The light is near' in the presence of darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        If I look for Sheol as my house,
   If I have spread my couch in the darkness,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        If I have said to corruption, 'You are my father;'
   To the worm, 'My mother,' and 'my sister;'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Where then is my hope?
   As for my hope, who shall see it?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Shall it go down with me to the gates of Sheol,
   Or descend together into the dust?"
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="18" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Bildad the Shuhite answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "How long will you hunt for words?
   Consider, and afterwards we will speak.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Why are we counted as animals,
   Which have become unclean in your sight?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        You who tear yourself in your anger,
   Shall the earth be forsaken for you?
   Or shall the rock be removed out of its place?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        "Yes, the light of the wicked shall be put out,
   The spark of his fire shall not shine.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        The light shall be dark in his tent,
   His lamp above him shall be put out.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        The steps of his strength shall be shortened,
   His own counsel shall cast him down.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        For he is cast into a net by his own feet,
   And he wanders into its mesh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        A snare shall take him by the heel;
   A trap shall lay hold on him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        A noose is hidden for him in the ground,
   A trap for him in the way.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Terrors shall make him afraid on every side,
   And shall chase him at his heels.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        His strength shall be famished,
   Calamity shall be ready at his side.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        The members of his body shall be devoured,
   The firstborn of death shall devour his members.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        He shall be rooted out of his tent where he trusts.
   He shall be brought to the king of terrors.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        There shall dwell in his tent that which is none of his.
   Sulfur shall be scattered on his habitation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        His roots shall be dried up beneath,
   Above shall his branch be cut off.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        His memory shall perish from the earth.
   He shall have no name in the street.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        He shall be driven from light into darkness,
   And chased out of the world.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        He shall have neither son nor grandson among his people,
   Nor any remaining where he sojourned.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Those who come after shall be astonished at his day,
   As those who went before were frightened.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Surely such are the dwellings of the unrighteous,
   This is the place of him who doesn't know God."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="19" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "How long will you torment me,
   And crush me with words?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        You have reproached me ten times.
   You aren't ashamed that you attack me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        If it is true that I have erred,
   My error remains with myself.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        If indeed you will magnify yourselves against me,
   And plead against me my reproach;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Know now that God has subverted me,
   And has surrounded me with his net.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "Behold, I cry out of wrong, but I am not heard:
   I cry for help, but there is no justice.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        He has walled up my way so that I can't pass,
   And has set darkness in my paths.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        He has stripped me of my glory,
   And taken the crown from my head.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        He has broken me down on every side, and I am gone.
   My hope he has plucked up like a tree.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        He has also kindled his wrath against me.
   He counts me among his adversaries.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        His troops come on together,
   Build a siege ramp against me,
   And encamp around my tent.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "He has put my brothers far from me.
   My acquaintances are wholly estranged from me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        My relatives have gone away.
   My familiar friends have forgotten me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Those who dwell in my house, and my maids, count me for a
      stranger.
   I am an alien in their sight.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        I call to my servant, and he gives me no answer;
   I beg him with my mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        My breath is offensive to my wife.
   I am loathsome to the children of my own mother.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Even young children despise me.
   If I arise, they speak against me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        All my familiar friends abhor me.
   They whom I loved have turned against me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        My bones stick to my skin and to my flesh.
   I have escaped by the skin of my teeth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        "Have pity on me, have pity on me, you my friends;
   For the hand of God has touched me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Why do you persecute me as God,
   And are not satisfied with my flesh?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        "Oh that my words were now written!
   Oh that they were inscribed in a book!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        That with an iron pen and lead
   They were engraved in the rock forever!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        But as for me, I know that my Redeemer lives.
   In the end, he will stand upon the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        After my skin is destroyed,
   Then in my flesh shall I see God,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        Whom I, even I, shall see on my side.
   My eyes shall see, and not as a stranger.

"My heart is consumed within me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        If you say, 'How we will persecute him!'
   Because the root of the matter is found in me,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        Be afraid of the sword,
   For wrath brings the punishments of the sword,
   That you may know there is a judgment."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="20" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Zophar the Naamathite answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Therefore do my thoughts give answer to me,
   Even by reason of my haste that is in me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        I have heard the reproof which puts me to shame;
   The spirit of my understanding answers me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Don't you know this from old time,
   Since man was placed on earth,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        That the triumphing of the wicked is short,
   The joy of the godless but for a moment?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Though his height mount up to the heavens,
   And his head reach to the clouds,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Yet he shall perish forever like his own dung,
   Those who have seen him shall say, 'Where is he?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        He shall fly away as a dream, and shall not be found:
   Yes, he shall be chased away like a vision of the night.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        The eye which saw him shall see him no more,
   Neither shall his place any more see him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        His children shall seek the favor of the poor.
   His hands shall give back his wealth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        His bones are full of his youth,
   But youth shall lie down with him in the dust.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        "Though wickedness is sweet in his mouth,
   Though he hide it under his tongue,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Though he spare it, and will not let it go,
   But keep it still within his mouth;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Yet his food in his bowels is turned.
   It is cobra venom within him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        He has swallowed down riches, and he shall vomit them up again.
   God will cast them out of his belly.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        He shall suck cobra venom.
   The viper's tongue shall kill him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        He shall not look at the rivers,
   The flowing streams of honey and butter.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        That for which he labored he shall restore, and shall not
      swallow it down;
   According to the substance that he has gotten, he shall not rejoice.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        For he has oppressed and forsaken the poor.
   He has violently taken away a house, and he shall not build it up.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        "Because he knew no quietness within him,
   He shall not save anything of that in which he delights.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        There was nothing left that he didn't devour,
   Therefore his prosperity shall not endure.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        In the fullness of his sufficiency, distress shall overtake him:
   The hand of everyone who is in misery shall come on him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        When he is about to fill his belly, God will cast the
      fierceness of his wrath on him.
   It will rain on him while he is eating.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        He shall flee from the iron weapon.
   The bronze arrow shall strike him through.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        He draws it forth, and it comes out of his body.
   Yes, the glittering point comes out of his liver.
   Terrors are on him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        All darkness is laid up for his treasures.
   An unfanned fire shall devour him.
   It shall consume that which is left in his tent.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        The heavens shall reveal his iniquity,
   The earth shall rise up against him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        The increase of his house shall depart;
   They shall rush away in the day of his wrath.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        This is the portion of a wicked man from God,
   The heritage appointed to him by God."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="21" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Listen diligently to my speech.
   Let this be your consolation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Allow me, and I also will speak;
   After I have spoken, mock on.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        As for me, is my complaint to man?
   Why shouldn't I be impatient?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Look at me, and be astonished.
   Lay your hand on your mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        When I remember, I am troubled.
   Horror takes hold of my flesh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "Why do the wicked live,
   Become old, yes, and grow mighty in power?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Their child is established with them in their sight,
   Their offspring before their eyes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Their houses are safe from fear,
   Neither is the rod of God upon them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Their bulls breed without fail.
   Their cows calve, and don't miscarry.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        They send forth their little ones like a flock.
   Their children dance.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        They sing to the tambourine and harp,
   And rejoice at the sound of the pipe.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        They spend their days in prosperity.
   In an instant they go down to Sheol.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        They tell God, 'Depart from us,
   For we don't want to know about your ways.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        What is the Almighty, that we should serve him?
   What profit should we have, if we pray to him?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Behold, their prosperity is not in their hand:
   The counsel of the wicked is far from me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        "How often is it that the lamp of the wicked is put out?
   That their calamity comes on them?
   That God distributes sorrows in his anger?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        That they are as stubble before the wind,
   As chaff that the storm carries away?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        You say, 'God lays up his iniquity for his children.'
   Let him recompense it to himself, that he may know it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Let his own eyes see his destruction.
   Let him drink of the wrath of the Almighty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        For what does he care for his house after him,
   When the number of his months is cut off?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        "Shall any teach God knowledge,
   Seeing he judges those who are high?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        One dies in his full strength,
   Being wholly at ease and quiet.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        His pails are full of milk.
   The marrow of his bones is moistened.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        Another dies in bitterness of soul,
   And never tastes of good.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        They lie down alike in the dust,
   The worm covers them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        "Behold, I know your thoughts,
   The devices with which you would wrong me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        For you say, 'Where is the house of the prince?
   Where is the tent in which the wicked lived?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        Haven't you asked wayfaring men?
   Don't you know their evidences,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        That the evil man is reserved to the day of calamity?
   That they are led forth to the day of wrath?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        Who shall declare his way to his face?
   Who shall repay him what he has done?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        Yet shall he be borne to the grave,
   Men shall keep watch over the tomb.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        The clods of the valley shall be sweet to him.
   All men shall draw after him,
   As there were innumerable before him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="34"/>
                        So how can you comfort me with nonsense,
   Seeing that in your answers there remains only falsehood?"
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="22" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Eliphaz the Temanite answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Can a man be profitable to God?
   Surely he who is wise is profitable to himself.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Is it any pleasure to the Almighty, that you are righteous?
   Or does it benefit him, that you make your ways perfect?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Is it for your piety that he reproves you,
   That he enters with you into judgment?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Isn't your wickedness great?
   Neither is there any end to your iniquities.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        For you have taken pledges from your brother for nothing,
   And stripped the naked of their clothing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        You haven't given water to the weary to drink,
   And you have withheld bread from the hungry.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        But as for the mighty man, he had the earth.
   The honorable man, he lived in it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        You have sent widows away empty,
   And the arms of the fatherless have been broken.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Therefore snares are round about you.
   Sudden fear troubles you,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Or darkness, so that you can not see,
   And floods of waters cover you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        "Isn't God in the heights of heaven?
   See the height of the stars, how high they are!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        You say, 'What does God know?
   Can he judge through the thick darkness?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Thick clouds are a covering to him, so that he doesn't see.
   He walks on the vault of the sky.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Will you keep the old way
   Which wicked men have trodden,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Who were snatched away before their time,
   Whose foundation was poured out as a stream,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Who said to God, 'Depart from us;'
   And, 'What can the Almighty do for us?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Yet he filled their houses with good things,
   But the counsel of the wicked is far from me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        The righteous see it, and are glad;
   The innocent laugh them to scorn,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Saying, 'Surely those who rose up against us are cut off,
   The fire has consumed the remnant of them.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        "Acquaint yourself with him, now, and be at peace.
   Thereby good shall come to you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Please receive instruction from his mouth,
   And lay up his words in your heart.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        If you return to the Almighty, you shall be built up,
   If you put away unrighteousness far from your tents.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        Lay your treasure in the dust,
   The gold of Ophir among the stones of the brooks.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        The Almighty will be your treasure,
   Precious silver to you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        For then shall you delight yourself in the Almighty,
   And shall lift up your face to God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        You shall make your prayer to him, and he will hear you.
   You shall pay your vows.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        You shall also decree a thing, and it shall be established to
      you.
   Light shall shine on your ways.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        When they cast down, you shall say, 'be lifted up.'
   He will save the humble person.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        He will even deliver him who is not innocent;
   Yes, he shall be delivered through the cleanness of your hands."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="23" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Even today is my complaint rebellious.
   His hand is heavy in spite of my groaning.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Oh that I knew where I might find him!
   That I might come even to his seat!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        I would set my cause in order before him,
   And fill my mouth with arguments.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        I would know the words which he would answer me,
   And understand what he would tell me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Would he contend with me in the greatness of his power?
   No, but he would listen to me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        There the upright might reason with him,
   So I should be delivered forever from my judge.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        "If I go east, he is not there;
   If west, I can't find him;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        He works to the north, but I can't see him;
   He turns south, but I can't catch a glimpse of him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        But he knows the way that I take.
   When he has tried me, I shall come forth like gold.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        My foot has held fast to his steps.
   His way have I kept, and not turned aside.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        I haven't gone back from the commandment of his lips.
   I have treasured up the words of his mouth more than my necessary
      food.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        But he stands alone, and who can oppose him?
   What his soul desires, even that he does.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        For he performs that which is appointed for me.
   Many such things are with him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Therefore I am terrified at his presence.
   When I consider, I am afraid of him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        For God has made my heart faint.
   The Almighty has terrified me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Because I was not cut off before the darkness,
   Neither did he cover the thick darkness from my face.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="24" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Why aren't times laid up by the Almighty?
   Why don't those who know him see his days?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        There are people who remove the landmarks.
   They violently take away flocks, and feed them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        They drive away the donkey of the fatherless,
   And they take the widow's ox for a pledge.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        They turn the needy out of the way.
   The poor of the earth all hide themselves.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Behold, as wild donkeys in the desert,
   They go forth to their work, seeking diligently for food;
The wilderness yields them bread for their children.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        They cut their provender in the field.
They glean the vineyard of the wicked.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        They lie all night naked without clothing,
And have no covering in the cold.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        They are wet with the showers of the mountains,
And embrace the rock for lack of a shelter.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        There are those who pluck the fatherless from the breast,
And take a pledge of the poor,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        So that they go around naked without clothing.
   Being hungry, they carry the sheaves.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        They make oil within the walls of these men.
   They tread wine presses, and suffer thirst.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        From out of the populous city, men groan.
   The soul of the wounded cries out,
   Yet God doesn't regard the folly.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "These are of those who rebel against the light;
   They don't know the ways of it,
   Nor abide in the paths of it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        The murderer rises with the light.
   He kills the poor and needy.
   In the night he is like a thief.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        The eye also of the adulterer waits for the twilight,
   Saying, 'No eye shall see me.'
   He disguises his face.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        In the dark they dig through houses.
   They shut themselves up in the daytime.
   They don't know the light.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        For the morning is to all of them like thick darkness,
   For they know the terrors of the thick darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        "They are foam on the surface of the waters.
   Their portion is cursed in the earth:
   They don't turn into the way of the vineyards.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Drought and heat consume the snow waters;
   So does Sheol those who have sinned.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        The womb shall forget him.
   The worm shall feed sweetly on him.
   He shall be no more remembered.
   Unrighteousness shall be broken as a tree.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        He devours the barren who don't bear.
   He shows no kindness to the widow.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Yet God preserves the mighty by his power.
   He rises up who has no assurance of life.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        God gives them security, and they rest in it.
   His eyes are on their ways.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        They are exalted; yet a little while, and they are gone.
   Yes, they are brought low, they are taken out of the way as all
      others,
   And are cut off as the tops of the ears of grain.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        If it isn't so now, who will prove me a liar,
   And make my speech worth nothing?"
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="25" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Bildad the Shuhite answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Dominion and fear are with him;
   He makes peace in his high places.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Can his armies be counted?
   On whom does his light not arise?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        How then can man be just with God?
   Or how can he who is born of a woman be clean?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Behold, even the moon has no brightness,
   And the stars are not pure in his sight;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        How much less man, who is a worm!
   The son of man, who is a worm!"
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="26" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "How have you helped him who is without power!
   How have you saved the arm that has no strength!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        How have you counseled him who has no wisdom,
   And plentifully declared sound knowledge!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        To whom have you uttered words?
   Whose spirit came forth from you?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        "Those who are deceased tremble,
   Those beneath the waters and all that live in them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Sheol is naked before God,
   And Abaddon has no covering.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        He stretches out the north over empty space,
   And hangs the earth on nothing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        He binds up the waters in his thick clouds,
   And the cloud is not burst under them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        He encloses the face of his throne,
   And spreads his cloud on it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        He has described a boundary on the surface of the waters,
   And to the confines of light and darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        The pillars of heaven tremble
   And are astonished at his rebuke.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        He stirs up the sea with his power,
   And by his understanding he strikes through Rahab.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        By his Spirit the heavens are garnished.
   His hand has pierced the swift serpent.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Behold, these are but the outskirts of his ways.
   How small a whisper do we hear of him!
   But the thunder of his power who can understand?"
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="27" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Job again took up his parable, and said,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "As God lives, who has taken away my right,
   The Almighty, who has made my soul bitter.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        (For the length of my life is still in me,
   And the spirit of God is in my nostrils);
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Surely my lips shall not speak unrighteousness,
   Neither shall my tongue utter deceit.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Far be it from me that I should justify you.
   Until I die I will not put away my integrity from me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        I hold fast to my righteousness, and will not let it go.
   My heart shall not reproach me so long as I live.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "Let my enemy be as the wicked,
   Let him who rises up against me be as the unrighteous.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        For what is the hope of the godless, when he is cut off,
   When God takes away his life?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Will God hear his cry,
   When trouble comes on him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Will he delight himself in the Almighty,
   And call on God at all times?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        I will teach you about the hand of God.
   That which is with the Almighty will I not conceal.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Behold, all of you have seen it yourselves;
   Why then have you become altogether vain?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "This is the portion of a wicked man with God,
   The heritage of oppressors, which they receive from the Almighty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        If his children are multiplied, it is for the sword.
   His offspring shall not be satisfied with bread.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Those who remain of him shall be buried in death.
   His widows shall make no lamentation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Though he heap up silver as the dust,
   And prepare clothing as the clay;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        He may prepare it, but the just shall put it on,
   And the innocent shall divide the silver.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        He builds his house as the moth,
   As a booth which the watchman makes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        He lies down rich, but he shall not do so again.
   He opens his eyes, and he is not.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Terrors overtake him like waters;
   A tempest steals him away in the night.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        The east wind carries him away, and he departs;
   It sweeps him out of his place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        For it hurls at him, and does not spare,
   As he flees away from his hand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        Men shall clap their hands at him,
   And shall hiss him out of his place.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="28" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Surely there is a mine for silver,
   And a place for gold which they refine.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Iron is taken out of the earth,
   And copper is smelted out of the ore.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Man sets an end to darkness,
   And searches out, to the furthest bound,
   The stones of obscurity and of thick darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        He breaks open a shaft away from where people live.
   They are forgotten by the foot.
   They hang far from men, they swing back and forth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        As for the earth, out of it comes bread;
   Underneath it is turned up as it were by fire.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Sapphires come from its rocks.
   It has dust of gold.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        That path no bird of prey knows,
   Neither has the falcon's eye seen it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        The proud animals have not trodden it,
   Nor has the fierce lion passed by there.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        He puts forth his hand on the flinty rock,
   And he overturns the mountains by the roots.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        He cuts out channels among the rocks.
   His eye sees every precious thing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        He binds the streams that they don't trickle;
   The thing that is hidden he brings forth to light.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        "But where shall wisdom be found?
   Where is the place of understanding?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Man doesn't know its price;
   Neither is it found in the land of the living.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        The deep says, 'It isn't in me.'
   The sea says, 'It isn't with me.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        It can't be gotten for gold,
   Neither shall silver be weighed for its price.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        It can't be valued with the gold of Ophir,
   With the precious onyx, or the sapphire.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Gold and glass can't equal it,
   Neither shall it be exchanged for jewels of fine gold.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        No mention shall be made of coral or of crystal:
   Yes, the price of wisdom is above rubies.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        The topaz of Ethiopia shall not equal it,
   Neither shall it be valued with pure gold.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Whence then comes wisdom?
   Where is the place of understanding?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Seeing it is hidden from the eyes of all living,
   And kept close from the birds of the sky.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Destruction and Death say,
   'We have heard a rumor of it with our ears.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        "God understands its way,
   And he knows its place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        For he looks to the ends of the earth,
   And sees under the whole sky.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        He establishes the force of the wind;
   Yes, he measures out the waters by measure.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        When he made a decree for the rain,
   And a way for the lightning of the thunder;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        Then did he see it, and declare it.
   He established it, yes, and searched it out.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        To man he said,
   'Behold, the fear of the Lord, that is wisdom.
   To depart from evil is understanding.'"
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="29" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Job again took up his parable, and said,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Oh that I were as in the months of old,
   As in the days when God watched over me;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        When his lamp shone on my head,
   And by his light I walked through darkness;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        As I was in the ripeness of my days,
   When the friendship of God was in my tent;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        When the Almighty was yet with me,
   And my children were around me;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        When my steps were washed with butter,
   And the rock poured out streams of oil for me!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        When I went forth to the city gate,
   When I prepared my seat in the street,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        The young men saw me and hid themselves,
   The aged rose up and stood;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        The princes refrained from talking,
   And laid their hand on their mouth;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        The voice of the nobles was hushed,
   And their tongue stuck to the roof of their mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        For when the ear heard me, then it blessed me;
   And when the eye saw me, it commended me:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Because I delivered the poor who cried,
   And the fatherless also, who had none to help him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        The blessing of him who was ready to perish came on me,
   And I caused the widow's heart to sing for joy.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        I put on righteousness, and it clothed me.
   My justice was as a robe and a diadem.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        I was eyes to the blind,
   And feet to the lame.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        I was a father to the needy.
   The cause of him who I didn't know, I searched out.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        I broke the jaws of the unrighteous,
   And plucked the prey out of his teeth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Then I said, 'I shall die in my own house,
   I shall number my days as the sand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        My root is spread out to the waters,
   The dew lies all night on my branch;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        My glory is fresh in me,
   My bow is renewed in my hand.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        "Men listened to me, waited,
   And kept silence for my counsel.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        After my words they didn't speak again;
   My speech fell on them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        They waited for me as for the rain.
   Their mouths drank as with the spring rain.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        I smiled on them when they had no confidence.
   They didn't reject the light of my face.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        I chose out their way, and sat as chief.
   I lived as a king in the army,
   As one who comforts the mourners.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="30" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "But now those who are younger than I, have me in derision,
   Whose fathers I would have disdained to put with my sheep dogs.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Of what use is the strength of their hands to me,
   Men in whom ripe age has perished?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        They are gaunt from lack and famine.
   They gnaw the dry ground, in the gloom of waste and desolation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        They pluck salt herbs by the bushes.
   The roots of the broom are their food.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        They are driven forth from the midst of men;
   They cry after them as after a thief;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        So that they dwell in frightful valleys,
   And in holes of the earth and of the rocks.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Among the bushes they bray;
   And under the nettles they are gathered together.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        They are children of fools, yes, children of base men.
   They were flogged out of the land.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        "Now I have become their song.
   Yes, I am a byword to them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        They abhor me, they stand aloof from me,
   And don't hesitate to spit in my face.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        For he has loosed his cord, and afflicted me;
   And they have thrown off restraint before me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        On my right hand rise the rabble.
   They thrust aside my feet,
   They cast up against me their ways of destruction.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        They mar my path,
   They set forward my calamity,
   Without anyone's help.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        As through a wide breach they come,
   In the midst of the ruin they roll themselves in.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Terrors are turned on me.
   They chase my honor as the wind.
   My welfare has passed away as a cloud.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        "Now my soul is poured out within me.
   Days of affliction have taken hold on me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        In the night season my bones are pierced in me,
   And the pains that gnaw me take no rest.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        By great force is my garment disfigured.
   It binds me about as the collar of my coat.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        He has cast me into the mire.
   I have become like dust and ashes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        I cry to you, and you do not answer me.
   I stand up, and you gaze at me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        You have turned to be cruel to me.
   With the might of your hand you persecute me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        You lift me up to the wind, and drive me with it.
   You dissolve me in the storm.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        For I know that you will bring me to death,
   To the house appointed for all living.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        "However doesn't one stretch out a hand in his fall?
   Or in his calamity therefore cry for help?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        Didn't I weep for him who was in trouble?
   Wasn't my soul grieved for the needy?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        When I looked for good, then evil came;
   When I waited for light, there came darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        My heart is troubled, and doesn't rest.
   Days of affliction have come on me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        I go mourning without the sun.
   I stand up in the assembly, and cry for help.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        I am a brother to jackals,
   And a companion to ostriches.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        My skin grows black and peels from me.
   My bones are burned with heat.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        Therefore is my harp turned to mourning,
   And my pipe into the voice of those who weep.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="31" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "I made a covenant with my eyes,
   How then should I look lustfully at a young woman?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        For what is the portion from God above,
   And the heritage from the Almighty on high?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Is it not calamity to the unrighteous,
   And disaster to the workers of iniquity?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Doesn't he see my ways,
   And number all my steps?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        "If I have walked with falsehood,
   And my foot has hurried to deceit
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        (Let me be weighed in an even balance,
   That God may know my integrity);
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        If my step has turned out of the way,
   If my heart walked after my eyes,
   If any defilement has stuck to my hands,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Then let me sow, and let another eat;
   Yes, let the produce of my field be rooted out.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        "If my heart has been enticed to a woman,
   And I have laid wait at my neighbor's door;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Then let my wife grind for another,
   And let others sleep with her.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        For that would be a heinous crime;
   Yes, it would be an iniquity to be punished by the judges:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        For it is a fire that consumes to destruction,
   And would root out all my increase.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "If I have despised the cause of my man-servant
   Or of my maid-servant,
   When they contended with me;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        What then shall I do when God rises up?
   When he visits, what shall I answer him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Didn't he who made me in the womb make him?
   Didn't one fashion us in the womb?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        "If I have withheld the poor from their desire,
   Or have caused the eyes of the widow to fail,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Or have eaten my morsel alone,
   And the fatherless has not eaten of it
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        (No, from my youth he grew up with me as with a father,
   Her have I guided from my mother's womb);
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        If I have seen any perish for want of clothing,
   Or that the needy had no covering;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        If his heart hasn't blessed me,
   If he hasn't been warmed with my sheep's fleece;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        If I have lifted up my hand against the fatherless,
   Because I saw my help in the gate:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Then let my shoulder fall from the shoulder-blade,
   And my arm be broken from the bone.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        For calamity from God is a terror to me,
   By reason of his majesty I can do nothing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        "If I have made gold my hope,
   And have said to the fine gold, 'You are my confidence;'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        If I have rejoiced because my wealth was great,
   And because my hand had gotten much;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        If I have seen the sun when it shined,
   Or the moon moving in splendor,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        And my heart has been secretly enticed,
   My hand threw a kiss from my mouth:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        This also would be an iniquity to be punished by the judges;
   For I should have denied the God who is above.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        "If I have rejoiced at the destruction of him who hated me,
   Or lifted up myself when evil found him;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        (Yes, I have not allowed my mouth to sin
   By asking his life with a curse);
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        If the men of my tent have not said,
   'Who can find one who has not been filled with his meat?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        (The sojourner has not lodged in the street;
   But I have opened my doors to the traveler);
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        If like Adam I have covered my transgressions,
   By hiding my iniquity in my heart,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="34"/>
                        Because I feared the great multitude,
   And the contempt of families terrified me,
   So that I kept silence, and didn't go out of the door--
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="35"/>
                        Oh that I had one to hear me!
   (Behold, here is my signature, let the Almighty answer me);
   Let the accuser write my indictment!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="36"/>
                        Surely I would carry it on my shoulder;
   And I would bind it to me as a crown.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="37"/>
                        I would declare to him the number of my steps.
   As a prince would I go near to him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="38"/>
                        If my land cries out against me,
   And the furrows of it weep together;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="39"/>
                        If I have eaten the fruits of it without money,
   Or have caused the owners of it to lose their life:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="40"/>
                        Let briars grow instead of wheat,
   And stinkweed instead of barley."

   The words of Job are ended.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="32" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        So these three men ceased to answer Job, because he was
righteous in his own eyes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Then the wrath of Elihu, the son of
Barachel, the Buzite, of the family of Ram, was kindled against Job.
His wrath was kindled, because he justified himself rather than God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Also his wrath was kindled against his three friends, because
they had found no answer, and yet had condemned Job.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Now Elihu
had waited to speak to Job, because they were elder than he.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        When Elihu saw that there was no answer in the mouth of these three
men, his wrath was kindled.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Elihu the son of Barachel the Buzite answered,
"I am young, and you are very old;
   Therefore I held back, and didn't dare show you my opinion.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        I said, 'Days should speak,
   And multitude of years should teach wisdom.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        But there is a spirit in man,
   And the breath of the Almighty gives them understanding.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        It is not the great who are wise,
   Nor the aged who understand justice.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Therefore I said, 'Listen to me;
   I also will show my opinion.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        "Behold, I waited for your words,
   And I listened for your reasoning,
   While you searched out what to say.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Yes, I gave you my full attention,
   But there was no one who convinced Job,
   Or who answered his words, among you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Beware lest you say, 'We have found wisdom,
   God may refute him, not man:'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        For he has not directed his words against me;
   Neither will I answer him with your speeches.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        "They are amazed. They answer no more.
   They don't have a word to say.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Shall I wait, because they don't speak,
   Because they stand still, and answer no more?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        I also will answer my part,
   And I also will show my opinion.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        For I am full of words.
   The spirit within me constrains me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Behold, my breast is as wine which has no vent;
   Like new wineskins it is ready to burst.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        I will speak, that I may be refreshed.
   I will open my lips and answer.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Please don't let me respect any man's person,
   Neither will I give flattering titles to any man.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        For I don't know how to give flattering titles;
   Or else my Maker would soon take me away.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="33" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "However, Job, Please hear my speech,
   And listen to all my words.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        See now, I have opened my mouth.
   My tongue has spoken in my mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        My words shall utter the uprightness of my heart;
   That which my lips know they shall speak sincerely.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        The Spirit of God has made me,
   And the breath of the Almighty gives me life.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        If you can, answer me;
   Set your words in order before me, and stand forth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Behold, I am toward God even as you are:
   I am also formed out of the clay.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Behold, my terror shall not make you afraid,
   Neither shall my pressure be heavy on you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        "Surely you have spoken in my hearing,
   I have heard the voice of your words, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        'I am clean, without disobedience.
   I am innocent, neither is there iniquity in me:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Behold, he finds occasions against me,
   He counts me for his enemy:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        He puts my feet in the stocks,
   He marks all my paths.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        "Behold, I will answer you. In this you are not just;
   For God is greater than man.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Why do you strive against him,
   Because he doesn't give account of any of his matters?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        For God speaks once,
   Yes twice, though man pays no attention.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        In a dream, in a vision of the night,
   When deep sleep falls on men,
   In slumbering on the bed;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Then he opens the ears of men,
   And seals their instruction,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        That he may withdraw man from his purpose,
   And hide pride from man.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        He keeps back his soul from the pit,
   And his life from perishing by the sword.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        He is chastened also with pain on his bed,
   With continual strife in his bones;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        So that his life abhors bread,
   And his soul dainty food.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        His flesh is so consumed away, that it can't be seen;
   His bones that were not seen stick out.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Yes, his soul draws near to the pit,
   And his life to the destroyers.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        "If there is beside him an angel,
   An interpreter, one among a thousand,
   To show to man what is right for him;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        Then God is gracious to him, and says,
   'Deliver him from going down to the pit,
   I have found a ransom.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        His flesh shall be fresher than a child's;
   He returns to the days of his youth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        He prays to God, and he is favorable to him,
   So that he sees his face with joy:
   He restores to man his righteousness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        He sings before men, and says,
   'I have sinned, and perverted that which was right,
   And it didn't profit me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        He has redeemed my soul from going into the pit,
   My life shall see the light.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        "Behold, God works all these things,
   Twice, yes three times, with a man,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        To bring back his soul from the pit,
   That he may be enlightened with the light of the living.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        Mark well, Job, and listen to me:
   Hold your peace, and I will speak.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        If you have anything to say, answer me:
   Speak, for I desire to justify you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        If not, listen to me:
   Hold your peace, and I will teach you wisdom."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="34" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Moreover Elihu answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Hear my words, you wise men;
   Give ear to me, you who have knowledge.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        For the ear tries words,
   As the palate tastes food.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Let us choose for us that which is right.
   Let us know among ourselves what is good.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        For Job has said, 'I am righteous,
   God has taken away my right:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Notwithstanding my right I am considered a liar;
   My wound is incurable, though I am without disobedience.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        What man is like Job,
   Who drinks up scoffing like water,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Who goes in company with the workers of iniquity,
   And walks with wicked men?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        For he has said, 'It profits a man nothing
   That he should delight himself with God.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        "Therefore listen to me, you men of understanding:
   Far be it from God, that he should do wickedness,
   From the Almighty, that he should commit iniquity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        For the work of a man will he render to him,
   And cause every man to find according to his ways.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Yes surely, God will not do wickedly,
   Neither will the Almighty pervert justice.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Who gave him a charge over the earth?
   Or who has appointed him over the whole world?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        If he set his heart on himself,
   If he gathered to himself his spirit and his breath;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        All flesh would perish together,
   And man would turn again to dust.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        "If now you have understanding, hear this.
   Listen to the voice of my words.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Shall even one who hates justice govern?
   Will you condemn him who is righteous and mighty?--
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Who says to a king, 'Vile!'
   Or to nobles, 'Wicked!'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Who doesn't respect the persons of princes,
   Nor regards the rich more than the poor;
   For they all are the work of his hands.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        In a moment they die, even at midnight;
   The people are shaken and pass away,
   The mighty are taken away without hand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        "For his eyes are on the ways of a man,
   He sees all his goings.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        There is no darkness, nor thick gloom,
   Where the workers of iniquity may hide themselves.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        For he doesn't need to consider a man further,
   That he should go before God in judgment.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        He breaks in pieces mighty men in ways past finding out,
   And sets others in their place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        Therefore he takes knowledge of their works.
   He overturns them in the night, so that they are destroyed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        He strikes them as wicked men
   In the open sight of others;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        Because they turned aside from following him,
   And wouldn't have regard in any of his ways:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        So that they caused the cry of the poor to come to him,
   He heard the cry of the afflicted.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        When he gives quietness, who then can condemn?
   When he hides his face, who then can see him?
   Alike whether to a nation, or to a man:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        That the godless man may not reign,
   That there be no one to ensnare the people.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        "For has any said to God,
   'I am guilty, but I will not offend any more.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        Teach me that which I don't see.
   If I have done iniquity, I will do it no more'?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        Shall his recompense be as you desire, that you refuse it?
   For you must choose, and not I.
   Therefore speak what you know.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="34"/>
                        Men of understanding will tell me,
   Yes, every wise man who hears me:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="35"/>
                        'Job speaks without knowledge,
   His words are without wisdom.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="36"/>
                        I wish that Job were tried to the end,
   Because of his answering like wicked men.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="37"/>
                        For he adds rebellion to his sin.
   He claps his hands among us,
   And multiplies his words against God."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="35" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Moreover Elihu answered,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Do you think this to be your right,
   Or do you say, 'My righteousness is more than God's,'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        That you ask, 'What advantage will it be to you?
   What profit shall I have, more than if I had sinned?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        I will answer you,
   And your companions with you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Look to the heavens, and see.
   See the skies, which are higher than you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        If you have sinned, what effect do you have against him?
   If your transgressions are multiplied, what do you do to him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        If you are righteous, what do you give him?
   Or what does he receive from your hand?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Your wickedness may hurt a man as you are;
   And your righteousness may profit a son of man.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        "By reason of the multitude of oppressions they cry out;
   They cry for help by reason of the arm of the mighty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        But none says, 'Where is God my Maker,
   Who gives songs in the night,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Who teaches us more than the animals of the earth,
   And makes us wiser than the birds of the sky?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        There they cry, but none gives answer,
   Because of the pride of evil men.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Surely God will not hear an empty cry,
   Neither will the Almighty regard it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        How much less when you say you don't see him.
   The cause is before him, and you wait for him!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        But now, because he has not visited in his anger,
   Neither does he greatly regard arrogance.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Therefore Job opens his mouth with empty talk,
   And he multiplies words without knowledge."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="36" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Elihu also continued, and said,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Bear with me a little, and I will show you;
   For I still have something to say on God's behalf.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        I will get my knowledge from afar,
   And will ascribe righteousness to my Maker.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        For truly my words are not false.
   One who is perfect in knowledge is with you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        "Behold, God is mighty, and doesn't despise anyone.
   He is mighty in strength of understanding.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        He doesn't preserve the life of the wicked,
   But gives to the afflicted their right.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        He doesn't withdraw his eyes from the righteous,
   But with kings on the throne,
   He sets them forever, and they are exalted.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        If they are bound in fetters,
   And are taken in the cords of afflictions,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Then he shows them their work,
   And their transgressions, that they have behaved themselves proudly.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        He also opens their ears to instruction,
   And commands that they return from iniquity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        If they listen and serve him,
   They shall spend their days in prosperity,
   And their years in pleasures.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        But if they don't listen, they shall perish by the sword;
   They shall die without knowledge.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "But those who are godless in heart lay up anger.
   They don't cry for help when he binds them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        They die in youth.
   Their life perishes among the unclean.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        He delivers the afflicted by their affliction,
   And opens their ear in oppression.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Yes, he would have allured you out of distress,
   Into a broad place, where there is no restriction.
   That which is set on your table would be full of fatness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        "But you are full of the judgment of the wicked.
   Judgment and justice take hold of you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Don't let riches entice you to wrath,
   Neither let the great size of a bribe turn you aside.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Would your wealth sustain you in distress,
   Or all the might of your strength?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Don't desire the night,
   When people are cut off in their place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Take heed, don't regard iniquity;
   For this you have chosen rather than affliction.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Behold, God is exalted in his power.
   Who is a teacher like him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        Who has prescribed his way for him?
   Or who can say, 'You have committed unrighteousness?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        "Remember that you magnify his work,
   Whereof men have sung.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        All men have looked thereon.
   Man sees it afar off.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        Behold, God is great, and we don't know him.
   The number of his years is unsearchable.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        For he draws up the drops of water,
   Which distill in rain from his vapor,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        Which the skies pour down
   And drop on man abundantly.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        Yes, can any understand the spreading of the clouds,
   And the thunderings of his pavilion?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        Behold, he spreads his light around him.
   He covers the bottom of the sea.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        For by these he judges the people.
   He gives food in abundance.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        He covers his hands with the lightning,
   And commands it to strike the mark.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        The noise of it tells about him,
   And the cattle also concerning the storm that comes up.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="37" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Yes, at this my heart trembles,
   And is moved out of its place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Hear, oh, hear the noise of his voice,
   The sound that goes out of his mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        He sends it forth under the whole sky,
   And his lightning to the ends of the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        After it a voice roars.
   He thunders with the voice of his majesty;
   He doesn't hold back anything when his voice is heard.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        God thunders marvelously with his voice.
   He does great things, which we can't comprehend.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        For he says to the snow, 'Fall on the earth;'
   Likewise to the shower of rain,
   And to the showers of his mighty rain.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        He seals up the hand of every man,
   That all men whom he has made may know it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Then the animals go into coverts,
   And remain in their dens.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Out of its chamber comes the storm,
   And cold out of the north.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        By the breath of God, ice is given,
   And the breadth of the waters is frozen.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Yes, he loads the thick cloud with moisture.
   He spreads abroad the cloud of his lightning.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        It is turned round about by his guidance,
   That they may do whatever he commands them
   On the surface of the habitable world,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Whether it is for correction, or for his land,
   Or for lovingkindness, that he causes it to come.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        "Listen to this, Job:
   Stand still, and consider the wondrous works of God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Do you know how God controls them,
   And causes the lightning of his cloud to shine?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Do you know the workings of the clouds,
   The wondrous works of him who is perfect in knowledge?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        You whose clothing is warm,
   When the earth is still by reason of the south wind?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Can you, with him, spread out the sky,
   Which is strong as a cast metal mirror?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Teach us what we shall tell him;
   For we can't make our case by reason of darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Shall it be told him that I would speak?
   Or should a man wish that he were swallowed up?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Now men don't see the light which is bright in the skies,
   But the wind passes, and clears them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Out of the north comes golden splendor;
   With God is awesome majesty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        We can't reach the Almighty,
   He is exalted in power;
   In justice and great righteousness he will not oppress.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        Therefore men revere him.
   He doesn't regard any who are wise of heart."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="38" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Yahweh answered Job out of the whirlwind,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Who is this who darkens counsel
   By words without knowledge?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Brace yourself like a man,
   For I will question you, then you answer me!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        "Where were you when I laid the foundations of the earth?
   Declare, if you have understanding.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Who determined the measures of it, if you know?
   Or who stretched the line on it?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Whereupon were the foundations of it fastened?
   Or who laid its cornerstone,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        When the morning stars sang together,
   And all the sons of God shouted for joy?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        "Or who shut up the sea with doors,
   When it broke forth from the womb,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        When I made clouds the garment of it,
   Thick darkness a swaddling-band for it,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Marked out for it my bound,
   Set bars and doors,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        And said, 'Here you may come, but no further;
   Here shall your proud waves be stayed?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        "Have you commanded the morning in your days,
   And caused the dawn to know its place;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        That it might take hold of the ends of the earth,
   And shake the wicked out of it?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        It is changed as clay under the seal,
   And stands forth as a garment.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        From the wicked, their light is withheld,
   The high arm is broken.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        "Have you entered into the springs of the sea?
   Or have you walked in the recesses of the deep?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Have the gates of death been revealed to you?
   Or have you seen the gates of the shadow of death?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Have you comprehended the earth in its breadth?
   Declare, if you know it all.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        "What is the way to the dwelling of light?
   As for darkness, where is the place of it,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        That you should take it to the bound of it,
   That you should discern the paths to the house of it?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Surely you know, for you were born then,
   And the number of your days is great!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Have you entered the treasuries of the snow,
   Or have you seen the treasures of the hail,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        Which I have reserved against the time of trouble,
   Against the day of battle and war?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        By what way is the lightning distributed,
   Or the east wind scattered on the earth?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        Who has cut a channel for the flood water,
   Or the path for the thunderstorm;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        To cause it to rain on a land where no man is;
   On the wilderness, in which there is no man;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        To satisfy the waste and desolate ground,
   To cause the tender grass to spring forth?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        Does the rain have a father?
   Or who fathers the drops of dew?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        Out of whose womb came the ice?
   The gray frost of the sky, who has given birth to it?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        The waters become hard like stone,
   When the surface of the deep is frozen.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        "Can you bind the cluster of the Pleiades,
   Or loosen the cords of Orion?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        Can you lead forth the constellations in their season?
   Or can you guide the Bear with her cubs?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        Do you know the laws of the heavens?
   Can you establish the dominion of it over the earth?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="34"/>
                        "Can you lift up your voice to the clouds,
   That abundance of waters may cover you?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="35"/>
                        Can you send forth lightnings, that they may go?
   Do they report to you, 'Here we are?'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="36"/>
                        Who has put wisdom in the inward parts?
   Or who has given understanding to the mind?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="37"/>
                        Who can number the clouds by wisdom?
   Or who can pour out the bottles of the sky,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="38"/>
                        When the dust runs into a mass,
   And the clods of earth stick together?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="39"/>
                        "Can you hunt the prey for the lioness,
   Or satisfy the appetite of the young lions,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="40"/>
                        When they crouch in their dens,
   And lie in wait in the thicket?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="41"/>
                        Who provides for the raven his prey,
   When his young ones cry to God,
   And wander for lack of food?
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="39" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Do you know the time when the mountain goats give birth?
   Do you watch when the doe bears fawns?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Can you number the months that they fulfill?
   Or do you know the time when they give birth?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        They bow themselves, they bring forth their young,
   They end their labor pains.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Their young ones become strong.
   They grow up in the open field.
   They go forth, and don't return again.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        "Who has set the wild donkey free?
   Or who has loosened the bonds of the swift donkey,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Whose home I have made the wilderness,
   And the salt land his dwelling-place?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        He scorns the tumult of the city,
   Neither hears he the shouting of the driver.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        The range of the mountains is his pasture,
   He searches after every green thing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        "Will the wild ox be content to serve you?
   Or will he stay by your feeding trough?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Can you hold the wild ox in the furrow with his harness?
   Or will he till the valleys after you?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Will you trust him, because his strength is great?
   Or will you leave to him your labor?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Will you confide in him, that he will bring home your seed,
   And gather the grain of your threshing floor?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "The wings of the ostrich wave proudly;
   But are they the pinions and plumage of love?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        For she leaves her eggs on the earth,
   Warms them in the dust,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        And forgets that the foot may crush them,
   Or that the wild animal may trample them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        She deals harshly with her young ones, as if they were not hers.
   Though her labor is in vain, she is without fear,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Because God has deprived her of wisdom,
   Neither has he imparted to her understanding.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        When she lifts up herself on high,
   She scorns the horse and his rider.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        "Have you given the horse might?
   Have you clothed his neck with a quivering mane?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Have you made him to leap as a locust?
   The glory of his snorting is awesome.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        He paws in the valley, and rejoices in his strength:
   He goes out to meet the armed men.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        He mocks at fear, and is not dismayed;
   Neither does he turn back from the sword.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        The quiver rattles against him,
   The flashing spear and the javelin.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        He eats up the ground with fierceness and rage,
   Neither does he stand still at the sound of the trumpet.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        As often as the trumpet sounds he snorts, 'Aha!'
   He smells the battle afar off,
   The thunder of the captains, and the shouting.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        "Is it by your wisdom that the hawk soars,
   And stretches her wings toward the south?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        Is it at your command that the eagle mounts up,
   And makes his nest on high?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        On the cliff he dwells, and makes his home,
   On the point of the cliff, and the stronghold.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        From there he spies out the prey.
   His eyes see it afar off.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        His young ones also suck up blood.
   Where the slain are, there he is."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="40" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Moreover Yahweh answered Job,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Shall he who argues contend with the Almighty?
   He who argues with God, let him answer it."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Then Job answered Yahweh,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        "Behold, I am of small account. What shall I answer you?
   I lay my hand on my mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        I have spoken once, and I will not answer;
   Yes, twice, but I will proceed no further."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Then Yahweh answered Job out of the whirlwind,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "Now brace yourself like a man.
   I will question you, and you will answer me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Will you even annul my judgment?
   Will you condemn me, that you may be justified?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Or have you an arm like God?
   Can you thunder with a voice like him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        "Now deck yourself with excellency and dignity.
   Array yourself with honor and majesty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Pour forth the fury of your anger.
   Look on everyone who is proud, and bring him low.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Look on everyone who is proud, and humble him.
   Crush the wicked in their place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Hide them in the dust together.
   Bind their faces in the hidden place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Then I will also admit to you
   That your own right hand can save you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        "See now, behemoth, which I made as well as you.
   He eats grass as an ox.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Look now, his strength is in his loins,
   His force is in the muscles of his belly.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        He moves his tail like a cedar:
   The sinews of his thighs are knit together.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        His bones are like tubes of brass.
   His limbs are like bars of iron.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        He is the chief of the ways of God.
   He who made him gives him his sword.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Surely the mountains bring him forth food,
   Where all the animals of the field do play.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        He lies under the lotus trees,
   In the covert of the reed, and the marsh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        The lotuses cover him with their shade.
   The willows of the brook surround him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        Behold, if a river overflows, he doesn't tremble.
   He is confident, though the Jordan swells even to his mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        Shall any take him when he is on the watch,
   Or pierce through his nose with a snare?
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="41" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        "Can you draw out Leviathan with a fishhook?
   Or press down his tongue with a cord?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Can you put a rope into his nose?
   Or pierce his jaw through with a hook?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Will he make many petitions to you?
   Or will he speak soft words to you?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Will he make a covenant with you,
   That you should take him for a servant forever?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Will you play with him as with a bird?
   Or will you bind him for your girls?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Will traders barter for him?
   Will they part him among the merchants?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Can you fill his skin with barbed irons,
   Or his head with fish-spears?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Lay your hand on him.
   Remember the battle, and do so no more.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Behold, the hope of him is in vain.
   Will not one be cast down even at the sight of him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        None is so fierce that he dare stir him up.
   Who then is he who can stand before me?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Who has first given to me, that I should repay him?
   Everything under the heavens is mine.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        "I will not keep silence concerning his limbs,
   Nor his mighty strength, nor his goodly frame.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Who can strip off his outer garment?
   Who shall come within his jaws?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Who can open the doors of his face?
   Around his teeth is terror.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Strong scales are his pride,
   Shut up together with a close seal.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        One is so near to another,
   That no air can come between them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        They are joined one to another;
   They stick together, so that they can't be pulled apart.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        His sneezing flashes forth light,
   His eyes are like the eyelids of the morning.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Out of his mouth go burning torches,
   Sparks of fire leap forth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Out of his nostrils a smoke goes,
   As of a boiling pot over a fire of reeds.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        His breath kindles coals.
   A flame goes forth from his mouth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        In his neck there is strength.
   Terror dances before him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        The flakes of his flesh are joined together.
   They are firm on him. They can't be moved.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        His heart is as firm as a stone,
   Yes, firm as the lower millstone.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        When he raises himself up, the mighty are afraid.
   They retreat before his thrashing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        If one lay at him with the sword, it can't avail;
   Nor the spear, the dart, nor the pointed shaft.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        He counts iron as straw;
   And brass as rotten wood.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        The arrow can't make him flee.
   Sling stones are like chaff to him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        Clubs are counted as stubble.
   He laughs at the rushing of the javelin.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        His undersides are like sharp potsherds,
   Leaving a trail in the mud like a threshing sledge.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        He makes the deep to boil like a pot.
   He makes the sea like a pot of ointment.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        He makes a path to shine after him.
   One would think the deep had white hair.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        On earth there is not his equal,
   That is made without fear.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="34"/>
                        He sees everything that is high:
   He is king over all the sons of pride."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="42" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Job answered Yahweh,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "I know that you can do all things,
   And that no purpose of yours can be restrained.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        You asked, 'Who is this who hides counsel without knowledge?'
   Therefore I have uttered that which I did not understand,
   Things too wonderful for me, which I didn't know.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        You said, 'Listen, now, and I will speak;
   I will question you, and you will answer me.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        I had heard of you by the hearing of the ear,
   But now my eye sees you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Therefore I abhor myself,
   And repent in dust and ashes."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        It was so, that after Yahweh had spoken these words to Job,
Yahweh said to Eliphaz the Temanite, "My wrath is kindled against you,
and against your two friends; for you have not spoken of me the thing
that is right, as my servant Job has.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Now therefore, take to
yourselves seven bulls and seven rams, and go to my servant Job, and
offer up for yourselves a burnt offering; and my servant Job shall pray
for you, for I will accept him, that I not deal with you according to
your folly. For you have not spoken of me the thing that is right, as
my servant Job has."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        So Eliphaz the Temanite and Bildad the Shuhite and Zophar the
Naamathite went, and did what Yahweh commanded them, and Yahweh
accepted Job.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Yahweh turned the captivity of Job, when he prayed for his
friends. Yahweh gave Job twice as much as he had before.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Then
came there to him all his brothers, and all his sisters, and all those
who had been of his acquaintance before, and ate bread with him in his
house. They comforted him, and consoled him concerning all the evil
that Yahweh had brought on him. Everyone also gave him a piece of
money, and everyone a ring of gold.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        So Yahweh blessed the latter end of Job more than his
beginning. He had fourteen thousand sheep, six thousand camels, one
thousand yoke of oxen, and a thousand female donkeys.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        He had
also seven sons and three daughters.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        He called the name of the
first, Jemimah; and the name of the second, Keziah; and the name of the
third, Keren Happuch.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        In all the land were no women found so
beautiful as the daughters of Job. Their father gave them an
inheritance among their brothers.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        After this Job lived one
hundred forty years, and saw his sons, and his sons' sons, to four
generations.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        So Job died, being old and full of days.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
