<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title>Alcibiades 1</title>
<author>Plato</author>
<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

</titleStmt>



    <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <date type="release">1996</date>
    </publicationStmt> 
    <notesStmt>
        <note anchored="true">Text was scanned at St. Olaf Spring, 1992.</note>
        <note>Perseus 2.0</note>
    </notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
    <monogr>
        <author>Plato</author>
        <title>Plato in Twelve Volumes, translated by W.R.M. Lamb.</title>
        <imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
            <date>1927</date>
        </imprint>
    </monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>


</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
    <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
            replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">           
            <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
    </refsDecl>

<!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="text"/>
<state unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="text"/>
<state unit="page"/>
</refsDecl>-->
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
    <particDesc>
        <person><persName>Socrates</persName></person>
        <person><persName>Alcibiades</persName></person>
    </particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
    <change when="2017-05-15" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion.</change>
    <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
    <change when="1992-07-01" who="WPM">Tagged in conformance with Prose.e dtd.</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg013.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<head>Alcibiades 1</head>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="103">                    
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="103"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="103a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Son of Cleinias, I think it must surprise you that I, the first of all your lovers, am the only one of them who has not given up his suit and thrown you over, and whereas they have all pestered you with their conversation I have not spoken one word to you for so many years. The cause of this has been nothing human, but a certain spiritual opposition, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Socrates refers to the <q type="emph">spiritual sign</q> which occasionally warned him against an intended action: cf. <bibl n="Plat. Apol. 31c">Plat. Apol. 31c-d</bibl>, <bibl n="Plat. Apol. 40a">Plat. Apol. 40a-b</bibl>.</note> of whose power you shall be informed at some later time. However, it now opposes me no longer, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="103b"/>so I have accordingly come to you; and I am in good hopes that it will not oppose me again in the future. Now I have been observing you all this time, and have formed a pretty good notion of your behavior to your lovers: for although they were many and high-spirited, everyone of them has found your spirit too strong for him and has run away.</said></p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="104">                    
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="104"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="104a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> Let me explain the reason of your spirit being too much for them. You say you have no need of any man in any matter; for your resources are so great, beginning with the body and ending with the soul, that you lack nothing. You think, in the first place, that you are foremost in beauty and stature—and you are not mistaken in this, as is plain for all to see—and in the second place, that you are of the most gallant family in your city, the greatest city in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="104b"/>that there you have, through your father, very many of the best people as your friends and kinsmen, who would assist you in case of need, and other connections also, through your mother, who are not a whit inferior to these, nor fewer. And you reckon upon a stronger power than all those that I have mentioned, in Pericles, son of Xanthippus, whom your father left as guardian of you and your brother when he died, and who is able to do whatever he likes not only in this city but all over <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> and among many great nations of the barbarians. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="104c"/>And I will add besides the wealth of your house: but on this, I observe, you presume least of all. Well, you puff yourself up on all these advantages, and have overcome your lovers, while they in their inferiority have yielded to your might, and all this has not escaped you; so I am very sure that you wonder what on earth I mean by not getting rid of my passion, and what can be my hope in remaining when the rest have fled.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Perhaps also, Socrates, you are not aware that <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="104d"/>you have only just anticipated me. For I, in fact, had the intention of coming and asking you first that very same question—what is your aim and expectation in bothering me by making a particular point of always turning up wherever I may be. For I really do wonder what can be your object, and should be very glad if you would tell me.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then you will listen to me, presumably, with keen attention if, as you say, you long to know what I mean, and I have in you a listener who will stay to hear me out.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, to be sure: only speak.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="104e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Look to it, then; for it would be no wonder if I should make as much difficulty about stopping as I have made about starting.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> My good sir, speak; for I will listen.</said></p></div>
    
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="105">
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Speak I must, I suppose. Now, although it is hard for a lover to parley with a man who does not yield to lovers, I must make bold nevertheless to put my meaning into words. For if I saw you, Alcibiades, content with the things I set forth just now, and minded to pass your life in enjoying them, I should long ago have put away my love, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="105"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="105a"/>so at least I persuade myself: but as it is, I shall propound to your face quite another set of your thoughts, whereby you will understand that I have had you continually before my mind. For I believe, if some god should ask you: <q type="spoken">Alcibiades, do you prefer to live with your present possessions, or to die immediately if you are not to have the chance of acquiring greater things?</q> I believe you would choose to die. But let me tell you what I imagine must be the present hope of your life. You think that if you come shortly before the Athenian Assembly—which <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="105b"/>you expect to occur in a very few days—you will stand forth and prove to the people that you are more worthy of honor than either Pericles or anyone else who has ever existed, and that having proved this you will have the greatest power in the state; and that if you are the greatest here, you will be the same among all the other Greeks, and not only Greeks, but all the barbarians who inhabit the same continent with us. And if that same god should say to you again, that you are to hold sway here in <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName>, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="105c"/>but are not to be allowed to cross over into <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> and to interfere with the affairs of that region, I believe you would be equally loth to live on those sole conditions either—if you are not to fill, one may say, the whole world with your name and your power; and I fancy that, except Cyrus and Xerxes, you think there has never existed a single man who was of any account. So then that this is your hope, I know well enough; I am not merely guessing. And I daresay you will reply, since you know that what I say is true: <q type="spoken">Well, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="105d"/>Socrates, and what has that to do with your point?</q> I am going to tell you, dear son of Cleinias and Deinomache. Without me it is impossible for all those designs of yours to be crowned with achievement; so great is the power I conceive myself to have over your affairs and over you, and it is for this very reason, I believe, that the god has so long prevented me from talking with you, and I was waiting to see when he would allow me. For as <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="105e"/>you have hopes of proving yourself in public to be invaluable to the state and, having proved it, of winning forthwith unlimited power, so do I hope to win supreme power over you by proving that I am invaluable to you, and that neither guardian nor kinsman nor anyone else is competent to transmit to you the power that you long for except me, with the god’s help, however. In your younger days, to be sure, before you had built such high hopes, the god, as I believe, prevented me from talking with you, in order that I might not waste my words: but now he has set me on; <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="106"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="106a"/>for now you will listen to me.</said></p></div>
          
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="106">          
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> You seem to me far more extraordinary, Socrates, now that you have begun to speak, than before, when you followed me about in silence; though even then you looked strange enough. Well, as to my intending all this or not, you have apparently made your decision, and any denial of mine will not avail me to persuade you. Very good: but supposing I have intended ever so much what you say, how are you the sole means through which I can hope to attain it? Can you tell me?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="106b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Are you asking whether I can make a long speech, such as you are used to hearing? No, my gift is not of that sort. But I fancy I could prove to you that the case is so, if you will consent to do me just one little service.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, if you mean a service that is not troublesome, I consent.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Do you consider it troublesome to answer questions put to you?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, I do not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then answer.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Ask.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, you have the intentions <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="106c"/>which I say you have, I suppose?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Be it so, if you like, in order that I may know what you will say next.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Now then: you intend, as I say, to come forward as adviser to the Athenians in no great space of time; well, suppose I were to take hold of you as you were about to ascend the platform, and were to ask you: <q type="spoken">Alcibiades, on what subject do the Athenians propose to take advice, that you should stand up to advise them? Is it something about which you have better knowledge than they?</q> What would be your reply?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="106d"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I should say, I suppose, it was something about which I knew better than they.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then you are a good adviser on things about which you actually know.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you know only the things you have learnt from others or discovered yourself?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What could I know besides?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And can it be that you would ever have learnt or discovered anything without being willing either to learn it or to inquire into it yourself?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, would you have been willing to inquire into or learn what you thought you knew?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="106e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So there was a time when you did not think that you knew what you now actually know.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> There must have been.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, but I know pretty nearly the things that you have learnt: tell me if anything has escaped me. You learnt, if I recollect, writing and harping and wrestling; as for fluting, you refused to learn it. These are the things that you know, unless perhaps there is something you have been learning unobserved by me; and this you were not, I believe, if you so much as stepped out of doors either by night or by day.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, I have taken no other lessons than those.</said></p></div> 
    
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="107">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="107"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="107a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then tell me, will it be when the Athenians are taking advice how they are to do their writing correctly that you are to stand up and advise them?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Upon my word, not I.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, about strokes on the lyre?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Not at all.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Nor in fact are they accustomed to deliberate on throws in wrestling either at the Assembly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, to be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then what will be the subject of the advice? For I presume it will not be about building.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="107b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For a builder will give better advice than you in that matter.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Nor yet will it be about divination?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For there again a diviner will serve better than you.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Whether he be short or tall, handsome or ugly, nay, noble or ignoble.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For on each subject the advice comes from one who knows, not one who has riches.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And whether their mentor be poor or rich will make no difference to the Athenians when they deliberate <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="107c"/>for the health of the citizens; all that they require of their counsellor is that he be a physician.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Naturally.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then what will they have under consideration if you are to be right in standing up, when you do so, as their counsellor?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Their own affairs, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Do you mean with regard to shipbuilding, and the question as to what sort of ships they ought to get built?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, I do not, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Because, I imagine, you do not understand shipbuilding. Is that, and that alone, the reason?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is just the reason.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="107d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, on what sort of affairs of their own do you mean that they will be deliberating?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> On war, Socrates, or on peace, or on any other of the state’s affairs.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Do you mean that they will be deliberating with whom they ought to make peace, and on whom they ought to make war, and in what manner?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And on whom it is better to do so, ought they not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="107e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And at such time as it is better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Certainly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And for so long as they had better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Now if the Athenians should deliberate with whom they should wrestle close, and with whom only at arm’s length, and in what manner, would you or the wrestling-master be the better adviser?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> The wrestling-master, I presume.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And can you tell me what the wrestling-master would have in view when he advised as to the persons with whom they ought or ought not to wrestle close, and when and in what manner? What I mean is something like this: ought they not to wrestle close with those with whom it is better to do so?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p></div> 
    
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="108">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="108"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="108a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And so far as is better, too?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> So far.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And at such time also as is better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Certainly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But again, when one sings, one has sometimes to accompany the song with harping and stepping?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, one has.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And at such time as is better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And so far as is better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I agree.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well now, since you applied the term <q type="emph">better</q> to the two cases <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="108b"/>of harping for accompaniment of a song and close wrestling, what do you call the <q type="emph">better</q> in the case of harping, to correspond with what in the case of wrestling I call gymnastic? What do you call the other?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do not understand.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, try to copy me: for my answer gave you, I think, what is correct in every instance; and that is correct, I presume, which proceeds by rule of the art, is it not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And was not the art here gymnastic?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="108c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And I said that the better <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Socrates means by <q type="emph">better</q> or <q type="emph">the better way</q> the general method of attaining excellence in any art.</note> in the case of wrestling was gymnastic.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> You did.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And I was quite fair?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I think so.</said></p>
            <p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Come then, in your turn—for it would befit you also, I fancy, to argue fairly <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Socrates here repeats <foreign xml:lang="grc">καλῶς</foreign> (which means <gloss>handsomely</gloss> as well as <gloss>correctly</gloss>) in allusion to Alcibiades’ good looks. Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Alc. 1.113b">Plat. Alc.1 113b</bibl></note>—tell me, first, what is the art which includes harping and singing and treading the measure correctly? What is it called as a whole? You cannot yet tell me?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, try another way: who are the goddesses that foster the art?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> The Muses, you mean, Socrates?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="108d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> I do. Now, just think, and say by what name the art is called after them.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Music, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><q type="socalled">Music</q> with the Greeks included poetry and dancing as well as our <q type="emph">music.</q></note> I suppose you mean.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Yes, I do. And what is that which proceeds correctly by its rule? As in the other case I was correct in mentioning to you gymnastic as that which goes by the art, so I ask you, accordingly, what you say in this case. What manner of proceeding is required?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> A musical one, I suppose.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> You are right. Come then, what is it that you term <q type="emph">better,</q> in respect of what is better in waging war and being at peace? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="108e"/>Just as in our other instances you said that the <q type="emph">better</q> implied the more musical and again, in the parallel case, the more gymnastical, try now if you can tell me what is the <q type="emph">better</q> in this case.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But I am quite unable.</said></p></div>
       
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="109">       
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But surely that is disgraceful; for if you should speak to somebody as his adviser on food, and say that one sort was better than another, at this time and in this quantity, and he then asked you—What do you mean by the <q type="emph">better,</q> Alcibiades?—in a matter like that you could tell him you meant the more wholesome, although you do not set up to be a physician; yet in a case where you set up <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="109"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="109a"/>to have knowledge and are ready to stand up and advise as though you knew, are you not ashamed to be unable, as appears, to answer a question upon it? Does it not seem disgraceful?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Very.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then consider and do your best to tell me the connection of <q type="emph">better</q> in being at peace or at war with those to whom we ought to be so disposed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, I am considering, but I fail to perceive it.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But you must know what treatment it is that we allege against each other when we enter upon a war, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="109b"/>and what name we give it when we do so?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do: we say we are victims of deceit or violence or spoliation.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Enough: how do we suffer each of these things? Try and tell me what difference there is between one way and another.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Do you mean by that, Socrates, whether it is in a just way or an unjust way?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Precisely.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, there you have all the difference in the world.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, on which sort are you going to advise the Athenians to make war—those who are acting unjustly, or those who are doing what is just?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="109c"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is a hard question: for even if someone decides that he must go to war with those who are doing what is just, he would not admit that they were doing so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For that would not be lawful, I suppose?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed; nor is it considered honorable either.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So you too will appeal to these things in making your speeches?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Necessarily.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then must not that <q type="emph">better</q> about which I was asking in reference to making or not making war, on those on whom we ought to or not, and when we ought to or not, be simply and solely the juster?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently it is.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="109d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> How now, friend Alcibiades? Have you overlooked your own ignorance of this matter, or have I overlooked <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Cf. above, <bibl n="Plat. Alc. 1.106e">Plat. Alc.1 106e</bibl>.</note> your learning it and taking lessons of a master who taught you to distinguish the more just and the more unjust? And who is he? Inform me in my turn, in order that you may introduce me to him as another pupil.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> You are joking, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> No, I swear by our common God of Friendship, whose name <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="109e"/>I would by no means take in vain. Come, if you can, tell me who the man is.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But what if I cannot? Do you think I could not know about what is just and unjust in any other way?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Yes, you might, supposing you discovered it.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But do you not think I might discover it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Yes, quite so, if you inquired.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> And do you not think I might inquire?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> I do, if you thought you did not know.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> And was there not a time when I held that view?</said></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="110">
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well spoken. Then can you tell me at what time it was <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="110"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="110a"/>that you thought you did not know what is just and unjust? Pray, was it a year ago that you were inquiring, and thought you did not know? Or did you think you knew? Please answer truly, that our debates may not be futile.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, I thought I knew.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And two years, and three years, and four years back, were you not of the same mind?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I was.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But, you see, before that time you were a child, were you not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So I know well enough that then you thought you knew.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> How do you know it so well?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="110b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Many a time I heard you, when as a child you were dicing or playing some other game at your teacher’s or elsewhere, instead of showing hesitation about what was just and unjust, speak in very loud and confident tones about one or other of your playmates, saying he was a rascal and a cheat who played unfairly. Is not this a true account?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But what was I to do, Socrates, when somebody cheated me?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Yet if you were ignorant then whether you were being unfairly treated or not, how can you ask—<q type="spoken">What are you to do?</q></said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="110c"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, but on my word, I was not ignorant: no, I clearly understood that I was being wronged.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So you thought you knew, even as a child, it seems, what was just and unjust.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I did; and I knew too.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> At what sort of time did you discover it? For surely it was not while you thought you knew.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then when did you think you were ignorant? Consider; I believe you will fail to find such a time.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Upon my word, Socrates, I really cannot say.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="110d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So you do not know it by discovery.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Not at all, apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But you said just now that you did not know it by learning either; and if you neither discovered nor learnt it, how do you come to know it, and whence?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, perhaps that answer I gave you was not correct, that I knew it by my own discovery.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then how was it done?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I learnt it, I suppose, in the same way as everyone else.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Back we come to the same argument. From whom? Please tell me.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="110e"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> From the many.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> They are no very serious teachers with whom you take refuge, if you ascribe it to the many!</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, are they not competent to teach?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Not how to play, or not to play, draughts; and yet that, I imagine, is a slight matter compared with justice. What? Do you not think so?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then if they are unable to teach the slighter, can they teach the more serious matter?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I think so: at any rate, there are many other things that they are able to teach, more serious than draughts.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> What sort of things?</said></p></div>
            
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="111">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="111"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="111a"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> For instance, it was from them that I learnt to speak Greek, and I could not say who was my teacher, but can only ascribe it to the same people who, you say, are not serious teachers.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Ah, gallant sir, the many may be good teachers of that, and they can justly be praised for their teaching of such subjects.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> And why?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Because in those subjects they have the equipment proper to good teachers.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What do you mean by that?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> You know that those who are going to teach anything should first know it themselves, do you not?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="111b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And that those who know should agree with each other and not differ?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But if they differ upon anything, will you say that they know it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then how can they be teachers of it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> By no means.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well now, do you find that the many differ about the nature of stone or wood? If you ask one of them, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="111c"/>do they not agree on the same answer, and make for the same things when they want to get a piece of stone or wood? It is just the same, too, with everything of the sort: for I am pretty nearly right in understanding you to mean just this by knowing how to speak Greek, am I not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And on these matters, as we stated, they not only agree with each other and with themselves in private, but states also use in public the same terms about them to each other, without any dispute?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> They do.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="111d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then naturally they will be good teachers of these matters.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And if we should wish to provide anyone with knowledge of them, we should be right in sending him to be taught by <q type="mentioned">the many</q> that you speak of?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Certainly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But what if we wished to know not only what men were like or what horses were like, but which of them were good runners or not? Would the many still suffice to teach us this?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you have ample proof that they do not know this, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="111e"/>and are not proficient teachers of it, in their not agreeing about it at all with themselves?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I have.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what if we wished to know not only what men were like, but what healthy or diseased men were like? Would the many suffice to teach us?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you would have proof of their being bad teachers of that, if you saw them differing about it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I should.</said></p></div>
                
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="112">
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, do you now find that the many agree with themselves or each other <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="112"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="112a"/>about just and unjust men or things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Far from it, on my word, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> In fact, they differ most especially on these points?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Very much so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And I suppose you never yet saw or heard of people differing so sharply on questions of health or the opposite as to fight and kill one another in battle because of them.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But on questions of justice or injustice I am sure you have; <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="112b"/> and if you have not seen them, at any rate you have heard of them from many people, especially Homer. For you have heard <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb" place="unspecified"> i.e., at the recitations of rhapsodes; cf. the <title>Ion</title> of Plato.</note> the <title>Odyssey</title> and the <title>Iliad</title>?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I certainly have, I suppose, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And these poems are about a difference of just and unjust</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And from this difference arose the fights and deaths of the Achaeans, and of the Trojans as well, and of the suitors of Penelope in their strife with Odysseus.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="112c"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And I imagine that when the Athenians and Spartans and Boeotians lost their men at <placeName key="perseus,Tanagra">Tanagra</placeName>, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">457 B.C.</note> and later at <placeName key="tgn,7011235">Coronea</placeName>, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">447 B.C.</note> among whom your own father perished, the difference that caused their deaths and fights was solely on a question of just and unjust, was it not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then are we to say that these people understand those questions, on which <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="112d"/>they differ so sharply that they are led by their mutual disputes to take these extreme measures against each other?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you refer me to teachers of that sort, whom you admit yourself to be without knowledge?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It seems I do.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then how is it likely that you should know what is just and unjust, when you are so bewildered about these matters and are shown to have neither learnt them from anyone nor discovered them for yourself?.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> By what you say, it is not likely.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="112e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> There again, Alcibiades, do you see how unfairly you speak?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> In what ?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> In stating that I say so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, do you not say that l do not know about the just and unjust?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Not at all.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, do I say it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> How, pray ?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> I will show you, in the following way. If I ask you which is the greater number, one or two, you will answer <q type="emph">two</q>?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, I shall.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> How much greater?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> By one.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then which of us says that two are one more than one?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And I was asking, and you were answering?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p></div>
            
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="113">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="113"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="113a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then is it I, the questioner, or you the answerer, that are found to be speaking about these things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what if I ask what are the letters in <q type="emph">Socrates,</q> and you tell me? Which will be the speaker?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Come then, tell me, as a principle, when we have question and answer, which is the speaker—the questioner, or the answerer?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> The answerer, I should say, Socrates.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="113b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And throughout the argument so far, I was the questioner?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you the answerer?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Quite so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, which of us has spoken what has been said?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently, Socrates, from what we have admitted, it was I.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And it was said that Alcibiades, the fair son of Cleinias, did not know about just and unjust, but thought he did, and intended to go to the Assembly as adviser to the Athenians on what he knows nothing about; is not that so?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="113c"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
            <p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then, to quote Euripides, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><bibl n="Eur. Hipp. 352">Eur. Hipp. 352</bibl>—<foreign xml:lang="grc">σοῦ τάδ’, οὐκ ἐμοῦ κλύεις</foreign>.</note> the result is, Alcibiades, that you may be said to have <quote type="verse"><l met="iambic">heard it from yourself, not me,</l></quote><bibl n="Eur. Hipp. 352">Eur. Hipp. 352</bibl> and it is not I who say it, but you, and you tax me with it in vain. And indeed what you say is quite true. For it is a mad scheme this, that you meditate, my excellent friend—of teaching things that you do not know, since you have taken no care to learn them.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="113d"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I think, Socrates, that the Athenians and the rest of the Greeks rarely deliberate as to which is the more just or unjust course: for they regard questions of this sort as obvious; and so they pass them over and consider which course will prove more expedient in the result. For the just and the expedient, I take it, are not the same, but many people have profited by great wrongs that they have committed, whilst others, I imagine, have had no advantage from doing what was right.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> What then? Granting that the just and the expedient <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="113e"/>are in fact as different as they can be, you surely do not still suppose you know what is expedient for mankind, and why it is so?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, what is the obstacle, Socrates,—unless you are going to ask me again from whom I learnt it, or how I discovered it for myself?</said></p></div>
                
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="114">                
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> What a way of going on! If your answer is incorrect, and a previous argument can be used to prove it so, you claim to be told something new, and a different line of proof, as though the previous one were like a poor worn-out coat which you refuse to wear any longer; you must be provided instead with something clean and unsoiled in the way of evidence. <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="114"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="114a"/>But I shall ignore your sallies in debate, and shall none the less ask you once more, where you learnt your knowledge of what is expedient, and who is your teacher, asking in one question all the things I asked before; and now you will clearly find yourself in the same plight, and will be unable to prove that you know the expedient either through discovery or through learning. But as you are dainty, and would dislike a repeated taste of the same argument, I pass over this question of whether you know or do not know <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="114b"/>what is expedient for the Athenians: but why have you not made it clear whether the just and the expedient are the same or different? If you like, question me as I did you, or if you prefer, argue out the matter in your own way.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But I am not sure I should be able, Socrates, to set it forth to you.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, my good sir, imagine I am the people in Assembly; even there, you know, you will have to persuade each man singly, will you not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the same man may well persuade one person singly, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="114c"/>and many together, about things that he knows, just as the schoolmaster, I suppose, persuades either one or many about letters?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And again, will not the same man persuade either one or many about number?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And this will be the man who knows—the arithmetician?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Quite so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you too can persuade a single man about things of which you can persuade many?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Presumably.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And these are clearly things that you know.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the only difference between the orator <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="114d"/>speaking before the people and one who speaks in a conversation like ours is that the former persuades men in a number together of the same things, and the latter persuades them one at a time?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It looks like it.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Come now, since we see that the same man may persuade either many or one, try your unpracticed hand on me, and endeavor to show that the just is sometimes not expedient.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> You are insolent, Socrates!</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> This time, at any rate, I am going to have the insolence to persuade you of the opposite of that which you decline to prove to me.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Speak, then.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Just answer my questions.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="114e"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, you yourself must be the speaker.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> What? Do you not wish above all things to be persuaded?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> By all means, to be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you would best be persuaded if you should say <q type="spoken">the case is so</q>?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I agree.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then answer; and if you do not hear your own self say that the just is expedient, put no trust in the words of anyone again.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I will not: but I may as well answer; for I do not think I shall come to any harm.</said></p></div>
            

                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="115">
                <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="115"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="115a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> You are quite a prophet! Now tell me, do you consider some just things to be expedient, and others not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And again, some noble, and some not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What do you mean by that question?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> I would ask whether anyone ever seemed to you to be doing what was base and yet just.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Never.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, are all just things noble?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what of noble things, in their turn? Are they all good, or some only, while others are not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> In my opinion, Socrates, some noble things are evil.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And some base things are good?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="115b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Do you mean as in one of the many cases where men have gone to rescue a comrade or kinsman in battle, and have been either wounded or killed, while those who did not go to the rescue, as duty bade, have got off safe and sound?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Precisely.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And such a rescue you call noble, in respect of the endeavor to save those whom it was one’s duty to save; and this is courage, is it not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But you call it evil, in respect of the deaths and wounds?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="115c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And is not the courage one thing, and the death another?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Certainly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then it is not in the same respect that rescuing one’s friends is noble and evil?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then see if, inasmuch as it is noble, it is also good; for in the present case you were admitting that the rescue was noble in respect of its courage: now consider this very thing, courage, and say whether it is good or bad. Consider it in this way: which would you choose to have, good things or evil?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Good.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="115d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And most of all, the greatest goods, and of such things you would least allow yourself to be deprived?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then what do you say of courage? At what price would you allow yourself to be deprived of it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I would give up life itself if I had to be a coward.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then you regard cowardice as the uttermost evil.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> On a par with death, it seems.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And life and courage are the extreme opposites of death and cowardice?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="115e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you would most desire to have the former, and least the latter?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Is that because you think the former best, and the latter worst?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So you reckon courage among the best things, and death among the worst.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then the rescue of one’s friends in battle, inasmuch as it is noble in respect of the working of good by courage, you have termed noble?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But evil, in respect of the working of evil by death?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="116">
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So we may fairly describe each of these workings as follows: as you call either of them evil because of the evil it produces, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="116"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="116a"/>so you must call it good because of the good it produces.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I believe that is so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And again, are they noble inasmuch as they are good, and base inasmuch as they are evil?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then in saying that the rescue of one’s friends in battle is noble and yet evil, you mean just the same as if you called the rescue good, but evil.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I believe what you say is true, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So nothing noble, in so far as it is noble, is evil, and nothing base, in so far as it is base, is good.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="116b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Now then, consider it again in this way: whoever does nobly, does well too, does he not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And are not those who do well happy?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And they are happy because of the acquisition of good things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Certainly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And they acquire these by doing well and nobly?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So doing well is good?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And welfare is noble?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="116c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Hence we have seen again that noble and good are the same thing.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then whatever we find to be noble we shall find also to be good, by this argument at least.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> We must.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, are good things expedient or not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Expedient.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And do you remember what our admissions were about just things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I think we said that those who do just things must do noble things.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And that those who do noble things must do good things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="116d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And that good things are expedient?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Hence just things, Alcibiades, are expedient.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> So it seems.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well now, are not you the speaker of all this, and I the questioner?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I seem to be, apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So if anyone stands up to advise either the Athenians or the Peparethians, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Peparethus is a small island off the coast of <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>.</note> imagining that he understands what is just and unjust, and says that just things are sometimes evil, could you do other than laugh him to scorn, since you actually say yourself that <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="116e"/>just and expedient are the same?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But by Heaven, Socrates, I do not even know what I am saying, I feel altogether in such a strange state! For from moment to moment I change my view under your questioning.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And are you unaware, my friend, what this feeling is?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I am, quite.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, do you suppose that if someone should ask you whether you have two eyes or three, two hands or four, or anything else of that sort, you would answer differently from moment to moment, or always the same thing?</said></p></div>
    
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="117">
                <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="117"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="117a"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I begin to have misgivings about myself, but still I think I should make the same answer.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the reason would be, because you know?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I think so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then if you involuntarily give contradictory answers, clearly it must be about things of which you are ignorant.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Very likely.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you say you are bewildered in answering about just and unjust, noble and base, evil and good, expedient and inexpedient? Now, is it not obvious that your bewilderment is caused by your ignorance of these things?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="117b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I agree.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then is it the case that when a man does not know a thing he must needs be bewildered in spirit regarding that thing?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well now, do you know in what way you can ascend to heaven?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> On my word, not I.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Is that too a kind of question about which your judgement is bewildered?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Do you know the reason, or shall I state it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> State it.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> It is, my friend, that while not knowing the matter you do not suppose that you know it.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="117c"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Here again, how do you mean?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Do your share, in seeing for yourself. Are you bewildered about the kind of thing that you do not know and are aware of not knowing? For instance, you know, I suppose, that you do not know about the preparation of a tasty dish?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Quite so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then do you think for yourself how you are to prepare it, and get bewildered, or do you entrust it to the person who knows?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do the latter.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what if you should be on a ship at sea? Would you think <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="117d"/>whether the tiller should be moved inwards or outwards, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The <q type="mentioned">tiller</q> was the handle of an oar at the side of the stern, and was moved towards or away from the center of the ship.</note> and in your ignorance bewilder yourself, or would you entrust it to the helmsman, and be quiet?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I would leave it to him.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So you are not bewildered about what you do not know, so long as you know that you do not know?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It seems I am not,</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then do you note that mistakes in action also are due to this ignorance of thinking one knows when one does not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Here again, how do you mean?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> We set about acting, I suppose, when we think we know what we are doing?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="117e"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But when people think they do not know, I suppose they hand it over to others?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And so that kind of ignorant person makes no mistakes in life, because they entrust such matters to others?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Who then are those who make mistakes? For, I take it, they cannot be those who know.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="118">
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But since it is neither those who know, nor those of the ignorant <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="118"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="118a"/>who know that they do not know, the only people left, I think, are those who do not know, but think that they do?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, only those.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then this ignorance is a cause of evils, and is the discreditable sort of stupidity?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And when it is about the greatest matters, it is most injurious and base?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> By far.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, can you mention any greater things than the just, the noble, the good, and the expedient?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And it is about these, you say, that you are bewildered?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But if you are bewildered, is it not clear from what has gone before <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="118b"/>that you are not only ignorant of the greatest things, but while not knowing them you think that you do?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I am afraid so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Alack then, Alcibiades, for the plight you are in! I shrink indeed from giving it a name, but still, as we are alone, let me speak out. You are wedded to stupidity, my fine friend, of the vilest kind; you are impeached of this by your own words, out of your own mouth; and this, it seems, is why you dash into politics before you have been educated. And you are not alone in this plight, but you share it with most of those who manage our city’s affairs, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="118c"/>except just a few, and perhaps your guardian, Pericles.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, you know, Socrates, they say he did not get his wisdom independently, but consorted with many wise men, such as Pythocleides <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A musician of <placeName key="tgn,7010867">Ceos</placeName> (who was perhaps also a Pythagorean philosopher) who taught in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> and Anaxagoras <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">An Ionian philosopher who lived in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> c. 480-430 B.C.</note>; and now, old as he is, he still confers with <placeName key="tgn,2274807">Damon</placeName> <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">An Athenian musician and sophist.</note> for that very purpose.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, but did you ever find a man who was wise in anything and yet unable to make another man wise in the same things as himself? For instance, the man who taught you letters was wise himself, and also made you wise, and anyone else he wished to, did he not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="118d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you too, who learnt from him, will be able to make another man wise?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the same holds of the harper and the trainer?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Certainly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For, I presume, it is a fine proof of one’s knowing anything that one knows, when one is able to point to another man whom one has made to know it.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I agree.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, can you tell me whom Pericles made wise? One of his sons, to begin with?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="118e"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But what if the two sons of Pericles were simpletons, Socrates?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, Cleinias, your brother.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But why should you mention Cleinias, a madman?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, if Cleinias is mad and the two sons of Pericles were simpletons, what reason are we to assign, in your case, for his allowing you to be in your present condition?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I believe I am myself to blame for not attending to him.</said></p></div>
                
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="119">    
            <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="119"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="119a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But tell me of any other Athenian or foreigner, slave or freeman, who is accounted to have become wiser through converse with Pericles; as I can tell you that Pythodorus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A friend of Zeno: cf. <bibl n="Plat. Parm. 126a">Plat. Parm. 126</bibl>.</note> son of Isolochus, and Callias, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">An Athenian general.</note> son of Calliades, became through that of Zeno <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Of <placeName key="perseus,Elea">Elea</placeName>, in S. Italy; a disciple of Parmenides who criticized the Pythagorean teaching.</note>; each of them has paid Zeno a hundred minae, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">About 600-800 pounds, or the total expenses of two or three years at an English University.</note> and has become both wise and distinguished.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, upon my word, I cannot.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Very good: then what is your intention regarding yourself? Will you remain as you are, or take some trouble?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="119b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> We must put our heads together, Socrates. And indeed, as soon as you speak, I take the point and agree. For the men who manage the city’s affairs, apart from a few, do strike me as uneducated.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then what does that mean?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That if they were educated, I suppose anyone who undertook to contend against them would have to get some knowledge and practice first, as he would for a match with athletes: but now, seeing that these men have gone in for politics as amateurs, what need is there for me to practise and have the trouble of learning? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="119c"/>For I am sure that my natural powers alone will give me an easy victory over them.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Ho, ho, my good sir, what a thing to say! How unworthy of your looks and your other advantages!</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What is your meaning now, Socrates? What is the connection?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> I am grieved for you, and for my love.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, pray?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> That you should expect your contest to be with the men we have here.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, but with whom is it to be?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Is that a worthy question to be asked by a man who considers himself high-spirited?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="119d"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> How do you mean? Is not my contest with these men?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, suppose you were intending to steer a warship into action, would you be content to be the best hand among the crew at steering or, while regarding this skill as a necessary qualification, would you keep your eye on your actual opponents in the fight, and not, as now, on your fellow-fighters? These, I conceive, you ought so far to surpass that they would not feel fit to be your opponents, but only <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="119e"/>to be your despised fellow-fighters against the enemy, if you mean really to make your mark with some noble action that will be worthy both of yourself and of the city.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, I do mean to.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So you think it quite fitting for you to be satisfied if you are better than the soldiers, but neglect to keep your eye on the enemy’s leaders with a view to showing yourself better than they are, or to plan and practise against them!</said></p></div>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="120">    
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="120"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="120a"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of whom are you speaking now, Socrates?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Do you not know that our city makes war occasionally on the Spartans and on the Great King?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And if you are minded to be the head of our state, you would be right in thinking that your contest is with the kings of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That sounds like the truth.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> No, my good friend; you ought rather to keep your eye on Meidias <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="120b"/>the quail-filliper <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Meidias is mentioned by Aristophanes (<bibl n="Aristoph. Birds 1297">Aristoph. Birds 1297</bibl>) for his skill in the game of filliping quails which were specially trained not to flinch.</note> and others of his sort—who undertake to manage the city’s affairs, while they still have the slavish hair <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Slaves in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> were largely natives of western <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>. and had thick, close hair, very different from the wavy locks of the Greeks.</note> (as the women would say) showing in their minds through their lack of culture, and have not yet got rid of it; who, moreover, have come with their outlandish speech to flatter the state, not to rule it—to these, I tell you, should your eyes be turned; and then you can disregard yourself, and need neither learn what is to be learnt for the great contest in which you are to be engaged, nor practise <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="120c"/>what requires practice, and so ensure that you are perfectly prepared before entering upon a political career.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, Socrates, I believe you are right; though I think neither the Spartan generals nor the Persian king are at all different from other people.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But, my excellent friend, consider what this notion of yours means.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> In regard to what?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> First of all, do you think you would take more pains over yourself <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="120d"/>if you feared them and thought them terrible, or if you did not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Clearly, if I thought them terrible.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And do you think you will come to any harm by taking pains over yourself?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> By no means; rather that I shall get much benefit.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And on this single count that notion <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e. about the Spartan generals and the Persian king, <bibl n="Plat. Alc. 1.120c">Plat. Alc.1 120c</bibl>.</note> of yours is so much to the bad.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> True.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then, in the second place, observe the probability that it is false.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> How so?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Is it probable that noble races should produce <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="120e"/>better natures, or not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Clearly, noble races would.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And will not the well-born, provided they are well brought up, probably be perfected in virtue?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That must be so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then let us consider, by comparing our lot with theirs, whether the Spartan and Persian kings appear to be of inferior birth. Do we not know that the former are descendants of Hercules and the latter of Achaemenes, and that the line of Hercules and the line of Achaemenes go back to Perseus, son of Zeus?</said></p></div>
            
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="121">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="121"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="121a"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, and mine, Socrates, to Eurysaces, and that of Eurysaces to Zeus!</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Yes, and mine, noble Alcibiades, to Daedalus, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Socrates’ father, Sophroniscus, was a sculptor, and Daedalus was the legendary inventor of sculpture.</note> and Daedalus to Hephaestus, son of Zeus! But take the lines of those people, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e., the kings of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>.</note> going back from them: you have a succession of kings reaching to Zeus—on the one hand, kings of <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>; on the other, of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>, which they have always ruled, and frequently <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> also, as at present; whereas we are private persons ourselves, and so were our fathers. And then, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="121b"/>suppose that you had to make what show you could of your ancestors, and of <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName> as the native land of Eurysaces, or of <placeName key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName> as the home of the yet earlier Aeacus, to impress Artaxerxes, son of Xerxes, how you must expect to be laughed at! Why, I am afraid we are quite outdone by those persons in pride of birth and upbringing altogether. Or have you not observed how great are the advantages of the Spartan kings, and how their wives are kept under statutory ward of the ephors, in order that every possible precaution may be taken against the king being born <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="121c"/>of any but the Heracleidae? And the Persian king so far surpasses us that no one has a suspicion that he could have been born of anybody but the king before him; and hence the king’s wife has nothing to guard her except fear. When the eldest son, the heir to the throne, is born, first of all the king’s subjects who are in his palace have a feast, and then for ever after on that date the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> celebrates the king’s birthday with sacrifice and feasting: but when we are born, as the comic poet <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The saying, which became proverbial, is thought to have occurred in one of the (now lost) plays of Plato, the Athenian comic poet, who lived c. <date from="-0460" to="-0389">460</date>-389 B.C.</note> says, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="121d"/><cit><quote type="verse">even the neighbors barely notice it,</quote><bibl>Plato Comicus?</bibl></cit> Alcibiades. After that comes the nurture of the child, not at the hands of a woman-nurse of little worth, but of the most highly approved eunuchs in the king’s service, who are charged with the whole tendance of the new-born child, and especially with the business of making him as handsome as possible by moulding his limbs into a correct shape; and while doing this they are in high honor. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="121e"/>When the boys are seven years old they are given horses and have riding lessons, and they begin to follow the chase. And when the boy reaches fourteen years he is taken over by the royal tutors, as they call them there: these are four men chosen as the most highly esteemed among the Persians of mature age, namely, the wisest one, the justest one, the most temperate one, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="122"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="122a"/>and the bravest one.</said></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="122">
               <p><said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> The first of these teaches him the magian lore of Zoroaster, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Zoroaster was the reputed founder of the Persian religion, of which the ministers were the Magi or hereditary priests.</note> son of Horomazes; and that is the worship of the gods: he teaches him also what pertains to a king. The justest teaches him to be truthful all his life long; the most temperate, not to be mastered by even a single pleasure, in order that he may be accustomed to be a free man and a veritable king, who is the master first of all that is in him, not the slave; while the bravest trains him to be fearless and undaunted, telling him that to be daunted is to be enslaved. But you, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="122b"/>Alcibiades, had a tutor set over you by Pericles from amongst his servants,who was old as to be the most useless of them, Zopyrus the Thracian. I might describe to you at length the nurture and education of your competitors, were it not too much of a task; and besides, what I have said suffices to show the rest that follows thereon. But about your birth, Alcibiades, or nurture or education, or about those of any other Athenian, one may say that nobody cares, unless it be some lover whom you chance to have. And again, if you chose to glance at the wealth, the luxury, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="122c"/>the robes with sweeping trains, the anointings with myrrh, the attendant troops of menials, and all the other refinements of the Persians, you would be ashamed at your own case, on perceiving its inferiority to theirs. Should you choose, again, to look at the temperance and orderliness, the facility and placidity, the magnanimity and discipline, the courage and endurance, and the toil-loving, success-loving, honor-loving spirit of the Spartans, you would count yourself but a child <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="122d"/>in all these things. If again you regard wealth, and think yourself something in that way, I must not keep silence on this point either, if you are to realize where you stand. For in this respect you have only to look at the wealth of the Spartans, and you will perceive that our riches here are far inferior to theirs. Think of all the land that they have both in their own and in the Messenian country: not one of our estates could compete with theirs in extent and excellence, nor again in ownership of slaves, and especially of those of the helot class, nor yet of horses, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="122e"/>nor of all the flocks and herds that graze in <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>. However, I pass over all these things: but there is more gold and silver privately held in <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> than in the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>; for during many generations treasure has been passing in to them from every part of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and often from the barbarians also, but not passing out to anyone; and just as in the fable of Aesop, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="123"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="123a"/>where the fox remarked to the lion on the direction of the footmarks, the traces of the money going into <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> are clear enough, but nowhere are any to be seen of it coming out;</said></p></div>
                
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="123">
<p><said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> so that one can be pretty sure that those people are the richest of the Greeks in gold and silver, and that among themselves the richest is the king; for the largest and most numerous receipts of the kind are those of the kings, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="123b"/>and besides there is the levy of the royal tribute in no slight amount, which the Spartans pay to their kings. Now, the Spartan fortunes, though great compared with the wealth of other Greeks, are nought beside that of the Persians and their king. For I myself was once told by a trustworthy person, who had been up to their court, that he traversed a very large tract of excellent land, nearly a day’s journey, which the inhabitants called the girdle of the king’s wife, and another which was similarly called her veil; <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="123c"/>and many other fine and fertile regions reserved for the adornment of the consort; and each of these regions was named after some part of her apparel. So I imagine, if someone should say to the king’s mother Amestris, who was wife of Xerxes, <q type="spoken">The son of Deinomache <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The mother of Alcibiades.</note> intends to challenge your son; the mother’s dresses are worth perhaps fifty minae at the outside, while the son has under three hundred acres at Erchiae, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, about fifteen miles east of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note></q> she would wonder to what on earth this <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="123d"/>Alcibiades could be trusting, that he proposed to contend against Artaxerxes; and I expect she would remark—<q type="spoken">The only possible things that the man can be trusting to for his enterprise are industry and wisdom; for these are the only things of any account among the Greeks.</q> Whereas if she were informed that this Alcibiades who is actually making such an attempt is, in the first place, as yet barely twenty years old, and secondly, altogether uneducated; and further, that when his lover tells him that he must first learn, and take pains over himself, and practise, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="123e"/>before he enters on a contest with the king, he refuses, and says he will do very well as he is; I expect she would ask in surprise, <q type="spoken">On what, then, can the youngster rely?</q> And if we told her, <q type="spoken">On beauty, stature, birth, wealth, and mental gifts,</q> she would conclude we were mad, Alcibiades, when she compared the advantages of her own people in all these respects.</said></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="124">
                    <p><said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> And I imagine that even Lampido, daughter of Leotychides <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="124"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="124a"/>and wife of Archidamus and mother of Agis, who have all been kings, would wonder in the same way, when she compared her people’s resources, at your intention of having a contest with her son despite your bad upbringing. And yet, does it not strike you as disgraceful that our enemies’ wives should have a better idea of the qualities that we need for an attempt against them than we have ourselves? Ah, my remarkable friend, listen to me and the Delphic motto, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="124b"/> <q type="emph">Know thyself</q>; for these people are our competitors, not those whom you think; and there is nothing that will give us ascendancy over them save only pains and skill. If you are found wanting in these, you will be found wanting also in achievement of renown among Greeks and barbarians both; and of this I observe you to be more enamored than anyone else ever was of anything.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well then, what are the pains that I must take, Socrates? Can you enlighten me? For I must say your words are remarkably like the truth.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Yes, I can: but we must put our heads together, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Cf. above, <bibl n="Plat. Alc. 1.119b">Plat. Alc. 1.119b</bibl>.</note> you know, as to the way in which <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="124c"/>we can improve ourselves to the utmost. For observe that when I speak of the need of being educated I am not referring only to you, apart from myself; since my case is identical with yours except in one point.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What is that ?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> My guardian is better and wiser than your one, Pericles.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Who is he, Socrates?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> God, Alcibiades, who until this day would not let me converse with you; and trusting in him I say that through no other man but me will you attain to eminence.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="124d"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> You are jesting, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Perhaps; I am right, however, in saying that we need to take pains—all men rather badly, but we two very badly indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> As to me, you are not wrong.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Nor, I fear, as to myself either.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Then what can we do?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> There must be no crying off or skulking, my good friend.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, for that would indeed be unseemly, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> It would; so let us consider in common. Now tell me: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="124e"/>we say, do we not, that we wish to be as good as possible?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> In what excellence?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Clearly that which is the aim of good men.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Good in what?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Clearly, good in the management of affairs.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> What sort of affairs? Horsemanship?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, no.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Because we should apply to horsemen?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, seamanship, do you mean?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Because we should apply to seamen?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, what sort of thing? The business of what men?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of Athenian gentlemen.</said></p></div>
            
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="125">
                <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="125"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="125a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Do you mean by <q type="mentioned">gentlemen</q> the intelligent or the unintelligent?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> The intelligent.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And everyone is good in that wherein he is intelligent?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And bad wherein he is unintelligent?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then is the shoemaker intelligent in the making of foot-gear?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Certainly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So he is good in that article?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Good.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well now, is not the shoemaker unintelligent in the making of clothes?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="125b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So he is bad in that?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then, on this showing, the same man is both bad and good.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, can you say that good men are also bad?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But whoever do you mean by the good?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I mean those who are able to rule in the city.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Not, I presume, over horses?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, no.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But over men?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> When they are sick?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Or at sea?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I say, no.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Or harvesting?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="125c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Doing nothing, or doing something?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Doing something, I say.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Doing what? Try and let me know.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, men who do business with each other and make use of one another, as is our way of life in our cities.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then you speak of ruling over men who make use of men?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Over boatswains who make use of rowers?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, no.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Because that is the pilot’s distinction?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, do you mean ruling over men who are flute-players, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="125d"/>and who lead the singing and make use of dancers?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, no.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Because, again, that is the chorus-teacher’s function?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But whatever do you mean by being able to rule over men who make use of men?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I mean ruling over men in the city who share in it as fellow-citizens, and do business with each other.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, what art is this? Suppose I should ask you over again, as I did just now, what art makes men know how to rule over fellow-sailors?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> The pilot’s.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="125e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what knowledge—to repeat what was said a moment ago—makes them rule over their fellow-singers?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That which you just mentioned, the chorus-teacher’s.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well now, what do you call the knowledge of one’s fellow-citizens?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Good counsel, I should say, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, and is the pilot’s knowledge evil counsel?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, no.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Rather good counsel?</said></p></div>
            
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="126">          
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="126"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="126a"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> So I should think, for the preservation of his passengers.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Quite right. And now, for what is the good counsel of which you speak?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> For the better management and preservation of the city.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what is it that becomes present or absent when we get this better management and preservation? If, for example, you should ask me, <q type="spoken">What is it that becomes present or absent when the body is better managed and preserved?</q>—I should reply, <q type="spoken">Health becomes present, and disease absent.</q> Do not you think so too?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="126b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And if, again, you asked me, <q type="spoken">What becomes present in a better condition of the eyes?</q>—I should answer in just the same way, <q type="spoken">Sight becomes present, and blindness absent.</q> So, in the case of the ears, deafness is caused to be absent, and hearing to be present, when they are improved and getting better treatment.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Correct.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, what is it that becomes present or absent when a state is improved and has better treatment and management?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="126c"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To my mind, Socrates, friendship with one another will be there, while hatred and faction will be absent.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Now, by friendship do you mean agreement or disagreement?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Agreement.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what art is it that causes states to agree about numbers?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Arithmetic.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what of individuals? Is it not the same art?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And it makes each single person agree with himself?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what art makes each of us agree with himself <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="126d"/>as to which is the longer, a span or a cubit? Is it not mensuration?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And it makes both individuals and states agree with each other?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what about the balance? Is it not the same here too?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It is.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then what is that agreement of which you speak, and about what? And what art secures it? And is it the same in an individual as in a state, when one agrees with oneself and with another?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Most likely.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, what is it? Do not flag in your answers, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="126e"/>but do your best to tell me.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I suppose I mean the friendship and agreement that you find when a father and mother love their son, and between brother and brother, and husband and wife.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then do you suppose, Alcibiades, that a husband can possibly agree with his wife about woolwork, when he does not understand it, and she does?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Oh, no.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Nor has he any need, since that is a woman’s pursuit.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p></div>
            
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="127">
                    <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="127"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="127a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Or again, could a woman agree with a man about soldiering, when she has not learnt it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Oh, no.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Because, I expect you will say again, that is a man’s affair.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I would.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then, by your account, there are some pursuits belonging to women, and some to men?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So in these, at any rate, there is no agreement between men and women.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And hence no friendship either, if, as we said, friendship is agreement.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So women are not loved by men, in so far as they do their own work.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="127b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It seems not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Nor are men by women, in so far as they do theirs.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And states, therefore, are not well ordered in so far as each person does his own business? <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Charm. 161e">Plat. Charm. 161e</bibl>, <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 1.332">Plat. Rep. 1.332</bibl> ff.</note></said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I think they are, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> How can you say that? Without the presence of friendship, which we say must be there if states are well ordered, as otherwise they are not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> But it seems to me that friendship arises among them just on that account—that each of the two parties does its own business.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="127c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> It was not so a moment since: but now, what do you mean this time? Does friendship arise where there is no agreement? And is it possible that agreement should arise where some know about the business, but others do not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Impossible.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And are they doing what is just or unjust, when each man does his own business?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What is just, of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And when the citizens do what is just in the city, does not friendship arise among them?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Again I think that must be so, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then whatever do you mean by that friendship or agreement <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="127d"/>about which we must be wise and well-advised in order that we may be good men? For I am unable to learn either what it is, or in whom; since it appears that the same persons sometimes have it, and sometimes not, by your account.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, by Heaven, Socrates, I do not even know what I mean myself, and I fear that for some time past I have lived unawares in a disgraceful condition.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But you must take heart. For had you perceived your plight <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="127e"/>at fifty, it would be hard for you to take pains with yourself; whereas here you are at the time of life when one ought to perceive it.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Then what should one do on perceiving it, Socrates?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Answer the questions asked, Alcibiades: only do that, and with Heaven’s favor—if we are to put any trust in my divination—you and I shall both be in better case.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That shall be, so far as my answering can avail.</said></p></div>
                
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="128">                
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Come then, what is <q type="mentioned">taking pains over oneself</q>— <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="128"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="128a"/>for we may perchance be taking, unawares, no pains over ourselves, though we think we are—and when does a man actually do it? Does he take pains over himself at the same time as over his own things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I at least believe so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well now, when does a man take pains over his feet? Is it when he takes pains over what belongs to his feet?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do not understand.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Is there anything you can name as belonging to the hand? For instance, does a ring belong to any other part of a man but the finger?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And so the shoe also belongs to the foot, in the same way?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And likewise clothes and coverlets belong to the whole body?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="128b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Now when we take pains over our shoes, we take pains over our feet?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do not quite understand, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, but, Alcibiades, you speak of taking proper pains over this or that matter, do you not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And do you call it proper pains when someone makes a thing better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then what art makes shoes better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Shoe-making.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So by shoe-making we take pains over our shoes?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="128c"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And over our foot too by shoe-making? Or by that art whereby we make feet better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> By that art.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And is it not the same one for making our feet as for making the whole body better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I think so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And is not that gymnastic?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Certainly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So by gymnastic we take pains over our foot, but by shoe-making over what belongs to our foot?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Quite so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And by gymnastic over our hands, but by ring-engraving over what belongs to the hand?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And by gymnastic over the body, but by weaving <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="128d"/>and the rest over what belongs to the body?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Absolutely so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then for taking pains over a thing itself and over what belongs to it we use different arts.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So when you take pains over your belongings you are not taking pains over yourself.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Not at all.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For the arts, it seems, that one used for taking pains over oneself and over one’s belongings would not be the same.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Come then, whatever kind of art can we use for taking pains over ourselves?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I cannot say.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="128e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, so much at least has been admitted, that it is not one which would help us to make a single one of our possessions better, but one which would help to make ourselves so?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Now, should we ever have known what art makes a shoe better, if we had not known a shoe?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Impossible.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Nor could we know what art makes rings better, if we had no cognizance of a ring.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> True.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, could we ever know what art makes the man himself better, if we were ignorant of what we are ourselves?</said></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="129">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="129"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="129a"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Impossible.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, and is it an easy thing to know oneself, and was it a mere scamp who inscribed these words on the temple at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>; or is it a hard thing, and not a task for anybody?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I have often thought, Socrates, that it was for anybody; but often, too, that it was very hard.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But, Alcibiades, whether it is easy or not, here is the fact for us all the same: if we have that knowledge, we are like to know what pains to take over ourselves; but if we have it not, we never can.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is so.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="129b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Come then, in what way can the same-in-itself <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">This seems to be a sudden adumbration of the Platonic <q type="emph">idea</q> or form which remains constant, and so <q type="emph">the same,</q> behind the shifting objects of sense related to it through its influences or impress. Cf. below, <bibl n="Plat. Alc. 1.130d">Plat. Alc. 1.130d</bibl>.</note> be discovered? For thus we may discover what we are ourselves; whereas if we remain in ignorance of it we must surely fail.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Rightly spoken.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Steady, then, in Heaven’s name! To whom are you talking now? To me, are you not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And I in turn to you ?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then the talker is Socrates?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the hearer, Alcibiades?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And Socrates uses speech in talking?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="129c"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you call talking and using speech the same thing, I suppose.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But the user and the thing he uses are different, are they not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> How do you mean?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For instance, I suppose a shoemaker uses a round tool, and a square one, and others, when he cuts.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the cutter and user is quite different from what he uses in cutting?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And in the same way what the harper uses in harping will be different from the harper himself?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, that is what I was asking just now—whether the user <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="129d"/>and what he uses are always, in your opinion, two different things.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> They are.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then what are we to say of the shoemaker? Does he cut with his tools only, or with his hands as well?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> With his hands as well.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So he uses these also?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Does he use his eyes, too, in his shoe-making?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And we admit that the user and what he uses are different things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then the shoemaker and the harper are different from <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="129e"/>the hands and eyes that they use for their work?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And man uses his whole body too?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And we said that the user and what he uses are different?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So man is different from his own body?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It seems so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then whatever is man?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I cannot say.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Oh, but you can—that he is the user of the body.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p></div> 

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="130">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="130"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="130a"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the user of it must be the soul?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It must.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And ruler?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Now, here is a remark from which no one, I think, can dissent.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What is it?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> That man must be one of three things.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Soul, body, or both together as one whole.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Very well.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But yet we have admitted that what actually rules the body is man?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="130b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> We have.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And does the body rule itself?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> By no means.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Because we have said that it is ruled.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then that cannot be what we are seeking.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It seems not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well then, does the combination of the two rule the body, so that we are to regard this as man?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Perhaps it is.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> The unlikeliest thing in the world: for if one of the two does not share in the rule, it is quite inconceivable that the combination of the two can be ruling.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> You are right.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="130c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But since neither the body nor the combination of the two is man, we are reduced, I suppose, to this: either man is nothing at all, or if something, he turns out to be nothing else than soul.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Precisely so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, do you require some yet clearer proof that the soul is man?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, I assure you: I think it is amply proved.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And if it is tolerably, though not exactly, we are content; exact knowledge will be ours later, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="130d"/>when we have discovered the thing that we passed over just now because it would involve much consideration.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What is that?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> The point suggested in that remark a moment ago, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Alc. 1.129b">Plat. Alc. 1.129b</bibl>.</note> that we should first consider the same-in-itself; but so far, instead of the same, we have been considering what each single thing is in itself. And perhaps we shall be satisfied with that: for surely we cannot say that anything has more absolute possession of ourselves than the soul.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And it is proper to take the view that you and I are conversing with each other, while we make use of words, by intercourse of soul with soul?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Quite so.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="130e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, that is just what we suggested a little while ago—that Socrates, in using words to talk with Alcibiades, is holding speech, not with your face, it would seem, but with Alcibiades—that is, with his soul.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I believe so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then he who enjoins a knowledge of oneself bids us become acquainted with the soul.</said></p></div> 
            
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="131">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="131"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="131a"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> So it seems.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And anyone who gets to know something belonging to the body knows the things that are his, but not himself.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then no physician, in so far as he is a physician, knows himself, nor does any trainer, in so far as he is a trainer.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It seems not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And farmers, and craftsmen generally, are far from knowing themselves. For these people, it would seem, do not even know their own things, but only things still more remote than their own things, in respect of the arts which they follow; since they know <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="131b"/>but the things of the body, with which it is tended.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So if knowing oneself is temperance, none of these people is temperate in respect of his art.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> None, I agree.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And that is why these arts are held to be sordid, and no acquirements for a good man.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Quite so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then once again, whoever tends his body tends his own things, but not himself?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It looks rather like it.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But whoever tends his money tends neither himself nor <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="131c"/>his own things, but only things yet more remote than his own things?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I agree.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So that the money-maker has ceased to do his own business.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Correct.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And if anyone is found to be a lover of Alcibiades’ body, he has fallen in love, not with Alcibiades, but with something belonging to Alcibiades?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Your lover is rather he who loves your soul?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> He must be, apparently, by our argument.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And he who loves your body quits you, and is gone, as soon as its bloom is over?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="131d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Whereas he who loves your soul will not quit you so long as it makes for what is better?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> So it seems.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And I am he who does not quit you, but remains with you when your body’s prime is over, and the rest have departed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, and I am glad of it, Socrates, and hope you will not go.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then you must endeavor to be as handsome as you can.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, I shall endeavor.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> You see how you stand: Alcibiades, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="131e"/>the son of Cleinias, it seems, neither had nor has any lover except one only, and that a cherished one, Socrates, the son of Sophroniscus and Phaenarete.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> True.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And you said that I only just anticipated you in coming to you, for otherwise you would have come to me first for the purpose of inquiring why I am the only one who does not leave you?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, that was so.</said></p></div>
                
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="132">                
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then the reason was that I was the only lover of you, whereas the rest were lovers of what is yours; and that is losing its charm, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="132"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="132a"/>while you are beginning to bloom. So now, if you are not blighted and deformed by the Athenian people, I shall never forsake you. For my chiefest fear is of your being blighted by becoming a lover of the people, since many a good Athenian has come to that ere now. For fair of face is <quote>the people of great-hearted Erechtheus;</quote><bibl n="Hom. Il. 2.547">Hom. Il. 2.547</bibl> but you should get a view of it stripped: so take the precaution that I recommend.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What is it?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="132b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Exercise yourself first, my wonderful friend, in learning what you ought to know before entering on politics; you must wait till you have learnt, in order that you may be armed with an antidote and so come to no harm.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Your advice seems to me good, Socrates; but try to explain in what way we can take pains over ourselves.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, we have made one step in advance; for there is a pretty fair agreement now as to what we are, whereas we were afraid we might fail of this and take pains, without knowing it, over something other than ourselves.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is so.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="132c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the next step, we see, is to take care of the soul, and look to that.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Clearly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> While handing over to others the care of our bodies and our coffers.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Quite so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then how shall we obtain the most certain knowledge of it? For if we know that, it seems we shall know ourselves also. In Heaven’s name, do we fail to comprehend the wise words of the Delphic inscription, which we mentioned just now?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> With what intent do you say that, Socrates?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="132d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> I will tell you what I suspect to be the real advice which the inscription gives us. I rather think there are not many illustrations of it to be found, but only in the case of sight.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> What do you mean by that?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Consider in your turn: suppose that, instead of speaking to a man, it said to the eye of one of us, as a piece of advice <q type="spoken">See thyself,</q> how should we apprehend the meaning of the admonition? Would it not be, that the eye should look at that by looking at which it would see itself?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Clearly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then let us think what object there is anywhere, by looking at which <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="132e"/>we can see both it and ourselves.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Why, clearly, Socrates, mirrors and things of that sort.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Quite right. And there is also something of that sort in the eye that we see with?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p></div>
                
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="133">   
            <p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And have you observed that the face of the person who looks into another’s eye is shown in the optic confronting him, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="133"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="133a"/>as in a mirror, and we call this the pupil, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The Greek <foreign xml:lang="grc">κόρη</foreign> and the Latin <q type="foreign">pupilla</q> both mean <gloss>little girl</gloss> or <gloss>doll,</gloss> and were used to indicate the dark center of the eye in which a tiny image can be seen reflected.</note> for in a sort it is an image of the person looking?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="133b"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then an eye viewing another eye, and looking at the most perfect part of it, the thing wherewith it sees, will thus see itself.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But if it looks at any other thing in man or at anything in nature but what resembles this, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e. it must look at the pupil of a man’s eye, or at what is comparable to that <q type="mentioned">perfect part</q> in other things.</note> it will not see itself.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then if an eye is to see itself, it must look at an eye, and at that region of the eye in which the virtue of an eye is found to occur; and this, I presume, is sight.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And if the soul too, my dear Alcibiades, is to know herself, she must surely look at a soul, and especially at that region of it in which occurs the virtue of a soul—wisdom, and at any other part of a soul which resembles this?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I agree, Socrates.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="133c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And can we find any part of the soul that we can call more divine than this, which is the seat of knowledge and thought?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> We cannot.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then this part of her resembles God, and whoever looks at this, and comes to know all that is divine, will gain thereby the best knowledge of himself.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And self-knowledge we admitted to be temperance. <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Above, <bibl n="Plat. Alc. 1.131b">Plat. Alc. 1.131b</bibl>.</note></said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So if we have no knowledge of ourselves and no temperance, shall we be able to know our own belongings, good or evil?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> How can that be, Socrates?</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="133d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For I expect it seems impossible to you that without knowing Alcibiades you should know that the belongings of Alcibiades are in fact his.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Impossible indeed, upon my word.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Nor could we know that our belongings are ours if we did not even know ourselves?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> How could we?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And so, if we did not so much as know our belongings, we could not know the belongings of our belongings either?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently not.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then we were not quite correct in admitting just now that there are people who, without knowing themselves, know their belongings, while others know their belongings’ belongings. For it seems to be the function of one man and one art to discern all three— <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="133e"/>himself, his belongings, and the belongings of his belongings.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It looks like it.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And anyone who is ignorant of his belongings will be similarly ignorant, I suppose, of the belongings of others.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Quite so.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And if ignorant of others’ affairs, he will be ignorant also of the affairs of states.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> He must be.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then such a man can never be a statesman.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> No, nor an economist either.</said></p></div>
            
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="134">
                <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="134"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="134a"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Nor will he know what he is doing.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, I agree.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And will not he who does not know make mistakes?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> To be sure.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And when he makes mistakes, will he not do ill both in private and in public?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And doing ill he will be wretched?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, very.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And what of those for whom he is doing so?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> They will be wretched also.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then it is impossible to be happy if one is not temperate and good.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Impossible.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="134b"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So it is the bad men who are wretched.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes, very.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And hence it is not he who has made himself rich that is relieved of wretchedness, but he who has made himself temperate.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So it is not walls or warships or arsenals that cities need, Alcibiades, if they are to be happy, nor numbers, nor size, without virtue.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> No, indeed.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And if you are to manage the city’s affairs properly and honorably, you must impart virtue to the citizens.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="134c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But could one possibly impart a thing that one had not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> How, indeed?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then you or anyone else who is to be governor and curator, not merely of himself and his belongings in private, but of the state and its affairs, must first acquire virtue himself.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Hence it is not licence or authority for doing what one pleases that you have to secure to yourself or the state, but justice and temperance.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="134d"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For you and the state, if you act justly and temperately, will act so as to please God.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Naturally.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And, as we were saying in what went before, you will act with your eyes turned on what is divine and bright.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well, and looking thereon you will behold and know both yourselves and your good.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And so you will act aright and well?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="134e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Well now, if you act in this way, I am ready to warrant that you must be happy.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> And I can rely on your warranty.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> But if you act unjustly, with your eyes on the godless and dark, the probability is that your acts will resemble these through your ignorance of yourselves.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is probable.</said></p></div>
                
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="135">                
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> For if a man, my dear Alcibiades, is at liberty to do what he pleases, but is lacking in mind, what is the probable result to him personally, or to the state as well? For instance, if he is sick and at liberty to do what he pleases—without a medical mind, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="135"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="135a"/>but with a despot’s power which prevents anyone from even reproving him—what will be the result? Will not his health, in all likelihood, be shattered?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Again, in a ship, if a man were at liberty to do what he chose, but were devoid of mind and excellence in navigation, do you perceive what must happen to him and his fellow-sailors?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do: they must all perish.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And in just the same way, if a state, or any office or authority, is lacking in excellence or virtue, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="135b"/>it will be overtaken by failure?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> It must.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then it is not despotic power, my admirable Alcibiades, that you ought to secure either to yourself or to the state, if you would be happy, but virtue.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> That is true.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And before getting virtue, to be governed by a superior is better than to govern, for a man as well as a child.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the better is also nobler?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And the nobler more becoming?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Of course.</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="135c"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then it becomes a bad man to be a slave, since it is better.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> So vice is a thing that becomes a slave.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Apparently.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And virtue becomes a free man.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Yes.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And we should shun, my good friend, all slavishness?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Most certainly, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> And do you now perceive how you stand? Are you on the side of the free, or not?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I think I perceive only too clearly.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Then do you know how you may escape from the condition in which you now find yourself? Let us not give it a name, where a handsome person is concerned!</said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="135d"/>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> I do.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> How?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> If it be your wish, Socrates.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> That is not well said, Alcibiades.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, what should I say?</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> If it be God’s will.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Then I say it. And yet I say this besides, that we are like to make a change in our parts, Socrates, so that I shall have yours and you mine. For from this day onward it must be the case that I am your attendant, and you have me always in attendance on you. <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><foreign xml:lang="grc">παιδαγωγεῖν</foreign> is used here simply in the sense of <gloss>following about as personal attendant.</gloss></note></said></p>

<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="135e"/>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> Ah, generous friend! So my love will be just like a stork; for after hatching a winged love in you it is to be cherished in return by its nestling. <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">It was commonly believed that aged storks were fed by younger storks which they had previously hatched and reared.</note></said></p>
<p><said who="#Alcibiades"><label>Alc.</label> Well, that is the position, and I shall begin here and now to take pains over justice.</said></p>
<p><said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> I should like to think you will continue to do so; yet I am apprehensive, not from any distrust of your nature, but in view of the might of the state, lest it overcome both me and you.</said></p></div>
            </div>
        </body></text>

</TEI>