<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>For The Soldier from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="Intro" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What could have been the
        view of my opponents in disregarding the point at issue, and in seeking to traduce my
        character? Is it that they are unaware that their business is to speak on that point? Or,
        though well aware of this, do they consider it will pass unobserved that they have more to
        state on anything than on what is their business? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>That
        those statements are made in a spirit of contempt, not for me, but for the point at issue, I
        clearly understand if, however, they suppose that from mere ignorance you will be induced by
        their aspersions to condemn me, this to me would be a surprise. <milestone n="3"
          unit="section"/>I did indeed suppose, gentlemen of the jury, that I had to face my trial
        on the charge referred, not on my character; but, as my opponents are traducing me, it is
        necessary to deal with all<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Yet, in what follows, we are
          spared the usual commendation of the speaker's character. He means, apparently (see the
          next sentence), the whole story of how he came to be fined.</note> of their points in my
        defence. So then, to begin with, I will inform you as to the writ against me.<milestone
          n="Narr" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>The year before last, after I had arrived in the city, I
        had not yet been in residence for two months when I was enrolled as a soldier. On learning
        what had been done, I at once suspected that I had been enrolled for some improper reason.
        So I went to the general,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Whose duty it was to make up
          lists of citizens of military age, with instructions for specific, and post them on
          statues in the market-place.</note> and pointed out that I had already served in the army;
        but I met with most unfair treatment. I was grossly insulted but, although indignant, I kept
        quiet. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>In my perplexity I consulted one of our citizens as
        to the measures that I should take: I was told that they even threatened to put me in
        prison, on the ground that "Polyaenus had been as long a time in residence as
          Callicrates.”<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Apparently Polyaenus had complained that a
          man named Callicrates, who had not been enlisted, had enjoyed a longer leave at home than
          himself.</note>
        <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>Now my conversation just mentioned had been held at
        Philius's bank: yet Ctesicles and his follow-officers,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
          >i.e., the generals, who made the selection of men for military service.</note> on a
        report from somebody that I was abusing them, although the terms of the law only forbid the
        abuse of a magistrate at session of his court,—decided unlawfully to punish me. They imposed
        the fine, but instead of attempting to exact it, at the expiration of their term of office
        they recorded it on a register which they handed over to the clerks of the Treasury<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In the temple of Pallas on the Acropolis.</note>
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>So much for their operations; but the clerks of the
        Treasury, taking a very different view from theirs, demanded an explanation from the persons
        who had handed over the record, and inquired into the grounds of the charge. Hearing what
        had occurred, and impressed by the strange treatment I had received, they at first urged
        them to let me off, pointing out that it was not reasonable that any of our citizens should
        be registered as public debtors out of personal enmity; then, failing to dissuade them, they
        took upon themselves the risk of a trial before you, and ruled that the penalty was null and
          void<gap/><note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A gap follows in the text, which should show
          that witnesses were called.</note><milestone n="Proof" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Well, that I was let off by the Treasury clerks, you now
        know. But although I consider that merely on the strength of this demonstration I ought to
        stand cleared of the impeachment, I will put in a yet stronger array both of laws and of
        other justifications. Now, please, take the law.<quote type="Law"><title>Law</title></quote>
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>You have heard how the law
        expressly enjoins the punishment of those who utter abuse at a session of the court. But I
        have produced witnesses to the fact that I did not enter the magistrates' hall, and that, as
        the fine was unjustly imposed on me, I neither owe it nor in justice ought to pay it.
          <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>For if it is evident that I did not go into the court,
        and the law enjoins that the fine is to be due from those who misbehave inside it, it is
        manifest that I have done no wrong, but because of enmity, and for no such act, have been
        fined against all reason. They knew in their own hearts that they had done wrong; <milestone
          n="11" unit="section"/>for they neither submitted their act to investigation,<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">At the investigation of their acts (<foreign xml:lang="greek"
            >eu)qu/nai</foreign> held by <foreign xml:lang="greek">eu)/qunoi</foreign>, officials
          chosen by lot from the tribes), to which all magistrates had to submit, they omitted this
          fine, on the ground that the matter had been referred to the Treasury.</note> nor went
        into a law-court to get their proceedings confirmed by a vote. However, supposing they had
        been correct in imposing a fine on me, and had got the imposition confirmed in your court, I
        should stand fairly cleared of the impeachment by the release of the Treasury clerks.
          <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>For if they were not competent to exact or remit it,
        being lawfully fined I should reasonably owe the payment; but if they have power to remit,
        subject to rendering an account of their proceedings, they will easily be visited with the
        proper penalty for any wrong they have done. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>Of the manner
        in which my name was handed over, and the fine imposed on me, you are now informed: but you
        must be apprised, not only of the charge referred, but also of the pretext for this enmity.
        I had made friends with Sostratus before their enmity began, because I knew he had done
        remarkable service to the State. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>I became well-known
        through his personal influence, but did not make use of it either to avenge myself on an
        enemy or to serve a friend: for while he lived I was necessarily inactive on account of my
        age and when he passed away I injured none of my accusers either in word or in deed, and I
        can give such an account of myself as will show that in justice ought much rather to receive
        benefits than ill-treatment from my opponents. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Well, the
        circumstances that I have mentioned had the effect of accumulating their anger, though they
        had no real excuse for enmity. And so, having taken their oaths to enroll only those who had
        not served in the field, they violated those oaths, and then brought my case before the
        people for decision on a capital charge,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The penalty being
          the loss of civic rights consequent on confiscation.</note>
        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>after having fined me for abusing the magistrates, and
        having utterly disregarded the claims of justice they were exerting themselves to injure me
        on any sort of plea, and they would have stopped at nothing so long as they could do me
        grievous injury and also win great advantage for themselves, seeing that when they are sure
        of neither of these ends they make everything of less account than their injustice.
          <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>Nay, the men who showed their contempt for the people of
        your city disdained also to show fear of the gods: so reckless and lawless were their
        proceedings that they did not even attempt to defend their actions; and finally, considering
        the revenge that they had taken on me insufficient, they took the last step of expelling me
        from the city.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">He means, by implication, if their suit for
          the fine should be successful.</note>
        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>In this mood of lawless violence they have not cared at
        all to conceal their injustice, but have summoned me here again on the same charge; and
        although I have done no wrong, they denounce me and abuse me with a shower of calumnies that
        have no connection with the tenor of my life, but are conformable and habitual to their own
          character.<milestone n="Concl" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>These persons, then, are endeavoring on any sort of plea
        to get me cast in this suit. But you must neither be incited by their calumnies to condemn
        me, nor invalidate the decision of those who have acted on a better, and on a just,
          consideration.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">He refers to the treasury
          officials.</note> For their action was entirely in accordance with the laws and fair
        dealing, and it is plain that they have committed no injustice, but made most account of
        what is just. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>The injustice of these men only caused me a
        moderate annoyance, as I considered it ordained that one should harm one's enemies and serve
        one's friends;<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">This doctrine was accepted by Greek thought
          as part of the fixed order of things: it appears in <bibl n="Hes. WD 351">Hes. WD
            351</bibl>, <bibl n="Pind. P. 2">Pind. P. 2.83</bibl>, and a saying of Simonides to this
          effect is taken by Plato as the starting-point of his discussion of justice in <bibl
            n="Plat. Rep. 1.332">Plat. Rep. 1.332</bibl>.</note> but to be derived of justice at
        your hands would cause me a far deeper distress. For it will be thought that my evil plight
        is due, not to enmity, but to an evil condition of the State. <milestone n="21"
          unit="section"/>Professedly, indeed, I am on trial for the matter<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">Namely, confiscation.</note> of this writ, but actually for my citizenship. If
        I obtain justice—and I have confidence in your verdict—I may remain in this city; but if the
        summons of these men should lead to my unjust conviction, I should run away. For with what
        hope to bear me up must I mingle with the citizens, or with what purpose in life, when I
        knew the zeal of my opponents, and could not tell where to look for any of my just rights?
          <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>Put justice, therefore, above everything else; reflect
        that you grant pardon even for glaring acts of injustice; and do not allow those who are
        guilty of no injustice to be unjustly entangled in the greatest misfortunes.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
