<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Fragments </title>
        <author>Epictetus</author>
        <editor role="editor" n="transl">George Long</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>



      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Discourses of Epictetus, with the Encheridion and Fragments</title>
            <author>Epictetus</author>
            <respStmt>
              <name>George Long</name>
              <resp>translator</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
              <publisher>George Bell and Sons</publisher>
              <date>1890</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="silent" status="high">
          <!--&Perseus.OCR;-->
          <p>Perseus OCR</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="text"/>
        <refState unit="book"/>
        <refState n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="text"/>
        <refState n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
        <language ident="la">Latin</language>
        <language ident="de">German</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>31-Oct-03</date>
<respStmt><name>AEM</name><resp>markup</resp></respStmt>
<item>initial markup
</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
      <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <head>Fragments of Epictetus</head>
      <div type="book" n="0">
        <p>THESE Fragments are entitled <title xml:lang="la">Epicteti Fragmenta maxime ex Ioanne
            Stobaeo, Antonio, et Maximo collecta</title> (ed. Schweig.). There are some notes and
          emendations on the Fragments; and a short dissertation on them by Schweighaeuser.</p>
        <p>Nothing is known of Stobaeus nor of his time, except the fact that he has preserved some
          extracts of an ethical kind from the New Platonist Hierocles, who lived about the middle
          of the fifth century A. D.; and it is therefore concluded that Stobaeus lived after
          Hierocles. The fragments attributed to Epictetus are preserved by Stobaeus in his work
          entitled <foreign xml:lang="grc">'*anfolo/gion</foreign>, or Florilegium or Sermones.</p>
        <p>Antonius Monachus, a Greek monk, also made a Florilegium, entitled Melissa (the bee). His
          date is uncertain, but it was certainly much later than the time of Stobaeus.</p>
        <p>Maximus, also named the monk, and reverenced as a saint, is said to have been a native of
          Constantinople, and born about A. D. <date when="0580">580</date>.</p>
        <p>Some of the Fragments contained in the edition of Schweighaeuser are certainly not from
          Epictetus. Many of the fragments are obscure; but they are translated as accurately as I
          can translate them, and the reader must give to them such meaning as he can. <pb n="406"
          /></p>
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p>THE life which is implicated with fortune (depends on fortune) is like a winter
            torrent: for it is turbulent, and full of mud, and difficult to cross, and tyrannical,
            and noisy, and of short duration.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p>A soul which is conversant with virtue is like an ever flowing source, for it is pure
            and tranquil and potable and sweet<note anchored="true">Consult the Lexicons for this
              sense of <foreign xml:lang="grc">no/stimos</foreign>.</note> and communicative
            (social), and rich and harmless and free from mischief.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p>If you wish to be good, first believe that you are bad.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p>It is better to do wrong seldom and to own it, and to act right for the most part, than
            seldom to admit that you have done wrong and to do wrong often.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p>Check (punish) your passions (<foreign xml:lang="grc">pa/fh</foreign>), that you may
            not be punished by them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p>Do not so much be ashamed of that (disgrace) which proceeds from men's opinion as fly
            from that which comes from the truth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p>If you wish to be well spoken of, learn to speak well (of others): and when you have
            learned to speak well of them, try to act well, and so you will reap the fruit of being
            well spoken of.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p>Freedom and slavery, the one is the name of virtue, and the other of vice: and both are
            acts of the will. But where there is no will, neither of them touches (affects) <pb
              n="407"/> these things. But the soul is accustomed to be master of the body, and the
            things which belong to the body have no share in the will. For no man is a slave who is
            free in his will.<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p>It is an evil chain, fortune (a chain) of the body, and vice of the soul. For he who is
            loose (free) in the body, but bound in the soul is a slave: but on the contrary he who
            is bound in the body, but free (unbound) in the soul, is free.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p>The bond of the body is loosened by nature through death, and by vice through
              money:<note anchored="true"><quote>He does not say this 'that it is bad if a man by
                money should redeem himself from bonds,' but he means that 'even a bad man, if he
                has money, can redeem himself from the bonds of the body and so secure his
                liberty.'</quote> Schweig.</note> but the bond of the soul is loosened by learning,
            and by experience and by discipline.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p>If you wish to live without perturbation and with pleasure, try to have all who dwell
            with you good. And you will have them good, if you instruct the willing, and dismiss
            those who are unwilling (to be taught): for there will fly away together with those who
            have fled away both wickedness and slavery; and there will be left with those who remain
            with you goodness and liberty.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p>It is a shame for those who sweeten drink with the gifts of the bees, by badness to
            embitter reason which is the gift of the gods.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p>No man who loves money, and loves pleasure, and loves fame, also loves mankind, but
            only he who loves virtue. <pb n="408"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p>As you would not choose to sail in a large and decorated and gold-laden ship (or ship
            ornamented with gold), and to be drowned; so do not choose to dwell in a large and
            costly house and to be disturbed (by cares).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p>When we have been invited to a banquet, we take what is set before us: but if a guest
            should ask the host to set before him fish or sweet cakes, he would be considered to be
            an unreasonable fellow. But in the world we ask the Gods for what they do not give; and
            we do this though the things are many which they have given.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p>They are amusing fellows, said he (Epictetus), who are proud of the things which are
            not in our power. A man says, I am better than you, for I possess much land, and you are
            wasting with hunger. Another says, I am of consular rank. Another says, I am a
            Procurator (<foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pi/tropos</foreign>). Another, I have curly hair.
            But a horse does not say to a horse, I am superior to you, for I possess much fodder,
            and much barley, and my bits are of gold and my harness is embroidered: but he says, I
            am swifter than you. And every animal is better or worse from his own merit (virtue) or
            his own badness. Is there then no virtue in man only? and must we look to the hair, and
            our clothes and to our ancestors?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p>The sick are vexed with the physician who gives them no advice, and think that he has
            despaired of them. But why should they not have the same feeling towards the
            philosopher, and think that he has despaired of their coming to a sound state of mind,
            if he says nothing at all that is useful to a man? <pb n="409"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p>Those who are well constituted in the body endure both heat and cold: and so those who
            are well constituted in the soul endure both anger and grief and excessive joy and the
            other affects.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p>Examine yourself whether you wish to be rich or to be happy. If you wish to be rich,
            you should know that it is neither a good thing nor at all in your power: but if you
            wish to be happy, you should know that it is both a good thing and in your power, for
            the one is a temporary loan of fortune, and happiness comes from the will.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p>As when you see a viper or an asp or a scorpion in an ivory or golden box, you do not
            on account of the costliness of the material love it or think it happy, but because the
            nature of it is pernicious, you turn away from it and loathe it; so when you shall see
            vice dwelling in wealth and in the swollen fulness of fortune, be not struck by the
            splendour of the material, but despise the false character of the morals.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p>Wealth is not one of the good things; great expenditure is one of the bad; moderation
              (<foreign xml:lang="grc">swfrosu/nh</foreign>)is one of the good things. And
            moderation invites to frugality and the acquisition of good things: but wealth invites
            to great expenditure and draws us away from moderation. It is difficult then for a rich
            man to be moderate, or for a moderate man to be rich.<note anchored="true">'How hardly
              shall they that have riches enter the kingdom of God.' Mark x. 23 (Mrs. Carter). This
              expression in Mark sets forth the danger of riches, a fact which all men know who use
              their observation. In the next verse the truth is expressed in this form, 'How hard it
              is for them that trust in riches to enter into the kingdom of God.' The Stoics viewed
              wealth as among the things which are indifferent, neither good nor bad.</note>
            <pb n="410"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p>As if you were begotten or born in a ship, you would not be eager to be the master of
            it (<foreign xml:lang="grc">kubernh/ths</foreign>), so—.<note anchored="true">The other
              member of the comparison has been omitted by some accident in the MSS. Wolf in his
              Latin version supplied by conjecture the omission in this manner: <quote xml:lang="la"
                >'ita neque in terris divitiae tibi expe tendae sunt. '</quote> Schweig.</note> For
            neither there (in the ship) will the ship naturally be connected with you, nor wealth in
            the other case; but reason is every where naturally connected with you. As then reason
            is a thing which naturally belongs to you and is born in you, consider this also as
            specially your own and take care of it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p>If you had been born among the Persians, you would not have wished to live in Hellas
            (Greece), but to have lived in Persia happy: so if you are born in poverty, why do you
            seek to grow rich, and why do you not remain in poverty and be happy?<note
              anchored="true">To some persons the comparison will not seem apt. Also the notion that
              every man should be taught to rise above the condition in which he is born is, in the
              opinion of some persons, a better teaching I think that it is not. Few persons have
              the talents and the character which enable them to rise from a low condition; and the
              proper lesson for them is to) stay in the condition in which they are born and to be
              content with it. Those who have the power of rising from a low condition will rise
              whether they are advised to attempt it or not: and generally they will not be able to
              rise without doing something useful to society. Those who have ability sufficient to
              raise themselves from a low estate, and at the same time to do it to the damage of
              society, are perhaps only few, but certainly there are such persons. They rise by
              ability, by the use of fraud, by bad means almost innumerable. They gain wealth, they
              fill high places, they disturb society, they are plagues and pests, and the world
              looks on sometimes with stupid admiration until death removes the dazzling and
              deceitful image, and honest men breathe freely again <p>In the Church of England
                Catechism there are two answers to two questions, one on our duty to God, the other
                on our duty to our neighbour. Both the answers would be accepted by Epictetus,
                except such few words as were not applicable to the circumstances of his age. The
                second answer ends with the words 'to learn and labour to get mine own living and to
                do my duty in that state of life unto which it shall please God to call
              me.'</p></note>
            <pb n="411"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p>As it is better to lie compressed it a narrow bed and be healthy than to be tossed with
            disease on a broad couch, so also it is better to contract yourself within a small
            competence and to be happy than to have a great fortune and to be wretched.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p>It is not poverty which produces sorrow, but desire; nor does wealth release from fear,
            but reason (the power of reasoning, <foreign xml:lang="grc">logismo/s</foreign>). If
            then you acquire this power of reasoning, you will neither desire wealth nor complain of
            poverty.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p>Neither is a horse elated nor proud of his manger and trappings and coverings, nor a
            bird of his little shreds of cloth and of his nest: but both of them are proud of their
            swiftness, one proud of the swiftness of the feet, and the other of the wings. Do you
            also then not be greatly proud of your food and dress and, in short, of any external
            things, but be proud of your integrity and good deeds (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >eu)poii/a</foreign>).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p>To live well differs from living extravagantly: for the first comes from moderation and
            a sufficiency (<foreign xml:lang="grc">au)tarkei/as</foreign>) and good order and
            propriety and frugality; but the other comes from intemperance and luxury and want of
            order and want of propriety. And the end (the consequence) of the one is true praise,
            but of the other blame. If then you wish to live well, do not seek to be commended for
            profuse expenditure.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p>Let the measure to you of all food and drink be the first satisfying of the desire; and
            let the food and the pleasure be the desire (appetite) itself: and you will neither take
            more than is necessary, nor will you want cooks, and you will be satisfied with the
            drink that comes in the way. <pb n="412"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p>Make your manner of eating neither luxurious nor gloomy, but lively and frugal, that
            the soul may not be perturbed through being deceived by the pleasures of the body, and
            that it may despise them; and that the soul may not be injured by the enjoyment of
            present luxury, and the body may not afterwards suffer from disease.<note
              anchored="true">Mrs. Carter says, 'I have not translated this fragment, because I do
              not understand it.' Schweighaeuser says also that he does not understand it. I have
              given what may be the meaning; but it is not an exact translation, which in the
              present state of the text is not possible.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p>Take care that the food which you put into the stomach does not fatten (nourish) you,
            but the cheerfulness of the mind: for the food is changed into excrement, and ejected,
            and the urine also flows out at the same time; but the cheerfulness, even if the soul be
            separated, remains always uncorrupted.<note anchored="true">This fragment is perhaps
              more corrupt than XXIX. See Schweig.'s note. I see no sense in <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                >e)/painos</foreign>, and I have used the word <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                >ou)=ros</foreign>, which is a possible reading. The conclusion appears quite
              unintelligible.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p>In banquets remember that you entertain two guests, body and soul: and whatever you
            shall have given to the body you soon eject: but what you shall have given to the soul,
            you keep always.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p>Do not mix anger with profuse expenditure and serve them up to your guests. Profusion
            which fills the body is quickly gone; but anger sinks into the soul and remains for a
            long time. Consider then that you be not transported with anger and insult your guests
            at a great expense; but rather please them with frugality and by gentle behaviour.<note
              anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note>
            <pb n="413"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <p>In your banquets (meals) take care that those who serve (your slaves) are not more than
            those who are served; for it is foolish for many souls (persons) to wait on a few
            couches (seats).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <p>It is best if even in the preparations for a feast you take a part of the labour, and
            at the enjoyment of the food, while you are feasting, you share with those who serve the
            things which are before you. But if such behaviour be unsuitable to the occasion,
            remember that you are served when you are not labouring by those who are labouring, when
            you are eating by those who are not eating, when you are drinking by those who are not
            drinking, while you are talking by those who are silent, while you are at ease by those
            who are under constraint; and if you remember this, you will neither being heated with
            anger be guilty of any absurdity yourself, nor by irritating another will you cause any
              mischief.<note anchored="true">I am not sure about the exact meaning of the
              conclusion. See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p>Quarrelling and contention are every where foolish, and particularly in talk over wine
            they are unbecoming: for a man who is drunk could not teach a man who is sober, nor on
            the other hand could a drunken man be convinced by a sober man. But where there is not
            sobriety, it will appear that to no purpose have you laboured for the result of
              persuasion.<note anchored="true">This is not a translation of the conclusion. Perhaps
              it is some. thing like the meaning. See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p>Grasshoppers (cicadae) are musical: snails have no voice. Snails have pleasure in being
            moist, but grasshoppers in being dry. Next the dew invites forth the snails and for this
            they crawl out: but on the contrary the sun when he is hot, rouses the grasshoppers and
            they sing in the sun. Therefore if you wish to be a musical <pb n="414"/> man and to
            harmonize well with others, when over the cups the soul is bedewed with wine, at that
            time do not permit the soul to go forth and to be polluted; but when in company
            (parties) it is fired by reason, then bid her to matter oracular words and to sing the
            oracles of justice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p>Examine in three ways him who is talking with you, as superior, or as inferior, or as
            equal: and if he is supe- rior, you should listen to him and be convinced by him: but if
            he is inferior, you should convince him; if he is equal, you should agree with him; and
            thus you will never be guilty of being quarrelsome.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p>It is better by assenting to truth to conquer opinion, than by assenting to opinion to
            be conquered by truth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p>If you seek truth, you will not seek by every means to gain a victory; and if you have
            found truth, you will have the gain of not being defeated.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p>Truth conquers with itself; but opinion conquers among those who are external.<note
              anchored="true">This is not clear.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p>It is better to live with one free man and to be without fear and free, than to be a
            slave with many.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <p>What you avoid suffering, do not attempt to make others suffer. You avoid slavery: take
            care that others are not your slaves. For if you endure to have a slave, you appear to
            be a slave yourself first. For vice has no community with virtue, nor freedom with
            slavery. <pb n="415"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p>As he who is in health would not choose to be served (ministered to) by the sick, nor
            for those who dwell with him to be sick, so neither would a free man endure to be served
            by slaves, or for those who live with him to be slaves.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p>Whoever you are who wish to be not among the number of slaves, release yourself from
            slavery: and you will be free, if you are released from desire. For neither Aristides
            nor Epaminondas nor Lycurgus through being rich and served by slaves were named the one
            just, the other a god, and the third a saviour, but because they were poor and delivered
            Hellas (Greece) from slavery.<note anchored="true">It is observed that the term 'just'
              applies to Aristides; the term 'god' was given to Lycurgus by the Pythia or Delphic
              oracle; the name 'saviour' by his own citizens to Epaminondas.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p>If you wish your house to be well managed, imitate the Spartan Lycurgus. For as he did
            not fence his city with walls, but fortified the inhabitants by virtue and preserved the
            city always free;<note anchored="true">Schweig. quotes Polybius ix. 10, 1, 'a city is
              not adorned by external things, but by the virtue of those who dwell in it.' Alcaeus
              says, 22, Bergk, Poetae Lyrici Graeci, <date when="1843">1843</date>,— <quote
                xml:lang="grc"><lg>
                  <l>ou) li/foi</l>
                  <l>teixe/wn eu)= dedoma/menoi,</l>
                  <l>a)ll' a)/ndres to/lios pu/rgos a)rh/i+oi</l>
                </lg></quote></note> so do you not cast around (your house) a large court and raise
            high towers, but strengthen the dwellers by good will and fidelity and friendship, and
            then nothing harmful will enter it, not even if the whole band of wickedness shall array
            itself against it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p>Do not hang your house round with tablets and pictures, but decorate it with moderation
              (<foreign xml:lang="grc">swfrosu/nh</foreign>): for the one is of a foreign
            (unsuitable) kind, and a temporary deception of the eyes; but the other is a natural and
            indelible, and perpetual ornament of the house. <pb n="416"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p>Instead of an herd of oxen, endeavour to assemble herds of friends in your house.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p>As a wolf resembles a dog, so both a flatterer, and an adulterer and a parasite,
            resemble a friend. Take care then that instead of watch dogs you do not without knowing
            it let in mischievous wolves.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p>To be eager that your house should be admired by being whitened with gypsum, is the
            mark of a man who has no taste: but to set off (decorate) our morals by the goodness of
            our communication (social habits) is the mark of a man who is a lover of beauty and a
            lover of man.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p>If you begin by admiring little things,<note anchored="true">Schweig. says that in the
              reading <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)a\n fauma/zh|s ta\ mikra\ prw=ton</foreign> the word
                <foreign xml:lang="grc">prw=ton</foreign> is wanting in four MSS., and that Schow
              omitted <foreign xml:lang="grc">prw=ton</foreign>, and that he has followed Schow. But
                <foreign xml:lang="grc">pow=ton</foreign> is in Schweig.'s text.</note> you will not
            be thought worthy of great things: but if you despise the little, you will be greatly
            admired.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p>Nothing is smaller (meaner) than love of pleasure, and love of gain and pride. Nothing
            is superior to magnani- mity, and gentleness, and love of mankind, and beneficence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p>They bring forward (they name, they mention) the peevish philosophers (the Stoics),
            whose opinion it is that pleasure is not a thing conformable to nature, but is a thing
            which is consequent on the things which are conformable to nature, as justice,
            temperance, freedom. What <pb n="417"/> then? is the soul pleased and made tranquil by
            the pleasures of the body which are smaller, as Epicurus says; and is it not pleased
            with its own good things, which are the greatest? And indeed nature has given to me
            modesty, and I blush much when I think of saying any thing base (indecent). This motion
            (feeling) does not permit me to make (consider) pleasure the good and the end (purpose)
            of life.<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p>In Rome the women have in their hands Plato's Polity (the Republic), because it allows
            (advises) the women to be common, for they attend only to the words of Plato, not to his
            meaning. Now he does not recommend marriage and one man to cohabit with one woman, and
            then that the women should be common: but he takes away such a marriage, and introduces
            another kind of marriage. And in fine, men are pleased with finding excuses for their
            faults. Yet philosophy says that we ought not to stretch out even a finger without a
              reason.<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p>Of pleasures those which occur most rarely give the greatest delight.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p>If a man should transgress moderation, the things which give the greatest delight would
            become the things which give the least.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p>It is just to commend Agrippinus for this reason, that though he was a man of the
            highest worth, he never praised himself; but even if another person praised him, he
            would blush. And he was such a man (Epictetus said) that he would write in praise of any
            thing disagreeable that befel him; if it was a fever, he would write of a fever; if he
            was disgraced, he would write of disgrace; if he were banished, of banishment. And on
            one occasion (he mentioned) when he was going to dine, a messenger <pb n="418"/> brought
            him news that Nero commanded him to go into banishment; on which Agrippinus said, Well
            then we will dine at Aricia.<note anchored="true">See i. 1, note 13 and 14.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p>Diogenes said that no labour was good, unless the end (purpose) of it was courage and
            strength (<foreign xml:lang="grc">to/nos</foreign>) of the soul, but not of the
            body.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p>As a true balance is neither corrected by a true balance nor judged by a false balance,
            so also a just judge is neither corrected by just judges nor is he judged (condemned) by
            unjust judges.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p>As that which is straight does not need that which is straight, so neither does the
            just need that which is just.<note anchored="true">Rather obscure, says Schweig. Compare
              Frag. lviii. and lxvi</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p>Do not give judgment in one court (of justice) before you have been tried yourself
            before justice.<note anchored="true">Compare lviii. Schweig.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p>If you wish to make your judgments just, listen not to (regard not) any of those who
            are parties (to the suit), nor to those who plead in it, but listen to justice
            itself.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p>You will fail (stumble) least in your judgments, if you yourself fail (stumble) least
            in your life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p>It is better when you judge justly to be blamed un. deservedly by him who has been
            condemned than when you judge unjustly to be justly blamed by (before) nature.<note
              anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note>
            <pb n="419"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p>As the stone which tests the gold is not at all tested itself by the gold, so it is
            with him who has the faculty of judging.<note anchored="true">Schweig. suggests that
                <foreign xml:lang="grc">o( lo/gos</foreign> has been omitted before the words
                <foreign xml:lang="grc">o( to\ krith/rion e)/xwn</foreign>. <p>See the fragment of
                Chilo on the stone which tries gold. Bergk, Poetae Lyrici Graeci, ed. 1, p.
              568.</p></note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p>It is shameful for the judge to be judged by others.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p>As nothing is straighter than that which is straight, so nothing is juster than that
            which is just.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p>Who among us does not admire the act of Lycurgus the Lacedaemonian? For after he was
            maimed in one of his eyes by one of the citizens, and the young man: was delivered up to
            him by the people that he might punish him as he chose, Lycurgus spared him: and after
            instructing him and making him a good man he brought him into the theatre. When the
            Lacedaemonians expressed their surprise, Lycurgus said, I received from you this youth
            when he was insolent and violent: I restore him to you gentle and a good citizen.<note
              anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p>Pittacus after being wronged by a certain person and having the power of punishing him
            let him go, saying, Forgiveness is better than revenge: for forgiveness is the sign of a
            gentle nature, but revenge the sign of a savage nature.<note anchored="true">Pittacus
              was one of the seven wise men, as they are named. Some authorities state that he lived
              in the seventh century B. C. By this maxim he anticipated one of the Christian
              doctrines by six centuries.</note>
            <pb n="420"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p>But before every thing this is the act of nature to bind together and to fit together
            the movement towards the appearance of that which is becoming (fit) and useful.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <p>To suppose that we shall be easily despised by others, if we do not in every way do
            some damage to those who first show us their hostility, is the mark of very ignoble and
            foolish men: for (thus) we affirm that the man is considered to be contemptible because
            of his inability to do damage; but much rather is a man considered to be contemptible
            because of his inability to do what is good (useful).<note anchored="true">See Mrs.
              Carter's note, who could only translate part of this fragment: and Schweig.'s
              emendation and note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p>When you are attacking (or going to attack) any person violently and with threats,
            remember to say to yourself first, that you are (by nature) mild (gentle); and if you do
            nothing savage, you will continue to live without repentance and without blame.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p>A man ought to know that it is not easy for him to have an opinion (or fixed
            principle), if he does not daily say the same things, and hear the same things, and at
            the same time apply them to life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p> [Nicias was so fond of labour (assiduous) that he often asked his slaves, if he had
            bathed and if he had dined.]<note anchored="true">LXXIII.—LXXV.—Schweig. has inclosed
              these three fragments in [ ]. They are not from Epictetus, but from Plutarch's
              treatise <foreign xml:lang="grc">ai) presbute/rm politeute/on.</foreign></note>
            <pb n="421"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p> [The slaves of Archimedes used to drag him by force from his table of diagrams and
            anoint him; and Archimedes would then draw his figures on his own body when it had been
            anointed.]</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p>[Lampis the shipowner being asked how he acquired his wealth, answered, With no
            difficulty, my great wealth; but my small wealth (my first gains), with much
            labour.]</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p>Solon having been asked by Periander over their cups (<foreign xml:lang="grc">para\
              po/ton</foreign>), since he happened to say nothing, Whether he was silent for want of
            words or because he was a fool, replied: No fool is able to be silent over his
              cups.<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p>Attempt on every occasion to provide for nothing so much as that which is safe: for
            silence is safer than speaking. And omit speaking whatever is without sense and
            reason.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p>As the fire-lights in harbours by a few pieces of dry- wood raise a great flame and
            give sufficient help to ships which are wandering on the sea; so also an illustrious man
            in a state which is tempest-tossed, while he is himself satisfied with a few things does
            great services to his citizens.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p>As if you attempted to manage a ship, you would certainly learn completely the
            steersman's art, [so if you would administer a state, learn the art of managing a
            state]. For it will be in your power, as in the first case to manage the whole ship, so
            in the second case also to manage the whole state.<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s
              note. There is evidently something omitted in the text, which omission is supplied by
              the words inclosed thus [ ]. Schweig. proposes to change <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                >kuberna=|n</foreign> into <foreign xml:lang="grc">kubista=n</foreign>. See his
              remark on <foreign xml:lang="grc">pa=san . . po/lin</foreign>. Perhaps he is
              right.</note>
            <pb n="422"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p>If you propose to adorn your city by the dedication of offerings (monuments), first
            dedicate to yourself (decorate yourself with) the noblest offering of gentleness, and
            justice and beneficence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p>You will do the greatest services to the state, if you shall raise not the roofs of the
            houses, but the souls of the citizens: for it is better that great souls should dwell in
            small houses than for mean slaves to lurk in great houses.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p>Do not decorate the walls of your house with the valuable stones from Euboea and
            Sparta; but adorn the minds (breasts) of the citizens and of those who administer the
            state with the instruction which comes from Hellas (Greece). For states are well
            governed by the wisdom judgement) of men, but not by stone and wood.<note
              anchored="true">The marbles of Carystus in Euboea and the marbles of Taenarum near
              Sparta were used by the Romans, and perhaps by the Greeks also, for architectural
              decoration. (Strabo, x. 416, and viii. 367, ed. Cas.) Compare <cit>
                <bibl n="Hor. Carm. 2.18.1">Horace, Carm. ii. 18.</bibl>
                <quote xml:lang="la"><lg>
                    <l>Non ebur neque aureum</l>
                    <l>Mea renidet in domo lacunar, etc.</l>
                  </lg></quote>
              </cit></note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p>As, if you wished to breed lions, you would not care about the costliness of their
            dens, but about the habits of the animals; so, if you attempt to preside over your
            citizens, be not so anxious about the costliness of the buildings as careful about the
            manly character of those who dwell in them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <note anchored="true">This fragment contains a lesson for the administration of a state.
            The good must be protected, and the bad must be improved by dis- cipline and
            punishment.</note>
          <p>As a skilful horse-trainer does not feed (only) the good colts and allow to starve
            those who are disobedient to the rein, but he feeds both alike, and chastises the one
            more <pb n="423"/> and forces him to be equal to the other:<note anchored="true">I am
              not sure what <foreign xml:lang="grc">me/rei</foreign> means.</note> so also a careful
            man and one who is skilled in political power, attempts to treat well those citizens who
            have a good character, but does not will that those who are of a contrary character
            should be ruined at once; and he in no manner grudges both of them their food, but he
            teaches and urges on with more vehemence him who resists reason and law.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p>As a goose is not frightened by cackling nor a sheep by bleating, so let not the
            clamour of a senseless multitude alarm you.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <note anchored="true">See in the Index Graecitatis the word <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >duswpei=n</foreign></note>
          <p>As a multitude, when they without reason demand of you any thing of your own, do not
            disconcert you, so dc not be moved from your purpose even by a rabble when they unjustly
            attempt to move you.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p>What is due to the state pay as quickly as you can, and you will never be asked for
            that which is not due.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p>As the sun does not wait for prayers and incantations to be induced to rise, but
            immediately shines and is saluted by all: so do you also not wait for clappings of
            hands, and shouts and praise to be induced to do good, but be a doer of good
            voluntarily, and you will be beloved as much as the sun.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p>Neither should a ship rely on one small anchor, nor should life rest on a single
            hope.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p>We ought to stretch our legs and stretch our hopes only to that which is possible. <pb
              n="424"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="91">
          <p>When Thales was asked what is most universal, he answered, Hope, for hope stays with
            those who have nothing else.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="92">
          <p>It is more necessary to heal the soul than the body, for to die is better than to live
            a bad life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="93">
          <p>Pyrrho used to say that there is no difference between dying and living: and a man said
            to him, Why then do you not die? Pyrrho replied, Because there is no difference.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="94">
          <note anchored="true">Compare Xenophon, <bibl n="Xen. Mem. 1.4.17">Memorab. i. 4,
              17</bibl>. <p>The body is here, and elsewhere in Epictetus, considered as an
              instrument, which another uses who is not the body; and that which so uses the body
              must be something which is capable of using the body and a power which possesses what
              we name intelligence and consciousness. Our bodies, as Bishop Butler says, are what we
              name matter, and differ from other matter only in being more closely connected with us
              than other matter. It would be easy to pass from these notions to the notion that this
              intelligence and power, or to use a common word. the soul, is something which exists
              independent of the body, though we only know the soul while it acts within and on the
              body, and by the body.</p></note>
          <p>Admirable is nature, and, as Xenophon says, a lover of animated beings. The body then,
            which is of all things the most unpleasant and the most foul (dirty), we love and take
            care of; for if we were obliged for five days only to take care of our neighbour's body,
            we should not be able to endure it. Consider then what a thing it would be to rise in
            the morning and rub the teeth of another, and after doing some of the necessary offices
            to wash those parts. In truth it is wonderful that we love a thing to which we perform
            such services every day. I fill this bag, and then I empty it;<note anchored="true">This
              bag is the body, or that part of it which holds the food which is taken into the
              mouth.</note> what is more troublesome? But I must act as the servant of God. For this
            reason I remain <pb n="425"/> (here), and I endure to wash this miserable body, to feed
            it and to clothe it. But when I was younger, God imposed on me also another thing, and I
            submitted to it. Why then do you not submit, when Nature who has given us this body
            takes it away? I love the body, you may say. Well, as I said just now, Nature gave you
            also this love of the body: but Nature says, Leave it now, and have no more trouble
            (with it).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="95">
          <p>When a man dies young, he blames the gods. When he is old and does not die, he blames
            the gods because he suffers when he ought to have already ceased from suffering. And
            nevertheless, when death approaches, he wishes to live, and sends to the physician and
            intreats him to omit no care or trouble. Wonderful, he said, are men, who are neither
            willing to live nor to die.<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s excellent note on this
              fragment. There is manifestly a defect in the text, which Schweig.'s note
              supplies.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="96">
          <p>To the longer life and the worse, the shorter life, if it is better, ought by all means
            to be preferred.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="97">
          <p>When we are children our parents deliver us to a paedagogue to take care on all
            occasions that we suffer no harm. But when we are become men, God delivers us to our
            innate conscience (<foreign xml:lang="grc">suneidh/sei</foreign>) to take care of us.
            This guardianship then we must in no way despise, for we shall both displease God and be
            enemies to our own conscience.<note anchored="true">Mrs. Carter suggests that <foreign
                xml:lang="grc">a)pa/reston</foreign> in the text should be <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                >a)pa/restoi</foreign>: and so Schweig. has it.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="98">
          <p>[We ought to use wealth as the material for some act, not for every act alike.] <pb
              n="426"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="99">
          <p>[Virtue then should be desired by all men more than wealth which is dangerous to the
            foolish; for the wickedness of men is increased by wealth. And the more a man is without
            sense, the more violent is he in excess, for he has the means of satisfying his mad
            desire for pleasures.<note anchored="true"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="100">
          <p>What we ought not to do, we should not even think of doing.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="101">
          <p>Deliberate much before saying or doing anything, for you will not have the power of
            recalling what has been said or done.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="102">
          <p>Every place is safe to him who lives with justice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="103">
          <p>Crows devour the eyes of the dead, when the dead have no longer need of them. But
            flatterers destroy the souls of the living and blind their eyes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="104">
          <p>The anger of an ape and the threats of a flatterer should be considered as the
            same.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="105">
          <p>Listen to those who wish to advise what is useful, but not to those who are eager to
            flatter on all occasions; for the first really see what is useful, but the second look
            to that which agrees with the opinion of those who possess power, and imitating the
            shadows of bodies they assent to what is said by the powerful. <pb n="427"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="106">
          <p>The man who gives advice ought first to have regard to the modesty and character
            (reputation) of those whom he advises; for those who have lost the capacity of blushing
            are incorrigible.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="107">
          <p>To admonish is better than to reproach: for admonition is mild and friendly, but
            reproach is harsh and insulting; and admonition corrects those who are doing wrong, but
            reproach only convicts them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="108">
          <p>Give of what you have to strangers (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ce/nois</foreign>) and to
            those who have need: for he who gives not to him who wants, will not receive himself
            when he wants.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="109">
          <p>A pirate had been cast on the land and was perishing through the tempest. A man took
            clothing and gave it to him, and brought the pirate into his house, and supplied him
            with every thing else that was necessary. When the man was reproached by a person for
            doing kindness to the bad, he replied, I have shown this regard not to the man, but to
              mankind.<note anchored="true">Mrs. Carter in her notes often refers to the Christian
              precepts, but she says nothing here. The fragment is not from Epictetus; but, whether
              the story is true or not, it is an example of the behaviour of a wise and good
              man.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="110">
          <p>A man should choose (pursue) not every pleasure, but the pleasure which leads to the
              good.<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s interpretation and emendation. I doubt if he
              is right.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="111">
          <p>It is the part of a wise man to resist pleasures, but of a foolish man to be a slave to
            them. <pb n="428"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="112">
          <p>Pleasure, like a kind of bait, is thrown before (in front of) every thing which is
            really bad, and easily allures greedy souls to the hook of perdition.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="113">
          <p>Choose rather to punish your appetites than to be punished through them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="114">
          <p>No man is free who is not master of himself.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="115">
          <p>The vine bears three bunches of grapes: the first is that of pleasure, the second of
            drunkenness, the third of violence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="116">
          <p>Over your wine do not talk much to display your learning; for you will utter bilious
              stuff.<note anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="grc">xolera\ ga\r
                a)pofqe/gch|</foreign>. See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="117">
          <p>He is intoxicated who drinks more than three cups: and if he is not intoxicated, he has
            exceeded moderation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="118">
          <p>Let your talk of God be renewed every day, rather than your food.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="119">
          <p>Think of God more frequently than you breathe.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="120">
          <p>If you always remember that whatever you are doing in the soul or in the body, God
            stands by as an inspector, you will never err (do wrong) in all your prayers and in all
            your acts, but you will have God dwelling with you.<note anchored="true">This is the
              doctrine of God being in man. See the Index.</note>
            <pb n="429"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="121">
          <p>As it is pleasant to see the sea from the land, so it is pleasant for him who has
            escaped from troubles to think of them.<note anchored="true">Compare Lucretius ii. the
              beginning.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="122">
          <p>Law intends indeed to do service to human life, but it is not able when men do not
            choose to accept her services; for it is only in those who are obedient to her that she
            displays her special virtue.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="123">
          <p>As to the sick physicians are as saviours, so to those also who are wronged are the
            laws.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="124">
          <p>The justest laws are those which are the truest.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="125">
          <p>To yield to law and to a magistrate and to him who is wiser than yourself, is
            becoming.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="126">
          <p>The things which are done contrary to law are the same as things which are not
            done.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="127">
          <p>In prosperity it is very easy to find a friend; but in adversity it is most difficult
            of all things.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="128">
          <p>Time relieves the foolish from sorrow, but reason relieves the wise.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="129">
          <p>He is a wise man who does not grieve for the things which he has not, but rejoices for
            those which he has. <pb n="430"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="130">
          <p>Epictetus being asked how a man should give pain to his enemy answered, By preparing
            himself to live the best life that he can.<note anchored="true">Compare M. Antoninus,
              vi. 6.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="131">
          <p>Let no wise man be averse to undertaking the office of a magistrate (<foreign
              xml:lang="grc">tou= a)/rxein</foreign>): for it is both impious for a man to withdraw
            himself from being useful to those who have need of our services, and it is ignoble to
            give way to the worthless; for it is foolish to prefer being ill-governed to governing
            well.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="132">
          <p>Nothing is more becoming to him who governs than to despise no man and not show
            arrogance, but to preside over all with equal care.<note anchored="true">For <foreign
                xml:lang="grc">ou)de\n</foreign> Mrs. Carter prefers <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou)de\n
                ma=llon</foreign>: and also Schweig, does, or <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou)de\n a)/llo
                ma=llon</foreign>.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="133">
          <p>[In poverty any man lives (can live) happily, but very seldom in wealth and power
              (<foreign xml:lang="grc">a)rxai=s</foreign>). The value of poverty excels so much that
            no just man (<foreign xml:lang="grc">no/mimos</foreign>) would exchange poverty for
            disreputable wealth, unless indeed the richest of the Athenians Themistocles, the son of
            Neocles, was better than Aristides and Socrates, though he was poor in virtue. But the
            wealth of Themistocles and Themistocles himself have perished and have left no name. For
            all things die with death in a bad man, but the good is eternal.]<note anchored="true"
              >This fragment is not from Epictetus. See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="134">
          <p>Remember that such was, and is, and will be the nature of the universe, and that it is
            not possible that the things which come into being can come into being otherwise than
            they do now; and that not only men have participated in this change and transmutation,
            and all other living things which are on the earth, but also the things <pb n="431"/>
            which are divine. And indeed the very four elements are changed and transmuted up and
            down, and earth becomes water and water becomes air, and the air again is transmuted
            into other things, and the same manner of transmutation takes place from above to below.
            If a man attempts to turn his mind towards these thoughts, and to persuade himself to
            accept with willingness that which is necessary, he will pass through life with complete
            moderation and harmony.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="135">
          <p>He who is dissatisfied with things present and what is given by fortune is an ignorant
            man (<foreign xml:lang="grc">i)diw/ths</foreign>) in life: but he who bears them nobly
            and rationally and the things which proceed from them is worthy of being considered a
            good man.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="136">
          <p>All things obey and serve the world (the universe), earth and sea and sun and the rest
            of the stars, and the plants of earth and animals. And our body obeys it also both in
            disease and in health when it (the universe) chooses, both in youth and in age, and when
            it is passing through the other changes. What is reasonable then and in our power is
            this, for our judgment not to be the only thing which resists it (the universe): for it
            is strong and superior, and it has determined better about us by administering
            (governing) us also together with the whole. And besides, this opposition also is
            unreasonable and does nothing more than cause us to be tormented uselessly and to fall
            into pain and sorrow.</p>
          <p>The fragments which follow are in part assigned to Epictetus, in part to others.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="137">
          <p>Contentment, as it is a short road and pleasant, has great delight and little trouble.
              <pb n="432"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="138">
          <p>Fortify yourself with contentment, for this is an im- pregnable fortress.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="139">
          <p>Let nothing be valued more than truth: not even selec- tion of a friendship which lies
            without the influence of the affects, by which (affects) justice is both confounded
            (disturbed) and darkened.<note anchored="true">The meaning of the second part is
              confused and uncertain. See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="140">
          <p>Truth is a thing immortal and perpetual, and it gives to us a beauty which fades not
            away in time nor does it take away<note anchored="true">In place of <foreign
                xml:lang="grc">a)fairei= th\n</foreign> Mrs. Carter proposes to read <foreign
                xml:lang="grc">a)faireth/n</foreign></note> the freedom of speech which proceeds
            from justice; but it gives to us the knowledge of what is just and lawful, separating
            from them the unjust and refuting them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="141">
          <p>We should not have either a blunt knife or a freedom of speech which is ill
            managed.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="142">
          <p>Nature has given to men one tongue, but two ears, that we may hear from others twice as
            much as we speak.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="143">
          <p>Nothing really pleasant or unpleasant subsists by nature, but all things become so
            through habit (custom).<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="144">
          <p>Choose the best life, for custom (habit) will make it pleasant.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="145">
          <p>Be careful to leave your sons well instructed rather than rich, for the hopes of the
            instructed are better than the wealth of the ignorant. <pb n="433"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="146">
          <p>A daughter is a possession to her father which is not his own.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="147">
          <p>The same person advised to leave modesty to children rather than gold.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="148">
          <p>The reproach of a father is agreeable medicine, for it contains more that is useful
            than it contains of that which gives pain.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="149">
          <p>He who has been lucky in a son in law has found a son: but he who has been unlucky, has
            lost also a daughter.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="150">
          <p>The value of education (knowledge) like that of gold is valued in every place.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="151">
          <p>He who exercises wisdom exercises the knowledge which is about God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="152">
          <p>Nothing among animals is so beautiful as a man adorned by learning (knowledge).<note
              anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="153">
          <p>We ought to avoid the friendship of the bad and the enmity of the good.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="154">
          <p>The necessity of circumstances proves friends and detects enemies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="155">
          <p>When our friends are present, we ought to treat them well; and when they are absent, to
            speak of them well. <pb n="434"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="156">
          <p>Let no man think that he is loved by any man when he loves no man.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="157">
          <p>You ought to choose both physician and friend not the most agreeable, but the most
            useful.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="158">
          <p>If you wish to live a life free from sorrow, think of what is going to happen as if it
            had already happened.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="159">
          <p>Be free from grief not through insensibility like the irrational animals, nor through
            want of thought like the foolish, but like a man of virtue by having reason as the
            consolation of grief.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="160">
          <p>Whoever are least disturbed in mind by calamities, and in act struggle most against
            them, these are the best men in states and in private life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="161">
          <p>Those who have been instructed, like those who have been trained in the palaestra,
            though they may have fallen, rise again from their misfortune quickly and skilfully.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="162">
          <p>We ought to call in reason like a good physician as a help in misfortune.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="163">
          <p>A fool having enjoyed good fortune like intoxication to a great amount becomes more
            foolish.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="164">
          <p>Envy is the antagonist of the fortunate. <pb n="435"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="165">
          <p>He who bears in mind what man is will never be trou- bled at any thing which
            happens.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="166">
          <p>For making a good voyage a pilot (master) and wind are necessary: and for happiness
            reason and art.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="167">
          <p>We should enjoy good fortune while we have it, like the fruits of autumn.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="168">
          <p>He is unreasonable who is grieved (troubled) at the things which happen from the
            necessity of nature.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="book" n="0">
        <head>Some fragments of Epictetus omitted by Upton and by Meibomius.</head>
        <div type="chapter" n="169">
          <p>Of the things which are, God has put some of them in our power, and some he has not. In
            our own power he has placed that which is the best and the most important, that indeed
            through which he himself is happy, the use of appearances (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >fantasiw=n</foreign>). For when this use is rightly employed, there is freedom,
            happiness, tranquillity, constancy: and this is also justice and law, and temperance,
            and every virtue. But all other things he has not placed in our power. Wherefore we also
            ought to be of one mind with God, and making this division of things, to look after
            those which are in our power; and of the things not in our power, to intrust them to the
            Universe (<foreign xml:lang="grc">tw=| ko/smw|</foreign>), and whether it should require
            our children, or our country, or our body, or any thing else, willingly to give them
              up.<note anchored="true">This is a valuable fragment, and I think, a genuine fragment
              of Epictetus. <p>There is plainly a defect in the text, which Schweighaeuser has
                judiciously supplied.</p></note>
            <pb n="436"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="170">
          <p>When a young man was boasting in the theatre and saying, I am wise, for I have
            conversed with many wise men; Epictetus said, I also have conversed with many rich men,
            but I am not rich.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="171">
          <p>The same person said, It is not good for him who has been well taught to talk among the
            untaught, as it is not right for him who is sober to talk among those who are drunk.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="172">
          <p>Epictetus being asked, What man is rich, answered, He who is content (who has
            enough).</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="173">
          <p>Xanthippe was blaming Socrates, because he was making small preparation for receiving
            his friends: but Socrates said, If they are our friends, they will not care about it;
            and if they are not, we shall care nothing about them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="174">
          <p>When Archelaus was sending for Socrates to make him rich, Socrates told the messengers
            to return this answer: At Athens four measures (choenices) of meal are sold for one
            obolus (the sixth of a drachme), and the fountains run with water: if what I have is not
            enough (sufficient) for me, yet I am sufficient for what I have, and so it becomes
            sufficient for me. Do you not see that it was with no nobler voice that Polus acted the
            part of Oedipus as king than of Oedipus as a wanderer and beggar at Colonus? Then shall
            the good man appear to be inferior to Polus, and unable to act well every character
            (personage) im- posed on him by the Deity? and shall he not imitate Ulysses, who even in
            rags made no worse figure than in the soft purple robe?<note anchored="true">See
              Schweig.'s note on this fragment; and his remark on this words <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                >ou)k eu)fwno/teron ou)de\n</foreign>, and his proposed emendation.</note>
            <pb n="437"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="175">
          <p>What do I care, he (Epictetus) says, whether all things are composed of atoms (<foreign
              xml:lang="grc">a)to/mwn</foreign>), or of similar parts (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >o(moiomerw=n</foreign>) or of fire and earth? for is it not enough to know the nature
            of the good and the evil, and the measures (<foreign xml:lang="grc">me/tra</foreign>) of
            the desires and the aversions (<foreign xml:lang="grc">e)kkli/sewn</foreign>), and also
            the movements towards things and from them; and using these as rules to administer the
            affairs of life, but not to trouble ourselves about the things above us? For these
            things are perhaps incomprehensible to the human mind: and if any man should even
            suppose them to be in the highest degree comprehensible, what then is the profit of
            them, if they are comprehended? And must we not say that those men have needless trouble
            who assign these things as necessary to the philosopher's discourse? Is then also the
            precept written at Delphi superfluous, which is Know thyself? It is not so, he says.
            What then is the meaning of it? If a man gave to a choreutes (member of chorus) the
            precept to know himself, would he not have observed in the precept that he must direct
            his attention to himself?<note anchored="true">See Schweig.'s note, and his remark on
              the last line of the text.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="176">
          <p>You are a little soul carrying a dead body, as Epictetus said.<note anchored="true">See
              M. Antoninus, iv. 41.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="177">
          <p>He (Epictetus) said that he had discovered an art in giving assent; and in the topic
            (matter) of the move- ments he had discovered that we must observe attention, that the
            movements be subject to exception, (<foreign xml:lang="grc">mef'
              u(pecaire/sews</foreign>), that they be social, that they be according to the worth of
            each thing; and that we ought to abstain entirely from desire, and to employ aversion
              (<foreign xml:lang="grc">e)kkli/sei</foreign>) to none of the things which are not in
            our power.<note anchored="true">See the translation of M. Antoninus, xi. 37; where I
              have trans- lated this passage a little differently from the present translation. The
              meaning is the same. I do not know which is the better translation.</note>
            <pb n="438"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="178">
          <p>About no common thing, he said, the contest (dispute) is, but about being mad or
              not.<note anchored="true">See M. Antoninus, xi. 38</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="179">
          <p xml:lang="la"><bibl>AUL. GELLIUS, XVII. 19.</bibl> Favorinum ego audivi dicere
            Epictetum philosophum dixisse, 'plerosque istos qui philosophari videntur, philosophos
            esse hujuscemodi, <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)/neu tou= pra/ttein, me/xri tou=
              le/gein</foreign>.'<note anchored="true">Arian, Dissert. ii, 19.</note> Id significat,
            factis procul, verbis tenus. Jam illud est vehementius, quod Arrianus solitum eum
            dictitare in libris, quos de Dissertationibus ejus composuit, scriptum reliquit. Nam,
            'quum,'inquit, 'animadverterat hominem pudore amisso, importuna industria, corruptis
            moribus, audacem, confidentem lingua, caeteraque omnia praeter animum procurantem;
            istiusmodi,'inquit, 'hominemi quum viderat studia quoque et disciplinas philosophiae
            contrectare, et physica adire et meditari dialectica, multaque id genus theoremata
            suspicari sciscitarique, inclamabat deum atque hominum fidem, ac plerumque, inter
            clamandum his eum verbis increpabat: <foreign xml:lang="grc">*)/anqrwpe, pou= ba/lleis;
              ske/yai ei) keka/qartai to\ a)ggei=on. a)\n ga\r ei)s th\n oi)/hsin ba/llh|s,
              a)pw/leto. h)\n saph=|, h)\ ou)=ron h)\ o)\cos ge/noit' a)\n, h)\ ti tou/twn
              xei=ron</foreign>.' Nihil profecto his verbis gravius, nihil verius, quibus declarabat
            maximus philosophorum, 'literas atque doctrinas Philosophiae, quum in hominem falsum
            atque degenerem, tamquam in vas spurcum atque pollutum influxissent, verti, mutari,
            corrumpi, et (quod ipse <foreign xml:lang="grc">kunikw/teron</foreign> ait) urinam
            fieri, aut si quid est urina spurcius.' Praeterea idem ille Epictetus, quod ex eodem
            Favorino audivimus, solitus dicere est: 'duo esse vitia multo omnium gravissima et
            taeterrima, intolerantiam et incontinentiam, quum aut injurias quae sunt ferendae non
            toleramus neque ferimus, aut a quibus rebus voluptatibusque nos tenere debemus non
            tenemus. Itaque,' inquit, 'si quis haec duo verba cordi habeat, eaque sibi <pb n="439"/>
            imperando atque observando curet, is erit pleraque impeccabilis vitamque vivet
            tranquillissimam. Verba duo haec dicebat, <foreign xml:lang="grc">*)ane/xou kai\
              *)ape/xou</foreign>.'</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="180">
          <p><bibl>AUL. GELLIUS, XIX. 1.</bibl></p>
          <p xml:lang="la">Philosophus in disciplina Stoica celebratus. . . . ex sarcinula sua
            librum protulit Epicteti philosophi quintum <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >*dialece/an</foreign>: quas ab Arriano digestas congruere scriptis Zenonis et
            Chrysippi non dubium est. In eo libro Graeca scilicet oratione scriptum ad hanc
            sententiam legimus: 'Visa animi,' quas <foreign xml:lang="grc">fantasi/as</foreign>
            philosophi appellant, 'qui bus mens hominis prima statim specie accidentis ad ani mum
            rei pellitur, non voluntatis sunt, neque arbitraria, sed vi quadam sua inferunt sese
            hominibus noscitanda. Probationes autem quas <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >sugkataqe/seis</foreign> vocant, quibus eadem visa noscuntur ac dijudicantur,
            voluntariae sunt fiuntque hominum arbitratu. Propterea quum sonus aliquis aut caelo aut
            ex ruina aut repentinus [nesciusj pericali nuntius vel quid aliud ejusmodi factum,
            sapientis quoque animum paulisper moveri et contrahi et pallescere necessum est, non
            opinione alicujus mali praecepta, sed quibusdam motibus rapidis et inconsultis officium
            mentis atque rationis praevertentibus. Mox tamen ille sapiens ibidem [idem?] <foreign
              xml:lang="grc">ta\s toiau/tas fantasi/as</foreign>, id est, visa istaec animi sui
            terrifica non approbat: hoc est <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou)sugkatati/qetai ou)de\
              prosepidoca/zei</foreign>, sed abjicit respuitque, nec ei metuendum esse in his
            quidquam videtur. Atque hoc inter insipientis sapientisque animum differre dicunt, quod
            insipiens, qualia esse primo animi sui pulsu visa sunt saeva et aspera, talia esse vero
            putat, et eadem incepta tamquam jure metuenda sint, sua quoque assensione approbat
              <foreign xml:lang="grc">kai\ prosepidoca/zei</foreign> (hoc enim verbo Stoici quum
            super ista re disserunt utuntur). Sapiens autem quum breviter et strictim colore atque
            vultu motus est, <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou) sugkatati/qetai</foreign>, sed statum
            vigoremque sententiae suae retinet, quam de hujuscemodi visis semper habuit, ut de
            minime metuendis, sed fronte falsa et formidine inani territantibus.' <pb n="440"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="181">
          <p><bibl>Arnobius Advers. Gentes, in fine libri secundi.</bibl></p>
          <p xml:lang="la">Quum de animarum agitur salute ac de respectu nostri; 'aliquid et sine
            ratione faciendum est,'<note anchored="true">'Nempe ubi ratio deficit, ibi sola fiducia
              in Deum reposita et obsequio voluntati ejus ab ipso declaratae unice subjeto agendum
              est.' Schweig. See Encheirid. xxxii</note> ut Epictetum dixisse approbat Arrianus. <pb
              n="441"/></p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
