<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - Jonah</title>
                
                <editor>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor>
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                  <!-- <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>-->
             <refState unit="chapter"/><refState unit="verse"/></refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>14-Oct-99</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <resp>markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial markup from flat ASCII text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>5/27/09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>RS</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: world.english.xml,v $
			Revision 1.2  2010-06-29 22:00:29  student
			fixing place tags - AD

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:10:56  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.3  2009/05/27 16:11:31  rsingh04
			added/fixed cvs log keyword
                </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="Jonah" type="book">
                <head>Jonah</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="0" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Now the word of Yahweh came to Jonah the son of Amittai, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and preach
against it, for their wickedness has come up before me."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        But Jonah rose up to flee to Tarshish from the presence of
Yahweh. He went down to Joppa, and found a ship going to Tarshish; so
he paid its fare, and went down into it, to go with them to Tarshish
from the presence of Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        But Yahweh sent out a great wind on
the sea, and there was a mighty tempest on the sea, so that the ship
was likely to break up.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Then the mariners were afraid, and cried
every man to his god. They threw the cargo that was in the ship into
the sea, to lighten it. But Jonah had gone down into the innermost
parts of the ship, and he was laying down, and was fast asleep.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        So the shipmaster came to him, and said to him, "What do you mean,
sleeper? Arise, call on your gods! Maybe the gods will notice us, so
that we won't perish."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        They all said to each other, "Come, let us cast lots, that we
may know for whose cause this evil is on us." So they cast lots, and
the lot fell on Jonah.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Then they asked him, "Tell us, please, for
whose cause this evil is on us. What is your occupation? Where do you
come from? What is your country? Of what people are you?"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        He said to them, "I am a Hebrew, and I fear Yahweh, the God of
heaven, who has made the sea and the dry land."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Then were the men exceedingly afraid, and said to him, "What
is this that you have done?" For the men knew that he was fleeing from
the presence of Yahweh, because he had told them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Then said they
to him, "What shall we do to you, that the sea may be calm to us?" For
the sea grew more and more tempestuous.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        He said to them, "Take
me up, and throw me into the sea. Then the sea will be calm for you;
for I know that because of me this great tempest is on you."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Nevertheless the men rowed hard to get them back to the land;
but they could not, for the sea grew more and more tempestuous against
them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Therefore they cried to Yahweh, and said, "We beg you,
Yahweh, we beg you, let us not perish for this man's life, and don't
lay on us innocent blood; for you, Yahweh, have done as it pleased
you."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        So they took up Jonah, and threw him into the sea; and the
sea ceased its raging.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Then the men feared Yahweh exceedingly;
and they offered a sacrifice to Yahweh, and made vows.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Yahweh prepared a great fish to swallow up Jonah, and Jonah
was in the belly of the fish three days and three nights.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then Jonah prayed to Yahweh, his God, out of the fish's belly.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        He said,
"I called because of my affliction to Yahweh.
   He answered me.
Out of the belly of Sheol I cried.
   You heard my voice.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        For you threw me into the depths,
   In the heart of the seas.
The flood was all around me.
   All your waves and your billows passed over me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        I said, 'I have been banished from your sight;
   Yet I will look again toward your holy temple.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        The waters surrounded me,
   Even to the soul.
The deep was around me.
   The weeds were wrapped around my head.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        I went down to the bottoms of the mountains.
   The earth barred me in forever:
   Yet have you brought up my life from the pit, Yahweh my God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        "When my soul fainted within me, I remembered Yahweh.
   My prayer came in to you, into your holy temple.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Those who regard lying vanities forsake their own mercy.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        But I will sacrifice to you with the voice of thanksgiving.
   I will pay that which I have vowed.
Salvation belongs to Yahweh."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Yahweh spoke to the fish, and it vomited out Jonah on the dry
land.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        The word of Yahweh came to Jonah the second time, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Arise, go to Nineveh, that great city, and preach to it the
message that I give you."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        So Jonah arose, and went to Nineveh, according to the word of
Yahweh. Now Nineveh was an exceedingly great city, three days' journey
across.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Jonah began to enter into the city a day's journey, and
he cried out, and said, "Yet forty days, and Nineveh shall be
overthrown!"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        The people of Nineveh believed God; and they proclaimed a
fast, and put on sackcloth, from the greatest of them even to the least
of them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        The news reached the king of Nineveh, and he arose from
his throne, and took off his royal robe, covered himself with
sackcloth, and sat in ashes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        He made a proclamation and published
through Nineveh by the decree of the king and his nobles, saying, "Let
neither man nor animal, herd nor flock, taste anything; let them not
feed, nor drink water;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        but let them be covered with sackcloth,
both man and animal, and let them cry mightily to God. Yes, let them
turn everyone from his evil way, and from the violence that is in his
hands.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Who knows whether God will not turn and repent, and turn
away from his fierce anger, so that we might not perish?"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        God saw their works, that they turned from their evil way.
God repented of the evil which he said he would do to them, and he
didn't do it.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        But it displeased Jonah exceedingly, and he was angry.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        He prayed to Yahweh, and said, "Please, Yahweh, wasn't this what I said
when I was still in my own country? Therefore I hurried to flee to
Tarshish, for I knew that you are a gracious God, and merciful, slow to
anger, and abundant in lovingkindness, and you repent of the evil.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Therefore now, Yahweh, take, I beg you, my life from me; for it
is better for me to die than to live."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Yahweh said, "Is it right for you to be angry?"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Then Jonah went out of the city, and sat on the east side of
the city, and there made himself a booth, and sat under it in the
shade, until he might see what would become of the city.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Yahweh
God prepared a vine, and made it to come up over Jonah, that it might
be a shade over his head, to deliver him from his discomfort. So Jonah
was exceedingly glad because of the vine.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        But God prepared a worm
at dawn the next day, and it chewed on the vine, so that it withered.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        It happened, when the sun arose, that God prepared a sultry east
wind; and the sun beat on Jonah's head, so that he fainted, and
requested for himself that he might die, and said, "It is better for me
to die than to live."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        God said to Jonah, "Is it right for you to be angry about the
vine?"

   He said, "I am right to be angry, even to death."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Yahweh said, "You have been concerned for the vine, for which
you have not labored, neither made it grow; which came up in a night,
and perished in a night.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Shouldn't I be concerned for Nineveh,
that great city, in which are more than one hundred twenty thousand
persons who can't discern between their right hand and their left hand;
and also much cattle?"
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
