<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI.2>
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>De primo frigido</title>
<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
<author n="Plut.">Plutarch</author>
<editor role="editor" n="Loeb">Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</editor>
<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
</titleStmt>
<extent/>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<analytic/>
<monogr>
<author>Plutarch</author>
<title>Moralia</title>
<respStmt>
<resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
<name>Harold Cherniss and William C. Helmbold</name>
</respStmt>
<imprint>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
<publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
<date>1957</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope type="volume">12</biblScope>
</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<editorialDecl>
<correction method="silent">
<p>optical character recognition</p>
</correction>
</editorialDecl>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>
<!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>-->
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language id="greek">Greek</language>
<language id="eng">English</language>
<language id="la">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change>
<date>5/10</date>
<respStmt>
<name>RS</name>
<resp/>
</respStmt>
<item>tagged and parsed</item>
</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div1 type="section" n="intro">
<pb id="v.12.p.227"/>
<head>ον τηε πρινξιπλε οφ ξολδ ʽδε πριμο φριγιδὀ <lb/> ιντροδυξτιον</head>
<p>
					τηις λιττλε εσσαψ, ορ οπεν λεττερ το φαϝορινυς, ις νοτ
					ωριττεν ιν α ξοντροϝερσιαλ σπιριτ, τηουγη α φεω σηαρπ
					ξομμεντς αρε μαδε φρομ τιμε το τιμε. ηαϝινγ
					εσταβλισηεδ ʽξηαπτερς 5-7ʼ τηατ αν ελεμεντ οφ ξολδ
					ρεαλλψ εχιστς, πλυταρξη προξεεδς το ξονσιδερ ωηατ τηατ
					ελεμεντ μαψ βε. σινξε φιρε ις οβϝιουσλψ εχξλυδεδ,
					ξαν ιτ βε αιρ, ας τηε στοιξς βελιεϝε ʽ8-12ʼ, ορ ωατερ,
					ας εμπεδοξλες, ανδ αν εαρλψ περιπατετιξ, στρατο, ηολδ
					ʽ13-16ʼ ? ορ, ινδεεδ, μαψ ιτ βε εαρτη ιτσελφ ʽ17-22ʼ ?
					τηις λαττερ οπινιον ις αππαρεντλψ πυτ φορωαρδ βψ
					πλυταρξη ας αν οριγιναλ ξοντριβυτιον το τηεορετιξαλ
					πηψσιξς ανδ τηερε ις νο ρεασον το βελιεϝε ιτ ις νοτ ηις.
					τηε εσσαψ ξλοσες, ηοωεϝερ, ωιτη α ρεξομμενδατιον
					το σξεπτιξισμ,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See J. Schröter, <hi rend="italics">Plutarchs Stellung zur Skepsis</hi> (Greifswald, 1911), pp. 23 and 40. He compares other recomendations to the suspension of judgement, such as <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 430 f - 431 a. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> also Hartman, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, pp. 253 f.</note> σο τηατ ουρ αυτηορ μαψ νοτ ηαϝε ρεγαρδεδ ηις αττεμπτεδ προοφ ας ξογεντ, ας ινδεεδ ιτ ις
					νοτ.
				</p>
<p>
					τηε ωορκ ωας προβαβλψ ωριττεν ιν δελπηι ʽ<hi rend="italics">ξφ.</hi> 953
					ξ-δ ανδ ἐ αφτερ α.δ. 107-ʽ949 ε, νοτἐ ανδ αδδρεσσεδ
					το τηε ψουνγ πηιλοσοπηερ φαϝορινυς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">For the details see Ziegler's article on Plutarch in Pauly-Wissowa, <hi rend="italics">RE</hi>, col. 675.</note> τηε γρεατ λοϝερ
					οφ αριστοτλε ʽ<hi rend="italics">μορ.</hi> 734 φ̓, ωηο ις αλσο α σπεακερ ιν
					<hi rend="italics">σψμποσιαξς</hi>, ϝιιι. ιο. τηουγη φαϝορινυς ωας ιν αλλ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.228"/>
					
					λικελιηοοδ σομε τωεντψ ψεαρς ψουνγερ τηαν πλυταρξη,
					τηε τωο μεν δεδιξατεδ σεϝεραλ ωορκς το εαξη οτηερ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Lamprias cat. 132: Plutarch's <hi rend="italics">Letter to Favorinus on Friendship</hi> (or <hi rend="italics">The Use of Friends</hi>); Galen, <hi rend="italics">de Opt. Doctr.</hi> (i. 41 K): Favorinus's <hi rend="italics">Plutarch, or On the Academic Disposition</hi>. See also Suidas, <hi rend="italics">s.v.</hi>
<foreign lang="greek">Φαβωρῖνος</foreign>.</note>
					ιν τηε πρεσεντ εσσαψ ιτ ις, περηαπς, οδδ τηατ οφ τηε
					τηρεε θυοτατιονς φρομ αριστοτλε ονε ις α ρεβυκε ʽ950
					β̓, ονε ις αππαρεντλψ α παρτιαλ μισξιτατιον ʽ948 α, νοτἐ,
					ωηιλε τηε τηιρδ ις οφ νο ιμπορτανξε. νο δουβτ ιτ ις ιν
					ϝιρτυε οφ φαϝορινυσʼ ψουτη τηατ ηις ιδολ ις τρεατεδ σο
					λιγητλψ, ανδ τηατ τηε σξεπτιξαλ νοτε ις σουνδεδ σο
					φιρμλψ ατ τηε ενδ. τηε ψουνγ περιπατετιξ ωας αλσο
					θυοτεδ βψ πλυταρξη ʽφορ παρτιαλ ρεφυτατιον̓ ιν <hi rend="italics">μορ.</hi>
					271 ξ ; βυτ πλυταρξη ʽιφ ταρν<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Alexander the Great</hi>, ii. 298 f.</note> ανδ οτηερς αρε ριγητ̓
					βεξαμε μυξη μορε φαϝουραβλε το περιπατετιξς λατερ
					ιν ηις λιφε ʽε.γ. ιν τηε <hi rend="italics">λιφε οφ αλεχανδερ</hi>ʼ.ʼ
				</p>
<p>
					βερναρδακις ς τεχτ οφ τηις ωορκ ις ονε οφ ηις μοστ
					υνσατισφαξτορψ ; εϝεν φορ αν <hi rend="italics">εδιτιο μινορ</hi> ιτ ις ξαρελεσς
					ανδ ξονφυσεδ το α δεπλοραβλε εχτεντ. νορ αρε τηε
					μεανς οφ ξορρεξτινγ ανδ συππλεμεντινγ ιτ ατ ηανδ,
					τηε φιφτη τευβνερ ϝολυμε βεινγ στιλλ, ονε φεαρς, ιν
					τηε ρεμοτε φυτυρε. τηεν, τοο. τηε ονλψ πηοτογραπης
					αϝαιλαβλε ωερε τηοσε οφ ε ανδ Β. ωηιξη αρε νοτ λικελψ
					το αδδ μυξη το ουρ κνοωλεδγε.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the recent brisk controversy as to their relationship: Manton, <hi rend="italics">Class. Quart.</hi> xliii (1949), pp. 97-104; Hubert, <hi rend="italics">Rhein. Mus.</hi> xciii (1950), pp. 330-336; Einarson and De Lacy, <hi rend="italics">Class. Phil.</hi> xlvi (1951), p. 110, n. 56; Flaceliere, ed. Plutarch, <hi rend="italics">Amatorius</hi>, pp. 35 ff. The evidence in this essay, for what it may be worth, seems to make it unlikely that B was here copied from either E or an immediate descendant; they both appear to go back to a common ancestor, perhaps through several intermediaries: see, <hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi>, 951 a, b, d, 953 e. See now Cherniss <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, pp. 27, note <hi rend="italics">a</hi>; 31, 32.</note> ξονσεθυεντλψ τηε
					ονλψ ξουρσε τηατ σεεμεδ πρυδεντ ωας το ρετυρν το
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.229"/>
					
					ωψττενβαξη ωηερεϝερ τηερε ωας α ρεασοναβλε δουβτ.
					βερναρδακις ηας βεεν ταξιτλψ ξορρεξτεδ ʽορ αλτερεδ,
					ωηιξηεϝερ ιτ μαψ βἐ ιν α γοοδ μανψ πλαξες. τηις
					ηας βεεν δονε ξονσιστεντλψ ωηεν βοτη ε ανδ <foreign lang="greek">Β</foreign>
					αγρεε ωιτη ωψττενβαξηʼς ανδ ηυττενʼς σιλενξε ; βερναρδακισʼς σιλενξε, υνφορτυνατελψ, αππεαρς το ηαϝε νο
					σιγνιφιξανξε.
				</p>
<p>
					τηε ωορκ ις νο. 90 ιν τηε ξαταλογυε οφ λαμπριας.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.231"/>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="1">
<p>ις τηερε, τηεν, φαϝορινυς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the introduction to this essay.</note> αν αξτιϝε πρινξιπλε ορ
					συβστανξε οφ ξολδ ʽας φιρε ις οφ ηεατ̓ τηρουγη τηε
					πρεσενξε οφ ωηιξη ανδ τηρουγη παρτιξιπατιον ιν ωηιξη
					εϝερψτηινγ ελσε βεξομες ξολδ? ορ ις ξολδνεσς ρατηερ
					α νεγατιον οφ ωαρμτη, ας τηεψ σαψ δαρκνεσς ις οφ λιγητ
					ανδ ρεστ οφ μοτιον? ξολδ, ινδεεδ, σεεμς το ηαϝε τηε
					θυαλιτψ οφ βεινγ στατιοναρψ, ας ηεατ ηας τηατ οφ μοτιον;
					ωηιλε τηε ξοολινγ οφφ οφ ηοτ τηινγς ις νοτ ξαυσεδ βψ τηε
					πρεσενξε οφ ανψ φορξε,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As, for instance, the force of fire.</note> βυτ μερελψ βψ τηε δισπλαξεμεντ οφ ηεατ, φορ ιτ ξαν βε σεεν το δεπαρτ ξομπλετελψ
					ατ τηε σαμε τιμε ας τηε ρεμαινδερ ξοολς οφφ. τηε
					στεαμ, φορ εχαμπλε, ωηιξη βοιλινγ ωατερ εμιτς, ις
					εχπελλεδ ιν ξομπανψ ωιτη τηε δεπαρτινγ ηεατ; τηατ
					ις ωηψ τηε αμουντ βεξομες λεσς βψ ξοολινγ οφφ; φορ
					τηις ρεμοϝες τηε ηεατ ανδ νοτηινγ ελσε τακες ιτς πλαξε.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="2">
<p>φιρστ οφ αλλ, μυστ ωε νοτ βε ωαρψ οφ ονε ποιντ ιν
					τηις αργυμεντ ? ιτ ελιμινατες μανψ οβϝιους φορξες
					βψ ξονσιδερινγ τηεμ νοτ το βε θυαλιτιες ορ προπερτιες,
					βυτ μερελψ τηε νεγατιον οφ θυαλιτιες ορ προπερτιες,
					ωειγητ βεινγ τηε νεγατιον οφ λιγητνεσς ανδ ηαρδνεσς
					τηατ οφ σοφτνεσς, βλαξκ τηατ οφ ωηιτε, ανδ βιττερ τηατ
					οφ σωεετ, ανδ σο ιν ανψ οτηερ ξασε ωηερε τηερε ις α
					νατυραλ οπποσιτιον οφ φορξες ρατηερ τηαν α ρελατιον
					οφ ποσιτιϝε ανδ νεγατιϝε. ανοτηερ ποιντ ις τηατ αλλ
					νεγατιον ις ινερτ ανδ υνπροδυξτιϝε · βλινδνεσς, φορ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.233"/>
					
					εχαμπλε, ανδ δεαφνεσς, σιλενξε ορ δεατη. ηερε ψου
					ηαϝε τηε δεφεξτιον οφ α δεφινιτε φορμ ανδ τηε αννιηιλατιον οφ α ρεαλιτψ, νοτ σομετηινγ τηατ ις ιν ιτσελφ α παρτ
					οφ νατυρε ορ ρεαλιτψ. ιτ ις τηε νατυρε οφ ξολδνεσς,
					ηοωεϝερ, το προδυξε αφφεξτς ανδ αλτερατιονς ιν βοδιες
					τηατ ιτ εντερς νο λεσς τηαν τηοσε ξαυσεδ βψ ηεατ.
					μανψ οβjεξτς ξαν βε φροζεν σολιδ, ορ βεξομε ξονδενσεδ ορ μαδε ϝισξους, βψ ξολδ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As steam is condensed and oil becomes viscous.</note> μορεοϝερ, τηε
					προπερτψ ωηερεβψ ξολδνεσς προμοτες ρεστ ανδ ρεσιστς
					μοτιον ις νοτ ινερτ, βυτ αξτς βψ πρεσσυρε ανδ ρεσιστανξε. βεινγ ξονστριξτιϝε ανδ πρεσερϝατιϝε βεξαυσε οφ
					ιτς στρενγτη. τηις εχπλαινς ηοω, τηουγη νεγατιον ις α
					δισαππεαρανξε ανδ δεπαρτυρε οφ τηε ξοντραρψ φορξε,
					μανψ τηινγς μαψ ψετ βεξομε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The verb is ambiguous: <q direct="unspecified">become cold</q> or <q direct="unspecified">dry</q> or perhaps <q direct="unspecified">congealed.</q>
</note> ξολδ ωηιλε αλλ τηε τιμε
					ξονταινινγ ωιτηιν τηεμσελϝες ξονσιδεραβλε ωαρμτη.
					τηερε αρε εϝεν σομε οβjεξτς ωηιξη ξολδ σολιδιφιες ανδ
					ξονσολιδατες τηε μορε ρεαδιλψ τηε ηοττερ τηεψ αρε ·
					στεελ, φορ εχαμπλε, πλυνγεδ ιν ωατερ. τηε στοιξς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 1052 f; von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, pp. 134, 222; and see Hartman's explanation, <hi rend="italics">De Plutarcho</hi>, p. 566. Von Arnim thinks that the next five chapters also contain Stoic material.</note> αλσο
					αφφιρμ τηατ ιν τηε βοδιες οφ ινφαντ ξηιλδρεν τηε βρεατη ις
					τεμπερεδ βψ ξοολινγ ανδ, φρομ βεινγ α πηψσιξαλ συβστανξε, βεξομες α σουλ. τηις, ηοωεϝερ, ις δεβαταβλε ;
					ψετ σινξε τηερε αρε μανψ οτηερ εφφεξτς ωηιξη μαψ βε
					σεεν το βε προδυξεδ τηρουγη τηε αγενξψ οφ ξολδ, ωε
					αρε νοτ jυστιφιεδ ιν ρεγαρδινγ ιτ ας α νεγατιον.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="3">
<p>βεσιδες, α νεγατιον δοες νοτ περμιτ δεγρεες οφ
					λεσς ορ μορε. συρελψ νοβοδψ ωιλλ αφφιρμ τηατ ονε βλινδ
					μαν ις βλινδερ τηαν ανοτηερ, ορ ονε δυμβ μαν μορε
					σιλεντ τηαν ανοτηερ, ορ ονε ξορπσε δεαδερ τηαν ιτς
					φελλοω ; βυτ αμονγ ξολδ τηινγς τηερε ις α ωιδε ρανγε
					οφ δεϝιατιον φρομ μυξη το λιττλε, φρομ ϝερψ ξολδ το νοτ
					ϝερψ, ανδ, γενεραλλψ σπεακινγ, ιν δεγρεες οφ ιντενσιτψ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.235"/>
					
					ανδ ρεμισσιον, jυστ ας τηερε ις ιν ηοτ τηινγς. τηις
					οξξυρς βεξαυσε τηε ματτερ ινϝολϝεδ ις ιν διφφερεντ ξασες
					αξτεδ υπον βψ τηε οπποσινγ φορξες ωιτη μορε ορ λεσς
					ιντενσιτψ ; ιτ τηυς εχηιβιτς δεγρεες οφ ονε ορ τηε οτηερ,
					ανδ σο οφ ηοτ ανδ ξολδ. τηερε ις, ιν φαξτ, νο συξη
					τηινγ ας α βλενδινγ οφ ποσιτιϝε θυαλιτιες ωιτη νεγατιϝε
					ονες, νορ μαψ ανψ ποσιτιϝε φορξε αξξεπτ τηε ασσαυλτ
					οφ τηε νεγατιον τηατ ξορρεσπονδς το ιτ ορ τακε ιτ ιντο
					παρτνερσηιπ ; ινστεαδ ιτ γιϝες πλαξε το ιτ. νοω ηοτ
					τηινγς δο αδμιτ α βλενδινγ ωιτη ξολδ υπ το α ποιντ,
					jυστ ας δο βλαξκ ωιτη ωηιτε, ηιγη νοτες ωιτη λοω, σωεετ
					ταστες ωιτη σουρ ; ανδ τηις ηαρμονιους ασσοξιατιον
					οφ ξολουρς ανδ σουνδς, δρυγς ανδ σαυξες, προδυξες
					μανψ ξομβινατιονς τηατ αρε πλεασαντ ανδ γρατεφυλ
					το τηε σενσες.
				</p>
<p>
					φορ τηε οπποσιτιον οφ α νεγατιον το α ποσιτιϝε
					θυαλιτψ ις αν ιρρεξονξιλαβλε ηοστιλιτψ, σινξε τηε εχιστενξε οφ τηε ονε ις τηε αννιηιλατιον οφ τηε οτηερ. τηε
					οτηερ οπποσιτιον, ηοωεϝερ, οφ ποσιτιϝε φορξες, ιφ ιτ
					οξξυρς ιν δυε μεασυρε, ις οφτεν οπερατιϝε ιν τηε αρτς,
					ανδ ϝερψ οφτεν ινδεεδ ιν ϝαριους πηενομενα οφ
					νατυρε, εσπεξιαλλψ ιν ξοννεχιον ωιτη τηε ωεατηερ
					ανδ τηε σεασονς ανδ τηοσε ματτερς φρομ ωηιξη τηε
					γοδ δεριϝες ηις τιτλε οφ ηαρμονιζερ ανδ μυσιξιαν,
					βεξαυσε ηε οργανιζες ανδ ρεγυλατες τηεμ. ηε δοες
					νοτ ρεξειϝε τηεσε ναμες μερελψ φορ βρινγινγ σουνδς
					οφ ηιγη ανδ λοω πιτξη, ορ βλαξκ ανδ ωηιτε ξολουρς, ιντο
					ηαρμονιους φελλοωσηιπ, βυτ βεξαυσε ηε ηας αυτηοριτψ
					οϝερ τηε ασσοξιατιον ανδ δισυνιον οφ ηεατ ανδ ξολδ ιν
					τηε υνιϝερσε, το σεε τηατ τηεψ οβσερϝε δυε μεασυρε
					ιν τηειρ ξομβινατιον ανδ σεπαρατιον, ανδ βεξαυσε, βψ
					ελιμινατινγ τηε εχξεσς οφ ειτηερ, ηε βρινγς βοτη ιντο
					προπερ ορδερ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="4">
<p>φυρτηερμορε, ωε φινδ τηατ ξολδ ξαν βε περξειϝεδ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.237"/>
					
					ας ωελλ ας ηεατ; βυτ μερε νεγατιον ξαννοτ βε σεεν ορ
					ηεαρδ ορ τουξηεδ ορ ρεξογνιζεδ βψ τηε οτηερ σενσες.
					περξεπτιον, ιν φαξτ, μυστ βε οφ σομετηινγ εχιστεντ;
					βυτ ωηερε νοτηινγ εχιστεντ ις οβσερϝεδ, πριϝατιον μαψ
					βε ινφερρεδ, βεινγ τηε νεγατιον οφ εχιστενξε, ας βλινδνεσς ις οφ σιγητ, σιλενξε οφ σουνδ, ϝοιδ ανδ εμπτινεσς
					οφ ματτερ. ωε ξαννοτ περξειϝε α ϝοιδ βψ τουξη ; βυτ
					ωηερε νο ματτερ ξαν βε τουξηεδ, ϝοιδ ις ινφερρεδ.
					νορ ξαν ωε ηεαρ σιλενξε ; ψετ, εϝεν τηουγη ωε ηεαρ
					νοτηινγ, ωε ινφερ σιλενξε. νορ, ιν τηε σαμε ωαψ, ις
					σενσε αξτιϝε ωηεν τηινγς αρε υνσεεν ορ βαρε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As, when a hill has been stripped of timber, you cannot see the trees.</note>; τηερε
					ις, ρατηερ, ινφερενξε φρομ τηε νεγατιον οφ περξεπτιον.
					ιφ, τηερεφορε, ξολδ ωερε α πριϝατιον οφ ωαρμτη, ωε
					ουγητ νοτ το βε αβλε το φεελ ιτ, βυτ ονλψ το ινφερ ιτ
					φρομ τηε δεφιξιενξψ ιν ωαρμτη ; βυτ ιφ ξολδ ις περξειϝεδ βψ τηε ξοντραξτιον ανδ ξονδενσατιον οφ ουρ
					φλεση ʽjυστ ας ηεατ ις βψ τηε ωαρμινγ ανδ λοοσενινγ
					οφ ιτ̓, ξλεαρλψ τηερε ις σομε σπεξιαλ φιρστ πρινξιπλε ανδ
					σουρξε οφ ξολδνεσς, jυστ ας τηερε ις οφ ηεατ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="5">
<p>ανδ ψετ ανοτηερ ποιντ· πριϝατιον οφ ανψ σορτ ις
					σομετηινγ σιμπλε ανδ υνξομπλιξατεδ, ωηερεας συβστανξες ηαϝε μανψ διφφερενξες ανδ ποωερς. σιλενξε,
					φορ εχαμπλε, ις οφ ονλψ ονε κινδ, ωηιλε σουνδ ϝαριες,
					σομετιμες αννοψινγ, ατ οτηερ τιμες δελιγητινγ, τηε
					περξεπτιον. βοτη ξολουρς ανδ φιγυρες σηοω τηε σαμε
					ϝαριατιον, φορ τηεψ προδυξε διφφερεντ εφφεξτς ον διφφερεντ οξξασιονς ωηεν τηεψ μεετ τηε εψε ; βυτ τηατ
					ωηιξη ξαννοτ βε τουξηεδ ανδ ις ωιτηουτ ξολουρ ορ ανψ
					θυαλιτψ ωηατεϝερ, αδμιτς νο διφφερενξε, βυτ ις αλωαψς
					τηε σαμε.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="6">
<p>ις ξολδ, τηεν, σο λικε τηις σορτ οφ πριϝατιον τηατ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.239"/>
					
					ιτ προδυξες νο εφφεξτς τηατ διφφερ ? ορ ις τηε ξοντραρψ
					τρυε · δο νοτ γρεατ ανδ υσεφυλ πλεασυρες αξξρυε το
					ουρ βοδιες φρομ τηε πρεσενξε οφ ξολδ, ας ωελλ ας μιγητψ
					δετριμεντς ανδ παινς ανδ δεπρεσσιονς, βεφορε ωηιξη
					τηε ηεατ δοες νοτ αλωαψς δεπαρτ ανδ θυιτ τηε φιελδ ?
					οφτεν, ρατηερ, τηουγη ξυτ οφφ ωιτηιν, ιτ μακες α στανδ
					ανδ γιϝες βαττλε. τηις στρυγγλε οφ ηοτ ανδ ξολδ ις
					ξαλλεδ σηιϝερινγ ορ σηακινγ ; ανδ ιφ ηεατ ις οϝερξομε,
					φρεεζινγ ανδ τορπορ σετ ιν ; βυτ ιφ ξολδ ις δεφεατεδ,
					τηερε ις διφφυσεδ τηρουγη τηε βοδψ α ρελαχεδ ανδ
					πλεασαντλψ ωαρμ σενσατιον ωηιξη ηομερ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See, <hi rend="italics">e.g., Odyssey</hi>, vi. 156; <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxiii. 598, 600; and <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 454 d, 735 f.</note> ξαλλς <q direct="unspecified">το
						βε αγλοω.</q> συρελψ τηεσε φαξτς αρε οβϝιους το εϝερψονε ; ανδ ιτ ις ξηιεφλψ βψ τηεσε εφφεξτς τηατ ξολδ ις
					σηοων το βε ιν οπποσιτιον το ηεατ, νοτ ας α νεγατιον
					ορ πριϝατιον, βυτ ας ονε συβστανξε ορ ονε στατε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Heat, for example, may be said to be a <q direct="unspecified">state</q> or condition of metal.</note> το
					ανοτηερ · ιτ ις νοτ α μερε δεστρυξτιον ορ αβολιτιον οφ
					ηεατ, βυτ α ποσιτιϝε συβστανξε ορ φορξε. οτηερωισε
					ωε μιγητ jυστ ας ωελλ εχξλυδε ωιντερ φρομ τηε λιστ
					οφ σεασονς ορ τηε νορτηερλψ βλαστς φρομ τηατ οφ ωινδς,
					ον τηε πρετεχτ τηατ τηεψ αρε ονλψ α δεφιξιενξψ οφ ηοτ
					ωεατηερ ορ σουτηερλψ γαλες ανδ ηαϝε νο προπερ οριγιν
					οφ τηειρ οων.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="7">
<p>φυρτηερμορε, γιϝεν φουρ πριμαρψ βοδιες ιν τηε
					υνιϝερσε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, pp. 315 ff., Empedocles, frag. B 17. The doctrine is clearly stated by, for example, Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> ii. 10. The author of the <hi rend="italics">Epinomis</hi> (981 c) adds a fifth element, aether (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 951 d <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>).</note> ωηιξη, βεξαυσε οφ τηειρ θυαντιτψ, σιμπλιξιτψ, ανδ ποτεντιαλιτψ, μοστ jυδγες ρεγαρδ ας βεινγ
					τηε ελεμεντς ορ φιρστ πρινξιπλες οφ εϝερψτηινγ ελσε - 
					ι μεαν φιρε, ωατερ, αιρ, ανδ εαρτη - τηε νυμβερ οφ
					πριμαρψ, σιμπλε θυαλιτιες μυστ βε τηε σαμε. ανδ
					ωηατ σηουλδ τηεσε βε βυτ ωαρμτη ανδ ξολδ, δρψνεσς
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.241"/>
					
					ανδ μοιστυρε, ωηιξη βψ τηειρ ϝερψ νατυρε ξαυσε αλλ
					τηε ελεμεντς το αξτ ανδ βε αξτεδ υπον?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Post translates his emendation: <q direct="unspecified">by which all things are qualified through the natural action of the elements,</q> pointing out that elements have nothing but size, shape, and motion. Fire causes heat, but its atoms are not themselves hot.</note> Jυστ ας ιν
					γραμμαρ ωε ηαϝε ελεμεντς λονγ ανδ σηορτ ανδ ιν
					μυσιξ ελεμεντς ηιγη ανδ λοω ιν πιτξη - ανδ ιν νειτηερ
					ξασε ις ονε ελεμεντ μερελψ α νεγατιον οφ τηε οτηερ - 
					σο αλσο ιν πηψσιξαλ βοδιες ωε μυστ ασσυμε αν ελεμενταρψ οπποσιτιον οφ ωετ το δρψ ανδ ξολδ το ηοτ, ανδ
					ιν τηις ωαψ ωε σηαλλ βε φαιτηφυλ βοτη το λογιξ ανδ το
					εχπεριενξε. ορ αρε ωε, ας ολδ αναχιμενες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 95; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Diller, <hi rend="italics">Hermes</hi>, lxvii, pp. 35 f.</note> μαινταινεδ, το λεαϝε νειτηερ ηοτ νορ ξολδ ιν τηε ρεαλμ οφ
					βεινγ, βυτ το τρεατ τηεμ ας στατες βελονγινγ εθυαλλψ
					το ανψ ματτερ ανδ οξξυρρινγ ας α ρεσυλτ οφ ξηανγες
					ωιτηιν ιτ ? ηε αφφιρμς, ιν φαξτ, τηατ ανψτηινγ ωηιξη
					υνδεργοες ξοντραξτιον ανδ ξονδενσατιον οφ ματτερ
					ις ξολδ, ωηιλε ανψτηινγ τηατ συφφερς ραρεφαξτιον ανδ
					διστεντιον - τηις ξομες ξλοσε το ηις οων πηρασινγ - ις
					ηοτ. σο τηερε ις νο ξοντραδιξτιον ιν τηε ρεμαρκ τηατ
					τηε μαν βλεω βοτη ηοτ ανδ ξολδ,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Aesop's <hi rend="italics">Fables</hi> (no. 60 in Chambry's Bude edition, vol. i, pp. 131 ff.), where the satyr renounces friendship with the man because the latter blows both hot and cold through the same mouth.</note> φορ βρεατη γροως
					ξολδ ωηεν ιτ ις ξομπρεσσεδ ανδ ξονδενσεδ βψ τηε λιπς ;
					βυτ ωηεν ιτ ις εχπελλεδ φρομ τηε μουτη λεφτ σλαξκ, ιτ
					βεξομες ηοτ τηρουγη ραρεφαξτιον. αριστοτλε,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably (<hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the note on 950 b <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>) <hi rend="italics">Problemata</hi>, xxxiv. 7 (964 a 10 ff.); contrast Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 79 a-c.</note> ηοωεϝερ, ηολδς τηατ ιν τηις αναχιμενες ωας μιστακεν ·
					ωηεν τηε μουτη ις σλαξκ, ωηατ ις εχηαλεδ ις ωαρμ αιρ
					φρομ ουρ οων βοδιες ; βυτ ωηεν ωε ξομπρεσς τηε
					λιπς ανδ βλοω, ιτ ις νοτ αιρ φρομ ουρσελϝες, βυτ τηε ξολδ
					αιρ ιν φροντ οφ τηε μουτη τηατ ις προπελλεδ φορωαρδ ανδ
					μακες ξονταξτ.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.243"/>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="8">
<p>περηαπς ωε σηουλδ νοω λεαϝε τηε θυεστιον
					ωηετηερ ηεατ ανδ ξολδ αρε συβστανξες ; ιφ σο, λετ υς
					αδϝανξε τηε αργυμεντ το τηε νεχτ ποιντ ανδ ινθυιρε
					ωηατ σορτ οφ συβστανξε ξολδνεσς ηας, ανδ ωηατ ις ιτς
					φιρστ πρινξιπλε ανδ νατυρε. νοω τηοσε ωηο αφφιρμ
					τηατ τηερε αρε ξερταιν υνεϝεν, τριανγυλαρ φορματιονς
					ιν ουρ βοδιες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 53 c, 54 b-c.</note> ανδ τηατ σηιϝερινγ ανδ τρεμβλινγ,
					σηυδδερινγ ανδ τηε λικε μανιφεστατιονς, προξεεδ φρομ
					τηις ρουγη ιρρεγυλαριτψ, εϝεν ιφ τηεψ αρε ωρονγ ιν τηε
					παρτιξυλαρς, ατ λεαστ δεριϝε τηε φιρστ πρινξιπλε φρομ
					τηε προπερ πλαξε ; φορ τηε ινϝεστιγατιον σηουλδ βεγιν,
					ας ιτ ωερε φρομ τηε ϝερψ ηεαρτη,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Or, perhaps, <q direct="unspecified">with Hestia,</q> as the first principle of the cosmos (see, for example, Ritter, on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 247 a, pp. 123-124 of his edition). This passage is somewhat obscurely quoted below in 954 f. There were already three different interpretations known to the scholiast on Plato, <hi rend="italics">Euthyphro</hi>, 3 a (p. 2, ed. Greene).</note> φρομ τηε συβστανξε
					οφ αλλ τηινγς. τηις ις, ιτ ωουλδ σεεμ, τηε γρεατ διφφερενξε βετωεεν α πηιλοσοπηερ ανδ α πηψσιξιαν ορ α
					φαρμερ ορ α φλυτε-πλαψερ ; φορ τηε λαττερ αρε ξοντεντ
					το εχαμινε τηε ξαυσες μοστ ρεμοτε φρομ τηε φιρστ
					ξαυσε, σινξε ας σοον ας τηε μοστ ιμμεδιατε ξαυσε οφ
					αν εφφεξτ ις γρασπεδ - τηατ φεϝερ ις βρουγητ αβουτ βψ
					εχερτιον ορ αν οϝερφλοω οφ βλοοδ, τηατ ρυστινγ οφ γραιν
					ις ξαυσεδ βψ δαψς οφ βλαζινγ συν αφτερ α ραιν, τηατ α
					λοω νοτε ις προδυξεδ βψ τηε ανγλε ανδ ξονστρυξτιον
					οφ τηε πιπες - τηατ ις ενουγη το εναβλε α τεξηνιξιαν
					το δο ηις προπερ jοβ. βυτ ωηεν τηε νατυραλ πηιλοσοπηερ σετς ουτ το φινδ τηε τρυτη ας α ματτερ οφ σπεξυλατιϝε κνοωλεδγε, τηε δισξοϝερψ οφ ιμμεδιατε ξαυσες
					ις νοτ τηε ενδ, βυτ τηε βεγιννινγ οφ ηις jουρνεψ το
					τηε φιρστ ανδ ηιγηεστ ξαυσες. τηις ις τηε ρεασον ωηψ
					πλατο ανδ δεμοξριτυς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Wyttenbach suggested <q direct="unspecified">Xenocrates</q> for <q direct="unspecified">Democritus</q> in this passage, which may be right, though his proposal is not considered by either Mullach or Heinze.</note> ωηεν τηεψ ωερε ινθυιρινγ
					ιντο τηε ξαυσες οφ ηεατ ανδ ηεαϝινεσς, ωερε ριγητ νοτ
					το στοπ τηειρ ινϝεστιγατιον ωιτη εαρτη ανδ φιρε, βυτ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.245"/>
					
					το γο ον ξαρρψινγ βαξκ σενσιβλε πηενομενα το ρατιοναλ
					οριγινς υντιλ τηεψ ρεαξηεδ, ας ιτ ωερε, τηε μινιμυμ
					νυμβερ οφ σεεδς.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="9">
<p>νεϝερτηελεσς ιτ ις βεττερ φορ υς φιρστ το ατταξκ
					τηινγς περξεπτιβλε το τηε σενσες,ιν ωηιξη εμπεδοξλες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 319, frag. B 21, part of which is quoted below in 949 f.</note>
					ανδ στρατο<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See Fritz Wehrli, <hi rend="italics">Die Schule des Aristoteles</hi>, Part V. frag. 49.</note> ανδ τηε στοιξς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 952 c, 1053 f; von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, pp. 140 f.</note> λοξατε τηε συβστανξες
					τηατ υνδερλιε τηε θυαλιτιες, τηε στοιξς ασξριβινγ τηε
					πριμορδιαλλψ ξολδ το τηε αιρ, εμπεδοξλες ανδ στρατο
					το ωατερ ; ανδ σομεονε ελσε μαψ, περηαπς, βε φουνδ
					το αφφιρμ τηατ εαρτη ις τηε οριγιναλ συβστανξε οφ ξολδνεσς.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">As Plutarch himself: see below, 952 c ff. (chapters 17-22).</note> βυτ λετ υς εχαμινε στοιξ δοξτρινε βεφορε τηε
					οτηερς.
				</p>
<p>
					σινξε φιρε ις νοτ ονλψ ωαρμ βυτ βριγητ, τηε οπποσιτε
					νατυραλ εντιτψ ʽτηεψ σαψ̓ μυστ βε βοτη ξολδ ανδ δαρκ ·
					ας γλοομψ ις τηε οπποσιτε οφ βριγητ, σο ις ξολδ οφ ηοτ.
					βεσιδες, ας δαρκνεσς ξονφουνδς τηε σιγητ, σο ξολδ
					ξονφυσες τηε σενσε οφ τουξη. ηεατ, ον τηε οτηερ ηανδ,
					τρανσμιτς τηε σενσατιον οφ τουξηινγ, ας βριγητνεσς
					δοες τηατ οφ σεεινγ. ιτ φολλοως, τηεν, τηατ ιν νατυρε
					τηε πριμορδιαλλψ δαρκ ις αλσο τηε πριμορδιαλλψ ξολδ ;
					ανδ τηατ ιτ ις αιρ ωηιξη ις πριμορδιαλλψ δαρκ δοες νοτ,
					ιν φαξτ, εσξαπε τηε νοτιξε οφ τηε ποετς σινξε τηεψ υσε
					τηε τερμ <q direct="unspecified">αιρ</q> φορ <q direct="unspecified">δαρκνεσς</q>·
					<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>τηιξκ αιρ λαψ αλλ αβουτ τηε σηιπς, νορ ξουλδ
					</l>
<l>τηε μοον σηινε φορτη φρομ ηεαϝεν.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, ix. 144-145. Words for <q direct="unspecified">air</q> in Homer often mean <q direct="unspecified">mist</q> or <q direct="unspecified">fog.</q>
</note>
</l>
</quote>
					ανδ ανοτηερ ινστανξε ·
					<quote rend="blockquote">σο ξλαδ ιν αιρ τηεψ ϝισιτ αλλ τηε εαρτη.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Works and Days</hi>, 255.</note>
</quote>
<pb id="v.12.p.247"/>
					
					ανδ ανοτηερ·
					<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>τηε αιρ ατ ονξε ηε σξαττερεδ ανδ δισπελλεδ τηε μιστ;
					</l>
<l>τηε συν σηονε φορτη ανδ αλλ τηε βαττλε ξαρνε ιν ϝιεω.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xvii. 649-650.</note>
</l>
</quote>
					τηεψ αλσο ξαλλ τηε λιγητλεσς αιρ <hi rend="italics">κνεπηας</hi>, βεινγ ας ιτ
					ωερε, <hi rend="italics">κενον πηαους</hi>
<q direct="unspecified">ϝοιδ οφ λιγητ</q> ; ανδ ξολλεξτεδ
					ανδ ξονδενσεδ αιρ ηας βεεν τερμεδ <hi rend="italics">νεπηος</hi>
<q direct="unspecified">ξλουδ</q>
					βεξαυσε ιτ ις α νεγατιον οφ λιγητ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch's etymologies here are no more scientific or convincing than those to be found in his <hi rend="italics">Roman Questions</hi>, L.C.L. vol. iv, pp. 6-171.</note> φλεξκς ιν τηε σκψ
					ανδ μιστ ανδ φογ ανδ ανψτηινγ ελσε τηατ δοες νοτ
					προϝιδε α τρανσπαρεντ μεδιυμ φορ λιγητ το ρεαξη ουρ
					σενσες αρε μερελψ ϝαριατιονς οφ αιρ ; ανδ ιτς ινϝισιβλε
					ανδ ξολουρλεσς παρτ ις ξαλλεδ ηαδες ανδ αξηερον.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<q direct="unspecified">Invisible</q>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> 953 a below and Plato, <hi rend="italics">Cratylus</hi>, 403 a ff.; <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 81 c-d and contrast <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 942 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; <q direct="unspecified">colourless,</q>
<hi rend="italics">achroston, Acheron. Cf.</hi> L. Parmentier, <q direct="unspecified">Recherches sur le traite d'Isis et d'Osiris de Plut.,</q>
<hi rend="italics">Mem. Acad. Belg.</hi> ii. 2 (1912/13), pp. 71 ff.</note> ιν
					τηε σαμε ωαψ, τηεν, ας αιρ ις δαρκ ωηεν λιγητ ις γονε,
					σο ωηεν ηεατ δεπαρτς τηε ρεσιδυε ις ξολδ αιρ ανδ
					νοτηινγ ελσε. ανδ τηις ις τηε ρεασον ωηψ ιτ ηας βεεν
					τερμεδ ταρταρυς βεξαυσε οφ ιτς ξολδνεσς. ηεσιοδ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 119; contrast Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedo</hi>, 112 a ff.</note>
					μακες τηις οβϝιους ωηεν ηε ωριτες <q direct="unspecified">μυρκψ ταρταρυς</q> ; ανδ το σηακε ανδ σηιϝερ ωιτη ξολδ ις το
					<q direct="unspecified">ταρταριζε.</q>
<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Servius on Vergil, <hi rend="italics">Aen.</hi> vi. 577.</note> συξη, τηεν, ις τηε ρεασον φορ τηεσε
					ναμες.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="10">
<p>σινξε ξορρυπτιον, ιν εαξη ξασε, ις α ξηανγε οφ
					τηε τηινγς τηατ αρε ξορρυπτεδ ιντο τηειρ οπποσιτες,
					λετ υς σεε ωηετηερ τηε σαψινγ ηολδς γοοδ τηατ <q direct="unspecified">τηε
						δεατη οφ φιρε ις τηε βιρτη οφ αιρ.</q>
<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 168, Heraclitus, frag. 76 (frag. 25, ed. Bywater, p. 11). <hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 392 c-d.</note> φιρε, ινδεεδ,
					περισηες λικε α λιϝινγ ξρεατυρε,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 281 f, 702 e-f; 703 b.</note> βεινγ ειτηερ εχτινγυισηεδ βψ μαιν φορξε ορ δψινγ ουτ οφ ιτσελφ. νοω
					ιφ ιτ ις εχτινγυισηεδ, τηατ μακες τηε ξηανγε οφ φιρε
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.249"/>
					
					ιντο αιρ μορε ξονσπιξυους. σμοκε, ιν φαξτ, ις α φορμ
					οφ αιρ, ας ις ρεεκ ανδ εχηαλατιον, ωηιξη, το θυοτε
					πινδαρ,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Isth.</hi> iv. 112.</note>
<quote rend="blockquote">σταβς ατ τηε αιρ ωιτη υνξτυους σμοκε.</quote>
					νεϝερτηελεσς, εϝεν ωηεν φιρε γοες ουτ φορ λαξκ οφ
					νουρισημεντ, ονε μαψ σεε, ας φορ ινστανξε ιν τηε ξασε
					οφ λαμπς, τηε απεχ οφ τηε φλαμε πασσινγ οφφ ιντο μυρκψ,
					δυσκψ αιρ. μορεοϝερ, τηε ϝαπουρ ασξενδινγ φρομ ουρ
					βοδιες ωηεν, αφτερ α βατη ορ σωεατ, ξολδ ωατερ ις
					πουρεδ ον τηεμ, συφφιξιεντλψ ιλλυστρατες τηε ξηανγε
					οφ ηεατ, ας ιτ περισηες, ιντο τηε αιρ ; ανδ τηις ιμπλιες
					τηατ ιτ ις τηε νατυραλ οπποσιτε οφ φιρε. φρομ τηις τηε
					στοιξς δρεω τηε ξονξλυσιον τηατ αιρ ωας πριμορδιαλλψ
					δαρκ ανδ ξολδ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="11">
<p>μορεοϝερ, φρεεζινγ, ωηιξη ις τηε μοστ εχτρεμε
					ανδ ϝιολεντ εφφεξτ οφ ξολδ ιν βοδιες, ις α ξονδιτιον
					οφ ωατερ, βυτ α φυνξτιον οφ αιρ. φορ ωατερ οφ ιτσελφ ις
					φλυιδ, υνξονγεαλεδ ανδ νοτ ξοηεσιϝε ; βυτ ωηεν ιτ ις
					ξομπρεσσεδ βψ αιρ βεξαυσε οφ ιτς ξολδ στατε, ιτ βεξομες
					ταυτ ανδ ξομπαξτ. τηις ις τηε ρεασον φορ τηε σαψινγ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Included without authority among Callimachus's fragments (787 = anon. 384) by Schneider, but rejected by Pfeiffer.</note>
<quote rend="blockquote">ιφ σουτηωινδ ξηαλλενγες νορτη, ινσταντλψ σνοω ωιλλ αππεαρ.</quote>
					φορ αφτερ τηε σουτηωινδ ηας ξολλεξτεδ τηε μοιστυρε
					ας ραω ματεριαλ, τηε βορεαλ αιρ τακες οϝερ ανδ ξονγεαλς ιτ. τηις ις παρτιξυλαρλψ εϝιδεντ ιν σνοωφιελδς ·
					ωηεν τηεψ ηαϝε δισξηαργεδ α πρελιμιναρψ εχηαλατιον
					οφ αιρ τηατ ις τηιν ανδ ξολδ, τηεψ μελτ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 691 f and Hubert's references <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>
</note> αριστοτλε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 212, ed. Rose and <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 695 d.</note>
					αλσο δεξλαρες τηατ ωηετστονες οφ λεαδ ωιλλ μελτ ανδ
					βεξομε φλυιδ ιν τηε ωιντερτιμε τηρουγη εχξεσς οφ ξολδ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.251"/>
					
					ωηεν νο ωατερ ις ανψωηερε νεαρ τηεμ ; ιτ σεεμς
					προβαβλε τηατ τηε αιρ ωιτη ιτς ξολδνεσς φορξες τηε
					βοδιες τογετηερ υντιλ ιτ ξρυσηες ανδ βρεακς τηεμ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">There is here probably a confusion of lead and tin, for both of which the term <hi rend="italics">stannum</hi> is used in Latin. Tin is reduced to powder by severe cold, owing to transformation to its allotrope. In [Aristotle], <hi rend="italics">De Mir. Ausc.</hi> 50 (p. 257, L.C.L.) the more nearly correct statement appears that tin melts in severe cold. This note is due to the suggestion of O. T. Benfey of Haverford College.</note>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="12">
<p>φυρτηερμορε, πορτιονς οφ ωατερ ωιλλ φρεεζε
					σοονερ τηαν τηε σπρινγ φρομ ωηιξη τηεψ αρε δραων,
					φορ τηε αιρ μορε ρεαδιλψ μαστερς τηε σμαλλερ αμουντ.
					ιφ ψου ωιλλ δραω φρομ α ωελλ ξολδ ωατερ ιν α jαρ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably Plutarch is thinking of a jar of porous earthenware, such as are commonly used to cool water in the Near East.</note> ανδ
					λετ ιτ δοων αγαιν ιντο τηε ωελλ ιν συξη α ωαψ τηατ τηε
					jαρ δοες νοτ τουξη τηε ωατερ, βυτ ις συσπενδεδ ιν τηε
					αιρ, ανδ ιφ ψου ωαιτ α σηορτ τιμε, ψου ωιλλ φινδ τηατ τηε
					ωατερ ηας βεξομε ξολδερ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 690 b-e.</note> τηις ις ϝερψ γοοδ εϝιδενξε
					τηατ τηε φιρστ ξαυσε οφ ξολδνεσς ις νοτ ωατερ βυτ αιρ.
					ξερταινλψ, νονε οφ τηε γρεατ ριϝερς φρεεζες τηρουγη
					ιτς εντιρε δεπτη ; φορ τηε αιρ δοες νοτ πενετρατε δοων
					ιντο τηε ωηολε, βυτ μερελψ ρενδερς στατιοναρψ ας
					μυξη ας, βψ ξονταξτ ανδ προχιμιτψ, ιτ ινξλυδες ωιτηιν
					τηε ρανγε οφ ιτς ξολδνεσς. ανδ τηις ις τηε ρεασον ωηψ
					βαρβαριανς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Thracians, according to 968 f ff. <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> also Pliny, <hi rend="italics">Nat. Hist.</hi> viii. 103; Aelian, <hi rend="italics">De Natura Animal.</hi> vi. 24; xiv. 26.</note> δο νοτ ξροσς φροζεν ριϝερς υντιλ τηεψ ηαϝε
					τριεδ τηεμ ουτ ωιτη φοχες · ιφ τηε ιξε ις νοτ τηιξκ, βυτ
					μερελψ συπερφιξιαλ, τηε φοχες περξειϝε τηις βψ τηε
					σουνδ οφ τηε ξυρρεντ ρυννινγ υνδερνεατη ανδ ρετυρν
					το τηε βανκ. σομε εϝεν ξατξη φιση βψ ωεακενινγ ανδ
					σοφτενινγ τηε ιξε ωιτη ηοτ ωατερ - ενουγη οφ τηε ιξε,
					ατ λεαστ, το αδμιτ τηειρ λινες ; σο τηε ξολδ ηας νο εφφεξτ
					ατ α δεπτη. ψετ τηε ωατερ νεαρ τηε συρφαξε υνδεργοες
					σο γρεατ α ξηανγε τηρουγη φρεεζινγ τηατ σηιπς αρε
					ξρυσηεδ βψ ιτ ωηεν ιτ ις φορξεδ ιν ον ιτσελφ ανδ σθυεεζεδ
					τιγητ, ας τηοσε ρελατε ωηο ρεξεντλψ πασσεδ τηε ωιντερ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.253"/>
					
					ωιτη ξαεσαρ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Probably the reference is to Trajan and the Second Dacian War (a.d. 105-107). Plutarch's intimate friends, Sosius Senecio, is known to have taken part in it.</note> ον τηε δανυβε. νεϝερτηελεσς, ωηατ
					ηαππενς ιν ουρ οων ξασε ις αμπλε τεστιμονψ · αφτερ
					ωαρμ βατης ανδ σωεατς ωε αρε ξοολερ, σινξε ουρ βοδιες
					αρε ρελαχεδ ανδ πορους, σο τηατ ωε τακε ιν α γοοδ δεαλ
					οφ ξολδ αλονγ ωιτη τηε αιρ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 690 c-d.</note> τηε σαμε τηινγ ηαππενς
					το ωατερ, τοο · ιτ φρεεζες φαστερ ωηεν ιτ ηας φιρστ βεεν
					ηεατεδ, τηυς βεξομινγ μορε συσξεπτιβλε το αιρ ; ανδ
					τηοσε ωηο δραω οφφ βοιλινγ ωατερ ανδ συσπενδ ιτ ιν
					τηε αιρ δο τηις, συρελψ, ονλψ το σεξυρε τηε αδμιχτυρε
					οφ γρεατ θυαντιτιες οφ αιρ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 690 c-d.</note> σο νοω, φαϝορινυς, τηε
					αργυμεντ τηατ αττριβυτες τηε πριμαλ φορξε οφ ξολδ το
					τηε αιρ δεπενδς ον συξη πλαυσιβιλιτιες ας τηεσε.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="13">
<p>βυτ τηε αργυμεντ ωηιξη αττριβυτες ιτ το ωατερ
					φινδς ιν τηε σαμε ωαψ φαξτς το συππορτ ιτ; εμπεδοξλες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 319, frag. B 21, lines 3 and 5. Plutarch apparently used a version different from those known to Aristotle and Simplicius. The evidence is complicated and may be consulted in Diels-Kranz. On Empedocles' meaning see Cherniss, <hi rend="italics">Aristotle's Criticism of the Presocratics</hi>, p. 110.</note> σαψς σομετηινγ λικε τηις ·
					<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>βεηολδ τηε συν, εϝερψωηερε βριγητ ανδ ωαρμ;
					</l>
<l>ανδ τηεν τηε ραιν, το αλλ μεν δαρκ ανδ ξολδ.</l>
</quote>
					βψ τηυς σεττινγ ξολδ αγαινστ ηοτ, ας ηε δοες δαρκ
					αγαινστ βριγητ, ηε ηας γιϝεν υς το υνδερστανδ τηατ
					δαρκ ανδ ξολδ βελονγ το τηε σαμε συβστανξε, ας δο
					αλσο βριγητ ανδ ηοτ. ανδ ουρ σενσες βεαρ ωιτνεσς
					τηατ δαρκνεσς ις αν αττριβυτε οφ ωατερ, νοτ οφ αιρ, σινξε
					νοτηινγ, το πυτ ιτ σιμπλψ, ις βλαξκενεδ βψ αιρ ανδ
					εϝερψτηινγ ις βψ ωατερ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 364 b.</note> φορ ιφ ψου τηροω τηε ωηιτεστ
					ωοολ ορ τηε ωηιτεστ γαρμεντ ιντο ωατερ, ιτ ωιλλ ξομε
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.255"/>
					
					ουτ βλαξκ ανδ ιτ ωιλλ ρεμαιν βλαξκ υντιλ τηε μοιστυρε
					ις εϝαπορατεδ βψ ηεατ ορ ις σθυεεζεδ ουτ βψ σομε σορτ
					οφ ωρινγινγ ορ πρεσσυρε. ωηεν α πατξη οφ γρουνδ ις
					σπρινκλεδ, τηε σποτς ωηιξη αρε ξοϝερεδ βψ τηε δροπς
					τυρν βλαξκ, βυτ τηε ρεστ ρεμαινς ας ιτ ωας. ιν φαξτ,
					οφ ωατερ ιτσελφ τηε δεεπεστ λοοκς τηε δαρκεστ βεξαυσε
					τηερε ις σο μυξη οφ ιτ, ωηιλε τηοσε παρτς τηατ λιε νεαρ
					τηε αιρ φλαση ανδ σπαρκλε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 952 f <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>.</note>; ανδ οφ τηε οτηερ λιθυιδς
					οιλ ις τηε μοστ τρανσπαρεντ, ας ξονταινινγ τηε μοστ
					αιρ. α προοφ οφ τηις ις ιτς λιγητνεσς, βψ ρεασον οφ ωηιξη
					ιτ μαινταινς ιτσελφ ον τηε συρφαξε οφ αλλ οτηερ τηινγς,
					βυοψεδ υπ βψ τηε αιρ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 696 b, 702 b.</note> ιφ ιτ ις σπρινκλεδ υπον τηε
					ωαϝες, ιτ ωιλλ ξαλμ τηε σεα, νοτ βεξαυσε ιτ ις σο σμοοτη
					τηατ τηε ωινδς σλιπ οφφ ιτ, ας αριστοτλε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Problemata</hi>, 961 a 23 ff., though this work is surely not by Aristotle in the form in which it has come down to us.</note> αφφιρμεδ ; βυτ
					βεξαυσε τηε ωαϝες αρε δισσιπατεδ ωηεν τηεψ αρε
					στρυξκ βψ ανψ μοιστ συβστανξε. βυτ ιτ ις πεξυλιαρ το
					οιλ τηατ ιτ προϝιδες λιγητ ανδ σιγητ ατ τηε βοττομ σινξε
					τηε μοιστ ελεμεντς αρε ιντερσπερσεδ ωιτη αιρ ; ιτ ις,
					ιν φαξτ, νοτ ονλψ ον τηε συρφαξε τηατ ιτ προϝιδες λιγητ
					φορ τηοσε ωηο πασς τηε νιγητ ατ σεα ; ιτ δοες σο αλσο
					φορ σπονγε-διϝερς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 981 e <hi rend="italics">infra</hi>; Oppian, <hi rend="italics">Hal.</hi> v. 638 ff.</note> βελοω τηε συρφαξε ωηεν ιτ ις βλοων
					ουτ οφ τηειρ μουτης. αιρ, τηερεφορε, ηας νο γρεατερ
					προπορτιον οφ δαρκνεσς τηαν ωατερ ηας, ανδ ιτ ηας
					λεσς ξολδ. ξερταινλψ οιλ, ωηιξη ηας μορε αιρ τηαν ανψ
					οτηερ μοιστ συβστανξε, ις λεαστ ξολδ; ανδ ωηεν ιτ
					φρεεζες, ιτ φορμς α σοφτ jελλψ · τηε αιρ τηατ ις ιντερμιχεδ
					δοες νοτ περμιτ ιτ το φρεεζε ηαρδ. τηεψ διπ νεεδλες,
					ιρον ξλασπς, ανδ αλλ δελιξατε αρτιφαξτς ιν οιλ ρατηερ τηαν
					ιν ωατερ, φεαρινγ τηατ τηε ωατερʼς εχξεσσιϝε φριγιδιτψ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.257"/>
					
					μαψ διστορτ τηεμ. ιτ ις, ιν φαξτ, φαιρερ το jυδγε τηε
					αργυμεντ βψ τηις εϝιδενξε τηαν βψ τηατ οφ ξολουρ,
					σινξε σνοω ανδ ηαιλ ανδ ιξε αρε ατ τηειρ βριγητεστ ωηεν
					τηεψ αρε ξολδεστ. μορεοϝερ, πιτξη ις βοτη ηοττερ ανδ
					δαρκερ τηαν ηονεψ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="14">
<p>ι αμ συρπρισεδ, νεϝερτηελεσς, ωηεν τηοσε ωηο
					μαινταιν τηατ τηε αιρ ις ξολδ βεξαυσε ιτ ις δαρκ δο νοτ
					περξειϝε τηατ οτηερς τηινκ ιτ μυστ βε ηοτ βεξαυσε ιτ
					ις λιγητ. φορ δαρκνεσς ις νοτ σο ξλοσελψ ξοννεξτεδ ανδ
					ακιν το ξολδ ας ηεαϝινεσς ανδ σταβιλιτψ αρε ; μανψ
					τηινγς, ιν φαξτ, ωηιξη ηαϝε νο ηεατ αρε βριγητ, βυτ
					νοτηινγ ξολδ ις βυοψαντ, λιγητ, ανδ σοαρινγ. ωηψ,
					τηε ϝερψ ξλουδς, ας λονγ ας τηεψ αρε ακιν το τηε συβστανξε οφ αιρ, φλοατ αλοφτ; βυτ ας σοον ας τηεψ ξηανγε το
					μοιστυρε, τηεψ φαλλ ατ ονξε ανδ λοσε τηειρ λιγητνεσς νο
					λεσς τηαν τηειρ ωαρμτη ας ξολδνεσς γροως ωιτηιν τηεμ.
					ξοντραριωισε, ωηεν ηεατ συπερϝενες, τηεψ ρεϝερσε
					τηε μοϝεμεντ αγαιν, φορ τηειρ συβστανξε βεγινς το
					σοαρ ας σοον ας ιτ ηας ξηανγεδ το αιρ.
				</p>
<p>
					νορ ις τηε αργυμεντ φρομ δεστρυξτιον τρυε ειτηερ ;
					φορ ωηεν ανψτηινγ ις δεστροψεδ, ιτ δοες νοτ περιση βψ
					βεξομινγ ιτς οπποσιτε, τηουγη ιτ δοες περιση βψ τηε
					αξτιον οφ ιτς οπποσιτε, ας φιρε, φορ ινστανξε, ις ξηανγεδ
					βψ ωατερ ιντο αιρ. φορ οφ ωατερ αεσξηψλυς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Nauck, <hi rend="italics">Trag. Graec. Frag.</hi> pp. 107-108, frag. 360.</note> σπεακς
					ιν τραγιξ στψλε, βυτ αξξυρατελψ, ας
					<quote rend="blockquote">τηε ριοτ-θυελλινγ jυστιξερ οφ φιρε.</quote>
					ανδ ωηεν ηομερ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxi. 330-383; 435-469. The river is the Xanthus.</note> ματξηεδ ηεπηαεστυς αγαινστ τηε
					ριϝερ ανδ απολλο αγαινστ ποσειδον ιν τηε βαττλε, ηε
					διδ ιτ ρατηερ ας α πηιλοσοπηερ τηαν ας α ποετ. ανδ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.259"/>
					
					αρξηιλοξηυς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica Graeca</hi>, i. 237, frag. 86; Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Elegy and Iambus</hi> (L.C.L.), ii, p. 146, frag. 93; quoted again in <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 1070 a, <hi rend="italics">Life of Demetrius</hi>, 35 (905 e).</note> εχπρεσσεδ ηιμσελφ ωελλ ον α ωομαν
					ωηο ωας οφ τωο μινδς ·
					<quote rend="blockquote">
<l>ωιτη γυιλεφυλ τηουγητς σηε βορε
					</l>
<l>ιν ονε ηανδ ωατερ, ιν τηε οτηερ φιρε.</l>
</quote>
					αμονγ τηε περσιανς ιτ ωας τηε μοστ ξομπελλινγ πλεα
					το γαιν αν ενδ, ονε ωηιξη ωουλδ αδμιτ νο ρεφυσαλ, ιφ
					τηε συππλιαντ τοοκ φιρε, στοοδ ιν α ριϝερ, ανδ τηρεατενεδ
					τηατ ιφ ηε λοστ ηις συιτ, ηε ωουλδ δροπ τηε φιρε ιντο τηε
					ωατερ. νοω ηε γοτ ωηατ ηε ασκεδ, βυτ τηουγη ηε
					διδ σο, ηε ωας πυνισηεδ φορ τηε τηρεατ, ον τηε γρουνδ
					τηατ ιτ ωας ξοντραρψ το λαω ανδ αγαινστ νατυρε. αγαιν,
					τηε φαμιλιαρ προϝερβ τηατ ις ον εϝερψονεʼς λιπς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">But, curiously enough, not to be found in the <hi rend="italics">Paroemiographi Graeci</hi>, as edited by Leutsch and Schneidewin.</note>
<q direct="unspecified">το
						μιχ φιρε ωιτη ωατερ,</q> ας αν εχαμπλε οφ τηε ιμποσσιβλε,
					σεεμς το βεαρ ωιτνεσς τηατ ωατερ ις ηοστιλε το φιρε,
					ωηιξη ις δεστροψεδ βψ ιτ ανδ σο ις πυνισηεδ βψ βεινγ
					εχτινγυισηεδ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the quotation from Aeschylus <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, 950 e.</note>; ιτ ις νοτ σο αφφεξτεδ βψ αιρ, ωηιξη, ον
					τηε ξοντραρψ, συππορτς φιρε ανδ ωελξομες ιτ ιν ιτς
					ξηανγεδ φορμ. φορ ιφ ανψτηινγ ιντο ωηιξη τηε τηινγ
					δεστροψεδ ξηανγες ις ιτς οπποσιτε, ωηψ ωιλλ φιρε, ανψ
					μορε τηαν ωατερ, σεεμ οπποσιτε το αιρ ? φορ αιρ
					ξηανγες ιντο ωατερ βψ ξονδενσατιον, ανδ ιντο φιρε βψ
					ραρεφαξτιον jυστ ας, ον τηε οτηερ ηανδ, ωατερ ϝανισηες
					ιντο αιρ βψ ραρεφαξτιον, βυτ ιντο εαρτη βψ ξονδενσατιον.
					νοω τηεσε προξεσσες τακε πλαξε, ιν μψ οπινιον, νοτ
					βεξαυσε τηεσε ελεμεντς αρε ξοντραρψ ορ ηοστιλε το ονε
					ανοτηερ, βυτ βεξαυσε τηεψ αρε ιν ξλοσε αφφινιτψ ανδ ρελατιονσηιπ. βυτ μψ οππονεντς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Presumably those who, in 950 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>, claim that air is cold because it is dark.</note> ωηιξηεϝερ ωαψ τηεψ
					στατε τηειρ ξασε, ρυιν τηειρ προοφ. ξερταινλψ ιτ ις περφεξτλψ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.261"/>
					
					αβσυρδ φορ τηεμ το σαψ τηατ ωατερ ις φροζεν βψ αιρ
					ωηεν τηεψ ηαϝε νεϝερ σεεν αιρ ιτσελφ φρεεζινγ. φορ
					ξλουδς, μιστς, ανδ φλεξκς ιν τηε σκψ αρε νοτ ξονγελατιονς, βυτ ξονδενσατιονς ανδ τηιξκενινγς οφ αιρ τηατ ις
					μοιστ ανδ ϝαπορους. βυτ ωατερλεσς, δρψ αιρ νεϝερ
					αδμιτς λοσς οφ ηεατ το τηε ποιντ ωηερε συξη α ξηανγε
					μιγητ οξξυρ. τηερε αρε, ιν φαξτ, μουνταινς ωηιξη δο
					νοτ κνοω ξλουδς ορ δεω ορ μιστ βεξαυσε τηειρ πεακς
					ρεαξη α ρεγιον οφ πυρε αιρ τηατ ηας νο ηυμιδιτψ ατ αλλ.
					φρομ τηις φαξτ ιτ ις εσπεξιαλλψ οβϝιους τηατ ιτ ις τηε
					ξονδενσατιον ανδ δενσιτψ βελοω τηατ ξοντριβυτε το αιρ
					τηε ξολδ, μοιστ ελεμεντ τηατ ις φουνδ ιν ξομβινατιον
					ωιτη ιτ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="15">
<p>ιτ ις ρεασοναβλε τηατ τηε λοωερ πορτιον οφ λαργε
					ριϝερς σηουλδ νοτ φρεεζε ; φορ τηε υππερ πορτιον, βεινγ
					φροζεν, δοες νοτ τρανσμιτ τηε εχηαλατιον ωηιξη ις,
					αξξορδινγλψ, σηυτ ιν ανδ τυρνεδ βαξκ, ανδ σο προϝιδες
					ηεατ φορ τηε δεεπ ωατερς. α δεμονστρατιον οφ τηις
					ις τηε φαξτ τηατ ωηεν τηε ιξε μελτς αγαιν α γρεατ
					θυαντιτψ οφ ϝαπουρ ρισες φρομ τηε ωατερς. τηις ις αλσο
					τηε ρεασον ωηψ τηε βοδιες οφ ανιμαλς αρε ωαρμερ ιν
					τηε ωιντερ, βεξαυσε τηε ηεατ ις δριϝεν ινωαρδς βψ τηε
					ξολδ φρομ ωιτηουτ ανδ τηεψ κεεπ ιτ ωιτηιν τηεμ.
				</p>
<p>
					νοω δραωινγ οφφ ωατερ ανδ συσπενδινγ ιτ ιν τηε
					αιρ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 949 f <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>; <hi rend="italics">Mor.</hi> 690 b-e.</note> νοτ ονλψ τακες αωαψ ιτς ωαρμτη, βυτ ιτς ξολδνεσς
					αλσο; τηοσε, τηερεφορε, ωηο ωαντ α ϝερψ ξολδ δρινκ
					τακε ξαρε νοτ το διστυρβ τηε σνοωπαξκς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 691 c - 692 a for snow packed in chaff and the like.</note> ορ τηε ωετ
					ματτερ τηατ ις φορμεδ φρομ τηεμ βψ ξομπρεσσιον,
					φορ μοϝεμεντ εχπελς βοτη ηεατ ανδ ξολδ.
				</p>
<p>
					τηατ συξη α φυνξτιον οφ ξολδ βελονγς νοτ το αιρ, βυτ
					το ωατερ, μαψ βε δεμονστρατεδ ας φολλοως φρομ α φρεση
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.263"/>
					
					σταρτ. ιν τηε φιρστ πλαξε, ιτ ις ιμπροβαβλε τηατ αιρ,
					ωηιξη λιες αδjαξεντ το τηε αετηερ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">On the difference between <hi rend="italics">aer</hi> and <hi rend="italics">aether</hi> see the lucid discussion of Guthrie, <hi rend="italics">The Greeks and their Gods</hi>, pp. 207 f.</note> ανδ τουξηες ανδ ις
					τουξηεδ βψ τηε ρεϝολϝινγ φιερψ συβστανξε, σηουλδ ηαϝε
					α φορξε τηατ ις ξοντραρψ το τηατ οφ αετηερ. φορ ονε
					τηινγ, ιτ ις ιμποσσιβλε φορ τωο συβστανξες ωηοσε βουνδαριες τουξη ανδ αρε ξοντιγυους νοτ το βε αξτεδ υπον
					βψ εαξη οτηερ - ανδ ιφ αξτεδ υπον, φορ τηε ωεακερ νοτ
					το βε ξονταμινατεδ βψ τηε φορξε τηατ ρεσιδες ιν τηε
					στρονγερ. νορ ις ιτ ρεασοναβλε το συπποσε τηατ νατυρε
					ηας πλαξεδ σιδε βψ σιδε δεστροψερ ανδ ϝιξτιμ, ας τηουγη
					σηε ωερε τηε αυτηορ οφ στριφε ανδ δισσενσιον, νοτ οφ
					υνιον ανδ ηαρμονψ. σηε δοες, ινδεεδ, μακε υσε οφ
					οπποσιτες το ξονστιτυτε τηε υνιϝερσε ; ψετ σηε δοες
					νοτ εμπλοψ τηεμ ωιτηουτ α τεμπερινγ ελεμεντ, ορ
					ωηερε τηεψ ωιλλ ξολλιδε. σηε δισποσες τηεμ ρατηερ
					σο τηατ α σπαξε ις σκιππεδ ανδ αν ινσερτεδ στριπ δυλψ
					ασσιγνεδ ωηερεβψ τηεψ ωιλλ νοτ δεστροψ ονε ανοτηερ,
					βυτ μαψ ενjοψ ξομμυνιξατιον ανδ ξο-οπερατιον. ανδ
					τηις στριπ ις οξξυπιεδ βψ αιρ, συφφυσεδ ας ιτ ις τηρουγη
					α σπαξε υνδερ τηε φιρε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, the aether. See also Cherniss, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> p. 126.</note> βετωεεν ιτ ανδ ωατερ. ιτ
					μακες διστριβυτιον βοτη ωαψς ανδ ρεξειϝες ξοντριβυτιονς φρομ βοτη, βεινγ ιτσελφ νειτηερ ηοτ νορ ξολδ, βυτ
					α βλενδινγ ανδ υνιον οφ τηε τωο. ωηεν τηεσε αρε σο
					φυσεδ, τηεψ μεετ ωιτηουτ ινjυρψ ανδ τηε φυσεδ ματτερ
					σενδς φορτη ορ τακες το ιτσελφ τηε οπποσινγ εχτρεμες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Heat and cold.</note>
					ωιτηουτ ϝιολενξε.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="16">
<p>τηεν, τοο, αιρ ις εϝερψωηερε εθυαλ; τηουγη
					νειτηερ ωιντερ νορ ξολδ ις ιδεντιξαλ εϝερψωηερε. ιτ
					ις νο αξξιδεντ τηατ σομε παρτς οφ τηε ωορλδ αρε ξολδ
					ανδ δαμπ, ωηιλε οτηερς αρε ηοτ ανδ δρψ ; ιτ ις δυε
					το τηε εχιστενξε οφ α σινγλε συβστανξε τηατ ινξλυδες
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.265"/>
					
					ξολδνεσς ανδ ωετνεσς ιν ονε. τηε γρεατερ παρτ οφ
					αφριξα ις ηοτ ανδ ωιτηουτ ωατερ ; ωηιλε τηοσε ωηο
					ηαϝε τραϝελλεδ τηρουγη σξψτηια, τηραξε, ανδ ποντυς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch may be thinking of the old kingdom of Pontus, which included tracts south, east, and north of the Black Sea.</note>
					ρεπορτ τηατ τηεσε ρεγιονς ηαϝε γρεατ λακες ορ μαρσηες
					ανδ αρε τραϝερσεδ βψ μανψ δεεπ ριϝερς. ας φορ τηε
					ρεγιονς τηατ λιε βετωεεν, τηοσε τηατ αρε νεαρ λακες
					ανδ μαρσηες αρε εσπεξιαλλψ ξολδ βεξαυσε οφ τηε εχηαλατιονς φρομ τηε ωατερ, ποσιδονιυς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The fragment has not yet been numbered in L. Edelstein's forthcoming collection; for the literature see <hi rend="italics">A.J.P.</hi> lvii (1936), p. 301 and n. 61.</note> τηεν, ιν
					αφφιρμινγ τηατ τηε φρεσηνεσς ανδ μοιστνεσς οφ μαρση
					αιρ ις τηε ρεασον φορ τηε ξολδ, ηας δονε νοτηινγ το
					διστυρβ τηε πλαυσιβιλιτψ οφ τηε αργυμεντ; ηε ηας,
					ρατηερ, μαδε ιτ μορε πλαυσιβλε. φορ φρεση αιρ ωουλδ
					νοτ αλωαψς σεεμ ξολδερ ιφ ξολδ διδ νοτ τακε ιτς οριγιν
					φρομ μοιστυρε. σο ηομερ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Odyssey</hi>, v. 469.</note> σποκε μορε τρυλψ ωηεν
					ηε αφφιρμεδ
					<quote rend="blockquote">τηε ριϝερ-αιρ βλοως ξηιλλ βεφορε τηε δαων,</quote>
					τηερεβψ ινδιξατινγ τηε σουρξε οφ ξολδνεσς.
				</p>
<p>
					ουρ σενσες, μορεοϝερ, οφτεν δεξειϝε υς ανδ ωε
					ιμαγινε, ωηεν ωε τουξη ξολδ γαρμεντς ορ ξολδ ωοολ,
					τηατ ωε αρε τουξηινγ μοιστ οβjεξτς · τηις ις βεξαυσε
					ωετ ανδ ξολδ ηαϝε α ξομμον συβστανξε ανδ τηειρ
					νατυρες ηαϝε α ξλοσε αφφινιτψ ανδ ρελατιονσηιπ. ιν ϝερψ
					ξολδ ξλιματες τηε λοω τεμπερατυρε οφτεν βρεακς
					ϝεσσελς ωηετηερ τηεψ αρε οφ βρονζε ορ οφ ξλαψ - νοτ,
					οφ ξουρσε, ωηεν τηεψ αρε εμπτψ, βυτ ονλψ ωηεν τηεψ
					αρε φυλλ ανδ τηε ωατερ εχερτς πρεσσυρε βψ μεανς οφ
					ιτς ξολδνεσς. τηεοπηραστυς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The fragment is apparently omitted by Wimmer.</note> το βε συρε, δεξλαρες τηατ
					τηε αιρ βρεακς τηεσε ϝεσσελς, υσινγ τηε λιθυιδ ας α
					σπικε. βυτ τακε ξαρε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">This seems to be addressed to Favorinus's Peripatetic sympathies.</note> τηατ τηερε ισνʼτ μορε ωιτ τηαν
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.267"/>
					
					τρυτη ιν συξη α ρεμαρκ! φορ ιφ ιτ ωερε σο, ϝεσσελς φυλλ
					οφ πιτξη ορ οφ μιλκ ωουλδ μορε ρεαδιλψ βε βροκεν βψ
					τηε αιρ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">That is, than those full of water.</note>
</p>
<p>
					ωατερ, ηοωεϝερ, σεεμς το βε ξολδ οφ ιτσελφ, ανδ
					πριμορδιαλλψ σο. ιτ ις τηε αντιτηεσις, ιν ιτς ξολδνεσς,
					το τηε ηεατ οφ φιρε, jυστ ας ιν ιτς ωετνεσς το τηε δρψνεσς
					οφ φιρε, ανδ ιν ιτς ηεαϝινεσς το τηε οτηερʼς λιγητνεσς.
					το συμ υπ · φιρε ις οφ α δισιντεγρατινγ ανδ σεπαρατιϝε
					νατυρε, ωηιλε ωατερ ις αδηεσιϝε ανδ ρετεντιϝε, ηολδινγ
					ανδ γλυινγ τογετηερ βψ μεανς οφ ιτς μοιστνεσς.
					εμπεδοξλες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 318, frag. B 19. Plutarch seems to have mistaken Empedocles' meaning, though some would invoke frag. B 34. In general, while Plutarch is said to have written ten books on Empedocles (Lamprias catalogue no. 43), he does not seek the difficult poet's meaning very carefully.</note> αλλυδεδ το τηις, ωηεν, ας οφτεν ας ηε
					μεντιονεδ τηεμ, ηε τερμεδ φιρε α <q direct="unspecified">δεστρυξτιϝε
						στριφε</q> ανδ ωατερ <q direct="unspecified">τεναξιους λοϝε.</q> φορ τηε
					νουρισημεντ οφ φιρε ις τηατ ωηιξη ξαν βε ξηανγεδ
					ιντο φιρε ανδ ονλψ τηινγς τηατ ηαϝε αφφινιτψ ανδ α
					ξλοσε ρελατιονσηιπ το ιτ ξαν βε σο ξηανγεδ ; ωηιλε
					ιτς οπποσιτες, λικε ωατερ, αρε νοτ εασιλψ ξηανγεδ το
					φιρε. ωατερ ιτσελφ ις πραξτιξαλλψ ινξομβυστιβλε, ανδ ιτ
					ρενδερς ματτερ συξη ας δαμπ γρασς ανδ μοιστ τιμβερ
					ϝερψ ηαρδ το ξονσυμε ; τηε γρεεννεσς ιν τηεμ προδυξες α δυσκψ, δυλλ φλαμε βεξαυσε, βψ διντ οφ ξολδ, ιτ
					στρυγγλες αγαινστ ηεατ ας αγαινστ ιτς νατυραλ ενεμψ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="17">
<p>νοω ψου μυστ πυρσυε τηε συβjεξτ βψ ξομπαρινγ
					τηεσε αργυμεντς ωιτη τηοσε οφ μψ οππονεντς. φορ
					ξηρψσιππυς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Von Arnim, <hi rend="italics">S.V.F.</hi> ii, p. 140; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 1053 e.</note> τηινκινγ τηατ τηε αιρ ις πριμορδιαλλψ
					ξολδ βεξαυσε ιτ ις αλσο δαρκ, μερελψ μεντιονεδ τηοσε
					ωηο αφφιρμ τηατ ωατερ ις ατ α γρεατερ διστανξε φρομ τηε
					αετηερ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 951 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> τηαν ις αιρ ; ανδ, ωισηινγ το μακε τηεμ σομε
					ανσωερ, ηε σαιδ, <q direct="unspecified">ιφ σο, ωε μιγητ ας ωελλ δεξλαρε τηατ
						εϝεν εαρτη ις πριμορδιαλλψ ξολδ βεξαυσε ιτ ις ατ τηε
						
						<pb id="v.12.p.269"/>
						
						γρεατεστ διστανξε φρομ τηε αετηερ</q> - τοσσινγ οφφ τηις
					αργυμεντ ας ιφ ιτ ωερε υττερλψ ιναδμισσιβλε ανδ αβσυρδ.
					βυτ ι ηαϝε α μινδ το μαινταιν τηε τηεσις τηατ εαρτη
					τοο ις νοτ δεστιτυτε οφ προβαβλε ανδ ξονϝινξινγ αργυμεντς, ανδ ι σηαλλ σταρτ ωιτη τηε ονε τηατ ξηρψσιππυς
					ηας φουνδ μοστ σερϝιξεαβλε φορ αιρ. ανδ ωηατ ις τηις ?
					ωηψ, τηατ ιτ ις πριμορδιαλλψ δαρκ ανδ ξολδ. φορ ιφ ηε
					τακες τηεσε τωο παιρς οφ οπποσινγ φορξες ανδ ασσυμες
					τηατ ονε μυστ οφ νεξεσσιτψ αξξομπανψ τηε οτηερ,
					τηερε αρε, συρελψ, ιννυμεραβλε οπποσιτιονς ανδ αντιπατηιες βετωεεν τηε αετηερ ανδ τηε εαρτη ωιτη ωηιξη
					ονε μιγητ συπποσε τηις το βε ξονσιστεντ. φορ ιτ
					ις νοτ ονλψ οπποσεδ ας ηεαϝψ το λιγητ ανδ ας μοϝινγ
					βψ γραϝιτψ δοωνωαρδς, νοτ υπωαρδς, ορ ας δενσε
					το ραρε ορ ας σλοω ανδ σταβλε το μοβιλε ανδ αξτιϝε,
					βυτ ας ηεαϝιεστ το λιγητεστ ανδ ας δενσεστ το ραρεστ
					ανδ, φιναλλψ, ας ιμμοϝαβλε οφ ιτσελφ το σελφ-μοϝινγ,
					ανδ ας οξξυπψινγ τηε ξεντραλ ποσιτιον ιν τηε υνιϝερσε
					το ρεϝολϝινγ φορεϝερ αρουνδ α ξεντρε. ιτ ις νοτ αβσυρδ,
					τηεν, ιφ οπποσιτιονς σο νυμερους ανδ ιμπορταντ ξαρρψ
					ωιτη τηεμ τηε οπποσιτιον οφ ξολδ ανδ ηεατ ας ωελλ.
					<q direct="unspecified">ψες,</q> ξηρψσιππυς μαψ σαψ, <q direct="unspecified">βυτ φιρε ις βριγητ.</q>
					ις νοτ τηε εαρτη, τηεν, δαρκ ? ωηψ, ιτ ις τηε δαρκεστ
					ανδ μοστ υνιλλυμινατεδ οφ αλλ τηινγς. ξερταινλψ αιρ
					ις φιρστ οφ αλλ το παρτιξιπατε ιν λιγητ; ιτ ις ινσταντλψ
					αλτερεδ ανδ ωηεν ιτ ις σατυρατεδ, ιτ διστριβυτες
					ιλλυμινατιον εϝερψωηερε, λενδινγ ιτσελφ το λιγητ ας α
					βοδψ ιν ωηιξη το ρεσιδε. φορ ωηεν τηε συν αρισες,
					ας ονε οφ τηε διτηψραμβιξ ωριτερς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica Graeca</hi>, ii. 302; Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi> (L.C.L.), iii, p. 460 (adespota no. 95).</note> ηας σαιδ,
					<quote rend="blockquote">ιτ στραιγητωαψ φιλλς τηε μιγητψ ηομε οφ τηε αιρ-βορνε ωινδς.</quote>
<pb id="v.12.p.271"/>
					
					νεχτ τηε αιρ, μοϝινγ δοωνωαρδ, ινφυσες α παρτ οφ ιτς
					βριγητνεσς ιντο τηε λακες ανδ τηε σεα, ανδ τηε δεπτης
					οφ τηε ριϝερς φλαση βριγητλψ,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Aeschylus, <hi rend="italics">Prometheus</hi>, 90, and 950 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> το τηε εχτεντ τηατ αιρ
					ις αβλε το πενετρατε τηεμ. οφ αλλ βοδιες ονλψ τηε
					εαρτη ρεμαινς ξονσταντλψ ωιτηουτ λιγητ, ιμπενετραβλε
					το τηε ιλλυμινατιον οφ συν ορ μοον ; ψετ ιτ ις ωαρμεδ
					βψ τηεμ ανδ περμιτς τηε ηεατ το σινκ ιν ανδ ωαρμ
					ιτ υπ το α σλιγητ δεπτη. βυτ βεξαυσε ιτ ις σολιδ, εαρτη
					δοες νοτ γιϝε πασσαγε το λιγητ, βυτ ις ενξιρξλεδ βψ
					λιγητ ον ιτς συρφαξε ονλψ, ωηιλε τηε ιννερ παρτς αρε
					ξαλλεδ δαρκνεσς ανδ ξηαος ανδ ηαδες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Invisible Place, according to the etymology adopted above in 948 f.</note> - σο τηατ
					ερεβυς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Hesiod, <hi rend="italics">Theogony</hi>, 125. The original meaning of Erebus is actually <q direct="unspecified">darkness</q>.</note> τυρνς ουτ το βε τηε συβτερρανεαν ανδ ιντεριορ
					δαρκνεσς. τηεν, τοο, τηε ποετς τελλ υς τηατ νιγητ
					ωας βορν οφ εαρτη<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 331, Empedocles, frag. B 48; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 1006 f.</note> ανδ ματηεματιξιανς δεμονστρατε
					τηατ νιγητ ις τηε σηαδοω οφ εαρτη βλοξκινγ τηε λιγητ
					οφ τηε συν. τηε αιρ, ινδεεδ, ις σατυρατεδ ωιτη δαρκνεσς βψ τηε εαρτη, jυστ ας ιτ ις ωιτη λιγητ βψ τηε συν.
					τηε υνλιγητεδ πορτιον οφ τηε αιρ ις τηε αρεα οφ νιγητ,
					αμουντινγ το τηε σπαξε οξξυπιεδ βψ τηε εαρτηʼς
					σηαδοω. τηις ις τηε ρεασον ωηψ μεν μακε υσε οφ τηε
					αιρ ουτ οφ δοορς εϝεν ωηεν ιτ ις νιγητ, ας ωελλ ας μανψ
					βεαστς ωηιξη δο τηειρ παστυρινγ ιν τηε δαρκνεσς, σινξε
					ιτ ρεταινς σομε ϝεστιγες οφ λιγητ ανδ δισπερσεδ γλιμμερινγς οφ ραδιανξε ; βυτ τηε ηουσε-βουνδ μαν ωηο
					ις υνδερ α ροοφ ις υττερλψ βλινδ ανδ ωιτηουτ λιγητ
					ινασμυξη ας τηερε τηε εαρτη ενϝελοπς ηιμ φρομ αλλ
					διρεξτιονς. ωηολε σκινς, φυρτηερμορε, ανδ ηορνς οφ
					ανιμαλς δο νοτ λετ λιγητ πασς τηρουγη τηεμ βεξαυσε
					οφ τηειρ σολιδιτψ ; ψετ ιφ σεξτιονς αρε σαωεδ οφφ ανδ
					πολισηεδ, τηεψ βεξομε τρανσλυξεντ ωηεν ονξε τηε
					αιρ ηας βεεν μιχεδ ωιτη τηεμ. ιτ ις αλσο μψ οπινιον
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.273"/>
					
					τηατ τηε εαρτη ις ξαλλεδ βλαξκ βψ τηε ποετς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">e.g.</hi> Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, ii. 699; Alcman, 36 (Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">Lyra Graeca</hi>, i, p. 76; Diehl, <hi rend="italics">Anthologia Lyrica Graeca</hi>, ii. 27); Sappho, 38 (Edmonds, <hi rend="italics">op. cit.</hi> i, p. 208).</note> ωηενεϝερ
					τηεψ ηαϝε οξξασιον το δο σο, βεξαυσε οφ ιτς μυρκψ ανδ
					λιγητλεσς ξηαραξτεριστιξς. τηε ρεσυλτ, τηεν, οφ τηεσε
					ξονσιδερατιονς ις τηατ τηε μυξη-πριζεδ αντιτηεσις οφ
					λιγητ ανδ δαρκνεσς βελονγς το εαρτη ρατηερ τηαν το αιρ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="18">
<p>τηις, ηοωεϝερ, ηας νο ρελεϝανξε το τηε θυεστιον
					υνδερ δισξυσσιον ; φορ ιτ ηας βεεν σηοων τηατ τηερε
					αρε μανψ ξολδ οβjεξτς ωηιξη αρε βριγητ ανδ μανψ
					ηοτ ωηιξη αρε δυλλ ανδ δαρκ. ψετ τηερε αρε θυαλιτιες
					μορε ξλοσελψ ξοννεξτεδ τηατ βελονγ το ξολδνεσς ·
					ηεαϝινεσς, σταβιλιτψ, σολιδιτψ, ανδ ρεσιστανξε το ξηανγε.
					αιρ ηας νο παρτ ατ αλλ ιν τηεμ, ωηιλε εαρτη ηας α γρεατερ
					σηαρε ιν αλλ οφ τηεμ τηαν ωατερ ηας. ξολδ, μορεοϝερ,
					ις περξεπτιβλψ ονε οφ τηε ηαρδεστ οφ τηινγς ανδ ιτ
					μακες τηινγς ηαρδ ανδ υνψιελδινγ. τηεοπηραστυς,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Frag. 184 Wimmer.</note>
					φορ ινστανξε, τελλς υς τηατ ωηεν φροζεν φιση αρε δροππεδ
					ον τηε γρουνδ, τηεψ αρε βροκεν ανδ σμασηεδ το βιτς
					jυστ λικε οβjεξτς οφ γλασς ορ εαρτηενωαρε. ανδ ατ
					δελπηι ψου ψουρσελφ ηεαρδ, ιν τηε ξασε οφ τηοσε ωηο
					ξλιμβεδ παρνασσυς το ρεσξυε τηε τηψιαδες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">The Thyiades were Attic women, devotees of Dionysus, who went every other year to Delphi to join in the midwinter festival. See Guthrie, <hi rend="italics">The Greeks and their Gods</hi>, p. 178.) The rites must have involved considerable discomfort and even risk, as Dodds says (edition of Euripides, <hi rend="italics">Bacchae</hi>, p. xi).</note> ωηεν
					τηεψ ωερε τραππεδ βψ α φιερξε γαλε ανδ σνοωστορμ,
					τηατ τηειρ ξαπες ωερε φροζεν σο στιφφ ανδ ωοοδεν τηατ
					ωηεν τηεψ ωερε οπενεδ ουτ, τηεψ βροκε ανδ σπλιτ
					απαρτ. εχξεσσιϝε ξολδ, βεξαυσε οφ ιτς ηαρδνεσς ανδ
					ιμμοβιλιτψ, αλσο στιφφενς τηε μυσξλες ανδ ρενδερς τηε
					τονγυε σπεεξηλεσς, φορ ιτ ξονγεαλς τηε μοιστ ανδ
					τενδερ παρτς οφ τηε βοδψ.
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.275"/>
</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="19">
<p>ιν ϝιεω οφ τηεσε ξονσιδερατιονς, ρεγαρδ τηε
					φαξτς ιν τηε φολλοωινγ λιγητ · εϝερψ φορξε, πρεσυμαβλψ,
					ωηενεϝερ ιτ πρεϝαιλς, βψ α λαω οφ νατυρε ξηανγες ανδ
					τυρνς ιντο ιτσελφ ωηατεϝερ ιτ οϝερξομες. ωηατ ις
					μαστερεδ βψ ηεατ ις ρεδυξεδ το φλαμες, ωηατ ις
					μαστερεδ βψ ωινδ τυρνς το αιρ ; ανδ ανψτηινγ τηατ
					φαλλς ιντο τηε ωατερ, υνλεσς ιτ γετς ουτ θυιξκλψ, δισσολϝες ανδ λιθυεφιες. ιτ φολλοως, τηεν, τηατ ωηατεϝερ
					ις ξομπλετελψ φροζεν μυστ τυρν ιντο πριμορδιαλ ξολδ.
					νοω φρεεζινγ ις εχτρεμε ρεφριγερατιον τηατ τερμινατες
					ιν α ξομπλετε αλτερατιον ανδ πετριφαξτιον ωηεν, σινξε
					τηε ξολδ ηας οβταινεδ ξομπλετε μαστερψ, τηε μοιστ
					ελεμεντς αρε φροζεν σολιδ ανδ τηε ηεατ ις σθυεεζεδ
					ουτ. τηις ις τηε ρεασον ωηψ τηε εαρτη ατ ιτς βοττομμοστ ποιντ ις πραξτιξαλλψ αλλ σολιδ φροστ ανδ ιξε. φορ
					τηερε υνδιλυτεδ ανδ υνμιτιγατεδ ξολδ αβιδες ατ βαψ,
					τηρυστ βαξκ το τηε ποιντ φαρτηεστ ρεμοϝεδ φρομ τηε
					φλαμινγ αετηερ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See 951 d above.</note> ας φορ τηεσε φεατυρες τηατ αρε
					ϝισιβλε, ξλιφφς ανδ ξραγς ανδ ροξκς, εμπεδοξλες<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, i, p. 296, frag. A 69; <hi rend="italics">cf. Mor.</hi> 691 b and Hubert's references <hi rend="italics">ad loc.</hi>
</note> τηινκς
					τηατ τηεψ ηαϝε βεεν φιχεδ ιν πλαξε ανδ αρε υπηελδ βψ
					ρεστινγ ον τηε φιρε τηατ βυρνς ιν τηε δεπτης οφ τηε
					εαρτη ; βυτ τηε ινδιξατιονς αρε ρατηερ τηατ αλλ τηεσε
					τηινγς φρομ ωηιξη τηε ηεατ ωας σθυεεζεδ ουτ ανδ
					εϝαπορατεδ ωερε ξομπλετελψ φροζεν βψ τηε ξολδ ; ανδ
					φορ τηις ρεασον τηεψ αρε ξαλλεδ <hi rend="italics">παγοι</hi>.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Crags and rocks are called <hi rend="italics">pagoi</hi> (as the Areo-pagus, <q direct="unspecified">Mars Hill,</q> at Athens), which Plutarch correctly connects with the verb meaning <q direct="unspecified">freeze</q> or <q direct="unspecified">solidify</q> and uses to confute Empedocles.</note> σο αλσο τηε
					πεακς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch is speaking of volcanoes like Aetna with a lava bed on top.</note> οφ μανψ οφ τηεμ ηαϝε α βλαξκ ξρυστ ωηερε τηε
					ηεατ ηας βεεν εχπελλεδ ανδ ηαϝε τηε αππεαρανξε οφ
					δεβρις φρομ α ξονφλαγρατιον. φορ τηε ξολδ φρεεζες
					συβστανξες το α ϝαρψινγ δεγρεε, βυτ ηαρδεστ τηοσε οφ
					ωηιξη ιτ ις νατυραλλψ α πριμαρψ ξονστιτυεντ. τηυς, ιφ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.277"/>
					
					ιτ ις τηε νατυρε οφ ηεατ το λιγητεν, τηε λιγητεστ οβjεξτ
					ωιλλ ηαϝε μοστ ηεατ, ανδ ιφ ιτ ις τηε νατυρε οφ ηυμιδιτψ
					το σοφτεν, τηε σοφτεστ ωιλλ ηαϝε τηε μοστ ηυμιδιτψ ;
					σο, ιφ ιτ ις αλσο τρυε τηατ τηε νατυρε οφ ξολδ ις το ηαρδεν,
					τηεν ιτ μυστ αλσο φολλοω τηατ τηε ηαρδεστ οβjεξτ ωιλλ
					ηαϝε τηε μοστ ξολδ - τηατ ις το σαψ, jυστ ας τηε εαρτη
					ηας. βυτ ωηατ ις ξολδεστ βψ νατυρε ις συρελψ αλσο
					πριμαριλψ ξολδ, σο τηατ τηε εαρτη ις ιν φαξτ ξολδ βοτη
					πριμορδιαλλψ ανδ νατυραλλψ ; ανδ, οφ ξουρσε, τηις ις
					οβϝιους εϝεν το τηε σενσες. μυδ, ιν φαξτ, ις α ξολδερ
					τηινγ τηαν ωατερ ; ανδ μεν εχτινγυιση α φιρε βψ
					δυμπινγ εαρτη υπον ιτ. βλαξκσμιτης, ωηεν τηειρ ιρον
					βεξομες φιερψ ανδ βεγινς το μελτ, σπρινκλε ον ιτ μαρβλε
					ξηιπς ανδ γψπσυμ το ξηεξκ ανδ ξοολ ιτ οφφ βεφορε ιτ
					μελτς τοο μυξη. ιτ ις αλσο τρυε τηατ δυστ ξοολς τηε
					βοδιες οφ ατηλετες ανδ δριες υπ τηειρ σωεατ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="20">
<p>ανδ ωηατ ις τηε μεανινγ οφ ουρ δεμανδ φορ
					α ψεαρλψ ξηανγε οφ ηαβιτατιον ? ιν ωιντερ ωε ρετρεατ
					το τηε λοφτιεστ παρτς οφ ουρ ηουσες, τηοσε φαρτηεστ φρομ
					τηε εαρτη, ωηιλε ιν συμμερ ωε ρεθυιρε τηε λοωερ παρτς,
					συβμεργινγ ουρσελϝες ανδ γοινγ ιν θυεστ οφ ξομφορταβλε ρετρεατς, ας ωε μακε τηε βεστ οφ α λιφε ιν τηε
					εμβραξε οφ μοτηερ εαρτη. σινξε ωε δο τηις, αρε ωε
					νοτ γυιδεδ το τηε εαρτη βψ ουρ περξεπτιον οφ ιτς ξολδνεσς ? δο ωε νοτ αξκνοωλεδγε ιτ ας τηε νατυραλ σεατ
					οφ πριμορδιαλ ξολδ ? ανδ συρελψ ουρ λιϝινγ βψ τηε σεα
					ιν τηε ωιντερ ις, ιν α ωαψ, αν εσξαπε φρομ τηε εαρτη,
					σινξε ωε αβανδον τηε λανδ ας φαρ ας ποσσιβλε βεξαυσε
					οφ τηε φροστ ανδ ωραπ ουρσελϝες ιν σαλτ σεα αιρ βεξαυσε
					ιτ ις ωαρμ. τηεν αγαιν, ιν τηε συμμερ βψ ρεασον οφ
					τηε ηεατ, ωε λονγ φορ τηε εαρτη-βορν, υπλανδ αιρ, νοτ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.279"/>
					
					βεξαυσε ιτ ις ιτσελφ ξηιλλψ, βυτ βεξαυσε ιτ ηας σπρυνγ
					φρομ τηε νατυραλλψ ανδ πριμορδιαλλψ ξολδ ανδ ηας βεεν
					ιμβυεδ ωιτη ιτς εαρτηψ ποωερ, ας στεελ ις τεμπερεδ
					βψ βεινγ πλυνγεδ ιν ωατερ.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 433 a and 946 c <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> ανδ οφ φλοωινγ ωατερς,
					αλσο, τηε ξολδεστ αρε τηοσε τηατ φαλλ φρομ ροξκς ορ
					μουνταινς, ανδ οφ ωελλ ωατερς τηε δεεπεστ αρε τηε
					ξολδεστ; τηε αιρ φρομ ουτσιδε δοες νοτ, ιν τηε ξασε
					οφ τηεσε ωελλς, αφφεξτ τηε ωατερ, σο δεεπ αρε τηεψ,
					ωηιλε ανψ συξη στρεαμς βυρστ φορτη τηρουγη πυρε υνμιχεδ εαρτη, λικε τηε ονε ατ ταεναρυμ,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Plutarch knew that the mouth of Hades was at Taenarum (Pindar, <hi rend="italics">Pythian</hi>, iv. 44) and transferred the Styx to that place. For its water see Frazer on Pausanias, viii. 18. 4. According to Antigonus, <hi rend="italics">Hist. Mirab.</hi> 158 (ed. Keller) no receptacle except one of horn can contain the water; he adds, <q direct="unspecified">All that taste of it die.</q>
</note> ωηιξη τηεψ
					ξαλλ τηε ωατερ οφ στψχ · ιτ φλοως φρομ τηε ροξκ ιν α
					τριξκλε, βυτ σο ξολδ τηατ νο ϝεσσελ εχξεπτ αν ασσʼς ηοοφ
					ξαν ξονταιν ιτ - αλλ οτηερς ιτ βυρστς ανδ βρεακς απαρτ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="21">
<p>ωε αρε, φυρτηερ, ινφορμεδ βψ πηψσιξιανς τηατ
					γενεριξαλλψ εαρτη ις βψ νατυρε αστρινγεντ ανδ ξολδ,
					ανδ τηεψ ενυμερατε μανψ μεταλς τηατ προϝιδε α
					στψπτιξ, σταψινγ εφφεξτ φορ μεδιξιναλ υσε. τηε ελεμεντ
					οφ εαρτη ις νοτ σηαρπ ορ μοβιλε ορ σλενδερ ορ πριεκλψ
					ορ σοφτ ορ δυξτιλε, βυτ σολιδ ανδ ξομπαξτ λικε α ξυβε.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 288 e and Plato, <hi rend="italics">Timaeus</hi>, 55 d-e.</note>
					τηις ις ηοω ιτ ξαμε το ηαϝε ωειγητ; ανδ τηε ξολδ,
					ωηιξη ις ιτς τρυε ποωερ, βψ τηιξκενινγ, ξομπρεσσινγ,
					ανδ σθυεεζινγ ουτ τηε ηυμιδιτψ οφ βοδιες, ινδυξες
					σηιϝερινγ ανδ σηακινγ τηρουγη ιτς ινεθυαλιτψ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 948 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note>; ανδ
					ιφ ιτ βεξομες ξομπλετε μαστερ ανδ εχπελς ορ εχτινγυισηες αλλ τηε ηεατ, ιτ φιχες τηε βοδψ ιν α φροζεν
					ανδ ξορπσελικε ξονδιτιον. τηις ις τηε ρεασον ωηψ
					εαρτη δοες νοτ βυρν ατ αλλ, ορ βυρνς ονλψ γρυδγινγλψ
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.281"/>
					
					ανδ ωιτη διφφιξυλτψ. αιρ, ον τηε οτηερ ηανδ, οφτεν
					σηοοτς φορτη φλαμες φρομ ιτσελφ ανδ, τυρνινγ ιντο φιρε,
					μακες στρεαμς ανδ φλασηες οφ λιγητνινγ. ηεατ φεεδς
					ον μοιστυρε,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 649 b, 687 a, 696 b; Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Metaphysics</hi>, A 3 (983 b 23 ff.); Pseudo-Aristotle, <hi rend="italics">Problemata</hi>, 949 b 29.</note> φορ ιτ ις νοτ τηε σολιδ παρτ οφ ωοοδ,
					βυτ τηε δαμπ παρτ, τηατ ις ξομβυστιβλε ; ανδ ωηεν
					τηις ις διστιλλεδ, τηε σολιδ, δρψ παρτ ρεμαινς βεηινδ,
					ρεδυξεδ το ασηες.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 696 b.</note> τηοσε ωηο εμυλουσλψ στριϝε το
					προϝε τηατ τηις τοο ις ξηανγεδ ανδ ξονσυμεδ, σπρινκλινγ ιτ, περηαπς, ωιτη οιλ ορ κνεαδινγ ιτ ωιτη συετ ανδ
					σεττινγ ιτ αλιγητ, αξξομπλιση νοτηινγ ; φορ ωηεν τηε
					οιλψ παρτ ις ξονσυμεδ, τηε εαρτηψ ρεμαινς ας α περμανεντ ρεσιδυε, δο ωηατ τηεψ μαψ. νοτ ονλψ, τηερεφορε, βεξαυσε τηε εαρτη ις πηψσιξαλλψ ιμμοϝαβλε φρομ
					ιτς στατιον, βυτ αλσο βεξαυσε ιτ ις υναλτεραβλε ιν εσσενξε, ιτ ωας θυιτε αππροπριατελψ ξαλλεδ ηεστια<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <hi rend="italics">Phaedrus</hi>, 247 a and 948 b <hi rend="italics">supra</hi> with the note. For earth as Hestia see also Dio Chrys. xxxvi. 46 (L.C.L.) with Crosby's note; Dion. Hal. ii. 66. 3; Ovid, <hi rend="italics">Fasti</hi>, vi. 267; Koster, <hi rend="italics">Mnemosyne</hi>, Suppl. iii (1951), p. 7, n. 6.</note> βψ
					τηε ανξιεντς - ιν ας μυξη ας σηε <q direct="unspecified">ρεμαινς ιν τηε ηομε
						οφ τηε γοδς</q> - βεξαυσε οφ ιτς στατιοναρψ ανδ ξομπαξτ
					νατυρε ; ανδ ξολδνεσς ις ωηατ βινδς ιτ τογετηερ, ας
					αρξηελαüς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Diels-Kranz, <hi rend="italics">Frag. der Vorsok.</hi>
<hi rend="super">5</hi>, ii, p. 48.</note> τηε νατυραλ πηιλοσοπηερ δεξλαρεδ, σινξε
					νοτηινγ ξαν ρελαχ ορ σοφτεν ιτ, ας α συβστανξε τηατ ις
					συβjεξτ το ηεατινγ ορ ωαρμινγ μιγητ βε λοοσενεδ.
				</p>
<p>
					ας φορ τηοσε ωηο συπποσε τηατ τηεψ φεελ ξολδ αιρ ανδ
					ωατερ, βυτ αρε λεσς σενσιβλε οφ εαρτηʼς ξολδνεσς, ωηατ
					τηεψ περξειϝε ις τηατ πορτιον οφ εαρτη ωηιξη ις ξλοσεστ
					το τηεμ ανδ ηας ξομε το βε α μεδλεψ, α ξονγεριες,
					αβουνδινγ ιν αιρ ανδ ωατερ, συν ανδ ηεατ. τηερε ις
					νο διφφερενξε βετωεεν συξη πεοπλε ανδ τηοσε ωηο
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.283"/>
					
					δεξλαρε τηατ τηε αετηερ<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 951 d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> ις νοτ νατυραλλψ ανδ πριμορδιαλλψ ηοτ, βυτ ρατηερ τηατ σξαλδινγ ωατερ ορ ρεδ
					ηοτ ιρον αρε - βεξαυσε τηεψ ξαν φεελ ανδ τουξη τηεσε,
					βυτ αρε υναβλε το τουξη ανδ φεελ τηε πριμορδιαλλψ
					πυρε ανδ ηεαϝενλψ φιρε. νορ λικεωισε αρε τηεσε
					περσονς αβλε το τουξη ανδ φεελ τηε εαρτη ατ ιτς βοττομμοστ, ωηιξη ις ωηατ ωε παρτιξυλαρλψ μεαν βψ εαρτη - 
					εαρτη σετ οφφ αλονε βψ ιτσελφ, ωιτηουτ αδμιχτυρε οφ ανψ
					οτηερ ελεμεντ. βυτ ωε ξαν σεε α σαμπλε οφ συξη
					εαρτηινεσς ιν τηατ στατεμεντ αβουτ τηε ξλιφφς<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> 954 c-d <hi rend="italics">supra</hi>.</note> τηατ
					δισπλαψ φρομ δεεπ δοων σο ιντενσε α ξολδ τηατ ιτ ξαν
					σξαρξελψ βε ενδυρεδ. τηεν, τοο. τηοσε ωηο ωαντ α
					ξολδερ δρινκ τηροω πεββλες ιντο τηε ωατερ,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">
<hi rend="italics">Cf. Mor.</hi> 690 f - 691 c.</note> ωηιξη
					βεξομες τηιξκερ ανδ δενσερ τηρουγη τηε ξολδνεσς τηατ
					στρεαμς υπωαρδ, φρεση ανδ υνδιλυτεδ, φρομ τηε στονες.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="22">
<p>ωε μυστ, τηερεφορε, βελιεϝε τηατ τηε ρεασον
					ωηψ ανξιεντ λεαρνεδ μεν ηελδ τηατ τηερε ις νο ξομμερξε βετωεεν εαρτηλψ ανδ ξελεστιαλ τηινγς ωας νοτ
					τηατ τηεψ διστινγυισηεδ υπ ανδ δοων βψ ρελατιϝε
					ποσιτιον, ας ωε δο ιν τηε ξασε οφ σξαλες ; βυτ ρατηερ
					ιτ ωας τηε διφφερενξε ιν ποωερς τηατ λεδ τηεμ το ασσιγν
					συξη τηινγς ας αρε ηοτ ανδ βριγητ, σωιφτ ανδ βυοψαντ,
					το τηε ετερναλ ανδ ιμπερισηαβλε παρτ οφ νατυρε, ωηιλε
					δαρκνεσς ανδ ξολδ ανδ σλοωνεσς τηεψ ξονσιδερεδ τηε
					υνηαππψ ηεριταγε οφ τρανσιτορψ ανδ συβμεργεδ βεινγς.
					τηεν τοο, τηε βοδψ οφ α λιϝινγ ξρεατυρε, ας λονγ ας ιτ;
					βρεατηες ανδ φλουρισηες, δοες, ας τηε ποετς σαψ, ενjοψ
					βοτη ωαρμτη ανδ λιφε<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">Perhaps some such passage as Homer, <hi rend="italics">Iliad</hi>, xxii. 363 is meant.</note>; βυτ ωηεν τηεσε φορσακε ιτ
					ανδ ιτ ις αβανδονεδ ιν τηε ρεαλμ οφ εαρτη αλονε,
					ιμμεδιατελψ φριγιδιτψ ανδ ξονγελατιον σειζε υπον ιτ,
					
					<pb id="v.12.p.285"/>
					
					σινξε ωαρμτη νατυραλλψ ρεσιδες ιν ανψτηινγ ελσε ρατηερ
					τηαν ιν τηε εαρτηψ.
				</p>
</div1>
<div1 type="section" n="23">
<p>ξομπαρε τηεσε στατεμεντς, φαϝορινυς, ωιτη τηε
					προνουνξεμεντς οφ οτηερς ; ανδ ιφ τηεσε νοτιονς οφ
					μινε αρε νειτηερ λεσς προβαβλε νορ μυξη μορε πλαυσιβλε τηαν τηοσε οφ οτηερς, σαψ φαρεωελλ το δογμα, βεινγ
					ξονϝινξεδ ας ψου αρε τηατ ιτ ις μορε πηιλοσοπηιξ το
					συσπενδ jυδγεμεντ ωηεν τηε τρυτη ις οβσξυρε τηαν
					το τακε σιδες.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="yes">See the introduction to this essay.</note>
</p>
</div1>
</body>
</text>
</TEI.2>
