<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Can Virtue Be Taught?</title>
            <author>Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="translator">William Clark Helmbold</editor>
         	<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
         	<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
         	<respStmt>
         		<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
         		<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
         		<name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
         		<name>Bridget Almas</name>
         	   <name>Angelia Hanhardt</name>
         	</respStmt>
         	<funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
      	<publicationStmt>
      		<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
      		<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
      		<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      		<date type="release">2010-12-13</date>
      	</publicationStmt>
      	<sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name role="translator">William Clark Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date type="printing">1939</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            	<ref target="https://archive.org/details/moraliainfifteen06plutuoft/page/4">The Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      	<p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture</p>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
         	<cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="section" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
         		<p>This pointer pattern extracts sections</p>
         	</cRefPattern>
            <!--<state unit="section"/>-->
         </refsDecl>
      	<!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>-->
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         	<language ident="deu">German</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
      	<change who="RS" when="2010-05">tagged and parsed</change>
      	<change who="Sophia Elzie" when="2019-07-12">EpiDoc and CTS Conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
      	
<div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg093.perseus-eng3" type="translation" xml:lang="eng"> <head>CAN VIRTUE BE TAUGHT? <foreign xml:lang="lat">(AN VIRTUS DOCERI POSSIT)</foreign></head> <lb/> 
<div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="intro"> <pb xml:id="v.6.p.2"/> <head>INTRODUCTION</head> <p rend="indent"> This slight and possibly fragmentary essay, or declamation, makes no considerable addition to the theory of knowledge. Virtue is assumed to be an <q>art</q>; since the practice of all other arts is unsuccessful without instruction, Virtue (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀρετή</foreign>), or the Good Life (<foreign xml:lang="grc">τὸ εὖ ζῆν</foreign>), or Prudence (<foreign xml:lang="grc">φρόνησις</foreign>) - for Plutarch appears to equate the three - must be learned, if we are to be successful in the dependent arts. Plutarch appeals as usual to common sense, but does not take the trouble to prove any of his assumptions; yet the work, even in its present mutilated state, is a graceful exercise in popular philosophy. </p> 
<p rend="indent">While Plutarch’s slipshod and half-defined position is not directly contrary to that of Plato (<foreign xml:lang="lat">e.g.</foreign> in the <title rend="italic">Meno</title>), it must be observed that two pupils of Socrates, Crito and Simon, wrote works with the titles, <foreign xml:lang="grc">οὐκ ἐκ τοῦ μαθεῖν οἱ ἀγαθοί</foreign> (<title rend="italic">That Men are not made Good by Instruction</title>) and <foreign xml:lang="grc">Περὶ ἀρετῆς ὅτι οὐ διδακτόν</foreign> (<title rend="italic">That Virtue cannot be Taught</title>), respectively.<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Diogenes Laertius, ii. 121, 122.</note> Whether these books differed radically from the Platonic or Socratic position, as developed in the <title rend="italic">Meno</title> and the <title rend="italic">Republic</title>, cannot be argued here. </p> 
<p rend="indent">We must note in passing that G. Siefert (<title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Commentationes Ienenses</title>, 1896, pp. 102-105) held that Plutarch <pb xml:id="v.6.p.3"/> wrote this work in connexion with the <title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">De Fortuna</title> (see the parallels recorded in the notes) and that it is not mutilated, but unfinished.<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <q> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Ne hic quidem liber fragmentum est, sed schedula tantum a Plutarcho in suum usum obiter composita.</foreign> </q> </note> This is quite possible.<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Xylander’s supposition, recently repeated without argument by Hartman, that this is not a work of Plutarch, seems untenable.</note> </p> 
<p rend="indent">The text is very uncertain, for although the essay appears in several important classes of MSS., they differ considerably among themselves. The text which must serve as the basis of the present translation is only presented with the greatest hesitation. </p> 
<p rend="indent">The work appears as No. 180 in the Lamprias catalogue, where it bears the title <foreign xml:lang="grc">Περὶ ἀρετῆς εἰ διδκτέον ἡ ἀρετή</foreign>.<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspeciifed" anchored="true">. Bernardakis would rightly emend to <foreign xml:lang="grc">διδακτὸν</foreign>.</note></p> </div> <pb xml:id="v.6.p.5"/> 
<div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="1"> <p rend="indent">When we discuss Virtue we debate the question whether Prudence, Justice, and the Good Life can be taught; then we are surprised that the achievements of orators, pilots, musicians, architects, and farmers are past counting, whereas <q>good men</q> is only a name and a mere term, like <q>Centaurs,</q> <q>Giants,</q> or <q>Cyclopes</q>! And it is impossible to find any deed that is faultless as regards its virtue, or any character undefiled by passion, or any life untouched by dishonour; but even if Nature does spontaneously produce something that is excellent, this excellence is obscured by much that is foreign to it, like wheat mixed with wild and impure stuff.<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">i.e.</foreign> tares; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 51 a.</note> Men learn to play the harp, to dance and to read, to farm and to ride the horse; they learn to put on shoes and to don garments, they are taught to pour wine and to bake meat. All these things it is impossible to do properly without instruction; but shall that for the attainment of which all these things are done, that is, the Good Life, be unteachable, irrational, requiring no skill, and fortuitous? </p> </div> 
<div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="2"> <p rend="indent">O mortal men! Why do we assert that virtue <pb xml:id="v.6.p.7"/> is unteachable, and thus make it non-existent? For if learning begets virtue, the prevention of learning destroys it. Yet truly, as Plato<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <title rend="italic">Cleitophon</title>, 407 c; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 534 f.</note> says, just because a foot of verse is out of measure with the lyre and fails to harmonize with it, brother does not war with brother, nor does friend quarrel with friend, nor do states conceive hatred toward other states and wreak upon each other the most extreme injuries and suffer them as well; nor can anyone say that civil strife has ever broken out in a state over a question of accent, as, for instance, whether we should read Telchines or Telchines,<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The latter, according to Herodianus Technicus, i. p. 17 (ed. Lentz).</note> nor that a quarrel has ever arisen in a household between husband and wife as to which is the warp and which the woof. Yet, for all that, no one, unless he has received instruction, would attempt to handle a loom or a book or a lyre, though he would suffer no great harm if he did so, but he is merely afraid of becoming ridiculous (for, as Heracleitus<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Diels, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="deu">Frag. d. Vorsokratiker</title> <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>, i. p. 172, Frag. 95; the fragment is given more fully in <title rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 644 f and in a different form in Frag. 1 of <title rend="italic">That Women Also Should be Educated</title> (Bernardakis, vol. vii. p. 125).</note> says, <q>It is better to conceal ignorance</q>); but everyone thinks that without instruction he will handle successfully a home, a marriage, a commonwealth, a magistracy - though he has not learned how to get along with wife, or servant, or fellow-citizen, or subject, or ruler! </p> 
<p rend="indent">Diogenes, when he saw a child eating sweet-meats, gave the boy’s tutor a cuff, rightly judging the fault to be, not that of him who had not learned, but of him who had not taught. Then, when it is impossible <pb xml:id="v.6.p.9"/> to eat and drink politely in company if one has not learned from childhood, as Aristophanes<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Adapted from <title rend="italic">Clouds</title>, 983.</note> says, <quote rend="blockquote"> <l>Not to laugh like a clown, nor dainties gulp down, nor to </l> <l>cross one leg on the other;</l> </quote> yet can men enter without censure the fellowship of a household, a city, a marriage, a way of life, a magistracy, if they have not learned how they should get along with fellow-beings? When Aristippus was asked by someone, <q>So you are everywhere, it seems, aren’t you?</q> <q>Well then,</q> he replied with a laugh, <q>I am wasting my fare,<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Juvenal, viii. 97: <foreign xml:lang="lat">furor est post omnia perdere naulum</foreign>, which indicates the proverbial character of the expression. Aristippus, having the <emph>entree</emph> everywhere, need waste no money in transit.</note> if indeed I am everywhere.</q> Why, then, would you also not say, <q>If men do not become better by teaching, the fee given to their tutors is wasted</q>? For these are the first to receive the child when it has been weaned and, just as nurses mould its body with their hands,<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 3 e; Plato, <title rend="italic">Republic</title>, 377 c.</note> so tutors by the habits they inculcate train the child’s character to take a first step, as it were, on the path of virtue. So the Spartan,<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 452 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra</foreign>.</note> when he was asked what he effected by his teaching, said, <q>I make honourable things pleasant to children.</q> And yet what do tutors teach? To walk in the public streets with lowered head; to touch salt-fish with but one finger, but fresh fish, bread, and meat with two<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The point is obscure and the text corrupt.</note>; to sit in such and such a posture; in such and such a way to wear their cloaks.<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 5 a and 99 d. See Aristophanes, <title rend="italic">Clouds</title>, 973 ff., for the way good boys should sit and walk in public; <title rend="italic">Birds</title>, 1568, for the proper way to wear a cloak.</note> <pb xml:id="v.6.p.11"/> </p> </div> 
<div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="3"> <p rend="indent">What then? He who says that the physician’s art concerns itself with rashes and hang-nails, but not with pleurisy or fever or inflammation of the brain, in what does he differ from one who says that schools and lectures and precepts are for instruction in trifling and childish duties, but that for the great and supreme duties there is only brute knocking about and accident? For just as he is ridiculous who declares that one must be taught before pulling at the oar, but may steer the boat even without having learned; so one who grants that the other arts are acquired by learning, but deprives virtue of this, appears to be acting directly contrary to the practice of the Scythians. For the Scythians, as Herodotus<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Herodotus, iv. 2, which passage is not at all explicit, but appears to mean that the slaves are blinded to prevent their stealing that part of the milk considered most valuable by their masters.</note> says, blind their slaves that these may hand over the cream to themselves; but such a man as this gives Reason, like an eye, as it were, to the subservient and ancillary arts, while denying it to virtue. </p> 
<p rend="indent">Yet when Callias, son of Charias, asked the general Iphicrates,<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 99 e, 187 b.</note> <q>Who are you? Bowman, targeteer, horseman, or hoplite?</q> Iphicrates replied, <q>None of these, but the one who commands them all.</q> Ridiculous, therefore, is the man who declares that the art of using the bow, or of fighting in heavy armour, or of manipulating the sling, or of riding a horse may be taught, but that the art of commanding and leading an army comes as it chances and to whom it chances without previous instruction! Surely he is yet more ridiculous who affirms that prudence alone cannot be taught, for without prudence <pb xml:id="v.6.p.13"/> there can be no gain or profit from the other arts. But if prudence is in command, the principle which orders all the arts, which assigns each person to a place of usefulness,<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">There is, perhaps, a lacuna at this point, as indicated by Pohlenz, who supplies <q>how, then, must one not pay even more heed to prudence than to the other arts?</q> </note> what joy, for instance, can one have at a banquet, though the servants are welltrained and have learned to <quote rend="blockquote">Carve the meat and roast it well and pour the wine,<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Homer, <title rend="italic">Od.</title> xv., 323.</note> </quote> if there be no system nor order in the servitors?<note xml:lang="eng" resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Possibly a large part of the essay is missing.</note> </p> </div> </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>