<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Hemorrhoids</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 20, 2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							<date>1886</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Aph.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Epid.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>

			<div type="section" n="1">
				<head>Part 1</head>
				<p> The disease of the hemorrhoids is formed in this way: if bile or phlegm be
					determined to the veins in the rectum, it heats the blood in the veins; and
					these veins becoming heated attract blood from the nearest veins, and being
					gorged the inside of the gut swells outwardly, and the heads of the veins are
					raised up, and being at the same time bruised by the faeces passing out, and
					injured by the blood collected in them, they squirt out blood, most frequently
					along with the faeces, but sometimes without faeces. It is to be cured thus:
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="2">
				<head>Part 2</head>
				<p> In the first place it should be known in what sort of a place they are formed.
					For cutting, excising, sewing, binding, applying putrefacient means to the
					anus,-all these appear to be very formidable things, and yet, after all, they
					are not attended with mischief. I recommend seven or eight small pieces of iron
					to be prepared, a fathom in size, in thickness like a thick specillum, and bent
					at the extremity, and a broad piece should be on the extremity, like a small
						obolus<note>I would direct the attention of my surgical readers to the form
						of the ancient cautery <hi rend="ital">or</hi>burning iron; it resembles a
						small coin, that is to say, it was a disk. I have often thought that modern
						practitioners in surgery erred in making their cauteries globular, instead
						of making them flat disks like the ancient.</note>. Having on the preceding
					day first purged the man with medicine, on the day of the operation apply the
					cautery. Having laid him on his back, and placed a pillow below the breech,
					force out the anus as much as possible with the fingers, and make the irons
					red-hot, and burn the pile until it be dried up, and so as that no part may be
					left behind. And burn so as to leave none of the hemorrhoids unburnt, for <pb
						n="p.352"/>you should burn them all up. You will recognize the hemorrhoids
					without difficulty, for they project on the inside of the gut like dark-colored
					grapes, and when the anus is forced out they spurt blood. When the cautery is
					applied the patient's head and hands should be held so that he may not stir, but
					he himself should cry out, for this will make the rectum project the more. When
					you have performed the burning, boil lentils and tares, finely triturated in
					water, and apply as a cataplasm for five or six days. But on the seventh, cut a
					soft sponge into a very slender slice, its width should be about six inches
					square. Then a thin smooth piece of cloth, of the same size as the sponge, is to
					be smeared with honey and applied; and with the index finger of the left hand
					the middle of the sponge is to be pushed as far up as possible; and afterward
					wool is to be placed upon the sponge so that it may remain in the anus. And
					having girded the patient about the loins and fastened a shawl to the girdle,
					bring up this band from behind between the legs and attach it to the girdle at
					the navel. Then let the medicine which I formerly said is calculated to render
					the skin thick and strong, be bound on. These things should be kept on for not
					less than twenty days. The patient should once a day take a draught from flour
					or millet, or bran, and drink water. When the patient goes to stool the part
					should be washed with hot water. Every third day he should take the bath. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="3">
				<head>Part 3</head>
				<p> Another method of cure:-Having got the anus to protrude as much as possible,
					foment with hot water, and then cut off the extremities of the hemorrhoids. But
					this medicine should be prepared beforehand, as an application to the
					wound:-Having put urine into a bronze vessel, sprinkle upon the urine the flower
					of bronze calcined and finely triturated; then, when it is moistened, shake the
					vessel and dry in the sun. When it becomes dry, let it be scraped down and
					levigated, and apply with the finger to the part, and having oiled compresses,
					apply them, and bind a sponge above. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="4">
				<head>Part 4</head>
				<p> Another method:-There grows upon the bleeding condyloma, a protuberance like the
					fruit of the mulberry, and if the condyloma be far without, an envelope of flesh
					is adherent to it. <pb n="p.353"/>Having placed the man over two round stones
					upon his knees, examine, for you will find the parts near the anus between the
					buttocks inflated, and blood proceeding from within. If, then, the condyloma
					below the cover be of a soft nature, bring it away with the finger, for there is
					no more difficulty in this than in skinning a sheep, to pass the finger between
					the hide and the flesh. And this should be accomplished without the patient's
					knowledge, while he is kept in conversation. When the condyloma is taken off,
					streaks of blood necessarily flow from the whole of the torn part. It must be
					speedily washed with a decoction of galls, in a dry wine, and the bleeding vein
					will disappear along with the condyloma, and its cover will be replaced. The
					older it is, the more easy the cure. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="5">
				<head>Part 5</head>
				<p> But if the condyloma be higher up, you must examine it with the speculum, and
					you should take care not to be deceived by the speculum; for when expanded, it
					renders the condyloma level with the surrounding parts, but when contracted, it
					shows the tumor right again. It is to be removed by smearing it with black
					hellebore on the finger. Then, on the third day, wash it out with a dry wine.
					You need not be surprised that there is no discharge of blood when you remove
					the condyloma, for neither, if you cut off the hands or legs at the
					articulations will there be any flow of blood; but if you cut them off above or
					below the joints, you will find there hollow veins which pour out blood, and you
					will have difficulty in stopping the bleeding. In the same manner, the bleeding
					vein in the anus, if you cut it above or below the point of separation of the
					condyloma, will pour forth blood; but if you take away the condyloma at its
					junction (<hi rend="ital">with the natural parts?</hi>) there will be no flow of
					blood. If matters then be thus put to rights, it will be well; but otherwise
					burn it, taking care not to touch the place with the iron, but bringing it close
					so as to dry it up, and apply the flos aeris in the urine. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="6">
				<head>Part 6</head>
				<p> Another method of curing hemorrhoids:-You must prepare a cautery like the <hi
						rend="ital">arundo phragmites</hi>, and an iron that exactly fits is to be
					adapted to it; then the tube being introduced into the anus, the iron, red hot,
					is to be passed down it, and frequently drawn out, so that the part may bear the
					more heat, and no sore <pb n="p.354"/>may result from the heating, and the dried
					veins may heal up. But if you are neither disposed to burn nor excise, having
					first fomented with plenty hot water and turned out the anus, levigate myrrh,
					and having burnt galls and Egyptian alum, in the proportion of one and a half to
					the other things, and as much of melanteria; these things are all to be used in
					a dry state. The hemorrhoid will separate under the use of these medicines, like
					a piece of burnt hide. You are to proceed thus until the whole are removed, and
					a half part of burnt chalcitis does the same thing. But if you wish to effect
					the cure by suppositories, take the shell of the part fish a third part of
					plumbago, bitumen, alum, a little of the flos aeris, galls, a little verdigris;
					having poured a small quantity of boiled honey on these, and formed an oblong
					suppository, apply until you remove them. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="7">
				<head>Part 7</head>
				<p> An hemorrhoid in a woman may be thus cured. Having fomented with plenty of hot
					water, boil in the water certain of the fragrant medicines, add pounded
					tamarisk, roasted litharge and galls, and pour on them white wine, and oil, and
					the grease of a goose, pounding all together. Give to use after fomenting. In
					fomenting the anus is to be made to protrude as much as possible.<pb n="p.355"
					/></p>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
