<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Italy </title>
				<author n="Appian">Appian</author>
				<editor role="editor">Horace White</editor>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
			</titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
			
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Appian</author>
						<title>The Foreign Wars</title>
						<editor role="editor">Horace White</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>THE MACMILLAN COMPANY</publisher>
							<date>1899</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="medium" method="silent">&Perseus.OCR;</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				refState unit="text"/>
				refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
				refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<!--<refsDecl>
				refState unit="text"/>
				refState unit="section"/>
				</refsDecl>-->
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
				<language ident="la">Latin</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		
		
		<revisionDesc><!--
			<change><date>13-Nov-02</date><respStmt><name>DMM</name><resp>markup</resp></respStmt>
				<item>
					$Log: appian.fw_eng.xml,v $
					Revision 1.1  2009-10-07 21:00:33  rsingh04
					began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

					Revision 1.7  2009/08/19 15:57:58  lcerrato
					fixing Athenaeus refs

					Revision 1.6  2009/07/06 17:34:09  student
					edited entity tags CEH

					Revision 1.5  2009/02/27 22:29:25  rsingh04
					fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

					Revision 1.4  2009/01/29 17:19:10  rsingh04
					fixed chunking scheme
					
					Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 21:10:51  packel
					places/dates now actually tagged
					
					Revision 1.2  2004/08/10 13:09:32  amahoney
					fix the XML files so they are valid, make the SGML obsolete so no one is confused
					
				</item></change><change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>--><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc></teiHeader><text xml:lang="en">
				<body>
					
					<head>CONCERNING ITALY</head>
					<div type="chapter">
						<head>Fragments</head>
						<cit n="I">
							<bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							<quote><p>The Volsci, in nowise terrified by the misfortunes of their  neighbors, made war against the Romans and laid siege to their colonies.</p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="II">
							<bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 263</note>The people refused to elect Marcius (Coriolanus) when <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-491">491</date></note> he sought the consulship, not because they considered him unfit, but because they feared his domineering spirit.</p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="III">
							<bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 265</note>Marcius being inflamed against the Romans when they <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-489">489</date></note> banished him went over to the Volsci, meditating no small revenge.</p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="IV">
							<bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 266</note>When he arrived there, having renounced his own country <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-488">488</date></note> and kin, he did not meditate anything in particular, but intended to side with the Volsci against his country.<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Mendelssohn considers this whole fragment corrupt.</note></p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="V">
							<bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							<quote><milestone unit="section" n="1"/><p>When Marcius had been banished, and had taken refuge with the Volsci, and made war against the Romans, and was encamped at a distance of only four hundred stades from the city, the people threatened to betray the walls to  the enemy unless the Senate would send an embassy to  him to treat for peace. The Senate reluctantly sent plenipotentiaries for this purpose. When they arrived at the camp of the Volsci and were brought into his presence and that of the Volscian chiefs, they offered oblivion and permission to return to the city if he would discontinue the war, and they reminded him that the Senate had never done him any wrong. He, while accusing the people of the many wrongs they had done to him and to the Volsci, promised nevertheless that the latter would come to terms with them if they would surrender the land and towns they had taken from the Volsci and admit them to citizenship on the same terms as the Latins. But if the vanquished were to keep what belonged to the victors, he did not see how peace could be made. Having named these conditions, he dismissed the ambassadors and gave them thirty days to consider. Then he turned against the remaining Latin towns, and having captured seven of them in the thirty days, he came back to receive the answer of the Romans.
							</p><milestone unit="section" n="2"/><p>They replied that if he would withdraw his army from the Roman territory they would send an embassy to him to conclude peace on fair terms. When he refused this, they sent ten others to beg him that nothing should be done unworthy of his native country, and to allow a treaty to be made, not by his command, but of their own free will, for he should regard the honor of his country and the principles of his ancestors, who had never done him any wrong. He replied merely that he would give them three days more in order that they might think better of it. Then the Romans sent their priests to him wearing their sacred vestments to add their entreaties. To these he said that either they must obey his commands or they need not come to him again. Then the Romans prepared for a siege and brought stones and missiles upon the walls to fight off Marcius from above.
							</p><milestone unit="section" n="3"/><p>Now Valeria, the daughter of Publicola, brought a company of women to Veturia, the mother of Marcius, and to Volumnia his wife. All these, clad in mourning garments and bringing their children to join in the supplication, implored that they would go out with them to meet Marcius, and beseech him to spare them and their country. The Senate allowed these women to go alone to the camp of  the enemy. Marcius admiring the high courage of the city,  where even the women were inspired by it, advanced to meet them, sending away the rods and axes of the lictors, out of respect for his mother. He ran forward and embraced her, brought her into the council of the Volsci, and told her to tell what she wanted.
							</p><milestone unit="section" n="4"/><p>She said that, being his mother, she was as much wronged as he in his banishment from the city; that she saw that the Romans had already suffered grievously at his hands, and had paid a sufficient penalty, so much of their territory had been laid waste and so many of their towns demolished, and themselves reduced to the extremity of sending their consuls and priests, and finally his own mother and wife, as ambassadors to him, and offering to rescind the decree and to grant him forgetfulness of the past and a safe return to his home. "Do not," she said, "cure an evil by an incurable evil. Do not be the cause of calamities that will smite yourself as well as those you injure. Whither do you carry the torch? From the fields to the city? From the city to your own hearthstone? From your own hearthstone to the temples of the gods? Have mercy, my son, on me and on your country as we plead." After she had thus spoken Marcius replied that the country which had cast him out was not his, but rather the land which had given him shelter. Nothing was dear to him that was unjust, nor was anybody his enemy who treated him well. He told her to cast her eyes upon the men here present with whom he had exchanged the pledge of mutual fidelity, who had granted him citizenship, had chosen him their general, and had intrusted to him their private interests. lie mentioned the honors bestowed upon him and the oath he had sworn, and he urged his mother to consider his friends and enemies hers also.
							</p><milestone unit="section" n="5"/><p>While he was still speaking, she, in a burst of anger, and holding her hands up to heaven, invoked their household gods. "Two processions of women," said she, "have set forth </title></note></p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="V.b">
							<bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							<quote><p>Marcius did not think proper to gainsay either of these [demands].</p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="VI">
							<bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 275</note>(The Fabii) were as much to be pitied for their misfortunes <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-479">479</date></note> as they were worthy of praise for their bravery. For it was a great misfortune to the Romans, on account of their number, the dignity of a noble house, and its total destruction. The day on which it happened was ever after considered unlucky.<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">The tale of the Fabian family and their voluntary assumption of the war against the Veientians, and their total destruction in an ambuscade is related in Livy, ii. 48-50.</note></p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="VII">
							<bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 283</note>The army was incensed against the general (Appius Claudius) <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-471">471</date></note> from remembrance of old wrongs, and refused to obey him. They fought badly on purpose, and took to flight, putting bandages on their bodies as though they were wounded. They broke up camp and tried to retreat, putting the blame on the unskilfulness of their commander.</p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="VIII">
							<bibl>FROM PEIRESC</bibl>
							<quote><p><milestone unit="section" n="1"/>Bad omens from Jupiter were observed after the capture  of Veii. The soothsayers said that some religious duty had <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 359</note> been neglected, and Camillus remembered that it had been <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-395">395</date></note> forgotten to appropriate a tenth of the plunder to the god that had given the oracle concerning the lake. Accordingly the Senate decreed that those who had taken anything from Veii should make an estimate, each one for himself, and bring in a tenth of it under oath. Their religious feeling was such that they did not hesitate to add to the votive offering a tenth of the produce of the land that had already been sold, as well as of the spoils. With the money thus obtained they sent to the temple of Delphi a golden cup which stood on a pedestal of brass in the treasury of Rome and Massiliat<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Marseilles.</note> until Onomarchus melted the cup during the Phocæan war. The pedestal is still standing.<note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 363</note>
							</p><milestone unit="section" n="2"/><p>Camillus was afterwards accused before the people of <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-391">391</date></note> being himself the author of those bad omens and portents. The people, who had been for some time set against him, fined him heavily, having no pity for him although he had recently lost a son. His friends contributed the money in order that the person of Camillus might not be disgraced. In deep grief he went into exile in the city of Ardea, praying the prayer of Achilles that the time might come when the Romans would long for Camillus. And in fact this came <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 365</note> to pass very soon, for when the Gauls captured the city, the <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-389">389</date></note> people fled for succor to Camillus and again chose him Dictator, as has been told in my Gallic history.<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Livy, v. 32 <foreign>seq.</foreign> Plutarch, <title>Life of Camillus.</title></note></p></quote>
						</cit>
						<cit n="IX">
							<bibl>FROM PEIRESC</bibl>
							<quote><p>When Marcus Manlius, the patrician, saved the city of Rome from a Gallic invasion, he received the highest honors. <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 370</note> At a later period when he saw an old man, who had often <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. date when="-384">384</date></note> fought for his country, reduced to servitude by a money lender, he paid the debt for him. Being highly commended for this act, he released all his own debtors from their obligations. His glory being much increased thereby, he paid the debts of many others. Being much elated by his popularity, he even proposed that all debts should be cancelled, or that the people should sell the lands that had not yet been distributed and apply the proceeds for the relief of debtors.</p></quote>
						</cit>
					
				</body>
			</text>
			
			</TEI>