<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>On the Scrutiny of Evandros</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="Intro" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="Proof" unit="part"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/><gap reason="lost"/>nor expecting that now, after this lapse of time, they will be strict
        in their scrutiny, since you are conscious of having committed many grievous offences
        against them; but these, you believe, some of them have forgotten, and will not even recall
        them to mind. Well, for my part I am quite indignant that he should come before you in the
        confidence of this hope, as though the persons whom he had wronged were different and
        distinct from those who are to give their verdict on these matters, and as though it were
        not the same people that have been his victims and are also to be his hearers. It is
        yourselves who are responsible for this: <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>for you do not
        bear in mind that these men, when the city was subject to the Lacedaemonians, did not
        vouchsafe you a share even in the common slavery, but actually expelled you from the city;
        while you, after setting her free, made them partakers, not only in that freedom, but also
        in the judicature and in the public business of the Assembly. They have some reason, then,
        for thus convicting you of fatuity. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>This man is one of
        them, and he is not content to be allowed to share these rights, but claims as well, before
        paying the penalty for those actions, to hold office once more.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"
        />I am informed that today he will make but a brief reply to the charges brought against
        him, skimming over the facts and shuffling off the accusation with his defence; and he will
        tell how he and his family have spent a great amount on the State, have performed public
        services with ardent zeal, and have won many brilliant victories<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">In dramatic or athletic contests.</note> under the democracy; that he himself
        is an orderly person, and is not seen acting as others of our people venture to act, but
        prefers to mind his own business. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>But I find no difficulty
        in countering those statements. As regards the public services, I say that his father would
        have done better not to perform them than to spend so much of his substance: for it was on
        account of this that he won the confidence of the people and overthrew the democracy; and so
        our memory of these deeds must be more abiding than of the offerings he has set up<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In the temples at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, etc.</note> in
        record of those services. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>As to his love of quiet, I say
        that we ought not to investigate his sobriety today, when there is no chance for him to be
        licentious: we should rather examine that period in which, being free to choose either way
        of life, he preferred to mark his citizenship by illegal acts. For the fact of his
        committing no offences now is due to those who have prevented him; but what he did then was
        owing to the man’s character and to those who vouchsafed him a free hand. So that if he
        claims to pass the scrutiny on this score, you should form this conception of the case, if
        you would not seem fatuous in his sight. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>And if they have recourse to the further argument that time does not allow of
        your electing another man, and that his failure to pass your scrutiny must inevitably leave
        the ancestral sacrifices unperformed, you should reflect that the time has already long gone
        by. For tomorrow is the last remaining day of the year, and on that day a sacrifice is
        offered to Zeus the Saviour, when it is impossible to complete a panel of jurymen in
        defiance of the laws.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Apparently the law forbade any court
          to sit on that day.</note>
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>If all these difficulties are the contrivance of this man,
        what are we to expect, when once he has passed the scrutiny, of the man who will have
        persuaded the outgoing magistrates to commit an illegality in his interest? Will he contrive
        just a few things of this sort in the course of a year? For my part, I think not. <milestone
          n="8" unit="section"/>But you have to consider, not this question alone, but whether piety
        is better served by the sacrifices on behalf of the future magistrate being offered by the
        king-archon and his fellow-magistrates,—as has in fact been done in the past,—or by this
        man, whom those who know about him have testified to be not even without stained hands<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Probably referring to murders committed in compliance with the
          violent measures of the Thirty.</note>; and whether you have sworn to install a magistrate
        who has not passed the scrutiny or, after holding the scrutiny, to crown the man who is
        worthy of the office? <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>That is what you have to consider.
        Reflect also on the fact that the author of the law concerning scrutinies had chiefly in
        view the magistrates of the oligarchy; for he thought it monstrous that the men responsible
        for the overthrow of the democracy should regain office under that very constitution, and
        get control over the laws and over the city of which they had formerly taken charge only to
        maim her with such shameful and terrible injuries. Hence it is not right to be careless of
        the scrutiny, or to make it of so slight account as to ignore it: no, you should keep guard
        over it; for on the just title of each magistrate depends the safety of the government and
        of your whole people. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>Suppose that he were now under
        scrutiny for admission to the Council, and he had his name registered on the tablets as
        having served in the cavalry under the Thirty: even without an accuser you would reject him.
        And now, when he is found, not merely to have served in the cavalry and on the Council, but
        to have also committed offences against the people, will it not be strange behavior on your
        part not to show that you have the same feelings towards him? <milestone n="11"
          unit="section"/>Besides, had he qualified for the Council, he would have held his seat as
        one in a body of five hundred, for a year only; so that, if in that period he had wished to
        commit an offence, he would have been easily prevented by the others. But, if he is approved
        for this office, he will hold it all by himself, and as a member of the Council of the
        Areopagus he will obtain control over the most important matters for an unlimited time.<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The gravest criminal charges, and cases of sacrilege, were
          brought before the ancient court of the Areopagus.</note>
        <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>It therefore behoves you to be stricter in your scrutiny
        for this office than for any other one. Else, what do you suppose will be the attitude of
        the great body of the citizens, when they become aware that the man who ought to have been
        punished for his offences has been approved by you for this high post; when they find a man
        judging murder cases who should have been tried himself by the Council of the Areopagus; and
        when, moreover, they see him crowned and established in control of heiresses and orphans,
        whose bereavement, in some cases, he has himself brought about? <milestone n="13"
          unit="section"/>Do you not think they will show a resentful temper, and will hold you
        responsible for it all, when they put themselves back in those former times, in which many
        of them were hauled to prison and destroyed without trial by these men, or compelled to flee
        their own country; and when they further reflect that this same person, who has brought
        about the rejection of Leodamas, has caused this man to qualify, by acting as accuser of the
        former and undertaking the defence of the latter? And what is the attitude of Evandros
        towards the city? How many troubles has he brought upon her? <milestone n="14"
          unit="section"/>Again, if you heed his words, what ill odor must you expect to incur! For,
        in the former case, they supposed it was anger that caused you to reject Leodamas; but if
        you approve this man, they will be convinced that you have given an unjust sentence on the
        other. These men are on their trial before you; but you are on yours before the whole city,
        which is watching even now to see what view you will take of her. <milestone n="15"
          unit="section"/>Let none of you imagine that I am accusing Evandros to oblige Leodamas,
        because he is a friend of mine: no, it is only from my solicitude for you and for the city.
        This you may easily apprehend from the actual circumstances. For it is to Leodamas’s
        interest that this man should be approved, since that would most surely discredit you, and
        give you the repute of placing oligarchs instead of democrats in the magistracy; but it is
        to your interest to reject this man, for you will get the credit of having acted justly also
        in rejecting the other. But if you do not reject this man, you will appear to have been
        unjust in the other case also. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>And yet, I am told, he will assert that this scrutiny affects, not merely
        him, but all those who remained in the city, and he will remind you of your oaths and
          covenants<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e., not to cherish enmity against the party
          of the town.</note> in the hope that he will thus contrive to enlist the men who remained
        in the city to aid him in this scrutiny. But I desire, on behalf of the people, to give him
        this brief reply: the people do not take the same view of all those who remained in the
        city, but regard those who commit offences like his with the feelings that I say they
          ought,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e., with severity.</note> while towards the rest
        they feel the opposite. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>The proof of this is that the
        latter have received no less honor from the city than those who marched on Phyle and got
        possession of the Peiraeus. And with good reason: for the character of these last is known
        to them only as shown under democracy, and they have not yet made trial of what it would be
        under oligarchy; whereas they have had sufficient test of those others under each kind of
        government to give grounds for confidence.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The more
          liberal-minded of the party of the town have been tried by the test of oligarchy as well
          as that of democracy, and deserve the full benefit of the reconciliation.</note>
        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>They consider that the arrests and executions were due to
        the defendant and his like, whereas the escapes were owing to the other citizens: in fact,
        if all had been of the same mind as they, neither exile nor restoration nor any other of the
        events that have occurred would have befallen the city. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>As
        to the further point which some find unaccountable,—how it was that their large numbers were
        worsted by the little band of the Peiraeus,—this can only be attributed to the prudent
        policy of those citizens; for they chose to concert a government with the restored exiles
        rather than an enslavement to the Lacedaemonians with the Thirty. <milestone n="20"
          unit="section"/>It is therefore they, not these persons, whom the people have
        distinguished with the highest honors, appointing them to cavalry commands, generalships and
        embassies in their service; and they have never repented of it. Those who had committed
        numerous offences caused them to decree the institution of scrutinies; those who had done
        nothing of the sort, to make their covenants. So much for my reply to you on behalf of the
        people. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It is your
        business, gentlemen of the Council, to inquire whether you will reach a better decision in
        the matter of this scrutiny by listening to me or to Thrasybulus, who will defend this man.
        Well, concerning myself or my father or my ancestors he will have nothing to allege that
        points to hatred of the people. For he cannot say that I took part in the oligarchy, as I
        underwent the scrutiny for manhood<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In his eighteenth
          year.</note> at a later date than that; or that my father did either, since he died while
        holding command in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, long before those
        seditions; <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>or that my ancestors were subject to the
        despots, for they continually persisted in raising rebellion against them. Nor yet will he
        assert that we acquired our fortune in the war, and have spent nothing on the city: quite
        the contrary, our estate during the peace amounted to eighty talents, and the whole of it
        was spent in the war on the deliverance of the city. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>But
        on my part I shall be able to tell of this person<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
          >Thrasybulus.</note> three things so grave in their enormity that each deed is worthy of
        death. First, for payment received, he raised a revolution in <placeName key="tgn,7002683"
          >Boeotia</placeName>, and deprived us of that alliance; second, he surrendered our
          ships<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In a fight at the <placeName key="tgn,7002638"
            >Hellespont</placeName>, <date value="-387">387</date> B.C. Cf. <bibl
            n="Xen. Hell. 5.1.27">Xen. Hell. 5.1.27</bibl>.</note> and confronted the city with the
        problem of its safety; <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>and last, from the prisoners of
        war, whose loss he himself had caused, he extracted a bribe of thirty minae, by declaring
        that he would not obtain their release unless they supplied him with this sum from their own
        pockets. So now you are acquainted with the life of each of us: decide accordingly which of
        us two you ought to believe regarding the scrutiny of Evandros, and by so doing you will
        avoid mistake.</p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
