<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>The Book of Prognostics</title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 20, 2003</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							              <date>1886</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="">English</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="lat"
              type="edition"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg003.perseus-eng1">
			         <pb n="p.43"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 1 </head>
				           <p> It appears to me a most excellent thing for the physician to cultivate
					Prognosis; for by foreseeing and foretelling, in the presence of the sick, the
					present, the past, and the future, and explaining the omissions which patients
					have been guilty of,<note>Galen, in his Commentary on this clause of the
						sentence, acutely remarks that patients are justly disposed to form a high
						opinion of a physician who points out to them symptoms of their complaint
						which they themselves had omitted to mention to him. And Staphanus further
						remarks that the patient naturally estimates highly the acumen of the
						physician who detects any errors in regimen which he has been guilty of,
						such as drinking water, or eating fruit when forbidden; (Ed. Dietz, p. 54;)
						or when he has some disease about him, such as bubo or inflammation, which
						he wishes to conceal. (Ibid., p. 63.)</note> he will be the more readily
					believed to be acquainted with the circumstances of the sick; so that men will
					have confidence to intrust themselves to such a physician. And he will manage
					the cure best who has foreseen what is to happen from the present state of
					matters. For it is impossible to make all the sick well; this, indeed, would
					have been better than to be able to foretell what is going to happen; but since
					men die, some even before calling the physician, from the violence of the
					disease, and some die immediately after calling him, having lived, perhaps, only
					one day or a little longer, and before the physician could bring his art to
					counteract the disease; it therefore becomes necessary to know the nature of
					such affections, how far they are above the powers of the constitution; and,
					moreover, if there be anything divine in the diseases, and to learn a
					foreknowledge of this also. Thus a man will be the more esteemed to be a good
					physician, for he will be the better able to treat those aright who can be
					saved, having long <pb n="p.44"/>anticipated everything; and by seeing and
					announcing beforehand those who will live and those who will die, he will thus
					escape censure.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 2 </head>
				           <p> He should observe thus in acute diseases: first, the countenance of the patient,
					if it be like those of persons in health, and more so, if like itself, for this
					is the best of all; whereas the most opposite to it is the worst, such as the
					following; a sharp nose, hollow eyes, collapsed temples; the ears cold,
					contracted, and their lobes turned out: the skin about the forehead being rough,
					distended, and parched; the color of the whole face being green, black, livid,
					or lead-colored. If the countenance be such at the commencement of the disease,
					and if this cannot be accounted for from the other symptoms, inquiry must be
					made whether the patient has long wanted sleep; whether his bowels have been
					very loose; and whether he has suffered from want of food; and if any of these
					causes be confessed to, the danger is to be reckoned so far less; and it becomes
					obvious, in the course of a day and a night, whether or not the appearance of
					the countenance proceeded from these causes. But if none of these be said to
					exist, if the symptoms do not subside in the aforesaid time, it is to be known
					for certain that death is at hand. And, also, if the disease be in a more
					advanced stage either on the third or fourth day, and the countenance be such,
					the same inquiries as formerly directed are to be made, and the other symptoms
					are to be noted, those in the whole countenance, those on the body, and those in
					the eyes; for if they shun the light, or weep involuntarily, or squint, or if
					the one be less than the other, or if the white of them be red, livid, or has
					black veins in it; if there be a gum upon the eyes, if they are restless,
					protruding, or are become very hollow; and if the countenance be squalid and
					dark, or the color of the whole face be changed- all these are to be reckoned
					bad and fatal symptoms. The physician should also observe the appearance of the
					eyes from below the eyelids in sleep; for when a portion of the white appears,
					owing to the eyelids not being closed together, and when this is not connected
					with diarrhea or purgation from medicine, or when the patient does not sleep<pb n="p.45"/> thus from habit, it is to be reckoned an unfavorable and very
					deadly symptom; but if the eyelid be contracted, livid, or pale, or also the
					lip, or nose, along with some of the other symptoms, one may know for certain
					that death is close at hand. It is a mortal symptom, also, when the lips are
					relaxed, pendent, cold, and blanched.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 3 </head>
				           <p> It is well when the patient is found by his physician reclining upon either his
					right or his left side, having his hands, neck, and legs slightly bent, and the
					whole body lying in a relaxed state, for thus the most of persons in health
					recline, and these are the best of postures which most resemble those of healthy
					persons. But to lie upon one's back, with the hands, neck, and the legs
					extended, is far less favorable. And if the patient incline forward, and sink
					down to the foot of the bed, it is a still more dangerous symptom; but if he be
					found with his feet naked and not sufficiently warm, and the hands, neck, and
					legs tossed about in a disorderly manner and naked, it is bad, for it indicates
					aberration of intellect. It is a deadly symptom, also, when the patient sleeps
					constantly with his mouth open, having his legs strongly bent and plaited
					together, while he lies upon his back; and to lie upon one's belly, when not
					habitual to the patient to sleep thus while in good health, indicates delirium,
					or pain in the abdominal regions. And for the patient to wish to sit erect at
					the acme of a disease is a bad symptom in all acute diseases, but particularly
					so in pneumonia. To grind the teeth in fevers, when such has not been the custom
					of the patient from childhood, indicates madness and death, both which dangers
					are to be announced beforehand as likely to happen; and if a person in delirium
					do this it is a very deadly symptom. And if the patient had an ulcer previously,
					or if one has occurred in the course of the disease, it is to be observed; for
					if the man be about to die the sore will become livid and dry, or yellow and dry
					before death.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 4 </head>
				           <p> Respecting the movement of the hands I have these observations to make: When in
					acute fevers, pneumonia, phrenitis, or headache, the hands are waved before the
					face, hunting <pb n="p.46"/> through empty space, as if gathering bits of straw,
					picking the nap from the coverlet, or tearing chaff from the wall- all such
					symptoms are bad and deadly.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 5 </head>
				           <p> Respiration, when frequent, indicates pain or inflanunation in the parts above
					the diaphragm: a large respiration performed at a great interval announces
					delirium; but a cold respiration at nose or mouth is a very fatal symptom. Free
					respiration is to be looked upon as contributing much to the safety of the
					patient in all acute diseases, such as fevers, and those complaints which come
					to a crisis in forty days.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 6 </head>
				           <p> Those sweats are the best in all acute diseases which occur on the critical
					days, and completely carry off the fever. Those are favorable, too, which taking
					place over the whole body, show that the man is bearing the disease better. But
					those that do not produce this effect are not beneficial. The worst are cold
					sweats, confined to the head, face, and neck; these in an acute fever
					prognosticate death, or in a milder one, a prolongation of the disease; and
					sweats which occur over the whole body, with the characters of those confined to
					the neck, are in like manner bad. Sweats attended with a miliary eruption, and
					taking place about the neck, are bad; sweats in the form of drops and of vapour
					are good. One ought to know the entire character of sweats, for some are
					connected with prostration of strength in the body, and some with intensity of
					the inflammation.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 7 </head>
				           <p> That state of the hypochondrium is best when it is free from pain, soft, and of
					equal size on the right side and the left. But if inflamed, or painful, or
					distended; or when the right and left sides are of disproportionate sizes;- all
					these appearances are to be dreaded. And if there be also pulsation in the
					hypochondrium, it indicates perturbation or delirium; and the physician should
					examine the eyes of such persons; for if their pupils be in rapid motion, such
					persons may be expected to go mad. A swelling in the hypochondrium, that is hard
					and painful, is very bad, provided it occupy the whole hypochondrium; but if it
					be on either side, it is less dangerous when on the left. Such swellings at the
					commencement of the disease prognosticate speedy death; but if the fever has
					passed twenty days, and the <pb n="p.47"/>swelling has not subsided, it turns to
					a suppuration.<note>The author evidently alluded to hepatitis ending in abscess.
						This would seem to have been a very common termination of inflammation of
						the liver in Greece, as it is often described in the ancient medical works.
						Se PAULUS AEGINETA, B. III., 46, and the authorities quoted there in the
						Sydenham Society's edition.</note> A discharge of blood from the nose occurs
					to such in the first period, and proves very useful; but inquiry should be made
					if they have headache or indistinct vision; for if there be such, the disease
					will be determined thither. The discharge of blood is rather to be expected in
					those who are younger than thirty-five years. Such swellings as are soft, free
					from pain, and yield to the finger, occasion more protracted crises, and are
					less dangerous than the others. But if the fever continue beyond sixty days,
					without any subsidence of the swelling, it indicates that empyema is about to
					take place; and a swelling in any other part of the cavity will terminate in
					like manner. Such, then, as are painful, hard, and large, indicate danger of
					speedy death; but such as are soft, free of pain, and yield when pressed with
					the finger, are more chronic than these. Swellings in the belly less frequently
					form abscesses than those in the hypochondrium; and seldomest of all, those
					below the navel are converted into suppuration; but you may rather expect a
					hemorrhage from the upper parts. But the suppuration of all protracted swellings
					about these parts is to be anticipated. The collections of matter there are to
					be thus judged of: such as are determined outwards are the best when they are
					small, when they protrude very much, and swell to a point; such as are large and
					broad, and which do not swell out to a sharp point, are the worst. Of such as
					break internally, the best are those which have no external communication, but
					are covered and indolent; and when the whole place is free from discoloration.
					That pus is best which is white, homogeneous, smooth, and not at all fetid; the
					contrary to this is the worst.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 8 </head>
				           <p> All dropsies arising from acute diseases are bad; for they do not remove the
					fever, and are very painful and fatal. The most of them commence from the flanks
					and loins, but some from the liver; in those which derive their origin from the
					flanks and loins the feet swell, protracted diarrhoeas supervene, which neither
						<pb n="p.48"/>remove the pains in the flanks and loins, nor soften the
					belly, but in dropsies which are connected with the liver there is a tickling
					cough, with scarcely any perceptible expectoration, and the feet swell; there
					are no evacuations from the bowels, unless such as are hard and forced; and
					there are swellings about the belly, sometimes on the one side and sometimes on
					the other, and these increase and diminish by turns.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 9 </head>
				           <p> It is a bad symptom when the head, hands, and feet are cold, while the belly and
					sides are hot; but it is a very good symptom when the whole body is equally hot.
					The patient ought to be able to turn round easily, and to be agile when raised
					up; but if he appear heavy in the rest of his body as well as in his hands and
					feet, it is more dangerous; and if, in addition to the weight, his nails and
					fingers become livid, immediate death may be anticipated; and if the hands and
					feet be black it is less dangerous than if they be livid, but the other symptoms
					must be attended, to; for if he appear to bear the illness well, and if certain
					of the salutary symptoms appear along with these there may be hope that the
					disease will turn to a deposition, so that the man may recover; but the
					blackened parts of the body will drop off. When the testicles and members are
					retracted upwards, they indicate strong pains and danger of death.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 10 </head>
				           <p> With regard to sleep- as is usual with us in health, the patient should wake
					during the day and sleep during the night. If this rule be anywise altered it is
					so far worse: but there will be little harm provided he sleep in the morning for
					the third part of the day; such sleep as takes place after this time is more
					unfavorable; but the worst of all is to get no sleep either night or day; for it
					follows from this symptom that the insomnolency is connected with sorrow and
					pains, or that he is about to become delirious.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 11 </head>
				           <p> The excrement is best which is soft and consistent, is passed at the hour which
					was customary to the patient when in health, in quantity proportionate to the
					ingests; for when the passages are such, the lower belly is in a healthy state.
					But if the discharges be fluid, it is favorable that they are not accompanied
					with a noise, nor are frequent, nor in great quantity; for <pb n="p.49"/>the man
					being oppressed by frequently getting up, must be deprived of sleep; and if the
					evacuations be both frequent and large, there is danger of his falling into
					deliquium animi. But in proportion to the ingesta he should have evacuations
					twice or thrice in the day, once at night and more copiously in the morning, as
					is customary with a person in health. The faeces should become thicker when the
					disease is tending to a crisis; they ought to be yellowish and not very fetid.
					It is favorable that round worms be passed with the discharges when the disease
					is tending to a crisis. The belly, too, through the whole disease, should be
					soft and moderately distended; but excrements that are very watery, or white, or
					green, or very red, or frothy, are all bad. It is also bad when the discharge is
					small, and viscid, and white, and greenish, and smooth; but still more deadly
					appearances are the black, or fatty, or livid, or verdigris-green, or fetid.
					Such as are of varied characters indicate greater duration of the complaint, but
					are no less dangerous; such as those which resemble scrapings, those which are
					bilious, those resembling leeks, and the black; these being sometimes passed
					together, and sometimes singly. It is best when wind passes without noise, but
					it is better that flatulence should pass even thus than that it should be
					retained; and when it does pass thus, it indicates either that the man is in
					pain or in delirium, unless he gives vent to the wind spontaneously. Pains in
					the hypochondria, and swellings, if recent, and not accompanied with
					inflammation, are relieved by borborygmi supervening in the hypochondrium, more
					especially if it pass off with faeces, urine, and wind; but even although not,
					it will do good by passing along, and it also does good by descending to the
					lower part of the belly.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 12 </head>
				           <p> The urine is best when the sediment is white, smooth, and consistent during the
					whole time, until the disease come to a crisis, for it indicates freedom from
					danger, and an illness of short duration; but if deficient, and if it be
					sometimes passed clear, and sometimes with a white and smooth sediment, the
					disease will be more protracted, and not so void of danger. But if the urine be
					reddish, and the sediment consistent and smooth, the affection, in this case,
					will be more protracted than the former, <pb n="p.50"/>but still not fatal. But
					farinaceous sediments in the urine are bad, and still worse are the leafy; the
					white and thin are very bad, but the furfuraceous are still worse than these.
					Clouds carried about in the urine are good when white, but bad if black. When
					the urine is yellow and thin, it indicates that the disease is unconcocted; and
					if it (the disease) should be protracted, there maybe danger lest the patient
					should not hold out until the urine be concocted. But the most deadly of all
					kinds of urine are the fetid, watery, black, and thick; in adult men and women
					the black is of all kinds of urine the worst, but in children, the watery. In
					those who pass thin and crude urine for a length of time, if they have otherwise
					symptoms of convalescence, an abscess may be expected to form in the parts below
					the diaphragm. And fatty substances floating on the surface are to be dreaded,
					for they are indications of melting. And one should consider respecting the
					kinds of urine, which have clouds, whether they tend upwards or downwards, and
					upwards or downwards, and the colors which they have and such as fall downwards,
					with the colors as described, are to be reckoned good and commended; but such as
					are carried upwards, with the colors as described, are to be held as bad, and
					are to be distrusted. But you must not allow yourself to be deceived if such
					urine be passed while the bladder is diseased; for then it is a symptom of the
					state, not of the general system, but of a particular viscus.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 13 </head>
				           <p> That vomiting is of most service which consists of phlegm and bile mixed
					together, and neither very thick nor in great quantity; but those vomitings
					which are more unmixed are worse. But if that which is vomited be of the color
					of leeks or livid, or black, whatever of these colors it be, it is to be
					reckoned bad; but if the same man vomit all these colors, it is to be reckoned a
					very fatal symptom. But of all the vomitings, the livid indicates the danger of
					death, provided it be of a fetid smell. But all the smells which are somewhat
					putrid and fetid, are bad in all vomitings.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 14 </head>
				           <p> The expectoration in all pains about the lungs and sides, should be quickly and
					easily brought up, and a certain degree of yellowness should appear strongly
					mixed up with the sputum. <pb n="p.51"/> But if brought up long after the
					commencement of the pain, and of a yellow or ruddy color, or if it occasions
					much cough, or be not strongly mixed, it is worse; for that which is intensely
					yellow is dangerous, but the white, and viscid, and round, do no good. But that
					which is very green and frothy is bad; but if so intense as to appear black, it
					is still more dangerous than these; it is bad, if nothing is expectorated, and
					the lungs discharge nothing, but are gorged with matters which boil (as it were)
					in the air-passages. It is bad when coryza and sneezing either precede or follow
					affections of the lungs, but in all other affections, even the most deadly,
					sneezing is a salutary symptom. A yellow spittle mixed up with not much blood in
					cases of pneumonia, is salutary and very beneficial if spit up at the
					commencement of the disease, but if on the seventh day, or still later, it is
					less favorable. And all sputa are bad which do not remove the pain. But the
					worst is the black, as has been described. Of all others the sputa which remove
					the pain are the best.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 15 </head>
				           <p> When the pains in these regions do not cease, either with the discharge of the
					sputa, nor with alvine evacuations, nor from venesection, purging with medicine,
					nor a suitable regimen, it is to be held that they will terminate in
					suppurations. Of empyemata such as are spit up while the sputum is still
					bilious, are very fatal, whether the bilious portion be expectorated separate,
					or along with the other; but more especially if the empyema begin to advance
					after this sputum on the seventh day of the disease. It is to be expected that a
					person with such an expectoration shall die on the fourteenth day, unless
					something favorable supervene. The following are favorable symptoms: to support
					the disease easily, to have free respiration, to be free from pain, to have the
					sputa readily brought up, the whole body to appear equally warm and soft, to
					have no thirst, the urine, and faeces, sleep, and sweats to be all favorable, as
					described before; when all these symptoms concur, the patient certainly will not
					die; but if some of these be present and some not, he will not survive longer
					than the fourteenth day. The bad symptoms are the opposite of these, namely, to
					bear the disease with difficulty, respiration large and dense, the pain not
					ceasing, the sputum <pb n="p.52"/>scarcely coughed up, strong thirst, to have
					the body unequally affected by the febrile heat, the belly and sides intensely
					hot, the forehead, hands, and feet cold; the urine, and excrements, the sleep,
					and sweats, all bad, agreeably to the characters described above; if such a
					combination of symptoms accompany the expectoration, the man will certainly die
					before the fourteenth day, and either on the ninth or eleventh. Thus then one
					may conclude regarding this expectoration, that it is very deadly, and that the
					patient will not survive until the fourteenth day. It is by balancing the
					concomitant symptoms whether good or bad, that one is to form a prognosis; for
					thus it will most probably prove to be a true one. Most other suppurations
					burst, some on the twentieth, some on the thirtieth, some on the fortieth, and
					some as late as the sixtieth day.<note>The observations of Andral have in some
						measure confirmed the opinion of Hippoc-rates and other authors, ancient and
						modern, that there are certain days in the duration of the disease in which
						there is a greater tendency to amelioration. Of ninety-three cases, he found
						twenty-three give way on the seventh, thirteen on the eleventh, eleven on
						the fourteenth, and nine on the twentieth days. The recoveries in the
						remaining cases commenced on twelve out of forty-two non-critical days, as
						many as eleven being ascribed to the tenth day. Thus the recoveries on
						critical days averaged as high as four-teen, while those on non-critical
						scarcely exceeded three." (Dr. C. J. B. Williams on Pneumonia, Cyclop. of
						Pract. Med., vol. iii., p. 405.) See also Andral, Clin. Med., c. ii., p.
						365.</note>
               </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 16 </head>
				           <p> One should estimate when the commencement of the suppuration will take place, by
					calculating from the day on which the patient was first seized with fever, or if
					he had a rigor, and if he says, that there is a weight in the place where he had
					pain formerly, for these symptoms occur in the commencement of suppurations. One
					then may expect the rupture of the abscesses to take place from these times
					according to the periods formerly stated. But if the empyema be only on either
					side, one should turn him and inquire if he has pain on the other side; and if
					the one side be hotter than the other, and when laid upon the sound side, one
					should inquire if he has the feeling of a weight hanging from above, for if so,
					the empyema will be upon the opposite side to that on which the weight was
					felt.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 17 </head>
				           <p> Empyema may be recognized in all cases by the following symptoms: In the first
					place, the fever does not go off, but is <pb n="p.53"/>slight during the day,
					and increases at night, and copious sweats supervene, there is a desire to
					cough, and the patients expectorate nothing worth mentioning, the eyes become
					hollow, the cheeks have red spots on them, the nails of the hands are bent, the
					fingers are hot especially their extremities, there are swellings in the feet,
					they have no desire of food, and small blisters (phlyctaenae) occur over the
					body. These symptoms attend chronic empyemata, and may be much trusted to; and
					such as are of short standing are indicated by the same, provided they be
					accompanied by those signs which occur at the commencement, and if at the same
					time the patient has some difficulty of breathing. Whether they will break
					earlier or later may be determined by these symptoms; if there be pain at the
					commencement, and if the dyspnoea, cough, and ptyalism be severe, the rupture
					may be expected in the course of twenty days or still earlier; but if the pain
					be more mild, and all the other symptoms in proportion, you may expect from
					these the rupture to be later; but pain, dyspnoea, and ptyalism, must take place
					before the rupture of the abscess. Those patients recover most readily whom the
					fever leaves the same day that the abscess bursts,- when they recover their
					appetite speedily, and are freed from the thirst,- when the alvine discharges
					are small and consistent, the matter white, smooth, uniform in color, and free
					of phlegm, and if brought up without pain or strong coughing. Those die whom the
					fever does not leave, or when appearing to leave them it returns with an
					exacerbation; when they have thirst, but no desire of food, and there are watery
					discharges from the bowels; when the expectoration is green or livid, or
					pituitous and frothy; if all these occur they die, but if certain of these
					symptoms supervene, and others not, some patients die and some recover, after a
					long interval. But from all the symptoms taken together one should form a
					judgment, and so in all other cases.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 18 </head>
				           <p>When abscesses form about the ears, after peripneumonic affections, or
					depositions of matter take place in the inferior extremities and end in fistula,
					such persons recover. The following observations are to be made upon them: if
					the fever persist, and the pain do not cease, if the expectoration be not <pb n="p.54"/>normal, and if the alvine discharges be neither bilious, nor free
					and unmixed; and if the urine be neither copious nor have its proper sediment,
					but if, on the other hand, all the other salutary symptoms be present, in such
					cases abscesses may be expected to take place. They form in the inferior parts
					when there is a collection of phlegm about the hypochondria; and in the upper
					when the hypochondria continue soft and free of pain, and when dyspnoea having
					been present for a certain time, ceases without any obvious cause. All deposits
					which take place in the legs after severe and dangerous attacks of pneumonia,
					are salutary, but the best are those which occur at the time when the sputa
					undergo a change; for if the swelling and pain take place while the sputa are
					changing from yellow and becoming of a purulent character, and are expectorated
					freely, under these circumstances the man will recover most favorably and the
					abscess becoming free of pain, will soon cease; but if the expectoration is not
					free, and the urine does not appear to have the proper sediment, there is danger
					lest the limb should be maimed, or that the case otherwise should give trouble.
					But if the abscesses disappear and go back, while expectoration does not take
					place, and fever prevails, it is a bad symptom; for there is danger that the man
					may get into a state of delirium and die. Of persons having empyema after
					peripneumonic affections, those that are advanced in life run the greatest risk
					of dying; but in the other kinds of empyema younger persons rather die. In cases
					of empyema treated by the cautery or incision, when the matter is pure, white,
					and not fetid, the patient recovers; but if of a bloody and dirty character, he
					dies.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 19 </head>
				           <p> Pains accompanied with fever which occur about the loins and lower parts, if
					they attack the diaphragm, and leave the parts below, are very fatal. Wherefore
					one ought to pay attention to the other symptoms, since if any unfavorable one
					supervene, the case is hopeless; but if while the disease is determined to the
					diaphragm, the other symptoms are not bad, there is great reason to expect that
					it will end in empyema. When the bladder is hard and painful, it is an extremely
					bad and mortal symptom, more especially in cases attended with continued <pb n="p.55"/>fever; for the pains proceeding from the bladder alone are to kill
					the patient; and at such a time the bowels are not moved, or the discharges are
					hard and forced. But urine of a purulent character, and having a white and
					smooth sediment, relieves the patient. But if no amendment takes place in the
					characters of the urine, nor the bladder become soft, and the fever is of the
					continual type, it may be expected that the patient will die in the first stages
					of the complaint. This form attacks children more especially, from their seventh
					to their fifteenth year.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 20 </head>
				           <p> Fevers come to a crisis on the same days as to number on which men recover and
					die. For the mildest class of fevers, and those originating with the most
					favorable symptoms, cease on the fourth day or earlier; and the most malignant,
					and those setting in with the most dangerous symptoms, prove fatal on the fourth
					day or earlier. The first class of them as to violence ends thus: the second is
					protracted to the seventh day, the third to the eleventh, the fourth to the
					fourteenth, the fifth to the seventeenth, and the sixth to the twentieth. Thus
					these periods from the most acute disease ascend by fours up to twenty. But none
					of these can be truly calculated by whole days, for neither the year nor the
					months can be numbered by entire days. After these in the same manner, according
					to the same progression, the first period is of thirty-four days, the second of
					forty days, and the third of sixty days. In the commencement of these it is very
					difficult to determine those which will come to a crisis after a long interval;
					for these beginnings are very similar, but one should pay attention from the
					first day, and observe further at every additional tetrad, and then one cannot
					miss seeing how the disease will terminate. The constitution of quartans is
					agreeable to the same order. Those which will come to a crisis in the shortest
					space of time, are the easiest to be judged of; for the differences of them are
					greatest from the commencement, thus those who are going to recover breathe
					freely, and do not suffer pain, they sleep during the night, and have the other
					salutary symptoms, whereas those that are to die have difficult respiration, are
					delirious, troubled with insomnolency, and have other bad symptoms. Matters
					being thus, one may conjecture, according <pb n="p.56"/> to the time, and each
					additional period of the diseases, as they proceed to a crisis. And in women,
					after parturition, the crises proceed agreeably to the same ratio.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 21 </head>
				           <p> Strong and continued headaches with fever, if any of the deadly symptoms be
					joined to them, are very fatal. But if without such symptoms the pain be
					prolonged beyond twenty days, a discharge of blood from the nose or some abscess
					in the inferior parts may be anticipated; but while the pain is recent, we may
					expect in like manner a discharge of blood from the nose, or a suppuration,
					especially if the pain be seated above the temples and forehead; but the
					hemorrhage is rather to be looked for in persons younger than thirty years, and
					the suppuration in more elderly persons.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 22 </head>
				           <p> Acute pain of the ear, with continual and strong fever, is to be dreaded; for
					there is danger that the man may become delirious and die. Since, then, this is
					a hazardous spot, one ought to pay particular attention to all these symptoms
					from the commencement. Younger persons die of this disease on the seventh day,
					or still earlier, but old persons much later; for the fevers and delirium less
					frequently supervene upon them, and on that account the ears previously come to
					a suppuration, but at these periods of life, relapses of the disease coming on
					generally prove fatal. Younger persons die before the ear suppurates; only if
					white matter run from the ear, there may be hope that a younger person will
					recover, provided any other favorable symptom be combined.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 23 </head>
				           <p> Ulceration of the throat with fever, is a serious affection, and if any other of
					the symptoms formerly described as being bad, be present, the physician ought to
					announce that his patient is in danger. Those quinsies are most dangerous, and
					most quickly prove fatal, which make no appearance in the fauces, nor in the
					neck, but occasion very great pain and difficulty of breathing; these induce
					suffocation on the first day, or on the second, the third, or the fourth. Such
					as, in like manner, are attended with pain, are swelled up, and have redness
					(erythema) in the throat, are indeed very fatal, but more protracted than<pb n="p.57"/> the former, provided the redness be great. Those cases in which
					both the throat and the neck are red, are more protracted, and certain persons
					recover from them, especially if the neck and breast be affected with erythema,
					and the erysipelas be not determined inwardly. If neither the erysipelas
					disappear on the critical day, nor any abscess form outwardly, nor any pus be
					spit up, and if the patient fancy himself well, and be free from pain, death, or
					a relapse of the erythema is to be apprehended. It is much less hazardous when
					the swelling and redness are determined outwardly; but if determined to the
					lungs, they superinduce delirium, and frequently some of these cases terminate
					in empyema. It is very dangerous to cut off or scarify enlarged uvulae while
					they and red and large, for inflammations and hemorrhages supervene; but one
					should try to reduce such swellings by some other means at this season. When the
					whole of it is converted into an abscess, which is called Uva, or when the
					extremity of the variety called Columella is larger and round, but the upper
					part thinner, at this time it will be safe to operate. But it will be better to
					open the bowels gently before proceeding to the operation, if time will permit,
					and the patient be not in danger of being suffocated.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 24 </head>
				           <p> When the fevers cease without any symptoms of resolution occurring, and not on
					the critical days, in such cases a relapse may be anticipated. When any of the
					fevers is protracted, although the man exhibits symptoms of recovery, and there
					is no longer pain from any inflammation, nor from any other visible cause, in
					such a case a deposit, with swelling and pain, may be expected in some one of
					the joints, and not improbably in those below. Such deposits occur more readily
					and in less time to persons under thirty years of age; and one should
					immediately suspect the formation of such a deposit, if the fever be protracted
					beyond twenty days; but to aged persons these less seldom happen, and not until
					the fever be much longer protracted. Such a deposit may be expected, when the
					fever is of a continual type, and that it will pass into a quartan, if it become
					intermittent, and its paroxysms come on in an irregular manner, and if in this
					form it approach autumn. As deposits form most readily in persons below thirty
					years of age, so quartans most commonly occur to persons beyond that age. It is
					proper to know that deposits occur most readily in winter, that then they are
					most protracted, but are less given to return. Whoever, in a fever that is not
					of a fatal character, says that he has pain in his head, and that something dark
					appears to be before his eyes, and that he has pain at the stomach, will be
					seized with vomiting of bile; but if rigor also attack him, and the inferior
					parts of the hypochondrium are cold, vomiting is still nearer at hand; and if he
					eat or drink anything at such a season, it will be quickly vomited. In these
					cases, when the pain commences on the first day, they are particularly oppressed
					on the fourth and the fifth; and they are relieved on the seventh, but the
					greater part of them begin to have pain on the third day, and are most
					especially tossed on the fifth, but are relieved on the ninth or eleventh; but
					in those who begin to have pains on the fifth day, and other matters proceed
					properly with them, the disease comes to a crisis on the fourteenth day. But
					when in such a fever persons affected with headache, instead of having a dark
					appearance before their eyes, have dimness of vision, or flashes of light appear
					before their eyes, and instead of pain at the pit of the stomach, they have in
					their hypochondrium a fullness stretching either to the right or left side,
					without either pain or inflammation, a hemorrhage from the nose is to be
					expected in such a case, rather than a vomiting. But it is in young persons
					particularly that the hemorrhage is to be expected, for in persons beyond the
					age of thirty-five, vomitings are rather to be anticipated. Convulsions occur to
					children if acute fever be present, and the belly be they cannot sleep, are
					agitated, and moan, and change color, and become green, livid, or ruddy. These
					complaints occur most readily to children which are very young up to their
					seventh year; older children and adults are not equally liable to be seized with
					convulsions in fevers, unless some of the strongest and worst symptoms precede,
					such as those which occur in frenzy. One must judge of children as of others,
					which will die and which recover, from the whole of the symptoms, as they have
						been<pb n="p.59"/> specially described.<note>Our author here and elsewhere
						impresses it upon his readers that it is from the <hi rend="ital">tout
							ensemble</hi> of the symptoms that a judgment is to be formed in every
						case. This is evidently a remark of the most vital importance in forming a
						prognosis.</note> These things I say respecting acute diseases, and the
					affections which spring from them.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 25 </head>
				           <p> He who would correctly beforehand those that will recover, and those that will
					die, and in what cases the disease will be protracted for many days, and in what
					cases for a shorter time, must be able to form a judgment from having made
					himself acquainted with all the symptoms, and estimating their powers in
					comparison with one another, as has been described, with regard to the others,
					and the urine and sputa, as when the patient coughs up pus and bile together.
					One ought also to consider promptly the influx of epidemical diseases and the
					constitution of the season. One should likewise be well acquainted with the
					particular signs and the other symptoms, and not be ignorant how that, in every
					year, and at every season, bad symptoms prognosticate ill, and favorable
					symptoms good, since the aforesaid symptoms appear to have held true in Libya,
					in Delos, and in Scythia,<note>It has excited a great deal of discussion and
						difference of opinion to determine what our author means by specifying these
						three places; but the explanation given by Galen in his Commentary seems to
						me quite satisfactory. According to him, the meaning of our author is that
						good and bad symptoms tell the same in all places, in the hot regions of
						Libya, the cold of Scythia, and the temperate of Delos. It is further to be
						borne in mind that Odessus in Scythia, and Cyrene in Libya, were the
						extremities of the Grecian world, whilst Delos may be regarded as its
						centre. It is proper to remark, however, that by the three places mentioned,
						Erotian understands the three quarters of the earth-Africa, Asia, and
						Europe.</note> from which it may be known that, in the same regions, there
					is no difficulty in attaining a knowledge of many more things than these; if
					having learned them, one knows also how to judge and reason correctly of them.
					But you should not complain because the name of any disease may happen not to be
					described here, for you may know all such as come to a crisis in the
					aforementioned times, by the same symptoms.<note>The meaning of this last
						sentence has been supposed to be somewhat ambiguous; but to me it appears
						evidently to be this, that the rules of prognosis, as laid down above, apply
						to all diseases of an acute character, whether their names happen to be
						mentioned in the course of this work or not, so that it should not be
						considered a defect in the work that any one is omitted.</note>
               </p>
			         </div>


		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
