<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On The Estate Of Aristarchus from Speeches (ENGLISH). Machine readable
					text</title>
				<author>Isaeus</author>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>


			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Isaeus</author>
						<title>Isaeus with an English translation by Edward Seymour Forster,
							M.A.</title>

						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
								Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1962</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="speech"/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English </language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek </language>
				<language ident="latin">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--
<change><date>March 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>September 1992</date><respStmt><name>D. Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed notes and regularized citations</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
			<change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>

			<div n="hypothesis" type="section">
				<p>A certain Aristarchus was the father of four children, Cyronides, Demochares, the
					mother of the speaker of this oration, and another daughter. During his lifetime
					he gave Cyronides in adoption to be heir of the estate of his maternal
					grandfather Xenaenetus, and left his other children as his own heirs.
					Subsequently Demochares died without issue, as also did one of the daughters,
					and the whole estate passed by law to the mother of the speaker. Such was the
					position of affairs; but, after the death of Aristarchus, Aristomenes, his
					brother and now the legal representative of his brother's children, gave his own
					daughter in marriage to Cyronides, the son of Aristarchus, who had been adopted
					out of the family, having promised to obtain for him the estate of Aristarchus.
					This he succeeded in doing; for, when a son was born to Cyronides, they first
					gave him his grandfather's name, calling him Aristarchus (II.), and then had him
					adopted into his grandfather's family, on the ground that the latter had given
					instructions to this effect, and Aristomenes handed over to him all his
					grandfather's estate. Aristarchus (II.), dying without issue, constituted his
					own brother Xenaenetus (II.) by will as his heir. This being so and Xenaenetus
					being in possession of the property of Aristarchus the elder, the son of the
					latter's daughter claims the estate from him, asserting that he is himself by
					law the sole heir to the fortune of Aristarchus the elder. For, he declares,
					Cyronides passed out of the family by adoption, and his father, having a
					legitimate son, namely, Demochares, could not adopt a child; nor were
					Demochares, being under age, and the other sister who predeceased him in a
					position to adopt a son into their father's family. Therefore, he argues, since
					the adoption of Aristarchus the younger was not good in law, his will could not
					stand either; for how could he pass on to another property which he acquired
					without right? The will being thus annulled, the estate ought naturally to pass
					to the speaker as son of the legitimate daughter of Aristarchus the elder. Such
					is the subject; the discussion is concerned with validity, namely, that of a
					written document; for the questions are whether such a will ought to stand and
					which party has the better claim. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="1" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I could wish, gentlemen, that, as Xenaenetus here
					finds it easy to lie with boldness, so I with like confidence could speak the
					truth to you in presenting my claim; for then, I think, it would immediately
					become clear to you whether we have unjustly come forward to claim the
					inheritance and whether our opponents have been for a long time in wrongful
					possession of this fortune. But, as it is, we are not on equal terms; for they
					are both able speakers and clever plotters, so that they have often pleaded
					before you on behalf of others, whereas I, so far from speaking on behalf of
					another, have never before pleaded on my own behalf in a private suit, and
					therefore deserve great indulgence at your hands. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="2" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I was obliged, it is true, owing to the
					impossibility of obtaining justice against my opponents, to add to my petition
					at the preliminary inquiry that my mother was sister of Aristarchus (II.).<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See Introduction.</note> This will not, however,
					make your decision any the less easy, if you ask yourselves the question in the
					light of the laws whether the estate which Aristarchus (II.) has bequeathed to
					my opponent was his own or whether it was property to which he had no right.
					This question is a perfectly legal one; for the law ordains that a man can
					dispose of what is his own to anyone he likes, but it has never given anyone
					power over the possessions of another. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="3" type="section">
				<p>This, then, is the first point which I shall try to make clear to you, if you
					will give me your kind attention; for you will recognize that this estate
					belonged from the first, not to my opponents but to my mother, who inherited it
					from her father, and, secondly, that Aristarchus (II.) seized it without the
					sanction of any law, and that he and the members of his family are wronging my
					mother in violation of every law. I will try to put the matter before you, going
					back to a point which will enable you to form the clearest conception of the
					facts. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="4" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Aristarchus (I.), gentlemen, belonged to the deme
					of Sypalettus. He married the daughter of Xenaenetus (I.) of Acharnae, by whom
					he had two sons, Cyronides and Demochares, and two daughters, one of whom was my
					mother. Cyronides, the father of my opponent and of the other party<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., Aristarchus II.</note> who illegally kept
					possession of this estate, was adopted into another family, so that he had no
					further claim to the property. On the death of Aristarchus (I.), the father of
					these two sons, Demochares his son became his heir; but, when he died in his
					minority and the other sister also died, my mother became heiress to the whole
					of the family estate. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="5" type="section">
				<p>Thus from the beginning all this fortune really belonged to my mother; but,
					although she ought to have passed by marriage, together with her fortune, into
					the hands of her nearest relative, she is being abominably treated. For
					Aristomenes, the brother of Aristarchus the elder, having a son and a daughter
					of his own, neglected to make her his own wife or to have her married to his own
					son by an adjudication of the court; refusing both these alternatives, he gave
					his own daughter in marriage to Cyronides, endowing her with the fortune which
					belonged to my mother. Xenaenetus here and Aristarchus (II.), now deceased, were
					the issue of this marriage. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="6" type="section">
				<p>This is the injury, this the manner, gentlemen, in which my mother was deprived
					of her fortune. Subsequently Aristomenes gave my mother in marriage to my
					father. On the death of Cyronides, they introduced Xenaenetus's brother<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., Aristarchus II.</note> as the adopted son
					of Aristarchus (I.), a proceeding which cannot be justified by any law, as I
					will demonstrate to you by many proofs. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="7" type="section">
				<p>I will produce witnesses to testify, in the first place, that Cyronides entered
					by adoption into the family of Xenaenetus (I.) and belonged to that family at
					the time of his death; secondly, that Aristarchus (I.), to whom this estate
					belonged, predeceased his son Demochares, and that Demochares died while yet a
					minor, as did also the other sister, with the result that the estate devolved on
					to my mother. Please summon the witnesses to these facts.<quote type="Witnesses"
							><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="8" type="section">
				<p>Thus, gentlemen, the estate now in question belonged to my mother from the
					beginning, since Cyronides was adopted out of the family into that of Xenaenetus
					(I.), and his father, Aristarchus (I.), left his property to his son Demochares,
					who left it to his own sister, my mother. But since they are so exceedingly
					impudent and claim this fortune against all right, you must see, gentlemen, that
					no law whatever authorized the introduction of Aristarchus (the younger) into
					the ward of Aristarchus (the elder); if you see this, you will clearly apprehend
					that the illegal detainer of the property had no right to dispose of it either.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="9" type="section">
				<p>I think that you are all aware, gentlemen, that the introduction of adopted
					children is always carried out by a will, the testator simultaneously devising
					his estate and adopting the son, and that this is the only legal method. If,
					therefore, anyone shall assert that Aristarchus (I.) himself made a will, he
					will be saying what is not true; for, while he possessed a legitimate son,
					Demochares, he could not have wished to do so and he was not permitted to devise
					his property to anyone else. Again, if they declare that Demochares adopted
					Aristarchus (II.) after the death of Aristarchus (I.), they will likewise be
					lying. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="10" type="section">
				<p>For a minor is not allowed to make a will; for the law expressly forbids any
					child—or woman—to contract for the disposal of more than a bushel of barley. Now
					evidence has been given you that Aristarchus (I.) predeceased his son Demochares
					and that the latter died after his father; and so, even supposing they had made
					wills, Aristarchus (II.) could never have inherited this property under their
						wills.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Which would be invalid because
						Aristarchus (I.) could not make a will in favor of anyone except Demochares,
						and predeceased Demochares, who, having died under age, was incapable of
						making a will.</note> Now read the laws which show that neither of them had
					the right to make a will.<quote type="Laws"><title>Laws</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="11" type="section">
				<p>Nor again, gentlemen, could Cyronides give Aristarchus (I.) a son by adoption; he
					could, it is true, have returned to his father's family, if he had left a son in
					the family of Xenaenetus (I.), but there is no law which permits him to
					introduce a son of his own to take his place. If they assert the existence of
					such a law they will be lying. So, not even if they assert that the adoption was
					carried out by Cyronides, will they be able to point to any law which authorized
					him to do so; but from their own assertions it will become still more evident to
					you that they are illegally and impudently detaining my mother's property. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="12" type="section">
				<p>Furthermore, gentlemen, though Aristomenes or Apollodorus might have had my
					mother adjudicated to them in marriage, yet they had no right to her estate.
					Seeing that neither Apollodorus nor Aristomenes, if either of them had married
					my mother, could possibly have had the disposal of her property—in accordance
					with the law which does not allow anyone to have the disposal of the property of
					an heiress except her sons, who obtain possession of it on reaching the second
					year after puberty—it would be strange if Aristarchus is going to be allowed,
					after giving her in marriage to another, to introduce a son to inherit her
					fortune. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="13" type="section">
				<p>It would indeed be an extraordinary state of affairs. Again, her own father, in
					default of male heirs, could not have disposed of his estate without disposing
					of her with it; for the law ordains that he may dispose of his property to
					whomsoever he wishes, if he disposes of his daughters with it. But when one who
					has refused to take the heiress in marriage and is not her father but her
					cousin, introduces an heir to her fortune in violation of every law, is this to
					be recognized as a valid act? Who of you can possibly believe it to be so? </p>
			</div>
			<div n="14" type="section">
				<p>For myself, gentlemen, I am perfectly certain that neither Xenaenetus nor anyone
					else can prove that this estate does not belong to my mother, having come to her
					through her brother Demochares. But, if, after all, they venture to deal with
					the question, order them to indicate the law under which the adoption has been
					carried out in favor of Aristarchus (II.) and to declare who carried it out.
					This is a perfectly just demand. But I know that they will not be able to
					indicate any such law. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="15" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>That the estate, then, belonged to my mother from
					the beginning and that she has been unjustly deprived of it by my opponents,
					has, I think, been sufficiently demonstrated by my arguments, by the evidence
					which has been produced, and by the citation of the actual laws. Indeed, these
					men are so perfectly well aware that they are wrongfully in possession of this
					fortune that they do not rest their argument solely upon the legality of the
					introduction of Aristarchus (II.) to the members of the ward, but also allege
					that Xenaenetus's father has paid a judgement-debt on behalf of the estate<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Wyse suggests that Aristarchus I. died in debt
						to the state and therefore without civic rights, and that Cyronides settled
						his liabilities to save the estate from confiscation and the heir from the
						disabilities which he would inherit.</note> in order that, if their claim on
					the former ground should not seem just, it may appear that they have a good
					claim to the estate on the second ground. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="16" type="section">
				<p>I shall show you, gentlemen, by convincing proofs that there is no truth in what
					they say. For if, as they allege, this estate had been insolvent, they would
					never have expended any money upon it—for it was not their business to do so,
					but those who had the right to claim my mother's hand ought to have concerned
					themselves with the matter—nor would they have introduced a son as the adopted
					child of Aristarchus (I.) to inherit his estate, if they were not going to get
					any advantage but only suffer considerable loss. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="17" type="section">
				<p>Other people indeed, when they have had monetary losses, introduce their children
					into other families in order that they may not share in their parents' loss of
					civic rights; and did my opponents adopt themselves into a succession and family
					which was insolvent, in order that they might lose in addition what they already
					possessed? Nay, it is impossible the estate was unencumbered and descended to my
					mother, and these men, in their greed for money and their anxiety to rob her,
					devised all this story. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="18" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Some among you, gentlemen, may be surprised at the
					delay, and ask how it is that we allowed so long an interval to elapse, and,
					being defrauded, took no steps in the matter, and are only now putting in our
					claim. Now, although I think it unjust that anyone should have less than his due
					rights through inability or neglect to assert them—for such a consideration
					should not be taken into account, but only the justice or injustice of his
					plea—yet even for this delay, gentlemen, we can furnish an explanation. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="19" type="section">
				<p>My father received a dowry when he engaged himself to my mother and married her,
					but, while these men were enjoying the estate, he had no means of obtaining its
					restitution; for when, at my mother's instance, he raised the question, they
					threatened that they themselves would obtain the adjudication of her hand and
					marry her, if he were not satisfied to keep her with only a dowry. Now my father
					would have allowed them to enjoy an estate of even double the value so as not to
					be deprived of her. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="20" type="section">
				<p>That is why my father never brought a suit for the estate. Then came the
					Corinthian war,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><dateRange from="-394"
							to="-386">394</dateRange>-386 B.C.</note> in which my father and I were
					obliged to serve, so that neither of us could have obtained justice. When peace
					was restored, I had unfortunate difficulties with the public treasury,<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Debtors to the public treasury were temporarily
						deprived of their rights as citizens and therefore could not engage in
						litigation.</note> so that it was not easy for me to contend with my
					opponents. Thus we have good reasons for our conduct in the matter. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="21" type="section">
				<p>But the time has now come when it is only right that my opponent should declare
					who it was that gave him the estate, and what laws justify his introduction in
					the ward, and why it is that my mother was not heiress to this fortune. These
					are the points on which you must give your verdict, not as to whether we are
					late in demanding what is our own. If they cannot explain these points, you
					would be justified in deciding that the estate is mine. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="22" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I am sure they will not be able to do so; for it
					is difficult to argue against law and justice. But they will talk about the
					deceased, saying how sad it is that so brave a man has fallen in battle and
					declaring that it is unjust to set aside his will. I myself, gentlemen, am of
					opinion that any will which a man may make about his own property ought to be
					valid, but that wills which concern other people's property ought not to have
					the same validity as those in which a man disposes of what is his own. Now this
					property is clearly not theirs but ours; </p>
			</div>
			<div n="23" type="section">
				<p>and so, if he takes refuge in this argument and produces witnesses to testify
					that Aristarchus (I.) made a will, you must order him to prove also that what he
					devised was his own. This is only just, for it would be a most terrible state of
					affairs if Cyronides and my opponents, his children, are not only to possess the
					fortune of Xenaenetus (I.) of the value of more than four talents, but are also
					to receive this estate, while I, though my mother was the rightful owner and I
					am descended from the same ancestors as Cyronides, am not to receive even my
					mother's estate, especially as these men cannot indicate the person through whom
					it has been transmitted to them. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="24" type="section">
				<p>Yet in all justice, just as the holder of a disputed piece of land must produce
					the mortgagee or vendor, or else prove that he has had it adjudicated to him by
					the court, so ought these men to set forth their titles in detail and claim to
					have the estate adjudicated to them, instead of ejecting my mother, the daughter
					of Aristarchus (I.), from her paternal inheritance before any suit has been
					heard. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="25" type="section">
				<p>But no doubt, gentlemen, it is not enough for Xenaenetus (II.) to have dissipated
					the fortune of Aristomenes in unnatural debauchery; he thinks that he ought to
					dispose of this estate also in like manner. I, on the other hand, gentlemen,
					though my means are slender, bestowed my sisters in marriage, giving them what
					dowry I could; and as one who leads an orderly life and performs the duties
					assigned to him and serves in the army, I demand not to be deprived of my
					mother's paternal estate. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="26" type="section">
				<p>I have proved to you that Cyronides, the father of my opponents, was adopted into
					another family and did not return to his father's house; that the father of
					Cyronides and of my mother left this estate to Demochares; that Demochares died
					in his minority, and that it was upon my mother that this estate then
					devolved.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
