<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Second Olynthiac </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by J. H. Vince, M.A.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1930</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>6/2/92</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserted quotedtext tag around verse</item>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>On many occasions, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, one
                    may, I think, recognize the manifest favor of heaven towards our city, and not
                    least at the present crisis. That Philip has found men willing to fight him,
                    situated on his frontiers and possessed of considerable power, above all so
                    determined that they regard any accommodation with him as both delusive and
                    fatal to their own country—this has all the appearance of a super-human, a
                    divine beneficence. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>So the time has come, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    to look to it that we do not prove more unfriendly to ourselves than
                    circumstances have been, for we shall show ourselves the meanest of mankind, if
                    we abandon not only the cities and the places which we once called our own, but
                    the very allies that fortune has raised up for us and the chances she throws in
                    our way. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>Now I do not choose, Athenians, to enumerate the resources of Philip and by such
                    arguments to call on you to rise to the occasion. Do you ask why? Because it
                    seems to me that any dissertation on that topic is a tribute to his enterprise,
                    but a record of our failure. For the higher he has raised himself above his
                    proper level, the more he wins the admiration of the world; but the more you
                    have failed to improve your opportunities, the greater is the discredit that you
                    have incurred. All this then I will waive. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>For an impartial investigation, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, would trace the source of Philip's greatness not to
                    himself, but to this very platform. Of transactions, then, for which Philip
                    should be grateful to those whose policy has served his interests, and for which
                    you might well demand satisfaction, I do not find this the proper time for
                    speaking. There are, however other topics open to me; you will be the better for
                    having heard them, and if you will consent to scrutinize them accurately, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you will find in them
                    grave charges against Philip. On these topics I shall endeavor to address you.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>Now to call a man perjured and faithless, without drawing attention to his acts,
                    might justly be termed mere abuse; but to describe his conduct in detail and
                    convict him on the whole count fortunately requires only a short speech.
                    Moreover, I have two reasons for thinking the story worth the telling: Philip
                    shall appear as worthless as he really is, and those who stand aghast at his
                    apparent invincibility shall see that he has exhausted all the arts of chicanery
                    on which his greatness was founded at the first, and that his career has now
                    reached its extreme limit. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>For my own part, Athenians, I too should be inclined to regard Philip with
                    mingled fear and admiration, if I saw that his success had crowned a career of
                    integrity. But when I consider him attentively, I find that at the outset, when
                    the Olynthians were anxious to consult you, but certain persons were for
                    excluding them from our Assembly, he won our simple hearts by promising to hand
                    over <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName> to us and by
                    negotiating that secret treaty<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The proposed
                        surrender of <placeName key="perseus,Pydna">Pydna</placeName> in exchange
                        for <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>.</note> once
                    so much talked about. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>I find that next he won the friendship of the Olynthians by capturing <placeName
                        key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName>, which was yours, and thus wronging
                    you, his former allies,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If the Greek is sound,
                        this must allude to Philip's offer of alliance with <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> ten years before. But perhaps we
                        should omit <foreign xml:lang="grc">u(ma=s</foreign> with Blass. The allies
                        will then be the Potidaeans, as the Scholiast explains.</note> in presenting
                    it to them. Lastly he has won over the Thessalians by promising to bestow
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002751">Magnesia</placeName> upon them and by
                    undertaking to conduct the Phocian war<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        Sacred War of 355-346.</note> in their interests. In a word, he has
                    hoodwinked everyone that has had any dealings with him; he has played upon the
                    folly of each party in turn and exploited their ignorance of his own character.
                    That is how he has gained his power. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>Now even as he has raised himself by these arts, while every community imagined
                    that they were to be the recipients of his favors, so by these same arts he is
                    bound to be brought low again now that the utter selfishness of his conduct has
                    been amply demonstrated. Yes, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, this is the turning point of Philip's career. If not,
                    let someone step up and prove to me—or rather to you—that my words are untrue,
                    or that those who have been once deceived will continue to trust him, or that
                    the Thessalians who stooped to become his slaves would not now welcome their
                    emancipation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>Again, if anyone here admits the truth of this, but fancies that Philip will
                    remain master of the situation, being already in possession of the fortresses
                    and harbors and other points of vantage, he is mistaken. For when a league is
                    knit together by goodwill, when all the allied states have the same interests,
                    then the individual members are willing to remain steadfast, sharing the toil
                    and enduring the hardships; but when a man has gained power, as Philip has, by
                    rapacity and crime, then the first pretext, some trifling slip, overthrows and
                    shatters all. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>It is impossible, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    impossible to gain permanent power by injustice, perjury, and falsehood. Once in
                    a way and for a brief season such things endure, and fed with hopes make, it may
                    be, a brave show of blossom, but at the last they are detected and fall to
                    pieces. For a house, I take it, or a ship or anything of that sort must have its
                    chief strength in its substructure; and so too in affairs of state the
                    principles and the foundations must be truth and justice. There is no vestige of
                    these today in the power that Philip has built up. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>I urge you strongly to send help to <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                        >Olynthus</placeName>, and the best and quickest method that anyone can
                    suggest will please me most. To the Thessalians you must send an embassy to
                    inform some of them of our intentions and to stir up the others; for they have
                    already decided to demand the restoration of <placeName key="tgn,7012084"
                        >Pagasae</placeName> and to protest against the occupation of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002751">Magnesia</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>But you must make sure, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                    >Athens</placeName>, that our envoys do not confine themselves to words; they
                    must be able to give some practical proof that we have taken the field in a way
                    worthy of our city and that we are really grappling with the situation. All
                    words, apart from action, seem vain and idle, especially words from Athenian
                    lips; for the greater our reputation for a ready tongue, the greater the
                    distrust it inspires in all men.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>You must indeed prove the thoroughness of your reformation and the importance of
                    your change of policy by raising money, by serving in the field, and by doing
                    everything with a will, if you want anyone to take you seriously. If you consent
                    to carry through the necessary reforms at once, not only will Philip's
                    alliances, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, prove
                    unstable and untrustworthy, but the weakness of his native power and sovereignty
                    will be completely exposed. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>Yes, the power and sovereignty of <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                        >Macedonia</placeName> is indeed, as an adjunct, no slight contribution, as
                    you found it when on your side against <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                        >Olynthus</placeName> in the days of Timotheus.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">In 364 an Athenian force under Timotheus joined Perdiccas,
                        king of <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, in an attack on
                        the Olynthian confederacy.</note> On another occasion, in dealing with
                        <placeName key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName>, the Olynthians found its
                    cooperation of some value; and lately it came to the help of the Thessalians in
                    their factions and feuds against the ruling house. The accession, I suppose,
                    even of a small force is in every way helpful; but by itself <placeName
                        key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> is weak and full of defects. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>For indeed Philip by all that might be deemed to constitute his greatness, by his
                    wars and his campaigns, has only reduced his country below its natural level of
                    insecurity. You must not imagine, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, that his subjects share his tastes. No: glory is his
                    sole object and ambition; in action and in danger he has elected to suffer
                    whatever may befall him putting before a life of safety the distinction of
                    achieving what no other king of <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                        >Macedonia</placeName> ever achieved. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>But his subjects have no share in the glory that results. They are perpetually
                    buffeted and wearied and distressed by these expeditions north and south, never
                    suffered to give their time to their business or their private affairs, never
                    able to dispose of such produce as they can raise, because the war has closed
                    all the markets in their land. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>Hence it is not difficult to see how the majority of the Macedonians regard
                    Philip. As for his household troops and footguards, they have indeed the name of
                    admirable soldiers, well grounded in the science of war; but one who has lived
                    on the spot, a man incapable of falsehood, has informed me that they are no
                    better than other soldiers. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>If there is anyone among them who can be described as experienced in war and
                    battle, I was told that Philip from jealousy keeps all such in the background,
                    because he wants to have the credit himself of every action, among his many
                    faults being an insatiable ambition. Any fairly decent or honest man, who cannot
                    stomach the licentiousness of his daily life, the drunkenness and the lewd
                    dancing, is pushed aside as of no account. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>All the rest about his court, he said, are robbers and toadies, men capable of
                    getting drunk and performing such dances as I hesitate to name to you here. This
                    report is obviously true, for the men who were unanimously expelled from
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, as being of far looser
                    morals than the average mountebank—I mean Callias the hangman and fellows of
                    that stamp, low comedians, men who compose ribald songs to raise a laugh against
                    their boon companions—these are the men he welcomes and loves to have about him.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>These are perhaps trivial things, and yet, Athenians, to wise men they afford an
                    important proof of the infatuation of his character. For the present, however,
                    his prosperity throws all this into the shade (for success is apt to cover a
                    multitude of faults); but if he trips, then we shall know all about his vices.
                    And it seems to me, Athenians, that we shall not have to wait long for the
                    exposure, if heaven wills and you so resolve. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>For just as in our bodies, so long as a man is in sound health, he is conscious
                    of no pain, but if some malady assails him, every part is set a-working, be it
                    rupture or sprain or any other local affection; even so is it with states and
                    monarchies; as long as their wars are on foreign soil, few detect their
                    weaknesses, but when the shock of battle is on their frontiers, it makes all
                    their faults perfectly clear. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>But if any of you, Athenians, seeing Philip's good fortune, thinks that he is in
                    that respect a formidable antagonist, he reasons like a prudent man. For fortune
                    is indeed a great weight in the scales; I might almost say it is everything in
                    human affairs. All the same, if you gave me the choice, I should prefer the
                    fortune of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to Philip's,
                    provided that you are willing to do your duty yourselves, even to a limited
                    extent; for I am sure you have far greater claims than he upon the favor of the
                    gods. Yet, I think, we sit here doing nothing. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>But one who is himself idle cannot possibly call upon his friends, much less upon
                    the gods, to work for him. No wonder that Philip, sharing himself in the toils
                    of the campaign, present at every action, neglecting no chance and wasting no
                    season, gets the better of us, while we procrastinate and pass resolutions and
                    ask questions. I cannot wonder at this: the contrary would rather surprise me,
                    that we, performing no single duty of a combatant, should overcome the man who
                    fulfils them all. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>Nay, I am surprised that you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, who once withstood the Lacedaemonians in defence of the
                    rights of Hellas, who spurned the opportunity, repeatedly offered, of
                    self-aggrandizement, who lavished your treasure and jeoparded your lives in the
                    field that others might enjoy their rights, now shrink from service and grudge
                    to pay your contributions for the sake of your own possessions. I am surprised
                    that you, who have so often saved the other states, both all of them together
                    and each separately in turn, should sit down under the loss of what is your own.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>All this I wonder at, and at another thing besides. I wonder that no one here,
                    men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, can count up how many
                    years you have been at war with Philip, and what you have been doing all that
                    long time. Surely you must know that all that time you have been hesitating,
                    hoping that some other state would take action, accusing and sitting in
                    judgement on one another, and still hoping, hoping—doing in fact pretty much
                    what you are doing now. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>And are you so unintelligent, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, as to hope that the same policy that has brought our
                    state from success to failure will raise us from failure to success? Surely that
                    is neither reasonable nor natural; for in all things it is much easier to keep
                    than to gain. But, in the present instance, of what was once ours the war has
                    left us nothing to keep and everything to gain. This, then, is our own task
                    today. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>I say it is your duty to serve cheerfully in person and to reserve your censures
                    till you are masters of the situation. Then, judging all on their merits, assign
                    praise to the deserving and punishment to the wrongdoers, and render excuse
                    impossible by mending your own deficiencies; for you have no right to be severe
                    critics of others' conduct, unless you first set your own house in order. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>Why is it, think you, men of Athens, that all the generals you dispatch—if I am
                    to tell you something of the truth about them—leave this war to itself and
                    pursue little wars of their own? It is because in this war the prizes for which
                    you contend are your own—(if, for instance, <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                        >Amphipolis</placeName> is captured, the immediate gain will be yours)—while
                    the officers have all the dangers to themselves and no remuneration; but in the
                    other case the risks are smaller and the prizes fall to the officers and the
                        soldiers—<placeName key="tgn,7002579">Lampsacus</placeName>, for example,
                    and Sigeum, and the plunder of the merchant-ships. So they turn aside each to
                    what pays him best. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>But you, whenever you turn your attention to your reverses, sit in judgement on
                    your officers, but acquit them whenever in defence they plead their necessities.
                    Hence the outcome is strife and contention among yourselves, some taking this
                    side and some that, while the interests of the state suffer. You conduct your
                    party-politics, Athenians as you used to conduct your taxpaying—by
                        syndicates.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Since the year <date
                            when="0378">378</date> for the payment of the war-tax (<foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">e)isfora/</foreign>), and since <date when="0357"
                            >357</date> for the trierarchy also, the citizens had been divided into
                        a number of <foreign xml:lang="grc">summori/ai</foreign>, such that each
                        comprised an equal fraction of the private wealth of the community. They
                        were also divided into four classes according to property, the first class
                        consisting of the wealthiest citizens, who prepaid the whole required sum
                        into the exchequer and then recovered the money due from the less wealthy
                        classes—a system which produced the abuses remedied by Demosthenes in 340.
                        The richest man in a symmory was called the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >h(gemw/n</foreign> or chairman and had under him an <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">e)pimelhth/s</foreign> or director. The comparison here
                        is only a rough-and-ready one. Each political party in the Assembly has an
                        orator (<foreign xml:lang="grc">h(gemw/n</foreign>) at its head, a favorite
                        general (<foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pimelhth/s</foreign>) whose claims it
                        supports, and a group of backers who applaud (=the 300 who pay).</note> Each
                    syndicate has an orator for chairman, with a general under him and three hundred
                    to do the shouting. The rest of you are attached now to one party and now to
                    another. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>Surely this system must be abandoned. You must be once more your own masters, and
                    must give to all alike the same chance to speak, to counsel, to act. But if you
                    authorize one class of men to issue orders like absolute monarchs, and force
                    another class to equip the galleys and pay the war-tax and serve in the field,
                    while yet a third class has no other public duty than to vote the condemnation
                    of the latter, you will never get anything essential done at the right time.
                    There will always be some class with a grievance, who will fail you, and then it
                    will be your privilege to punish them instead of the enemy.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="31">
                <p>To sum up, I propose that all should contribute equitably, each according to his
                    means, that all should serve in turn until all have taken part in the campaign,
                    that all who wish to address you should have a fair hearing, and that you should
                    adopt the best advice offered, not just what this man or that man is pleased to
                    suggest. If you do this, you will be able to congratulate the speaker at once
                    and yourselves later on, when you find the cause of the nation prospering.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
