<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Third Philippic </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by J. H. Vince, M.A.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1930</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>6/2/92</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserted quotedtext tag around verse</item>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>Many speeches are delivered, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, at almost every meeting of the Assembly, about the
                    wrongs that Philip has been committing, ever since the conclusion of peace, not
                    only against you but also against the other states, and all the speakers would,
                    I am sure, admit in theory, though they do not put it in practice, that the
                    object both of our words and deeds must be to check and chastise his arrogance;
                    yet I perceive that all our interests have been so completely betrayed and
                    sacrificed, that—I am afraid it is an ominous thing to say, but yet the
                    truth—even if all who address you had wanted to propose, and all of you had
                    wanted to pass, measures that were bound to bring our affairs into the worst
                    possible plight, I do not think they could have been in a worse condition than
                    they are today. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>Perhaps, indeed, this condition of our affairs may be attributed to many causes
                    and not just to one or two, but a careful examination will convince you that it
                    is above all due to those who study to win your favour rather than to give you
                    the best advice. Some of them, Athenians, interested in maintaining a system
                    which brings them credit and influence, have no thought for the future [;and
                    therefore think you should have none either];; while others, by blaming and
                    traducing those in authority, make it their sole aim that our city shall
                    concentrate her attention on punishing her own citizens, while Philip shall be
                    free to say and do whatever he pleases.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>But such methods of dealing with public affairs, familiar though they are to you,
                    are the cause of your calamities. I claim for myself, Athenians, that if I utter
                    some home-truths with freedom, I shall not thereby incur your displeasure. For
                    look at it this way. In other matters you think it is so necessary to grant
                    general freedom of speech to everyone in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> that you even allow aliens and slaves to share in the
                    privilege, and many more menials may be observed among you speaking their minds
                    with more liberty than citizens enjoy in other states; but from your
                    deliberations you have banished it utterly. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>Hence the result is that in the Assembly your self-complacency is flattered by
                    hearing none but pleasant speeches, but your policy and your practice are
                    already involving you in the gravest peril. Therefore, if such is your temper
                    now, I have nothing to say; but if, apart from flattery, you are willing to hear
                    something to your advantage, I am ready to speak. For though the state of our
                    affairs is in every way deplorable, and though much has been sacrificed,
                    nevertheless it is possible, if you choose to do your duty, that all may yet be
                    repaired. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>And what I am going to say may perhaps seem a paradox, but it is true. The worst
                    feature of the past is our best hope for the future. What, then, is that
                    feature? It is that your affairs go wrong because you neglect every duty, great
                    or small; since surely, if they were in this plight in spite of your doing all
                    that was required, there would not be even a hope of improvement. But in fact it
                    is your indifference and carelessness that Philip has conquered; your city he
                    has not conquered. Nor have you been defeated—no! you have not even made a move.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>[;If, then, we were all agreed that Philip is at war with <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and is violating the peace, the only
                    task of a speaker would be to come forward and recommend the safest and easiest
                    method of defence; but since some of you are in such a strange mood that, though
                    Philip is seizing cities, and retaining many of your possessions, and inflicting
                    injury on everybody, you tolerate some speakers who repeatedly assert in the
                    Assembly that the real aggressors are certain of ourselves, we must be on our
                    guard and set this matter right. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>For there is grave danger that anyone who proposes and urges that we shall defend
                    ourselves may incur the charge of having provoked the war. I therefore first of
                    all state and define this question—whether it is in our power to discuss the
                    alternative of peace or war.];<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Probably the
                        second clause has no connection with the first, but is an alternative form
                        of the beginning of the next sentence.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>If indeed <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> can remain at peace
                    and if the choice rests with us— to take that point first—I personally feel that
                    we are bound to do so; and if anyone says that we can, I call upon him to move a
                    resolution and to do something and to play us no tricks; but if there is another
                    person concerned, with sword in hand and a mighty force at his back, who imposes
                    on you with the name of peace but himself indulges in acts of war, what is left
                    but to defend ourselves? If you choose to follow his example and profess that
                    you are at peace, I raise no objection. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>But if anyone mistakes for peace an arrangement which will enable Philip, when he
                    has seized everything else, to march upon us, he has taken leave of his senses,
                    and the peace that he talks of is one that you observe towards Philip, but not
                    Philip towards you. That is the advantage which he is purchasing by all his
                    expenditure of money—that he should be at war with you, but that you should not
                    be at war with him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>If we are going to wait for him to acknowledge a state of war with us, we are
                    indeed the simplest of mortals; for even if he marches straight against
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> and the <placeName
                        key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>, he will not admit it, if we may
                    judge from his treatment of the other states. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>For take the case of the Olynthians; when he was five miles from their city, he
                    told them there must be one of two things, either they must cease to reside in
                        <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>, or he in <placeName
                        key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, though on all previous occasions,
                    when accused of hostile intentions, he indignantly sent ambassadors to justify
                    his conduct. Again, when he was marching against the Phocians, he still
                    pretended that they were his allies, and Phocian ambassadors accompanied him on
                    his march, and most people here at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> contended that his passage through <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName><note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">In July 346, when the Phocians were holding <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName> against Philip, the
                        Athenians refused to help them, being misled by Aeschines and Philocrates,
                        who represented that Philip's real hostility was directed against the
                        Thebans. See <bibl n="Dem. 18.35">Dem. 18.35</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 5.10"
                            >Dem. 5.10</bibl>.</note> would be anything but a gain to the Thebans.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>And then again quite lately, after entering <placeName key="tgn,7001399"
                        >Thessaly</placeName> as a friend and ally, he seized Pherae and still
                    retains it; and lastly, he informed those poor wretches, the people of Oreus,
                    that he had sent his soldiers to pay them a visit of sympathy in all goodwill,
                    for he understood that they were suffering from acute internal trouble, and it
                    was the duty of true friends and allies to be at their side on such occasions.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>And do you imagine that, while in the case of those who could have inflicted no
                    harm, though they might perhaps have protected themselves against it, he
                    preferred to deceive them rather than to crush them after due warning, in your
                    case he will give warning of hostilities, especially when you are so eager to be
                    deceived? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>Impossible! For indeed he would be the most fatuous man on earth if, when you,
                    his victims, charge him with no crime, but throw the blame on some of your own
                    fellow-citizens, he should compose your mutual differences and jealousies, and
                    invite you to turn them against himself, and should deprive his own hirelings of
                    the excuses with which they put you off, saying that at any rate it is not
                    Philip who is making war on <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>But, in heaven's name, is there any intelligent man who would let words rather
                    than deeds decide the question who is at peace and who is at war with him?
                    Surely no one. Now it was Philip who at the very start, as soon as peace was
                    concluded, before Diopithes was appointed general, before the force now in the
                        <placeName key="tgn,7017285">Chersonese</placeName> had been dispatched,
                    proceeded to occupy Serrium and Doriscus and expelled from the Fort Serreum and
                    the Sacred Mount the garrison which your own general had posted there. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>Yet what did that move of his mean? For it was peace that he had sworn<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Not strictly true; for Philip had not yet taken
                        the oath, though the Athenians had. Hence Blass wished to read<foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">ei)rh/nh . . . w)mw/moto</foreign>.</note> to observe;
                    and let no one say, “What of all this? How do any of these things concern
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>?” For whether they were
                    small things, or whether they were no concern of yours, may be another question.
                    But religion and justice, whether a man violates them in a small matter or in a
                    great, have the same importance. Tell me now: when he sends mercenaries to the
                        <placeName key="tgn,7017285">Chersonese</placeName>, your claim to which has
                    been recognized by the king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>
                    and by all the Greeks, when he admits that he is helping the Cardians and writes
                    to tell you so, what does he mean? For he says that he is not at war, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>but for my part, so far from admitting that in acting thus he is not observing
                    the peace with you, I assert that when he lays hands on <placeName
                        key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>, sets up tyrannies in <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, makes his way, as now, into <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>, hatches plots in the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>, and carries out all operations
                    with his armed force, he is breaking the peace and making war upon you—unless
                    you are prepared to say that men who bring up the siege-engines are keeping the
                    peace until they actually bring them to bear on the walls. But you will not
                    admit that; for he who makes and devises the means by which I may be captured is
                    at war with me, even though he has not yet hurled a javelin or shot a bolt. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>In what then consists your danger, if anything should happen? In the alienation
                    of the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>, in the control of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> by one who is at war with you, and in
                    the defection of the Peloponnesians to his side. Am I still to say that the man
                    who brings this siege-engine to bear on your city is at peace with you? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>So far from saying that, I date his hostility from the very day when he wiped out
                    the Phocians. I say that you will be wise if you defend yourselves now, but if
                    you let the opportunity pass, you will not be able to act even when you desire
                    to. I so far dissent, Athenians, from all you counsellors that I do not think
                    you ought to trouble yourselves now about the <placeName key="tgn,7010345"
                        >Chersonese</placeName> or <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium"
                        >Byzantium</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>Help them, if you will, guard them from harm [;supply the troops already there
                    with all that they require];, but let your deliberations embrace all the Greek
                    states and the great danger that besets them. But I wish to tell you the grounds
                    for my alarm about our condition, so that if my reasoning is sound, you may
                    adopt it as your own and take forethought for yourselves, even if you refuse to
                    take it for the others also; but if I seem to you a driveler and a dotard,
                    neither now nor at any other time pay any heed to me as if I were in my senses.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>As for the fact, then, that Philip rose to greatness from small and humble
                    beginnings, that the Greek states are mutually disloyal and factious, and that
                    the increase of Philip's power in the past was a far greater miracle than the
                    completion of his conquests now that he has already gained so much, these and
                    all such topics on which I might expatiate, I will pass over in silence. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>I observe, however, that all men, and you first of all, have conceded to him
                    something which has been the occasion of every war that the Greeks have ever
                    waged. And what is that? The power of doing what he likes, of calmly plundering
                    and stripping the Greeks one by one, and of attacking their cities and reducing
                    them to slavery. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>Yet your hegemony in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> lasted
                    seventy-five years, that of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>
                    twenty-nine, and in these later times <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName> too gained some sort of authority after the battle of
                    Leuctra. But neither to you nor to the Thebans nor to the Lacedaemonians did the
                    Greeks ever yet, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    concede the right of unrestricted action, or anything like it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>On the contrary, when you, or rather the Athenians of that day, were thought to
                    be showing a want of consideration in dealing with others, all felt it their
                    duty, even those who had no grievance against them, to go to war in support of
                    those who had been injured; and again, when the Lacedaemonians had risen to
                    power and succeeded to your position of supremacy, and when they set to work to
                    encroach on others and interfered unduly with the established order of things,
                    all the Greeks were up in arms, even those who had no grievance of their own.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>Why need I refer to the other states? Nay, we ourselves and the Lacedaemonians,
                    though at the outset we could not have specified any wrong at each other's
                    hands, thought it our duty to fight on account of wrongs which we saw the other
                    states suffering. Yet all the faults committed by the Lacedaemonians in those
                    thirty years, and by our ancestors in their seventy years of supremacy, are
                    fewer, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, than the
                    wrongs which Philip has done to the Greeks in the thirteen incomplete years in
                    which he has been coming to the top—or rather, they are not a fraction of them.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>[;And this is easily proved by a short calculation.]; I pass over <placeName
                        key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="perseus,Methone">Methone</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="perseus,Apollonia">Apollonia</placeName> and the two and thirty cities
                    in or near <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>, all of which Philip
                    has destroyed so ruthlessly that a traveler would find it hard to say whether
                    they had ever been inhabited. I say nothing of the destruction of the important
                    nation of the Phocians. But how stands the case of the Thessalians? Has he not
                    robbed them of their free constitutions and of their very cities, setting up
                    tetrarchies in order to enslave them, not city by city, but tribe by tribe? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>Are not tyrannies already established in <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                        >Euboea</placeName>, an island, remember, not far from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>? Does he not write explicitly in his letters, “I am at
                    peace with those who are willing to obey me”? And he does not merely write this
                    without putting it into practice; but he is off to the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>, just as before he hurried to
                        <placeName key="perseus,Ambracia">Ambracia</placeName>; in the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> he occupies the important city of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName>; only the other day he
                    intrigued against the Megarians. Neither the Greek nor the barbarian world is
                    big enough for the fellow's ambition. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>And we Greeks see and hear all this, and yet we do not send embassies to one
                    another and express our indignation. We are in such a miserable position, we
                    have so entrenched ourselves in our different cities, that to this very day we
                    can do nothing that our interest or our duty demands; we cannot combine, we
                    cannot take any common pledge of help or friendship; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>but we idly watch the growing power of this man, each bent (or so it seems to me)
                    on profiting by the interval afforded by another's ruin, taking not a thought,
                    making not an effort for the salvation of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName>. For that Philip, like the recurrence or attack of a
                    fever or some other disease, is threatening even those who think themselves out
                    of reach, of that not one of you is ignorant. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>Ay, and you know this also, that the wrongs which the Greeks suffered from the
                    Lacedaemonians or from us, they suffered at all events at the hands of true-born
                    sons of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and they might have
                    been regarded as the acts of a legitimate son, born to great possessions, who
                    should be guilty of some fault or error in the management of his estate: so far
                    he would deserve blame and reproach, yet it could not be said that it was not
                    one of the blood, not the lawful heir who was acting thus. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="31">
                <p>But if some slave or superstitious bastard had wasted and squandered what he had
                    no right to, heavens! how much more monstrous and exasperating all would have
                    called it! Yet they have no such qualms about Philip and his present conduct,
                    though he is not only no Greek, nor related to the Greeks, but not even a
                    barbarian from any place that can be named with honor, but a pestilent knave
                    from <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, whence it was never yet
                    possible to buy a decent slave. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="32">
                <p>Yet what is wanting to crown his insolence? Not content with the destruction of
                    cities, is he not organizing the Pythian games, the common festival of the
                    Greeks, and if he cannot be present in person, sending his menials to act as
                    stewards? [;Is he not master of <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                        >Thermopylae</placeName> and the passes into <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName>, holding those places with his garrisons and his
                    mercenaries? Has he not the right of precedence at the Oracle, ousting us and
                    the Thessalians and the Dorians and the rest of the Amphictyons from a privilege
                    which not even all Greek states can claim?]; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="33">
                <p>Does he not dictate to the Thessalians their form of government? Does he not send
                    mercenaries, some to Porthmus to expel the Eretrian democracy, others to Oreus
                    to set up the tyranny of Philistides? Yet the Greeks see all this and suffer it.
                    They seem to watch him just as they would watch a hailstorm, each praying that
                    it may not come their way, but none making any effort to stay its course. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="34">
                <p>And it is not only his outrages on <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName> that go unavenged, but even the wrongs which each
                    suffers separately. For nothing can go beyond that. Are not the Corinthians hit
                    by his invasion of <placeName key="perseus,Ambracia">Ambracia</placeName> and
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002712">Leucas</placeName>? The Achaeans by his vow to
                    transfer <placeName key="tgn,7011174">Naupactus</placeName> to the Aetolians?
                    The Thebans by his theft of <placeName key="perseus,Echinus"
                    >Echinus</placeName>? And is he not marching even now against his<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This translation is justified by <bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.87">Dem. 18.87</bibl>. Others “their allies,” since the
                        Byzantines are known to have helped the Thebans with money in the Sacred
                        War. (Cauer, <title>Del. Inscr. Gr.</title> 353.)</note> allies the
                    Byzantines? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="35">
                <p>Of our own possessions, not to mention other places, is he not holding Cardia,
                    the greatest city in the <placeName key="tgn,7017285">Chersonese</placeName>? In
                    spite of such treatment, we hesitate one and all, we play the coward, we keep an
                    eye on our neighbors, distrusting one another rather than our common foe. Yet if
                    he treats us all with such brutality, what do you think he will do when he has
                    got each of us separately into his clutches? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="36">
                <p>What then is the cause of this? For not without reason, not without just cause,
                    the Greeks of old were as eager for freedom as their descendants today are for
                    slavery. There was something, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, something which animated the mass of the Greeks but
                    which is lacking now, something which triumphed over the wealth of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>, which upheld the liberties of
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, which never lost a single
                    battle by sea or land, something the decay of which has ruined everything and
                    brought our affairs to a state of chaos. And what was that? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="37">
                <p>[;It was nothing recondite or subtle, but simply that]; men who took bribes from
                    those who wished to rule <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> or ruin
                    her, were hated by all, and it was the greatest calamity to be convicted of
                    receiving a bribe, and such a man was punished with the utmost severity [;and no
                    intercession, no pardon was allowed];. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="38">
                <p>At each crisis, therefore, the opportunity for action, with which fortune often
                    equips the careless against the vigilant [;and those who shrink from deeds
                    against those who fulfil their duties];, could not be bought at a price from our
                    politicians or our generals; no, nor our mutual concord, nor our distrust of
                    tyrants and barbarians, nor, in a word, any such advantage. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="39">
                <p>Now, however, all these things have been sold in open market, and in place of
                    them we have imported vices which have infected <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName> with a mortal sickness. And what are those vices? Envy
                    of the man who has secured his gains; contempt for him who confesses; [;pardon
                    for those who are convicted;]; hatred for him who censures such dealings; and
                    every other vice that goes hand in hand with corruption. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="40">
                <p>For war-galleys, men in abundance, money and material without stint, everything
                    by which one might gauge the strength of our cities, these we as a body possess
                    today in number and quantity far beyond the Greeks of former times. But all our
                    resources are rendered useless, powerless, worthless by these traffickers. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="41">
                <p>That this is so, you surely see for yourselves with regard to the present, and
                    you need no evidence of mine, but that it was the opposite in the days of old I
                    will prove, not in my own words, but by the written record of your ancestors,
                    which they engraved on a bronze pillar and set up in the Acropolis. [;It was not
                    for their own use, for without these documents their instinct was right; but it
                    was that you might have these examples to remind you that such cases ought to be
                    regarded seriously.]; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="42">
                <p>“Arthmius of Zelea,” it says, “son of Pythonax, outlaw and enemy of the people of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and of their allies,
                    himself and his family.” Then is recorded the reason for this punishment:
                    “because he conveyed the gold of the Medes to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
                        >Peloponnese</placeName>.” So runs the inscription. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="43">
                <p>I earnestly implore you to consider what was the intention of the Athenians who
                    did this thing, or what was their proud claim. They proscribed as their enemy
                    and the enemy of their allies, disfranchising him and his family, a man of
                    Zelea, one Arthmius, a slave of the Great King (for Zelea is in <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>), because in the service of his master he
                    conveyed gold, not to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> but to
                    the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The occasion of this decree, to which Demosthenes refers in
                            <bibl n="Dem. 19.271">Dem. 19.271</bibl>, is not known. According to
                            <bibl n="Plut. Them. 6">Plut. Them. 6</bibl> it was Themistocles who
                        proposed it; but a schol. on Aristides names Cimon. The date in the former
                        case would be before 471; in the latter it would be after 457, and may be
                        connected with the mission of Megabazus to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
                            >Sparta</placeName> in 455, mentioned by <bibl n="Thuc. 1.109">Thuc.
                            1.109</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="44">
                <p>This was not outlawry as commonly understood; for what mattered it to a native of
                    Zelea if he was to be debarred from a share in the common rights of Athenian
                    citizens? But the statutes relating to murder provide for cases where
                    prosecution for murder is not allowed [;but where it is a righteous act to slay
                    the murderer];; “and he shall die an outlaw,” says the legislator. This simply
                    means that anyone slaying a member of Arthmius's family would be free from
                    blood-guilt. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="45">
                <p>So our ancestors thought that they were bound to consider the welfare of all
                    Greeks, for except on that assumption bribery and corruption in the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> would be no concern of theirs; and
                    in chastising and punishing all whom they detected, they went so far as to set
                    the offenders' names on a pillar. The natural result was that the Greek power
                    was dreaded by the barbarian, not the barbarian by the Greeks. But that is no
                    longer so. For that is not your attitude towards these and other offences. What
                    then is your attitude? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="46">
                <p>[;You know it yourselves. For why should you bear the whole blame, when all the
                    other Greeks are just as bad as you? That is why I assert that the present
                    crisis calls for earnest zeal and wise counsel. What counsel?];<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The last two words seem pointless. Perhaps <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">ti/nos</foreign>; is the attempt of a scribe to join the
                        longer to the shorter version.</note> Do you want me to tell you, and will
                    you promise not to be angry?<quote type="Record">
                        <title>[;He reads </title>
                    </quote><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A frank description of the Athenian
                        attitude, which should follow here, has dropped out, and the lemma, which is
                        found in S and other good MSS., seems to be a poor attempt to fill the gap.
                        It is difficult to imagine any official document that would be of use to the
                        orator here.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="47">
                <p>Now there is a foolish argument advanced by those who want to reassure the
                    citizens. Philip, they say, after all is not yet what the Lacedaemonians were;
                    they were masters of every sea and land; they enjoyed the alliance of the king
                    of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>; nothing could stand against
                    them: and yet our city defended itself even against them and was not
                    overwhelmed. But for my own part, while practically all the arts have made a
                    great advance and we are living today in a very different world from the old
                    one, I consider that nothing has been more revolutionized and improved than the
                    art of war. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="48">
                <p>For in the first place I am informed that in those days the Lacedaemonians, like
                    everyone else, would spend the four or five months of the summer “season” in
                    invading and laying waste the enemy's territory with heavy infantry and levies
                    of citizens, and would then retire home again; and they were so old-fashioned,
                    or rather such good citizens,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Greek means
                        true to the spirit of a free, constitutional state. Aristotle describes
                            the<foreign xml:lang="grc">politiko\n plh=qos</foreign>as one which is
                        “naturally warlike and qualified to rule or be ruled according to laws which
                        distribute offices by merit” (<bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 3.1288a">Aristot. Pol.
                            3.17.4</bibl>).</note> that they never used money to buy an advantage
                    from anyone, but their fighting was of the fair and open kind. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="49">
                <p>But now you must surely see that most disasters are due to traitors, and none are
                    the result of a regular pitched battle. On the other hand you hear of Philip
                    marching unchecked, not because he leads a phalanx of heavy infantry, but
                    because he is accompanied by skirmishers, cavalry, archers, mercenaries, and
                    similar troops. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="50">
                <p>When, relying on this force, he attacks some people that is at variance with
                    itself, and when through distrust no one goes forth to fight for his country,
                    then he brings up his artillery and lays siege. I need hardly tell you that he
                    makes no difference between summer and winter and has no season set apart for
                    inaction. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="51">
                <p>Since, however, you all know this, you must take it into account and not let the
                    war pass into your own country; you must not invite catastrophe through keeping
                    your eyes fixed on the simple strategy of your old war with the Lacedaemonians,
                    but arrange your political affairs and your military preparations so that your
                    line of defence may be as far away from <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> as possible, give him no chance of stirring from his
                    base, and never come to close grips with him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="52">
                <p>For so far as a campaign is concerned, provided, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, we are willing to do what is
                    necessary, we have many natural advantages, such as the nature of his territory,
                    much of which may be harried and devastated, and countless others; but for a
                    pitched battle he is in better training than we are. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="53">
                <p>But it is not enough to adopt these suggestions, nor even to oppose him with
                    active military measures, but both from calculation and on principle you must
                    show your hatred of those who speak publicly on his behalf; and you must reflect
                    that it is impossible to defeat the enemies of our city until you have chastised
                    those who within our very walls make themselves their servants. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="54">
                <p>And that, as all Heaven is my witness, you will never be able to do; but you have
                    reached such a height of folly or of madness or—I know not what to call it, for
                    this fear too has often haunted me, that some demon is driving you to your doom,
                    that from love of calumny or envy or ribaldry, or whatever your motive may be,
                    you clamor for a speech from these hirelings, some of whom would not even
                    disclaim that title, and you derive amusement from their vituperations. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="55">
                <p>This is serious enough, but there is worse to follow; for you have granted to
                    these men more security for the pursuance of their policy than to your own
                    defenders. Yet mark what troubles are in store for those who lend an ear to such
                    counsellors. I will mention some facts which will be familiar to you all. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="56">
                <p>At <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> there were two parties
                    in the state: Philip's men, entirely subservient to him, and the patriots,
                    striving to preserve the freedom of their countrymen. Which, pray, ruined their
                    country? Which betrayed the cavalry, whose betrayal sealed the doom of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>? The partisans of
                    Philip; the men who, when the city was still standing, tried to defame and
                    slander the patriotic statesmen, until the Olynthian democracy was actually
                    induced to expel Apollonides.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The democratic
                        leader, afterwards honored with the citizenship of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="57">
                <p>Now it was not at <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> only
                    that this habit produced every kind of evil result; but at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Eretria">Eretria</placeName>, when the democrats, ridding
                    themselves of Plutarchus and his mercenaries, held the city together with
                    Porthmus, some of them were for handing the government over to you, others to
                    Philip. The latter on most points, or rather on all, gained the ear of the
                    sorely tried and ill-starred Eretrians, and at last persuaded them to expel
                    their real champions. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="58">
                <p>For of course Philip, whom they fancied their ally, sent Hipponicus with a
                    thousand mercenaries, razed the walls of Porthmus, and set up three tyrants,
                    Hipparchus, Automedon, and Clitarchus. Twice since then they have tried to
                    deliver themselves, and twice he has driven them from their homes [;on the first
                    occasion sending Eurylochus with his mercenaries, on the second Parmenio];. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="59">
                <p>And what need is there to mention most of the cases? But at Oreus Philistides,
                    Menippus, Socrates, Thoas, and Agapaeus, the very men who now control the city,
                    were, as everyone knew, Philip's agents, but Euphraeus, a man who once resided
                    here at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, was working for the
                    freedom and emancipation of his countrymen. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="60">
                <p>It would be a long story to tell you how this man was repeatedly outraged and
                    insulted by the people; but a year before the capture of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Eretria">Eretria</placeName>, detecting the machinations of
                    Philistides and his party, he denounced him as a traitor. Then a number of
                    fellows banded together, with Philip for their paymaster and managing director,
                    and dragged Euphraeus off to prison for setting the city in an uproar. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="61">
                <p>When the democrats of Oreus saw this, instead of rescuing him and knocking the
                    others on the head, they showed no resentment against them and gloated over
                    Euphraeus, saying that he deserved all he had got. Then having all the liberty
                    of action they desired, they intrigued for the capture of the city and prepared
                    to carry out their plot, while any of the common folk who saw what they were at
                    were terrorized into silence, having the fate of Euphraeus before their eyes.
                    And so abject was their condition that, with this danger looming ahead, no one
                    dared to breathe a syllable until the enemy, having completed their
                    preparations, were approaching the gates; and then some were for defence, the
                    others for surrender. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="62">
                <p>But since that base and shameful capture of the city, the latter have been its
                    rulers and tyrants; those who sheltered them before, and had been ready to take
                    any measures against Euphraeus, were rewarded with banishment or death; and the
                    noble Euphraeus slew himself, giving thus a practical proof of the honesty and
                    disinterested patriotism of his opposition to Philip. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="63">
                <p>Perhaps you wonder why the people of <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                        >Olynthus</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Eretria"
                        >Eretria</placeName> and Oreus were more favorably inclined to Philip's
                    advocates than to their own. The explanation is the same as at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that the patriots, however much
                    they desire it, cannot sometimes say anything agreeable, for they are obliged to
                    consider the safety of the state; but the others by their very efforts to be
                    agreeable are playing into Philip's hands. The patriots demanded a war-subsidy,
                    the others denied its necessity; the patriots bade them fight on and mistrust
                    Philip, the others bade them keep the peace, until they fell into the snare.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="64">
                <p>Not to go into particulars, it is the same tale everywhere, one party speaking to
                    please their audience, the other giving advice that would have ensured their
                    safety. But at the last there were many things that the people were induced to
                    concede, not as before for their own gratification nor through ignorance, but
                    gradually yielding because they thought that their discomfiture was inevitable
                    and complete. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="65">
                <p>And, by Heaven, that is what I certainly fear will be your experience, when you
                    count your chances and discover that there is nothing left for you to do. And
                    yet I pray, Athenians, that such may not be the issue of events. Better to die a
                    thousand times than pay court to Philip [;and abandon any of your loyal
                    counsellors.]; A fine return the people of Oreus have gained for handing
                    themselves over to Philip's friends and rejecting Euphraeus! </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="66">
                <p>A fine return the democrats of <placeName key="perseus,Eretria"
                        >Eretria</placeName> have gained for spurning your embassy and capitulating
                    to Clitarchus! They are slaves, doomed to the whipping-post and the scaffold. A
                    fine clemency he showed to the Olynthians, who voted Lasthenes their master of
                    the horse and banished Apollonides! </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="67">
                <p>It is folly and cowardice to cherish such hopes, to follow ill counsel and refuse
                    to perform any fraction of your duties, to lend an ear to the advocates of your
                    enemies and imagine that your city is so great that no conceivable danger can
                    befall it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="68">
                <p>Ay, and a disgrace too it is to have to say, when all is over, “Why! who would
                    have thought it? For of course we ought to have done this or that, and not so
                    and so.” Many things could be named by the Olynthians today, which would have
                    saved them from destruction if only they had then foreseen them. Many could be
                    named by the Orites, many by the Phocians, many by every ruined city. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="69">
                <p>But of what use to them is that? While the vessel is safe, whether it be a large
                    or a small one, then is the time for sailor and helmsman arid everyone in his
                    turn to show his zeal and to take care that it is not capsized by anyone's
                    malice or inadvertence; but when the sea has overwhelmed it, zeal is useless.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="70">
                <p>So we too, Athenians, as long as we are safe, blessed with a very great city,
                    ample advantages, and the fairest repute—what are we to do? Perhaps some of my
                    hearers have long been eager to ask that question. I solemnly promise that I
                    will answer it and will also move a resolution, for which you can vote if so
                    disposed. To begin with ourselves, we must make provision for our defence, I
                    mean with war-galleys, funds, and men; for even if all other states succumb to
                    slavery, we surely must fight the battle of liberty. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="71">
                <p>Then having completed all these preparations and made our purpose clear, we must
                    lose no time in calling upon the other Greeks, and we must inform them by
                    sending ambassadors [;in every direction, to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
                        >Peloponnese</placeName>, to <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                    >Rhodes</placeName>, to <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>, to the
                    Great King—for even his interests are not unaffected if we prevent Philip from
                    subduing the whole country—]; so that if you win them over, you may have someone
                    to share your dangers and your expenses when the time comes, or if not, that you
                    may at least delay the course of events. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="72">
                <p>For since the war is against an individual and not against the might of an
                    organized community, even delay is not without its use; nor were those embassies
                    useless which you sent round the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
                        >Peloponnese</placeName> last year to denounce Philip, when I and our good
                    friend Polyeuctus here and Hegesippus and the rest went from city to city and
                    succeeded in checking him, so that he never invaded <placeName
                        key="perseus,Ambracia">Ambracia</placeName> nor even started against the
                        <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="73">
                <p>I do not, however, suggest that you should invite the rest, unless you are ready
                    to do for yourselves what is necessary; for it would be futile to abandon our
                    own interests and pretend that we are protecting those of others, or to overlook
                    the present dangers and alarm our neighbors with dangers to come. That is not my
                    meaning. But I do contend that we must send supplies to the forces in the
                        <placeName key="tgn,7017285">Chersonese</placeName> and satisfy all their
                    demands, and while we make preparation ourselves, we must summon, collect,
                    instruct, and exhort the rest of the Greeks. That is the duty of a city with a
                    reputation such as yours enjoys. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="74">
                <p>But if you imagine that <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> will be
                    saved by Chalcidians or Megarians, while you run away from the task, you are
                    wrong. For they may think themselves lucky if they can save themselves
                    separately. But this is a task for you; it was for you that your ancestors won
                    this proud privilege and bequeathed it to you at great and manifold risk. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="75">
                <p>But if every man sits idle, consulting his own pleasure and careful to avoid his
                    own duty, not only will he find no one to do it for him, but I fear that those
                    duties that we wish to shirk may all be forced upon us at once. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="76">
                <p>These are my views and these are my proposals, and if they are carried out, I
                    believe that even now we may retrieve our fortunes. If anyone has anything
                    better to propose, let him speak and advise. But whatever you decide, I pray
                    heaven it may be to your advantage.</p>
            </div>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
