<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Disowned</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:1lg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1936</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianhar05luciuoft/page/476/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202111?urlappend=%3Bseq=488">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.5.p.477"/>
<head>Disowned<note xml:lang="eng"><p>The fictitious case which underlies this declamation is
outlined in the argument that precedes the text. An earlier
treatment of the same theme is to be found in the Controversiae
of Seneca Rhetor (IV, 5). In the Lucianic piece, the speaker’s
references to his stepmother constitute a notable example of
sustained irony as a rhetorical device.1</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="0"><p>


A son who had been disowned studied medicine. When his
father became insane and had been given up by the other
doctors, he cured him by administering a remedy, and was again
received into the family. After that, he was ordered to
cure his stepmother, who was insane, and as he refused to do so,
he is now being disowned again.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.5.p.477.n.1"><p>The words in italics are supplied to give the approximate sense of those lost in the Greek text. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1">
    <p>There is nothing novel or surprising, gentlemen of
the jury, in my father’s present course, and this is
not the first time that he has displayed such anger ;
on the contrary, he keeps this law always in readiness
and resorts to this court by habit.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.5.p.477.n.2"><p>The law permitting a father to disown his son, and the court before which his complaint had to be presented. No certain case of disownment at Athens is known; but Dionysius of Halicarnassus (Arch., II, 26) says that provisions for it were included in the codes of Solon, Pittacus, and Charondas, there is one in Plato’s Laws (XI, 928D; it involves a family council), and Egyptian documents attest it. P. M. Meyer, in publishing one of them (Juristische Papyri, No. XI) cites Cod. Just., VIII, 46, 6: abdicatio, quae Graeco more ad alienandos liberos usurpatur et apoceryxis dicebatur, Romanis legibus non comprobatur. </p></note>, There is, however,
something of novelty in my present plight, in that I
am under no personal charge, but am in jeopardy of
punishment on behalf of my profession because it
cannot in every particular obey his behests. But what
could be more absurd than to give treatment under
orders, in accordance, not with the powers of the profession, but with the desires of my father? I could
wish, to be sure, that medical science had a remedy




<pb n="v.5.p.479"/>

of such sort that it could check not only insanity
but unjust anger, in order that I might cure my
father of this disorder also. As things are, his
madness has been completely assuaged, but his
anger is growing worse, and (what is hardest of all)
he is sane to everyone else and insane towards me
alone, his physician. You see, therefore, what fee
I receive for my attendance—I am disowned by him
once more and put away from my family a second
time, as if I had been taken back for a brief space
merely that I might be more disgraced by being
turned out of the household repeatedly.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
For my part, in cases which can be cured I do not
wait to be summoned; on the previous occasion, for
instance, I came to his relief uncalled. But when a
case is perfectly desperate, I am unwilling even to
essay it. And in respect to this woman I am with
good reason even less venturesome, since I take into
consideration how I should be treated by my father
if I were to fail, when without having so much as begun treating her I am disowned. I am indeed
pained, gentlemen of the jury, at my stepmother’s
serious condition (for she was a good woman), at
my father’s distress on her account, and most of all
at my own apparent disobedience and real inabilit
to do the'service which is enjoined upon me, bot
because of the extraordinary violence of the illness
and the ineffectiveness of the art of healing. I do
not think, however, that it is just to disown a man
who declines at the outset to promise what he
cannot perform.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
The charges on which he disowned me before
can be readily understood from the present situation.
To those charges I have made a sufficient answer, I

<pb n="v.5.p.481"/>

think, by my subsequent life, and these accusations
which he now brings I shall dispose of to the best of
my ability; but first I shall tell you a little about my
position.</p>

<p>
I who am so difficult and disobedient, who so disgrace my father and act so unworthily of my family,
on the former occasion thought it behoved me to
make little opposition to him when he was making
all that clamour and straining his lungs. On leaving
the house, I expected to have a grand jury and a
true verdict in my subsequent life, with its disclosure
that I was at a very great remove from those offences
with which I had been charged by my father, that I
had devoted myself to the noblest of pursuits, and
that I was frequenting the best company. I foresaw,
too, something like this, suspecting even then that it
indicated no great sanity in a father to be angry
unjustly and to concoct false accusations against a
son. And there were those who held all that to be
the beginning of madness, the hostile demonstration
and skirmish-fire of the disease that was soon to
fall upon him—the insensate hatred, the cruel law,
the ready abusiveness, the grim tribunal, the clamour,
the anger, and in general the atrabiliousness which
impregnated the whole proceedings. Therefore I
expected that perhaps I should some day need a
knowledge of medicine.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
I went abroad, then, studied with the most famous
physicians in foreign parts, and by dint of great
labour and insistent zeal thoroughly mastered the
art. On my return I found my father by then defin-


<pb n="v.5.p.483"/>

itively insane and given up by the local physicians, who
had not profound insight and could not accurately distinguish different forms of disease. Yet I did as was
natural for an uprigne son to do, neither cherishing
a grudge because of my being disowned, nor waiting
to be sent after; for I had no fault to find with him
personally, but all those offences were of extraneous
origin and, as I have said already, peculiar to the
disease. So I came without being called, but did
not begin the treatment at once. It is not our
custom to do so, and the art of medicine does not recommend that course; we are taught first of all to
observe whether the disease is curable or irremediable
and beyond the limits of medical skill. Then, if it
is manageable, we put our hands to it and make
every effort to save the patient; but if we see that
the ailment already has the upper hand and is victorious, we do not touch it at all, observing an ancient
law of the progenitors of the art of medicine, who
say that one must not lay hand to those who are
overmastered.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.5.p.483.n.1"><p>Hippocrates, de Arte, 3. </p></note></p>

<p>
Since I saw that my father was still within hope
and his ailment not beyond professional skill, after
long observation and accurate investigation of all
details I set my hand to it at last and compounded
my remedy confidently, although many of those
present were suspicious of my prescription, critical of
my treatment of the case, and ready to bring charges
against me.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
My stepmother was present also,
panic-stricken and distrustful, not because she hated
me but because she was fearful and well aware that
he was in a bad way; she knew it because she alone
associated exclusively with him and lived side by


<pb n="v.5.p.485"/>

side with his disorder. Nevertheless, without any
timidity (for I knew that the symptoms would not
cheat me or betray the profession) I applied the
treatment at the nick of time for the attempt,
although some of my friends advised me not to be
overbold for fear that failure bring upon me a more
serious imputation of avenging myself upon my father
with poison, having conceived a grudge against him
for what I had suffered at his hands.
</p>

<p>To sum it up, he became well at once, recovered
his sanity, and was thoroughly in command of his
faculties. Those present were amazed, and my
stepmother was full of praise, making it plain to all
that she was delighted with my success and his
sanity. And as for my father here (for I am able to
testify on his behalf) without delay and without
asking any advice in this matter, as soon as he had
heard the whole story from those who were there, he
annulled the disownment and made me his son once
more, calling me his saviour and benefactor, admitting
that he had tested me thoroughly, and defending
himself for his former charges. This event gave joy
to many, the men of rectitude who were there, and
pain to those who preferred the disownment of a
son to his resumption. I saw, anyhow, at the time
that not all were equally pleased with the affair, but
at once one or another showed changed colour, disturbed eyes, and an angry face, such as comes from
jealousy and hatred.</p>

<p>
Well, we were rejoicing and making merry, as
was natural, since we had regained each other,
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
when
after a short time my stepmother suddenly began
to be afflicted, gentlemen of the jury, with an ailment
which was severe and unusual. I observed the

<pb n="v.5.p.487"/>

affliction constantly from the moment when it began,
Her form of insanity was not simple or superficial ;
some trouble of long ago, lurking in the soul, had
broken out and won its way into the open. We have,
of course, many symptoms of incurable madness,
but in the case of this woman I have observed one
that is novel; towards everyone else she is very
civil and gentle, and in their presence the disease is
peaceful, but if she sees any physician and simply
hears that he is one, she is beyond all things exasperated against him, and this in itself is proof that
her condition is bad and incurable.</p>

<p>
Seeing this, I was distressed and pitied the woman,
who was worthy of it and unfortunate beyond her
deserts.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
My father, in his inexperience (for he
does not know either the origin of the trouble that
holds her in its grip, or its cause, or the extent of the
infirmity), bade me treat her and give her the same
medicine; for he thinks that madness has but one
form, that the ailment is simple, and that her illness
is identical with his, permitting the same treatment.
When I say what is as true as true can be, that it is
impossible to save his wife and confess that I am
worsted by the disorder, he is indignant and angry,
and says that I am deliberately shirking and giving
the woman up, thus making the ineffectiveness of
the art of medicine a reproach against me. He does,
indeed, what is habitually done by people who are
offended; all are angry at those who speak the
truth in frankness. In spite of that, I shall plead to
the best of my ability against him, not only for myself
but for my art.


<pb n="v.5.p.489"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
First, I shall begin with the law under which he
wishes to disown me, in order that he may discover
that his power is now no longer what it was before.
The lawgiver, father,has not permitted all to exercise
the privilege of disownment, or upon all sons, or as
often as they choose, or upon all manner of grounds.
On the contrary, just as he has conceded to fathers
the right to exercise such anger, just so he has made
provision in behalf of sons, that they may not suffer it
unjustly ; and for that reason he has not allowed the
punishment to be inflicted freely or without trial,
but has ordered men to be summoned to court and
empanelled as investigators who will not be influenced
either by anger or by malice in determining what is
just. For he knew that many people on many
occasions are obsessed by senseless reasons for
anger; that one believes a malicious falsehood, while
another relies upon a servant or an unfriendly female.
It was not his idea, therefore, that the thing should
go untried or that sons should at once lose their case
by default. Water is measured,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.5.p.489.n.1"><p>Time for speaking is apportioned to each side by the waterclock (κλέψυδρα). </p></note> a hearing is given,
and nothing is left uninvestigated.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
Accordingly, since it is within your powers, since
my father controls only the charge, and you who sit
in judgement control the decision whether his accusation is reasonable, do not yet consider his specific
allegation against me and the ground of his present
indignation, but first examine that other point,
whether he should still be allowed to disown a son
when, after once for all disowning him, using the
privilege that derives from the law and exercising to
the full this paternal suzerainty, he has subsequently


<pb n="v.5.p.491"/>

taken him back again and annulled the disownment.
I say that such a thing is most unjust—for punishments, precisely in the case of children, to be interminable, their condemnations numerous, and their
fear eternal; for the law at one moment to share
the prosecutor’s anger, only soon afterward to relax,
and then again to be as severe as before; in a word,
for justice to be altered this way and that to conform
to the momentary opinion of fathers. No, the first
time it is right to give the parent free rein, to share
his anger with him, to make him arbiter of the
punishment; but if, once for all, he expends his
privilege, makes full use of the law, satisfies his anger,
and then afterwards takes back his son, persuaded
that he deserves it, he must abide by it, and not keep
shifting, changing his mind, and altering his decision.
</p>

<p>
When that son was born there was no way, of
course, to ascertain whether he would turn out to be
bad or good, and on that account the privilege of
repudiating children who are unworthy of their
family has been allowed to their parents, since they
determined to bring them up at a time when they
were unaware ofthis.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
When, however, under no constraint but able to do as he pleases, a man himself,
of his own motion and after putting his son to
the test, takes him back, what pretext for change of
mind remains, or what further recourse to the law?
The legislator would say to you: “If he was bad and
deserved to be disowned, what made you ask him
back? Why did you readmit him to your house?
Why did you nullify the law? You were free and
at liberty not to do this. Surely it cannot be conceded that you should make sport of the laws and that


<pb n="v.5.p.493"/>

the courts should be convened to suit your changes
of mind, that the laws should be relaxed one moment
and enforced the next and the jurors sit to register,
or rather to execute, your decisions, inflicting a
penalty at one time, bringing you together at another,
as often as it shall please you. You begat him
once for all, you brought him up once for all, and
have once for all, in return for this, the power to
disown him, and then only if you are held to be
doing it justly. This persistence, this interminability, this prodigious casualness is beyond the legal
right of a father.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
In Heaven’s name, gentlemen of the jury, do not
permit him, once he has effected the reinstatement
of his own free will, set aside the decision of the
former court, and nullified his anger, to reinvoke the
same penalty and to recur to the right of a father
when its term by now is over and done with, inoperative in his case alone because it is already used
up. You perceive, surely, that in all courts where
jurors are drawn by lot, if a man thinks that the
verdict is unjust, the law allows him to appeal from
them to another tribunal; but if people have themselves of their own accord agreed upon jurors and
willingly committed the arbitrament to them, that is
not then the case. For there was no need to consult
them at all; but if a man has selected them of his own
choice, he ought to remain content with their decision.
So it is with you: a son who seemed to you unworthy
of his lineage need never have been taken back, but
one whom you have pronounced good and taken


<pb n="v.5.p.495"/>

back again you will not thereafter be able to disown ;
for you yourself have borne witness that he does not
deserve to undergo this again, and have acknowledged
that he is good. It is fitting, therefore, that his
reinstatement should be irrevocable and the reconciliation binding after deliberation so oft-repeated,
and two sessions of court, one (the first) in which
you repudiated him, the other (your own) when you
changed your mind and undid it. By setting aside
the earlier decision you have guaranteed your later
determination. Abide, then, by your latest purpose
and maintain your own verdict; you must be a
father, for that is what you decided, what you
approved, what you ratified.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
Even if I were not your own son, but adopted, and
you wished to disown me, I should not think you
could; for what it was possible not to do at all, it is
unjust to undo once it has taken place. But when
a son has been got by birth, and then again by choice
and decision, how is it reasonable to put him away
again and deprive him repeatedly of that single
relationship? If I happened to be a slave, and at
first, thinking me vicious, you had put me in irons,
but on becoming convinced that I was not a wrongdoer you had let me go and set me free, would it be
in your power, if you became angry on occasion, to
bring me back into the same condition of slavery? By
no means, for the laws require that such pacts should
be permanent and under all circumstances valid.</p>

<p>
Upon the point that it is no longer in his power to
disown one whom he has once disowned and then of
his own accord taken back I still have much to say ;
nevertheless, I shall make an end.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
But consider
what manner of man he will now be disowning. I do

<pb n="v.5.p.497"/>

not mean that then I was but a layman, whereas
now I am a physician, for my profession would avail
me nothing in this respect. Nor that then I was
young, whereas now I am well on in years and
derive from my age the right to have it believed
that I would do no wrong; for that too is perhaps
trivial. But at that time, even if he had suffered
no wrong, as I should maintain, yet he had received
no benefit from me when he excluded me from the
house ; whereas now I have recently been his saviour
and benefactor. What could be more ungrateful
than that, after he had been saved through me and
had escaped so great a danger, he should at once
make return in this way, taking no account of that
cure; nay, should so easily forget and try to drive
into loneliness a man who, when he might justly
have exulted over those who had unjustly cast
him out, not only had borne him no grudge but
actually had saved his life and made him sound of
mind?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
It is no trifling or commonplace benefit, gentlemen
of the jury, that I have conferred upon him; and
yet I am accounted worthy of treatment like this.
Although he himself does not know what happened
then, you all know how he acted and felt and what his
condition was when, taking him in hand after the
other doctors had given up, while the members of
the family were avoiding him and not venturing
even to approach him, I made him what you see him,
so that he is able to bring charges and argue about the
laws. Stay! you can see your counterpart, father;
you were nearly as your wife is now, when I brought
you back to your former sanity. Truly it is not just
that I should receive such a recompense for it, or that


<pb n="v.5.p.499"/>

you should employ your reason only against me.
That I have done you no little good is clear from the
very charges which you bring; you hate me because
I do not cure your wife when she is at the end of
everything and in an utterly wretched plight. Since
I freed you from a similar condition, why are you
not far rather overjoyed and thankful to have been
liberated from a state so terrible? Instead, and it is
most ungrateful—you no sooner recover your sanity
than you bring me to court and after your life has
been saved, seek to punish me, reverting to that
old-time hatred and citing the self-same law. It is a
handsome fee, in truth, that you pay in this manner
to the art of healing, and a fitting price for your
medicines, to employ your sanity only to attack your
physician !
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
Will you, gentlemen of the jury, empower this
man to punish his benefactor, to banish his saviour,
to hate the one who made him sane, to take vengeance
on the one who set him on his feet? Not if you do
what is just. For if I were really now guilty of the
greatest offences, there was no slight gratitude
owing me previously; keeping this in sight and in
mind, he would have done well to ignore the present
and to be prompt to forgive for the sake of the past,
especially if the benefaction were so great as to
overtop everything subsequent. That, I think, is
true of mine toward this man, whom I saved, who
is my debtor for the whole of his life, to whom I
have given existence, sanity, and intelligence, and
that at a time when all the others had finally given
up and were confessing themselves defeated by the
malady.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
My benefaction, I think, is the greater because,


<pb n="v.5.p.501"/>

although I was not his son at that time and had no
imperative reason to take the case but was free
and independent, having been released from the
responsibility imposed by nature, nevertheless I was
not indifferent but came voluntarily, unsummoned,
on my own initiative; I gave my assistance, lavished
my attentions, brought about a cure, and set my
father on his feet, preserving him for myself, pleading
my own cause against his disownment, stilling his
anger by my friendliness, annulling the law by my
love, purchasing by a great benefaction my reentrance into the family, demonstrating my loyalty
to my father at a crisis so dangerous, bringing about
my own adoption with the help of my profession, and
proving myself a legitimate son in his time of dire
need.</p>

<p>
What do you suppose my sufferings were, what my
exertions, to be with him, to wait upon him, to watch
my opportunity, now yielding to the full force of the
ailment, now bringing my professional skill to bear
when the disorder abated a little? And truly, of all
these duties that are included in medical science,
the most dangerous is to treat such patients and to
approach people in that condition, for often they
loose their frenzy upon those who are near them,
when their ailment has become severe. And yet
none of these considerations made me hesitant or
faint-hearted. I joined battle with the disease and
measured myself against it in every way, and so at
last prevailed by means of my remedy.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
Let no one, hearing this, be quick to remark:
“What sort of feat is it, and how great, to give a
remedy?”’ Many things must precede this; one
must prepare the way for the medicine, make the

<pb n="v.5.p.503"/>

body easy to cure, and take thought for the patient’s
whole condition, purging him, reducing him, nourishing him with the proper foods, rousing him as
much as is expedient, planning for periods of sleep,
contriving periods of solitude. Those who have any
other sickness can readily be persuaded to consent to
all this, but the insane because of their independence
of spirit are hard to influence and hard to direct,
dangerous to the physician, and hard to conquer by
the treatment. Often when we think we are near
the goal at last and become hopeful, some trivial
slip, occurring when the illness has reached its
height, easily overturns everything that has been
done, hampers the treatment, and thwarts our skill.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>
When a man has endured all this, has wrestled with
an illness so serious, and has conquered the ailment
of all ailments most difficult to master, will you
empower the plaintiff to disown him again, permit
him to interpret the laws in any way he will against
a benefactor, and allow him to fight with nature?
</p>

<p>I, obeying nature, save and preserve my father for
my own sake, gentlemen of the jury, even if he
wrongs me; but that father, following, he says, the
laws, ruins the son that has done him a benefit, and
deprives him of his family. He is his son’s enemy,
I am my father’s friend. I cherish nature, he slights
and insults her just claims. To think of a father who
hates his son unjustly! To think of a son that loves his
father still more unjustly! For I bring it as a charge


<pb n="v.5.p.505"/>

against myself, since my father constrains me to do
so, that I who am hated love when I should not and
love more than I ought. Yet it is nature’s behest
that fathers love their sons more than sons their
fathers. He, however, deliberately slights even the
laws, which preserve for the family sons who have
done no wrong, as well as nature, who draws parents
into great affection for their children. It cannot be
said that, having exceptional grounds for good-will
towards me, he pays me exceptional dues of good-will
and runs the measure over, or that at least he imitates
and rivals me in my love; no, alas! he even hates
one who loves him, repels one who cherishes him,
injures one who helps him, and disowns one who
clings to him. Aye, though the laws are kindly to
children, he employs them against me as if they
were unkindly. Ah, what a conflict you wish to
precipitate, father, between the laws and nature !
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
Truly, truly, this matter is not as you will have it
tobe. Youillinterpret the laws, father, for they are
well made. Nature and law are not at war in the
matter of good-will; they go hand in hand there,
and work together for the righting of wrongs. You
mistreat your benefactor; you wrong nature. Why
wrong the laws, as well as nature? They mean to
be good, and just, and kindly to children, but you will
not allow it, inciting them repeatedly against one
son as if his name were legion, and not suffering
them to rest contented with punishments when they
are willing to rest contented with demonstrations
of filial affection; and yet they were not made,
surely, as a menace to those who have done no
wrong. Indeed, the laws permit suit to be brought
on the charge of ingratitude against persons who do

<pb n="v.5.p.507"/>

not help those who have helped them.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.5.p.507.n.1"><p>The existence of a law making ingratitude (dyapio7ia) actionable was part of the accepted tradition of the Greek rhetorical seHnee (Sopater in Walz, Rhetores Graect, VIII, 175 and 239; Cyrus, tbsd., 391; cf. Seneca, de Benef., III, 6, 1). For its existence outside the schools the evidence is conflicting. The name of the action is included in the list given by Pollux, VIII, 31, and Valerius Maximus (V, 3, ext. 3) says that Athens had such a law. On the other hand, Xenophon puts into the mouth of Socrates (Mem., II, 2,13; ef. Cyrop. I, 2,7) the statement that Athens took no cognisance of ingratitude except toward parents, and Seneca (loc. cit.) says that no nation except the Macedonians had a law against it, </p></note>_ But when a
man, besides failing to render like for like, even
deems it right to inflict punishment in return for
the very benefits that he has received, think whether
there is any exaggeration of injustice which he has
overlooked !</p>

<p>
That it is neither possible for him to disown a
son after having already once for all exhausted his
paternal right and made use of the laws, nor yet just
to thrust away one who has shown himself so great
a benefactor and exclude him from the house has
been, I think, sufficiently established.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
Therefore
let us now come to the ground of disownment and
let us see what the nature of the charge is. It is
necessary to recur once more to the intent of the
lawgiver; for, suppose we grant you briefly the
right to disown as often as you wish and also concede
you this right even against your benefactor, you are
not to disown casually, I take it, or for any and eve
cause. The lawgiver does not say that the father
may disown for any reason that he may chance to
allege—that it is enough just to express the wish
and find a fault. Else why should we need a court?
No, he commits it to you, gentlemen of the jury,
to consider whether the father’s anger is based upon
just and sufficient grounds or not. This, then, is
what you should now look into. And IJ shall begin
with what immediately followed his insanity.



<pb n="v.5.p.509"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
The first act of his sanity was to set aside the disownment, and I was a saviour, a benefactor, all in
allto him. No charge, I take it, could go with that.
And as to what followed, what do you censure in all
of it? What service, what attention proper to a son
did I omit? When did I sleep away from home?
Of what ill-timed carouses, of what riotous revels do
you accuse me? What licentiousness has there
been? What pander have I assaulted? Who has
filed any charges? Nobody at all. Yet these are
the deeds for which the law especially sanctions disownment.
</p>

<p>
“No, but your stepmother began to be ill.” Well,
do you accuse me of that, and demand satisfaction
for the illness?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
“No,” he says. What, then?
“That when you are ordered to treat her, you do not
consent; and on that account would merit disownment for disobeying your father.” Deferring for a
moment the question what sort of orders on his
part, when I cannot obey them, cause me to be
considered disobedient, I first assert simply that the
law does not allow him to issue all orders, and that I
am not obliged to obey all orders under all circumstances. In the matter of commands, sometimes
disobedience is unexceptionable, sometimes it justifies anger and punishment. If you yourself are ill,
and I am indifferent; if you bid me manage the
household, and I am neglectful; if you direct me to
oversee the estate, and I am indiligent—all this and
the like of it affords reasonable grounds for a father’s
censure. But these other matters are within the discretion of us children, belonging as they do to our
callings and the exercise of them; particularly if
the father himself is in no way wronged. For

<pb n="v.5.p.511"/>

really, if a scribe’s father gives him the order,
“Write this, my boy, not that,” or a musician’s
father, “Play this tune, not that,” or a coppersmith’s father, “Forge things like this, not like that,”
would anyone put up with his disowning his son
because the son does not exercise his calling in
accordance with the views of the father? No one,
I think.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
In the case of the medical profession, the more
distinguished it is and the more serviceable to the
world, the more unrestricted it should be for those
who practise it. It is only just that the art of healing should carry with it some privilege in respect to
the liberty of practising it; that no compulsion and
no commands should be put upon a holy calling,
taught by the gods and exercised by men of learning; that it should not be subject to enslavement
by the law, or to voting and judicial punishment, or
to fear and a father’s threats and a layman’s wrath.
Consequently, if I were to say to you, as clearly and
expressly as this: ‘I am unwilling to give treatment,
and I do not do so, although Ican; my knowledge of
the profession is for my benefit alone and my father’s,
and to others I wish to be a layman,” what tyrant
so high-handed that he would constrain me to practise
my calling against my will? Such things should, in
my opinion, be amenable to entreaties and supplications, not to laws and fits of anger and courts: the
physician ought to be persuaded, not ordered; he
ought to be willing, not fearful; he ought not to be
haled to the bedside, but to take pleasure in coming
of his own accord. Surely his calling is exempt
from paternal compulsion in view of the fact that


<pb n="v.5.p.513"/>

physicians have honours, precedence, immunities,
and privileges publicly bestowed on them by states.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>
This, then, is what I might say without circumlocution in behalf of my profession if you had had me
taught and had been at much pains and expense that
I might learn, and I were nevertheless reluctant to
undertake this one cure, which was possible. But as
things stand, consider how absolutely unreasonable
a thing you are doing in not allowing me to use my
own possession freely. I did not learn this profession
while I was your son or subject to your jurisdiction,
and yet I learned it for you (aye, you were the first to
profit by it) though I had no help from you towards
learning it. What teacher did you furnish money
for? What supply of drugs? None at all. No,
poor as I was, in want of necessities, and pitied by
my teachers, I got myself educated, and the assistance
towards learning which I had from my father was
grief, loneliness, poverty, the hatred of my family,
and the aversion of my kinsmen. In return for this,
do you now think fit to utilize my profession and wish
to be master of all that I acquired when you were
not my master? Be content if I have already done
you a good turn of my own accord, without previous
indebtedness to you, for then as now nothing could
have been required of meas an expressionof gratitude.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
Surely my act of kindness should not become an
obligation for the future, nor should the fact that I
conferred a benefit of my own free will constitute a
reason that I should be ordered to do it against my
will; neither should it become customary that once a
"man has cured anybody, he must for ever treat all
those whom his former patient wishes him to treat.
Under those conditions we should have elected our

<pb n="v.5.p.515"/>

patients to be our masters, paying them, too, by
playing slave to them and executing all their orders.
What could be more inequitable than this? Because
I restored you to health in this way when you had
fallen severely ill, do you think that you are therefore
empowered to abuse my skill?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
That is what I might have said if what he enjoined
upon me were possible, and I were refusing to obey
him in absolutely everything, and under compulsion.
But as things are, consider now what his commands
are like. “Since you have cured me,” says he,
“from insanity, since my wife too is insane and has
the same symptoms” (for so he thinks), “and has
been given up by others in the same way, and since
you can do everything, as you have shown, cure her
too and free her forthwith from the disorder.”” That,
to hear it so simply put, might seem very reasonable,
particularly to a layman, inexperienced in matters
of medicine. But if you will listen to my plea on
behalf of my profession, you will discover that all
things are not possible to us, that the natures of
ailments are not alike, that the cure is not the same
or the same medicines effective in all cases; and
then it will be clear that there is a great difference
between not wishing to do a thing and not being
able. Suffer me to indulge in scientific discourse
about these matters, and do not consider my discussion of them tactless, beside the point, or alien
and unseasonable.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>
In the first place, the natures and temperaments of
human bodies are not the same, although they are


<pb n="v.5.p.517"/>

admittedly composed of the same elements, but
some contain more, or perhaps less, of this, others
of that. And I say further that even the bodies of
males are not all equal or alike either in temperament or in constitution. So it is inevitable that the
diseases which arise in them should be different both
in intensity and in kind, and that some bodies should
be easy to cure and amenable to treatment, while
others are completely hopeless, being easily affected
and quickly overcome. Therefore, to think that all
fevers or consumptions or inflammations of the lungs
or madnesses, if of one and the same kind, are alike
in all bodies is not what one expects of sound-minded,
sensible men who have investigated such matters.
No, the same ailment is easy to cure in this person
but not in that. Just so, I take it, with wheat;
if you cast the same seed into different plots of ground,
it will grow in one way in the ground that is level,
deep-soiled, well watered, blessed with sunshine
and breezes, and thoroughly tilled, yielding a full,
rich, abundant harvest, no doubt, but otherwise in a
stony farm on a mountain, or in ground with little
sun, or in the foothills; to put it generally, in
different ways according to the various soils. So too
diseases become prolific and luxuriant or less so
through the soils which receive them. Omitting
this point and leaving it entirely uninvestigated, my
father expects all attacks of insanity in all bodies to
be alike and their treatment the same.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>
In addition to these important distinctions, it is
easy to grasp the fact that the bodies of women differ
very widely from those of men, both in respect to


<pb n="v.5.p.519"/>

the dissimilarity of their diseases and in respect to
one’s hopefulness or despair of a cure. For the
bodies of men are well-knit and sinewy, since they
have been trained by toils and exercises, and by an
open-air life; but those of women are weak and
soft from being reared indoors, and white for lack of
blood, deficiency of heat, and an excessive supply
of the moist humour. They are therefore more
susceptible than those of men, prone to diseases,
intolerant of medical treatment, and above all, more
liable to attacks of insanity ; for since women have
much bad temper, frivolity, and instability, but little
physical strength, they easily fall into this affection.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>
It is not right, then, to ask of the physicians the
same treatment for both, when we know that there
is a great gulf between them, dissociated as they have
been from the very first in their entire mode of life,
and in all their activities and all their pursuits. So
when you say “It is a case of insanity,” add, “insanity in a woman,” and do not confuse all these
variations by subsuming them under the title of
insanity, which seems always one and the same
thing, but distinguish them, as is right, in their
nature and see what can be done in each case. That
is what we do, for, as I remember telling you in the
beginning of my speech, the first thing that we consider is the constitution and temperament of the
patient’s body, what quality predominates in it,
whether it is inclined to be hot or cold, whether it is


<pb n="v.5.p.521"/>

vigorous or senile, tall or short, fat or lean, and
everything of that sort. In short, if a man examines
into these matters to begin with, he will be very
trustworthy when he expresses any doubt or makes
any promise.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>
To be sure, of madness itself there are countless
varieties, with many causes and even dissimilar
names; for perversity, eccentricity, delirium, and
lunacy are not the same thing, but are all names
that signify whether one is more or less in the grip
of the disease. The causes, too, are of one sort
with men, another with women, and even among
men they are of one sort with the young and
different with the aged; for instance, with the young
usually excess of humours, whereas in the case of the
old, groundless prejudice and insensate anger against
members of the family, attacking them frequently,
disturbs them at first, then gradually deranges them
to the point of insanity. Women are affected by
many things which easily incline them to this
ailment, especially by excessive hatred of someone,
or jealousy of an enemy who is prospering, or grief of
some sort, or anger; these passions, slowly smouldering and acquiring strength in a long lapse of time,
produce madness.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p>
That, father, is what has happened to your wife,
and it may be that something has grieved her recently, for she, of course, hated nothing at all. However that may be, she has a seizure, at all events, and
in the circumstances cannot be cured by a physician.
If anyone else should engage to do it, if anyone —
should relieve her, you may then hate me as offending


<pb n="v.5.p.523"/>

against you. Indeed, father, I shall not hesitate to
say further that even if her case were not so wholly
desperate, but some hope of saving her still were in
sight, even then I should not have undertaken her
case lightly or ventured to prescribe for her out of
hand, fearing mischance and the slanderous tongues
of the common sort. You are aware that everybody
thinks that all stepmothers entertain some hatred
of their stepsons, even if they are good women, and
that in this they suffer from a sort of insanity affecting women in common. Perhaps someone would
have suspected, if the ailment had gone badly and
the’ remedies had not been effective, that the treatment had been malevolent and treacherous.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg052.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="32"><p>
As regards your wife, father, the case stands thus,
and I tell you so after careful observation—she will
never be better, even if she takes medicine a thousand
times. For that reason it is not proper to make any
attempt, unless you are trying to force me into sheer
failure and wish to give me a bad name. Let me
continue to be envied by my fellow-practitioners !
If, however, you disown me again, I certainly,
though totally alone in the world, will not pray that
any adversity may befall you; but what if (Heaven
forfend !) your affliction returns once more? Somehow it often happens that such afflictions, under
irritation, do recur. What shall I be required to do?
I will treat you even then, you may be sure, and
shall never desert the post which Nature has commanded sons to hold, nor ever, so far as in me lies,
forget my origin. And then, if you recover your
mind, may I expect you some day to take me back
again? Look! even now by these actions of yours
you are bringing on the disorder and provoking the

<pb n="v.5.p.525"/>

ailment. You have only just recovered from that
terrible plight, and yet you strain your lungs shouting; more than that, you are angry, you take to
hatred, and you invoke the laws. Ah, father, that
is the way your former seizure began!
</p></div>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>

