<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Odes (English). Machine readable text - N.</title>
                <author>Pindar</author>
                <editor role="translator">Diane Arnson Svarlien</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>


            <notesStmt>
                <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"> Diane Arnson Svarlien typed in her
                    translation. Basic SGML tagging by EM </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <bibl default="false">
                    <title>Odes</title>
                    <author>Pindar</author>
                    <editor role="translator">Diane Arnson Svarlien</editor>
                    <date>1990</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl default="false">
                <correction default="false" status="high" method="silent">
                    <p> professional data entry</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="line"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:l[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts poem and line</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                
                <cRefPattern n="poem"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts poem</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>8/9</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Ted Armstrong</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Proofread for typos.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>1990</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EM and SFSH</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Make sure that the file matches new DTDs.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>8/91</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EM</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Revise DTDs and recheck texts.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>9/91</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>WPM</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Entered Hubbard's revisions.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>11/91</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>WPM</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Entered Svarlien's responses to Hubbard.</item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2016-01-22" who="TDBuck">editied mark-up, CTS compatible</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0033.tlg003.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>Nemean Odes</head>
                <p/>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="1">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 1</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Chromius of Aetna</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Chariot Race</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0476">476</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Sacred place where Alpheus breathed again; Ortygia, scion of renowned
                        Syracuse, bed of Artemis, sister of <placeName key="perseus,Delos"
                            >Delos</placeName> ! From you sweet-voiced </l>
                    <l n="5"> song rushes out to give great praise for storm-footed horses, by the
                        grace of Aetnaean Zeus. The chariot of Chromius and <placeName
                            key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> urge me to harness a song of
                        praise for deeds of victory. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="8"> The foundations of the song have been laid with the gods, and with
                        this man's god-given excellence. </l>
                    <l n="10"> The summit of perfect glory is found in good fortune. The Muse loves
                        to remember great contests. Sow some splendor on the island, which Zeus the
                        lord of <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> gave to Persephone;
                        he nodded assent with his flowing hair, that as the best land on the
                        fruitful earth <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    
                    <l n="15"> he would make <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> fertile
                        and prosperous in her cities blossoming with wealth. And the son of Cronus
                        sent her a people enamored of bronze-armored battle, horsemen often wedded
                        to the golden leaves of <placeName key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName>
                        's olive. I have embarked on the occasion for many themes, without flinging
                        a false word. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="19"> I have arrived singing of fine deeds at the courtyard gates </l>
                    <l n="20"> of a man who loves guests, where a beautifully arranged meal has been
                        prepared for me, and the halls are often familiar with strangers from other
                        lands. It is his lot to have noble friends to bring against his slanderers,
                        like water against smoke. </l>
                    <l n="25"> Various men have various skills. It is right for a man to follow
                        straight paths, and strive according to his nature. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="26"> For strength manifests itself in action, and intelligence in
                        counsels, for those who have the inborn skill of foreseeing the future. Son
                        of Hagesidamus, your way of life </l>
                    <l n="30"> grants you the enjoyment of many things. I take no pleasure in
                        keeping great wealth hidden away in my hall, but in using what I have to be
                        successful and to win a good name by helping my friends. For the hopes of
                        men who toil much come to all alike. <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="33"> But as for me, I cling to the theme of Heracles gladly, rousing an
                        ancient story from among the great heights of his excellence, </l>
                    <l n="35"> how, when the son of Zeus suddenly came out of his mother's womb into
                        the brilliant light, escaping her birth-pangs, with his twin brother,
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="37"> he did not escape the notice of gold-throned Hera when he was placed
                        in his saffron swaddling-clothes. But the queen of the gods, </l>
                    <l n="40"> stung in her heart, immediately sent serpents. The doors opened, and
                        they crept into the spacious inner-chamber, eager to coil their swift jaws
                        around the babies. But Heracles lifted his head straight up, and had his
                        first experience of battle, <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="44"> seizing </l>
                    <l n="45"> the two necks of the serpents in his two irresistible hands. When
                        they were strangled, time squeezed the breath of life out of their
                        unspeakable limbs. Unbearable fear <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                            resp="Svarlien"> Reading with Snell <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >de/os</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">be/los</foreign> .
                        </note> struck the women who were then helping Alcmena at her bedside; </l>
                    <l n="50"> for she herself leapt to her feet from her bed, unrobed as she was,
                        and tried to ward off the violent attack of the monsters. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="51"> And swiftly the chiefs of the Cadmeans rushed in together in their
                        bronze armor, and Amphitryon came brandishing a sword bared from its
                        scabbard, stricken with sharp distress. For each man alike is oppressed by
                        his own trouble, but the heart recovers quickly from someone else's grief.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    
                    <l n="55"> He stood, possessed by overwhelming astonishment and delight. For he
                        saw the supernatural courage and power of his son; the immortals had turned
                        the story of the messengers to falsehood for him. </l>
                    <l n="60"> And he called his neighbor, the outstanding prophet of Zeus the
                        highest, the truthful seer Teiresias. And the prophet told him and all the
                        men what fortunes the boy would encounter: <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="62"> how many he would slay on land, and how many lawless monsters at sea.
                        And he told of a certain one, </l>
                    <l n="65"> most hateful, who walked with crooked insolence towards men, whom the
                        boy would send to his doom. For he said that when the gods meet the giants
                        in battle on the plain of Phlegra, the shining hair of the giants will be
                        stained with dirt beneath the rushing arrows of that hero. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="69"> But he himself </l>
                    <l n="70"> will have allotted to him in peace, as an extraordinary reward for
                        his great hardship, continuous peace for all time among the homes of the
                        blessed. He will receive flourishing Hebe as his bride and celebrate the
                        wedding-feast, and in the presence of Zeus the son of Cronus he will praise
                        the sacred law. <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien">
                            Reading with Snell <foreign xml:lang="grc">no/mon</foreign> for <foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">do/mon</foreign> . </note>
                    </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="2">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 2</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Timodemus of Acharnae</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Pancratium</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0485">485</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Just as the Homeridae, the singers of woven verses, most often begin
                        with Zeus as their prelude, so this man has received a first down-payment of
                        victory in the sacred games by winning </l>
                    <l n="5"> in the grove of Nemean Zeus, which is celebrated in many hymns.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="6"> And if the life that guides him straight along the path of his fathers
                        has given him as an adornment to great Athens, it must be that the son of
                        Timonous will often reap the finest bloom of the Isthmian games, and be
                        victorious in the Pythian contests. </l>
                    <l n="10"> It is right <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="11"> for Orion to travel not far from the mountain Pleiades. And certainly
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName> can raise a warrior. In
                        Troy Hector heard of Aias. And you, Timodemus, are exalted </l>
                    <l n="15"> by your enduring spirit of valor in the pancratium. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="16"> Acharnae has long been famous for fine men. And in everything that
                        has to do with contests, the sons of Timodemus are proclaimed the most
                        outstanding. Beside <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName> ,
                        ruling on high, they carried off four victories in the games, </l>
                    <l n="20"> while the men of Corinth <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 5"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="21"> have already given them eight garlands in the glades of noble Pelops;
                        in the Nemean contest of Zeus they have won seven times, and at home their
                        victories are countless. Citizens, praise Zeus in a victory procession for
                        Timodemus' glorious homecoming. </l>
                    <l n="25"> Begin with a sweet-singing voice! </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="3">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 3</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Aristocleides of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Pancratium</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0475">475</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Queenly Muse, our mother! I entreat you, come in the sacred month of
                            <placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> to the much-visited
                        Dorian island of Aegina. For beside the waters of the Asopus young men are
                        waiting, craftsmen of honey-voiced </l>
                    <l n="5"> victory-songs, seeking your voice. Various deeds thirst for various
                        things; but victory in the games loves song most of all, the most auspicious
                        attendant of garlands and of excellence. <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="9"> Send an abundance of it, from my wisdom; </l>
                    <l n="10"> begin, divine daughter, an acceptable hymn to the ruler of the
                        cloud-filled sky, and I will communicate it by the voices of those singers
                        and by the lyre. The hymn will have a pleasant toil, to be the glory of the
                        land where the ancient Myrmidons lived, whose marketplace, famous long ago, </l>
                    <l n="15"> Aristocleides, through your ordinance, did not stain with dishonor by
                        proving himself too weak in the strenuous <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="17"> course of the pancratium. But in the deep plain of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> , his triumph-song brings a
                        healing cure for wearying blows. Still, if the son of Aristophanes, who is
                        beautiful, and whose deeds match his looks, </l>
                    <l n="20"> embarked on the highest achievements of manliness, it is not easy to
                        cross the trackless sea beyond the pillars of Heracles, <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="22"> which that hero and god set up as famous witnesses to the furthest
                        limits of seafaring. He subdued the monstrous beasts in the sea, and tracked
                        to the very end the streams of the shallows, </l>
                    <l n="25"> where he reached the goal that sent him back home again, and he made
                        the land known. My spirit, towards what foreign headland are you turning my
                        voyage? I bid you to summon the Muse in honor of Aeacus and his race;
                        consummate justice attends the precept, “praise the noble.” <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    
                    <l n="30"> And no man should prefer to desire what is alien. Search at home; you
                        have won a suitable adornment for singing something sweet. Among old
                        examples of excellence is king Peleus, who rejoiced when he cut a matchless
                        spear, and who alone, without an army, captured Iolcus, </l>
                    <l n="35"> and caught the sea-nymph Thetis after many struggles. And powerful
                        Telamon, the comrade of Iolaus, sacked the city of Laomedon; <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="38"> and once he followed him to meet the bronze-bowed strength of the
                        Amazons. And fear, the subduer of men, never dulled the edge of his mind. </l>
                    <l n="40"> A man with inborn glory has great weight; but he who has only learned
                        is a man in darkness, breathing changeful purposes, never taking an
                        unwavering step, but trying his hand at countless forms of excellence with
                        his ineffectual thought. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="43"> But golden-haired Achilles, staying in the home of Philyra as a
                        child, played at great deeds, often </l>
                    <l n="45"> brandishing in his hands a javelin with a short blade; swift as the
                        wind, he dealt death to wild lions in battle, and he slew wild boars and
                        carried their panting bodies to the Centaur, son of Cronus, first when he
                        was six years old, and afterwards for all the time he spent there. </l>
                    <l n="50"> Artemis and bold Athena gazed at him with wonder, <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="51"> as he slew deer without the help of dogs and crafty nets; for he
                        excelled with his feet. I have this story as it was told by earlier
                        generations. Deep-thinking Cheiron reared Jason under his stone roof, and
                        later Asclepius, </l>
                    <l n="55"> whom he taught the gentle-handed laws of remedies. And he arranged a
                        marriage for Peleus with the lovely-bosomed <note place="unspecified"
                            anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Reading with Snell <foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">a)glao/kolpon</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >a)glao/karpon</foreign> . </note> daughter of Nereus, and brought
                        up for her their incomparable child, nurturing his spirit with all fitting
                        things, <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="59"> so that when the blasts of the sea-winds sent him </l>
                    <l n="60"> to <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> , he might
                        withstand the spear-clashing war-shout of the Lycians and Phrygians and
                        Dardanians; and when he came into close conflict with the spear-bearing
                        Ethiopians, he might fix it in his mind that their leader, powerful Memnon
                        the kinsman of Helenus, should not return to his home. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="64"> From that point the light of the Aeacids has been fixed to shine far. </l>
                    <l n="65"> Zeus, it is your blood and your contest at which my song aimed its
                        shot, shouting the joy of this land with the voices of young men. Their cry
                        is well-suited to victorious Aristocleides, who linked this island with
                        glorious praise and the sacred </l>
                    <l n="70"> Theoric temple of the Pythian god with splendid ambitions. By trial
                        the accomplishment is made manifest, of that in which a man proves himself
                        preeminent, <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="72"> as a boy among young boys, a man among men, or, thirdly, among
                        elders, according to each stage which we,the race of men, possess. </l>
                    <l n="75"> And mortal life sets in motion four excellences, and bids us to think
                        of what is at hand. You are <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                            resp="Svarlien"> Reading with Snell <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >a)/pessi</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)/pesti</foreign> .
                        </note> not without these excellences. Farewell, my friend! I am sending
                        this to you, honey mixed with white milk, crested with foam from mixing, a
                        draught of song accompanied by the Aeolian breathings of flutes, <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 4"/>
                    </l>
                  
                    <l n="80"> although it is late. The eagle is swift among birds: he swoops down
                        from afar, and suddenly seizes with his talons his blood-stained quarry; but
                        chattering daws stay closer to the ground. By the grace of <placeName
                            key="tgn,2244631">Clio</placeName> on her lovely throne and because of
                        your victorious spirit, the light has shone on you from <placeName
                            key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7011116"
                            >Epidaurus</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Megara"
                            >Megara</placeName> . </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="4">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 4</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Timasarchus of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Boys' Wrestling</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0473">473</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> When toils have been resolved, festivity is the best physician; and
                        songs, the skillful daughters of the Muses, soothe with their touch. And
                        warm water does not wet the limbs so gently </l>
                    <l n="5"> as praise that accompanies the lyre. Speech lives longer than deeds;
                        whatever words the tongue, with the favor of the Graces, draws from the deep
                        mind. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="9"> May it be mine to set forth such speech, in honor of Zeus the son of
                        Cronus, and <placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> , </l>
                    <l n="10"> and Timasarchus' wrestling, as a prelude to my song. And may it be
                        welcomed by the home of the Aeacids, with its fine towers, that light which
                        shines for all, with justice that defends the stranger. And if your father
                        Timocritus had still been warmed by the strength of the sun, playing
                        embroidered notes on the cithara </l>
                    <l n="15"> and bending to this strain, he would have often celebrated his
                        triumphant son, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="17"> because he had sent back from the contest at Cleonae a chain of
                        garlands, and from splendid, illustrious Athens; and because in seven-gated
                        Thebes, </l>
                    <l n="20"> beside Amphitryon's splendid tomb, the Cadmeans gladly crowned him
                        with flowers, for the sake of Aegina. For he looked on <note
                            place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Reading with Snell
                            and MSS <foreign xml:lang="grc">kate/draken</foreign> for <foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">kate/dramen</foreign> . </note> a hospitable city,
                        when he came as a friend to friends, to the prosperous court of Heracles,
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                 
                    <l n="25"> with whom once powerful Telamon destroyed <placeName
                            key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> and the Meropes and the great and
                        terrible warrior Alcyoneus, but not before that giant had laid low, by
                        hurling a rock, twelve chariots and twice twelve horse-taming heroes who
                        were riding in them. </l>
                    <l n="30"> A man who did not understand this proverb would appear to be
                        inexperienced in battle: since “it is likely that the doer will also
                        suffer.” <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 5"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="33"> The laws of song and the hurrying hours prevent me from telling a
                        long story, </l>
                    <l n="35"> and I am drawn, by a magic charm on my heart, to touch on the
                        new-moon festival. Nevertheless, although the deep salt sea holds you around
                        the middle, strain against treacherous plots. We will be seen arriving in
                        the light far above our enemies. But another man, with an envious glance, </l>
                    <l n="40"> broods in the darkness over an empty thought <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 6"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="41"> that falls to the ground. As for me, I know that whatever excellence
                        ruling destiny gave me, time will creep forward and bring it to its
                        appointed perfection. Weave out, sweet lyre, right now, </l>
                    <l n="45"> the beloved song with Lydian harmony, for Oenone and <placeName
                            key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> , where Teucer the son of Telamon
                        reigns far from home; but Aias holds ancestral <placeName key="tgn,7002340"
                            >Salamis</placeName> , <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 7"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="49"> and Achilles holds the shining island in the Euxine sea. </l>
                    <l n="50"> Thetis rules in <placeName key="perseus,Phthia">Phthia</placeName> ,
                        and Neoptolemus in the expanses of <placeName key="tgn,7002705"
                            >Epirus</placeName> , where jutting ox-pasturing headlands, beginning in
                            <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> , slope down to the
                        Ionian sea. But beside the foot of <placeName key="tgn,4008379"
                            >Pelion</placeName> , </l>
                    <l n="55"> Peleus turned a warlike hand against Iolcus and gave it in subjection
                        to the Haemones <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"
                            >Following Snell's punctuation.</note>
                        <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 8"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="57"> after encountering the crafty arts of Acastus' wife Hippolyte. With
                        the sword of Daedalus, the son of Pelias sowed the seeds of death for Peleus </l>
                    <l n="60"> from an ambush. But Cheiron rescued him and carried out the destiny
                        which had been fated by Zeus. And Peleus, having thwarted all-powerful fire,
                        and the sharp claws of bold-plotting lions, and the edge of their terrible
                        teeth, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 9"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="65"> married one of the Nereids throned on high, and saw the fine circle
                        of seats in which the lords of sky and sea were sitting, as they gave him
                        gifts and revealed the future strength of his race. Beyond Gadeira towards
                        the western darkness there is no passage; turn back </l>
                    <l n="70"> the ship's sails again to the mainland of <placeName
                            key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> , for it is impossible for me to
                        tell the full story of the sons of Aeacus. <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="str. 10"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="73"> For the Theandridae, having pledged my word, I went as a ready herald
                        of the limb-strengthening contests </l>
                    <l n="75"> at <placeName key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> and the
                        Isthmus and <placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> , where,
                        whenever they make trial of their skill, they return home with the glorious
                        fruit of garlands; in that home, Timasarchus, we hear that your family is an
                        attendant of victory songs. But if </l>
                    <l n="80"> in honor of your uncle Callicles you bid me <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="str. 11"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="81"> to build a monument whiter than Parian stone, know that gold, when it
                        is refined, shows all radiance, and a song in honor of noble deeds makes a
                        man equal in fortune to kings. </l>
                    <l n="85"> May that man, who dwells beside the stream of <placeName
                            key="tgn,1120946">Acheron</placeName> , hear my voice singing, where in
                        the contest of the loud-roaring wielder of the trident he flourished with
                        crowns of Corinthian wild celery. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 12"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="89"> Euphanes, your aged grandfather, </l>
                    <l n="90"> once willingly sang his praises, child. Each man has his own
                        generation; and each man expects to speak best of what he has seen himself.
                        If he were praising Melesias, how he would throw his opponent in the
                        struggle! Weaving his words, impossible to wrestle down in speech; </l>
                    <l n="95"> with gentle thoughts towards noble men, but a rough adversary to his
                        opponents. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="5">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 5</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Pytheas of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Boys' Pancratium</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0483">483</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> I am not a sculptor, to make statues that stand motionless on the same
                        pedestal. Sweet song, go on every merchant-ship and rowboat that leaves
                        Aegina, and announce that Lampon's powerful son Pytheas </l>
                    <l n="5"> won the victory garland for the pancratium at the Nemean games, a boy
                        whose cheeks do not yet show the tender season that is mother to the dark
                        blossom. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="7"> He has brought honor to the Aeacids, the heroic spearmen descended
                        from Cronus and Zeus and the golden Nereids, and to his mother city, a land
                        friendly to guests. </l>
                    <l n="10"> Once by the altar of father Zeus Hellenius the illustrious sons of
                        Endais and the strong, mighty Phocus stood and prayed, stretching their
                        hands to the sky, that the city would one day be famous for men and ships.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="13"> Phocus was the son of the goddess Psamatheia; he was born by the
                        shore of the sea. Reverence restrains me from speaking of an enormous and
                        unjust venture, </l>
                    <l n="15"> how indeed they left the glorious island, and what divine power drove
                        the brave men from Oenone. I will stop: it is not always beneficial for the
                        precise truth to show her face, and silence is often the wisest thing for a
                        man to heed. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="19"> But if it is resolved to praise wealth, or the strength of hands, or
                        iron war, </l>
                    <l n="20"> let someone mark off a long jump for me from this point. I have a
                        light spring in my knees, and eagles swoop over the sea. The most beautiful
                        chorus of Muses sang gladly for the Aeacids on Mt. Pelion, and among them
                        Apollo, sweeping the seven-tongued lyre with a golden plectrum, <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                 
                    <l n="25"> led all types of strains. And the Muses began with a prelude to Zeus,
                        then sang first of divine Thetis and of Peleus; how Hippolyte, the opulent
                        daughter of Cretheus, wanted to trap him with deceit. With elaborate
                        planning she persuaded her husband, the watcher of the Magnesians, to be a
                        partner in her plot, and she forged a false story; </l>
                    <l n="30"> that Peleus had made an attempt on her <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="31"> in Acastus' own bed. But the opposite was true; for she often begged
                        him and coaxed him with all her heart, but her reckless words provoked his
                        temper. Without hesitating he refused Acastus' bride, fearing the anger of
                        father Zeus, the god of hospitality. And from the sky Zeus who rouses the
                        clouds noticed, </l>
                    <l n="35"> Zeus the king of the immortals, and he promised that soon he would
                        make one of the Nereids of the golden distaff the sea-dwelling wife of
                        Peleus, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="37"> after gaining the consent of their brother-in-law Poseidon, who often
                        comes from <placeName key="perseus,Aegae">Aegae</placeName> to the famous
                        Dorian Isthmus. There joyful bands welcome the god with the cry of
                        reed-pipes, and contend with the bold strength of their limbs. </l>
                    <l n="40"> The fortune that is born along with a man decides in every deed. And
                        you, Euthymenes from Aegina, have twice fallen into the arms of Victory and
                        attained embroidered hymns. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="43"> Truly even now, Pytheas, your mother's brother honors the kindred
                        race of that hero following after you. <placeName key="perseus,Nemea"
                            >Nemea</placeName> is linked to him, and Aegina's festival month which
                        belongs to Apollo. </l>
                    <l n="45"> And he was victorious over his peers both at home and in the lovely
                        hollows of the hill of Nisus. I rejoice, because every state strives for
                        noble deeds. Know that through the help of Menander's good fortune you won
                        sweet requital for your toils. <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="49"> It is fitting that a trainer of athletes should come from Athens. </l>
                    <l n="50"> But if you come to Themistius, let there be no more coldness! Lift up
                        your voice, and hoist the sails to the top-most yard; proclaim him as a
                        boxer, and tell how he claimed double excellence with his victory in the
                        pancratium at <placeName key="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> . Bring to
                        the porch of Aeacus green garlands of flowers, in company with the
                        golden-haired Graces. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="6">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 6</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Alcimidas of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Boys' Wrestling</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0465">465</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> There is one race of men, one race of gods; and from a single mother
                        we both draw our breath. But all allotted power divides us: man is nothing,
                        but for the gods the bronze sky endures as a secure home forever.
                        Nevertheless, we bear some resemblance to the immortals, either in greatness </l>
                    <l n="5"> of mind or in nature, although we do not know, by day or by night,
                        towards what goal fortune has written that we should run. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="8"> Even now Alcimidas gives visible proof that his hereditary qualities
                        are like the fruitful fields, which, in alternation, </l>
                    <l n="10"> at one time give men yearly sustenance from the plains, and at
                        another time gather strength from repose. He has come from the lovely games
                        of <placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> , the athletic boy who,
                        pursuing this ordinance of Zeus, has shown that he is a successful hunter in
                        the wrestling ring, <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
              
                    <l n="15"> by planting his step in the tracks of his grandfather, his
                        blood-relative. For that man, an Olympic victor, was the first to bring
                        garlands from the Alpheus to the Aeacidae; and he had himself crowned five
                        times at the Isthmus, </l>
                    <l n="20"> and three times at <placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> ,
                        putting an end to the obscurity of Socleides, who proved to be the greatest
                        of the sons of Hagesimachus, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="24"> since he had three victorious sons who reached the summit of
                        excellence, </l>
                    <l n="25"> and who had a taste of toils. With the favorable fortune of the gods,
                        no other family has been proclaimed by the boxing contest in the center of
                        all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> as the guardian of more
                        garlands. I hope, with this great praise, to hit the target squarely, like
                        one who shoots from a bow. Come, Muse, give a straight course to the
                        glorious wind of song for this man. </l>
                    <l n="30"> For when men pass away <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="31"> songs and stories preserve their fine deeds for them, and there is no
                        shortage of these in the house of the Bassids. Their race has long been
                        famous, carrying a cargo of their own victory songs; for those who plough
                        the field of the Pierian Muses, they are able to provide a rich supply of
                        songs, because of their proud achievements. </l>
                    <l n="35"> In very holy <placeName key="tgn,7010770">Pytho</placeName> the blood
                        of this family was once victorious, his hands bound with leather
                        straps—Callias, who had found favor with <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="38"> the children of Leto of the golden distaff, and beside Castalia at
                        evening he was made radiant by the loud chorus of the Graces. </l>
                    <l n="40"> And the bridge of the untiring sea <note place="unspecified"
                            anchored="true" resp="Svarlien">i.e. the Isthmus of Corinth.</note>
                        honored Creontidas in the biennial festival of those who live around, when
                        bulls are slain in the sacred precinct of Poseidon. And the herb of the
                        Nemean lion once </l>
                    <l n="45"> crowned him when he was victorious beneath the shady primeval
                        mountains of Phlius. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="47"> There are broad avenues open on every side for storytellers to adorn
                        this glorious island, since the Aeacids provided them by example with an
                        outstanding share of great excellence. </l>
                    <l n="50"> Their name flies far, over the land and across the sea. It even
                        reached the Ethiopians, when Memnon did not return to his home; Achilles
                        descended from his chariot and fell upon <note place="unspecified"
                            anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Reading with Snell <foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">e)/mpese</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >e)/mbale</foreign> . </note> them, a grievous antagonist,
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="54"> when he slew the son of the shining Dawn with the edge </l>
                    <l n="55"> of his raging sword. Poets of former times found this highway, and I
                        myself am following them; this is my concern. But the wave that rolls
                        nearest to the ship is said to stir the spirit most of all. I came as a
                        messenger, willingly bearing on my back a double burden, </l>
                    <l n="60"> to proclaim that this twenty-fifth <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="61"> boast of victory from the games which men call sacred, Alcimidas, has
                        been provided by you for your glorious family. Beside the sacred precinct of
                        the son of Cronus, child, you and Polytimidas were deprived of two Olympic
                        garlands </l>
                    <l n="65"> by a sudden drawing of lots. I would say that Melesias is equal in
                        speed to a dolphin that darts through the salt sea; he is the charioteer who
                        guided your hands and strength. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="7">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 7</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Sogenes of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Boys' Pentathlon</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0467">467</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1">
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> On the
                            uncertainty of the date, see C. Carey,A Commentary on Five Odes of
                            Pindar ( <placeName key="tgn,7007567">New York</placeName>
                            <date when="1981">1981</date> ), p. 133. </note> Eleithuia, seated
                        beside the deep-thinking Fates, hear me, creator of offspring, child of Hera
                        great in strength. Without you we see neither the light nor the dark night
                        before it is our lot to go to your sister, Hebe, <note place="unspecified"
                            anchored="true" resp="Svarlien">Youth</note> with her lovely limbs. </l>
                    <l n="5"> Yet we do not all draw our first breath for equal ends. Under the yoke
                        of destiny, different men are held by different restraints. But it is by
                        your favor that, even so, Sogenes the son of Thearion, distinguished by his
                        excellence, is celebrated in song as glorious among pentathletes. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="9"> For he lives in a city that loves music, the city of the Aeacidae with
                        their clashing spears; </l>
                    <l n="10"> and they very much want to foster a spirit familiar with contests. If
                        someone is successful in his deeds, he casts a cause for sweet thoughts into
                        the streams of the Muses. For those great acts of prowess dwell in deep
                        darkness, if they lack songs, and we know of only one way to hold a mirror
                        up to fine deeds: </l>
                    <l n="15"> if, by the grace of Mnemosyne with her splendid headdress, one finds
                        a recompense for toils in glorious song. <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="17"> Skillful men know the wind that will come on the day after tomorrow,
                        and they do not suffer loss through the love of gain. The rich man and the
                        poor man alike travel together to the boundary of death. </l>
                    <l n="20"> And I expect that the story of Odysseus came to exceed his
                        experiences, through the sweet songs of Homer, <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="22"> since there is a certain solemnity in his lies and winged artfulness,
                        and poetic skill deceives, seducing us with stories, and the heart of the
                        mass of men is blind. For if </l>
                    <l n="25"> they had been able to see the truth, then mighty Aias, in anger over
                        the arms, would never have planted in his chest the smooth sword—Aias, who
                        was the most powerful in battle, except for Achilles, and whom the breath of
                        the unswerving Zephyr conveyed in swift ships, to bring back the wife of
                        golden-haired Menelaus <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                  
                    <l n="30"> from the city of Ilus. But the wave of Hades breaks over all alike;
                        it falls on the man who does not expect it, and on the one who does. There
                        is honor for those whose fame a god causes to grow luxuriant when they are
                        dead. Neoptolemus came to help, <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                            resp="Svarlien"> Adding a period after <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >teqnako/twn</foreign> and reading with C. Carey, <title>A
                                Commentary on Five Odes of Pindar</title>
                            <placeName key="tgn,7007567">New York</placeName>
                            <date when="1981">1981</date> , 148-50, <foreign xml:lang="grc">boaqe/wn
                                . . . mo/len</foreign> . </note> to the great navel of the
                        broad-bosomed earth. And he lies beneath the Pythian soil, </l>
                    <l n="35"> after he sacked the city of Priam, where even the Danaans toiled. But
                        on his return voyage he missed Scyros, and after wandering from their course
                        they came to Ephyra. <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="38"> He ruled in Molossia for a brief time; and his race always bore </l>
                    <l n="40"> this honor of his. He had gone to consult the god, bringing precious
                        things from the finest spoils of <placeName key="tgn,7014164"
                            >Troy</placeName> ; and there he met with a quarrel over the flesh of
                        his sacrifice, and a man struck him with a knife. <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="43"> The hospitable Delphians were grieved beyond measure; but he
                        fulfilled his fate. It was destined that within that most ancient grove one </l>
                    <l n="45"> of the ruling race of Aeacus should, for all time to come, stay
                        beside the fine-walled house of the god, and dwell there to preside over the
                        processions of heroes, which are honored by many sacrifices. <note
                            place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Following
                                <placeName key="tgn,2114280">Snell</placeName> 's punctuation,
                            period after <foreign xml:lang="grc">poluqu/ tois</foreign> and after
                                <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)kgo/nwn</foreign> , below. </note> As for
                        their justly earned good name, a few words will suffice: it is no lying
                        witness that presides over achievements of the offspring of you and Zeus, </l>
                    <l n="50"> Aegina. I have this bold speech to make, <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="51"> an authoritative path of words from their home, for their shining
                        excellence. But enough, for respite is sweet in every deed. Even honey may
                        cloy, and the delightful flowers of Aphrodite. Each of us differs in nature,
                        for we were each allotted a different life. </l>
                    <l n="55"> One man has this, others have something else; but for one man to win
                        the prize of complete happiness is impossible. I cannot say to whom Fate has
                        handed this consummation as a lasting possession. But to you, Thearion, she
                        gives a due measure of prosperity, <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="59"> and while you have gained a bold spirit for fine deeds, </l>
                    <l n="60"> she does not impair the wisdom of your mind. I am your friend;
                        averting the dark shadow of abuse, and bringing genuine glory, like streams
                        of water, to the man who is dear to me, I shall praise him. This wage is
                        worthy of good men. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="64"> If any Achaean man is nearby </l>
                    <l n="65"> who lives above the Ionian sea, he will not find fault with me. I
                        trust in my being their representative. And among my fellow townsmen, the
                        glance of my eye is bright; I have not overshot the mark, and I have thrust
                        all violence away from my path. May the rest of my days approach
                        benevolently. Anyone who knows the truth will declare whether I follow a
                        path that is out of tune, singing a twisted <note place="unspecified"
                            anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Reading with <placeName
                                key="tgn,2114280">Snell</placeName>
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">ya/gion</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >yo/gion</foreign> . </note> song. </l>
                    <l n="70"> Sogenes, of the Euxenid clan, I swear that I did not overstep the
                        line when I hurled, like a bronze-cheeked javelin, <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="72"> my swift tongue—a throw that disqualifies a man's strong neck from
                        the sweat of the wrestling-match, before his limbs fall under the burning
                        sun. If there was toil, greater delight follows. </l>
                    <l n="75"> Let me go on. If I rose too high and shouted loudly, I am not too
                        rude to pay my debt of gratitude to the victor. It is easy to weave
                        garlands. Strike up the song! The Muse welds together gold and white ivory
                        with coral, the lily she has stolen from beneath the ocean's dew. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 4"/>
                    </l>
              
                    <l n="80"> But in remembrance of Zeus and in honor of Nemea, whirl a far-famed
                        strain of song, softly. On this spot it is fitting to sing with a gentle
                        voice of the king of gods. For they say that he planted the seed of Aeacus,
                        received by the mother, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 5"/>
                    </l>
               
                    <l n="85"> to be a city-ruler in my <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                            resp="Svarlien"> Reading with <placeName key="tgn,2114280"
                                >Snell</placeName> and MSS <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)ma=|</foreign>
                            for <foreign xml:lang="grc">e(a=|</foreign> . </note> illustrious
                        fatherland, and to be a kindly <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                            resp="Svarlien"> Reading with <placeName key="tgn,2114280"
                                >Snell</placeName>
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">propra/on'</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >proprew=n'</foreign> . </note> friend and brother to you, Heracles.
                        If one man has any benefit from another, we would say that a neighbor, if he
                        loves his neighbor with an earnest mind, is a joy worth any price. But if a
                        god should also uphold this truth, </l>
                    <l n="90"> then under your protection, Heracles, you who subdued the Giants,
                        Sogenes would dwell happily, fostering a spirit of devotion to his father,
                        beside the rich and sacred road of his ancestors, <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 5"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="93"> since he has his house in your precincts, flanking him on either hand
                        as he goes, like the yoke-arms of a four-horse chariot. Blessed Heracles, </l>
                    <l n="95"> it is fitting for you to persuade the husband of Hera and the
                        gray-eyed virgin goddess; you are often able to give mortals courage against
                        the impasse of helplessness. Would that you might join their youth and
                        splendid old age to a strong and secure life, and weave it through to the
                        end </l>
                    <l n="100"> in good fortune, and may their children's children always have
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 5"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="101"> the honor of the present day, and a still better one to come. But my
                        heart will never say that I have done violence to Neoptolemus with cruel
                        words. To plough the same ground three or four times </l>
                    <l n="105"> is poverty of thought, like babbling “Corinth of Zeus” to children.
                    </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="8">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 8</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Deinias of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Double Foot Race</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0459">459</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Queenly Season of Youth, herald of the divine embraces of Aphrodite,
                        you who rest in the eyes of young girls and boys, and carry one man in the
                        gentle arms of compulsion, but handle another man differently. It is a
                        desirable thing, for one who has not strayed from due measure in any deed, </l>
                    <l n="5"> to be able to win the better kinds of love; <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="6"> such loves,the shepherds of Cyprian Aphrodite's gifts, attended the
                        marriage-bed of Zeus and Aegina. And from that union a son was born, the
                        king of Oenone, the best in hands and mind. Many men often prayed that they
                        might see him; for, unbidden, the choicest heroes that dwelled around him </l>
                    <l n="10"> wanted to submit to his commands willingly, <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="11"> those who marshalled their people in rocky Athens, and the
                        descendants of Pelops in <placeName key="tgn,1015125">Sparta</placeName> .
                        As a suppliant I cling to the sacred knees of Aeacus, on behalf of his dear
                        city and these citizens, bringing </l>
                    <l n="15"> a Lydian crown embroidered with song, glory from Nemea in the double
                        foot race for Deinias and his father Megas. For prosperity that is planted
                        with a god's blessing is more abiding for men; <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="18"> such prosperity as once loaded Cinyras with wealth in sea-washed
                            <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> . I stand with feet
                        lightly poised, catching my breath before I speak. </l>
                    <l n="20"> For many stories have been told in many ways. But to find something
                        new and submit it to the touchstone for testing is danger itself. Words are
                        a dainty morsel for the envious; and envy always clings to the noble, and
                        has no quarrel with worse men. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="23"> Envy devoured the son of Telamon, throwing him onto his own sword. A
                        man who was not gifted in speech, but brave in his heart, is held down by
                        oblivion </l>
                    <l n="25"> under deadly strife; and the greatest prize of honor has been offered
                        to the shifty lie. For in a secret vote the Danaans favored Odysseus; and
                        Aias, robbed of the golden armor, wrestled with death. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="28"> Truly, they did not tear equal wounds in the warm flesh of the enemy
                        when they were driven back </l>
                    <l n="30"> under the man-protecting spear, at one time around the newly-slain
                        corpse of Achilles, and on destructive days spent on other toils. It seems
                        that hateful Misrepresentation existed even long ago: a fellow traveler of
                        flattering tales, deceitful-minded, a malignant disgrace. She does violence
                        to the illustrious, and upholds the rotten glory of the obscure. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
              
                    <l n="35"> May I never have such a nature, father Zeus; may I stick to the
                        simple paths of life, so that when I die I will not fasten a bad name to my
                        children. Some men pray for gold, others for boundless land; I pray to find
                        favor with my fellow-citizens until my limbs are buried in the earth, by
                        praising what is praiseworthy and casting blame on wrongdoers. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
           
                    <l n="40"> Excellence grows among skillful and just men up to the liquid air, as
                        a tree shoots up fed by fresh dew. The uses of friends are of all kinds;
                        those in times of toil are the highest, yet delight also seeks to set a
                        trustworthy pledge before the eyes. Megas, to bring your soul back to life
                        again <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    
                    <l n="45"> is not possible for me. Empty hopes end in vain; but it is easy to
                        set up, for your fatherland and for the Chariads, a monument of the Muses in
                        honor of the twice illustrious feet of two men. I rejoice in letting fly a
                        boast suitable to such a deed; and with incantations a man </l>
                    <l n="50"> makes hardship painless. Truly, the song of victory existed long ago,
                        even before the quarrel arose between Adrastus and the race of Cadmus. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="9">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 9</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Chromius of Aetna</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Chariot Race</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0474">474</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Muses, we will go in victory procession from Apollo's shrine in
                            <placeName key="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> to newly-founded Aetna,
                        where the doors flung open wide are overwhelmed by guests, at the prosperous
                        home of Chromius. Make a sweet song of verses! For, mounting his chariot of
                        victorious horses, he gives the word to sing for the mother and her twin
                        children </l>
                    <l n="5"> who jointly watch over steep <placeName key="tgn,7010770"
                            >Pytho</placeName> . <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="6"> There is a saying among men: a noble deed when it is accomplished
                        should not be buried silently in the ground; and divine song is suited to
                        boasting. But we will wake the shouting lyre and the flute in honor of the
                        very pinnacle of horse-contests, which Adrastus established for Phoebus by
                        the streams of the Asopus. </l>
                    <l n="10"> Having mentioned them, I will adorn that hero with glorious honors,
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="11"> who, at the time when he was ruler there, made his city famous and
                        glorious with new festivals, and contests of men's strength, and hollow
                        chariots. For once Adrastus fled from bold-thinking Amphiaraus and terrible
                        civil strife, from his ancestral home, <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
                            >Argos</placeName> ; and the sons of Talaus were no longer rulers,
                        overpowered by sedition. </l>
                    <l n="15"> A stronger man puts an end to the previous justice. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="16"> The sons of Talaus gave man-conquering Eriphyle, as a faithful
                        pledge, in marriage to Amphiaraus son of Oicles, and became the most
                        powerful of the golden-haired Danaans; and once they led a noble army of men
                        to seven-gated Thebes—an expedition not attended by birds of good omen. In
                        their mad desire to leave home, the son of Cronus, by whirling his
                        lightning-bolt, urged them not to go, </l>
                    <l n="20"> but to abstain from the journey. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 5"
                        />
                    </l>
                    <l n="21"> And so that company, in bronze armor, and with their horses in
                        war-harnesses, was hastening to arrive at manifest doom. And planting <note
                            place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien">
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)reisa/menoi</foreign> . Wilamowitz: “ <foreign
                                xml:lang="la">reditum in Ismeni ripa sibi fixerunt.</foreign> ”
                        </note> their sweet return on the banks of the Ismenus, they fattened the
                        white-flowering smoke with their corpses <note place="unspecified"
                            anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Reading <foreign xml:lang="grc">sw/masi
                                pi/anan</foreign> (Bergk). </note> . For seven funeral pyres feasted
                        on their bodies' young limbs. But, for the sake of Amphiaraus, Zeus with his
                        all-powerful thunderbolt </l>
                    <l n="25"> split the deep-breasted earth, and concealed him together with his
                        horses, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 6"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="26"> before he could be struck in the back by the spear of Periclymenus,
                        and his warlike spirit disgraced. For amid divinely-sent panic even the
                        children of gods flee. If it is possible, son of Cronus, I would like to put
                        off for as long as I can this fierce trial of empurpled spears, this contest
                        for life and death; </l>
                    <l n="30"> and I pray to you, grant to the children of the Aetnaeans the
                        long-lived blessing of good laws, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 7"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="31"> father Zeus, and join the people with splendid celebrations in their
                        city. There they have men who love horses and whose souls are superior to
                        wealth. My words are hard to believe; for reverence, which brings renown, is
                        secretly beguiled by the love of gain. If you had been Chromius'
                        shield-bearer among foot-soldiers and horses, and in ship-battles, </l>
                    <l n="35"> you would have been able to judge the danger of the sharp battle-cry,
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 8"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="36"> because in battle it was that goddess, Reverence, who armed his
                        warrior-spirit to repel the destruction of the war-god. But few are able to
                        conspire with hand and heart to turn back against the ranks of the enemy the
                        cloud of slaughter that presses close upon them. Indeed men say that glory
                        blossomed for Hector beside the flowing Scamander; </l>
                    <l n="40"> and around the steep cliffs of the Helorus' banks <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 9"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="41"> at the place which men call “the passage of Rhea,” this light has
                        shone on the son of Hagesidamus, in his earliest manhood. I will tell of the
                        honors he won at other times, many on the dust of dry land and on the
                        neighboring sea. And out of toils, which are undertaken with the aid of
                        youth and justice, there comes a gentle life at the approach of old age. </l>
                    <l n="45"> Let him know that he has received marvellous prosperity from the
                        gods. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 10"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="46"> For if, together with many possessions, a man wins renown and glory,
                        there is no higher peak on which a mortal can set his feet. Peace loves the
                        symposium, and new-flourishing victory is fostered by soft song, and the
                        voice becomes bold beside the mixing-bowl. </l>
                    <l n="50"> Let someone mix the wine now, the sweet forerunner of victory-song,
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 11"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="51"> and dispense the powerful son of the vine in those silver goblets
                        which once Chromius' horses won for him and sent from holy <placeName
                            key="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> together with the duly twined
                        garlands of Leto's son. Father Zeus, I pray that I may celebrate this
                        excellence by the favor of the Graces, and excel many poets in honoring
                        victory with my verses, </l>
                    <l n="55"> throwing my shaft nearest of all to the mark of the Muses. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="10">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 10</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Theaeus of Argos</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Wrestling</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0444">444</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Graces, sing of the city of Danaus and his fifty daughters on their
                        splendid thrones, Hera's Argos, a home suitable for a god; it blazes with
                        countless excellences because of its bold deeds. Long indeed is the story of
                        Perseus and the Gorgon Medusa, </l>
                    <l n="5"> and many are the cities founded in <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                            >Egypt</placeName> by the devising of Epaphus. Nor did Hypermnestra go
                        astray, when she restrained in its scabbard her sword, which was alone in
                        its verdict. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="7"> And once the golden-haired, gray-eyed goddess made Diomedes an
                        immortal god; and the earth in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> , thunder-struck by the bolts of Zeus, swallowed up
                        the prophetic son of Oicles, Amphiaraus, the storm-cloud of war. </l>
                    <l n="10"> And Argos has long been the best city for women with beautiful hair;
                        Zeus made this saying clear by visiting Alcmena and Danae, and he united the
                        fruit of intelligence with straightforward justice in the father of Adrastus
                        and in Lynceus. <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="13"> And Zeus nourished the spear of Amphitryon, who attained the height
                        of prosperity and entered into kinship with that god, when, clad in bronze
                        armor, </l>
                    <l n="15"> he slew the Teleboae. Taking on the appearance of Amphitryon, the
                        king of the immortals entered the hall of that hero, bearing the fearless
                        seed of Heracles; whose bride Hebe, the most beautiful of the goddesses,
                        walks forever in <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> beside her
                        mother Hera, goddess of marriage. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="19"> My mouth is too small to tell the whole story of all the noble things
                        in which the precinct of Argos has a share. </l>
                    <l n="20"> And there is also the satiety of men, which is grievous to encounter.
                        But nevertheless, awaken the well-strung lyre, and take thought of
                        wrestling; the contest for the bronze shield calls the people to the
                        sacrifice of oxen in honor of Hera and to the trial of contests. There the
                        son of Ulias, Theaeus, was victorious twice, and gained forgetfulness of
                        toils that were bravely borne. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
               
                    <l n="25"> And he once was victor over the people of <placeName
                            key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> at <placeName key="tgn,7010770"
                            >Pytho</placeName> ; and, going with good fortune, he won the crown at
                        the Isthmus and at <placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> , and he
                        gave the Muses a field to plough, since he won three times at the gates of
                        the sea, and three times on the sacred ground, according to the ordinance of
                        Adrastus. Father Zeus, his mouth keeps silent what his heart truly desires.
                        The accomplishment of all </l>
                    <l n="30"> deeds rests with you. Adding boldness to a heart that does not shrink
                        from labor <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Omit
                            comma after <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou)d'</foreign> , taking it with
                                <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)mo/kqw</foreign> rather than with the verb
                            (Fennell, Farnell). </note> , he asks for your grace. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="31"> I sing what is known to the god <note place="unspecified"
                            anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Reading <foreign xml:lang="grc">qew=|
                                te kai\ o(/stis</foreign> , with the mss. </note> and to whoever
                        strives for the chief crown in the foremost games. <placeName
                            key="perseus,Pisa">Pisa</placeName> holds the highest ordinance, that of
                        Heracles. Still, the sweet voices of the Athenians at their festival twice
                        sang victory-songs as a prelude for Theaeus, </l>
                    <l n="35"> and in earth baked by fire olive oil came to the fine men of Hera's
                        city in jars with richly painted sides. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"
                        />
                    </l>
                    <l n="37"> Theaeus, the honor of successful contests often attends on the
                        well-known race of your maternal ancestors, by the favor of the Graces and
                        the Tyndarids. I would think it right, if I were a kinsman of Thrasyclus </l>
                    <l n="40"> and Antias, not to veil the light in my eyes. For this horse-breeding
                        city of Proetus has flourished with so many victories in the glens of
                        Corinth, and four times from the men of Cleonae. <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="43"> And from <placeName key="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> they
                        returned with silver wine-goblets, and from Pellana with soft wool cloaks
                        around their shoulders. </l>
                    <l n="45"> But it is impossible to give a full reckoning of their countless
                        prizes of bronze—for it would require long leisure to number them—which
                        Cleitor and <placeName key="perseus,Tegea">Tegea</placeName> and the upland
                        cities of the Achaeans and Mount Lycaeon set by the racecourse of Zeus for
                        men to win with the strength of their feet and hands. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="49"> But since Castor </l>
                    <l n="50"> and his brother Polydeuces came to Pamphaës to receive a hospitable
                        welcome, it is no wonder that it is innate in their race to be good
                        athletes; since the Dioscuri, guardians of spacious <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> , along with Hermes and
                        Heracles, administer the flourishing institution of the games, and they care
                        very much for just men. Indeed, the race of the gods is trustworthy.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    
                    <l n="55"> Changing places in alternation, the Dioscuri spend one day beside
                        their dear father Zeus, and the other beneath the depths of the earth in the
                        hollows of Therapne, each fulfilling an equal destiny, since Polydeuces
                        preferred this life to being wholly a god and living in heaven, when Castor
                        was killed in battle. </l>
                    <l n="60"> For Idas, angered for some reason about his cattle, stabbed him with
                        the point of his bronze spear. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="61"> Looking out from Taÿgetus, Lynceus saw them seated in the hollow of
                        an oak <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Reading
                                <foreign xml:lang="grc">h(me/nous</foreign> (Boeckh), although
                            Didymus defends <foreign xml:lang="grc">h(me/nos</foreign> as a Doric
                            acc. </note> ; for that man had the sharpest eye of all who live on
                        earth. He and Idas at once reached the spot with swift feet, and quickly
                        contrived a mighty deed; </l>
                    <l n="65"> and these sons of Aphareus themselves suffered terribly by the
                        devising of Zeus. For right away Polydeuces the son of Leda came in pursuit.
                        They were stationed opposite, near the tomb of their father; <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="67"> from there they seized the grave-column, monument to Hades, a
                        polished stone, and hurled it at the chest of Polydeuces. But they did not
                        crush him, or drive him back; rushing forward with his swift javelin, </l>
                    <l n="70"> he drove its bronze point into the ribs of Lynceus, and Zeus hurled
                        against Idas a fiery smoking thunderbolt. They burned together, deserted.
                        Strife with those who are stronger is a harsh companion for men. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 5"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="73"> Swiftly Polydeuces the son of Tyndareus went back to his mighty
                        brother, and found him not yet dead, but shuddering with gasps of breath. </l>
                    <l n="75"> Shedding warm tears amid groans, he spoke aloud: “Father, son of
                        Cronus, what release will there be from sorrows? Order me to die too, along
                        with him, lord. A man's honor is gone when he is deprived of friends; but
                        few mortals are trustworthy in times of toil <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 5"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="79"> to share the hardship.” So he spoke. And Zeus came face to face with
                        him, </l>
                    <l n="80"> and said these words: “You are my son. But Castor was begotten after
                        your conception by the hero, your mother's husband, who came to her and
                        sowed his mortal seed. But nevertheless I grant you your choice in this. If
                        you wish to escape death and hated old age, and to dwell in <placeName
                            key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> yourself with me and with Athena
                        and Ares of the dark spear, <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 5"/>
                    </l>
                    
                    <l n="85"> you can have this lot. But if you strive to save your brother, and
                        intend to share everything equally with him, then you may breathe for half
                        the time below the earth, and for half the time in the golden homes of
                        heaven.” When Zeus had spoken thus, Polydeuces did not have a second
                        thought. </l>
                    <l n="90"> He opened the eye, and then released the voice of the bronze-clad
                        warrior, Castor. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" subtype="poem" type="textpart" n="11">
                    <head>
                        <title>Nemean 11</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Aristagoras of Tenedos</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">on his installation as President of the
                            Council</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0446">446</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Daughter of Rhea, you who have received the town hall under your
                        protection, Hestia, sister of Zeus the highest and of Hera who shares his
                        throne, welcome Aristagoras to your dwelling, and welcome to a place near
                        your splendid scepter his companions, </l>
                    <l n="5"> who, in honoring you, guard Tenedos and keep her on a straight course;
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="6"> often they worship you, first of the gods, with libations, and often
                        with the savor of burnt sacrifice. Lyres and songs peal among them, and
                        Themis, who belongs to Zeus the god of hospitality, is honored with
                        everlasting feasts. With glory to the end </l>
                    <l n="10"> may he fulfill his twelve-month office, with his heart unwounded.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="11"> I call that man blessed in his father Hagesilas, in his marvellous
                        body, and in his inborn steadiness. But if any man who has prosperity
                        surpasses others in beauty, and displays his strength by being best in the
                        games, </l>
                    <l n="15"> let him remember that his robes are thrown around mortal limbs, and
                        that he will clothe himself with earth, the end of all. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="17"> Yet it is right for him to be praised in the good words of his
                        fellow-citizens, and for us to adorn him with the honeyed sound of songs.
                        For in contests of those who live around him, sixteen </l>
                    <l n="20"> splendid victories crowned Aristagoras and his illustrious
                        fatherland, in wrestling and in the proud pancratium. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="22"> But the too hesitant hopes of his parents restrained the boy's
                        strength from attempting the contests at <placeName key="tgn,7010770"
                            >Pytho</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Olympia"
                            >Olympia</placeName> . For I swear by the power of Oath: in my judgment,
                        whether he went to Castalia </l>
                    <l n="25"> or to the well-wooded hill of Cronus, he would have returned home in
                        finer fashion than the opponents who strove against him, <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="27"> having celebrated the four years' festival ordained by Heracles, and
                        having crowned his hair with purple wreaths. But, among mortals,
                        empty-headed pride </l>
                    <l n="30"> casts one man out of his goods; and a timid spirit foils another man
                        of the fine achievements that should be his, dragging him back by the hand
                        as he disparages his own strength too much. <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="33"> Truly, it was easy to recognize in him the ancient blood of Peisander
                        of Sparta, who came from Amyclae with Orestes, </l>
                    <l n="35"> leading here a bronze-armored host of Aetolians, and also the
                        blending of his blood with that of his mother's ancestor Melanippus, beside
                        the stream of the Ismenus. But ancient excellence <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="38"> yields strength in alternate generations of men; the dark fields do
                        not give fruit continuously, </l>
                    <l n="40"> nor are trees accustomed to bear an equal wealth of fragrant flowers
                        in every circling year, but in alternation. And thus the race of mortal men
                        is led <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="43"> by Fate. But no clear sign comes to mortals from Zeus. Nevertheless
                        we embark on bold endeavors, </l>
                    <l n="45"> longing for many deeds, for our limbs are bound by shameless hope,
                        while the streams of foresight lie far away. But we must hunt for due
                        measure in our love of gain. The madness of unattainable desires is too
                        sharp. </l>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
