<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Olympiodorus </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>It is perhaps necessary, men of the jury, even for those who have neither
                    practice nor skill in speaking to come into court when they have been wronged by
                    anyone, especially if it be by those who should be the last to wrong them, as
                    has now come to pass with me. For, although I have been unwilling, men of the
                    jury, to go to law with Olympiodorus, who is a relative of mine and whose sister
                    is my wife, I have been forced to do so because of the magnitude of the wrongs
                    which he has done me. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>If I were entering upon this course, men of the jury, without having been
                    wronged, or were trumping up a false charge against Olympiodorus, or if I were
                    unwilling to refer the matter to men who are friends both of Olympiodorus and
                    myself, or if I were refusing to adopt any other fair course of action, be
                    assured that I should be thoroughly ashamed, and should think myself a worthless
                    sort of fellow: but as it is, the loss I have suffered at the hands of
                    Olympiodorus is no small one; I have not refused to accept any referee, and I
                    swear by Zeus the Supreme that it is not willingly, but with the utmost possible
                    reluctance, that I have been forced by the defendant to bring this suit. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>I beg of you, therefore, men of the jury, when you have heard us both and have
                    sifted the matter for yourselves, preferably to find some settlement of our
                    quarrel and dismiss us, and thus become benefactors of us both; but if you
                    cannot succeed in this, of the courses remaining open to you, I beg you to give
                    your vote to him whose plea is just.First, then, the clerk shall read to you the
                    depositions which show that it is not I who am responsible for bringing the case
                    into court, but the defendant himself.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Read the
                        depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>That I offered reasonable and fitting terms to Olympiodorus has been testified to
                    you, men of the jury, by those who were present. Since, however, he does not
                    choose to do anything that is right, it is necessary for me to set forth before
                    you the matters in which I have been wronged by him. But the story is a short
                    one. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>There was a certain Comon of Halae,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There were
                        two demes of this name, one on the east coast of Attica and the other on the
                        Saronic Gulf. The former belonged to the tribe Aegeis, the latter to the
                        tribe Cecropis. There is nothing to show which one is here referred
                        to.</note> men of the, jury, a relative of ours. This Comon died without
                    issue after a very short illness; he had lived, however, many years, and was an
                    old man when he died. When I saw that he could not possibly recover, I sent for
                    the defendant Olympiodorus that he might be with us, and join with us in taking
                    all proper measures. And Olympiodorus, when he had come to me and to my wife,
                    who is his own sister, aided us in making all the arrangements. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>While we were thus occupied, this fellow Olympiodorus suddenly flung at me the
                    statement that his mother also was related to Comon, the dead man, and that it
                    was fair that he, too, should receive his share of all the property which Comon
                    left. I for my part, men of the jury, as I knew that he was lying and trying to
                    put a bold face on it, and that there was nobody else nearer of kin to Comon
                    than myself, became at first exceedingly wroth and indignant at the
                    shamelessness of his claim; presently, however, I reflected that it was not a
                    proper time for anger, and I made answer to him, that for the present it was our
                    duty to bury the dead man and do all else that custom called for, and that after
                    we should have discharged all these duties we would talk with one another. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>And Olympiodorus, men of the jury, assented to this, and said that I was quite
                    right. So when we had finished all this, and had done all that custom required,
                    we called in all our relatives and quietly discussed with one another the claims
                    which this fellow advanced. Now, men of the jury, why should I weary you or
                    myself by relating the various differences which arose between us as we talked
                    these matters over? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>The conclusion to which we came, however, it is necessary for you to hear. I
                    myself reached the decision regarding his claims, and he regarding mine, that we
                    should each take half of what Comon left, and there should be no further
                    unpleasantness between us. I chose, men of the jury, voluntarily to share the
                    inheritance with him rather than come into court and risk a trial with the
                    fellow, who is a relative, and to say unpleasant things of one who is a brother
                    of my wife and the uncle of my children, and hear disagreeable things from him.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>Thinking of all these things I came to terms with him.After this we drew up
                    written articles of agreement regarding all matters involved, and swore solemn
                    oaths to one another that we would in very truth divide fairly and honestly all
                    the visible property that there was, and that neither of us would in any respect
                    take advantage of the other in regard to Comon's estate; that we would make
                    joint inquiry for the rest, and would act in common in forming whatever plans
                    should from time to time be necessary. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>For we suspected, men of the jury, that others besides ourselves would come to
                    lay claim to the estate of Comon. For instance, there was my brother, on my
                    father's but not my mother's side, who was out of the country; and, if anyone
                    else wished to put in a claim, there was no way for us to prevent it; for the
                    laws ordain that anyone who chooses may put in a claim. Foreseeing all these
                    contingencies, we drew up our articles of agreement and swore our oaths in order
                    that neither of us might have the opportunity of doing anything whatever
                    independently, whether he should wish to do so or not, but that we should do
                    everything by mutual agreement. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>And we called to witness this agreement, first the gods in whose name we
                    exchanged our oaths, and our own relatives, and moreover Androcleides of
                        Acharnae,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Acharnae was a deme of the tribe
                        Oeneïs.</note> with whom we deposited the articles.<milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/>I wish now, men of the jury, to read the law in accordance with
                    which we drew up our agreement, and deposition of the person who has the
                    articles in his keeping.Read the law first.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>Now read the deposition of Androcleides.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>When we had exchanged oaths, and the articles had been deposited with
                    Androcleides, I divided the property into two shares, men of the jury. One share
                    consisted of the house in which Comon himself had lived, and the slaves engaged
                    in weaving sackcloth, and the other of another house and the slaves engaged in
                    grinding colors. Whatever ready money Comon left in the bank of Heracleides had
                    been nearly all spent on his burial and the other funeral rites, and on the
                    building of his tomb. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>And after I had divided the property into these two shares, I gave Olympiodorus
                    his choice to take whichever of the two shares he pleased; and he chose the
                    color-grinders and the small house, while I took the weavers and the
                    dwelling-house. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>This is what each of us had. Now in the share of this fellow Olympiodorus there
                    was a man, one of the color-grinders, whom Comon used to regard as most faithful
                    to himself; the man's name was Moschion. This slave had a pretty good knowledge
                    of all Comon's other affairs, and in particular knew where the money was which
                    Comon kept in the house; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>and Comon, who was oldish and who had confidence in him, was unaware that this
                    slave Moschion was stealing his money. He first stole from him one thousand
                    drachmae, which sum was kept separate from the rest of the money, and afterwards
                    seventy minae more. He was doing this without Comon's suspecting it, and the
                    fellow kept all this money in his own possession. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>Soon after we had divided the shares between us, men of the jury, we became
                    suspicious, and found out something about this money; and as a result of this
                    suspicion Olympiodorus here and I decided to put the man to the torture. And the
                    fellow, men of the jury, before he was put to the torture, voluntarily confessed
                    that he had stolen a thousand drachmae from Comon, and said that he still had in
                    his quarters all the money which had not been spent; but of the larger sum he
                    did not say a word at that time. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>So he paid back about six hundred drachmae. And of this sum which the man paid
                    back we made a just and fair division in accordance with the oaths which we had
                    sworn and the agreement deposited with Androcleides, I taking one half and the
                    defendant Olympiodorus the other. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>Not long after this, as a result of the suspicion against the slave in regard to
                    the money, the defendant had the man bound and again put to the torture. He did
                    this independently by himself without calling me in, although he had sworn to
                    make all inquiries and do everything in concert with me. And the fellow, men of
                    the jury, when racked by the torture made further confession that he had stolen
                    from Comon the seventy minae; and he restored this entire sum to the defendant
                    Olympiodorus. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>I, on my part, men of the jury, when I learned that the man had been tortured,
                    and that he had restored the money, supposed that Olympiodorus would pay me half
                    the amount, just as he had before paid me half of the one thousand drachmae. At
                    first I did not press him, thinking that he would recognize his obligation and
                    arrange matters for my interest and his own, so that each of us should have what
                    was fair in accordance with our oaths and our mutual agreement to share equally
                    in all that Comon left; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>but since he delayed, and did nothing, I had a talk with this man Olympiodorus,
                    and demanded that I receive my share of the money. But Olympiodorus here kept
                    finding one excuse after another, and putting me off. Moreover, at this very
                    time some other people filed claims to the estate of Comon, and Callippus, my
                    brother on my father's side, returned from abroad; and he too filed a claim for
                    half the estate. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>So Olympiodorus found in this another excuse for not paying me the money, since
                    there were many who were laying claim to the estate; and he said that I must
                    wait until the suits were settled. And I had to consent to this, and I did
                    consent. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>After this the defendant Olympiodorus and I took
                    counsel together, as we had sworn to do, to determine the best and safest way to
                    deal with the other claimants. And we decided, men of the jury, that the
                    defendant Olympiodorus should lay claim to the whole estate, and that,I should
                    claim a half, seeing that my brother Callippus claimed a half only. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>When all the claims had been heard before the archon, and the cases were due to
                    be tried in court, the defendant Olympiodorus and I were wholly unprepared for
                    an immediate trial because those who had suddenly appeared as claimants were so
                    many. However, in view of the situation that had developed, we looked into
                    things jointly to see if in any way a postponement could be brought about for
                    the present, so that we might get ourselves ready for the trial at our leisure.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>And it happened by a piece of good luck that you were persuaded by the
                    politicians to despatch troops into Acarnania,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Acarnania was a state on the west coast of Greece, north of the Gulf of
                        Corinth.</note> and the defendant Olympiodorus was among those called to
                    service, and he departed with the others on the expedition. Thus had come about,
                    as we thought, an excellent ground for postponement, the defendant being abroad
                    on military service. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>So, when the archon summoned into court all those who were filing claims
                    according to law, I entered a sworn statement, asking postponement on the ground
                    that the defendant Olympiodorus was abroad on military service, but to this
                    sworn statement our adversaries opposed another, attacking Olympiodorus; and as
                    they had the last word, they induced the jurors to decide that the defendant was
                    absent on account of the trial and not on public service. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>When the jurors had thus decided, the archon Pythodotus<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The date was <date when="-0343">343</date> B.C.</note> in
                    accordance with the law struck out the claim of the defendant; and when this
                    claim was stricken out I necessarily had to abandon my claim to half the estate.
                    After these steps had been taken, the archon adjudged the estate of Comon to our
                    opponents; for the laws compelled him to do so. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>They, as soon as they had won the adjudication, went at once to the Peiraeus and
                    proceeded to take over all that either of us had received from the division. I,
                    being at home, voluntarily gave over to them what I had (for it was necessary to
                    obey the laws), but since Olympiodorus was abroad, they carried off all his
                    effects except the money which he had separately taken from the man—the slave
                    whom he had put to the torture; for they had no means of getting hold of that
                    money. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Such were the events which happened in the absence
                    of Olympiodorus, and such the benefit I derived from my association with him.
                    But when he returned with the rest of the troops, the defendant Olympiodorus was
                    indignant, men of the jury, at what had occurred, and thought he had been
                    outrageously treated. However, when he was at the height of his indignation, we
                    again looked matters over, the defendant Olympiodorus and I, and took counsel
                    together to see how we could get back something of what we had lost. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>And as a result of our consultation we decided to summon into court in due legal
                    form those who had had the property adjudged to them; and in the circumstances
                    it seemed to be the safest course not to risk a joint suit against the other
                    claimants, but for each to act separately; and for the defendant Olympiodorus to
                    enter suit for the whole estate as he had done before, and conduct his case by
                    himself, and for me to enter suit for a half, since my brother Callippus claimed
                    the half only; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>so that, if Olympiodorus should win his case, I, in accordance with our agreement
                    and our oaths, might recover my share from him, while, if he should lose it and
                    the jurors give an adverse verdict, he might fairly and honestly recover his
                    share from me in accordance with our oaths and the agreement made between us.
                    After we had reached this conclusion, and it seemed safest both for Olympiodorus
                    and for me, all those who were in possession of the estate of Comon were
                    summoned according to law.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Read, please, the law
                    in accordance with which the summons was given.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="31">
                <p>It was in accordance with this law, men of the jury, that the summons was given,
                    and that we filed our counter-claims in the manner approved by Olympiodorus.
                    After this the archon conducted the preliminary examination for all claimants,
                    and when he had concluded this he brought the case into court. The defendant
                    Olympiodorus was the first to plead, and he said whatever he pleased and offered
                    whatever testimony he saw fit, while I, men of the jury, sat in silence on the
                    opposite platform. Since the trial had been fixed in this way, Olympiodorus
                    easily won his case; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="32">
                <p>but when he had got the verdict and we had accomplished in the court-room all
                    that we wished, when he had recovered from those who had previously won the
                    adjudication all that they had taken from us,—although he has all this now in
                    his possession as well as the money which he got from the slave who was put to
                    the torture, he has refused to do anything whatever that is fair toward me, but
                    keeps everything himself, even though he has given his oath and made an
                    agreement with me that in very truth we should take equal shares. These articles
                    of agreement are still up to this day in the custody of Androcleides, who has
                    himself given testimony before you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="33">
                <p>I wish, however, to bring before you depositions proving all the other statements
                    I have made, but first of all, to prove that at the outset the defendant and I,
                    having settled our differences by ourselves, took each an equal share of all the
                    property left by Comon of which we had knowledge.Take, please, this deposition
                    first, and then read all the rest.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="34">
                <p>Now, please take the challenge which I tendered him regarding the money which he
                    got from the slave who was put to the torture.<quote type="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote>Read now the other deposition, too, proving that, when our opponents had
                    received the adjudication, they took from us all that we had except the money
                    which Olympiodorus got from the man who was put to the torture.<quote
                        type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="35">
                <p>In what way, men of the jury, Olympiodorus and I originally divided between us
                    the visible estate of Comon, you have both heard from my statement, and it has
                    been proved to you by witnesses; and you have also learned that the defendant
                    got the sum of money from the slave, and that those who had previously won the
                    adjudication took all that was in our possession, until Olympiodorus won a
                    verdict in the second trial. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="36">
                <p>Now hear the reason which he gives for not paying me what is due, and for
                    refusing to do anything whatever that is fair; and to this, men of the jury, I
                    bid you give close heed, in order that you may not be misled presently by the
                    orators whom he has engaged against me.This defendant never says the same thing,
                    but one thing now and another then, just as it happens. He goes about bringing
                    forward absurd excuses, baseless insinuations, and false charges, and acts in
                    the whole business as a man of bad faith. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="37">
                <p>Hosts of people have heard him say, sometimes that he never got the money from
                    the slave at all; but again, when the contrary has been proved, he says that he
                    got the money from his own slave, and that he will give me no share of this
                    money or of anything else of the estate which Comon left. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="38">
                <p>And when anyone of our common friends asks him why he refuses to pay me, when he
                    has sworn to share everything equally and when the articles of agreement are
                    still in custody, he asserts that I have broken the agreement and have treated
                    him outrageously, and he states that I have all along been speaking and acting
                    in opposition to him. These are the excuses he offers. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="39">
                <p>The statements which the fellow makes, men of the jury, are insinuations which he
                    has himself made up, false excuses, and bits of trickery, got up with a view to
                    defrauding me of what he ought to pay me. But what I shall say to you to prove
                    that he is lying will be no mere insinuation on the contrary I shall prove in
                    glaring fashion his shamelessness, advancing proofs that are trustworthy and
                    known to everybody, and bringing forward witnesses regarding every point. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="40">
                <p>In the first place, men of the jury, I say that the defendant refused to refer
                    our differences to our common friends and relatives who had full knowledge of
                    all the circumstances of the case, and had followed them from the beginning; for
                    this reason, that he had full knowledge that if he made use of any falsehoods,
                    he would be refuted by them on the spot, whereas he thinks that now he may
                    perhaps lie before you without being detected. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="41">
                <p>Again I say, it is not consistent, Olympiodorus, that I should act in opposition
                    to you, and yet should join with you in expending whatever from time to time
                    became necessary, or that I should myself voluntarily abandon my claim, when you
                    were abroad and your claim was stricken off because it was thought that you were
                    absent on account of the trial and not on public service. For it was open to me
                    to press my own claim for one-half the estate; no human being opposed my claim,
                    but my opponents themselves allowed it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="42">
                <p>However, had I done this, I should by that very act have perjured myself, for I
                    had sworn and contracted with you to do in concert with you whatever should seem
                    to us on consultation to be best. Therefore the pretexts and charges on which
                    you base your refusal to act fairly toward me are absolutely silly. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="43">
                <p>And furthermore—do you suppose, Olympiodorus, that in the last trial for the
                    estate I should have permitted you either to utter so recklessly the statements
                    which you made to the jury, or to bring forward witnesses as you did regarding
                    the points you wished to prove, if I had not been acting in concert with you in
                    the trial?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="44">
                <p>For the fellow, men of the jury, said everything else that he pleased in the
                    court-room, and emphatically stated to the jurymen that I had rented from him
                    the house which I received as part of my share, and that I had borrowed of him
                    the money which I received—the half, that is, of the thousand drachmae recovered
                    from the slave. And he not only made these statements, but he produced
                    depositions to support them. And I said nothing whatever against all this, nor
                    did any human being hear a syllable aloud or muttered from me while he was
                    supporting his claim, but I admitted the truth of everything he chose to say.
                    For I was cooperating with you, Olympiodorus, according to our agreement. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="45">
                <p>If what I am saying is not true, why did I not proceed against the witnesses who
                    gave this evidence instead of keeping absolute silence? Or why did you,
                    Olympiodorus, never sue me for the rent of the house which you alleged was your
                    own and had been rented by you to me; or for the money which you told the
                    jurymen you had lent me? Why, I say, did you do neither of these things? How,
                    then, could any man be more clearly convicted than you have been of lying, of
                    making contradictory statements, and of preferring charges that lack all
                    foundation? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="46">
                <p>But here is the strongest proof of all, which will convince you, men of the jury,
                    of his bad faith and covetousness. If there were any truth in what he says, he
                    should have stated it and proved it before the trial came on, and before he
                    tested the jury as to how it would decide; and he should have taken a number of
                    witnesses and demanded that the articles of agreement be taken from the custody
                    of Androcleides on the ground that I was violating them, and acting against his
                    interests, and that the articles were no longer in force between him and me;
                    also he should have protested to Androcleides, who had the articles in his
                    possession, that he had no longer anything to do with these articles. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="47">
                <p>This is what he should have done, men of the jury, if there were any truth in
                    what he says; he should have gone by himself to Androcleides, and made this
                    protest, and gone also with many witnesses, in order that he might have many
                    persons who were aware of the fact.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But to prove
                    that he never took any of these steps, the clerk shall read you the deposition
                    of Androcleides himself with whom the articles of agreement are deposited.Read
                    the deposition.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="48">
                <p>Now, men of the jury, you must consider another thing which he has done. I
                    tendered him a challenge, and demanded that he go with me to Androcleides, with
                    whom the articles are deposited, and that we should jointly make copies of the
                    agreement and seal it up again, but that we should put the copies in the
                    evidence-box, in order that there might be no ground for suspicion, but that you
                    might hear everything plainly and fairly, and then vote as should seem to you
                    most just. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="49">
                <p>I tendered him this challenge, but he refused to do anything of the sort; no, he
                    has tried thus artfully to prevent your hearing the agreement from copies
                    jointly made.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To prove that I tendered him this
                    challenge, the clerk shall read you the deposition of the persons in whose
                    presence I tendered it. Read the deposition.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="50">
                <p>How, then, could it be made more plain that the fellow is unwilling to act justly
                    toward me in any way, that he thinks to rob me of what I ought to receive by
                    advancing excuses and preferring charges, and that he determined that you should
                    not hear the agreement which he asserts I have broken? But I challenged him then
                    before the witnesses who were present, and I challenge him again now before you
                    jurymen, and I demand that he consent, and I myself do consent, to have the
                    articles of agreement opened here in the court-room, to let you hear them, and
                    to have them sealed up again in your presence. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="51">
                <p>Androcleides is present here; for I gave him notice to come and bring the
                    articles of agreement. I consent, men of the jury, that they be opened during
                    the defendant's speech, in either his first or his second, it makes no
                    difference to me. But I wish you to hear the agreement and the oaths which
                    Olympiodorus the defendant and I swore to one another. If he consents, let this
                    be done, and do you hear for yourselves the articles when he shall see fit; and
                    if he refuses to take this course, will it not be plain without further proof,
                    men of the jury, that he is the most shameless of humankind, and that you may
                    rightly refuse to accept as true anything whatever that he says? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="52">
                <p>But why am I so earnest in urging this? The defendant himself knows well that he
                    has sinned against me and sinned against the gods in whose name he swore, and
                    that he is a perjurer. But something has deranged him, men of the jury, and he
                    is not in his senses. I am pained and I feel shame, men of the jury, at what I
                    am about to tell you, but I am forced to tell it, in order that you, in whose
                    hands the verdict lies, may hear all the facts before you reach the conclusion
                    regarding us which may seem to you best. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="53">
                <p>For my mentioning the things which I am about to tell you this fellow is himself
                    to blame, since he refused to settle our differences among our relatives, but
                    chose to brazen the matter out. For you must know, men of the jury, that this
                    fellow Olympiodorus has never married an Athenian woman in accordance with your
                    laws; he has no children nor has ever had any, but he keeps in his house a
                    mistress whose freedom he had purchased, and it is she who is the ruin of us all
                    and who drives the man on to a higher pitch of madness. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="54">
                <p>Is it not indeed a proof of his madness that he refuses to do anything whatever
                    that was stipulated in the agreement which was entered into with his full
                    consent and with my own, and which was confirmed by an oath?—especially when I
                    am striving, not in my own interest only, but in the interest of her to whom I
                    am married, his own sister, born of the same father and the same mother, and in
                    the interest of his niece, my daughter. For they are being wronged not less than
                    I, but even more. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="55">
                <p>Can anyone, indeed, say that they are not wronged and are not suffering
                    outrageous treatment, when they see this fellow's mistress, in defiance of all
                    decency, decked out with masses of jewels and with fine raiment, going abroad in
                    splendid state and flaunting the luxury purchased with what is ours, while they
                    are themselves too poor to enjoy such things? Are they not suffering a wrong
                    even greater than my own? And in adopting such a manner of life is not
                    Olympiodorus not manifestly mad and beside himself?<milestone ed="P" unit="para"
                    />Now, that he may not claim, men of the jury, that I am speaking thus with a
                    view to slandering him because of this suit, the clerk shall read you a
                    deposition from his relatives and mine.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="56">
                <p>The defendant Olympiodorus, then, is a person of this sort. He is not only
                    dishonest, but in the opinion of all his relatives and friends is proved by the
                    manner of life which he has adopted to be mentally deranged; to use the language
                    of the lawgiver Solon, he is beside himself as no other man ever was, for he is
                    under the influence of a woman who is a harlot. And Solon established a law<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This law is cited in <bibl n="Dem. 46.14">Dem.
                            46.14</bibl></note> that all acts shall be null and void which are done
                    by anyone under the influence of a woman, especially of a woman of her stamp.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="57">
                <p>In this matter the lawgiver made wise provision; and I entreat you—and not I
                    only, but my wife also, the sister of this Olympiodorus, and my daughter, his
                    niece,we all beg and implore you, men of the jury, (for I would have you imagine
                    that these women are here present before you), </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="58">
                <p>if it be possible, to prevail upon this fellow Olympiodorus not to do us wrong,
                    but if he refuses, and you cannot prevail upon him, then to bear in mind all
                    that has been said and give whatever verdict shall seem to you best and most in
                    accordance with justice. If you do this, you will reach a decision that is fair
                    and one that is to the advantage of us all, and especially to the advantage of
                    this fellow Olympiodorus himself.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
