<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Macartatus</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <editor role="translator">A. T. Murray</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">1996</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes Vol. V. Private Orations, XLI-XLIX. With an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date type="printing">1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/privateorationsw02demouoft">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>   
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="section"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-02-06" who="Lisa Cerrato">CTS and EpiDoc conversion</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg043.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
                <head>Sositheus Against Macartatus, In Regard to the Estate of Hagnias</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Since we have had suits before now, men of the jury, against these same men regarding the estate of Hagnias, and they do not cease from their lawless and violent conduct, endeavoring by hook or crook to keep what does not belong to them, it is perhaps necessary to set forth all that has been done from the beginning; </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>for you, men of the jury, will thus more easily follow the course of the whole argument, <milestone unit="section" resp="editor" n="2"/>and these men will be exhibited in their true character, and you will see that they began long ago and still continue to play their tricks, and to think that they may do whatever occurs to them. We therefore beg of you, men of the jury, to listen to our arguments with goodwill, and to follow with close attention. And I, on my part, will endeavor to give you the clearest information I can concerning the facts.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p rend="indent">The mother of this boy, men of the jury, being the nearest of kin to Hagnias of Oeon,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There were two demes bearing the name Oeon, one belonging to the tribe Leontis, the other to the tribe Hippothontis.</note> had the estate of Hagnias adjudged to her according to your laws; and of those who then made counter-claims to this estate not one ventured to swear that he was nearer of kin than the lady (for it was admitted by all that the inheritance belonged to her by virtue of nearest kinship), </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>but Glaucus of Oeon and Glaucon his brother presented themselves, having concocted a spurious will, and Theopompus, the father of Macartatus here, joined with them in getting up this whole scheme, and was their witness in most of the depositions that were put in. The will which they then produced was proved to be spurious, and they not only lost their case, but went out of court completely disgraced.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And Theopompus, the father of Macartatus here, although he was in town when the herald asked by proclamation whether anyone wished to lay claim to the estate of Hagnias by virtue of kinship or under a will, or to deposit security for the costs of such claim, yet did not venture to make a deposit, but by his own act gave judgement against himself that he had no conceivable claim on the estate of Hagnias.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>But, although the mother of this boy here became possessed of the inheritance, since she had prevailed in the suit over all those who disputed her claim, these men are abominable, as you see, and imagine that they need obey neither your laws nor the decisions of your courts, but they are trying by fair means or foul once more to take away from the lady the inheritance which you awarded to her.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>A conspiracy was formed, and a written agreement entered into, and deposited with Medeius of Hagnus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Hagnus was a deme of the tribe Acamantis.</note> by Theopompus, the father of Macartatus here, and by Glaucon and the Glaucus who was worsted in the former suit; and they added to themselves as a fourth another of their friends (Eupolemus was his name). All these men, having in common formed their plot, cited the lady before the archon for the adjudication of claims to the estate of Hagnias, declaring that the law prescribed that if anyone wished to enter a claim, citation should be made of the one to whom the estate had been adjudged and who had it in his possession.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>And when the archon brought the case into court, and the trial was to be held, they had everything cleverly arranged for the trial, and in particular the water which was to measure their speeches was four times as much as that allowed to us. For the archon, men of the jury, was obliged to pour into the water-clock an amphora<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The amphora contained about nine gallons.</note> of water for each claimant, and three choes<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The chous contained about 1/12 of an amphora.</note> for the reply; </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>so that I, who acted as pleader for the lady, was not only unable to explain to the jurymen the relationship and other matters as clearly as I could have wished, but could not even defend myself against the smallest fraction of the lies which they told about us; for I had but a fifth part of the water. Their scheme was this: to tell a wholly false story about us, but to back one another up and agree in everything.</p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p>So, since they had formed their plot in this way, and each backed up the other’s charges against us, when the four ballot-boxes<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">One ballot-box, that is, for each contestant. There were five in all, but the two brothers, Glaucus and Glaucon, were apparently counted as one, since their title was the same. This problem is discussed by Wyse in his introduction to <bibl n="Isaeus 11.1">Isaeus Hag.</bibl>.</note> were set out according to law, the jurymen, naturally enough, as I think, were deceived and could not agree with one another, and being led astray by this trick, they voted each as chance determined. And there were a very few more votes—some three or four—in the box of Theopompus than in that of the lady.</p></div> 
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p rend="indent">This, then, was what took place at that time. But when this boy was born, and it seemed a fitting time, I, being in no way incensed at what had happened, but considering that the former jurymen had met with a very natural experience, introduced this boy here to the clansmen of Hagnias in the interest of Eubulides, seeing that the boy was the son of his daughter, in order that the family might not become extinct.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p>For the elder Eubulides, men of the jury, who was next of kin to Hagnias, prayed to the gods above all else that a son might be born to him as a daughter had been, the mother of this boy; but since he failed of this hope and not a single male child was born to him, his next dearest wish was that a son of his daughter should be adopted into his own family and that of Hagnias and should be introduced to the members of his clan; for he thought, men of the jury, that of his surviving relatives this boy was nearest to him, and that in this way their house would best be preserved and kept from extinction.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p>And I was the one to render him this service, since I was husband to the daughter of Eubulides, she having been adjudged to me as being the nearest of kin, and I introduced this boy to the clansmen of Hagnias and Eubulides, to which fellowship Theopompus, the father of Macartatus here, belonged during his lifetime, and to which Macartatus now belongs.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"><p>And the fellow-clansmen of Macartatus here, who knew better than any others the pedigree of the family, seeing that he himself did not choose to risk a contest and did not remove the victim from the altar, as he should have done had the introduction of this boy not been legitimate, but demanded that they commit perjury,6 took the ballot while the victims were still burning, and carried it from the altar of Zeus Phatrius<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">So named, as god of the clan (phratry)—which was a religious institution.</note> in the presence of the defendant Macartatus, and gave a just verdict, men of the jury—that this boy was duly and rightfully introduced as the adopted son of Eubulides into the family of Hagnias.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15"><p>But when the fellow-clansmen of the defendant Macartatus had passed this vote, this boy, as the son of Eubulides, cited the defendant Macartatus for an adjudication of claims for the estate of Hagnias, and had a day appointed by the archon for the hearing, inscribing his brother’s name as his guardian; for it was no longer open to me, men of the jury, to stand inscribed as guardian, since I had got the boy adopted into the family of Eubulides. And the citation was made by this boy according to the same laws in accordance with which these men had cited his mother, who had won the former suit in court, and was in possession of the estate of Hagnias.</p></div> 
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16"><p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> Please read the law which ordains that citation shall be made of the person possessing the inheritance.</p> <p rend="center"><label>The Law</label></p> <p rend="indent"><quote type="statute">If any person shall claim the inheritance or the heiress after adjudication has been made, let him cite before the archon the person who has obtained the adjudication just as in other suits, and a deposit to cover costs shall be made by the claimant. And if he wins an adjudication without citation, the adjudication of the estate shall be of no effect. And if the person who has had the estate adjudged to him be not living, let the claimant cite in like manner the successor, provided that the period covered by the statute of limitations has not expired.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This period was five years.</note> And the claim upon the possessor shall be that he shall show on what terms the person whose property he holds had it adjudged to him.</quote></p></div> 
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17"><p rend="indent">You have heard the law, and it is a reasonable request I make of you, men of the jury. If I shall prove to you that this boy Eubulides here and Phylomachê, who is the mother of the boy and the daughter of Eubulides, are nearer of kin to Hagnias than Theopompus, the father of Macartatus, and not only that they are nearest of kin, but that there is absolutely no human being belonging to the house of Hagnias except the mother of this boy and the boy himself,—if I shall prove this, I beg of you, men of the jury, to give your aid to us.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18"><p rend="indent">At the first, men of the jury, it was my intention to write on a board all the kinsfolk of Hagnias, and thus to exhibit them to you one by one; but when I saw plainly that not all the jurymen would have an equally good view, but that those sitting at a distance would be at a disadvantage, it is perhaps necessary to instruct you by word of mouth, for thus all will be on the same footing. I, on my part, will endeavor to the best of my ability to inform you regarding the family of Hagnias in the fewest words possible.</p></div> 
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19"><p rend="indent">Buselus, men of the jury, was a member of the deme Oeon, and to him were born five sons, Hagnias and Eubulides and Stratius and Habron and Cleocritus. And all these sons of Buselus grew up to manhood, and their father Buselus divided his property among them all fairly and equitably, as was fitting. And when they had divided the property among themselves, each of them married a wife according to your laws, and sons and grandsons were born to them all, and there sprang up five households from the single one of Buselus; and they dwelt apart, each one having his own home and begetting his descendants.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20"><p>Now with regard to three of the brothers, sons of Buselus, and the descendants born to them, why should I trouble you, men of the jury, or myself by going into particulars about each one? For although they are in the same degree of relationship as Theopompus, and are as near of kin to Hagnias, whose estate is in question, not one of them has ever troubled us either at an earlier time or now, nor has made any claim to the estate of Hagnias or to the woman who is the heiress, who was assigned in marriage to me; for they considered that they had no claim whatever to anything belonging to Hagnias.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21"><p>It seems to me therefore that it would be entirely superfluous to say anything about them save only what I cannot help mentioning. Of Theopompus, however, the father of Macartatus, and of Macartatus the defendant himself, it is necessary for me to speak. Yet the story, men of the jury, is a short one. As you have just heard, Buselus had five sons. One of these was Stratius, the ancestor of Macartatus, and another was Hagnias, the ancestor of this boy.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22"><p>To Hagnias was born a son, Polemon, and a daughter, Phylomachê, sister of Polemon by the same father and the same mother; and to Stratius, the brother of Hagnias, there were born Phanostratus and Charidemus, the grandfather of the defendant Macartatus. Now I ask you, men of the jury, which is nearer of kin and more closely related to Hagnias, his son Polemon and his daughter Phylomachê, or Charidemus, the son of Stratius, and nephew of Hagnias? For my part I think that to every one of us his son and daughter are more nearly related than his nephew; and not only with us does this hold good, but also among all other people whether Greeks or barbarians.</p></div> 
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23"><p>Since, then, this is admitted, you will now easily follow the rest of the argument men of the jury, and you will see how arbitrary and how reckless these men are.</p> <p rend="indent">To Polemon, son of Hagnias, was born a son, Hagnias, having the name of his grandfather Hagnias, and this second Hagnias died without issue.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24"><p>But from Phylomachê, the sister of Polemon, and Philagrus, to whom her brother Polemon had given her in marriage, he being his first cousin (for Philagrus was the son of Eubulides, the brother of Hagnias)—from Philagrus, I say, the cousin of Polemon, and Phylomachê the sister of Polemon, there was born Eubulides the father of this boy’s mother. These sons, then, were born to Polemon and to Polemon’s sister Phylomachê. But to Charidemus, the son of Stratius, there was born a son Theopompus, the father of the defendant Macartatus.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25"><p>Again, then, I ask you, men of the jury, which is nearer of kin and more closely related to the first Hagnias, Hagnias, the son of Polemon, and Eubulides, the son of Phylomachê and Philagrus, or Theopompus, the son of Charidemus and grandson of Stratius? I am of the opinion, men of the jury, that if the son and the daughter are the nearest of kin, so, too, the son’s son and the daughter’s son are more nearly related than the son of a nephew and one who is a member of another branch of the family.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26"><p>Well, to Theopompus was born a son, Macartatus, the defendant, and to Eubulides, the son of Phylomachê, and cousin of Hagnias on his father’s side; this boy, who is to Hagnias the son of a first cousin on the father’s side; since Phylomachê, the mother of Eubulides and Polemon, the father of Hagnias, were brother and sister, born of the same father and the same mother. But to Macartatus here, the son of Theopompus, there has been no issue which is both in the family of Hagnias and in that of Stratius.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27"><p>Such being the facts, this boy here has one of the titles mentioned in the law, and up to which the law ordains that the right of succession should extend; for he is the child of the first cousin of Hagnias, since his father Eubulides was cousin to Hagnias, whose inheritance is in question. Theopompus, on the contrary, the father of the defendant Macartatus, could not have appropriated to himself any one of the titles mentioned in the law, for he belonged to another branch of the family, that of Stratius.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28"><p>But it is not fitting, men of the jury, that any man whatsoever should possess the estate of Hagnias, one who belongs to another branch, so long as there is left any one of those born of the branch of Hagnias; no, nor is it right to expel such person by violence, as these men are trying to do, while they are themselves more distantly related, and not of the same branch of the family. For this, men of the jury, is the point upon which Theopompus, the father of the defendant Macartatus, misled the jury.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29"><p>Who, then, are those still surviving in the branch of Hagnias? Phylomachê, my wife, who is the daughter of Eubulides, the cousin of Hagnias, and this boy, who has been adopted into the family of Eubulides and Hagnias. Theopompus, however, the father of the defendant Macartatus, not being himself of the branch of Hagnias, told the jurymen a monstrous lie regarding Phylomachê, the sister of Polemon and the aunt of Hagnias, alleging that she was not the sister of Polemon, the son of Hagnias, by the same father and mother, and another in pretending that he himself was of the same family as Hagnias, whereas he had never belonged to it.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30"><p>All these assertions Theopompus made fearlessly, not producing any witness who would have been responsible to us, but having only his associates to corroborate what he said; for they were leagued with one another and did everything in concert, in order to rob the lady, the mother of this boy here, of the inheritance which you by your votes had decided to be hers.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31"><p>I wish now, men of the jury, to produce witnesses in support of the statements which I have made to you—first, to prove that Phylomachê, the daughter of Eubulides, won judgement for the estate of Hagnias as being the nearest of kin, and then to establish the rest of the facts.</p> <p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> Read the deposition.</p> <p rend="center"><label>The Deposition</label></p> <p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponents state that they were present before the arbitrator in the archonship of Nicophemus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, in B.C. <date from="-0361" to="-0360">361</date>-360.</note> when Phylomachê, the daughter of Eubulides, won judgement for the estate of Hagnias against all who disputed her title.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32"><p rend="indent">That Phylomachê, the daughter of Eubulides, won judgement for the estate of Hagnias, you have heard, men of the jury. And she won it, not by wrongful trickery or conspiracy, but in the fairest manner possible, since we proved that she was nearest of kin to Hagnias, whose estate is in question, being the daughter of his cousin on his father’s side, and being of the same branch as Hagnias.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33"><p>When, therefore, Macartatus says that his father Theopompus won judgement for this estate, make answer to him on your part, men of the jury, that the lady also won judgement before Theopompus, the defendant’s father, and that the lady won her case fairly, since she was of the same branch as Hagnias, being the daughter of Eubulides, the cousin of Hagnias, but that Theopompus did not win the suit, but prevailed by trickery, being himself in no sense whatever of the branch of Hagnias.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34"><p>Make this reply to him yourselves, men of the jury, and also state that against this boy Eubulides, son of Eubulides, son of the first cousin on his father’s side of Hagnias, whose estate is in question, neither Theopompus, the father of Macartatus, nor any other man ever at any time won a judgement. At the present time the contest and the trial to adjudge the estate of Hagnias are between this son of Eubulides and the defendant Macartatus, the son of Theopompus; and whichever of these two shall in your judgement speak most in harmony with justice and the laws, to him, it is plain, you jurymen will give your votes.</p></div> 
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35"><p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> Read the remaining depositions; first, those proving that Phylomachê, the aunt of Hagnias, was sister by the same father and the same mother to Polemon, the father of Hagnias; after that he shall read all the other depositions which have to do with the pedigree.</p> <p rend="center"><label>The Depositions</label></p> <p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponents testify that they are fellow-demesmen of Philagrus, the father of Eubulides, and Polemon, the father of Hagnias, and that they know that Phylomachê, the mother of Eubulides, was considered to be the sister of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, by the same father and the same mother, and that they never heard from anyone that Polemon, the son of Hagnias, had a brother.</quote></p> <p rend="center"><label>Another</label></p></div> 
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36"><p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponents testify that Oenanthê, the mother of their grandfather Stratonides, was first cousin to Polemon, the father of Hagnias, their fathers having been brothers, and that they heard from their own father that Polemon, the father of Hagnias, never had any brother, but had a sister, born of the same father and the same mother, namely Phylomachê, the mother of Eubulides, the father of Phylomachê, wife of Sositheus.</quote></p> <p rend="center"><label>Another</label></p> <p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponent testifies that he is a relative and fellow-clansman and fellow-demesman of Hagnias and Eubulides, and that he heard from his own father and other relatives that Polemon, the father of Hagnias, never had any brother, but had a sister, born of the same father and the same mother, namely Phylomachê, the mother of Eubulides, the father of Phylomachê, wife of Sositheus.</quote></p> <p rend="center"><label>Another</label></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37"><p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponent testifies that Archimachus was his grandfather and adopted him as his son, and that he was a relative of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, and that he heard from Archimachus and his other relatives that Polemon, the father of Hagnias, never had any brother, but had a sister, born of the same father and the same mother, namely Phylomachê, the mother of Eubulides, the father of Phylomachê, wife of Sositheus.</quote></p> <p rend="center"><label>Another</label></p> <p rend="indent"><quote rend="deposition">The deponent testifies that his wife’s father Callistratus was first cousin to Polemon, the father of Hagnias, and to Charidemus, the father of Theopompus, their fathers having been brothers, and that his mother was daughter of a first cousin to Polemon, and that their mother often said to them that Phylomachê, the mother of Eubulides, was sister of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, born of the same father and the same mother, and that Polemon, the father of Hagnias, never had any brother.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38"><p rend="indent">In the former trial, men of the jury, when these men formed their conspiracy with one another and acted in concert, the whole group of them, in their contest against the lady, we, on our part, men of the jury, neither prepared depositions regarding facts that were admitted, nor summoned witnesses, but thought that in these matters at least we were perfectly safe; whereas our opponents had equipped themselves with all manner of shameless artifices for the trial, and had their minds set upon this thing alone—to deceive the jurymen for the moment.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39"><p>They had the audacity to assert that Polemon, the father of Hagnias, had no sister at all born of the same father and the same mother; so abominably impudent were they, seeking to mislead the jurymen in a matter of such importance and so well-known, and they spent all their efforts and strove beyond all else to establish this. We have, however, on this present occasion produced this host of witnesses regarding the sister of Polemon and aunt of Hagnias.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40"><p>On the defendant’s side let whoever will give evidence either that Polemon and Phylomachê were not brother and sister, born of the same father and the same mother, or that Polemon was not the son, and Phylomachê not the daughter, of Hagnias, the son of Buselus; or that Polemon was not the father of Hagnias, whose estate is in question, and Phylomachê, the sister of Polemon, not his aunt; </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41"><p>or that Eubulides was not the son of Phylomachê, or of Philagrus, the cousin of Hagnias; or this, that the still-living Phylomachê is not the daughter of Eubulides, the cousin of Hagnias, and this boy not his son, adopted according to your laws into the family of Eubulides or that Theopompus, the father of the defendant, Macartatus, belonged to the branch of Hagnias. Let anyone give testimony in his favor on whatever one of these points he chooses. But I know well that no mortal man will be so daring or so senseless.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42"><p rend="indent">However, that it may be the more clear to you, men of the jury, that in the former trial they got the upper hand through their shameless audacity, and that they advanced no just arguments, <label>(to the clerk)</label> read all the depositions that remain.</p> <p rend="center"><label>The Depositions</label></p> <p rend="center"><quote type="deposition">The deponent testifies that he is a relative of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, and that he heard from his father that Philagrus, the father of Eubulides, and Phanostratus, the father of Stratius, and Callistratus, the father of the wife of Sosias, and Euctemon, who was king,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, king-archon.</note> and Charidemus, the father of Theopompus and Stratocles, were first cousins to Polemon, their fathers all having been brothers, and that Eubulides, with reference to his father Philagrus, stood in the same degree of relationship as the sons of these men and Hagnias, while with reference to his mother Phylomachê, he was recognized as the first cousin of Hagnias on his father’s side, since he was the son of the paternal aunt of Hagnias.</quote></p> <p rend="center"><label>Another</label></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43"><p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponents testify that they are relatives of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, and of Philagrus, the father of Eubulides, and of Euctemon, who was king, and that they know that Euctemon was brother by the same father to Philagrus, the father of Eubulides, and that when suit for the adjudication of the estate of Hagnias was instituted by Eubulides against Glaucon, Euctemon was still living, being first cousin to Polemon, the father of Hagnias, their fathers having been brothers, and that Euctemon did not dispute with Eubulides his title to the estate of Hagnias, nor did anyone else on the score of kinship on that occasion.</quote></p> <p rend="center"><label>Another</label></p></div> 
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44"><p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponents testify that their father Strato was a relative of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, and of Charidemus, the father of Theopompus, and of Philagrus, the father of Eubulides, and that they heard from their father that Philagrus took for his first wife Phylomachê, the sister of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, born of the same father and the same mother, and that Philagrus had by Phylomachê a son Eubulides, and that after the death of Phylomachê Philagrus took a second wife Telesippê, and there was born a brother to Eubulides, namely Menestheus, of the same father but not of the same mother; and that when Eubulides made claim to the estate of Hagnias on the score of kinship, Menestheus did not dispute his title to the estate of Hagnias, nor did Euctemon, the brother of Philagrus, nor did anyone else on the score of kinship dispute the title of Eubulides on that occasion.</quote></p> <p rend="center"><label>Another</label></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45"><p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponent testifies that his father Archimachus was a relative of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, and of Charidemus, the father of Theopompus, and of Philagrus, the father of Eubulides, and that he heard from their father that Philagrus took for his first wife Phylomachê, the sister of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, born of the same father and the same mother, and that by Phylomachê he had a son Eubulides, and that after the death of Phylomachê Philagrus took a second wife Telesippê, and that Philagrus had by Telesippê a son Menestheus, a brother to Eubulides, of the same father but not of the same mother; and that when Eubulides. made claim to the estate of Hagnias on the score of kinship, Menestheus did not dispute his claim to the estate, nor did Euctemon, the brother of Philagrus, nor did anyone else on the score of kinship dispute the title of Eubulides on that occasion.</quote></p> <p rend="center"><label>Another</label></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46"><p rend="indent"><quote type="deposition">The deponent testifies that his mother’s father Callistratus was brother to Euctemon, who was king, and to Philagrus, the father of Eubulides, and that these men were first cousins to Polemon the father of Hagnias, and to Charidemus, the father of Theopompus, and that he heard from his mother that Polemon, the father of Hagnias, had no brother, but had a sister Phylomachê, born of the same father and the same mother, and that Philagrus married this Phylomachê, and they had a son Eubulides, the father of Phylomachê, the wife of Sositheus.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47"><p rend="indent">It was necessary to read these depositions, men of the jury, in order that we might not suffer the same experience as before, by being caught by these men unprepared. But far more convincing even than these shall be the testimony that Macartatus will give against himself, proving that neither his father Theopompus nor himself has any claim whatever to inherit anything from Hagnias, Theopompus being less near of kin, and belonging to quite a different branch of the family.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48"><p>For suppose one should ask, men of the jury, Who is the person who disputes this boy’s title to the estate of Hagnias? I know well that he would say, Macartatus. Born of what father? Theopompus. And of what mother? Apolexis, daughter of a Prospaltian,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Prospalta was a deme of the tribe Acamantis.</note> and sister of Macartatus, also a Prospaltian. And who was the father of Theopompus? Charidemus. And of whom was Charidemus the son? Of Stratius. And of whom Stratius? Of Buselus. This, men of the jury, is the branch of Stratius, one of the sons of Buselus; and these whose names you have heard are descendants of Stratius; and among them there is not one single name of those belonging to the branch of Hagnias, or even one that is similar.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49"><p>Now again I shall question this boy, asking who he is who contests the claim of Macartatus to the estate of Hagnias. The boy can make no other possible answer, men of the jury, than that he is Eubulides. The son of what father? Of Eubulides, the cousin of Hagnias. And of what mother? Of Phylomachê, who was the daughter of a first cousin to Hagnias on the father’s side. But of whom was Eubulides the son? Of Philagrus, the cousin of Hagnias. And of what mother? Of Phylomachê, the aunt of Hagnias.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50"><p>And of whom was Hagnias the son? Of Polemon. And of whom Polemon? Of Hagnias. And of whom Hagnias? Of Buselus. This is another branch, that of Hagnias, one of the sons of Buselus, and here there occurs not a single name identical with those of the descendants in the branch of Stratius, or even one that is similar; but they proceed in the branch of Hagnias with their own series of names, receiving them from one another. In every respect, then, and in every way it is proved that these men belong to another branch of the family and are more remote of kin, and that they are not entitled to inherit anything of the estate of Hagnias. For to show you to whom the law-giver grants the right of succession and inheritance, the clerk will read you these laws.</p> <p rend="center"><label>The Law</label></p></div> 
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51"><p rend="indent"><quote type="statute">Whenever a man dies without making a will, if he leaves female children his estate shall go with them, but if not, the persons herein mentioned shall be entitled to his property: if there be brothers by the same father, and if there be lawfully born sons of brothers, they shall take the share of the father. But if there are no brothers or sons of brothers, their descendants shall inherit it in like manner; but males and the sons of males shall take precedence, if they are of the same ancestors, even though they be more remote of kin.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The text is not wholly certain, and the precise meaning is therefore open to debate. The law is quoted also in <bibl n="Isaeus 7.20">Isaeus 7.20</bibl>, where the note of Wyse should be consulted. See also <bibl>Meier and Schömann, <title>Der Attisch Process</title>, p. 586</bibl>, and <bibl>Savage, <title>The Athenian Family</title>, pp. 128 ff.</bibl></note> If there are no relatives on the father’s side within the degree of children of cousins, those on the mother’s side shall inherit in like manner. But if there shall be no relatives on either side within the degree mentioned, the nearest of kin on the father’s side shall inherit. But no illegitimate child of either sex shall have the right of succession either to religious rites or civic privileges, from the time of the archonship of Eucleides.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was in <date when="-0403">403</date> B.C.</note></quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52"><p rend="indent">The law, men of the jury, expressly declares to whom the inheritance shall go. Not, by Heaven, to Theopompus nor to Macartatus, the son of Theopompus, who are in no sense whatever of the family of Hagnias. But to whom does it give the inheritance? To the descendants of Hagnias, to those who are in his branch of the family. This is what the law says, and this is what justice demands.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53"><p rend="indent">Now, then, men of the jury, the law-giver has not given these rights to the relatives without imposing upon them in the law a large number of duties, which the relatives must of necessity perform. No; there are full many obligations laid upon the relatives to perform for which the law admits of no excuse; they must absolutely be performed.</p> <p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> But, preferably, read the law itself—the first one.</p> <p rend="center"><label>The Law</label></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54"><p rend="indent"><quote type="statute">In regard to all heiresses who are classified as Thetes,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Solon had divided the people into four classes: (1) Those who received from their land an income of five hundred measures of barley or wine. These were called the <q type="foreign">Pentacosiomedimini,</q> or <q type="gloss">five hundred measure men.</q> (2) those who received three hundred measures. These were assumed to be able to furnish a horse for the army, and were therefore called <q type="term">Knights.</q> (3) Those who received two hundred measures. These could presumably own a yoke of oxen and were called <q type="foreign">Zeugitae,</q> or <q type="gloss">Yolk-men.</q> (4) those receiving less, or having no property in land. These were called <q type="foreign">Thetes,</q> i.e. <q type="gloss">Laborers</q> or <q type="gloss">Serfs.</q></note> if the nearest of kin does not wish to marry one, let him give her in marriage with a portion of five hundred drachmae, if he be of the class of Pentacosiomedimni, if of the class of Knights, with a portion of three hundred, and if of the class of Zeugitae, with one hundred and fifty, in addition to what is her own. If there are several kinsmen in the same degree of relationship, each one of them shall contribute to the portion of the heiress according to his due share. And if there be several heiresses, it shall not be necessary for a single kinsman to give in marriage more than one, but the next of kin shall in each case give her in marriage or marry her himself. And if the nearest of kin does not marry her or give her in marriage, the archon shall compel him either to marry her himself or give her in marriage. And if the archon shall not compel him, let him be fined a thousand drachmae, which are to be consecrate to Hera. And let any person who chooses denounce to the archon any person who disobeys this law.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55"><p rend="indent">You hear what the law says, men of the jury. But when it became necessary to sue for the hand of the heiress Phylomachê, the mother of this boy and the daughter of the first cousin of Hagnias on his father’s side, I came forward out of respect for the law and preferred my suit as being next of kin; but Theopompus, the father of Macartatus, neither came forward nor in any way disputed my claim, because he had no semblance of right, although he was of the same age as she.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56"><p>And yet, men of the jury, how can you fail to think it strange that Theopompus never made any claim for the hand of the heiress, who was the daughter of the first cousin of Hagnias on his father’s side, and yet demands to have the estate of Hagnias contrary to the laws? Could there be persons more shameless or more abominable than these?</p> <p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> Read the other laws also.</p> <p rend="center"><label>TheLaws</label></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57"><p rend="indent"><quote type="statute">Proclamation shall be made in the market-place to the shedder of blood by a kinsman within the degree of cousin and cousinship, and cousins and sons of cousins and sons-in-law and fathers-in-law and clansmen shall join in the pursuit. To secure condonation, if there be father or brother or sons, all must concur, or whoever opposes shall prevail. And if there be none of these and the slaying was involuntary, and the Fifty-one, the Ephetae,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Ephetae formed a court of fifty-one nobles (Eupatridae) having jurisdiction over cases of homicide. See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57</bibl>, with Sandys’s note.</note> shall agree that the slaying was involuntary, let the clansmen, ten in number, grant the right of entrance to the shedder of blood, if they see fit; and let these be chosen by the Fifty-one according to rank. And those who had shed blood before the enactment of this statute shall be bound by its provisions.—And when persons die in the demes and no one takes them up for burial, let the Demarch give notice to the relatives to take them up and bury them, and to purify the deme on the day on which each of them dies.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58"><p><quote type="statute" rend="merge">In the case of slaves he shall give notice to their masters, and in the case of freemen to those possessing their property; and if the deceased had no property, the Demarch shall give notice to the relatives of the deceased. And if, after the Demarch shall have given notice, the relatives do not take up the body, the Demarch shall contract for the taking up and burial of the body, and for the purification of the deme on the same day at the lowest possible cost. And if he shall not so contract, he shall be bound to pay a thousand drachmae into the public treasury. And whatsoever he shall expend, he shall exact double the amount from those liable; and if he does not exact it he shall himself be under obligation to repay it to the demesmen. And those who do not pay the rents due for the lands of the goddess or of the gods and the eponymous heroes shall be disenfranchised, themselves and their family and their heirs, until they shall make payment.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59"><p rend="indent">All these duties which the laws lay upon relatives to perform, they lay upon us, and compel us to perform them, men of the jury. But to Macartatus here they say not a word, nor to Theopompus, his father; for they belong in no sense to the family of Hagnias. Why, then, should the laws lay any duties upon them?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60"><p rend="indent">But the defendant, men of the jury, while he has no just argument whatever to make against the laws and the depositions which we produce, makes a show of indignation, and says he is being cruelly treated because, his father being dead, it falls to him to be defendant in this suit. But he does not bear in mind, men of the jury, that his father was a mortal man, and has met his end along with many others both younger and older than himself. Yet if Theopompus, the father of the defendant, is dead, the laws are not dead, nor is justice, nor are the jurymen with whom the verdict rests.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61"><p>The present contest and the present trial are not to decide whether one man has died before or after another, but whether or not it is right that the kinsmen of Hagnias, cousins and children of cousins to Hagnias on his father’s side, should be driven out from the family of Hagnias by persons belonging to the family of Stratius, who have no shadow of right to inherit the estate of Hagnias, but are more remote of kin. This is the question at issue in the present trial.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62"><p rend="indent">You will see even more clearly, men of the jury, from the following law, that the lawgiver Solon is very much in earnest in regard to those who are relatives, and not only gives them the property left by the deceased, but also lays upon them all the burdensome obligations.</p> <p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> Read the law.</p> <p rend="center"><label>The Law</label></p> <p rend="indent"><quote type="statute">The deceased shall be laid out in the house in any way one chooses, and they shall carry out the deceased on the day after that on which they lay him out, before the sun rises. And the men shall walk in front, when they carry him out, and the women behind. And no woman less than sixty years of age shall be permitted to enter the chamber of the deceased, or to follow the deceased when he is carried to the tomb, except those who are within the degree of children of cousins; nor shall any woman be permitted to enter the chamber of the deceased when the body is carried out, except those who are within the degree of children of cousins.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63"><p rend="indent">The law does not allow any woman except female relatives within the degree of cousinship to enter the chamber where the deceased lies, and it permits these same women to follow to the tomb. Now Phylomachê, the sister of Polemon, the father of Hagnias, was not cousin to Hagnias, but aunt; for she was sister to Polemon, the father of Hagnias. But Eubulides, the son of this woman, was cousin on his father’s side to Hagnias, whose inheritance is in question. And the mother of this boy here was the daughter of Eubulides.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64"><p>These female relatives the law commanded to be present at the laying out of the deceased, and to follow to the tomb, not the mother of Macartatus nor the wife of Theopompus; for she was in no way related to Hagnias, but was of another tribe, the Acamantis, and of another deme, that of Prospalta, so that she was not even apprised in any way at the time Hagnias lay dead.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65"><p>It is surely a most outrageous result that these men are scheming to bring about, that forsooth we and the women of our family should inherit the body of Hagnias, when he was dead, and should perform all the proper rites, as being relatives and nearest of kin, but that Macartatus should claim the right to possess the estate of the dead Hagnias, though he belongs to the house of Stratius and is descended from Apolexis, daughter of the Prospaltian and sister of Macartatus. But this is neither just nor righteous, men of the jury.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66"><p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> Now please read the words of the oracle brought from <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, from the shrine of the god, that you may see that it speaks in the same terms concerning relatives as do the laws of Solon.</p> <p rend="center"><label>Oracle</label></p> <p rend="indent"><quote type="oracle">May good fortune attend you. The people of the Athenians make inquiry about the sign which has appeared in the heavens, asking what the Athenians should do, or to what god they should offer sacrifice or make prayer, in order that the issue of the sign may be for their advantage. It will be well for the Athenians with reference to the sign which has appeared in the heavens that they sacrifice with happy auspices to Zeus most high, to Athena most high, to Heracles, to Apollo the deliverer, and that they send due offerings to the Amphiones;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Possibly, Amphion and Zethus; but their tomb was near <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. See <bibl n="Paus. 9.17.4">Paus. 9.17.4</bibl></note> that they sacrifice for good fortune to Apollo, god of the ways, to Leto and to Artemis, and that they make the streets steam with the savour of sacrifice; that they set forth bowls of wine and institute choruses and wreathe themselves with garlands after the custom of their fathers, in honor of all the Olympian gods and goddesses, lifting up the right hand and the left, and that they be mindful to bring gifts of thanksgiving after the custom of their fathers. And ye shall offer sacrificial gifts after the custom of your fathers to the hero-founder after whom ye are named; and for the dead their relatives shall make offerings on the appointed day according to established custom.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67"><p rend="indent">You hear, men of the jury, that Solon in the laws and the god in the oracle use the same language, bidding the relatives to perform rites for the departed on the proper days. But neither Theopompus nor the defendant Macartatus cared at all for these things; they cared only for this, that they might retain possession of what does not belong to them, and to complain that after having had the estate for so long, they must now defend their title to it. I should have thought, men of the jury, that one who unjustly keeps in his possession the property of another, should not make complaints if he has kept it in his possession longer than is right, but should be grateful, not to us, but to fortune, that so many unavoidable delays have occurred in the interim, so that he is not brought to trial until now.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68"><p rend="indent">Our opponents, then, men of the jury, are men of this stamp; they care nothing either for the extinction of the house of Hagnias, or for all the rest of their lawless deeds; men, who, O Zeus and the gods—but why should one mention the other things relative to them? There would be much indeed to tell of. But one thing which they have brought to pass is the most lawless and the most abominable, and most clearly proves that they care for nothing except their profit.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69"><p>For no sooner had Theopompus got the award of the estate of Hagnias in the manner which you have heard, than he at once gave proof that he knew well that he was in possession of what in no sense belonged to him. The thing which was of the greatest value on the farms belonging to Hagnias, and which was most admired by the neighbors and by everybody else, was the olive trees. These they dug up and rooted out, more than a thousand trees, from which a large quantity of oil was produced. These trees our opponents rooted out and sold, and received a huge sum of money. And they did this while the estate of Hagnias was still subject to adjudication in accordance with the very law which had permitted them to cite the mother of this boy here.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70"><p rend="indent">To prove that I speak the truth in this, that they rooted up the olive trees from the farms which Hagnias left, I will produce for you as witnesses the neighbors and others whom we summoned, when we made a solemn protest against this action.</p> <p><label>(To the clerk.)</label> Read the deposition.</p> <p rend="center"><label>Deposition</label></p> <p><quote type="deposition">The deponents testify that on being summoned by Sositheus they accompanied him to <placeName key="perseus,Araphen">Araphen</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Araphen">Araphen</placeName> was a deme of the tribe Aegeïs.</note> to the lands of Hagnias, after Theopompus had had the estate of Hagnias adjudged to him, and that Sositheus showed them the olive trees being rooted up from the land of Hagnias.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71"><p rend="indent">If now, men of the jury, it were against the dead man only that they had committed an outrage in doing this, their conduct would have been disgraceful, though in a less degree; but in reality it is against the whole city that they have committed this outrage, and they have broken your laws. You will know this, when you have heard the law.</p> <p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> Read the law.</p> <p rend="center"><label>The Law</label></p> <p rend="indent"><quote type="statute">If anyone shall dig up an olive tree at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, except it be for a sanctuary of the Athenian state or of one of its demes, or for his own use to the number of two olive trees each year, or except it be needful to use it for the service of one who is dead, he shall be fined one hundred drachmae, to he paid into the public treasury, for each tree, and the tenth part of this sum shall belong to the goddess. Furthermore he shall be obligated to pay to the private individual who prosecutes him one hundred drachmae for each olive tree. And suits concerning these matters shall be brought before the archons, according as they severally have jurisdiction. And the prosecutor shall deposit the court fees for his share. And when a person shall have been convicted, the archon before whom the case was brought shall make a report to the collectors of the amount due to the treasury, and of the amount due to the goddess, to the treasurers of the goddess. And if they fail to make such reports, they shall themselves be liable for the amount.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72"><p rend="indent">The law is thus severe. But pray ponder in your minds, men of the jury, what you must imagine us to have suffered in the past from these men and the insolence of these men, when they have shown contempt toward you, so great a people, and have done what the laws expressly forbid their doing, in thus contemptuously laying waste the farms which Hagnias left. The law forbids anyone to root up any of these things even out of his own land inherited from his fathers. Much indeed do these men care either about obedience to your laws or the saving of the house of Hagnias from extinction!</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73"><p rend="indent">I desire, men of the jury, to speak to you in a few words about myself, and to prove to you that I have, in a very different way from theirs, shown my concern that the house of Hagnias should not become extinct. For I, too, am myself of the family of Buselus. For Callistratus married the granddaughter of Habron, the son of Buselus, being himself the son of Eubulides and grandson of Buselus; and from the granddaughter of Habron and Callistratus, the nephew of Habron, our mother was born.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74"><p>I myself, when I had been awarded the hand of the mother of this boy, and four sons and one daughter had been born to me, gave them, men of the jury, the following names: to the eldest I gave, as was fitting, the name of my father Sosias, and thus I gave to the eldest this name that was his due; to the son born next after him I gave the name Eubulides, which was the name of the father of this boy’s mother; to the next after him I gave the name Menestheus, for Menestheus was a relative of my wife; and to the youngest I gave the name Callistratus, which was the name of my mother’s father. In addition to all this, I did not give my daughter in marriage into another family, but to my own brother’s son, in order that, if they had health, the children born of them should be of the same family as Hagnias.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75"><p>I, then, administered matters in this way, in order that the families springing from Buselus should as completely as possible be preserved. As for our opponents, let us examine them once more.</p> <p rend="indent"><label>(To the clerk.)</label> And first of all read this law.</p> <p rend="center"><label>Law</label></p> <p><quote type="statute">Let the archon take charge of orphans and of heiresses and of families that are becoming extinct, and of all women who remain in the houses of their deceased husbands, declaring that they are pregnant. Let him take charge of these, and not suffer anyone to do any outrage to them. And if anyone shall commit any outrage or any lawless act against them, he shall have power to impose a fine upon such person up to the limit fixed by law. And if the offender shall seem to him to be deserving of a more severe punishment, let him summon such a person, giving him five days’ notice, and bring him before the court of Heliaea, writing upon the indictment the penalty which he thinks is deserved. And if there be a conviction, let the court of Heliaea appoint for the one convicted what penalty he ought to suffer or pay.</quote></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76"><p rend="indent">How, now, could people more effectively bring a house to extinction than if, being themselves of another house, that of Stratius, they should dispossess those nearest of kin to Hagnias? Or again, if one should claim to possess the estate of Hagnias as being related by blood, when he bears a name that is not only not derived from the family of Hagnias, but not even from that of Stratius, the claimant’s own ancestor—no, when he has not the name of any other of all the descendants of Buselus, many as they are?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77"><p>Whence, then, does he get the name Macartatus? From his mother’s family. For he was adopted into the family of Macartatus of Prospalta, who was his mother’s brother, and he possesses that estate also. And so regardless of right is he that, when a son was born to him, he forgot to introduce him into the family of Hagnias, as a son to Hagnias, and that too while he was in possession of the estate of Hagnias, and claimed that he was related to him by male descent.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="78"><p>This son who was born to him Macartatus has introduced by his mother’s descent into the Prospaltians, and has suffered the family of Hagnias to become extinct, so far as this boy is concerned; but he alleges that his own father Theopompus was related to Hagnias. Yet the law of Solon ordains that males and the sons of males shall have precedence; but the defendant has thus lightly shown contempt both for Hagnias and for the laws, and has had his son introduced into the family of his mother. How could there be people more scornful of law or more arbitrary than these?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="79"><p rend="indent">Now this is not the only thing, men of the jury. There is a place of burial common to all those descended from Buselus (it is called the burial-place of the Buselidae, a large area, enclosed, after the manner of the men of old). In this burial-place lie all the other descendants of Buselus and Hagnias and Eubulides and Polemon, and all the rest of the host of those descended from Buselus, all these hold in common this place of burial.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="80"><p>But the father of the defendant Macartatus and the grandfather have no share in it, but they made for themselves a tomb apart, at a distance from that of the Buselidae. Do they appear to you, men of the jury, to belong in any sense to the house of Hagnias, except that they have seized and hold what does not belong to them? Whether the house of Hagnias and of Eubulides, the cousin of Hagnias, is to become extinct and have no name, has never in the least degree been an object of concern to them.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="81"><p rend="indent">I for my part, men of the jury, am defending to the full extent of my power the interest of those dead relatives, but it is not an easy task to contend against the intrigues of these men. I therefore deliver over to you this boy to be the object of your care in whatever way you may deem most just. He has been adopted into the house of Eubulides, and has been introduced to the clansmen, not mine, but those of Eubulides and Hagnias and the defendant, Macartatus.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="82"><p>And when he was being introduced, the rest of the clansmen cast their votes secretly, but the defendant Macartatus by an open vote declared that this boy was being rightly introduced as a son to Eubulides; for he did not wish to lay his hand upon the victim or to remove it from the altar, and thus make himself responsible; nay, he even received his portion of the flesh from the hand of this boy, and took it away with him, as did the rest of the clansmen.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="83"><p>Consider, men of the jury, that this boy is set before you as though he were the suppliant’s wand, on behalf of the deceased Hagnias and Eubulides and the other descendants of Hagnias, and that they supplicate you jurymen not to allow their house to be brought to extinction by these loathsome monsters, who are of the house of Stratius, and never belonged to that of Hagnias. Do not suffer them to keep what is not their own, but compel them to give it back into the house of Hagnias for those who are his relatives.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="84"><p>I verily am defending the interests of those relatives who are dead, and the laws established to protect them, and I beg of you also, men of the jury, I beseech you, I implore you, do not shut your eyes to the outrage done to this boy by the defendants, nor suffer his ancestors to be treated with even greater indignity than before, as will be the case, if these men accomplish what they desire. No; rally to the defence of the laws, and take thought for the dead, that their house be not brought to extinction. By doing this you will render a verdict which is just and consonant with your oaths, and in the interest of your own selves.</p> </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
