<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Amber, or the Swan</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg005.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
    <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
    <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
<date>1913</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
</monogr>
    <series>
        <title>Loeb Classical Library</title>
    </series>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianha01luciuoft/page/74/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.b000604153?urlappend=%3Bseq=86">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
    <language ident="eng">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg005.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.1.p.75"/>
<head>Amber, or the Swan<note xml:lang="eng">The introduction to a lecture, evidently familiar to Lucian’s public under two names.</note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg005.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>
With regard to amber, you doubtless share the
general belief in the story that poplars on the banks
of the river Eridanus shed tears of it in grief over ‘
Phaethon ; and that these poplars are the sisters of
Phaethon, who out of sorrow for the boy were
changed into trees and still drip tears—of amber!
Such tales, when I heard them from the lips of the
poets, made me expect that if ever I got to the
Eridanus, by going underneath one of the poplars
and holding out a fold of my cloak I could supply
myself with amber by catching a few of their tears.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg005.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

As a matter of fact, I did visit those parts not long ago
(on another errand, to be sure) ; and as I had to go up
the Eridanus, I kept a sharp lookout, but neither
poplars nor amber were to be seen. Indeed, the very
name of Phaethon was unknown to the natives. At
any rate, when I went into the matter and inquired
when we should reach the poplars—"the amber-poplars,”—the boatmen laughed and asked me to tell
them more plainly what I meant. So I told them
the story: that Phaethon was the child of the Sun,
and that on coming of age he asked his father to
let him drive the car and “do just one day” himself ;
his father consented, and he was thrown from the
car and killed. “And his sisters,” said I, “out of


<pb n="v.1.p.77"/>

sorrow turned into poplars somewhere in this neighbourhood of yours, on the banks of the Eridanus, at
the spot where he fell, and still weep for him with .
tears of amber.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg005.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
“Who told you that?” said they.
“The cheat and liar! We never saw any driver
fall from a car,and we haven't the poplars you speak
of. If we had anything of that sort, do you suppose
that for two obols we would row or tow our boats upstream, when we could get rich by picking up the
tears. of the poplars?”’ This remark struck me
uncommonly, and I held my tongue for shame that
I had acted like a child, and no mistake, in believing
the poets, who are such incredible liars that nothing
sensible finds any favour with them.
Well, this was one great expectation that I was
disappointed in; and I was as vexed as if I had let
the amber slip through my fingers, for I was already
imagining all the different uses which I should make
of it.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg005.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

But the other story I thought I should
find completely true there—the one about troops of
swans that sing on the banks of the river. So I put
a second question to the boatmen—for we were still
on our way up. “But, how about your swans?” I
asked. “At what time do they sing so melodiously,
ranged along the river, on this side and on that?
People say, at all events, that they were associates
of Apollo, men with the gift of song, who somewhere
in these parts changed into birds, and for that
reason do not forget their music, but still continue
to sing.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg005.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
ith a burst of laughter they replied :
"Why, man, aren’t you ever going to stop telling
lies about our country and our river? We are
always on the water, and have worked on the
Eridanus since we were children, almost; now and


<pb n="v.1.p.79"/>

then we see a few swans in the marshes by the
river, and they have a very unmusical and feeble
croak ; crows or daws are Sirens to them. As for
the sweet song you speak of, we never heard it or
even dreamed of it, so we wonder how these stories
about us got to your people.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg005.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

Many such deceptions can be practised on men
when they put faith in those who exaggerate everything they tell. Therefore I am now afraid on my
own account that you who have just come to town
and are about to hear me for the first time may
expect to find amber and swans here, and after
a while may go away laughing at the men who
promised you that ‘such treasures were abundant in
my discourse. But I swear that neither you nor
anyone else ever heard me make such boasts about
my compositions, and never will! Others, to be
sure, you can find in plenty of the Eridanus kind:
their words distil very gold instead of amber, and
they are far more melodious than the swans of
poetry. But as for my talk, you already see how
simple and matter-of-fact it is, and that there is no -
music to it. So look out that you do not set your
hopes of me too high, and thereby have an experience
like people who see things under water. They expect
them to be as large as they looked through the
water, from above, when the image was magnified
under the light ; and when they fish them up, they
are annoyed to find them a great deal smaller. I
warn you, therefore, at the ‘outset—don’t expect
that when you have bailed out the water and
exposed my thoughts you will make a great haul, or
else you will have yourselves to blame for your
expectations !


<pb n="v.1.p.81"/>

<note xml:lang="eng">
It need hardly be said that this belongs to the domain of
belles lettres, not of science. Like the Italian poets of the
Renaissance, the rhetoricians of the decadence delighted to
show their cunning by “praising” all manner of things good,
bad, and indifferent.</note>
</p></div></div>
</body></text></TEI>

