<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>II Chronicles</title>
                <author role="textgroup">Old Testament</author>
                <editor role="translator">Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release" notBefore="1999-10">Perseus 3.0</date>
                <idno type="filename">tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence> 
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor>Michael Paul Johnson</editor>
                        <edition>Revision of the American Standard Version of 1901</edition>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</publisher>
                            <date>2000-2024</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="http://ebible.org/bible/web">The World English Bible</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])" n="verse">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and verse.</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])" n="chapter">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter.</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2024-10-09" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS Conversion</change>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2010-06-29" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
            <change when="2009-10-08" who="rsingh04">began reorganizing texts module by collection. created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files</change>
            <change when="2009-05-27" who="rsingh04">added/fixed cvs log keyword</change>
            <change when="1999-10-14" who="Anne Mahoney">Initial markup from flat ASCII text</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2">   
<head>The Second Book of Chronicles</head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="1"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="1"><p>Solomon the son of David was strengthened in his kingdom, and Yahweh his God was with him, and magnified him exceedingly. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="2"><p>Solomon spoke to all Israel, to the captains of thousands and of hundreds, and to the judges, and to every prince in all Israel, the heads of the fathers’ [houses]. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="3"><p>So Solomon, and all the assembly with him, went to the high place that was at Gibeon; for there was the tent of meeting of God, which Moses the servant of Yahweh had made in the wilderness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="4"><p>But the ark of God had David brought up from Kiriath Jearim to [the place] that David had prepared for it; for he had pitched a tent for it at Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="5"><p>Moreover the brazen altar, that Bezalel the son of Uri, the son of Hur, had made, was there before the tent of Yahweh: and Solomon and the assembly sought to it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="6"><p>Solomon went up there to the brazen altar before Yahweh, which was at the tent of meeting, and offered one thousand burnt offerings on it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="7"><p>In that night did God appear to Solomon, and said to him, Ask what I shall give you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="8"><p>Solomon said to God, You have shown great lovingkindness to David my father, and have made me king in his place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="9"><p>Now, Yahweh God, let your promise to David my father be established; for you have made me king over a people like the dust of the earth in multitude. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="10"><p>Give me now wisdom and knowledge, that I may go out and come in before this people; for who can judge this your people, that is so great? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="11"><p>God said to Solomon, Because this was in your heart, and you have not asked riches, wealth, or honor, nor the life of those who hate you, neither yet have asked long life; but have asked wisdom and knowledge for yourself, that you may judge my people, over whom I have made you king: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="12"><p>wisdom and knowledge is granted to you; and I will give you riches, and wealth, and honor, such as none of the kings have had who have been before you; neither shall there any after you have the like. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="13"><p>So Solomon came from the high place that was at Gibeon, from before the tent of meeting, to Jerusalem; and he reigned over Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="14"><p>Solomon gathered chariots and horsemen: and he had one thousand four hundred chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, that he placed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="15"><p>The king made silver and gold to be in Jerusalem as stones, and cedars made he to be as the sycamore trees that are in the lowland, for abundance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="16"><p>The horses which Solomon had were brought out of Egypt and from Kue; the king’s merchants purchased them from Kue. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:1" n="17"><p>They brought up and brought out of Egypt a chariot for six hundred pieces of silver, and a horse for one hundred fifty: and so for all the kings of the Hittites, and the kings of Syria, did they bring them out by their means. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="2"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="1"><p>Now Solomon purposed to build a house for the name of Yahweh, and a house for his kingdom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="2"><p>Solomon counted out seventy thousand men to bear burdens, and eighty thousand men who were stone cutters in the mountains, and three thousand and six hundred to oversee them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="3"><p>Solomon sent to Huram the king of Tyre, saying, As you did deal with David my father, and did send him cedars to build him a house to dwell therein, [even so deal with me]. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="4"><p>Behold, I am about to build a house for the name of Yahweh my God, to dedicate it to him, and to burn before him incense of sweet spices, and for the continual show bread, and for the burnt offerings morning and evening, on the Sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the set feasts of Yahweh our God. This is [an ordinance] forever to Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="5"><p>The house which I build is great; for great is our God above all gods. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="6"><p>But who is able to build him a house, seeing heaven and the heaven of heavens can’t contain him? who am I then, that I should build him a house, save only to burn incense before him? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="7"><p>Now therefore send me a man skillful to work in gold, and in silver, and in brass, and in iron, and in purple, and crimson, and blue, and who knows how to engrave [all manner of] engravings, [to be] with the skillful men who are with me in Judah and in Jerusalem, whom David my father did provide. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="8"><p>Send me also cedar trees, fir trees, and algum trees, out of Lebanon; for I know that your servants know how to cut timber in Lebanon: and, behold, my servants shall be with your servants, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="9"><p>even to prepare me timber in abundance; for the house which I am about to build shall be great and wonderful. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="10"><p>Behold, I will give to your servants, the cutters who cut timber, twenty thousand measures of beaten wheat, and twenty thousand measures of barley, and twenty thousand baths of wine, and twenty thousand baths of oil. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="11"><p>Then Huram the king of Tyre answered in writing, which he sent to Solomon, Because Yahweh loves his people, he has made you king over them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="12"><p>Huram said moreover, Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel, that made heaven and earth, who has given to David the king a wise son, endowed with discretion and understanding, that should build a house for Yahweh, and a house for his kingdom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="13"><p>Now I have sent a skillful man, endowed with understanding, of Huram my father’s, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="14"><p>the son of a woman of the daughters of Dan; and his father was a man of Tyre, skillful to work in gold, and in silver, in brass, in iron, in stone, and in timber, in purple, in blue, and in fine linen, and in crimson, also to engrave any manner of engraving, and to devise any device; that there may be [a place] appointed to him with your skillful men, and with the skillful men of my lord David your father. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="15"><p>Now therefore the wheat and the barley, the oil and the wine, which my lord has spoken of, let him send to his servants: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="16"><p>and we will cut wood out of Lebanon, as much as you shall need; and we will bring it to you in floats by sea to Joppa; and you shall carry it up to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="17"><p>Solomon numbered all the sojourners who were in the land of Israel, after the numbering with which David his father had numbered them; and they were found one hundred fifty-three thousand six hundred. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:2" n="18"><p>He set seventy thousand of them to bear burdens, and eighty thousand who were stone cutters in the mountains, and three thousand six hundred overseers to set the people at work. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="3"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="1"><p>Then Solomon began to build the house of Yahweh at Jerusalem on Mount Moriah, where [Yahweh] appeared to David his father, which he made ready in the place that David had appointed, in the threshing floor of Ornan the Jebusite. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="2"><p>He began to build in the second [day] of the second month, in the fourth year of his reign. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="3"><p>Now these are the foundations which Solomon laid for the building of the house of God. The length by cubits after the first measure was sixty cubits, and the breadth twenty cubits. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="4"><p>The porch that was before [the house], the length of it, according to the breadth of the house, was twenty cubits, and the height one hundred twenty; and he overlaid it within with pure gold. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="5"><p>The greater house he made a ceiling with fir-wood, which he overlaid with fine gold, and worked thereon palm trees and chains. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="6"><p>He garnished the house with precious stones for beauty: and the gold was gold of Parvaim. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="7"><p>He overlaid also the house, the beams, the thresholds, and the walls of it, and the doors of it, with gold; and engraved cherubim on the walls. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="8"><p>He made the most holy house: the length of it, according to the breadth of the house, was twenty cubits, and the breadth of it twenty cubits; and he overlaid it with fine gold, amounting to six hundred talents. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="9"><p>The weight of the nails was fifty shekels of gold. He overlaid the upper chambers with gold. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="10"><p>In the most holy house he made two cherubim of image work; and they overlaid them with gold. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="11"><p>The wings of the cherubim were twenty cubits long: the wing of the one [cherub] was five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house; and the other wing was [likewise] five cubits, reaching to the wing of the other cherub. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="12"><p>The wing of the other cherub was five cubits, reaching to the wall of the house; and the other wing was five cubits [also], joining to the wing of the other cherub. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="13"><p>The wings of these cherubim spread themselves forth twenty cubits: and they stood on their feet, and their faces were toward the house. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="14"><p>He made the veil of blue, and purple, and crimson, and fine linen, and worked cherubim thereon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="15"><p>Also he made before the house two pillars of thirty-five cubits high, and the capital that was on the top of each of them was five cubits. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="16"><p>He made chains in the oracle, and put [them] on the tops of the pillars; and he made one hundred pomegranates, and put them on the chains. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:3" n="17"><p>He set up the pillars before the temple, one on the right hand, and the other on the left; and called the name of that on the right hand Jachin, and the name of that on the left Boaz. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="4"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="1"><p>Moreover he made an altar of brass, twenty cubits the length of it, and twenty cubits the breadth of it, and ten cubits the height of it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="2"><p>Also he made the molten sea of ten cubits from brim to brim, round in compass; and the height of it was five cubits; and a line of thirty cubits compassed it round about. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="3"><p>Under it was the likeness of oxen, which did compass it round about, for ten cubits, compassing the sea round about. The oxen were in two rows, cast when it was cast. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="4"><p>It stood on twelve oxen, three looking toward the north, and three looking toward the west, and three looking toward the south, and three looking toward the east: and the sea was set on them above, and all their hinder parts were inward. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="5"><p>It was a handbreadth thick; and the brim of it was worked like the brim of a cup, like the flower of a lily: it received and held three thousand baths. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="6"><p>He made also ten basins, and put five on the right hand, and five on the left, to wash in them; such things as belonged to the burnt-offering they washed in them; but the sea was for the priests to wash in. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="7"><p>He made the ten lampstands of gold according to the ordinance concerning them; and he set them in the temple, five on the right hand, and five on the left. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="8"><p>He made also ten tables, and placed them in the temple, five on the right side, and five on the left. He made one hundred basins of gold. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="9"><p>Furthermore he made the court of the priests, and the great court, and doors for the court, and overlaid the doors of them with brass. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="10"><p>He set the sea on the right side [of the house] eastward, toward the south. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="11"><p>Huram made the pots, and the shovels, and the basins. So Huram made an end of doing the work that he did for king Solomon in the house of God: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="12"><p>the two pillars, and the bowls, and the two capitals which were on the top of the pillars, and the two networks to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the top of the pillars, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="13"><p>and the four hundred pomegranates for the two networks; two rows of pomegranates for each network, to cover the two bowls of the capitals that were on the pillars. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="14"><p>He made also the bases, and the basins made he on the bases; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="15"><p>one sea, and the twelve oxen under it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="16"><p>The pots also, and the shovels, and the flesh-hooks, and all the vessels of it, did Huram his father make for king Solomon for the house of Yahweh of bright brass. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="17"><p>In the plain of the Jordan did the king cast them, in the clay ground between Succoth and Zeredah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="18"><p>Thus Solomon made all these vessels in great abundance: for the weight of the brass could not be found out. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="19"><p>Solomon made all the vessels that were in the house of God, the golden altar also, and the tables whereon was the show bread; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="20"><p>and the lampstands with their lamps, to burn according to the ordinance before the oracle, of pure gold; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="21"><p>and the flowers, and the lamps, and the tongs, of gold, and that perfect gold; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:4" n="22"><p>and the snuffers, and the basins, and the spoons, and the fire pans, of pure gold: and as for the entry of the house, the inner doors of it for the most holy place, and the doors of the house, [to wit], of the temple, were of gold. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="5"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="1"><p>Thus all the work that Solomon did for the house of Yahweh was finished. Solomon brought in the things that David his father had dedicated, even the silver, and the gold, and all the vessels, and put them in the treasuries of the house of God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="2"><p>Then Solomon assembled the elders of Israel, and all the heads of the tribes, the princes of the fathers’ [houses] of the children of Israel, to Jerusalem, to bring up the ark of the covenant of Yahweh out of the city of David, which is Zion. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="3"><p>nd all the men of Israel assembled themselves to the king at the feast, which was [in] the seventh month. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="4"><p>All the elders of Israel came: and the Levites took up the ark; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="5"><p>and they brought up the ark, and the tent of meeting, and all the holy vessels that were in the Tent; these did the priests the Levites bring up. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="6"><p>King Solomon and all the congregation of Israel, that were assembled to him, were before the ark, sacrificing sheep and oxen, that could not be counted nor numbered for multitude. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="7"><p>The priests brought in the ark of the covenant of Yahweh to its place, into the oracle of the house, to the most holy place, even under the wings of the cherubim. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="8"><p>For the cherubim spread forth their wings over the place of the ark, and the cherubim covered the ark and the poles of it above. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="9"><p>The poles were so long that the ends of the poles were seen from the ark before the oracle; but they were not seen outside: and there it is to this day. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="10"><p>There was nothing in the ark save the two tables which Moses put [there] at Horeb, when Yahweh made a covenant with the children of Israel, when they came out of Egypt. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="11"><p>It happened, when the priests were come out of the holy place, (for all the priests who were present had sanctified themselves, and did not keep their courses; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="12"><p>also the Levites who were the singers, all of them, even Asaph, Heman, Jeduthun, and their sons and their brothers, arrayed in fine linen, with cymbals and psalteries and harps, stood at the east end of the altar, and with them one hundred twenty priests sounding with trumpets;) </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="13"><p>it happened, when the trumpeters and singers were as one, to make one sound to be heard in praising and thanking Yahweh; and when they lifted up their voice with the trumpets and cymbals and instruments of music, and praised Yahweh, [saying], For he is good; for his lovingkindness endures forever; that then the house was filled with a cloud, even the house of Yahweh, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:5" n="14"><p>so that the priests could not stand to minister by reason of the cloud: for the glory of Yahweh filled the house of God. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="6"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="1"><p>Then spoke Solomon, Yahweh has said that he would dwell in the thick darkness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="2"><p>But I have built you a house of habitation, and a place for you to dwell in forever. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="3"><p>The king turned his face, and blessed all the assembly of Israel: and all the assembly of Israel stood. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="4"><p>He said, Blessed be Yahweh, the God of Israel, who spoke with his mouth to David my father, and has with his hands fulfilled it, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="5"><p>Since the day that I brought forth my people out of the land of Egypt, I chose no city out of all the tribes of Israel to build a house in, that my name might be there; neither chose I any man to be prince over my people Israel: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="6"><p>but I have chosen Jerusalem, that my name might be there; and have chosen David to be over my people Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="7"><p>Now it was in the heart of David my father to build a house for the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="8"><p>But Yahweh said to David my father, Whereas it was in your heart to build a house for my name, you did well that it was in your heart: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="9"><p>nevertheless you shall not build the house; but your son who shall come forth out of your loins, he shall build the house for my name. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="10"><p>Yahweh has performed his word that he spoke; for I am risen up in the room of David my father, and sit on the throne of Israel, as Yahweh promised, and have built the house for the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="11"><p>There have I set the ark, in which is the covenant of Yahweh, which he made with the children of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="12"><p>He stood before the altar of Yahweh in the presence of all the assembly of Israel, and spread forth his hands </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="13"><p>(for Solomon had made a brazen scaffold, five cubits long, and five cubits broad, and three cubits high, and had set it in the midst of the court; and on it he stood, and kneeled down on his knees before all the assembly of Israel, and spread forth his hands toward heaven;) </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="14"><p>and he said, Yahweh, the God of Israel, there is no God like you, in heaven, or on earth; who keep covenant and lovingkindness with your servants, who walk before you with all their heart; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="15"><p>who have kept with your servant David my father that which you did promise him: yes, you spoke with your mouth, and have fulfilled it with your hand, as it is this day. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="16"><p>Now therefore, Yahweh, the God of Israel, keep with your servant David my father that which you have promised him, saying, There shall not fail you a man in my sight to sit on the throne of Israel, if only your children take heed to their way, to walk in my law as you have walked before me. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="17"><p>Now therefore, Yahweh, the God of Israel, let your word be verified, which you spoke to your servant David. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="18"><p>But will God in very deed dwell with men on the earth? behold, heaven and the heaven of heavens can’t contain you; how much less this house which I have built! </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="19"><p>Yet have you respect to the prayer of your servant, and to his supplication, Yahweh my God, to listen to the cry and to the prayer which your servant prays before you; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="20"><p>that your eyes may be open toward this house day and night, even toward the place whereof you have said that you would put your name there; to listen to the prayer which your servant shall pray toward this place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="21"><p>Listen you to the petitions of your servant, and of your people Israel, when they shall pray toward this place: yes, hear from your dwelling-place, even from heaven; and when you hear, forgive. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="22"><p>If a man sin against his neighbor, and an oath is laid on him to cause him to swear, and he comes and swears before your altar in this house; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="23"><p>then hear from heaven, and do, and judge your servants, requiting the wicked, to bring his way on his own head; and justifying the righteous, to give him according to his righteousness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="24"><p>If your people Israel be struck down before the enemy, because they have sinned against you, and shall turn again and confess your name, and pray and make supplication before you in this house; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="25"><p>then hear from heaven, and forgive the sin of your people Israel, and bring them again to the land which you gave to them and to their fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="26"><p>When the sky is shut up, and there is no rain, because they have sinned against you; if they pray toward this place, and confess your name, and turn from their sin, when you do afflict them: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="27"><p>then hear in heaven, and forgive the sin of your servants, and of your people Israel, when you teach them the good way in which they should walk; and send rain on your land, which you have given to your people for an inheritance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="28"><p>If there be in the land famine, if there be pestilence, if there be blasting or mildew, locust or caterpillar; if their enemies besiege them in the land of their cities; whatever plague or whatever sickness there be; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="29"><p>whatever prayer and supplication be made by any man, or by all your people Israel, who shall know every man his own plague and his own sorrow, and shall spread forth his hands toward this house: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="30"><p>then hear from heaven, your dwelling-place and forgive, and render to every man according to all his ways, whose heart you know; (for you, even you only, know the hearts of the children of men;) </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="31"><p>that they may fear you, to walk in your ways, so long as they live in the land which you gave to our fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="32"><p>Moreover concerning the foreigner, who is not of your people Israel, when he shall come from a far country for your great name’s sake, and your mighty hand, and your outstretched arm; when they shall come and pray toward this house: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="33"><p>then hear from heaven, even from your dwelling-place, and do according to all that the foreigner calls to you for; that all the peoples of the earth may know your name, and fear you, as does your people Israel, and that they may know that this house which I have built is called by your name. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="34"><p>If your people go out to battle against their enemies, by whatever way you shall send them, and they pray to you toward this city which you have chosen, and the house which I have built for your name; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="35"><p>then hear from heaven their prayer and their supplication, and maintain their cause. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="36"><p>If they sin against you (for there is no man who doesn’t sin), and you are angry with them, and deliver them to the enemy, so that they carry them away captive to a land far off or near; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="37"><p>yet if they shall repent themselves in the land where they are carried captive, and turn again, and make supplication to you in the land of their captivity, saying, We have sinned, we have done perversely, and have dealt wickedly; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="38"><p>if they return to you with all their heart and with all their soul in the land of their captivity, where they have carried them captive, and pray toward their land, which you gave to their fathers, and the city which you have chosen, and toward the house which I have built for your name: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="39"><p>then hear from heaven, even from your dwelling-place, their prayer and their petitions, and maintain their cause, and forgive your people who have sinned against you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="40"><p>Now, my God, let, I beg you, your eyes be open, and let your ears be attentive, to the prayer that is made in this place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="41"><p>Now therefore arise, Yahweh God, into your resting-place, you, and the ark of your strength: let your priests, Yahweh God, be clothed with salvation, and let your saints rejoice in goodness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:6" n="42"><p>Yahweh God, don’t turn away the face of your anointed: remember [your] lovingkindnesses to David your servant. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="7"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="1"><p>Now when Solomon had made an end of praying, the fire came down from heaven, and consumed the burnt offering and the sacrifices; and the glory of Yahweh filled the house. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="2"><p>The priests could not enter into the house of Yahweh, because the glory of Yahweh filled Yahweh’s house. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="3"><p>All the children of Israel looked on, when the fire came down, and the glory of Yahweh was on the house; and they bowed themselves with their faces to the ground on the pavement, and worshiped, and gave thanks to Yahweh, [saying], For he is good; for his lovingkindness endures for ever. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="4"><p>Then the king and all the people offered sacrifice before Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="5"><p>King Solomon offered a sacrifice of twenty-two thousand oxen, and a hundred and twenty thousand sheep. So the king and all the people dedicated the house of God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="6"><p>The priests stood, according to their offices; the Levites also with instruments of music of Yahweh, which David the king had made to give thanks to Yahweh, (for his lovingkindness endures for ever,) when David praised by their ministry: and the priests sounded trumpets before them; and all Israel stood. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="7"><p>Moreover Solomon made the middle of the court holy that was before the house of Yahweh; for there he offered the burnt offerings, and the fat of the peace-offerings, because the brazen altar which Solomon had made was not able to receive the burnt offering, and the meal-offering, and the fat. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="8"><p>So Solomon held the feast at that time seven days, and all Israel with him, a very great assembly, from the entrance of Hamath to the brook of Egypt. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="9"><p>On the eighth day they held a solemn assembly: for they kept the dedication of the altar seven days, and the feast seven days. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="10"><p>On the three and twentieth day of the seventh month he sent the people away to their tents, joyful and glad of heart for the goodness that Yahweh had shown to David, and to Solomon, and to Israel his people. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="11"><p>Thus Solomon finished the house of Yahweh, and the king’s house: and all that came into Solomon’s heart to make in the house of Yahweh, and in his own house, he prosperously effected. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="12"><p>Yahweh appeared to Solomon by night, and said to him, I have heard your prayer, and have chosen this place to myself for a house of sacrifice. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="13"><p>If I shut up the sky so that there is no rain, or if I command the locust to devour the land, or if I send pestilence among my people; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="14"><p>if my people, who are called by my name, shall humble themselves, and pray, and seek my face, and turn from their wicked ways; then will I hear from heaven, and will forgive their sin, and will heal their land. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="15"><p>Now my eyes shall be open, and my ears attentive, to the prayer that is made in this place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="16"><p>For now have I chosen and made this house holy, that my name may be there forever; and my eyes and my heart shall be there perpetually. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="17"><p>As for you, if you will walk before me as David your father walked, and do according to all that I have commanded you, and will keep my statutes and my ordinances; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="18"><p>then I will establish the throne of your kingdom, according as I covenanted with David your father, saying, There shall not fail you a man to be ruler in Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="19"><p>But if you turn away, and forsake my statutes and my commandments which I have set before you, and shall go and serve other gods, and worship them; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="20"><p>then will I pluck them up by the roots out of my land which I have given them; and this house, which I have made holy for my name, will I cast out of my sight, and I will make it a proverb and a byword among all peoples. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="21"><p>This house, which is so high, everyone who passes by it shall be astonished, and shall say, Why has Yahweh done thus to this land, and to this house? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:7" n="22"><p>They shall answer, Because they forsook Yahweh, the God of their fathers, who brought them forth out of the land of Egypt, and laid hold on other gods, and worshiped them, and served them: therefore has he brought all this evil on them. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="8"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="1"><p>It happened at the end of twenty years, in which Solomon had built the house of Yahweh, and his own house, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="2"><p>that the cities which Huram had given to Solomon, Solomon built them, and caused the children of Israel to dwell there. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="3"><p>Solomon went to Hamath-zobah, and prevailed against it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="4"><p>He built Tadmor in the wilderness, and all the store-cities, which he built in Hamath. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="5"><p>Also he built Beth Horon the upper, and Beth Horon the lower, fortified cities, with walls, gates, and bars; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="6"><p>and Baalath, and all the store-cities that Solomon had, and all the cities for his chariots, and the cities for his horsemen, and all that Solomon desired to build for his pleasure in Jerusalem, and in Lebanon, and in all the land of his dominion. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="7"><p>As for all the people who were left of the Hittites, and the Amorites, and the Perizzites, and the Hivites, and the Jebusites, who were not of Israel; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="8"><p>of their children who were left after them in the land, whom the children of Israel didn’t consume, of them did Solomon raise a levy [of bondservants] to this day. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="9"><p>But of the children of Israel did Solomon make no servants for his work; but they were men of war, and chief of his captains, and rulers of his chariots and of his horsemen. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="10"><p>These were the chief officers of king Solomon, even two hundred fifty, who ruled over the people. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="11"><p>Solomon brought up the daughter of Pharaoh out of the city of David to the house that he had built for her; for he said, My wife shall not dwell in the house of David king of Israel, because the places are holy, whereunto the ark of Yahweh has come. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="12"><p>Then Solomon offered burnt-offerings to Yahweh on the altar of Yahweh, which he had built before the porch, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="13"><p>even as the duty of every day required, offering according to the commandment of Moses, on the Sabbaths, and on the new moons, and on the set feasts, three times in the year, [even] in the feast of unleavened bread, and in the feast of weeks, and in the feast of tents. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="14"><p>He appointed, according to the ordinance of David his father, the courses of the priests to their service, and the Levites to their offices, to praise, and to minister before the priests, as the duty of every day required; the doorkeepers also by their courses at every gate: for so had David the man of God commanded. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="15"><p>They didn’t depart from the commandment of the king to the priests and Levites concerning any matter, or concerning the treasures. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="16"><p>Now all the work of Solomon was prepared to the day of the foundation of the house of Yahweh, and until it was finished. [So] the house of Yahweh was completed. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="17"><p>Then went Solomon to Ezion Geber, and to Eloth, on the seashore in the land of Edom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:8" n="18"><p>Huram sent him by the hands of his servants ships, and servants who had knowledge of the sea; and they came with the servants of Solomon to Ophir, and fetched from there four hundred fifty talents of gold, and brought them to king Solomon. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="9"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="1"><p>When the queen of Sheba heard of the fame of Solomon, she came to prove Solomon with hard questions at Jerusalem, with a very great train, and camels that bore spices, and gold in abundance, and precious stones: and when she was come to Solomon, she talked with him of all that was in her heart. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="2"><p>Solomon told her all her questions; and there was not anything hid from Solomon which he didn’t tell her. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="3"><p>When the queen of Sheba had seen the wisdom of Solomon, and the house that he had built, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="4"><p>and the food of his table, and the sitting of his servants, and the attendance of his ministers, and their clothing, his cup bearers also, and their clothing, and his ascent by which he went up to the house of Yahweh; there was no more spirit in her. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="5"><p>She said to the king, It was a true report that I heard in my own land of your acts, and of your wisdom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="6"><p>However I didn’t believe their words, until I came, and my eyes had seen it; and, behold, the half of the greatness of your wisdom was not told me: you exceed the fame that I heard. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="7"><p>Happy are your men, and happy are these your servants, who stand continually before you, and hear your wisdom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="8"><p>Blessed be Yahweh your God, who delighted in you, to set you on his throne, to be king for Yahweh your God: because your God loved Israel, to establish them forever, therefore made he you king over them, to do justice and righteousness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="9"><p>She gave the king one hundred and twenty talents of gold, and spices in great abundance, and precious stones: neither was there any such spice as the queen of Sheba gave to king Solomon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="10"><p>The servants also of Huram, and the servants of Solomon, who brought gold from Ophir, brought algum trees and precious stones. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="11"><p>The king made of the algum trees terraces for the house of Yahweh, and for the king’s house, and harps and psalteries for the singers: and there were none such seen before in the land of Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="12"><p>King Solomon gave to the queen of Sheba all her desire, whatever she asked, besides that which she had brought to the king. So she turned, and went to her own land, she and her servants. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="13"><p>Now the weight of gold that came to Solomon in one year was six hundred and sixty-six talents of gold, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="14"><p>besides that which the traders and merchants brought: and all the kings of Arabia and the governors of the country brought gold and silver to Solomon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="15"><p>King Solomon made two hundred bucklers of beaten gold; six hundred [shekels] of beaten gold went to one buckler. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="16"><p>[he made] three hundred shields of beaten gold; three hundred [shekels] of gold went to one shield: and the king put them in the house of the forest of Lebanon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="17"><p>Moreover the king made a great throne of ivory, and overlaid it with pure gold. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="18"><p>nd there were six steps to the throne, with a footstool of gold, which were fastened to the throne, and stays on either side by the place of the seat, and two lions standing beside the stays. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="19"><p>Twelve lions stood there on the one side and on the other on the six steps: there was nothing like it made in any kingdom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="20"><p>All king Solomon’s drinking vessels were of gold, and all the vessels of the house of the forest of Lebanon were of pure gold: silver was nothing accounted of in the days of Solomon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="21"><p>For the king had ships that went to Tarshish with the servants of Huram; once every three years came the ships of Tarshish, bringing gold, and silver, ivory, and apes, and peacocks. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="22"><p>So king Solomon exceeded all the kings of the earth in riches and wisdom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="23"><p>All the kings of the earth sought the presence of Solomon, to hear his wisdom, which God had put in his heart. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="24"><p>They brought every man his tribute, vessels of silver, and vessels of gold, and clothing, armor, and spices, horses, and mules, a rate year by year. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="25"><p>Solomon had four thousand stalls for horses and chariots, and twelve thousand horsemen, that he bestowed in the chariot cities, and with the king at Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="26"><p>He ruled over all the kings from the River even to the land of the Philistines, and to the border of Egypt. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="27"><p>The king made silver to be in Jerusalem as stones, and cedars made he to be as the sycamore trees that are in the lowland, for abundance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="28"><p>They brought horses for Solomon out of Egypt, and out of all lands. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="29"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Solomon, first and last, aren’t they written in the history of Nathan the prophet, and in the prophecy of Ahijah the Shilonite, and in the visions of Iddo the seer concerning Jeroboam the son of Nebat? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="30"><p>Solomon reigned in Jerusalem over all Israel forty years. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:9" n="31"><p>Solomon slept with his fathers, and he was buried in the city of David his father: and Rehoboam his son reigned in his place. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="10"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="1"><p>Rehoboam went to Shechem; for all Israel were come to Shechem to make him king. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="2"><p>It happened, when Jeroboam the son of Nebat heard of it, (for he was in Egypt, where he had fled from the presence of king Solomon,) that Jeroboam returned out of Egypt. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="3"><p>They sent and called him; and Jeroboam and all Israel came, and they spoke to Rehoboam, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="4"><p>Your father made our yoke grievous: now therefore make you the grievous service of your father, and his heavy yoke which he put on us, lighter, and we will serve you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="5"><p>He said to them, Come again to me after three days. The people departed. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="6"><p>King Rehoboam took counsel with the old men, who had stood before Solomon his father while he yet lived, saying, What counsel give you me to return answer to this people? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="7"><p>They spoke to him, saying, If you are kind to this people, and please them, and speak good words to them, then they will be your servants forever. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="8"><p>But he forsook the counsel of the old men which they had given him, and took counsel with the young men who had grown up with him, who stood before him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="9"><p>He said to them, What counsel give you, that we may return answer to this people, who have spoken to me, saying, Make the yoke that your father did put on us lighter? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="10"><p>The young men who had grown up with him spoke to him, saying, Thus shall you tell the people who spoke to you, saying, Your father made our yoke heavy, but make you it lighter to us; thus shall you say to them, My little finger is thicker than my father’s loins. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="11"><p>Now whereas my father did lade you with a heavy yoke, I will add to your yoke: my father chastised you with whips, but I [will chastise you] with scorpions. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="12"><p>So Jeroboam and all the people came to Rehoboam the third day, as the king bade, saying, Come to me again the third day. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="13"><p>The king answered them roughly; and king Rehoboam forsook the counsel of the old men, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="14"><p>and spoke to them after the counsel of the young men, saying, My father made your yoke heavy, but I will add thereto: my father chastised you with whips, but I [will chastise you] with scorpions. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="15"><p>So the king didn’t listen to the people; for it was brought about of God, that Yahweh might establish his word, which he spoke by Ahijah the Shilonite to Jeroboam the son of Nebat. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="16"><p>When all Israel saw that the king didn’t listen to them, the people answered the king, saying, What portion have we in David? neither have we inheritance in the son of Jesse: every man to your tents, Israel: now see to your own house, David. So all Israel departed to their tents. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="17"><p>But as for the children of Israel who lived in the cities of Judah, Rehoboam reigned over them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="18"><p>Then king Rehoboam sent Hadoram, who was over the men subject to forced labor; and the children of Israel stoned him to death with stones. King Rehoboam made speed to get him up to his chariot, to flee to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:10" n="19"><p>So Israel rebelled against the house of David to this day. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="11"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="1"><p>When Rehoboam was come to Jerusalem, he assembled the house of Judah and Benjamin, one hundred eighty thousand chosen men, who were warriors, to fight against Israel, to bring the kingdom again to Rehoboam. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="2"><p>But the word of Yahweh came to Shemaiah the man of God, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="3"><p>Speak to Rehoboam the son of Solomon, king of Judah, and to all Israel in Judah and Benjamin, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="4"><p>Thus says Yahweh, You shall not go up, nor fight against your brothers: return every man to his house; for this thing is of me. So they listened to the words of Yahweh, and returned from going against Jeroboam. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="5"><p>Rehoboam lived in Jerusalem, and built cities for defense in Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="6"><p>He built Bethlehem, and Etam, and Tekoa, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="7"><p>Beth Zur, and Soco, and Adullam, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="8"><p>and Gath, and Mareshah, and Ziph, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="9"><p>and Adoraim, and Lachish, and Azekah, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="10"><p>and Zorah, and Aijalon, and Hebron, which are in Judah and in Benjamin, fortified cities. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="11"><p>He fortified the strongholds, and put captains in them, and stores of victuals, and oil and wine. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="12"><p>In every city [he put] shields and spears, and made them exceeding strong. Judah and Benjamin belonged to him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="13"><p>The priests and the Levites who were in all Israel resorted to him out of all their border. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="14"><p>For the Levites left their suburbs and their possession, and came to Judah and Jerusalem: for Jeroboam and his sons cast them off, that they should not execute the priest’s office to Yahweh; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="15"><p>and he appointed him priests for the high places, and for the male goats, and for the calves which he had made. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="16"><p>After them, out of all the tribes of Israel, such as set their hearts to seek Yahweh, the God of Israel, came to Jerusalem to sacrifice to Yahweh, the God of their fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="17"><p>So they strengthened the kingdom of Judah, and made Rehoboam the son of Solomon strong, three years; for they walked three years in the way of David and Solomon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="18"><p>Rehoboam took him a wife, Mahalath the daughter of Jerimoth the son of David, [and of] Abihail the daughter of Eliab the son of Jesse; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="19"><p>and she bore him sons: Jeush, and Shemariah, and Zaham. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="20"><p>After her he took Maacah the daughter of Absalom; and she bore him Abijah, and Attai, and Ziza, and Shelomith. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="21"><p>Rehoboam loved Maacah the daughter of Absalom above all his wives and his concubines: (for he took eighteen wives, and sixty concubines, and became the father of twenty-eight sons and sixty daughters.) </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="22"><p>Rehoboam appointed Abijah the son of Maacah to be chief, [even] the prince among his brothers; for [he was minded] to make him king. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:11" n="23"><p>He dealt wisely, and dispersed of all his sons throughout all the lands of Judah and Benjamin, to every fortified city: and he gave them victuals in abundance. He sought [for them] many wives. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="12"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="1"><p>It happened, when the kingdom of Rehoboam was established, and he was strong, that he forsook the law of Yahweh, and all Israel with him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="2"><p>It happened in the fifth year of king Rehoboam, that Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, because they had trespassed against Yahweh, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="3"><p>with twelve hundred chariots, and sixty thousand horsemen. The people were without number who came with him out of Egypt: the Lubim, the Sukkiim, and the Ethiopians. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="4"><p>He took the fortified cities which pertained to Judah, and came to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="5"><p>Now Shemaiah the prophet came to Rehoboam, and to the princes of Judah, who were gathered together to Jerusalem because of Shishak, and said to them, Thus says Yahweh, You have forsaken me, therefore have I also left you in the hand of Shishak. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="6"><p>Then the princes of Israel and the king humbled themselves; and they said, Yahweh is righteous. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="7"><p>When Yahweh saw that they humbled themselves, the word of Yahweh came to Shemaiah, saying, They have humbled themselves: I will not destroy them; but I will grant them some deliverance, and my wrath shall not be poured out on Jerusalem by the hand of Shishak. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="8"><p>Nevertheless they shall be his servants, that they may know my service, and the service of the kingdoms of the countries. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="9"><p>So Shishak king of Egypt came up against Jerusalem, and took away the treasures of the house of Yahweh, and the treasures of the king’s house: he took all away: he took away also the shields of gold which Solomon had made. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="10"><p>King Rehoboam made in their place shields of brass, and committed them to the hands of the captains of the guard, who kept the door of the king’s house. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="11"><p>It was so, that as often as the king entered into the house of Yahweh, the guard came and bore them, and brought them back into the guard-chamber. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="12"><p>When he humbled himself, the wrath of Yahweh turned from him, so as not to destroy him altogether: and moreover in Judah there were good things [found]. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="13"><p>So king Rehoboam strengthened himself in Jerusalem, and reigned: for Rehoboam was forty-one years old when he began to reign, and he reigned seventeen years in Jerusalem, the city which Yahweh had chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, to put his name there: and his mother’s name was Naamah the Ammonitess. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="14"><p>He did that which was evil, because he didn’t set his heart to seek Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="15"><p>Now the acts of Rehoboam, first and last, aren’t they written in the histories of Shemaiah the prophet and of Iddo the seer, after the manner of genealogies? There were wars between Rehoboam and Jeroboam continually. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:12" n="16"><p>Rehoboam slept with his fathers, and was buried in the city of David: and Abijah his son reigned in his place. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="13"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="1"><p>In the eighteenth year of king Jeroboam began Abijah to reign over Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="2"><p>Three years reigned he in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Micaiah the daughter of Uriel of Gibeah. There was war between Abijah and Jeroboam. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="3"><p>Abijah joined battle with an army of valiant men of war, even four hundred thousand chosen men: and Jeroboam set the battle in array against him with eight hundred thousand chosen men, who were mighty men of valor. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="4"><p>Abijah stood up on Mount Zemaraim, which is in the hill-country of Ephraim, and said, Hear me, Jeroboam and all Israel: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="5"><p>Ought you not to know that Yahweh, the God of Israel, gave the kingdom over Israel to David forever, even to him and to his sons by a covenant of salt? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="6"><p>Yet Jeroboam the son of Nebat, the servant of Solomon the son of David, rose up, and rebelled against his lord. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="7"><p>There were gathered to him worthless men, base fellows, who strengthened themselves against Rehoboam the son of Solomon, when Rehoboam was young and tender-hearted, and could not withstand them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="8"><p>Now you think to withstand the kingdom of Yahweh in the hand of the sons of David; and you are a great multitude, and there are with you the golden calves which Jeroboam made you for gods. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="9"><p>Haven’t you driven out the priests of Yahweh, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites, and made you priests after the manner of the peoples of [other] lands? so that whoever comes to consecrate himself with a young bull and seven rams, the same may be a priest of [those who are] no gods. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="10"><p>But as for us, Yahweh is our God, and we have not forsaken him; and [we have] priests ministering to Yahweh, the sons of Aaron, and the Levites in their work: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="11"><p>and they burn to Yahweh every morning and every evening burnt offerings and sweet incense: the show bread also [set they] in order on the pure table; and the lampstand of gold with the lamps of it, to burn every evening: for we keep the charge of Yahweh our God; but you have forsaken him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="12"><p>Behold, God is with us at our head, and his priests with the trumpets of alarm to sound an alarm against you. Children of Israel, don’t you fight against Yahweh, the God of your fathers; for you shall not prosper. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="13"><p>But Jeroboam caused an ambush to come about behind them: so they were before Judah, and the ambush was behind them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="14"><p>When Judah looked back, behold, the battle was before and behind them; and they cried to Yahweh, and the priests sounded with the trumpets. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="15"><p>Then the men of Judah gave a shout: and as the men of Judah shouted, it happened, that God struck Jeroboam and all Israel before Abijah and Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="16"><p>The children of Israel fled before Judah; and God delivered them into their hand. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="17"><p>Abijah and his people killed them with a great slaughter: so there fell down slain of Israel five hundred thousand chosen men. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="18"><p>Thus the children of Israel were brought under at that time, and the children of Judah prevailed, because they relied on Yahweh, the God of their fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="19"><p>Abijah pursued after Jeroboam, and took cities from him, Bethel with the towns of it, and Jeshanah with the towns of it, and Ephron with the towns of it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="20"><p>Neither did Jeroboam recover strength again in the days of Abijah: and Yahweh struck him, and he died. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="21"><p>But Abijah grew mighty, and took to himself fourteen wives, and became the father of twenty-two sons, and sixteen daughters. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:13" n="22"><p>The rest of the acts of Abijah, and his ways, and his sayings, are written in the commentary of the prophet Iddo. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="14"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="1"><p>So Abijah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David; and Asa his son reigned in his place. In his days the land was quiet ten years. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="2"><p>Asa did that which was good and right in the eyes of Yahweh his God: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="3"><p>for he took away the foreign altars, and the high places, and broke down the pillars, and hewed down the Asherim, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="4"><p>and commanded Judah to seek Yahweh, the God of their fathers, and to do the law and the commandment. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="5"><p>Also he took away out of all the cities of Judah the high places and the sun-images: and the kingdom was quiet before him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="6"><p>He built fortified cities in Judah; for the land was quiet, and he had no war in those years, because Yahweh had given him rest. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="7"><p>For he said to Judah, Let us build these cities, and make about them walls, and towers, gates, and bars; the land is yet before us, because we have sought Yahweh our God; we have sought him, and he has given us rest on every side. So they built and prospered. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="8"><p>Asa had an army that bore bucklers and spears, out of Judah three hundred thousand; and out of Benjamin, that bore shields and drew bows, two hundred eighty thousand: all these were mighty men of valor. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="9"><p>There came out against them Zerah the Ethiopian with an army of a million troops, and three hundred chariots; and he came to Mareshah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="10"><p>Then Asa went out to meet him, and they set the battle in array in the valley of Zephathah at Mareshah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="11"><p>Asa cried to Yahweh his God, and said, Yahweh, there is none besides you to help, between the mighty and him who has no strength: help us, Yahweh our God; for we rely on you, and in your name are we come against this multitude. Yahweh, you are our God; don’t let man prevail against you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="12"><p>So Yahweh struck the Ethiopians before Asa, and before Judah; and the Ethiopians fled. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="13"><p>Asa and the people who were with him pursued them to Gerar: and there fell of the Ethiopians so many that they could not recover themselves; for they were destroyed before Yahweh, and before his host; and they carried away very much booty. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="14"><p>They struck all the cities round about Gerar; for the fear of Yahweh came on them: and they despoiled all the cities; for there was much spoil in them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:14" n="15"><p>They struck also the tents of cattle, and carried away sheep in abundance, and camels, and returned to Jerusalem. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="15"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="1"><p>The Spirit of God came on Azariah the son of Oded: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="2"><p>and he went out to meet Asa, and said to him, Hear you me, Asa, and all Judah and Benjamin: Yahweh is with you, while you are with him; and if you seek him, he will be found of you; but if you forsake him, he will forsake you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="3"><p>Now for a long season Israel was without the true God, and without a teaching priest, and without law: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="4"><p>But when in their distress they turned to Yahweh, the God of Israel, and sought him, he was found of them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="5"><p>In those times there was no peace to him who went out, nor to him who came in; but great vexations were on all the inhabitants of the lands. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="6"><p>They were broken in pieces, nation against nation, and city against city; for God did vex them with all adversity. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="7"><p>But be you strong, and don’t let your hands be slack; for your work shall be rewarded. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="8"><p>When Asa heard these words, and the prophecy of Oded the prophet, he took courage, and put away the abominations out of all the land of Judah and Benjamin, and out of the cities which he had taken from the hill-country of Ephraim; and he renewed the altar of Yahweh, that was before the porch of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="9"><p>He gathered all Judah and Benjamin, and those who sojourned with them out of Ephraim and Manasseh, and out of Simeon: for they fell to him out of Israel in abundance, when they saw that Yahweh his God was with him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="10"><p>So they gathered themselves together at Jerusalem in the third month, in the fifteenth year of the reign of Asa. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="11"><p>They sacrificed to Yahweh in that day, of the spoil which they had brought, seven hundred oxen and seven thousand sheep. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="12"><p>They entered into the covenant to seek Yahweh, the God of their fathers, with all their heart and with all their soul; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="13"><p>and that whoever would not seek Yahweh, the God of Israel, should be put to death, whether small or great, whether man or woman. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="14"><p>They swore to Yahweh with a loud voice, and with shouting, and with trumpets, and with cornets. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="15"><p>All Judah rejoiced at the oath; for they had sworn with all their heart, and sought him with their whole desire; and he was found of them: and Yahweh gave them rest round about. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="16"><p>Also Maacah, the mother of Asa the king, he removed from being queen, because she had made an abominable image for an Asherah; and Asa cut down her image, and made dust of it, and burnt it at the brook Kidron. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="17"><p>But the high places were not taken away out of Israel: nevertheless the heart of Asa was perfect all his days. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="18"><p>He brought into the house of God the things that his father had dedicated, and that he himself had dedicated, silver, and gold, and vessels. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:15" n="19"><p>There was no more war to the five and thirtieth year of the reign of Asa. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="16"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="1"><p>In the six and thirtieth year of the reign of Asa, Baasha king of Israel went up against Judah, and built Ramah, that he might not allow anyone to go out or come in to Asa king of Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="2"><p>Then Asa brought out silver and gold out of the treasures of the house of Yahweh and of the king’s house, and sent to Ben Hadad king of Syria, who lived at Damascus, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="3"><p>[There is] a league between me and you, as [there was] between my father and your father: behold, I have sent you silver and gold; go, break your league with Baasha king of Israel, that he may depart from me. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="4"><p>Ben Hadad listened to king Asa, and sent the captains of his armies against the cities of Israel; and they struck Ijon, and Dan, and Abel Maim, and all the store-cities of Naphtali. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="5"><p>It happened, when Baasha heard of it, that he left off building Ramah, and let his work cease. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="6"><p>Then Asa the king took all Judah; and they carried away the stones of Ramah, and the timber of it, with which Baasha had built; and he built therewith Geba and Mizpah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="7"><p>At that time Hanani the seer came to Asa king of Judah, and said to him, Because you have relied on the king of Syria, and have not relied on Yahweh your God, therefore is the host of the king of Syria escaped out of your hand. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="8"><p>Weren’t the Ethiopians and the Lubim a huge host, with chariots and horsemen exceeding many? yet, because you did rely on Yahweh, he delivered them into your hand. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="9"><p>For the eyes of Yahweh run back and forth throughout the whole earth, to show himself strong in the behalf of them whose heart is perfect toward him. Herein you have done foolishly; for from henceforth you shall have wars. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="10"><p>Then Asa was angry with the seer, and put him in the prison-house; for he was in a rage with him because of this thing. Asa oppressed some of the people at the same time. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="11"><p>Behold, the acts of Asa, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="12"><p>In the thirty-ninth year of his reign Asa was diseased in his feet; his disease was exceeding great: yet in his disease he didn’t seek Yahweh, but to the physicians. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="13"><p>Asa slept with his fathers, and died in the one and fortieth year of his reign. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:16" n="14"><p>They buried him in his own tombs, which he had hewn out for himself in the city of David, and laid him in the bed which was filled with sweet odors and various kinds [of spices] prepared by the perfumers’ are: and they made a very great burning for him. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="17"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="1"><p>Jehoshaphat his son reigned in his place, and strengthened himself against Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="2"><p>He placed forces in all the fortified cities of Judah, and set garrisons in the land of Judah, and in the cities of Ephraim, which Asa his father had taken. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="3"><p>Yahweh was with Jehoshaphat, because he walked in the first ways of his father David, and didn’t seek the Baals, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="4"><p>but sought to the God of his father, and walked in his commandments, and not after the doings of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="5"><p>Therefore Yahweh established the kingdom in his hand; and all Judah brought to Jehoshaphat tribute; and he had riches and honor in abundance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="6"><p>His heart was lifted up in the ways of Yahweh: and furthermore he took away the high places and the Asherim out of Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="7"><p>Also in the third year of his reign he sent his princes, even Ben Hail, and Obadiah, and Zechariah, and Nethanel, and Micaiah, to teach in the cities of Judah; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="8"><p>and with them the Levites, even Shemaiah, and Nethaniah, and Zebadiah, and Asahel, and Shemiramoth, and Jehonathan, and Adonijah, and Tobijah, and Tob-adonijah, the Levites; and with them Elishama and Jehoram, the priests. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="9"><p>They taught in Judah, having the book of the law of Yahweh with them; and they went about throughout all the cities of Judah, and taught among the people. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="10"><p>The fear of Yahweh fell on all the kingdoms of the lands that were round about Judah, so that they made no war against Jehoshaphat. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="11"><p>Some of the Philistines brought Jehoshaphat presents, and silver for tribute; the Arabians also brought him flocks, seven thousand and seven hundred rams, and seven thousand and seven hundred male goats. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="12"><p>Jehoshaphat grew great exceedingly; and he built in Judah castles and cities of store. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="13"><p>He had many works in the cities of Judah; and men of war, mighty men of valor, in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="14"><p>This was the numbering of them according to their fathers’ houses: Of Judah, the captains of thousands: Adnah the captain, and with him mighty men of valor three hundred thousand; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="15"><p>and next to him Jehohanan the captain, and with him two hundred eighty thousand; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="16"><p>and next to him Amasiah the son of Zichri, who willingly offered himself to Yahweh; and with him two hundred thousand mighty men of valor. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="17"><p>Of Benjamin: Eliada a mighty man of valor, and with him two hundred thousand armed with bow and shield; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="18"><p>and next to him Jehozabad and with him one hundred eighty thousand ready prepared for war. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:17" n="19"><p>These were those who waited on the king, besides those whom the king put in the fortified cities throughout all Judah. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="18"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="1"><p>Now Jehoshaphat had riches and honor in abundance; and he joined affinity with Ahab. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="2"><p>After certain years he went down to Ahab to Samaria. Ahab killed sheep and oxen for him in abundance, and for the people who were with him, and moved him to go up [with him] to Ramoth-gilead. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="3"><p>Ahab king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat king of Judah, Will you go with me to Ramoth-gilead? He answered him, I am as you are, and my people as your people; and [we will be] with you in the war. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="4"><p>Jehoshaphat said to the king of Israel, Please inquire first for the word of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="5"><p>Then the king of Israel gathered the prophets together, four hundred men, and said to them, Shall we go to Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I forbear? They said, Go up; for God will deliver it into the hand of the king. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="6"><p>But Jehoshaphat said, Isn’t there here a prophet of Yahweh besides, that we may inquire of him? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="7"><p>The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, There is yet one man by whom we may inquire of Yahweh: but I hate him; for he never prophesies good concerning me, but always evil: the same is Micaiah the son of Imla. Jehoshaphat said, Don’t let the king say so. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="8"><p>Then the king of Israel called an officer, and said, Get quickly Micaiah the son of Imla. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="9"><p>Now the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah sat each on his throne, arrayed in their robes, and they were sitting in an open place at the entrance of the gate of Samaria; and all the prophets were prophesying before them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="10"><p>Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah made him horns of iron, and said, Thus says Yahweh, With these shall you push the Syrians, until they be consumed. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="11"><p>All the prophets prophesied so, saying, Go up to Ramoth-gilead, and prosper; for Yahweh will deliver it into the hand of the king. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="12"><p>The messenger who went to call Micaiah spoke to him, saying, Behold, the words of the prophets [declare] good to the king with one mouth: let your word therefore, Please be like one of theirs, and speak you good. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="13"><p>Micaiah said, As Yahweh lives, what my God says, that will I speak. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="14"><p>When he was come to the king, the king said to him, Micaiah, shall we go to Ramoth-gilead to battle, or shall I forbear? He said, Go up, and prosper; and they shall be delivered into your hand. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="15"><p>The king said to him, How many times shall I adjure you that you speak to me nothing but the truth in the name of Yahweh? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="16"><p>He said, I saw all Israel scattered on the mountains, as sheep that have no shepherd: and Yahweh said, These have no master; let them return every man to his house in peace. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="17"><p>The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, Didn’t I tell you that he would not prophesy good concerning me, but evil? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="18"><p>[Micaiah] said, Therefore hear you the word of Yahweh: I saw Yahweh sitting on his throne, and all the host of heaven standing on his right hand and on his left. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="19"><p>Yahweh said, Who shall entice Ahab king of Israel, that he may go up and fall at Ramoth-gilead? One spoke saying after this manner, and another saying after that manner. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="20"><p>There came forth a spirit, and stood before Yahweh, and said, I will entice him. Yahweh said to him, <q rend="single">How?</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="21"><p>He said, <q rend="single">I will go forth, and will be a lying spirit in the mouth of all his prophets.</q> He said, <q rend="single">You shall entice him, and shall prevail also: go forth, and do so.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="22"><p>Now therefore, behold, Yahweh has put a lying spirit in the mouth of these your prophets; and Yahweh has spoken evil concerning you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="23"><p>Then Zedekiah the son of Chenaanah came near, and struck Micaiah on the cheek, and said, Which way went the Spirit of Yahweh from me to speak to you? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="24"><p>Micaiah said, Behold, you shall see on that day, when you shall go into an inner chamber to hide yourself. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="25"><p>The king of Israel said, Take Micaiah, and carry him back to Amon the governor of the city, and to Joash the king’s son; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="26"><p>and say, Thus says the king, Put this fellow in the prison, and feed him with bread of affliction and with water of affliction, until I return in peace. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="27"><p>Micaiah said, If you return at all in peace, Yahweh has not spoken by me. He said, Hear, you peoples, all of you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="28"><p>So the king of Israel and Jehoshaphat the king of Judah went up to Ramoth-gilead. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="29"><p>The king of Israel said to Jehoshaphat, I will disguise myself, and go into the battle; but put you on your robes. So the king of Israel disguised himself; and they went into the battle. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="30"><p>Now the king of Syria had commanded the captains of his chariots, saying, Fight neither with small nor great, save only with the king of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="31"><p>It happened, when the captains of the chariots saw Jehoshaphat, that they said, It is the king of Israel. Therefore they turned about to fight against him: but Jehoshaphat cried out, and Yahweh helped him; and God moved them [to depart] from him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="32"><p>It happened, when the captains of the chariots saw that it was not the king of Israel, that they turned back from pursuing him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="33"><p>A certain man drew his bow at a venture, and struck the king of Israel between the joints of the armor. Therefore he said to the driver of the chariot, Turn your hand, and carry me out of the host; for I am sore wounded. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:18" n="34"><p>The battle increased that day: however the king of Israel stayed himself up in his chariot against the Syrians until the even; and about the time of the going down of the sun he died. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="19"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="1"><p>Jehoshaphat the king of Judah returned to his house in peace to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="2"><p>Jehu the son of Hanani the seer went out to meet him, and said to king Jehoshaphat, Should you help the wicked, and love those who hate Yahweh? for this thing wrath is on you from before Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="3"><p>Nevertheless there are good things found in you, in that you have put away the Asheroth out of the land, and have set your heart to seek God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="4"><p>Jehoshaphat lived at Jerusalem: and he went out again among the people from Beersheba to the hill-country of Ephraim, and brought them back to Yahweh, the God of their fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="5"><p>He set judges in the land throughout all the fortified cities of Judah, city by city, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="6"><p>and said to the judges, Consider what you do: for you don’t judge for man, but for Yahweh; and [he is] with you in the judgment. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="7"><p>Now therefore let the fear of Yahweh be on you; take heed and do it: for there is no iniquity with Yahweh our God, nor respect of persons, nor taking of bribes. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="8"><p>Moreover in Jerusalem did Jehoshaphat set of the Levites and the priests, and of the heads of the fathers’ [houses] of Israel, for the judgment of Yahweh, and for controversies. They returned to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="9"><p>He charged them, saying, Thus shall you do in the fear of Yahweh, faithfully, and with a perfect heart. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="10"><p>Whenever any controversy shall come to you from your brothers who dwell in their cities, between blood and blood, between law and commandment, statutes and ordinances, you shall warn them, that they not be guilty towards Yahweh, and so wrath come on you and on your brothers: this do, and you shall not be guilty. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:19" n="11"><p>Behold, Amariah the chief priest is over you in all matters of Yahweh; and Zebadiah the son of Ishmael, the ruler of the house of Judah, in all the king’s matters: also the Levites shall be officers before you. Deal courageously, and Yahweh be with the good. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="20"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="1"><p>It happened after this, that the children of Moab, and the children of Ammon, and with them some of the Ammonites, came against Jehoshaphat to battle. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="2"><p>Then there came some who told Jehoshaphat, saying, There comes a great multitude against you from beyond the sea from Syria; and, behold, they are in Hazazon Tamar (the same is En Gedi). </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="3"><p>Jehoshaphat feared, and set himself to seek to Yahweh; and he proclaimed a fast throughout all Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="4"><p>Judah gathered themselves together, to seek [help] of Yahweh: even out of all the cities of Judah they came to seek Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="5"><p>Jehoshaphat stood in the assembly of Judah and Jerusalem, in the house of Yahweh, before the new court; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="6"><p>and he said, Yahweh, the God of our fathers, aren’t you God in heaven? and aren’t you ruler over all the kingdoms of the nations? and in your hand is power and might, so that none is able to withstand you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="7"><p>Did not you, our God, drive out the inhabitants of this land before your people Israel, and give it to the seed of Abraham your friend forever? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="8"><p>They lived therein, and have built you a sanctuary therein for your name, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="9"><p>If evil come on us, the sword, judgment, or pestilence, or famine, we will stand before this house, and before you, (for your name is in this house,) and cry to you in our affliction, and you will hear and save. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="10"><p>Now, behold, the children of Ammon and Moab and Mount Seir, whom you would not let Israel invade, when they came out of the land of Egypt, but they turned aside from them, and didn’t destroy them; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="11"><p>behold, how they reward us, to come to cast us out of your possession, which you have given us to inherit. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="12"><p>Our God, will you not judge them? for we have no might against this great company that comes against us; neither know we what to do: but out eyes are on you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="13"><p>All Judah stood before Yahweh, with their little ones, their wives, and their children. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="14"><p>Then on Jahaziel the son of Zechariah, the son of Benaiah, the son of Jeiel, the son of Mattaniah, the Levite, of the sons of Asaph, came the Spirit of Yahweh in the midst of the assembly; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="15"><p>and he said, Listen you, all Judah, and you inhabitants of Jerusalem, and you king Jehoshaphat: Thus says Yahweh to you, Don’t be afraid you, neither be dismayed by reason of this great multitude; for the battle is not yours, but God’s. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="16"><p>Tomorrow go you down against them: behold, they come up by the ascent of Ziz; and you shall find them at the end of the valley, before the wilderness of Jeruel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="17"><p>You shall not need to fight in this [battle]: set yourselves, stand you still, and see the salvation of Yahweh with you, O Judah and Jerusalem; don’t be afraid, nor be dismayed: tomorrow go out against them: for Yahweh is with you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="18"><p>Jehoshaphat bowed his head with his face to the ground; and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem fell down before Yahweh, worshipping Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="19"><p>The Levites, of the children of the Kohathites and of the children of the Korahites, stood up to praise Yahweh, the God of Israel, with an exceeding loud voice. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="20"><p>They rose early in the morning, and went forth into the wilderness of Tekoa: and as they went forth, Jehoshaphat stood and said, Hear me, Judah, and you inhabitants of Jerusalem: believe in Yahweh your God, so shall you be established; believe his prophets, so shall you prosper. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="21"><p>When he had taken counsel with the people, he appointed those who should sing to Yahweh, and give praise in holy array, as they went out before the army, and say, Give thanks to Yahweh; for his lovingkindness endures forever. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="22"><p>When they began to sing and to praise, Yahweh set liers-in-wait against the children of Ammon, Moab, and Mount Seir, who had come against Judah; and they were struck. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="23"><p>For the children of Ammon and Moab stood up against the inhabitants of Mount Seir, utterly to kill and destroy them: and when they had made an end of the inhabitants of Seir, everyone helped to destroy another. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="24"><p>When Judah came to the watch-tower of the wilderness, they looked at the multitude; and, behold, they were dead bodies fallen to the earth, and there were none who escaped. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="25"><p>When Jehoshaphat and his people came to take the spoil of them, they found among them in abundance both riches and dead bodies, and precious jewels, which they stripped off for themselves, more than they could carry away: and they were three days in taking the spoil, it was so much. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="26"><p>On the fourth day they assembled themselves in the valley of Beracah; for there they blessed Yahweh: therefore the name of that place was called The valley of Beracah to this day. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="27"><p>Then they returned, every man of Judah and Jerusalem, and Jehoshaphat in the forefront of them, to go again to Jerusalem with joy; for Yahweh had made them to rejoice over their enemies. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="28"><p>They came to Jerusalem with psalteries and harps and trumpets to the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="29"><p>The fear of God was on all the kingdoms of the countries, when they heard that Yahweh fought against the enemies of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="30"><p>So the realm of Jehoshaphat was quiet; for his God gave him rest round about. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="31"><p>Jehoshaphat reigned over Judah: he was thirty-five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty-five years in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Azubah the daughter of Shilhi. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="32"><p>He walked in the way of Asa his father, and didn’t turn aside from it, doing that which was right in the eyes of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="33"><p>However the high places were not taken away; neither as yet had the people set their hearts to the God of their fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="34"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Jehoshaphat, first and last, behold, they are written in the history of Jehu the son of Hanani, which is inserted in the book of the kings of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="35"><p>After this did Jehoshaphat king of Judah join himself with Ahaziah king of Israel; the same did very wickedly: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="36"><p>and he joined himself with him to make ships to go to Tarshish; and they made the ships in Ezion Geber. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:20" n="37"><p>Then Eliezer the son of Dodavahu of Mareshah prophesied against Jehoshaphat, saying, Because you have joined yourself with Ahaziah, Yahweh has destroyed your works. The ships were broken, so that they were not able to go to Tarshish. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="21"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="1"><p>Jehoshaphat slept with his fathers, and was buried with his fathers in the city of David: and Jehoram his son reigned in his place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="2"><p>He had brothers, the sons of Jehoshaphat: Azariah, and Jehiel, and Zechariah, and Azariah, and Michael, and Shephatiah; all these were the sons of Jehoshaphat king of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="3"><p>Their father gave them great gifts, of silver, and of gold, and of precious things, with fortified cities in Judah: but the kingdom gave he to Jehoram, because he was the firstborn. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="4"><p>Now when Jehoram was risen up over the kingdom of his father, and had strengthened himself, he killed all his brothers with the sword, and various also of the princes of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="5"><p>Jehoram was thirty-two years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eight years in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="6"><p>He walked in the way of the kings of Israel, as did the house of Ahab; for he had the daughter of Ahab as wife: and he did that which was evil in the sight of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="7"><p>However Yahweh would not destroy the house of David, because of the covenant that he had made with David, and as he promised to give a lamp to him and to his children always. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="8"><p>In his days Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah, and made a king over themselves. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="9"><p>Then Jehoram passed over with his captains, and all his chariots with him: and he rose up by night, and struck the Edomites who surrounded him, along with the captains of the chariots. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="10"><p>So Edom revolted from under the hand of Judah to this day: then did Libnah revolt at the same time from under his hand, because he had forsaken Yahweh, the God of his fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="11"><p>Moreover he made high places in the mountains of Judah, and made the inhabitants of Jerusalem to play the prostitute, and led Judah astray. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="12"><p>There came a writing to him from Elijah the prophet, saying, Thus says Yahweh, the God of David your father, Because you have not walked in the ways of Jehoshaphat your father, nor in the ways of Asa king of Judah, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="13"><p>but have walked in the way of the kings of Israel, and have made Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem to play the prostitute, like as the house of Ahab did, and also have slain your brothers of your father’s house, who were better than yourself: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="14"><p>behold, Yahweh will strike with a great plague your people, and your children, and your wives, and all your substance; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="15"><p>and you shall have great sickness by disease of your bowels, until your bowels fall out by reason of the sickness, day by day. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="16"><p>Yahweh stirred up against Jehoram the spirit of the Philistines, and of the Arabians who are beside the Ethiopians: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="17"><p>and they came up against Judah, and broke into it, and carried away all the substance that was found in the king’s house, and his sons also, and his wives; so that there was never a son left him, save Jehoahaz, the youngest of his sons. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="18"><p>After all this Yahweh struck him in his bowels with an incurable disease. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="19"><p>It happened, in process of time, at the end of two years, that his bowels fell out by reason of his sickness, and he died of sore diseases. His people made no burning for him, like the burning of his fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:21" n="20"><p>Thirty-two years old was he when he began to reign, and he reigned in Jerusalem eight years: and he departed without being desired; and they buried him in the city of David, but not in the tombs of the kings. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="22"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="1"><p>The inhabitants of Jerusalem made Ahaziah his youngest son king in his place; for the band of men who came with the Arabians to the camp had slain all the eldest. So Ahaziah the son of Jehoram king of Judah reigned. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="2"><p>Forty-two years old was Ahaziah when he began to reign; and he reigned one year in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Athaliah the daughter of Omri. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="3"><p>He also walked in the ways of the house of Ahab; for his mother was his counselor to do wickedly. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="4"><p>He did that which was evil in the sight of Yahweh, as did the house of Ahab; for they were his counselors after the death of his father, to his destruction. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="5"><p>He walked also after their counsel, and went with Jehoram the son of Ahab king of Israel to war against Hazael king of Syria at Ramoth-gilead: and the Syrians wounded Joram. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="6"><p>He returned to be healed in Jezreel of the wounds which they had given him at Ramah, when he fought against Hazael king of Syria. Azariah the son of Jehoram king of Judah went down to see Jehoram the son of Ahab in Jezreel, because he was sick. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="7"><p>Now the destruction of Ahaziah was of God, in that he went to Joram: for when he was come, he went out with Jehoram against Jehu the son of Nimshi, whom Yahweh had anointed to cut off the house of Ahab. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="8"><p>It happened, when Jehu was executing judgment on the house of Ahab, that he found the princes of Judah, and the sons of the brothers of Ahaziah, ministering to Ahaziah, and killed them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="9"><p>He sought Ahaziah, and they caught him (now he was hiding in Samaria), and they brought him to Jehu, and killed him; and they buried him, for they said, He is the son of Jehoshaphat, who sought Yahweh with all his heart. The house of Ahaziah had no power to hold the kingdom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="10"><p>Now when Athaliah the mother of Ahaziah saw that her son was dead, she arose and destroyed all the seed royal of the house of Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="11"><p>But Jehoshabeath, the daughter of the king, took Joash the son of Ahaziah, and stole him away from among the king’s sons who were slain, and put him and his nurse in the bedchamber. So Jehoshabeath, the daughter of king Jehoram, the wife of Jehoiada the priest (for she was the sister of Ahaziah), hid him from Athaliah, so that she didn’t kill him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:22" n="12"><p>He was with them hid in the house of God six years: and Athaliah reigned over the land. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="23"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="1"><p>In the seventh year Jehoiada strengthened himself, and took the captains of hundreds, Azariah the son of Jeroham, and Ishmael the son of Jehohanan, and Azariah the son of Obed, and Maaseiah the son of Adaiah, and Elishaphat the son of Zichri, into covenant with him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="2"><p>They went about in Judah, and gathered the Levites out of all the cities of Judah, and the heads of fathers’ [houses] of Israel, and they came to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="3"><p>All the assembly made a covenant with the king in the house of God. He said to them, Behold, the king’s son shall reign, as Yahweh has spoken concerning the sons of David. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="4"><p>This is the thing that you shall do: a third part of you, who come in on the Sabbath, of the priests and of the Levites, shall be porters of the thresholds; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="5"><p>and a third part shall be at the king’s house; and a third part at the gate of the foundation: and all the people shall be in the courts of the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="6"><p>But let none come into the house of Yahweh, save the priests, and those who minister of the Levites; they shall come in, for they are holy: but all the people shall keep the charge of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="7"><p>The Levites shall compass the king round about, every man with his weapons in his hand; and whoever comes into the house, let him be slain: and be you with the king when he comes in, and when he goes out. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="8"><p>So the Levites and all Judah did according to all that Jehoiada the priest commanded: and they took every man his men, those who were to come in on the Sabbath; with those who were to go out on the Sabbath; for Jehoiada the priest didn’t dismiss the shift. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="9"><p>Jehoiada the priest delivered to the captains of hundreds the spears, and bucklers, and shields, that had been king David’s, which were in the house of God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="10"><p>He set all the people, every man with his weapon in his hand, from the right side of the house to the left side of the house, along by the altar and the house, by the king round about. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="11"><p>Then they brought out the king’s son, and put the crown on him, and [gave him] the testimony, and made him king: and Jehoiada and his sons anointed him; and they said, [Long] live the king. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="12"><p>When Athaliah heard the noise of the people running and praising the king, she came to the people into the house of Yahweh: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="13"><p>and she looked, and, behold, the king stood by his pillar at the entrance, and the captains and the trumpets by the king; and all the people of the land rejoiced, and blew trumpets; the singers also [played] on instruments of music, and led the singing of praise. Then Athaliah tore her clothes, and said, Treason! treason! </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="14"><p>Jehoiada the priest brought out the captains of hundreds who were set over the host, and said to them, Have her forth between the ranks; and whoever follows her, let him be slain with the sword: for the priest said, Don’t kill her in the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="15"><p>So they made way for her; and she went to the entrance of the horse gate to the king’s house: and they killed her there. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="16"><p>Jehoiada made a covenant between himself, and all the people, and the king, that they should be Yahweh’s people. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="17"><p>All the people went to the house of Baal, and broke it down, and broke his altars and his images in pieces, and killed Mattan the priest of Baal before the altars. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="18"><p>Jehoiada appointed the officers of the house of Yahweh under the hand of the priests the Levites, whom David had distributed in the house of Yahweh, to offer the burnt offerings of Yahweh, as it is written in the law of Moses, with rejoicing and with singing, according to the order of David. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="19"><p>He set the porters at the gates of the house of Yahweh, that no one who was unclean in anything should enter in. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="20"><p>He took the captains of hundreds, and the nobles, and the governors of the people, and all the people of the land, and brought down the king from the house of Yahweh: and they came through the upper gate to the king’s house, and set the king on the throne of the kingdom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:23" n="21"><p>So all the people of the land rejoiced, and the city was quiet. Athaliah they had slain with the sword. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="24"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="1"><p>Joash was seven years old when he began to reign; and he reigned forty years in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Zibiah, of Beersheba. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="2"><p>Joash did that which was right in the eyes of Yahweh all the days of Jehoiada the priest. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="3"><p>Jehoiada took for him two wives; and he became the father of sons and daughters. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="4"><p>It happened after this, that Joash was minded to restore the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="5"><p>He gathered together the priests and the Levites, and said to them, Go out to the cities of Judah, and gather of all Israel money to repair the house of your God from year to year; and see that you hasten the matter. However the Levites didn’t hurry. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="6"><p>The king called for Jehoiada the chief, and said to him, Why haven’t you required of the Levites to bring in out of Judah and out of Jerusalem the tax of Moses the servant of Yahweh, and of the assembly of Israel, for the tent of the testimony? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="7"><p>For the sons of Athaliah, that wicked woman, had broken up the house of God; and also all the dedicated things of the house of Yahweh did they bestow on the Baals. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="8"><p>So the king commanded, and they made a chest, and set it outside at the gate of the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="9"><p>They made a proclamation through Judah and Jerusalem, to bring in for Yahweh the tax that Moses the servant of God laid on Israel in the wilderness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="10"><p>All the princes and all the people rejoiced, and brought in, and cast into the chest, until they had made an end. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="11"><p>It was so, that whenever the chest was brought to the king’s officers by the hand of the Levites, and when they saw that there was much money, the king’s scribe and the chief priest’s officer came and emptied the chest, and took it, and carried it to its place again. Thus they did day by day, and gathered money in abundance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="12"><p>The king and Jehoiada gave it to such as did the work of the service of the house of Yahweh; and they hired masons and carpenters to restore the house of Yahweh, and also such as worked iron and brass to repair the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="13"><p>So the workmen worked, and the work of repairing went forward in their hands, and they set up the house of God in its state, and strengthened it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="14"><p>When they had made an end, they brought the rest of the money before the king and Jehoiada, whereof were made vessels for the house of Yahweh, even vessels with which to minister and to offer, and spoons, and vessels of gold and silver. They offered burnt offerings in the house of Yahweh continually all the days of Jehoiada. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="15"><p>But Jehoiada grew old and was full of days, and he died; one hundred thirty years old was he when he died. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="16"><p>They buried him in the city of David among the kings, because he had done good in Israel, and toward God and his house. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="17"><p>Now after the death of Jehoiada came the princes of Judah, and made obeisance to the king. Then the king listened to them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="18"><p>They forsook the house of Yahweh, the God of their fathers, and served the Asherim and the idols: and wrath came on Judah and Jerusalem for this their guiltiness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="19"><p>Yet he sent prophets to them, to bring them again to Yahweh; and they testified against them: but they would not give ear. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="20"><p>The Spirit of God came on Zechariah the son of Jehoiada the priest; and he stood above the people, and said to them, Thus says God, Why disobey you the commandments of Yahweh, so that you can’t prosper? because you have forsaken Yahweh, he has also forsaken you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="21"><p>They conspired against him, and stoned him with stones at the commandment of the king in the court of the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="22"><p>Thus Joash the king didn’t remember the kindness which Jehoiada his father had done to him, but killed his son. When he died, he said, Yahweh look on it, and require it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="23"><p>It happened at the end of the year, that the army of the Syrians came up against him: and they came to Judah and Jerusalem, and destroyed all the princes of the people from among the people, and sent all the spoil of them to the king of Damascus. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="24"><p>For the army of the Syrians came with a small company of men; and Yahweh delivered a very great host into their hand, because they had forsaken Yahweh, the God of their fathers. So they executed judgment on Joash. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="25"><p>When they were departed for him (for they left him very sick), his own servants conspired against him for the blood of the sons of Jehoiada the priest, and killed him on his bed, and he died; and they buried him in the city of David, but they didn’t bury him in the tombs of the kings. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="26"><p>These are those who conspired against him: Zabad the son of Shimeath the Ammonitess, and Jehozabad the son of Shimrith the Moabitess. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:24" n="27"><p>Now concerning his sons, and the greatness of the burdens [laid] on him, and the rebuilding of the house of God, behold, they are written in the commentary of the book of the kings. Amaziah his son reigned in his place. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="25"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="1"><p>Amaziah was twenty-five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Jehoaddan, of Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="2"><p>He did that which was right in the eyes of Yahweh, but not with a perfect heart. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="3"><p>Now it happened, when the kingdom was established to him, that he killed his servants who had killed the king his father. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="4"><p>But he didn’t put their children to death, but did according to that which is written in the law in the book of Moses, as Yahweh commanded, saying, The fathers shall not die for the children, neither shall the children die for the fathers; but every man shall die for his own sin. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="5"><p>Moreover Amaziah gathered Judah together, and ordered them according to their fathers’ houses, under captains of thousands and captains of hundreds, even all Judah and Benjamin: and he numbered them from twenty years old and upward, and found them three hundred thousand chosen men, able to go forth to war, who could handle spear and shield. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="6"><p>He hired also one hundred thousand mighty men of valor out of Israel for one hundred talents of silver. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="7"><p>But there came a man of God to him, saying, O king, don’t let the army of Israel go with you; for Yahweh is not with Israel, [to wit], with all the children of Ephraim. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="8"><p>But if you will go, do [valiantly], be strong for the battle: God will cast you down before the enemy; for God has power to help, and to cast down. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="9"><p>Amaziah said to the man of God, But what shall we do for the hundred talents which I have given to the army of Israel? The man of God answered, Yahweh is able to give you much more than this. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="10"><p>Then Amaziah separated them, [to wit], the army that had come to him out of Ephraim, to go home again: therefore their anger was greatly kindled against Judah, and they returned home in fierce anger. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="11"><p>Amaziah took courage, and led forth his people, and went to the Valley of Salt, and struck of the children of Seir ten thousand. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="12"><p>[other] ten thousand did the children of Judah carry away alive, and brought them to the top of the rock, and cast them down from the top of the rock, so that they all were broken in pieces. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="13"><p>But the men of the army whom Amaziah sent back, that they should not go with him to battle, fell on the cities of Judah, from Samaria even to Beth Horon, and struck of them three thousand, and took much spoil. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="14"><p>Now it happened, after that Amaziah was come from the slaughter of the Edomites, that he brought the gods of the children of Seir, and set them up to be his gods, and bowed down himself before them, and burned incense to them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="15"><p>Therefore the anger of Yahweh was kindled against Amaziah, and he sent to him a prophet, who said to him, Why have you sought after the gods of the people, which have not delivered their own people out of your hand? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="16"><p>It happened, as he talked with him, that [the king] said to him, Have we made you of the king’s counsel? Stop! Why should you be struck down? Then the prophet stopped, and said, I know that God has determined to destroy you, because you have done this, and have not listened to my counsel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="17"><p>Then Amaziah king of Judah took advice, and sent to Joash, the son of Jehoahaz the son of Jehu, king of Israel, saying, Come, let us look one another in the face. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="18"><p>Joash king of Israel sent to Amaziah king of Judah, saying, The thistle that was in Lebanon sent to the cedar that was in Lebanon, saying, Give your daughter to my son as wife: and there passed by a wild animal that was in Lebanon, and trod down the thistle. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="19"><p>You say, Behold, you have struck Edom; and your heart lifts you up to boast: abide now at home; why should you meddle to [your] hurt, that you should fall, even you, and Judah with you? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="20"><p>But Amaziah would not hear; for it was of God, that he might deliver them into the hand [of their enemies], because they had sought after the gods of Edom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="21"><p>So Joash king of Israel went up; and he and Amaziah king of Judah looked one another in the face at Beth-shemesh, which belongs to Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="22"><p>Judah was put to the worse before Israel; and they fled every man to his tent. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="23"><p>Joash king of Israel took Amaziah king of Judah, the son of Joash the son of Jehoahaz, at Beth-shemesh, and brought him to Jerusalem, and broke down the wall of Jerusalem from the gate of Ephraim to the corner gate, four hundred cubits. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="24"><p>[He took] all the gold and silver, and all the vessels that were found in the house of God with Obed-edom, and the treasures of the king’s house, the hostages also, and returned to Samaria. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="25"><p>Amaziah the son of Joash king of Judah lived after the death of Joash son of Jehoahaz king of Israel fifteen years. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="26"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Amaziah, first and last, behold, aren’t they written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="27"><p>Now from the time that Amaziah did turn away from following Yahweh they made a conspiracy against him in Jerusalem; and he fled to Lachish: but they sent after him to Lachish, and killed him there. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:25" n="28"><p>They brought him on horses, and buried him with his fathers in the city of Judah. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="26"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="1"><p>All the people of Judah took Uzziah, who was sixteen years old, and made him king in the room of his father Amaziah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="2"><p>He built Eloth, and restored it to Judah, after that the king slept with his fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="3"><p>Sixteen years old was Uzziah when he began to reign; and he reigned fifty-two years in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Jechiliah, of Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="4"><p>He did that which was right in the eyes of Yahweh, according to all that his father Amaziah had done. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="5"><p>He set himself to seek God in the days of Zechariah, who had understanding in the vision of God: and as long as he sought Yahweh, God made him to prosper. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="6"><p>He went forth and warred against the Philistines, and broke down the wall of Gath, and the wall of Jabneh, and the wall of Ashdod; and he built cities in [the country of] Ashdod, and among the Philistines. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="7"><p>God helped him against the Philistines, and against the Arabians who lived in Gur Baal, and the Meunim. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="8"><p>The Ammonites gave tribute to Uzziah: and his name spread abroad even to the entrance of Egypt; for he grew exceeding strong. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="9"><p>Moreover Uzziah built towers in Jerusalem at the corner gate, and at the valley gate, and at the turning [of the wall], and fortified them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="10"><p>He built towers in the wilderness, and hewed out many cisterns, for he had much cattle; in the lowland also, and in the plain: [and he had] farmers and vineyard keepers in the mountains and in the fruitful fields; for he loved farming. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="11"><p>Moreover Uzziah had an army of fighting men, who went out to war by bands, according to the number of their reckoning made by Jeiel the scribe and Maaseiah the officer, under the hand of Hananiah, one of the king’s captains. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="12"><p>The whole number of the heads of fathers’ [houses], even the mighty men of valor, was two thousand and six hundred. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="13"><p>Under their hand was an army, three hundred thousand and seven thousand and five hundred, who made war with mighty power, to help the king against the enemy. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="14"><p>Uzziah prepared for them, even for all the host, shields, and spears, and helmets, and coats of mail, and bows, and stones for slinging. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="15"><p>He made in Jerusalem engines, invented by skillful men, to be on the towers and on the battlements, with which to shoot arrows and great stones. His name spread far abroad; for he was marvelously helped, until he was strong. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="16"><p>But when he was strong, his heart was lifted up, so that he did corruptly, and he trespassed against Yahweh his God; for he went into the temple of Yahweh to burn incense on the altar of incense. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="17"><p>Azariah the priest went in after him, and with him eighty priests of Yahweh, who were valiant men: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="18"><p>and they withstood Uzziah the king, and said to him, It pertains not to you, Uzziah, to burn incense to Yahweh, but to the priests the sons of Aaron, who are consecrated to burn incense: go out of the sanctuary; for you have trespassed; neither shall it be for your honor from Yahweh God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="19"><p>Then Uzziah was angry; and he had a censer in his hand to burn incense; and while he was angry with the priests, the leprosy broke forth in his forehead before the priests in the house of Yahweh, beside the altar of incense. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="20"><p>Azariah the chief priest, and all the priests, looked on him, and, behold, he was leprous in his forehead, and they thrust him out quickly from there; yes, himself hurried also to go out, because Yahweh had struck him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="21"><p>Uzziah the king was a leper to the day of his death, and lived in a separate house, being a leper; for he was cut off from the house of Yahweh: and Jotham his son was over the king’s house, judging the people of the land. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="22"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Uzziah, first and last, did Isaiah the prophet, the son of Amoz, write. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:26" n="23"><p>So Uzziah slept with his fathers; and they buried him with his fathers in the field of burial which belonged to the kings; for they said, He is a leper: and Jotham his son reigned in his place. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="27"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="1"><p>Jotham was twenty-five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Jerushah the daughter of Zadok. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="2"><p>He did that which was right in the eyes of Yahweh, according to all that his father Uzziah had done: however he didn’t enter into the temple of Yahweh. The people did yet corruptly. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="3"><p>He built the upper gate of the house of Yahweh, and on the wall of Ophel he built much. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="4"><p>Moreover he built cities in the hill-country of Judah, and in the forests he built castles and towers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="5"><p>He fought also with the king of the children of Ammon, and prevailed against them. The children of Ammon gave him the same year one hundred talents of silver, and ten thousand measures of wheat, and ten thousand of barley. So much did the children of Ammon render to him, in the second year also, and in the third. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="6"><p>So Jotham became mighty, because he ordered his ways before Yahweh his God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="7"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Jotham, and all his wars, and his ways, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="8"><p>He was five and twenty years old when he began to reign, and reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:27" n="9"><p>Jotham slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city of David: and Ahaz his son reigned in his place. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="28"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="1"><p>Ahaz was twenty years old when he began to reign; and he reigned sixteen years in Jerusalem: and he didn’t do that which was right in the eyes of Yahweh, like David his father; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="2"><p>but he walked in the ways of the kings of Israel, and made also molten images for the Baals. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="3"><p>Moreover he burnt incense in the valley of the son of Hinnom, and burnt his children in the fire, according to the abominations of the nations whom Yahweh cast out before the children of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="4"><p>He sacrificed and burnt incense in the high places, and on the hills, and under every green tree. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="5"><p>Therefore Yahweh his God delivered him into the hand of the king of Syria; and they struck him, and carried away of his a great multitude of captives, and brought them to Damascus. He was also delivered into the hand of the king of Israel, who struck him with a great slaughter. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="6"><p>For Pekah the son of Remaliah killed in Judah one hundred twenty thousand in one day, all of them valiant men; because they had forsaken Yahweh, the God of their fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="7"><p>Zichri, a mighty man of Ephraim, killed Maaseiah the king’s son, and Azrikam the ruler of the house, and Elkanah who was next to the king. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="8"><p>The children of Israel carried away captive of their brothers two hundred thousand, women, sons, and daughters, and took also away much spoil from them, and brought the spoil to Samaria. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="9"><p>But a prophet of Yahweh was there, whose name was Oded: and he went out to meet the host that came to Samaria, and said to them, Behold, because Yahweh, the God of your fathers, was angry with Judah, he has delivered them into your hand, and you have slain them in a rage which has reached up to heaven. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="10"><p>Now you purpose to keep under the children of Judah and Jerusalem for bondservants and bondmaids to you: [but] aren’t there even with you trespasses of your own against Yahweh your God? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="11"><p>Now hear me therefore, and send back the captives, that you have taken captive of your brothers; for the fierce wrath of Yahweh is on you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="12"><p>Then certain of the heads of the children of Ephraim, Azariah the son of Johanan, Berechiah the son of Meshillemoth, and Jehizkiah the son of Shallum, and Amasa the son of Hadlai, stood up against those who came from the war, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="13"><p>and said to them, You shall not bring in the captives here: for you purpose that which will bring on us a trespass against Yahweh, to add to our sins and to our trespass; for our trespass is great, and there is fierce wrath against Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="14"><p>So the armed men left the captives and the spoil before the princes and all the assembly. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="15"><p>The men who have been mentioned by name rose up, and took the captives, and with the spoil clothed all who were naked among them, and arrayed them, and shod them, and gave them to eat and to drink, and anointed them, and carried all the feeble of them on donkeys, and brought them to Jericho, the city of palm trees, to their brothers: then they returned to Samaria. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="16"><p>At that time did king Ahaz send to the kings of Assyria to help him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="17"><p>For again the Edomites had come and struck Judah, and carried away captives. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="18"><p>The Philistines also had invaded the cities of the lowland, and of the South of Judah, and had taken Beth-shemesh, and Aijalon, and Gederoth, and Soco with the towns of it, and Timnah with the towns of it, Gimzo also and the towns of it: and they lived there. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="19"><p>For Yahweh brought Judah low because of Ahaz king of Israel; for he had dealt wantonly in Judah, and trespassed severely against Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="20"><p>Tilgath Pilneser king of Assyria came to him, and distressed him, but didn’t strengthen him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="21"><p>For Ahaz took away a portion out of the house of Yahweh, and out of the house of the king and of the princes, and gave it to the king of Assyria: but it didn’t help him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="22"><p>In the time of his distress did he trespass yet more against Yahweh, this same king Ahaz. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="23"><p>For he sacrificed to the gods of Damascus, which struck him; and he said, Because the gods of the kings of Syria helped them, [therefore] will I sacrifice to them, that they may help me. But they were the ruin of him, and of all Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="24"><p>Ahaz gathered together the vessels of the house of God, and cut in pieces the vessels of the house of God, and shut up the doors of the house of Yahweh; and he made him altars in every corner of Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="25"><p>In every city of Judah he made high places to burn incense to other gods, and provoked to anger Yahweh, the God of his fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="26"><p>Now the rest of his acts, and all his ways, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:28" n="27"><p>Ahaz slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the city, even in Jerusalem; for they didn’t bring him into the tombs of the kings of Israel: and Hezekiah his son reigned in his place. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="29"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="1"><p>Hezekiah began to reign when he was twenty-five years old; and he reigned twenty-nine years in Jerusalem: and his mother’s name was Abijah, the daughter of Zechariah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="2"><p>He did that which was right in the eyes of Yahweh, according to all that David his father had done. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="3"><p>He in the first year of his reign, in the first month, opened the doors of the house of Yahweh, and repaired them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="4"><p>He brought in the priests and the Levites, and gathered them together into the broad place on the east, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="5"><p>and said to them, Hear me, you Levites; now sanctify yourselves, and sanctify the house of Yahweh, the God of your fathers, and carry forth the filthiness out of the holy place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="6"><p>For our fathers have trespassed, and done that which was evil in the sight of Yahweh our God, and have forsaken him, and have turned away their faces from the habitation of Yahweh, and turned their backs. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="7"><p>Also they have shut up the doors of the porch, and put out the lamps, and have not burned incense nor offered burnt offerings in the holy place to the God of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="8"><p>Therefore the wrath of Yahweh was on Judah and Jerusalem, and he has delivered them to be tossed back and forth, to be an astonishment, and a hissing, as you see with your eyes. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="9"><p>For, behold, our fathers have fallen by the sword, and our sons and our daughters and our wives are in captivity for this. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="10"><p>Now it is in my heart to make a covenant with Yahweh, the God of Israel, that his fierce anger may turn away from us. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="11"><p>My sons, don’t be negligent now; for Yahweh has chosen you to stand before him, to minister to him, and that you should be his ministers, and burn incense. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="12"><p>Then the Levites arose, Mahath, the son of Amasai, and Joel the son of Azariah, of the sons of the Kohathites; and of the sons of Merari, Kish the son of Abdi, and Azariah the son of Jehallelel; and of the Gershonites, Joah the son of Zimmah, and Eden the son of Joah; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="13"><p>and of the sons of Elizaphan, Shimri and Jeuel; and of the sons of Asaph, Zechariah and Mattaniah; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="14"><p>and of the sons of Heman, Jehuel and Shimei; and of the sons of Jeduthun, Shemaiah and Uzziel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="15"><p>They gathered their brothers, and sanctified themselves, and went in, according to the commandment of the king by the words of Yahweh, to cleanse the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="16"><p>The priests went in to the inner part of the house of Yahweh, to cleanse it, and brought out all the uncleanness that they found in the temple of Yahweh into the court of the house of Yahweh. The Levites took it, to carry it out abroad to the brook Kidron. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="17"><p>Now they began on the first [day] of the first month to sanctify, and on the eighth day of the month came they to the porch of Yahweh; and they sanctified the house of Yahweh in eight days: and on the sixteenth day of the first month they made an end. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="18"><p>Then they went in to Hezekiah the king within [the palace], and said, We have cleansed all the house of Yahweh, and the altar of burnt offering, with all the vessels of it, and the table of show bread, with all the vessels of it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="19"><p>Moreover all the vessels, which king Ahaz in his reign did cast away when he trespassed, have we prepared and sanctified; and, behold, they are before the altar of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="20"><p>Then Hezekiah the king arose early, and gathered the princes of the city, and went up to the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="21"><p>They brought seven bulls, and seven rams, and seven lambs, and seven male goats, for a sin-offering for the kingdom and for the sanctuary and for Judah. He commanded the priests the sons of Aaron to offer them on the altar of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="22"><p>So they killed the bulls, and the priests received the blood, and sprinkled it on the altar: and they killed the rams, and sprinkled the blood on the altar: they killed also the lambs, and sprinkled the blood on the altar. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="23"><p>They brought near the male goats for the sin-offering before the king and the assembly; and they laid their hands on them: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="24"><p>and the priests killed them, and they made a sin-offering with their blood on the altar, to make atonement for all Israel; for the king commanded [that] the burnt offering and the sin-offering [should be made] for all Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="25"><p>He set the Levites in the house of Yahweh with cymbals, with psalteries, and with harps, according to the commandment of David, and of Gad the king’s seer, and Nathan the prophet; for the commandment was of Yahweh by his prophets. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="26"><p>The Levites stood with the instruments of David, and the priests with the trumpets. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="27"><p>Hezekiah commanded to offer the burnt offering on the altar. When the burnt offering began, the song of Yahweh began also, and the trumpets, together with the instruments of David king of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="28"><p>All the assembly worshiped, and the singers sang, and the trumpeters sounded; all this [continued] until the burnt offering was finished. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="29"><p>When they had made an end of offering, the king and all who were present with him bowed themselves and worshiped. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="30"><p>Moreover Hezekiah the king and the princes commanded the Levites to sing praises to Yahweh with the words of David, and of Asaph the seer. They sang praises with gladness, and they bowed their heads and worshiped. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="31"><p>Then Hezekiah answered, Now you have consecrated yourselves to Yahweh; come near and bring sacrifices and thank-offerings into the house of Yahweh. The assembly brought in sacrifices and thank-offerings; and as many as were of a willing heart [brought] burnt offerings. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="32"><p>The number of the burnt offerings which the assembly brought was seventy bulls, one hundred rams, and two hundred lambs: all these were for a burnt offering to Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="33"><p>The consecrated things were six hundred oxen and three thousand sheep. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="34"><p>But the priests were too few, so that they could not flay all the burnt offerings: therefore their brothers the Levites helped them, until the work was ended, and until the priests had sanctified themselves; for the Levites were more upright in heart to sanctify themselves than the priests. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="35"><p>Also the burnt offerings were in abundance, with the fat of the peace-offerings, and with the drink-offerings for every burnt offering. So the service of the house of Yahweh was set in order. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:29" n="36"><p>Hezekiah rejoiced, and all the people, because of that which God had prepared for the people: for the thing was done suddenly. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="30"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="1"><p>Hezekiah sent to all Israel and Judah, and wrote letters also to Ephraim and Manasseh, that they should come to the house of Yahweh at Jerusalem, to keep the Passover to Yahweh, the God of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="2"><p>For the king had taken counsel, and his princes, and all the assembly in Jerusalem, to keep the Passover in the second month. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="3"><p>For they could not keep it at that time, because the priests had not sanctified themselves in sufficient number, neither had the people gathered themselves together to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="4"><p>The thing was right in the eyes of the king and of all the assembly. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="5"><p>So they established a decree to make proclamation throughout all Israel, from Beersheba even to Dan, that they should come to keep the Passover to Yahweh, the God of Israel, at Jerusalem: for they had not kept it in great numbers in such sort as it is written. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="6"><p>So the posts went with the letters from the king and his princes throughout all Israel and Judah, and according to the commandment of the king, saying, You children of Israel, turn again to Yahweh, the God of Abraham, Isaac, and Israel, that he may return to the remnant that have escaped of you out of the hand of the kings of Assyria. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="7"><p>Don’t be you like your fathers, and like your brothers, who trespassed against Yahweh, the God of their fathers, so that he gave them up to desolation, as you see. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="8"><p>Now don’t you be stiff-necked, as your fathers were; but yield yourselves to Yahweh, and enter into his sanctuary, which he has sanctified forever, and serve Yahweh your God, that his fierce anger may turn away from you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="9"><p>For if you turn again to Yahweh, your brothers and your children shall find compassion before those who led them captive, and shall come again into this land: for Yahweh your God is gracious and merciful, and will not turn away his face from you, if you return to him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="10"><p>So the posts passed from city to city through the country of Ephraim and Manasseh, even to Zebulun: but they laughed them to scorn, and mocked them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="11"><p>Nevertheless certain men of Asher and Manasseh and of Zebulun humbled themselves, and came to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="12"><p>Also on Judah came the hand of God to give them one heart, to do the commandment of the king and of the princes by the word of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="13"><p>There assembled at Jerusalem much people to keep the feast of unleavened bread in the second month, a very great assembly. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="14"><p>They arose and took away the altars that were in Jerusalem, and all the altars for incense took they away, and cast them into the brook Kidron. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="15"><p>Then they killed the Passover on the fourteenth [day] of the second month: and the priests and the Levites were ashamed, and sanctified themselves, and brought burnt offerings into the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="16"><p>They stood in their place after their order, according to the law of Moses the man of God: the priests sprinkled the blood [which they received] of the hand of the Levites. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="17"><p>For there were many in the assembly who had not sanctified themselves: therefore the Levites had the charge of killing the Passovers for everyone who was not clean, to sanctify them to Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="18"><p>For a multitude of the people, even many of Ephraim and Manasseh, Issachar and Zebulun, had not cleansed themselves, yet did they eat the Passover otherwise than it is written. For Hezekiah had prayed for them, saying, The good Yahweh pardon everyone </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="19"><p>who sets his heart to seek God, Yahweh, the God of his fathers, though not [cleansed] according to the purification of the sanctuary. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="20"><p>Yahweh listened to Hezekiah, and healed the people. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="21"><p>The children of Israel who were present at Jerusalem kept the feast of unleavened bread seven days with great gladness; and the Levites and the priests praised Yahweh day by day, [singing] with loud instruments to Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="22"><p>Hezekiah spoke comfortably to all the Levites who had good understanding [in the service] of Yahweh. So they ate throughout the feast for the seven days, offering sacrifices of peace-offerings, and making confession to Yahweh, the God of their fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="23"><p>The whole assembly took counsel to keep other seven days; and they kept [other] seven days with gladness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="24"><p>For Hezekiah king of Judah did give to the assembly for offerings one thousand bulls and seven thousand sheep; and the princes gave to the assembly a thousand bulls and ten thousand sheep: and a great number of priests sanctified themselves. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="25"><p>All the assembly of Judah, with the priests and the Levites, and all the assembly who came out of Israel, and the sojourners who came out of the land of Israel, and who lived in Judah, rejoiced. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="26"><p>So there was great joy in Jerusalem; for since the time of Solomon the son of David king of Israel there was not the like in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:30" n="27"><p>Then the priests the Levites arose and blessed the people: and their voice was heard, and their prayer came up to his holy habitation, even to heaven. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="31"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="1"><p>Now when all this was finished, all Israel who were present went out to the cities of Judah, and broke in pieces the pillars, and hewed down the Asherim, and broke down the high places and the altars out of all Judah and Benjamin, in Ephraim also and Manasseh, until they had destroyed them all. Then all the children of Israel returned, every man to his possession, into their own cities. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="2"><p>Hezekiah appointed the courses of the priests and the Levites after their courses, every man according to his service, both the priests and the Levites, for burnt offerings and for peace-offerings, to minister, and to give thanks, and to praise in the gates of the camp of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="3"><p>[He appointed] also the king’s portion of his substance for the burnt-offerings, [to wit], for the morning and evening burnt offerings, and the burnt offerings for the Sabbaths, and for the new moons, and for the set feasts, as it is written in the law of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="4"><p>Moreover he commanded the people who lived in Jerusalem to give the portion of the priests and the Levites, that they might give themselves to the law of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="5"><p>As soon as the commandment came abroad, the children of Israel gave in abundance the first fruits of grain, new wine, and oil, and honey, and of all the increase of the field; and the tithe of all things brought they in abundantly. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="6"><p>The children of Israel and Judah, who lived in the cities of Judah, they also brought in the tithe of oxen and sheep, and the tithe of dedicated things which were consecrated to Yahweh their God, and laid them by heaps. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="7"><p>In the third month they began to lay the foundation of the heaps, and finished them in the seventh month. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="8"><p>When Hezekiah and the princes came and saw the heaps, they blessed Yahweh, and his people Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="9"><p>Then Hezekiah questioned the priests and the Levites concerning the heaps. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="10"><p>Azariah the chief priest, of the house of Zadok, answered him and said, Since [the people] began to bring the offerings into the house of Yahweh, we have eaten and had enough, and have left plenty: for Yahweh has blessed his people; and that which is left is this great store. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="11"><p>Then Hezekiah commanded to prepare chambers in the house of Yahweh; and they prepared them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="12"><p>They brought in the offerings and the tithes and the dedicated things faithfully: and over them Conaniah the Levite was ruler, and Shimei his brother was second. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="13"><p>Jehiel, and Azaziah, and Nahath, and Asahel, and Jerimoth, and Jozabad, and Eliel, and Ismachiah, and Mahath, and Benaiah, were overseers under the hand of Conaniah and Shimei his brother, by the appointment of Hezekiah the king, and Azariah the ruler of the house of God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="14"><p>Kore the son of Imnah the Levite, the porter at the east [gate], was over the freewill-offerings of God, to distribute the offerings of Yahweh, and the most holy things. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="15"><p>Under him were Eden, and Miniamin, and Jeshua, and Shemaiah, Amariah, and Shecaniah, in the cities of the priests, in their office of trust, to give to their brothers by courses, as well to the great as to the small: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="16"><p>besides those who were reckoned by genealogy of males, from three years old and upward, even everyone who entered into the house of Yahweh, as the duty of every day required, for their service in their offices according to their courses; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="17"><p>and those who were reckoned by genealogy of the priests by their fathers’ houses, and the Levites from twenty years old and upward, in their offices by their courses; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="18"><p>and those who were reckoned by genealogy of all their little ones, their wives, and their sons, and their daughters, through all the congregation: for in their office of trust they sanctified themselves in holiness. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="19"><p>Also for the sons of Aaron the priests, who were in the fields of the suburbs of their cities, in every city, there were men who were mentioned by name, to give portions to all the males among the priests, and to all who were reckoned by genealogy among the Levites. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="20"><p>Thus did Hezekiah throughout all Judah; and he worked that which was good and right and faithful before Yahweh his God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:31" n="21"><p>In every work that he began in the service of the house of God, and in the law, and in the commandments, to seek his God, he did it with all his heart, and prospered. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="32"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="1"><p>After these things, and this faithfulness, Sennacherib king of Assyria came, and entered into Judah, and encamped against the fortified cities, and thought to win them for himself. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="2"><p>When Hezekiah saw that Sennacherib was come, and that he was purposed to fight against Jerusalem, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="3"><p>he took counsel with his princes and his mighty men to stop the waters of the springs which were outside of the city; and they helped him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="4"><p>So there was gathered much people together, and they stopped all the springs, and the brook that flowed through the midst of the land, saying, Why should the kings of Assyria come, and find much water? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="5"><p>He took courage, and built up all the wall that was broken down, and raised [it] up to the towers, and the other wall outside, and strengthened Millo [in] the city of David, and made weapons and shields in abundance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="6"><p>He set captains of war over the people, and gathered them together to him in the broad place at the gate of the city, and spoke comfortably to them, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="7"><p>Be strong and of good courage, don’t be afraid nor dismayed for the king of Assyria, nor for all the multitude who is with him; for there is a greater with us than with him: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="8"><p>with him is an arm of flesh; but with us is Yahweh our God to help us, and to fight our battles. The people rested themselves on the words of Hezekiah king of Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="9"><p>After this did Sennacherib king of Assyria send his servants to Jerusalem, (now he was before Lachish, and all his power with him,) to Hezekiah king of Judah, and to all Judah who were at Jerusalem, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="10"><p>Thus says Sennacherib king of Assyria, Whereon do you trust, that you abide the siege in Jerusalem? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="11"><p>Does not Hezekiah persuade you, to give you over to die by famine and by thirst, saying, Yahweh our God will deliver us out of the hand of the king of Assyria? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="12"><p>Has not the same Hezekiah taken away his high places and his altars, and commanded Judah and Jerusalem, saying, You shall worship before one altar, and on it shall you burn incense? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="13"><p>Don’t you know what I and my fathers have done to all the peoples of the lands? Were the gods of the nations of the lands in any wise able to deliver their land out of my hand? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="14"><p>Who was there among all the gods of those nations which my fathers utterly destroyed, that could deliver his people out of my hand, that your God should be able to deliver you out of my hand? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="15"><p>Now therefore don’t let Hezekiah deceive you, nor persuade you after this manner, neither believe you him; for no god of any nation or kingdom was able to deliver his people out of my hand, and out of the hand of my fathers: how much less shall your God deliver you out of my hand? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="16"><p>His servants spoke yet more against Yahweh God, and against his servant Hezekiah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="17"><p>He wrote also letters, to rail on Yahweh, the God of Israel, and to speak against him, saying, As the gods of the nations of the lands, which have not delivered their people out of my hand, so shall the God of Hezekiah not deliver his people out of my hand. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="18"><p>They cried with a loud voice in the Jews’ language to the people of Jerusalem who were on the wall, to frighten them, and to trouble them; that they might take the city. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="19"><p>They spoke of the God of Jerusalem, as of the gods of the peoples of the earth, which are the work of men’s hands. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="20"><p>Hezekiah the king, and Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz, prayed because of this, and cried to heaven. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="21"><p>Yahweh sent an angel, who cut off all the mighty men of valor, and the leaders and captains, in the camp of the king of Assyria. So he returned with shame of face to his own land. When he was come into the house of his god, those who came forth from his own bowels killed him there with the sword. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="22"><p>Thus Yahweh saved Hezekiah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem from the hand of Sennacherib the king of Assyria, and from the hand of all [others], and guided them on every side. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="23"><p>Many brought gifts to Yahweh to Jerusalem, and precious things to Hezekiah king of Judah; so that he was exalted in the sight of all nations from thenceforth. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="24"><p>In those days Hezekiah was sick even to death: and he prayed to Yahweh; and he spoke to him, and gave him a sign. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="25"><p>But Hezekiah didn’t render again according to the benefit done to him; for his heart was lifted up: therefore there was wrath on him, and on Judah and Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="26"><p>Notwithstanding Hezekiah humbled himself for the pride of his heart, both he and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that the wrath of Yahweh didn’t come on them in the days of Hezekiah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="27"><p>Hezekiah had exceeding much riches and honor: and he provided him treasuries for silver, and for gold, and for precious stones, and for spices, and for shields, and for all manner of goodly vessels; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="28"><p>store-houses also for the increase of grain and new wine and oil; and stalls for all manner of animals, and flocks in folds. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="29"><p>Moreover he provided him cities, and possessions of flocks and herds in abundance; for God had given him very much substance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="30"><p>This same Hezekiah also stopped the upper spring of the waters of Gihon, and brought them straight down on the west side of the city of David. Hezekiah prospered in all his works. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="31"><p>However in [the business of] the ambassadors of the princes of Babylon, who sent to him to inquire of the wonder that was done in the land, God left him, to try him, that he might know all that was in his heart. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="32"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Hezekiah, and his good deeds, behold, they are written in the vision of Isaiah the prophet the son of Amoz, in the book of the kings of Judah and Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:32" n="33"><p>Hezekiah slept with his fathers, and they buried him in the ascent of the tombs of the sons of David: and all Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem did him honor at his death. Manasseh his son reigned in his place. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="33"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="1"><p>Manasseh was twelve years old when he began to reign; and he reigned fifty-five years in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="2"><p>He did that which was evil in the sight of Yahweh, after the abominations of the nations whom Yahweh cast out before the children of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="3"><p>For he built again the high places which Hezekiah his father had broken down; and he reared up altars for the Baals, and made Asheroth, and worshiped all the host of the sky, and served them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="4"><p>He built altars in the house of Yahweh, whereof Yahweh said, In Jerusalem shall my name be forever. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="5"><p>He built altars for all the host of the sky in the two courts of the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="6"><p>He also made his children to pass through the fire in the valley of the son of Hinnom; and he practiced sorcery, and used enchantments, and practiced sorcery, and dealt with those who had familiar spirits, and with wizards: he worked much evil in the sight of Yahweh, to provoke him to anger. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="7"><p>He set the engraved image of the idol, which he had made, in the house of God, of which God said to David and to Solomon his son, In this house, and in Jerusalem, which I have chosen out of all the tribes of Israel, will I put my name forever: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="8"><p>neither will I any more remove the foot of Israel from off the land which I have appointed for your fathers, if only they will observe to do all that I have commanded them, even all the law and the statutes and the ordinances [given] by Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="9"><p>Manasseh seduced Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, so that they did evil more than did the nations whom Yahweh destroyed before the children of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="10"><p>Yahweh spoke to Manasseh, and to his people; but they gave no heed. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="11"><p>Therefore Yahweh brought on them the captains of the host of the king of Assyria, who took Manasseh in chains, and bound him with fetters, and carried him to Babylon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="12"><p>When he was in distress, he begged Yahweh his God, and humbled himself greatly before the God of his fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="13"><p>He prayed to him; and he was entreated of him, and heard his supplication, and brought him again to Jerusalem into his kingdom. Then Manasseh knew that Yahweh he was God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="14"><p>Now after this he built an outer wall to the city of David, on the west side of Gihon, in the valley, even to the entrance at the fish gate; and he compassed Ophel about [with it], and raised it up to a very great height: and he put valiant captains in all the fortified cities of Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="15"><p>He took away the foreign gods, and the idol out of the house of Yahweh, and all the altars that he had built in the mountain of the house of Yahweh, and in Jerusalem, and cast them out of the city. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="16"><p>He built up the altar of Yahweh, and offered thereon sacrifices of peace-offerings and of thanksgiving, and commanded Judah to serve Yahweh, the God of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="17"><p>Nevertheless the people sacrificed still in the high places, but only to Yahweh their God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="18"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Manasseh, and his prayer to his God, and the words of the seers who spoke to him in the name of Yahweh, the God of Israel, behold, they are written among the acts of the kings of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="19"><p>His prayer also, and how [God] was entreated of him, and all his sin and his trespass, and the places in which he built high places, and set up the Asherim and the engraved images, before he humbled himself: behold, they are written in the history of Hozai. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="20"><p>So Manasseh slept with his fathers, and they buried him in his own house: and Amon his son reigned in his place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="21"><p>Amon was twenty-two years old when he began to reign; and he reigned two years in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="22"><p>He did that which was evil in the sight of Yahweh, as did Manasseh his father; and Amon sacrificed to all the engraved images which Manasseh his father had made, and served them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="23"><p>He didn’t humble himself before Yahweh, as Manasseh his father had humbled himself; but this same Amon trespassed more and more. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="24"><p>His servants conspired against him, and put him to death in his own house. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:33" n="25"><p>But the people of the land killed all those who had conspired against king Amon; and the people of the land made Josiah his son king in his place. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="34"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="1"><p>Josiah was eight years old when he began to reign; and he reigned thirty-one years in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="2"><p>He did that which was right in the eyes of Yahweh, and walked in the ways of David his father, and didn’t turn aside to the right hand or to the left. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="3"><p>For in the eighth year of his reign, while he was yet young, he began to seek after the God of David his father; and in the twelfth year he began to purge Judah and Jerusalem from the high places, and the Asherim, and the engraved images, and the molten images. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="4"><p>They broke down the altars of the Baals in his presence; and the sun-images that were on high above them he hewed down; and the Asherim, and the engraved images, and the molten images, he broke in pieces, and made dust of them, and strewed it on the graves [of those] who had sacrificed to them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="5"><p>He burnt the bones of the priests on their altars, and purged Judah and Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="6"><p>[So did he] in the cities of Manasseh and Ephraim and Simeon, even to Naphtali, in their ruins round about. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="7"><p>He broke down the altars, and beat the Asherim and the engraved images into powder, and hewed down all the sun-images throughout all the land of Israel, and returned to Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="8"><p>Now in the eighteenth year of his reign, when he had purged the land and the house, he sent Shaphan the son of Azaliah, and Maaseiah the governor of the city, and Joah the son of Joahaz the recorder, to repair the house of Yahweh his God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="9"><p>They came to Hilkiah the high priest, and delivered the money that was brought into the house of God, which the Levites, the keepers of the threshold, had gathered of the hand of Manasseh and Ephraim, and of all the remnant of Israel, and of all Judah and Benjamin, and of the inhabitants of Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="10"><p>They delivered it into the hand of the workmen who had the oversight of the house of Yahweh; and the workmen who labored in the house of Yahweh gave it to mend and repair the house; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="11"><p>even to the carpenters and to the builders gave they it, to buy hewn stone, and timber for couplings, and to make beams for the houses which the kings of Judah had destroyed. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="12"><p>The men did the work faithfully: and the overseers of them were Jahath and Obadiah, the Levites, of the sons of Merari; and Zechariah and Meshullam, of the sons of the Kohathites, to set it forward; and [others of] the Levites, all who were skillful with instruments of music. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="13"><p>Also they were over the bearers of burdens, and set forward all who did the work in every manner of service: and of the Levites there were scribes, and officers, and porters. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="14"><p>When they brought out the money that was brought into the house of Yahweh, Hilkiah the priest found the book of the law of Yahweh [given] by Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="15"><p>Hilkiah answered Shaphan the scribe, I have found the book of the law in the house of Yahweh. Hilkiah delivered the book to Shaphan. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="16"><p>Shaphan carried the book to the king, and moreover brought back word to the king, saying, All that was committed to your servants, they are doing. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="17"><p>They have emptied out the money that was found in the house of Yahweh, and have delivered it into the hand of the overseers, and into the hand of the workmen. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="18"><p>Shaphan the scribe told the king, saying, Hilkiah the priest has delivered me a book. Shaphan read therein before the king. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="19"><p>It happened, when the king had heard the words of the law, that he tore his clothes. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="20"><p>The king commanded Hilkiah, and Ahikam the son of Shaphan, and Abdon the son of Micah, and Shaphan the scribe, and Asaiah the king’s servant, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="21"><p>Go you, inquire of Yahweh for me, and for those who are left in Israel and in Judah, concerning the words of the book that is found; for great is the wrath of Yahweh that is poured out on us, because our fathers have not kept the word of Yahweh, to do according to all that is written in this book. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="22"><p>So Hilkiah, and they whom the king [had commanded], went to Huldah the prophetess, the wife of Shallum the son of Tokhath, the son of Hasrah, keeper of the wardrobe; (now she lived in Jerusalem in the second quarter;) and they spoke to her to that effect. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="23"><p>She said to them, Thus says Yahweh, the God of Israel: Tell you the man who sent you to me, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="24"><p>Thus says Yahweh, Behold, I will bring evil on this place, and on the inhabitants of it, even all the curses that are written in the book which they have read before the king of Judah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="25"><p>Because they have forsaken me, and have burned incense to other gods, that they might provoke me to anger with all the works of their hands; therefore is my wrath poured out on this place, and it shall not be quenched. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="26"><p>But to the king of Judah, who sent you to inquire of Yahweh, thus shall you tell him, Thus says Yahweh, the God of Israel: As touching the words which you have heard, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="27"><p>because your heart was tender, and you did humble yourself before God, when you heard his words against this place, and against the inhabitants of it, and have humbled yourself before me, and have torn your clothes, and wept before me; I also have heard you, says Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="28"><p>Behold, I will gather you to your fathers, and you shall be gathered to your grave in peace, neither shall your eyes see all the evil that I will bring on this place, and on the inhabitants of it. They brought back word to the king. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="29"><p>Then the king sent and gathered together all the elders of Judah and Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="30"><p>The king went up to the house of Yahweh, and all the men of Judah and the inhabitants of Jerusalem, and the priests, and the Levites, and all the people, both great and small: and he read in their ears all the words of the book of the covenant that was found in the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="31"><p>The king stood in his place, and made a covenant before Yahweh, to walk after Yahweh, and to keep his commandments, and his testimonies, and his statutes, with all his heart, and with all his soul, to perform the words of the covenant that were written in this book. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="32"><p>He caused all who were found in Jerusalem and Benjamin to stand [to it]. The inhabitants of Jerusalem did according to the covenant of God, the God of their fathers. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:34" n="33"><p>Josiah took away all the abominations out of all the countries that pertained to the children of Israel, and made all who were found in Israel to serve, even to serve Yahweh their God. All his days they didn’t depart from following Yahweh, the God of their fathers. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="35"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="1"><p>Josiah kept a Passover to Yahweh in Jerusalem: and they killed the Passover on the fourteenth [day] of the first month. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="2"><p>He set the priests in their offices, and encouraged them to the service of the house of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="3"><p>He said to the Levites who taught all Israel, who were holy to Yahweh, Put the holy ark in the house which Solomon the son of David king of Israel did build; there shall no more be a burden on your shoulders: now serve Yahweh your God, and his people Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="4"><p>Prepare yourselves after your fathers’ houses by your courses, according to the writing of David king of Israel, and according to the writing of Solomon his son. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="5"><p>Stand in the holy place according to the divisions of the fathers’ houses of your brothers the children of the people, and [let there be for each] a portion of a fathers’ house of the Levites. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="6"><p>Kill the Passover, and sanctify yourselves, and prepare for your brothers, to do according to the word of Yahweh by Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="7"><p>Josiah gave to the children of the people, of the flock, lambs and kids, all of them for the Passover offerings, to all who were present, to the number of thirty thousand, and three thousand bulls: these were of the king’s substance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="8"><p>His princes gave for a freewill- offering to the people, to the priests, and to the Levites. Hilkiah and Zechariah and Jehiel, the rulers of the house of God, gave to the priests for the Passover offerings two thousand and six hundred [small cattle], and three hundred oxen. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="9"><p>Conaniah also, and Shemaiah and Nethanel, his brothers, and Hashabiah and Jeiel and Jozabad, the chiefs of the Levites, gave to the Levites for the Passover offerings five thousand [small cattle], and five hundred oxen. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="10"><p>So the service was prepared, and the priests stood in their place, and the Levites by their courses, according to the king’s commandment. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="11"><p>They killed the Passover, and the priests sprinkled [the blood which they received] of their hand, and the Levites flayed them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="12"><p>They removed the burnt offerings, that they might give them according to the divisions of the fathers’ houses of the children of the people, to offer to Yahweh, as it is written in the book of Moses. So did they with the oxen. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="13"><p>They roasted the Passover with fire according to the ordinance: and the holy offerings boiled they in pots, and in caldrons, and in pans, and carried them quickly to all the children of the people. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="14"><p>Afterward they prepared for themselves, and for the priests, because the priests the sons of Aaron [were busied] in offering the burnt offerings and the fat until night: therefore the Levites prepared for themselves, and for the priests the sons of Aaron. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="15"><p>The singers the sons of Asaph were in their place, according to the commandment of David, and Asaph, and Heman, and Jeduthun the king’s seer; and the porters were at every gate: they didn’t need to depart from their service; for their brothers the Levites prepared for them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="16"><p>So all the service of Yahweh was prepared the same day, to keep the Passover, and to offer burnt-offerings on the altar of Yahweh, according to the commandment of king Josiah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="17"><p>The children of Israel who were present kept the Passover at that time, and the feast of unleavened bread seven days. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="18"><p>There was no Passover like that kept in Israel from the days of Samuel the prophet; neither did any of the kings of Israel keep such a Passover as Josiah kept, and the priests, and the Levites, and all Judah and Israel who were present, and the inhabitants of Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="19"><p>In the eighteenth year of the reign of Josiah was this Passover kept. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="20"><p>After all this, when Josiah had prepared the temple, Neco king of Egypt went up to fight against Carchemish by the Euphrates: and Josiah went out against him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="21"><p>But he sent ambassadors to him, saying, What have I to do with you, you king of Judah? [I come] not against you this day, but against the house with which I have war; and God has commanded me to make haste: forbear you from [meddling with] God, who is with me, that he not destroy you. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="22"><p>Nevertheless Josiah would not turn his face from him, but disguised himself, that he might fight with him, and didn’t listen to the words of Neco from the mouth of God, and came to fight in the valley of Megiddo. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="23"><p>The archers shot at king Josiah; and the king said to his servants, Have me away; for I am sore wounded. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="24"><p>So his servants took him out of the chariot, and put him in the second chariot that he had, and brought him to Jerusalem; and he died, and was buried in the tombs of his fathers. All Judah and Jerusalem mourned for Josiah. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="25"><p>Jeremiah lamented for Josiah: and all the singing men and singing women spoke of Josiah in their lamentations to this day; and they made them an ordinance in Israel: and, behold, they are written in the lamentations. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="26"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Josiah, and his good deeds, according to that which is written in the law of Yahweh, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:35" n="27"><p>and his acts, first and last, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2" n="36"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="1"><p>Then the people of the land took Jehoahaz the son of Josiah, and made him king in his father’s place in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="2"><p>Joahaz was twenty-three years old when he began to reign; and he reigned three months in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="3"><p>The king of Egypt deposed him at Jerusalem, and fined the land one hundred talents of silver and a talent of gold. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="4"><p>The king of Egypt made Eliakim his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem, and changed his name to Jehoiakim. Neco took Joahaz his brother, and carried him to Egypt. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="5"><p>Jehoiakim was Twenty-five years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: and he did that which was evil in the sight of Yahweh his God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="6"><p>Against him came up Nebuchadnezzar king of Babylon, and bound him in fetters, to carry him to Babylon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="7"><p>Nebuchadnezzar also carried of the vessels of the house of Yahweh to Babylon, and put them in his temple at Babylon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="8"><p>Now the rest of the acts of Jehoiakim, and his abominations which he did, and that which was found in him, behold, they are written in the book of the kings of Israel and Judah: and Jehoiachin his son reigned in his place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="9"><p>Jehoiachin was eight years old when he began to reign; and he reigned three months and ten days in Jerusalem: and he did that which was evil in the sight of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="10"><p>At the return of the year king Nebuchadnezzar sent, and brought him to Babylon, with the goodly vessels of the house of Yahweh, and made Zedekiah his brother king over Judah and Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="11"><p>Zedekiah was twenty-one years old when he began to reign; and he reigned eleven years in Jerusalem: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="12"><p>and he did that which was evil in the sight of Yahweh his God; he didn’t humble himself before Jeremiah the prophet [speaking] from the mouth of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="13"><p>He also rebelled against king Nebuchadnezzar, who had made him swear by God: but he stiffened his neck, and hardened his heart against turning to Yahweh, the God of Israel. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="14"><p>Moreover all the chiefs of the priests, and the people, trespassed very greatly after all the abominations of the nations; and they polluted the house of Yahweh which he had made holy in Jerusalem. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="15"><p>Yahweh, the God of their fathers, sent to them by his messengers, rising up early and sending, because he had compassion on his people, and on his dwelling-place: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="16"><p>but they mocked the messengers of God, and despised his words, and scoffed at his prophets, until the wrath of Yahweh arose against his people, until there was no remedy. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="17"><p>Therefore he brought on them the king of the Chaldeans, who killed their young men with the sword in the house of their sanctuary, and had no compassion on young man or virgin, old man or gray-headed: he gave them all into his hand. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="18"><p>All the vessels of the house of God, great and small, and the treasures of the house of Yahweh, and the treasures of the king, and of his princes, all these he brought to Babylon. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="19"><p>They burnt the house of God, and broke down the wall of Jerusalem, and burnt all the palaces of it with fire, and destroyed all the goodly vessels of it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="20"><p>Those who had escaped from the sword carried he away to Babylon; and they were servants to him and his sons until the reign of the kingdom of Persia: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="21"><p>to fulfill the word of Yahweh by the mouth of Jeremiah, until the land had enjoyed its Sabbaths: [for] as long as it lay desolate it kept Sabbath, to fulfill seventy years. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="22"><p>Now in the first year of Cyrus king of Persia, that the word of Yahweh by the mouth of Jeremiah might be accomplished, Yahweh stirred up the spirit of Cyrus king of Persia, so that he made a proclamation throughout all his kingdom, and [put it] also in writing, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg016.perseus-eng2:36" n="23"><p>Thus says Cyrus king of Persia, All the kingdoms of the earth has Yahweh, the God of heaven, given me; and he has charged me to build him a house in Jerusalem, which is in Judah. Whoever there is among you of all his people, Yahweh his God be with him, and let him go up. </p> </div> </div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
