<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - Nahum</title>
                
                <editor>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor>
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                  <!-- <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>-->
             <refState unit="chapter"/><refState unit="verse"/></refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>14-Oct-99</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <resp>markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial markup from flat ASCII text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>5/27/09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>RS</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: world.english.xml,v $
			Revision 1.2  2010-06-29 22:00:29  student
			fixing place tags - AD

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:10:56  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.3  2009/05/27 16:11:31  rsingh04
			added/fixed cvs log keyword
                </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="Nahum" type="book">
                <head>Nahum</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        An oracle about Nineveh. The book of the vision of Nahum the
Elkoshite.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Yahweh is a jealous God and avenges. Yahweh avenges
and is full of wrath. Yahweh takes vengeance on his adversaries, and he
maintains wrath against his enemies.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Yahweh is slow to anger, and
great in power, and will by no means leave the guilty unpunished.
Yahweh has his way in the whirlwind and in the storm, and the clouds
are the dust of his feet.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        He rebukes the sea, and makes it dry,
and dries up all the rivers. Bashan languishes, and Carmel; and the
flower of Lebanon languishes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        The mountains quake before him, and
the hills melt away. The earth trembles at his presence, yes, the
world, and all who dwell in it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Who can stand before his
indignation? Who can endure the fierceness of his anger? His wrath is
poured out like fire, and the rocks are broken apart by him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Yahweh is good, a stronghold in the day of trouble; and he knows those
who take refuge in him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        But with an overflowing flood, he will
make a full end of her place, and will pursue his enemies into
darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        What do you plot against Yahweh? He will make a full
end. Affliction won't rise up the second time.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        For entangled
like thorns, and drunken as with their drink, they are consumed utterly
like dry stubble.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        There is one gone forth out of you, who
devises evil against Yahweh, who counsels wickedness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Thus says
Yahweh: "Though they be in full strength, and likewise many, even so
they will be cut down, and he shall pass away. Though I have afflicted
you, I will afflict you no more.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Now will I break his yoke from
off you, and will burst your bonds apart."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Yahweh has commanded
concerning you: "No more descendants will bear your name. Out of the
house of your gods, will I cut off the engraved image and the molten
image. I will make your grave, for you are vile."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Behold, on the mountains the feet of him who brings good
news, who publishes peace! Keep your feasts, Judah! Perform your vows,
for the wicked one will no more pass through you. He is utterly cut off.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        He who dashes in pieces has come up against you. Keep the
fortress! Watch the way! Strengthen your loins! Fortify your power
mightily!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        For Yahweh restores the excellency of Jacob, as the
excellency of Israel; for the destroyers have destroyed them, and
ruined their vine branches.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        The shield of his mighty men is made
red. The valiant men are in scarlet. The chariots flash with steel in
the day of his preparation, and the pine spears are brandished.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        The chariots rage in the streets. They rush back and forth in the broad
ways. Their appearance is like torches. They run like the lightnings.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        He summons his picked troops. They stumble on their way. They
dash to its wall, and the protective shield is put in place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        The
gates of the rivers are opened, and the palace is dissolved.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        It
is decreed: she is uncovered, she is carried away; and her handmaids
moan as with the voice of doves, beating on their breasts.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        But
Nineveh has been from of old like a pool of water, yet they flee away.
"Stop! Stop!" they cry, but no one looks back.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Take the spoil of
silver. Take the spoil of gold, for there is no end of the store, the
glory of all goodly furniture.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        She is empty, void, and waste.
The heart melts, the knees knock together, their bodies and faces have
grown pale.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Where is the den of the lions, and the feeding-place
of the young lions, where the lion and the lioness walked, the lion's
cubs, and no one made them afraid?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        The lion tore in pieces
enough for his cubs, and strangled for his lionesses, and filled his
caves with the kill, and his dens with prey.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        "Behold, I am
against you," says Yahweh of Hosts, "and I will burn her chariots in
the smoke, and the sword will devour your young lions; and I will cut
off your prey from the earth, and the voice of your messengers will no
longer be heard."
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Woe to the bloody city! It is all full of lies and robbery.
The prey doesn't depart.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        The noise of the whip, the noise of the
rattling of wheels, prancing horses, and bounding chariots,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        the
horseman mounting, and the flashing sword, the glittering spear, and a
multitude of slain, and a great heap of corpses, and there is no end of
the bodies. They stumble on their bodies,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        because of the
multitude of the prostitution of the alluring prostitute, the mistress
of witchcraft, who sells nations through her prostitution, and families
through her witchcraft.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        "Behold, I am against you," says Yahweh
of Hosts, "and I will lift your skirts over your face. I will show the
nations your nakedness, and the kingdoms your shame.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        I will throw
abominable filth on you, and make you vile, and will set you a
spectacle.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        It will happen that all those who look at you will
flee from you, and say, 'Nineveh is laid waste Who will mourn for her?'
Where will I seek comforters for you?"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Are you better than No-Amon, who was situated among the
rivers, who had the waters around her; whose rampart was the sea, and
her wall was of the sea?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Cush and Egypt were her boundless
strength. Put and Libya were her helpers.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Yet was she carried
away. She went into captivity. Her young children also were dashed in
pieces at the head of all the streets, and they cast lots for her
honorable men, and all her great men were bound in chains.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        You
also will be drunken. You will be hidden. You also will seek a
stronghold because of the enemy.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        All your fortresses will be
like fig trees with the first-ripe figs: if they are shaken, they fall
into the mouth of the eater.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Behold, your troops in your midst
are women. The gates of your land are set wide open to your enemies.
The fire has devoured your bars.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Draw water for the siege.
Strengthen your fortresses. Go into the clay, and tread the mortar.
Make the brick kiln strong.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        There the fire will devour you. The
sword will cut you off. It will devour you like the grasshopper.
Multiply like grasshoppers. Multiply like the locust.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        You have
increased your merchants more than the stars of the skies. The
grasshopper strips, and flees away.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Your guards are like the
locusts, and your officials like the swarms of locusts, which settle on
the walls on a cold day, but when the sun appears, they flee away, and
their place is not known where they are.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Your shepherds slumber,
king of Assyria. Your nobles lie down. Your people are scattered on the
mountains, and there is no one to gather them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        There is no
healing your wound, for your injury is fatal. All who hear the report
of you clap their hands over you; for who hasn't felt your endless
cruelty?
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
