<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sayings of Spartan Women</title>
            <author>Plutarch</author>
            <editor>Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
               <name>Bridget Almas</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2010-12-13</date></publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date type="printing">1931</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
               </monogr>
               <ref target="https://archive.org/details/L245PlutarchMoraliaIIIKingsCommandersRomansSpartans/page/n469">The Internet Archive</ref></biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
            <p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest Epidoc standards</p>
            <p>The following text is encoded in accordance with Epxml:idoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
               matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
               replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
            <cRefPattern n="chapter"
               matchPattern="(\w+)"
               replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change who="Lisa Cerrato" when="2019-08-19">Epidoc and CTS Compliance</change>
         <change who="RS" when="2010-05-01">tagged and parsed</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body> 
         <div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg082b.perseus-eng2" type="translation" xml:lang="eng"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="intro"> <pb xml:id="v.3.p.453"/> 
  <head>INTRODUCTION</head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
<p rend="indent">Of the <title>Sayings of Spartan Women</title> the same may be said as of the <title>Sayings of Spartans</title>. It truly represents the work of Plutarch, and many of the sayings are repeated elsewhere in his writings; others perhaps in his writings that are now lost. Whether the sayings were collected in this form by Plutarch or by someone else is a matter of minor importance. </p> </div> </div> <pb xml:id="v.3.p.455"/> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1"> <head>ARGILEONIS</head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
<p rend="indent">Argileonis, the mother of Brasidas, when her son had met his death,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">At the battle of Amphipolis, 422 b.c.</note> and some of the citizens of Amphipolis arrived at Sparta and came to her, asked if her son had met his death honourably and in a manner worthy of Sparta. And when th ey proceeded to tell of his greatness, and declared that he was the best of all the Spartans in such enterprises, she said, <q>Sirs, my son was a gude and honourable mon, but Sparta has mony a mon better than him.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> the note on <title>Moralia</title>, 190 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> </p> </div> </div> 

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2"> <head>GORGO<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Gorgo later became the wife of Leonidas.</note> </head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
<p rend="indent">Gorgo, daughter of king Cleomenes, when Aristagoras of Miletus was urging her father to enter upon the war against the Persian king in behalf of the Ionians, promising a vast sum of money, and, in answer to Cleomenes’ objections, making the amount larger and larger, said, <q>Father, the miserable foreigner will be your ruin if you don’t get him out of the house pretty soon!</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Herodotus, v. 48-51.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
<p rend="indent">Once when her father told her to give some grain to a man by way of remuneration, and added, <q>It is because he showed me how to make the wine <pb xml:id="v.3.p.457"/> taste good,</q> she said, <q>Then, father, there will be more wine drunk, and the drinkers will become more intemperate and depraved.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> the note on <title>Moralia</title>, 218 d (4), where the same idea is attributed to Archidamus.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
<p rend="indent">When she had watched Aristagoras having his shoes put on and laced by one of the servants, she said, <q>Father, the foreigner hasn’t any hands!</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diogenes Laertius, vi. 44, where Diogenes the cynic goes Gorgo one better.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
<p rend="indent">When a foreigner made advances in a mild and leisurely way, she pushed him aside, saying, <q>Get away from here, you who cannot play a woman’s part either!</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
<p rend="indent">Being asked by a woman from Attica, <q>Why is it that you Spartan women are the only women that lord it over your men,</q> she said, <q>Because we are the only women that are mothers of men.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 227 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>, and the note.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
<p rend="indent">As she was encouraging her husband Leonidas, when he was about to set out for Thermopylae, to show himself worthy of Sparta, she asked what she should do; and he said, <q>Marry a good man, and bear good children.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 225 a (2), <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> </p> </div> </div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3"> <head>GYRTIAS</head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
<p rend="indent">Gyrtias, when on a time Acrotatus, her grandson, in a fight with other boys received many blows, and was brought home for dead, and the family and friends were all wailing, said, <q>Will you not stop your noise ? He has shown from what blood he was sprung.</q> And she said that people who were good for anything should not scream, but should try to find some remedy.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The last sentence is borrowed from Plato, <title>Republic</title>, 604 c.</note> <pb xml:id="v.3.p.459"/> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
<p rend="indent">When a messenger came from Crete bringing the news of the death of Acrotatus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Son of Areus I., king of Sparta. He fell in battle at Megalopolis in 265 bc., but the fact that hsi father Areus had been fighting in Crete may account for the intrusion of Crete here. Pausanias (viii. 27. 11) makes a more serious error in confusing this Acrotatus with his grandfather of the same name.</note> she said, <q>When he had come to the enemy, was he not bound either to be slain by them or to slay them ? It is more pleasing to hear that he died in a manner worthy of myself, his country, and his ancestors than if he had lived for all time a coward.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> the similar saying of a Spartan woman, quoted by Teles in Stobaeus, <title>Florilegium</title>, cviii. 83.</note> </p> </div> </div> 
            
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4"> <head>DAMATRIA</head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
<p rend="indent">Damatria heard that her son had been a coward and unworthy of her, and when he arrived, she made away with him. This is the epigram<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> the <title>Palatine Anthology</title>, vii. no. 433, or W. R. Paton, <title>The Greek Anthology</title> (in L.C.L.), ii. p. 238.</note> referring to her: <quote rend="blockquote">Sinner against our laws, Damatrius, slain by his mother, Was of the Spartan youth; she was of Sparta too.</quote> </p> </div> </div> 
            
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5"> <head>OTHER SPARTAN WOMEN TO FAME UNKNOWN</head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
<p rend="indent">Another Spartan woman made away with her son, who had deserted his post, on the ground that he was unworthy of his country, saying, <q>Not mine the scion.</q> This is the epigram referring to her<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> the variant version in the <title>Palatine Anthology</title>, vii. no. 433 (or W. R. Paton, <title>The Greek Anthology</title> (in L.C.L.), ii. p. 238).</note>: <quote rend="blockquote"> <l>Off to your fate through the darkness, vile scion, who makes such a hatred, So the Eurotas flow not e’en for the timorous deer. </l> <l>Worthless whelp that you are, vile remnant, be oif now to Hades; Off! for never I bore Sparta’s unworthy son.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 242 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra</foreign>.</note> </l> </quote> <pb xml:id="v.3.p.461"/> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
<p rend="indent">Another, hearing that her son had fallen on the field of battle, said:<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 235 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> <quote rend="blockquote"> <l>Let the poor cowards be mourned, but, with never a tear do I bury </l> <l>You, my son, who are mine, yea, and are Sparta’s as well.</l> </quote> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
<p rend="indent">Another, hearing that her son had been saved and had run away from the enemy, wrote to him, <q>Ill report is spread about ye; aither clear yersel’ of this or stop yer living.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
<p rend="indent">Another, when her sons had run away from battle and come to her, said, <q>Where have you come now in your cowardly flight, vile varlets ? Do you intend to slink in here whence you came forth?</q> And with these words she pulled up her garment and showed them.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 246 a, and Teles as quoted by Stobaeus, <title>Florilegium</title>, cviii. 83.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
<p rend="indent">One woman, observing her son coming towards her, inquired, <q>How fares our country?</q> And when he said, <q>All have perished,</q> she took up a tile and, hurling it at him, killed him, saying, <q>And so they sent you to bear the bad news to us!</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
<p rend="indent">As a man was narrating to his mother the noble death of his brother, she said, <q>Isn’t it a shame, then, to have missed his company on such a journey ?</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 242 b (22), <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra</foreign>.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
<p rend="indent">One woman sent forth her sons, five in number, to war, and, standing in the outskirts of the city, she awaited anxiously the outcome of the battle. And when someone arrived and, in answer to her inquiry, reported that all her sons had met death, she said, <pb xml:id="v.3.p.463"/> <q>I did not inquire about that, you vile varlet, but how fares our country ?</q> And when he declared that it was victorious, <q>Then,</q> she said, <q>I accept gladly also the death of my sons.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Plutarch’s <title>Life of Agesilaus</title>, chap. xxix. (612 c-d).</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
<p rend="indent">Another was burying her son, when a commonplace old woman came up to her and said, <q>Ah the bad luck of it, you puir woman.</q> <q>No, by Heaven,</q> said she, <q>but good luck; for I bore him that he might die for Sparta, and this is the very thing that has come to pass for me.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The story is told also by Teles in Stobaeus, <title>Florilegium</title>, cviii. 83; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> also Cicero, <title>Tusculan Disputations</title>, i. 42 (102).</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
<p rend="indent">When a woman from Ionia showed vast pride in a bit of her own weaving, which was very valuable, a Spartan woman pointed to her four sons, who were most well-behaved, and said, <q>Such should be the employments of the good and honourable woman, and it is over these that she should be elated and boastful.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Severus in Stobaeus, <title>Florilegium</title>, v. 47, and the similar story of the Roman Cornelia, the mother of the Gracchi.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
<p rend="indent">Another, hearing about her son that he was conducting himself badly in a foreign land, wrote to him, <q>Ill report is spread about ye; pit this from ye or else stop yer living.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 241 a (3), <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
<p rend="indent">Of somewhat similar character is this: Chian exiles came to Sparta, and accused Paedaretus of many misdeeds; whereupon his mother Teleutia sent for them and, after listening to their complaints, feeling that her son was in the wrong, sent him this letter: <q>Mither to Paedaretus. Aither dae better, or stay whare ye are, and gie up hope o’ gaen back safe to Sparta.</q> <pb xml:id="v.3.p.465"/> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
<p rend="indent">Another, when her son was being tried for some offence, said to him, <q>My child, either rid yourself of the charges, or rid yourself of life.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
<p rend="indent">Another, as she accompanied a lame son on his way to the field of battle, said, <q>At every step, my child, remember your valour.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 331 b; Stobaeus, <title>Florilegium</title>, vii. 29; Cicero, <title>De oratore</title>, ii. 61 (249).</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
<p rend="indent">Another, when her son came back to her from the field of battle wounded in the foot, and in great pain, said, <q>If you remember your valour, my child, you will feel no pain, and be quite cheerful.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 331 b; Stobaeus, <title>Florilegium</title>, vii. 29; Cicero, <title>De oratore</title>, ii. 61 (249).</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
<p rend="indent">A Spartan, wounded in battle and unable to walk, was crawling on all fours. He was mortified at being so ridiculous; but his mother said to him, <q>How much better to be joyful over your bravery rather than to be mortified at silly laughter.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
<p rend="indent">Another, as she handed her son his shield, exhorted him, saying, <q>Either this or upon this.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Referred to Gorgo as the author by Aristotle in his <title>Aphorisms</title>, as quoted by Stobaeus, <title>Florilegium</title>, vii. 31, but it is often spoken of as a regular Spartan custom. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign>, for example, the scholium on Thucydides, ii. 39. <p/>Ancient writers were not agreed whether the second half meant to fall upon the shield (dead or wounded) or to be brought home dead upon it. In support of the second (traditional) interpretation <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 235 a, and Valerius Maximus, ii. 7, ext. 2.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
<p rend="indent">Another, as her son was going forth to war, said, as she gave the shield into his hands, <q>This shield your father kept always safe for you; do you, therefore, keep it safe, or cease to live.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
<p rend="indent">Another, in answer to her son who said that the sword which he carried was short,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 191 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> said, <q>Add a step to it.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
<p rend="indent">Another, hearing that her son had been slain fighting bravely in the line of battle, said, <q>Yes, he <pb xml:id="v.3.p.467"/> was mine.</q> But learning in regard to her other son that he had played the coward and saved his life, she said, <q>No, he was not mine,</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 241 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
<p rend="indent">Another, hearing that her son had been killed in battle on the spot where he had been placed, said, <q>Lay him away, and let his brother take his place.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
<p rend="indent">Another, engaged in conducting a solemn public procession, heard that her son was victorious on the field of battle, but that he was dying from the many wounds he had received. She did not remove the garland from her head, but with a proud air said to the women near her, <q>How much more noble, my friends, to be victorious on the field of battle and meet death, than to win at the Olympic games and live!</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> the somewhat similar story about Xenophon in <title>Moralia</title>, 118 f.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
<p rend="indent">As a man was relating to his sister the noble death of her son, she said, <q>As glad as I am for him, I am sorry for you that you were left behind when you might have gone in such brave company.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 241 b (6), <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
<p rend="indent">A man sent to a Spartan woman to ask if she were inclined to look with favour upon seduction; she replied, <q>When I was a child I learned to obey my father, and made that my practice. Then when I became a married woman, my husband took that place. So if the man’s proposal is honourable, let him lay the matter before my husband first.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
<p rend="indent">A poor girl, being asked what dowry she brought to the man who married her, said, <q>The family virtue.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
<p rend="indent">A Spartan woman, being asked if she had made advances to her husband, said, <q>No, but my husband has made them to me.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 140 c.</note> <pb xml:id="v.3.p.469"/> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
<p rend="indent">A girl had secret relations with a man, and, after bringing on an abortion, she bore up so bravely, not uttering a single sound, that her delivery took place without the knowledge of her father and others who were near. For the confronting of her indecorum with decorum gained the victory over the poignant distress of her pains. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
<p rend="indent">A Spartan woman who was being sold as a slave, when asked what she knew how to do, said, <q>To be faithful.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
<p rend="indent">Another, taken captive, and asked a similar question, said, <q>To manage a house well.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
<p rend="indent">Another, asked by a man if she would be good if he bought her, said, <q>Yes, and if you do not buy me.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 234 c (39), <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
<p rend="indent">Another who was being sold as a slave, when the crier inquired of her what she knew how to do, said, <q>To be free.</q> And when the purchaser ordered her to do something not fitting for a free woman, she said, <q>You will be sorry that your meanness has cost you such a possession,</q> and committed suicide.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> <title>Moralia</title>, 234 b (37 and 38), <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> </p> </div> </div> </div> </body>
   </text>
</TEI>