<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Letters</title>
				<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
				<author>Demosthenes</author>
				<editor role="editor">Norman W. DeWitt</editor>
				<editor role="editor">Norman J. DeWitt</editor> &responsibility; &fund.AnnCPB; </titleStmt> &Perseus.publish; <sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
          <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by Norman W. DeWitt, Ph.D., and Norman J.
            DeWitt, Ph.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1949</date>
        </bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state delim="." unit="letter"/>
				<state unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state n="chunk" unit="card"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English </language>
				<language id="greek">Greek </language>
				<language id="la">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
	    <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">copyrighted CTS texts from sdl and classics in new canonical structure per github repo</change>
	    <change when="2010-08-31" who="rsingh04">cleaned up log keyword</change>
	    <change when="2009-11-16" who="rsingh04">moved more texts around based on copyright status</change>
	    <change when="2009-06-19" who="lcerrato">fixed bad bibls</change> 
	    <change when="2009-06-12" who="lcerrato">fixed bad bibls</change> 
	    <change when="2009-06-09" who="student">fixed bibl errors - zr</change>
	    <change when="2009-05-19" who="lcerrato">fixed bad bibls</change> 
	    <change when="2009-04-17" who="lcerrato">fixing bad bibls</change> 
	    <change when="2009-03-02" who="rsingh04">fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags</change>
	    <change when="2008-11-26" who="lcerrato">fixing bad bibls</change> 
	    <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change> 
	    <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
	    <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
	    <change when="2000-03-06" who="amahoney">remove spurious headers </change>
	    <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change> 
	    <change when="2000-02-29" who="amahoney">split the exordia and letters into separate files; add cards to the letters so they can chunk gracefully</change> 
	    <change when="2000-02-29" who="AEM"/>
	    <change when="2000-02-28" who="AEM">convert to P3</change> 
	    <change when="1992-06-26" who="EM">changed numbering of erotic elegy, exordia and letters to 0. from 61, 61 and 2</change>
	    <change when="1992-01-01" who="staff">Text was scanned at St. Olaf Spring, 1992.</change>
	  </revisionDesc>


	</teiHeader>

	<text lang="en">
		<body>
			<div1 type="Letter" n="1">
				<head>On Political Harmony</head>
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Citations from sects. 6 and 12 of this letter are
            found in Bekker’s <title>Anecdota</title>, Antiatticista pp. 111. 31. and 110. 5, a
            lexicographical work. This is evidence for authenticity.</note> For one who is about to
          take any serious step, whether in speech or action, I assume that the proper course is to
          take his beginning from the gods. Accordingly I entreat all the gods and goddesses that
          what is best for the democracy of the Athenians and for those who bear goodwill toward the
          democracy, both now and for time to come, I may myself be moved to write and the members
          of the Assembly to adopt. With this prayer, having hopes of good inspiration from the
          gods, I address this message.</p>
				<p>Demosthenes to the Council and the Assembly sends greeting. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Concerning the question of my return<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demosthenes is
            writing from exile on the island of Calauria south of <placeName key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, <date value="-323">323</date> B.C.</note> to my native land I
          always bear in mind that it will be for you as a body to decide; consequently I am writing
          nothing about it at the present moment. Observing, however, that the present occasion, if
          you but choose the right course, is capable of securing for you at one stroke glory and
          safety and freedom, not for yourselves alone but for all the rest of the Greeks as well,
          but that, if you act in ignorance or be led astray, it would not be easy to secure the
          same opportunity again, I thought I ought to place before the public the state of my
          opinion on these questions. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>It is a difficult thing, I
          know, for advice conveyed by letter to hold its ground,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Isocrates enlarges upon this difficulty, <bibl n="Isoc. L. 1.2">Isoc. L. 1.2-3</bibl>
            and <bibl n="Isoc. 5.25">Isoc. 5.25-26</bibl></note> because you Athenians have a way of
          opposing many suggestions without waiting to understand them. In the case of a speaker, of
          course, it is possible to perceive what you want and easy to correct your
          misapprehensions; but the written page possesses no such aid against those who raise a
          clamor. In spite of this fact, if you will but consent to listen in silence and have the
          patience to learn all that I have to say, I think that,&mdash;to speak in the hope of
          divine favour&mdash;brief though the writing is, I shall myself be found to be doing
          my duty by you with all goodwill and that I shall demonstrate clearly where your interests
          lie. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Not as supposing you were running short of speakers,
          or of those, either, who will say glibly and without real thought what happens to occur to
          them, did I decide to send the letter; but I desired, after putting plainly before those
          who like to make speeches all that I happen to know through experience and long
          association with public business, first, to furnish them with ample means of arriving at
          what I deem to be your interests, and second, to render easy for the people the choice of
          the best procedures. Such, then, were the considerations that prompted me to write the
          letter. <milestone n="1.5" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="5" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>First of all, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, it is necessary
          that you bring about harmony<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cicero saturated his mind
            with the writings of Demosthenes. &ldquo;Political harmony&rdquo; will be
            recognized as his political ideal: <title>Ad Atticum</title> 1. 14. 4; his friend
            Demitrius of Magnesia wrote on the subject: ibid. 8. 11. 7. The Romans deified this
            abstraction under the name <placeName key="tgn,1019348">Concordia</placeName></note>
          among yourselves for the common good of the State and drop all the contentions inherited
          from previous assemblies and, in the second place, that you all with one mind vigorously
          support your decisions, since the failure to follow either a uniform policy or to act
          consistently is not only unworthy of you and ignoble but, in addition, involves the
          greatest risks. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>Those things must not escape your
          attention either, which, though by themselves they are not sufficient to effect your
          purpose, yet when added to your military forces, will render all your aims much easier of
          accomplishment. To what, then, do I refer? Toward no city and toward none of the citizens
          in this or that city who have supported the existing order<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> were forced
            to set up pro-Macedonian governments after the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> in <date value="-338">338</date> B.C. A Macedonian garrison was
            stationed in <placeName key="tgn,7011071">Thebes</placeName>. <placeName key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName> was less harshly treated but outspoken advocates
            of freedom were out of favour.</note> must you harbor any bitterness<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The verb <foreign lang="greek">pikrai/nesqai</foreign> is cited as used by
            Demosthenes, Bekker, 1. p. 111. 31.</note> or bear a grudge. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Because the fear of such animosity causes those who are conscious of
          guilt in their own hearts, because necessary to the existing order and facing a manifest
          danger, to be zealous supporters of it, but relieved of this fear they will all become
          more amenable, and this is of no slight usefulness. Now, to proclaim such intentions in
          the various cities would be foolish, or rather quite impossible, but in whatever spirit
          you shall be seen treating your own fellow-citizens, such will be the expectation you will
          create in the minds of each group concerning your feeling toward the rest also. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Accordingly I say that in general you must not cast any blame or
          censure whatsoever upon any general or orator or private individual of the groups that are
          believed, at least previously, to have supported the existing order, but rather concede to
          all parties in the city that they have done their duty as public men, inasmuch as the
          gods, to whom be thanks, by saving the city have bestowed upon you the privilege of
          deciding afresh whatever you shall choose to do, and you must be of the opinion that, just
          as on board a ship, when some declare themselves for making good their escape by the sail
          and others by the oars, just as all proposals of both parties aim at salvation, so it is
          to meet a crisis created by the gods that the need has arisen. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>If you shall have made up your minds to regard past events in this way,
          you will gain the confidence of all and play the part of good and honorable men; you will
          also further your own interests not a little and will cause your opponents in the various
          cities either to change their minds, all of them, or will cause only a certain very small
          number of them, the ringleaders themselves, to be left. Acquit yourselves, therefore, with
          magnanimity and statesmanship in the general interest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> and bear in mind your own interests as Athenians.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The implication is that the interests of the Athenians
            coincide with the good of all, but the editors add <foreign lang="greek">mh\</foreign>:
            &ldquo;Do not think of your own interests.&rdquo;</note>
          <milestone n="10" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>I urge you to this line of conduct, though I have not myself met with such generosity
          from certain persons but have been unjustly and in a spirit of faction tossed off<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The odd metaphor derives from the reckless giving of
            presents in connection with the drinking of toasts at banquets. Lexicon under <foreign lang="greek">propi/nw</foreign>.</note> for the gratification of others. I do not
          think, however, that I have the right while satisfying my private resentment to hurt the
          public interest, nor do I at all mix my private enmity with the general good. On the
          contrary, the conduct I urge upon the rest of men I think I ought to be myself the first
          to practise. <milestone n="1.11" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="11" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now, the steps to be taken by way of preparation and the mistakes to be guarded against,
          and the measures by which one might, as human calculations go, most likely succeed, have
          been, for practical purposes, stated by me; but how to oversee our business from day to
          day and how to deal rightly with situations that arise unexpectedly, <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>how to know the right moment for each action and to judge which of our
          objectives it is possible to attain through negotiation<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Under the word <foreign lang="greek">o(mili/a</foreign> this passage is cited by
            Bekker, 1. p. 110. 4-6.</note> and which requires force in addition, these are the
          responsibility of the generals in charge. Therefore to give advice is to be in a very
          difficult position, because decisions that have been rightly taken and weighed with great
          care and pains are often spoiled through faulty execution on the part of those in
          authority. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>Yet I hope that all will be well this time;
          for if any man has assumed that Alexander was fortunate because he always succeeded,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Plutarch wrote an essay entitled &ldquo;Whether the
            success of Alexander was due to luck or ability.&rdquo;</note> let him reflect upon
          the fact that it was by doing and toiling and daring, not by sitting still, that he
          continued to be fortunate. Now, therefore, since Alexander is dead, Fortune is seeking
          some people with whom to co-operate, and you ought to become her choice. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>As for your leaders, through whom your interests must necessarily be
          handled, place at the head of your forces men whose loyalty is the greatest available, and
          as for yourselves, let every man of you repeat to himself a solemn promise to perform
          whatever he in particular shall be able and shall elect to do. And see to it that he does
          not break this pledge or shirk his responsibility, saying that he was deceived or misled
          and overpersuaded, <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>because you will never find others to
          make good the lack of those qualities in which you yourselves shall fall short; neither
          does it involve the same danger to change your minds often about matters wherein it will
          be in your power to do as you please as it does about matters over which war will arise;
          but in the case of the latter a change of mind means defeat of your purpose. So do nothing
          of this kind, but whatever you intend to execute honestly and promptly with your whole
          souls, vote for that, <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>and once you have passed a decree,
          adopt as your leaders Zeus of <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> and the
          rest of the gods, who have uttered in your interest many splendid, encouraging and true
          oracles, and summon them to your aid and after you have prayed to all of them for success
          with a vow of the fruits of victory,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf. <bibl n="Plut. Mar. 26">Plut. Marius 26</bibl>
            <foreign lang="greek">eu)/cato toi=s qeoi=s kata\ e(kato/mbhs</foreign>, &ldquo;He
            prayed to the gods for victory, taking a vow to sacrifice a hecatomb.&rdquo;</note>
          with good fortune attending you, proceed to liberate the Greeks. Farewell.</p>
			</div1>
			<milestone n="2" unit="card"/>
			<div1 type="Letter" n="2">
				<head>Concerning His Own Restoration</head>
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Three citations of this letter may be found in Walz’s
              <title>Rhetores Graeci</title>, which will be mentioned in the footnotes. Harpocration
            refers to sect. 20 under the name <title>Calauria</title>.</note> Demosthenes to the
          Council and the Assembly sends greeting</p>
				<p>I used to believe, because of my conduct in public life, that, as one who was guilty of
          no wrong toward you, I should not only never meet with such treatment as this<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The opening sentence down to this point is cited by
              <bibl>Hermog. Rhet. Graec. 3</bibl>, p. 349.</note> but, even if I should have
          committed some slight offence, that I might meet with forgiveness. Since, however, it has
          turned out as it has, so long as I observed you, without any manifest proof or even a
          scrutiny of evidence on the part of the Council,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">In
              <bibl n="Plut. Dem. 26">Plut. Dem. 26</bibl>, Plutarch informs us that the trial took
            place before the Areopagus. This was in the spring of <date value="-324">324</date> B.C.
            The exile lasted a year.</note> condemning all the accused on the strength of the
          unrevealed information of that body, I chose to make the best of it, thinking that you
          were surrendering rights no less valuable than those of which I was being deprived.
          Because, for the jurors under oath to assent to whatever the Council should declare,
          without any proof having been cited, that was a surrender of a constitutional right.
            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Since, however, you have happily become aware of the
          undue ascendancy. which certain members of the Council were contriving for themselves and
          since you are now deciding the cases in the light of the proofs and have found the
          secretiveness of these men deserving of censure, I think it is my right, with your
          consent, to enjoy the same acquittal as those who have incurred the like accusations, and
          not to be the only one to be deprived on a false charge of his fatherland, his property,
          and the company of those who are nearest and dearest to him. <milestone n="2.3" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>And you would have good reason, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to be concerned about my deliverance, not only for the reason that I
          have been outrageously treated, though guilty of doing you no wrong, but also for the sake
          of your good name abroad. For you must not imagine, just because no one reminds you of
          those times and occasions upon which I was of the greatest service to the city, <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>that the rest of the Greeks are not aware of them or have
          forgotten what I have accomplished in your behalf. At the present moment I hesitate to
          write of these services in detail for two reasons; one reason is that I am afraid of
          jealousy, in the face of which it is useless to speak the truth; the second is this, that
          because of the cowardice of the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> we
          are now compelled to do many things that are below the standard of those services of mine.
            <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>In brief, however, the record upon which I passed
          scrutiny as your servant was of such a kind as to make you envied by all because of it and
          myself confident in the greatest rewards from you. And when Fortune, as irresistible as
          she was unkind, decided as she pleased, and not according to justice, the struggle<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The reference is to the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, <date value="-338">338</date> B.C.</note> for
          the liberty of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> in which you engaged,
            <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>not even in the times that followed did I retreat from
          my loyalty toward you, nor did I bargain for anything in place of it, no man’s favour, no
          hopes of preferment, nor wealth, nor power, nor personal safety. Yet I observed that all
          these prizes were accruing to those who chose to play the game of politics to your
          detriment. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now one fact which is especially significant&mdash;although there are many
          significant facts which, it occurs to me, would justify me in speaking frankly&mdash;I
          shall not refrain from writing to you: although of men who are mentioned in history in all
          time, Philip had the most uncanny ability of all, whether through personal contact to
          persuade men to pay heed to his wishes or to corrupt with bribes the notable men in every
          one of the Greek cities, <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>I was the only man who did not
          fall a victim to either of these methods, a fact that brings to you also cause for pride,
          and although I met Philip often and parleyed with him on those matters on which you sent
          me as envoy,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demosthenes was one of ten envoys who
            negotiated with Philip the Peace of Philocrates in <date value="-346">346</date> B.C.
            and was several times sent on similar missions afterwards.</note> yet I kept my hands
          off the substantial sums he offered me, as many men are aware who still live. Just ponder
          what opinion these men may reasonably entertain of you, for to have dealt this treatment
          to such a man, while for myself I am sure it would seem a misfortune, though no conviction
          of vice, yet on your part it would seem defiance of justice.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This sentence is cited by Hermogenes, <title>Rhetores Graeci</title> 3, p.
            235 and by Maximus Planudes, ibid. 5, p.395.</note> I beg of you to change your verdict
          and cancel this imputation. <milestone n="2.9" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="9" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>All the considerations which I have mentioned above, however, I consider of less
          importance than my conduct from first to last and every day in public life, in which I
          showed myself in action to be a statesman, never encouraging any nursing of a grudge or a
          feud or the grasping for unfair advantage, whether shared or for myself, never preferring
          false charges against either citizen or alien, never being over-clever to work in secret
          against your interests but always working for them, if occasion should arise, and above
          board, subject to public approval. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>The older men would
          know&mdash;and in all fairness you ought to inform the younger ones&mdash;of the
          hearing granted Python<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Python, pupil of Isocrates and a
            presumptuous orator headed a deputation of all the Allies of Philip when they come to
              <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in <date value="-343">343</date>
            B.C. to accuse the people of unjust conduct. See <bibl n="Dem. 7.20">Dem.
            7.20-23</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 18.136">Dem. 18.136</bibl>, <bibl n="Plut. Dem. 9">Plut.
              Dem. 9</bibl>, and <bibl>Lucian Encomium 32</bibl>.</note> of <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName> before the Assembly when he arrived with
          the envoys from the Greeks, expecting to show that the city was acting unjustly, but went
          away with the tables turned against him after I, alone of those who spoke on that
          occasion, had brought out the rights of the matter in your defence. I forbear to mention
          all the embassies upon which I served in support of your interests, in which you were
          never worsted even in a single instance; <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>for I shaped my
          policy, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, not with an eye to
          helping you get the better of one another, nor whetting the State against itself, but
          furthering measures from which I thought a reputation for magnanimity would redound to
          you. With such aspirations you should all be delighted, and especially the younger men,
          not looking for someone who will always play the lackey to win your favour in his public
          conduct&mdash;for of this type there will never be a dearth&mdash;but for one who,
          actuated by loyalty, will even rebuke you for your errors of judgement. <milestone n="2.12" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="12" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now I pass over many other considerations, on the strength of which a different kind of a
          man and with no other service to his credit would justly demand to obtain acquittal; I
          mean the equipping of choruses and triremes and the contributing of money on all
            occasions.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Prosperous citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> were required from time to time to contribute
            money for the equipment of triremes, dramatic choruses, and religious deputations to
            various shrines. These were the <foreign lang="greek">lh|tourgi/ai</foreign>in contrast
            to the <foreign lang="greek">u(phresi/ai</foreign>mentioned in <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 52">Dem.
              Ex. 52</bibl>.</note> In these duties I shall be found, not only to have been the
          first to do my own part, but also to have urged the rest to do theirs. Reviewing these
          services one by one, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, consider
          how undeserved is the calamity that has now befallen me. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Since my present troubles are so abundant I am at a loss to know what I shall bemoan
          first. Will it be my advanced age,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">His age was sixty.
            Cicero was only a year older when he wrote his essay <bibl n="Cic. Sen.">Cic. <title>On
                Old Age.</title></bibl></note> at which, for the first time and contrary to my
          deserts, I am compelled to experience the hazards of a perilous exile? Or will it be the
          disgrace of having been convicted and ruined without any investigation or proof of guilt?
          Or will it be in disappointment of my hopes in place of which I have fallen heir to evils
          that rightfully belonged to others, <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>since neither
          because of my previous political record was I deserving punishment nor had the charges
          been proved upon which I was being tried. For I shall never be shown to have been one of
          the friends of Harpalus,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Harpalus was an absconding
            treasurer of Alexander who sought refuge in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>. Part of his illicit funds disappeared from the Acropolis, where
            they had been sequestered by the Athenians. Demosthenes was accused and convicted of
            accepting twenty talents. Few historians believe that he was guilty; some suggest that
            he may have spent part of the money in the cause of liberty.</note> and among the
          decrees that were passed concerning him only those proposed by me have afforded the State
          a clean record. From all these facts it is clear that I was caught in an unfortunate
          conjuncture, not taken in wrongdoing, and that through coming first on the list into court
          I unjustly fell foul of the public rage against all those involved in those charges.
            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Because, which of the just pleas that have saved those
          subsequently tried did not I myself advance? Or what proof did the Council allege against
          me? Or what proof could it now allege? There is none; for it is impossible to make facts
          out of what never happened. I refrain, however, from enlarging upon these topics, though
          there is plenty to write, for the consciousness of innocence has afforded me proof through
          experience that, while a feeble help in time of trouble, it is the most excruciating of
          all means of enhancing one’s suffering. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>So, since, quite
          rightly, you have become reconciled with all others involved in these charges, be
          reconciled with me also, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> for I
          have done no wrong against you, as I call upon the gods and heroes<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demigods or semi-divine ancestors of noble families.</note> to bear
          testimony. My witness is the whole extent of time that has gone by, which has a juster
          claim upon your credence than the unsupported charge which has now been brought against
          me; nor shall I be found to be the worst or the least trustworthy of those who have been
          falsely accused. <milestone n="2.17" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="17" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>And surely my departure from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> would not
          afford you just grounds for resentment against me, for it was not because I had renounced
          allegiance to you nor because I was looking to another quarter for comfort<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The suggestion is that another man might have offered his
            services to the Macedonians.</note> that I changed my residence to another country, but
          because, in the first place, I was pained at contemplating the disgrace of imprisonment,
          and in the second, on account of my age I was in no condition to endure the bodily
          discomforts. Besides, I did not think that you, either, were averse to my getting beyond
          the reach of revilement which, without benefiting you, was breaking me down. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>For, as indications that it was on you my thoughts were centered
          and on no others, you may note many items of evidence; for instance, I did not go to a
          city in which I was likely to play an outstanding role myself,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">He hints that he might have gone to some other city friendly to the
            Macedonians, where a welcome would have awaited him if he had renounced his allegiance
            to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> but to one where I knew
          our ancestors had gone when the Persian danger overtook them,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The Athenians abandoned the city before the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName> in <date value="-480">480</date> B.C.</note> and
          where I knew too there existed abundant goodwill toward yourselves. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>I refer to the city of <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>,
          to which it is my chief prayer that all the gods may be propitious, both because of its
          goodwill to you and because of its kindness to me, and my second prayer is that, having
          been delivered from this exile by you, I may be enabled to make repayment for kindnesses.
          In this city, when certain persons, thinking to make themselves agreeable to me, ventured
          to censure you for your arbitrary action in my regard, I preserved all reticence, as was
          my duty, which I believe was the chief reason for their being moved to admiration of me
          and honoring me in the name of the city. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Observing, however, that though the goodwill of the men there was strong, yet the power
          of the city was insufficient for the present need, I changed my residence and now have my
          quarters in the sanctuary of Poseidon in Calauria,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Calauria is situated south of <placeName key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName> in the
            Sardonic Gulf. Harpocration cites the letter under the name Calauria, an evidence of its
            authenticity.</note> not only for the sake of my personal safety, which through the
          protection of the god I hope is assured&mdash;because I am not quite certain; for the
          fact that it is in the power of unfriendly people to deal with matters as they choose
          renders frail and unpredictable the safety of a man in danger&mdash;but also because
          from here I look across the sea every day to my native land, toward which I am conscious
          in my heart of feeling an attachment as strong as I pray that I may enjoy on your part.
            <milestone n="2.21" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="21" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>In order, therefore, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that I
          may no longer be held in the grip of these present miseries, enact for me those measures
          you have already voted for the benefit of certain others, so that neither shall anything
          unworthy of you become my lot nor I be compelled to become the suppliant of rival powers;
          for that would not be an honorable thing for you either. Because, if the differences
          between you and me remain irreconcilable, it were better for me to be dead. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>With good reason you may have confidence that I entertain this
          thought and that I am not now indulging in idle bluff.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demosthenes terminated his second exile by taking poison rather than submit to capture
            by the soldiers of Antipater, <date value="-322">322</date> B.C. From this passage it
            seems that he had been prepared to do so the year before in the same Calauria.</note> I
          placed my fate in your hands, and I faced the trial in order that I might neither be a
          traitor to the truth nor place myself beyond the reach of any one of you, but that you
          might deal with me as you pleased; for I thought that those from whom I had received all
          my blessings ought to possess the privilege even of erring against me if they chose.
            <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>Since, however, a just Fortune&mdash;thanks be to
          her&mdash;prevailing over the unjust, has bestowed upon you the opportunity of
          deliberating twice on the same questions, no irremediable decree concerning my case having
          been passed, save me, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and vote
          a verdict worthy both of your own selves and of me. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>You
          will not find me to have done wrong on the score of any of my measures, or a fit person to
          be deprived of my civic rights or destroyed, but a man who is as much devoted to your
          democracy as the best patriots&mdash;not to say anything invidious<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">To claim that he was more loyal would be invidious.</note>&mdash;who
          of all men now living has accomplished most in your behalf and of all men of my time has
          available the most signal tokens of devotion to you. <milestone n="2.25" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="25" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Let not one of you think, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that
          through lack of manhood or from any other base motive I give way to my grief from the
          beginning to the end of this letter. Not so, but every man is ungrudgingly indulgent to
          the feelings of the moment, and those that now beset me&mdash;if only this had never
          come to pass&mdash;are sorrows and tears, longing both for my country and for you, and
          pondering over the wrongs I have suffered, all of which cause me to grieve. If you but
          scan this record fairly, in none of the political actions taken by me in your behalf will
          you find softness or lack of manhood attaching to me. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now thus far I am appealing to you all, but for those in particular who are attacking me
          in your presence I wish to say a word: so far as concerns all that they were doing in
          pursuance of the decrees passed by you in disregard of the truth, let it be allowed that
          these actions have been taken by them as your agents, and I lodge no complaint. Since,
          however, you have yourselves come to recognize these decrees for what they are, if they
          will yield in my case, just as they are allowing the prosecution to be dropped in the case
          of the other defendants, they shall have my thanks; but if they attempt to continue
          malicious, I appeal to you all to rally to my aid and not allow the enmity of these men to
          prevail. over the gratitude due to me from you. Farewell.</p>
			</div1>
			<milestone n="3" unit="card"/>
			<div1 type="Letter" n="3">
				<head>Concerning the Sons of Lycurgus</head>
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Eight citations of this letter by Hermogenes,
            Aristeides and others may be found in Walz’s <title>Rhetores Graeci</title>. It is also
            cited by Harpocration and by Antiatticista in Bekker’s <title>Anecdota</title>. It seems
            to have been known also to Photius and to the author of the <title>Etymologicum
              Magnum</title>. References to all of these will be found in the footnotes. In spite of
            these evidences of authenticity the majority of editors reject the letter. By Blass it
            is defended and of all six letters it certainly has the strongest case.</note>
          Demosthenes to the Council and the Assembly sends greeting.</p>
				<p>I sent you the previous letter about matters that concern myself, stating what steps I
          thought in justice ought to be taken by you; in regard to these you will take favorable
          action when it seems good to you. The message I now address to you I should not like you
          to overlook or to hear it in a spirit of contentiousness, but with due regard to the
          justness of it. For it happens that, although sojourning in an out-of-the-way place, I
          hear many people censuring you for your treatment of the sons of Lycurgus. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Now I should have sent you the letter merely out of regard for
          those services that Lycurgus performed during his lifetime, for which you would all, like
          myself, be in justice grateful if you would but do your duty. For Lycurgus, having taken a
          post in the financial department of the government<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Lycurgus managed the finances of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
            efficiently for twelve years &lpar;338-326&rpar;, for one legal term of four
            years as treasurer and for two terms through others. During this period the income of
            the State was doubled and a large building program was carried through. In politics
            Lycurgus was associated with Demosthenes. Though he ranked as one of the ten Attic
            orators, his style was rather forceful than polished. One speech, <title>Against
              Leocrates</title>, is extant and his Life in Ps. <bibl n="Plut. Dec. Orat. 1">Plut.
              Vit. 10 Orat.</bibl>, whose author seems to have made extensive use of the decree in
            his honor, <title>I.G.</title> 2. 456. Cf. also <title>I.G.</title> 2. 333, <dateRange from="1493" to="1496">1493</dateRange>-1496.</note> at the outset of his career and
          not being at all accustomed to draft documents pertaining to the general affairs of the
          Greeks and their relations with their allies, only when the majority of those who
          pretended to be the friends of democracy were deserting you, began to devote himself to
          the principles of the popular party, <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>not because from
          this quarter opportunity was offering to secure gifts and emoluments, since all such
          prizes were coming from the opposite party,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The
            Macedonians.</note> nor yet because he observed this policy to be the safer one, since
          there were many manifest dangers which a man was bound to incur who chose to speak on
          behalf of the people, but because he was truly democratic and by nature an honest man.
            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>And yet before his very eyes he observed those who
          might have assisted the cause of the people growing weak with the drift of events and
          their adversaries gaining strength in every way. None the less for all that, this brave
          man continued to adhere to such measures as he thought were in the people’s interest and
          subsequently he continued to perform his duty unfalteringly in word and deed, as was clear
          to see. As a consequence his surrender was straightway demanded,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The surrender of Lycurgus, along with that of Demosthenes and others, was
            demanded after the fall of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> in <date value="-335">335</date> B.C. Alexander was persuaded by the Athenian orator Demades to
            relent.</note> as all men are aware. <milestone n="3.5" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="5" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now I would have written this letter, as I said at the outset, for the sake of Lycurgus
          alone, but over and above that, believing it to be to your interest to know the criticisms
          being circulated among those who go abroad, I became all the more eager to dispatch the
          letter. I beg of those who for private reasons were at odds with Lycurgus to endure to
          hear what in truth and justice may be said in his behalf; for be well assured, men of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that, as things now are, the city is
          acquiring an evil reputation because of the way his sons have been treated. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>For none of the Greeks is ignorant that during the lifetime of
          Lycurgus you honored him extraordinarily,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">In addition to
            offices of trust Lycurgus several times received the honor of a crown and of statues at
            the public expense.</note> and, though many charges were brought against him by those
          who were envious of him, you never found a single charge to be true, and you so trusted
          him and believed him to be truly democratic beyond all others that you decided many points
          of justice on the ground that &ldquo;Lycurgus said so,&rdquo; and that sufficed
          for you. This would certainly not have happened unless it had seemed to you that he was so
          honest. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Today, therefore, all men, upon hearing that his
          sons are in prison, while pitying the dead man, sympathize with the children as innocent
          sufferers, and reproach you bitterly after a manner that I, for one, should not dare to
          write down for, touching the reports which make me vexed at those who utter them, and
          which I contradict as best I can, trying to come to your defence, I have written these
          only to the extent of making it clear to you that many people are blaming you, since I
          believe it to be to your interest to know this, though to quote their words verbatim I
          judge would be offensive. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Apart from mere abuse, however,
          I shall reveal all that certain people say and which I believe it to your advantage to
          have heard. For, after all, no one has supposed that you laboured under a misunderstanding
          and deception concerning the truth so far as Lycurgus himself is concerned, for the length
          of time during which, where subject to scrutiny,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">There
            was a board of thirty men at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> who
            acted as accountants and auditors. Ten of the thirty were called <foreign lang="greek">eu)/qunoi</foreign>; any official who handled public money could be charges before
            them with bribery or misappropriation of funds. All accounts were subject to their
            inspection. Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 48.3">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 48.3-4</bibl>;
              <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 53.2">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 53.2</bibl>.</note> he never was
          found guilty of any wrong toward you in either thought or deed and the fact that no human
          being could ever have accused you of indifference to any other action of his naturally
          eliminate the pretext of ignorance. <milestone n="3.9" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="9" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>So the explanation is left&mdash;what all would declare the conduct of vile
          men&mdash;that so long as you have use for each official you seem to be concerned for
          him but after that feel no obligation; for where else is one to expect that the gratitude
          due from you to the dead will be shown, when he observes the opposite treatment meted out
          to his children and his good name, which are the sole concerns of all men when facing
          death, that it may continue to be well with them? <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>And
          assuredly, to appear to do these things for the sake of money is also unworthy of truly
          honorable men, for it would be clearly inconsistent either with your magnanimity or with
          your general principles of conduct. For instance, if it were necessary to ransom the
          children from foreign captors by giving this sum out of the revenues, I believe you would
          all be eager to do it; but when I observe you reluctant to remit a fine which was imposed
          because of mere talk and envy, I do not know what judgement I can pass unless it be that
          you have launched upon a course of utterly bitter and truculent hostility toward the
          members of the popular party. If this be the case, you have made up your minds to
          deliberate neither righteously nor in the public interest. <milestone n="3.11" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="11" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>I am amazed if none of you thinks that it is a disgraceful thing for the people of
          Athens, who are supposed to be superior to all men in understanding and culture and have
          also maintained here for the unfortunate a common refuge in all ages, to show themselves
          less considerate than Philip, who, although naturally subject to no correction, <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>nursed as he was, in licence, still thought that at the moment of
          his greatest good fortune<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, <date value="-338">338</date> B.C.; the
            Greeks magnified its importance. Their liberty was lost by degrees, not suddenly.</note>
          he ought to be seen acting with the greatest humanity and did not venture to cast into
          chains the men who had faced him in the battle line, against whom he had staked his all,
          nor demand to know, &ldquo;Whose sons are they and what are their
            names?&rdquo;<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">An Athenian citizen was identified
            by three items: his own name, his father’s name, and his deme.</note> For unlike some of
          your orators, as it appears, he did not consider it would be either just or creditable to
          take the same action against all, but, taking into his reckoning the additional factor of
          station in life,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Antiatticista cites this passage under
              <foreign lang="greek">a)ci/a: a)nti\ tou= a)ci/wma</foreign> Bekker, 1. p. 77. 17-18.
              <foreign lang="greek">*)aci/a</foreign> equals Latin dignitas, the degree of
            distinction possessed by virtue of birth or achievement or both.</note> he assorted his
          verdicts accordingly. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>You, however, though Athenians and
          partners in a culture which is thought capable of making even stupid people tolerable, in
          the first place&mdash;and of all your actions this is the most
          heartless&mdash;hold the sons in chains as a penalty for offences which certain
          parties allege against the father<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The precise accusation
            is not known; it seems to have been concerned with the administration of the
            treasury.</note>; in the next place, you claim this action to be equality before the
          law, just as if you were inspecting equality in the field of weights or measures and not
          deliberating about men’s ethical and political principles. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>In testing these, if the actions of Lycurgus seem honest and
          public-spirited and inspired by loyalty, then it is justice that his sons should not only
          meet with no harm at your hands, but with all the benefits imaginable; yet if his actions
          seem quite the opposite, he ought to have been punished while he lived, and these children
          should not thus incur your anger on the ground of charges someone prefers against the
          father, because for all men death is an end of responsibility for all their offences.
            <milestone n="15" unit="section"/>Consequently, if you are going to be so minded that
          those who have conceived some grudge against those who espouse the cause of the people
          will not be reconciled even with dead men, but will persist in maintaining their enmity
          against the children, and if the people, in whose cause every friend of democracy labours,
          shall remember their gratitude only so long as they can use a man in the flesh and
          thereafter shall feel no concern, then nothing will be more miserable than to choose the
          post of champion of the people. <milestone n="3.16" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="16" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>If Moerocles<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Moerocles was archon in <date value="-324">324</date> B.C. His surrender had been demanded by Alexander in <date value="-335">335</date> B.C., which indicates his importance.</note> replies that this view is too
          subtle for his understanding, and that, to prevent them from running away, he put them in
          chains upon his own responsibility, demand of him why in the world he did not see the
          justice of this proceeding when Taureas, Pataecus, Aristogeiton and himself,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Nothing specific is known about these imprisonments, but it
            need not be assumed that all four men were under sentence at a single time. See next
            note. Taureas and Pataecus are unknown. For Aristogeiton see the two speeches against
            him.</note> though they had been committed to prison, were not only not in chains but
          would even address the Assembly. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>If, on the other hand,
          he shall say that he was not then archon, he had no right to speak, at any rate according
          to the laws.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">If Moerocles ordered the two sons of
            Lycurgus to be imprisoned but left Taureas, Pataecus and Aristogeiton at liberty, the
            charge against him is criminal partiality. If he denies that he was archon at the time
            and so lacked the authority to order these men to be detained in prison, then the minor
            charge still stands against him of addressing the Assembly while technically a prisoner
            himself. As a prisoner he would be subject to partial <foreign lang="greek">a)timi/a</foreign> or diminution of his rights as a citizen.</note> Accordingly, how
          can it be equal justice when some men are in office who have no right even to speak and
          others are in fetters whose father was useful to you in numerous ways? <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>I certainly cannot figure it out unless you mean to demonstrate this
          fact officially&mdash;that blackguardism, shamelessness and deliberate villainy are
          strong in the State and enjoy a better prospect of coming off safely, and that, if such
          men happen to get into a tight place, a way out is discovered, but to elect to live in
          honesty of principle, sobriety of life and devotion to the people will be hazardous and,
          if some false step is made, the consequences will be inescapable. <milestone n="3.19" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="19" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Furthermore, the fact that it is unjust to entertain concerning Lycurgus the opposite
          opinion to the one you held while he lived, and that justice demands that you should have
          more regard for the dead than for the living, and all such considerations I shall pass
          over, for I assume them to be universally agreed upon. Of the children of others, however,
          whom you recompensed for their fathers’ good services I would gladly see you reminded; for
          instance, the descendants of Aristeides, Thrasybulus, Archinus and many others.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">At times the Athenian Assembly bestowed extravagant gifts
            upon the children of famous men, as may be learned from <bibl n="Plut. Arist. 27">Plut.
              Arist. 27</bibl>. At other times it acted heartlessly, if we may believe <bibl n="Dem. 19.280">Dem. 19.280</bibl> ff. Archinus was one of the restorers of democracy
            in <date value="-403">403</date> B.C., but the greater share of the credit went to
            Thrasybulus.</note> Not by way of censure have I cited these examples, <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>for so far am I from censuring as to declare it my belief that such
          repayments are in the highest degree in the interest of the State, because you challenge
          all men by such conduct to be champions of the people, when they observe that, even if
          during their own lives envy shall stand in the way of their receiving merited honors, yet
          their children, at any rate, will be sure to receive their due rewards at your hands.
            <milestone n="3.21" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="21" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Is it not absurd, therefore, or rather even disgraceful, toward certain other men to keep
          alive the goodwill justly due them, in spite of the fact that the times of their
          usefulness are long past and after this interval you learn of their good deeds by hearsay
          and have not assumed them from things of which you have been eye-witnesses, but toward
          Lycurgus, whose political career and death are so recent, <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>you do not show yourselves so ready to display even pity and kindness as you were at all
          other times toward men whom you never knew and by whom you used to be wronged, and, worse
          still, your vengeance is visited upon his children, whom even an enemy, if only he were
          fair-minded and capable of reason, would pity? <milestone n="3.23" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="23" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Moreover, I am amazed if any one of you is ignorant of this fact also, that it is not to
          the interest of our political life, either, for this to become public knowledge, that
          those who have established friendship in a certain other quarter<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">That is, with the Macedonian court.</note> are sure to prosper in all
          things and fare better and, if some mishap occurs, the ways of escape are easier, but
          those who have attached themselves to the cause of the people will not only fare worse in
          other respects but for them alone of all men calamities will remain irremediable. Yet it
          is easy to demonstrate the truth of this, <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>for who of you
          does not know the incident of Laches<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Laches is known
            from an inscription as a syndic of the deme Aexon&ecirc; &lpar;I.G. 2. <date value="1197">1197</date>, p. 560, 13 f.&rpar;.</note> the son of Melanopus, whose
          lot it was to be convicted in a court of law precisely as the sons of Lycurgus in the
          present instance, but his entire fine was remitted when Alexander requested it by letter?
          And again, that it happened to Mnesibulus<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Mnesibulus is
            not otherwise known.</note> of Acharnae to be similarly convicted, the court condemning
          him just as it has the sons of Lycurgus, and to have the fine remitted, and rightly too,
          for the man was deserving? <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>And none of those who are now
          making such an outcry declared that by these actions the laws were being nullified. Quite
          rightly so, for they were not being nullified, if it be true that all our laws are enacted
          for the sake of just men and for the preservation of honest men, and that it is expedient
          neither to render the calamities of the unfortunate perpetual nor for men to show
          themselves void of gratitude. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>And furthermore, if it is
          expedient for these principles to hold true, as we would declare, not only were you not
          nullifying the laws where you released those men, but you were preserving the lifework of
          those men who enacted the laws, first, by releasing Laches in compliance with the request
          of Alexander and, secondly, by restoring Mnesibulus to his rights because of the sobriety
          of his life. <milestone n="3.27" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="27" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Beware of demonstrating, therefore, that to acquire some outside friendship<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Of the Macedonians.</note> is more profitable than to give
          one’s self in trust to the people and that it is better to remain in the ranks of the
          unknown than to become known as a man who in public life consults the interests of you,
          the majority. For although it is impossible for one who recommends policies and
          administers the commonwealth to please everyone, yet if a man, actuated by loyalty, has at
          heart the same interests as the people, he has a right to security of person. Otherwise
          you will teach everyone to serve the interests of others rather than those of the people
          and to shun recognition for doing any of those things that are to your advantage.
            <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>In short, it is a reproach common to all citizens, men
          of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and a misfortune of the State as a
          whole, that envy should be thought to be stronger among you than the grace of gratitude
          for services performed, and the more so because envy is a disease but the Graces<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">A verbal play on <foreign lang="greek">xa/rites</foreign>,
            &ldquo;feelings of gratitude&rdquo; or &ldquo;Graces.&rdquo;</note> have
          been assigned a place among the gods. <milestone n="3.29" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="29" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Furthermore, I am not going to omit the case of Pytheas<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Pytheas was a presumptuous politician of no formal education; he accused Demosthenes of
            receiving twenty talents from Harpalus; after Alexander’s death he joined Antipater
            during the siege of <placeName key="perseus,Lamia">Lamia</placeName>, <date value="-322">322</date> B.C.</note> either, who was a friend of the people down to his entrance
          into public life but after that was ready to do anything to injure you. For who does not
          know that this man, when, under the obligation to serve you, he was entering upon public
          life, was being hounded as a slave and was under indictment as an alien usurping the
          rights of a citizen and came near being sold by these men whose servant he now is and for
          whom he used to write the speeches against me, <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>but since
          he is himself now practising what he then accused others of doing, is in such easy
          circumstances as to keep two mistresses, who have escorted him&mdash;and kind it is of
          them&mdash;on the way to death by consumption,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The
            Greek word <foreign lang="greek">fqo/h</foreign> was peculiar enough to prick the
            interest of Harpocration, who cites this passage.</note> and to be able to discharge a
          debt of five talents more easily than he could have produced five drachmas previously, and
          besides all this, with the permission of you, the people, not only participates in the
          government, which is a common reproach to all, but also performs on your behalf the
            ancestral<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The point is that Pytheas himself lacked
            ancestors of note.</note> sacrifices at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>? <milestone n="3.31" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="31" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>So, when it is possible for all to behold object-lessons of such a kind and on such a
          scale, from which everyone would conclude that it does not pay to espouse the cause of the
          people, I begin to fear that some day you may become destitute of men who will speak on
          your behalf, especially when of the friends of the people some are being taken away by
          man’s natural destiny,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">That is, death by disease.</note>
          by accident, and by the lapse of time, such as Nausicles, Chares, Diotimus, Menestheus,
          and Eudoxus,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Nausicles and Diotimus are mentioned in the
              <bibl n="Dem. 18.114">Dem. 18.114</bibl>; both are known from inscriptions to have
            held important commands. The surrender of Diotimus was demanded by Alexander in <date value="-335">335</date> B.C. Chares held important commands between 367 and <date value="-335">335</date> B.C. Menestheus was given command of one hundred galleys in
              <date value="-335">335</date> B.C., 17. 20. Eudoxus seems to be otherwise
            unknown.</note> and also Euthydicus, Ephialtes and Lycurgus,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt"><bibl n="Din. 1.33">Din. 1.33</bibl> names Euthydicus as one whom
            Demosthenes claimed as a friend. Ephialtes was one of the ten whose surrender was
            demanded by Alexander in <date value="-335">335</date> B.C. He died in 334 while
            fighting on the side of the Persians against the Macedonians. For Lycurgus see above
            sect. 2 note.</note> and others you citizens have cast forth, such as Charidemus,
            Philocles<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">For Charidemus, leader of mercenaries, see
              <bibl n="Dem. 23">Dem. 23</bibl>, Introduction. There is extant a speech of Deinarchus
              <title>Against Philocles</title> &lpar;<bibl n="Din. 3.1">Din.
            Phil.</bibl>&rpar;. The latter was associated with Demosthenes in admitting Harpalus
            to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> with his illicit treasure. His
            exile was brief.</note> and myself, <milestone n="32" unit="section"/>men to whom not
          even you yourselves believe others to be superior in loyalty, though if you think certain
          others are equally loyal I feel no jealousy,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This is one
            of several similar colloquialisms signifying &ldquo;I don’t mind.&rdquo;</note>
          and it would be my desire, provided only that you will deal fairly with them and that they
          shall not meet with the treatment accorded us, that their number may be legion. When
          however, you give the public such object-lessons as the present, who is there who will be
          willing to give himself to this line of duty with sincere intentions toward you?
            <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>Yet surely you will find no dearth of those who will
          at least pretend to do so, for in the past there has been none. Heaven forbid that I
          should live to see them unmasked like those men, who, though now openly pursuing policies
          they then repudiated, feel before none of you either fear or shame! You should ponder
          these facts, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and not treat
          loyal men with disdain nor be persuaded by those who are leading the country on the way to
          bitter hatreds and cruelty. <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>For our present difficulties
          require goodwill and humanity far more than dissension and malice, an excess of which
          certain persons turn to their advantage, pursuing their business<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Antiatticista cites this passage under <foreign lang="greek">e)rgola/bos</foreign> Bekker’s <title>Anecdota</title> 1. p. 94. 3-4.</note> to your
          detriment with the expectation of returns, of which I pray that their calculations may
          cheat them. If any one of you ridicules these warnings he must be filled with a profound
          simplicity. For if, observing that things have happened which no one could have expected,
          he imagines things could not happen now which have happened already before now, when the
          people were set at variance with those who spoke in their behalf by men suborned for the
          purpose, has he not taken leave of his senses? <milestone n="3.35" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="35" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>If I were present in person I should be trying to explain these matters to you by word of
          mouth, but since I am in such a plight as I pray may be the lot of anyone who has uttered
          falsehoods against me to my ruin, I have sent my message in the form of a letter, in the
          first place, having supreme regard for your honor and your advantage and, in the second,
          because the same goodwill that I felt toward Lycurgus during his lifetime I believe it
          right to show that I feel also toward his sons. <milestone n="36" unit="section"/>If it
          has occurred to anyone that I have a great abundance<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">In
            this passage there is a running play of words based upon the common expression <foreign lang="greek">e)k th=s periousi/as</foreign>, &ldquo;out of one’s
            abundance.&rdquo; Note <foreign lang="greek">peri/esti . . . e)k tou= perio/ntos . .
              . peri/esti . . . perige/noito</foreign></note> of troubles of my own, I should not
          hesitate to say to him that I am as much concerned to defend your interests and to forsake
          none of my friends as I am about my own deliverance. Therefore, it is not out of the
          abundance of my troubles that I do this, but, actuated by one and the same earnestness and
          conviction, I devote my efforts to furthering both these interests of mine and those of
          yours with a single purpose, and the abundance I possess is of such a kind as I pray may
          abound for those who plot any evil against you. And on these topics I have said enough.
            <milestone n="3.37" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="37" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>This complaint, inspired by goodwill and affection, though now in outline only, I would
          gladly enlarge upon a little later in a long letter, which, if only I am alive, you may
          expect, unless justice shall be done me by you before that time, you who, O&mdash;what
          shall I say so as to seem neither to offend nor to fall short of the truth ?&mdash;you
          all too unfeeling men, who neither before the rest of the world nor before yourselves feel
          shame, who upon the same charges upon which you acquitted Aristogeiton have banished
          Demosthenes, <milestone n="38" unit="section"/>and the privileges which those who dare to
          set your authority at naught are permitted to have without your leave you do not grant to
          me, to enable me, if I can, by calling in the sums owing me and levying contributions<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Harpocration cites this passage under the verb <foreign lang="greek">e)rani/zw</foreign>. Photius and the <title>Etymologicum Magnum</title>
            cite the verb only.</note> upon my friends, to adjust my obligations to you and not,
          with old age and exile as the guerdon of my past toils in your behalf, be seen wandering
          from place to place on alien soil, a common reproach to all who have wronged me.
            <milestone n="3.39" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="39" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Although it was my wish that my return home might come about by way of an ordinance<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 18.13 ">Dem. 18.13 </bibl>
            <foreign lang="greek">e)n e)phrei/as ta/cei kai\ fqo/nou</foreign>, &ldquo;by way of
            spite and jealousy.&rdquo; For the meaning cf. sect. 41 of this letter.</note> of
          gratitude and magnanimity on your part and that for myself I might secure a dismissal of
          the false charges unjustly lodged against me, asking only for immunity from imprisonment
          for such time as you have granted for the payment of the fine, yet these requests you do
          not grant and you demand, as it is reported to me, &ldquo;Well, who is preventing him
          from being here and transacting this business?&rdquo; <milestone n="40" unit="section"/>It is knowing how to feel shame, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, it is faring in a way unworthy of my public services in your
          behalf, and it is the loss of my property through those men on whose account I was
          persuaded in the first place to become surety for their payments in order that they might
          not have to pay double the sum of which they were unable to pay the original amount.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">It was the law at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> that the amount of a debt owed to the State should be doubled if
            not paid when due. Demosthenes had made a bad loan, which rendered it impossible to pay
            his fine of fifty talents.</note> From these men, could I but return with your goodwill,
          I might possibly recover part, even if not all, so as not to live sordidly the rest of my
          life, but if I come on such terms as those who talk in this way demand of me, I shall be
          the victim at one and the same time of ignominy, destitution and fear. <milestone n="3.41" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="41" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>None of these considerations do you take into account but, grudging me the paltry words
          of a decree and an act of kindness,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">See <bibl n="Dem. L. 3.39">Dem. L. 3.39</bibl> &ldquo;by way of an ordinance of gratitude
            and magnanimity on your part.&rdquo;</note> you will allow me to perish, if it so
          happen, through your inaction, for I could appeal to no others but you. In that day you
          will say that I have been shamefully mistreated, I know for a certainty, when it will do
          neither you nor myself any good, for assuredly you do not expect that I have funds apart
          from my real and personal property, from which I am separated; the rest of my assets I
          wish to assemble if in a spirit of humanity instead of spitefulness you will but give me
          leave to attend to this business unmolested.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demosthenes
            was condemned to be held in prison until his fine should be paid; he insists that he
            must enjoy liberty if he is to collect the funds necessary for payment.</note>
          <milestone n="42" unit="section"/>Neither will you ever show that I received money from
          Harpalus, for neither was I tried and proved guilty nor did I take money, and if you are
          looking for excuse to the notorious decision of the Council or to the Areopagus,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">According to <bibl n="Plut. Dem. 26">Plut. Dem. 26</bibl>,
            the orator himself moved that the charges should be referred to the Areopagus, which
            promptly condemned him.</note> recall to mind the trial of Aristogeiton<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Aristogeiton was acquitted, according to Demosthenes, upon
            the same evidence. See <bibl n="Dem. L. 3.37">Dem. L. 3.37</bibl>.</note> and hide your
          heads in shame<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Eight references to this passage may be
            found in Walz’s <title>Rhetores Graeci</title>, which has an index.</note>; because I
          have no milder injunction for those who have committed this offence against me. <milestone n="43" unit="section"/>For surely you will not claim it was just, after information was
          laid in the very same words by the same Council, for that man to be exonerated and me to
          be ruined; you are not so void of reason. For I do not deserve it; I am not that kind of a
          person nor worse than he, though I am unfortunate, thanks to you, I admit, for why not
          unfortunate when on top of my other calamities I must compare myself with Aristogeiton,
          and to make matters worse, a ruined man with one who has secured acquittal? <milestone n="3.44" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="44" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>And do not assume from these words that it is anger that moves me, because I could not
          feel that way toward you. To those who are wronged, however, it brings a certain relief to
          tell their sorrows, just as it relieves those in pain to moan, because toward you I feel
          as much goodwill as I would pray you might have toward me. I have made this plain in
          everything and shall continue to do so, <milestone n="45" unit="section"/>for I have been
          resolved from the beginning that it is the duty of every man in public life, if only he be
          a fair-minded citizen, so to feel toward all his fellow-citizens as children ought to feel
          toward their parents, and, while praying that he may find them perfectly reasonable, yet
          to bear with them in a spirit of kindliness as they are<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This advice for children was possibly a commonplace. It is voiced by <bibl>Epicurus,
                <title>Vatican Collection</title> 62</bibl>.</note>; because defeat under such
          circumstances is judged among right-minded men to be an honorable and befitting victory.
          Farewell.</p>
			</div1>
			<milestone n="4" unit="card"/>
			<div1 type="Letter" n="4">
				<head>On the Slanderous Attacks of Theramenes</head>
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This letter is not cited in ancient authorities and
            there is less likelihood of its being genuine</note> Demosthenes to the Council and the
          Assembly sends greeting.</p>
				<p>I hear that Theramenes<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">There is no known connection
            between this obscure man and the Theramenes who played a conspicuous role during the
            latter years of the Peloponnesian War.</note> has uttered various slanderous statements
          concerning me and in particular that he taunts me with being ill-fated.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The implication is that Demosthenes was an unlucky person
            who brought bad luck to the State. Deinarchus in his speech <title>Against
              Demosthenes</title> 31-33 &lpar;<bibl n="Din. 1.31">Din. 1.31-33</bibl>&rpar;
            asserts that he also involved his collaborators in his own ill luck. It may he noted
            that <bibl n="Cic. pro Man. 10.28">Cicero, <title>For the Manilian Law</title> 10.
              28</bibl>, places <foreign lang="la">felicitas</foreign> on a par with <foreign lang="la">scientia rei militaris</foreign>, <foreign lang="la">virtus</foreign>, and
              <foreign lang="la">auctoritas</foreign>.</note> Now I am not astonished that this man
          should be ignorant that abusive language, which demonstrates no vice on the part of the
          one against whom it is spoken, carries no weight with fair-minded people. For if one who
          in his way of life is insolent, by birth is not a citizen, and was reared from childhood
          in a brothel, had even a faint perception in such matters, it would be more unintelligible
          than complete ignorance. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>As for this man, If some day I
          return and am restored to my rights, I shall plan to have a talk with him about the
          drunken abuse he directs at me and at you, and I believe that, even if he is devoid of
          shame, I shall render him more self-restrained. To you, however, in the interest of the
          common good, I wish to make known by letter what statements I have to make about these
          matters. Listen to my words with all attention, for I think they are not only worth
          hearing but also worth remembering. <milestone n="4.3" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>As for me, I assume that your city is the most fortunate in the world and the dearest to
          the gods, and I know that Zeus of <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> and
            Dione<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">At the shrine of Zeus at <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName> it was Dione, and not Hera, who was considered his consort.
            Elsewhere Dione was identified with Aphrodite or Venus.</note> and the Pythian Apollo
          are always saying this in their oracles and confirming with the seal of their approval the
          opinion that good fortune has her abode in the city among you. Moreover, all that the gods
          reveal about coming events it is obvious that they prophesy; but the epithets based upon
          past events they apply to experiences of the past. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Now,
          what I have done as a public man among you belongs in the class of events already past, on
          the ground of which the gods have bestowed upon you the epithet fortunate. How, then, is
          it fair for those who followed advice to be denominated fortunate but the adviser to
          receive the opposite epithet? Unless someone should give this explanation, that for the
          common good fortune, of which I was the counsellor, it is the gods who vouch, and to think
          they lie would be sacrilege, but that the personal slander, which Theramenes has directed
          against me, it is an insolent, shameless and not even intelligent person who has uttered.
            <milestone n="4.5" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="5" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now, it is not only by the words of the oracles coming from the gods that you will find
          the fortune you have enjoyed to be good but also by viewing it in the light of the facts
          themselves, if you will scan them rightly. For if as human beings you are willing to
          regard our affairs, you will find that our city, as a result of the policy I advised, has
          been very fortunate, but if you shall demand to receive those blessings which are reserved
          for the gods alone, you aim at the impossible. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>What,
          then, is reserved for gods but for men is impossible? To be in absolute control of all the
          blessings there are, both to possess them themselves and to bestow them upon others, and
          never in all eternity either to suffer anything bad or to look forward to suffering it.
          Next, these propositions having been laid down, as is proper, scan your blessings in
          comparison with those of the rest of mankind. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>No one, for
          instance, is so foolish as to assert that what has befallen either the Spartans, whom I
          never advised, or the Persians, whom I never even visited, is preferable to your present
          lot. I pass over the Cappadocians, the Syrians, and the beings who inhabit the land of
            <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> toward the ends of the earth, all of whom
          have had the misfortune to suffer many terrible and grievous afflictions. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>O yes, by Zeus, all will agree that you are faring better than these,
          but worse, they declare, than the Thessalians, Argives and Arcadians, or certain others,
          who had the luck to be in alliance with Philip. But you have come off far better than
          these, not only because you have not been reduced to slavery&mdash;and yet what
          blessing equals that?&mdash;but also because, while all those are thought to be
          responsible for the evils that have befallen the Greeks through Philip and their
          enslavement, in consequence of which they are hated with good reason, <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>you are seen to have struggled in defence of the Greeks at the expense
          of your lives, your property, your city, your territory and all you possess, in return for
          which you are entitled to glory and undying gratitude from all lovers of justice.
          Therefore, as a result of the counsels I gave, it has been the city’s good fortune to fare
          best of all the states that resisted Philip and there is the added gain of standing in
          higher repute than those who co-operated with him. <milestone n="4.10" unit="card"/>
          <milestone n="10" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>On these grounds, therefore, the gods, while giving favorable oracles to you, are turning
          back the unjust slander upon the head of him who utters it, and any man would recognize
          the facts if he chose to examine the practices in which he spends his life. For instance,
          he does by preference the very things that one might invoke upon him as a curse.
            <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>He is an enemy to his own parents but a friend to
          Pausanias the whoremonger, and though he swaggers like a man he allows himself to be used
          like a woman. He lords it over his own father but submits to degenerates. He regales his
          fancy with things by which all are disgusted, with foul language and with stories by which
          his hearers are pained; yet he never ceases to talk, as if he were a simple fellow and the
          soul of frankness.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Blass, who is inclined to reject this
            letter, calls attention to the Gorgianic antitheses in the preceding passage.</note>
          <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>I would not have written this had I not wished to stir
          in you the recollection of the vices that attach to him. For many terrible and shameful
          things, which a man would shrink from telling and would guard against mentioning in
          writing and, as I think, would be disgusted to hear of, each one of you, reminded by these
          words, knows to attach to this man, so that nothing indecent has been uttered by me and
          this man upon sight is a reminder to all of his own vices. Farewell.</p>
			</div1>
			<milestone n="5" unit="card"/>
			<div1 type="Letter" n="5">
				<head>To Heracleodorus</head>
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Schaefer judges the evidence against the genuineness
            of these last two letters to be decisive. If this one be genuine, it must be assumed
            that Heracleodorus is a citizen of some neighboring city, such as <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, because Demosthenes would have no need to
            write to a fellow-citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note>
          Demosthenes sends his good wishes to Heracleodorus.</p>
				<p>I am at a loss to know whether I ought to believe or disbelieve the news that Menecrates
          brings me. For he said that information had been laid against Epitimus, that Aratus<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The persons here named are citizens of some neighboring
            city and otherwise unknown.</note> had taken him to prison and that you were supporting
          the prosecution and were the most uncompromising of all toward him. I do beseech you in
          the name of Zeus the god of friendship and by all the gods not to get me involved in any
          disagreeable and embarrassing predicament. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For be well
          assured that, apart from my concern for the safety of Epitimus and my belief that it will
          be a great misfortune if anything should happen to him and you should be partly
          responsible for it, I am ashamed to face people who are familiar with the reports I have
          been making to everybody concerning yourself. I was convinced that I spoke the truth, not
          because I possessed confirmation from having associated with you, <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>but because I observed that, while gaining some renown, you were also
          glad to have an education, and that too in the school of Plato, the one that really has
          nothing to do with getting the better of people and the quackeries<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The reference is to the sophists, professional teachers who undertook to
            prepare their pupils for worldly success.</note> that concern themselves with this, but
          has been demonstrated to aim at the highest excellence and perfect justice in all things.
          By the gods I swear that it is impious for a man who has shared in this instruction not to
          be free from all deception and honest in all dealings. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>It
          would also be to me one of the most grievous disappointments if, after having started out
          to feel friendly toward you, I should be compelled to take the opposite decision instead,
          and if I assume that I have been slighted and deceived, even if I shall deny it, believe
          me, it will be so. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>If you have looked down upon us
          because we are not yet among the foremost men,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">If the
            letter is genuine, this evidence of date would point approximately to <date value="-355">355</date> B.C. The <title>First Philippic</title> was delivered in 351.</note>
          reflect that you too were once a young man of the same age as we are now, and that you
          have reached your present position through speech and action in public life. Such success
          may attend me also. For deliberative oratory I have mastered already<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Deinarchus in <bibl n="Din. 1.35">Din. 1.35</bibl> may be making a
            taunting reference to this boast.</note> and, with Fortune lending a hand, the practical
          experience also may follow. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now a fine tribute, a just return.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This looks like a
            proverbial expression. The reference is either to a favor conferred by Demosthenes and
            not mentioned here or to the good opinion he claims to have expressed.</note> Please
          make me this recompense. Neither allow yourself to be led by one of those whose judgement
          is inferior to your own nor submit to them, but try to bring those men around to your way
          of thinking, and so conduct yourself that we may not have to give up any of our judgements
          of you that were assumed to be true, but that for Epitimus some deliverance may be found
          and release from his perils. I too shall be on hand at whatever time you shall say is the
          fitting moment. Send me a written message or rather command me as a friend. Farewell.</p>
			</div1>
			<milestone n="6" unit="card"/>
			<div1 type="Letter" n="6">
				<head>To the Council and the Assembly of the Athenians</head>
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Schaefer thinks this letter to be the work of a scribe
            in the council of the Greek allies.</note> Demosthenes to the Council and the Assembly
          sends greeting.</p>
				<p>A letter has come from Antiphilus<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">From <bibl n="Plut. Phoc. 24">Plut. Phoc. 24</bibl> we learn that Antiphilus was commanding the
            army of the allies besieging Antipater in <placeName key="perseus,Lamia">Lamia</placeName>, winter of <dateRange from="-323" to="-322">323</dateRange>-322
            B.C.</note> to the councillors of the allies,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The
            council of the allies is thought to have been meeting at Phyl&ecirc; in northern
            Attica.</note> which, while satisfactorily phrased for those who wish to have good news
          in prospect, leaves many items unacceptable to those who toady to Antipater. These men,
          taking along with them the dispatch from Antipater that came to Corinth addressed to
            Deinarchus,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Deinarchus, youngest of the ten Attic
            orators, was opposed to Demosthenes and favored Macedon. His speech accusing Demosthenes
            of receiving twenty talents from Harpalus is extant. At the date of this letter he was
            in exile at Corinth, his birthplace.</note> have filled all the cities in the
          Peloponnesus with such reports as I pray that the gods may turn back upon their own heads.
            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>The man who now presents himself to you along with the
          bearer of this letter from me, having come from Polemaestus to the latter’s brother
            Epinicus,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">It may he assumed that Polemaestus was in
            the camp of the allies before Lamia and that his brother was attending the council of
            the allies in Phyl&ecirc;.</note> a man well disposed toward you and a friend of
          mine, was by him in turn brought to me. After I heard his story it seemed to me best to
          send him to you in order that, having heard a clear account of all that had happened in
          the camp from one who was present in the battle, you may be of good cheer for the present
          and assume that, the gods being willing, the final outcome will be as you wish.
          Farewell.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
