<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>On the Choreutes from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Antiphon</author>
        <editor role="translator">K. J. Maidment</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><idno type="OCLC">5331826</idno><idno type="ISBN">0674993403</idno></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=2">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=3">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=4">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.tetralogy">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Tetralogy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd
      </item></change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Checkmark
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/7/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed tetralogy names and div2s again, prior to importing
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>made some corrections to the SGML
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>also fixed quoted text which had no content, just the attribute.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>15 October 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: antiph_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-10-07 21:00:37  rsingh04
began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

Revision 1.6  2009/06/22 19:41:56  student
edited entity tags CEH

Revision 1.5  2008/11/21 21:38:13  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.4  2008/02/13 19:32:23  lcerrato
fixed incorrect bibl tags

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 21:10:04  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 15:48:40  packel
removed stray item tags

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:27:36  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:14:27  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2000/03/04 20:33:52  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.6  2000/01/28 23:23:50  dasmith
Made ID numbers be the tag content.

Revision 1.5  1999/10/15 23:08:23  dasmith
Make sure we get three sections at a time.

Revision 1.4  1999/10/15 21:20:01  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.


</item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="section">
        <p>True happiness for one who is but human, gentlemen, would mean a life in which his person
          is threatened by no peril: and well might that be the burden of our prayers. But well too
          might we pray that if we must perforce face danger, we may have at least the one
          consolation which is to my mind the greatest of blessings at such an hour, a clear
          conscience; so that if disaster should after all befall us, it will be due to no iniquity
          of ours and bring no shame; it will be the result of chance rather than of wrongdoing.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>It would be unanimously agreed, I think, that the laws which deal with cases such as the
          present are the most admirable and righteous of laws. Not only have they the distinction
          of being the oldest in this country, but they have changed no more than the crime with
          which they are concerned; and that is the surest token of good laws, as time and
          experience show mankind what is imperfect. Hence you must not use the speech for the
          prosecution to discover whether your laws are good or bad: you must use laws to discover
          whether or not the speech for the prosecution is giving you a correct and lawful
          interpretation of the case.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 5.14"
              >Antiph. 5.14</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>The person whom today's proceedings concern most of all is myself, because I am the
          defendant and in danger. Nevertheless, it is also, I think, of great importance to you who
          are my judges that you should reach a correct verdict in trials for murder, first and
          foremost because of the gods and your duty towards them, and secondly for your own sakes.
          A case of this kind can be tried only once<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Antiph. 5.87">Antiph. 5.87-89</bibl>.</note>; and if it is wrongly decided against
          the defendant, justice and the facts cannot prevail against that decision. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="section">
        <p>Once you condemn him, a defendant must perforce accept your verdict, even if he was not
          the murderer or concerned in the crime. The law banishes him from his city, its temples,
          its games, and its sacrifices, the greatest and the most ancient of human institutions;
          and he must acquiesce. So powerful is the compulsion of the law, that even if a man slays
          one who is his own chattel and who has none to avenge him, his fear of the ordinances of
          god and of man causes him to purify himself and withhold himself from those places
          prescribed by law, in the hope that by so doing he will best avoid disaster. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="section">
        <p>Most of the life of man rests upon hope; and by defying the gods and committing
          transgressions against them, he would rob himself even of hope, the greatest of human
          blessings. No one would venture either to disregard the sentence passed upon him because
          he was sure that he had had no part in the crime, or to disobey the law if he knew in his
          heart that he was guilty of such a deed. He has to submit to the verdict in defiance of
          the facts, or submit to the facts themselves, as the case may be, even if his victim has
          none to avenge him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" type="section">
        <p>The laws, the oaths, the sacrifices, the proclamations, in fact the whole of the
          proceedings in connection with trials for murder differ as profoundly as they do from the
          proceedings elsewhere simply because it is of supreme importance that the facts at issue,
          upon which so much turns, should themselves be rightly interpreted. Such a right
          interpretation means vengeance for him who has been wronged; whereas to find an innocent
          man guilty of murder is a mistake, and a sinful mistake, which offends both gods and laws.
          Nor is it as serious for the prosecutor to accuse the wrong person as it is for you judges
          to reach a wrong verdict. The charge brought by the prosecutor is not in itself effective;
          whether it becomes so, depends upon you, sitting in judgement. On the other hand, if you
          yourselves arrive at a wrong verdict, you cannot rid yourselves of the responsibility for
          so doing by blaming someone else for that verdict. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>My own attitude to my defence, gentlemen, is very different from that of my accusers to
          their prosecution. They, on their side, allege that their object in bringing this action
          is to discharge a sacred duty and to satisfy justice; whereas they have in fact treated
          their speech for the prosecution as nothing but an opportunity for malicious falsehood, and
          such behavior is the worst travesty of justice humanly possible. Their aim is not to
          expose any crime I may have committed in order to exact the penalty which it deserves, but
          to blacken me, even though I am entirely innocent, in order to have me punished with exile
          from this country. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" type="section">
        <p>I, on the other hand, consider that my first duty is to reply to the charge before the
          court by giving you a complete account of the facts. Afterwards, if you so desire, I shall
          be pleased to answer the remaining accusations made,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This
            promise is never directly fulfilled, but <bibl n="Antiph. 6.33">Antiph. 6.33</bibl> ff.
            deal with the general conduct of the prosecution.</note> as they will, I feel, turn to
          my own credit and advantage, and to the discomfiture of my opponents to whose impudence
          they are due. For it is indeed a strange fact, gentlemen: </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" type="section">
        <p>when they had the opportunity of avenging themselves on an enemy and doing the state a
          service by exposing and bringing home to me any public offence of which I had been guilty,
          as Choregus or otherwise, not one of them was able to prove that I had done your people
          any wrong, great or small.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This is presumably a reference
            to the speaker's <foreign xml:lang="greek">dokimasi/a</foreign> when elected a member of
            the <foreign xml:lang="greek">boulh/</foreign> in the preceding June. All magistrates
            had to submit to an inquiry into their general fitness to assume public office before
            they were installed.</note> Yet at today's trial, when they are prosecuting for
          prosecution to the charge before the court,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Antiph. 5.11">Antiph. 5.11</bibl>. There it is stated more explicitly that the
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">diwmosi/a</foreign> ensured against irrelevant
            charges.</note> they are seeking to achieve my downfall with a tissue of lies calculated
          to bring my public life into disrepute. If the state has in fact been wronged, they are
          compensating it not with redress, but with a mere accusation; while they are themselves
          demanding that reparation for a wrong which has been suffered by the state should be made
          to them in person. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" type="section">
        <p>Indeed, they deserve to win neither gratitude nor credence with these charges of theirs.
          The circumstances in which they are prosecuting are not such as to allow the state to
          obtain satisfaction if really wronged, and only so would they be entitled to its
          gratitude; while the prosecutor who refuses to confine himself to the charge before the
          court in an action such as the present does not so much deserve to be believed as to be
          disbelieved. I myself know well enough what your own feelings are; nothing save the facts
          immediately at issue would lead you either to condemn or to acquit, because only thus can
          the claims of heaven and of justice be satisfied. So with those facts I will begin. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>When I was appointed Choregus for the Thargelia,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">xorhgi/a</foreign> was one of the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >lhtourgi/ai</foreign>, or public duties, imposed upon the richer citizens by the
            state. A Choregus had to equip and train a chorus for one of the annual festivals, in
            this case the Thargelia, held in honor of Apollo and celebrated on the 7th of Thargelion
            (May 1st) by a competition between choirs of boys selected from the ten tribes, which
            were grouped in pairs for the purpose.</note> Pantacles<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Probably this is the Pantacles who appears as a lyric poet in a choregic inscription of
            the period ( I.G. i(2). 771). Aristophanes also refers jokingly to a Pantacles who got
            into difficulties with his helmet at the Panatheniac procession on one occasion (<bibl
              n="Aristoph. Frogs 1036">Aristoph. Frogs 1036</bibl>: first staged in 405); but it is
            not certain that he was the poet.</note> falling to me as poet and the Cecropid as the
          tribe that went with mine [;that is to say the Erechtheid];,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See critical note 6.</note> I discharged my office as efficiently and as
          scrupulously as I was able. I began by fitting out a training-room in the most suitable
          part of my house, the same that I had used when Choregus at the Dionysia.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e. the Great Dionysia (<foreign xml:lang="greek">ta\ e)n
              a)/stei *dionu/sia</foreign>), celebrated every March with a procession, choruses of
            boys, and tragic and comic performances. The speaker had undertaken the training of a
            chorus for the festival in some previous year.</note> Next, I recruited the best chorus
          that I could, without indicting a single fine, without extorting a single pledge,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Choregus was empowered to inflict fines upon parents who
            refused to allow their sons to perform without good reason. The “pledges” mentioned
            would presumably be exacted from parents who did proffer some excuse. If the excuse
            proved unsatisfactory, they would forfeit their money.</note> and without making a
          single enemy. Just as though nothing could have been more satisfactory or better suited to
          both parties, I on my side would make my demand or request, while the parents on theirs
          would send their sons along without demur, nay, readily. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>For a while after the arrival of the boys I had no time to look after them in person, as
          I happened to be engaged in suits against Aristion and Philinus,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For embezzelment of public monies. See <bibl n="Antiph. 6.35">Antiph.
              6.35</bibl>.</note> and was anxious to lose no time after the impeachment in
          sustaining my charges in a just and proper manner before the Council and the general
          public. Being thus occupied myself, I arranged that the needs of the chorus should be
          attended to by Phanostratus, a member of the same deme as my accusers here and a relative
          of my own (he is my son-in-law); and I told him to perform the task with all possible
          care. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" type="section">
        <p>Besides Phanostratus I appointed two others. The first, Ameinias, whom I thought a
          trustworthy man, belonged to the Erechtheid tribe and had been officially chosen by it to
          recruit and supervise its choruses at the various festivals; while the second, . . .,
          regularly recruited the choruses of the Cecropid tribe, to which he belonged, in the same
          way. There was yet a fourth, Philippus, whose duty it was to purchase or spend whatever
          the poet or any of the other three told him. Thus I ensured that the boys should receive
          every attention and lack nothing owing to my own preoccupation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" type="section">
        <p>Such were my arrangements as Choregus. If I am lying as regards any of them in order to
          exonerate myself, my accuser is at liberty to refute me on any point he likes in his
          second speech. For this is how it is, gentlemen: many of the spectators here present are
          perfectly familiar with every one of these facts, the voice of the officer who
          administered the oath is in their ears, and they are giving my defence their close
          attention; I would like them to feel that I am respecting that oath, and that if I
          persuade you to acquit me, it was by telling the truth that I did so. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>In the first place, then, I will prove to you that I did not tell the boy to drink the
          poison, compel him to drink it, give it to him to drink, or even witness him drinking it.
          And I am not insisting on these facts in order to incriminate someone else once I have
          cleared myself; no indeed—unless that someone else be Fortune; and this is not the first
          time, I imagine, that she has caused a man's death. Fortune neither I nor any other could
          prevent from fulfilling her destined part in the life of each of us. . . .<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Some such phrase as <foreign xml:lang="greek">kai\ moi
              ma/rturas tou/twn ka/lei</foreign> seems to have been lost. Cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 5.61"
              >Antiph. 5.61</bibl>.</note><quote type="Witnesses">Witnesses</quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>The facts have been confirmed by evidence as I promised, gentlemen; and you must let that
          evidence help you to decide which of the two sworn statements made,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For the <foreign xml:lang="greek">diwmosi/a</foreign> cf.<bibl
              n="Antiph. 5.11">Antiph. 5.11</bibl>.</note> the prosecution's or my own, reveals more
          respect for truth and for the oath by which it was preceded. The prosecution swore that I
          was responsible for the death of Diodotus as having instigated the act which led to
            it<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That <foreign xml:lang="greek">bouleu/santa to\n
              qa/naton</foreign> is not to be taken in the sense of “wilfully caused his death” is
            clear from <bibl n="Antiph. 6.19">Antiph. 6.19</bibl>.</note>; whereas I swore that I
          did not cause his death, whether by my own act or by instigation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Further, in making their charge, the prosecution invoke the principle that the
          responsibility rests with whoever told the boy to drink the poison, forced him to drink
          it, or gave it to him to drink. By that very principle, however, I will myself prove that
          I am innocent: for I neither told the boy to drink the poison, nor forced him to drink it,
          nor gave it to him to drink. I will even go a step further than they and add that I did
          not witness him drink it. If the prosecution say that it was a criminal act to tell him to
          drink it, I am no criminal: I did not tell him to drink it. If they say that it was a
          criminal act to force him to drink it, I am no criminal: I did not force him to drink it.
          And if they say that the responsibility rests with the person who gave him the poison, I
          am not responsible: I did not give it to him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Now accusations and lies can be indulged in at will, as they are at the command of each
          one of us. But that what never happened should be transformed into fact, that an innocent
          man should be transformed into a criminal is not, I feel, a matter which depends upon the
          eloquence of the prosecution; it is a question of what is right and what is true.
          Admittedly, with a deliberately planned murder, carried out in secret and with none to
          witness it, the truth can only be determined from the accounts given by the prosecutor and
          the defendant, and from them alone; their statements must be followed up with care and
          suspected on the slightest grounds and the final verdict must necessarily be the result of
          conjecture rather than certain knowledge. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" type="section">
        <p>But in the present instance, the prosecution themselves admit to begin with that the
          boy's death was not due to premeditation or design: and secondly, everything which
          happened happened publicly and before numerous witnesses, men and boys, free men and
          slaves, who would have ensured the complete exposure of the criminal, had there been one,
          and the instant refutation of anyone who accused an innocent person.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed"><bibl n="Antiph. 6.19">Antiph. 6.19</bibl> in the Greek consists of an
            intricate dependent clause without a main verb to complete the grammatical construction.
            By the time <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)cele/gxoito</foreign> has been reached, the
            initial <foreign xml:lang="greek">o(/pou</foreign> has been forgotten.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Both the spirit shown by my opponents and the way in which they set to work are worth
          noticing, gentlemen; for their behavior towards me has been very different from mine
          towards them from the outset. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" type="section">
        <p>Philocrates yonder presented himself before the Heliaea of the Thesmothetae<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e. before an ordinary Heliastic court (<foreign
              xml:lang="greek">dikasth/rion</foreign>).</note> on the very day of the boy's burial,
          and declared that I had murdered his brother, a member of the chorus, by forcing him to
          drink poison. At that, I presented myself before the court in my turn. I told the same
          jury that Philocrates had no right to place legal impediments in my way by coming to court
          with his outrageous charge, when I was bringing suits against Aristion and Philinus on the
          following day and the day after: for that was his only reason for making such allegations.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" type="section">
        <p>However, I said, there would be no difficulty in proving his monstrous accusation a lie,
          as there were plenty of witnesses, slave and free, young and old, in fact, over fifty in
          all, who knew how the drinking of the poison had been accounted for and were in complete
          possession of the facts and circumstances. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Not only did I make this declaration before the court, but I offered Philocrates a
          challenge there and then, and repeated it the following day in the presence of the same
          jury. Let him take with him as many witnesses as he liked: let him go to the persons who
          had been present at the accident (I specified them by name): and let him interrogate and
          cross-examine them. Let him question the free men as befitted free men; for their own
          sakes and in the interests of justice, they would give a faithful account of what had
          occurred. As to the slaves, if he considered that they were answering his questions
          truthfully, well and good; if he did not, I was ready to place all my own at his disposal
          for examination under torture, and should he demand any that did not belong to me, I
          agreed to obtain the consent of their owner and hand them over to him to examine as he
          liked. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" type="section">
        <p>That was the challenge which I addressed to him before the court; and not only the jurors
          themselves but numbers of private persons also were there to witness it. Yet the
          prosecution refused to bring the case to this issue at the time, and have persistently
          refused ever since. They knew very well that instead of supplying them with proof of my
          guilt, such an inquiry would supply me with proof that their own charge was totally unjust
          and unfounded. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>You do not need to be reminded, gentlemen, that the one occasion when compulsion is as
          absolute and as effective as is humanly possible, and when the rights of a case are
          ascertained thereby most surely and most certainly, arises when there is an abundance of
          witnesses, both slave and free, and it is possible to put pressure upon the free men by
          exacting an oath or word of honor, the most solemn and the most awful form of compulsion
          known to freemen, and upon the slaves by other devices, which will force them to tell the
          truth even if their revelations are bound to cost them their lives, as the compulsion of
          the moment has a stronger influence over each than the fate which he will suffer by
          compulsion afterwards.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A difficult sentence. Literally:
            “The compulsion which is present has more influence over each than that which is to
            come.” The meaning seems to be: the torture which they are suffering at the moment
              (<foreign xml:lang="greek">h( parou=sa a)na/gkh</foreign>) forces them to speak in
            spite of the fact that they will inevitably be put to death in consequence of their
            disclosures (<foreign xml:lang="greek">h( me/llousa a)na/gkh</foreign>). <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">a)na/gkh</foreign> is used in two slightly different senses—(1) of
            torture: that which leaves a man no choice but speak. (2) Of a death which is
            certain.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>It was to this, then, and nothing less that I challenged the prosecution. Every means
          which mortal man finds it necessary to use in order to discover the true rights of a
          matter, they had the opportunity of using; not the vestige of an excuse was left them. I,
          the defendant, the alleged criminal, was ready to give them the chance of proving my guilt
          in the fairest possible way; it was they, the prosecutors, the professedly injured party,
          who refused to obtain proof of such injury as they had sustained. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" type="section">
        <p>Suppose that the offer had come from them. Then had I refused to disclose who the
          eyewitnesses were: had I refused to hand over my servants at their request: or had I been
          afraid to accept some other challenge, they would be claiming that those facts in
          themselves afforded to my detriment the strongest presumption of the truth of their
          charge. Instead, it was I who issued the challenge, and the prosecution who evaded the
          test. So it was surely only fair that this same fact should afford me a presumption to
          their detriment that the charge which they have made against me is untrue. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Further, I am certain, gentlemen, that if the witnesses present at the accident were
          testifying in the prosecution's favor and against me, the prosecution would be treating
          them as supremely important: they would be showing that such unfavourable evidence was
          proof conclusive. As, however, these same witnesses are testifying that what I say is true
          and that what the prosecution say is not, they urge that the evidence of those witnesses
          in my favor is untrustworthy; according to them, it is their own statements which you
          should believe, statements which they would be attacking as false, were I making them
          myself without witnesses to support me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" type="section">
        <p>Yet it is strange that the witnesses who would be trustworthy, were their evidence
          favorable to the prosecution, are to be untrustworthy when it is favorable to me. Were I
          producing eyewitnesses when there had been none, or were I not producing the true
          eyewitnesses, there would be some ground for treating the statements of the prosecution as
          more trustworthy than my witnesses. But the prosecution admit that witnesses were actually
          present: I am producing those witnesses: and both I and all my witnesses are well known to
          have maintained from the very first day what we are repeating to you now. So what other
          means than these are to be employed to confirm what is true and to disprove what is not?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" type="section">
        <p>If a bare statement of the facts were made, but not supported by the evidence of
          witnesses, it might well be criticized for the absence of that support; and if witnesses
          were forthcoming, only to conflict with the presumptions furnished by the pleader, his
          opponent might well pass a corresponding criticism, should he so wish. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" type="section">
        <p>Now in my own case, you are being presented with an account which is reasonable, with
          evidence which is consistent with that account, with facts which are consistent with that
          evidence, with presumptions drawn immediately from those facts, and with two arguments of
          the greatest significance and weight in addition: </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" type="section">
        <p>the first, the circumstance that the prosecution have been proved impostors both by
          themselves and by me: and the second, the circumstance that I have been proved innocent
          both by the prosecution and by myself; for in refusing to obtain proof of such injury as
          they had sustained when I was ready for an inquiry into the crime with which they were
          charging me, they were clearly acknowledging my innocence and testifying to the injustice
          and falsity of their own accusation. If I supplement the evidence of my own witnesses with
          that of my opponents in person, what other expedients, what other proofs are necessary to
          establish my entire freedom from the charge? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>I feel that both the arguments and proofs which I have put before you, gentlemen, would
          justify you in acquitting me; you all know that the charge before the court does not
          concern me. However, to confirm you in that knowledge, I will go further. I will prove
          that my accusers here are the most reckless perjurors and the most godless scoundrels
          alive: that they have earned not only my own hatred, but the hatred of every one of you
          and of your fellow-citizens besides, by instituting this trial. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>On the first day, the day of the boy's death, and on the second, when the body was laid
          out, not even the prosecution themselves thought of accusing me of having played any kind
          of criminal part in the accident: on the contrary, they avoided neither meeting me nor
          speaking to me.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The force of <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >sunh=san kai\ diele/gonto</foreign> can be best conveyed by a negative. The
            implication is, of course, that had the prosecution believed the speaker guilty, they
            would have avoided all contact with him for fear of being tainted with the <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">mi/asma</foreign> which rested on him. Cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 2.1.10"
              >Antiph. 2.1.10</bibl>.</note> It was only on the third day, the day of the boy's
          burial, that they yielded to my enemies and set about bringing a charge and proclaiming me
          to be under the usual disabilities.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign
              xml:lang="greek">to\ ei)/rgesqai tw=n nomi/mwn</foreign> was the immediate consequence
            of a <foreign xml:lang="greek">pro/rrhsis</foreign>. A suspected murderer had to
            withdraw from intercourse with his fellows until his innocence had been established or
            his guilt expiated. Cf.<title>Herodes</title>, Introduction.</note> Now who was it who
          instigated them? And what reason had those others for wanting to do such a thing? I must
          enlighten you on these further points. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>I was about to prosecute Aristion, Philinus, Ampelinus, and the secretary to the
          Thesmothetae, with whose embezzlements they had been associated, on charges which I had
          presented to the Council in the form of an impeachment. As far as the facts of the case
          were concerned, they had no hope of acquittal: their offences were too serious. On the
          other hand, could they but induce my accusers here to register a charge and proclaim that
          I was under the statutory ban, they would, they thought, be safely rid of the whole
          business. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" type="section">
        <p>The law runs that the ban comes into force as soon as anyone has a charge of murder
          registered against him; and if placed under it, not only should I myself have been unable
          to proeeed with my case, but once the party responsible for the impeachment and in
          possession of the facts failed to proceed, the four would gain an acquittal without
          difficulty, and the wrong which they had done you would go unpunished. I was not, I may
          say, the first against whom Philinus and his companions had employed this device; they had
          already done the same to Lysistratus, as you have heard for yourselves.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Nothing further is known of Lysistratus.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>The prosecution started by doing their utmost to register a charge at once, on the day
          after the burial, before the house had been purified or the proper rites performed; they
          had taken care to choose the very day on which the first of the other four was to be
          tried, to make it impossible for me to proceed against a single one of them or present the
          court with any of their offences. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" type="section">
        <p>However, the Basileus read them the law, and showed that there was not sufficient time to
          register a charge or issue the necessary writs<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign
              xml:lang="greek">proklh/seis</foreign> are writs summoning the witnesses for the
            prosecution and defence.</note>; so I took the originators of the plot into court, and
          secured a conviction in every case—and you know the amount at which the damages were
          fixed. No sooner, however, did my accusers here find it impossible to give the help which
          they had been paid to give than they approached me and my friends with a request for a
          reconciliation, and offered to make amends for their past errors. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" type="section">
        <p>I took my friends' advice, and was formally reconciled to them on the Acropolis<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Scheibe conjectured <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)n
              *diipolei/ois</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)n th=| po/lei</foreign>, on
            the ground that Harpocration quotes the word Diipoleia as occurring in this speech. The
            Diipoleia (cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 2.4">Antiph. 2.4</bibl>) was an ancient festival
            celebrated annually in the first week of June on the Acropolis in honor of Zeus Polieus.
            Its date would suit the context; but the fact that the last part of the speech is
            apparently incomplete makes it possible that Harpocration is quoting from some lost
            passage.</note> in the presence of witnesses, who performed the ceremony near the temple
          of Athena. Afterwards, they met me and spoke to me in temples, in the Agora, in my house,
          in their own—everywhere in fact. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" type="section">
        <p>The crowning point was reached in the Council-chamber in front of the Council—heavens, to
          think of it! —when Philocrates here himself joined me on the tribune and conversed with
          me, his hand on my arm, addressing me by my name as I addressed him by his. No wonder that
          the Council was astounded to learn that I had been proclaimed under the ban by the very
          persons whom they had seen in my company chatting to me on the previous day.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">A reference to the sudden change of front shown by Philocrates
            when he saw that the Choregus had discovered his own activities.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>And now I want your attention, gentlemen: I want you to cast your minds back; for I shall
          not use witnesses alone to prove the facts to which I am now coming; your own knowledge of
          how the prosecution have acted will itself show you at once that I am telling the truth.
          To begin with, they complain of the Basileus and attribute his refusal to register their
          charge to activities of mine. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" type="section">
        <p>That complaint, however, will serve merely to damage their case by suggesting that their
          statements in general are untrue; for after registering the action, the Basileus was
          obliged to hold three preliminary inquiries in the course of the three months following,
          only bringing the case into court during the fourth—as he has done today. Yet only two
          months of office remained to him, Thargelion and Scirophorion.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The dates are roughly as given in the Introduction. The <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">*basileu/s</foreign> went out of office on the 21st June: Philocrates
            attempted to register his charge in the last week of April. Thargelion and Scirophorion
            were the last two months of the Attic year.</note> It would thus clearly have been
          impossible for him to bring the case into court during his own period of office; and he is
          not allowed to hand on an action for murder to his successor; such a thing has never been
          done by any Basileus in this country. So, as it was a case which he could neither bring
          into court nor hand on to his successor, he did not see why he should break your laws by
          registering it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" type="section">
        <p>There is, indeed, one very striking indication that he did not rob the prosecution of
          their rights: whereas Philocrates yonder tormented other magistrates who had to render
          account of their office<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >eu)/qunai</foreign> of a magistrate consisted of public examination of his accounts
            and general conduct at the end of his period of office. There was a corresponding
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">dokimasi/a</foreign>, or preliminary investigation of his
            fitness, before his installation.</note> with vexatious complaints, he failed to come
          forward with any grievance when this particular Basileus, whose conduct, we are told, had
          been so outrageously high handed, was rendering account of his. What clearer indication
          could I present to you that Philocrates had suffered no injury from either myself or him?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Moreover, after the present Basileus had come into office, there were thirty clear days
          from the first of Hecatombaeon onwards,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Hecatombaeon was
            the first month of the official Attic year; it extended from 22nd June to 21st July.
            Metageitnion followed it.</note> on any of which they could have registered their
          charge, had they wanted to; yet they did not do so. Similarly, they could have registered
          it any day they liked from the first of Metageitnion onwards. But even then they did not
          do so: they let twenty days of this second month by as well. Thus the total number of days
          in the present archonship on which they could have registered their charge, but failed to
          do so, was over fifty.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The words “over fifty” look like a
            rhetorical exaggeration. For the bearing of this and the following section on the date
            of the speech, see Introduction.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" type="section">
        <p>Ordinarily, anyone who has not time enough under one archon &lt;registers his charge as
          soon as he can under the next&gt;. But the prosecution, who were perfectly familiar with
          the laws concerned and could see that I was a member of the Council and used the
          Council-chamber —why, in that very chamber itself stands a shrine of Zeus the Councillor
          and Athena the Councillor, where members offer prayers as they enter; and I was one of
          those members: I did as they did: in their company I entered all our other sanctuaries: I
          offered sacrifices and prayers on behalf of this city: nay more, I acted as a Prytanis for
          the whole of the first Prytany save two days<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">boulh/</foreign> was divided into ten sections, each representing a
            tribe. Each section took it in turn to act as presidents (<foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >pruta/neis</foreign>) for a period known as a <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >prutanei/a</foreign>(one tenth of the year) at meetings of both the <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">boulh/</foreign> and the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >e)kklhsi/a</foreign>. The <foreign xml:lang="greek">pruta/neis</foreign> themselves
            were under the presidency of one of their number known as an <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >e)pista/ths</foreign> who was selected by lot. It was he who put motions to the vote
            in the Assembly. The Choregus was clearly <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >e)pista/ths</foreign> during his Prytany.</note>: I was to be seen sacrificing and
          making offerings on behalf of our sovereign people: I was to be seen putting motions to
          the vote: I was to be seen voicing my opinion on the most momentous, the most vital public
          questions. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" type="section">
        <p>And the prosecution were in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>: they
          witnessed it: by registering their charge they could have debarred me from it all. In
          spite of that, they did not see fit to do so. Yet if their wrong was real, their duty to
          alike enough to keep the memory of it fresh and to make it their constant thought. Then
          why did they fail to register a charge? Their reason was the same as their reason for not
          refusing to associate and converse with me. They associated with me because they did not
          think me a murderer and they refused to register a charge for exactly the same reason:
          they did not think that I had either killed the boy, been concerned in his death, or had
          any part in the affair at all. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Where indeed could one find fewer scruples or a greater contempt for law? Here are men
          who expect to persuade you to believe what they have failed to persuade themselves to
          believe, who bid you declare guilty the man whom they have themselves in fact declared
          innocent; whereas everyone else uses the facts to prove the worth of mere assertion, they
          use mere assertion for the purpose of discrediting the facts. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" type="section">
        <p>Indeed, if I had said nothing, established nothing, and produced evidence of nothing, but
          had proved to you the one fact that, whereas when paid to attack me the prosecution
          produced charges and proclamations, they frequented my society and were on speaking terms
          with me when there was no one to finance them, you would have heard enough to acquit me
          and treat the prosecution as the worst perjurors and the most impious scoundrels alive.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" type="section">
        <p>What accusation would they hesitate to bring, what court would they hesitate to mislead,
          what oaths would they feel any compunction in breaking, after taking thirty minae, as they
          have, from the Poristae, the Poletae, the Practores, and the clerks attached to them, to
          bring me into court,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For an explanation of this see
            Introduction.</note> after driving me from the Council-chamber, and after swearing oaths
          so solemn, all because during my Prytany I learned of their scandalous malpractices,
          brought them before the Council, and showed that an inquiry should be instituted and the
          matter probed to the bottom. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" type="section">
        <p>As it is, they themselves, those who struck the bargain with them, and the parties with
          whom the money was deposited are paying the price of their misdeeds<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Apparently it had come to light in the course of the investigations into the
            activities of the Practores, etc. that thirty minae had been promised Philocrates if his
            charge of homicide was successful. The money would be deposited with a third party, to
            be claimed by Philocrates when he had earned it.</note>; and the facts have been
          revealed so clearly that the prosecution will find it difficult to deny them, even if they
          wish to; such is the lack of success which they have had. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>What court, then, would they hesitate to invade with their lies, what oaths would they
          feel the slightest compunction in breaking? The impious scoundrels! They knew that you are
          the most conscientious and the fairest judges in this nation; yet they come before you
          intent on deceiving even you, if they can, in spite of the solemn oaths which they have
            sworn.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The repetitions in these closing paragraphs, and
            the absence of the usual <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)pi/logos</foreign> make it probable
            that the end of the speech, as we have it, is mutilated.</note></p>
      </div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
