<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Didache, or Teaching of the Twelve Apostles.</title>
        <author/>
        <editor role="translator">Kirsopp Lake</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
          <funder n="org:Tufts">Tufts University</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <date type="release">2019</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Didache</author>
            <title>The Apostolic Fathers with an English translation by Kirsopp Lake. In Two Volumes. Vol. I.</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date type="printing">1912</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
            <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.232411">Internet Archive</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern n="epistle" matchPattern="(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation marks="none"/>
          <correction method="silent" status="medium"><p>Perseus OCR in house AbbyyFR; single pass proofreading</p></correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-03-25" who="Lisa Cerrato">basic structural markup and single pass editing</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text xml:lang="eng">
		<body>
		  
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg1311.tlg001.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
  <pb xml:id="p.309"/>
  <head>THE DIDACHE, OR TEACHING OF THE TWELVE APOSTLES</head>
  <head>The Lord’s teaching to the heathen by the Twelve Apostles.</head>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">There are two Ways, one of Life and one of<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The two Ways</note> Death, and there is a great difference between the two Ways.</p></div>
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p rend="indent">The Way of Life is this: <q>First, thou shalt<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The Way of Life</note> love the God who made thee, secondly, thy neighbour as thyself; and whatsoever thou wouldst not have done to thyself, do not thou to another.</q><note type="footnote" resp="editor">This is the so-called <q>negative form of the Golden Rule.</q> It is found in some MSS. in the <q>Apostolic decrees</q> in Acts xv. 28, and is, in various forms, met with in Jewish and Early Christian literature.</note></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p rend="indent">Now, the teaching of these words is this:<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The explanation</note> <q>Bless those that curse you, and pray for your enemies, and fast for those that persecute you. For what credit is it to you if you love those that love you? Do not even the heathen do the same?</q> But, for your part, <q>love those that hate you,</q> and you will have no enemy.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q>Abstain from carnal</q> and bodily <q>lusts.</q> <q>If any man smite thee on the <pb xml:id="p.311"/> right cheek, turn to him the other cheek also,</q> and thou wilt be perfect. <q>If any man impress thee to go with him one mile, go with him two. If any man take thy coat, give him thy shirt also. If any man will take from thee what is thine, refuse it not</q>—not even if thou canst.<note type="footnote" resp="editor">The Greek is literally <q>for thou art not even able</q>; but this makes no sense, and though an emendation is difficult the sense must be something like that given by the translation—unless, indeed, the whole phrase be merely a flippant gloss, which has been erroneously taken into the text.</note></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Give to everyone<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Alms-giving</note> that asks thee, and do not refuse, for the Father’s will is that we give to all from the gifts we have received. Blessed is he that gives according to the mandate; for he is innocent. Woe to him who receives; for if any man receive alms under pressure of need he is innocent; but he who receives it without need shall be tried as to why he took and for what, and being in prison he shall be examined as to his deeds, and <q>he shall not come out thence until he pay the last farthing.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>But concerning this it was also said, <q>Let thine alms sweat into thine hands until thou knowest to whom thou art giving.</q></p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But the second commandment of the teaching<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The second part of the teaching</note> is this;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><q>Thou shalt do no murder; thou shalt not commit adultery</q>; thou shalt not commit sodomy; thou shalt not commit fornication; thou shalt not steal; thou shalt not use magic; thou shalt not use philtres; thou shalt not procure abortion, nor <pb xml:id="p.313"/> commit infanticide; <q>thou shalt not covet thy neighbour’s goods</q>;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>thou shalt not commit perjury, <q>thou shalt not bear false witness</q>; thou shalt not speak evil; thou shalt not bear malice.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Thou shalt not be double-minded nor double-tongued, for to be double-tongued is the snare of death.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Thy speech shall not be false nor vain, but completed in action.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Thou shalt not be covetous nor extortionate, nor a hypocrite, nor malignant, nor proud, thou shalt make no evil plan against thy neighbour.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Thou shalt hate no man; but some thou shalt reprove,<note type="footnote" resp="editor">On the ground of a comparison with Jude 22 f. etc., some think that <q>and some thou shalt pity</q> ought to be added.</note> and for some shalt thou pray, and some thou shalt love more than thine own life.</p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">My child, flee from every evil man and from all<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Further advice to the catechumen</note> like him.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Be not proud, for pride leads to murder, nor jealous, nor contentious, nor passionate, for from all these murders are engendered.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>My child, be not lustful, for lust leads to fornication, nor a speaker of base words, nor a lifter up of the eyes, for from all these is adultery engendered.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>My child, regard not omens, for this leads to idolatry; neither be an enchanter, nor an astrologer, nor a magician, neither wish to see these things, for from them all is idolatry engendered.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>My child, be not a liar, for lying leads to theft, nor a lover of money, nor vain-glorious, for from all these things <pb xml:id="p.315"/> are thefts engendered.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>My child, be not a grumbler, for this leads to blasphemy, nor stubborn, nor a thinker of evil, for from all these are blasphemies engendered,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>but be thou <q>meek, for the meek shall inherit the earth;</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>be thou long-suffering, and merciful and guileless, and quiet, and good, and ever fearing the words which thou hast heard.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>Thou shalt not exalt thyself, nor let thy soul be presumptuous. Thy soul shall not consort with the lofty, but thou shalt walk with righteous and humble men.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p>Receive the accidents that befall to thee as good, knowing that nothing happens without God.</p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
   <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">My child, thou shalt remember, day and night,<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The duty of the catechumen to the Church</note> him who speaks the word of God to thee, and thou shalt honour him as the Lord, for where the Lord’s nature is spoken of, there is he present.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And thou shalt seek daily the presence of the saints, that thou mayest find rest in their words.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Thou shalt not desire a schism, but shalt reconcile those that strive. Thou shalt give righteous judgment; thou shalt favour no man’s person in reproving transgression.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Thou shalt not be of two minds whether it shall be or not.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p rend="indent">Be not one who stretches out his hands to<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Against meanness</note> receive, but shuts them when it comes to giving.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Of <pb xml:id="p.317"/> whatsoever thou hast gained by thy hands thou shalt give a ransom for thy sins.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Thou shalt not hesitate to give, nor shalt thou grumble when thou givest, for thou shalt know who is the good Paymaster of the reward.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>Thou shalt not turn away the needy, but shalt share everything with thy brother, and shalt not say that it is thine own, for if you are sharers in the imperishable, how much more in the things which perish?</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p rend="indent">Thou shalt not withhold thine hand from thy<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Household duties</note> son or from thy daughter, but thou shalt teach them the fear of God from their youth up.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p>Thou shalt not command in thy bitterness thy slave or thine handmaid, who hope in the same God, lest they cease to fear the God who is over you both; for he comes not to call men with respect of persons, but those whom the Spirit has prepared.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p>But do you who are slaves be subject to your master, as to God’s representative, in reverence and fear.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p rend="indent">Thou shalt hate all hypocrisy, and everything<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Against hypocrisy</note> that is not pleasing to the Lord.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p>Thou shalt not forsake the commandments of the Lord, but thou shalt keep what thou didst receive, <q>adding nothing to it and taking nothing away.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"><p>In the congregation thou shalt confess thy transgressions, and thou shalt not betake thyself to prayer with an evil conscience. This is the way of life.</p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But the Way of Death is this: First of all, it is<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The Way of Death</note> wicked and full of cursing, murders, adulteries, lusts, fornications, thefts, idolatries, witchcrafts, charms, <pb xml:id="p.319"/> robberies, false witness, hypocrisies, a double heart, fraud, pride, malice, stubbornness, covetousness, foul speech, jealousy, impudence, haughtiness, boastfulness.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Persecutors of the good, haters of truth, lovers of lies, knowing not the reward of righteousness, not cleaving to the good nor to righteous judgment, spending wakeful nights not for good but for wickedness, from whom meekness and patience is far, lovers of vanity, following after reward, unmerciful to the poor, not working for him who is oppressed with toil, without knowledge of him who made them, murderers of children, corrupters of God’s creatures, turning away the needy, oppressing the distressed, advocates of the rich, unjust judges of the poor, altogether sinful; may ye be delivered, my children, from all these.</p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">See <q>that no one make thee to err</q> from this<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Final exhortation</note> Way of the teaching, for he teaches thee without God.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For if thou canst bear the whole yoke of the Lord, thou wilt be perfect, but if thou canst not, do what thou canst.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And concerning food, bear<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Food, and ‘things offered to idols.’</note> what thou canst, but keep strictly from that which is offered to idols, for it is the worship of dead gods.</p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Concerning baptism, baptise thus: Having first<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Baptism</note> rehearsed all these things, <q>baptise, in the Name of <pb xml:id="p.321"/> the Father and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit,</q> in running water;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>but if thou hast no running water, baptise in other water, and if thou canst not in cold, then in wrarm.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>But if thou hast neither, pour water three times on the head <q>in the Name of the Father, Son and Holy Spirit.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And before the baptism let the baptiser and him who is to be baptised fast, and any others who are able. And thou shalt bid him who is to be baptised to fast one or two days before.</p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let not your fasts be with the hypocrites, for<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Fasting</note> they fast on Mondays and Thursdays, but do you fast on Wednesdays and Fridays.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And do not pray as<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Prayer</note> the hypocrites, but as the Lord commanded in his Gospel, pray thus: <q>Our Father, who art in Heaven, hallowed be thy Name, thy Kingdom come, thy will be done, as in Heaven so also upon earth; give us to-day our daily<note type="footnote" resp="editor">This is the traditional translation of ἐπιούσιον, but it is by no means certain that it is correct. The word has from the beginning been a puzzle, and its meaning is not clearly known. See further any good commentary on the gospels.</note> bread, and forgive us our debt as we forgive our debtors, and lead us not into trial, but deliver us from the Evil One, for thine is the power and the glory for ever.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Pray thus three times a day.</p></div></div>
    
    <pb xml:id="p.323"/>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And concerning the Eucharist, hold<note type="footnote" resp="editor">The translation fails to preserve the play on the words, which might be rendered <q>concerning the giving of thanks, give thanks thus, etc.</q> But this would obscure the fact that εὐχαριστία is here quite clearly <q>Eucharist</q> (cf. v. 5).</note> Eucharist<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The Eucharist</note> thus:</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>First concerning the Cup, <q>We give thanks<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The Cup</note> to thee, our Father, for the Holy Vine of David thy child, which, thou didst make known to us through Jesus thy child; to thee be glory for ever.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And concerning the broken Bread: <q>We give thee thanks,<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The Bread</note> our Father, for the life and knowledge which thou didst make known to us through Jesus thy child. To thee be glory for ever.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">As this broken bread was scattered upon the mountains, but was brought together and became one, so let thy Church be gathered together from the ends of the earth into thy kingdom, for thine is the glory and the power through Jesus Christ for ever.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>But let none eat or drink of your Eucharist except those who have been baptised in the Lord’s Name. For concerning this also did the Lord say, <q>Give not that which is holy to the dogs.</q></p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But after you are satisfied with food, thus give<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The final prayer in the Eucharist</note> thanks:</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><q>We give thanks to thee, O Holy Father, for thy Holy Name which thou didst make to tabernacle <pb xml:id="p.325"/> in our hearts, and for the knowledge and faith and immortality which thou didst make known to us through Jesus thy Child. To thee be glory for ever.</q></p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q rend="merge">Thou, Lord Almighty, didst create all things for thy Name’s sake, and didst give food and drink to men for their enjoyment, that they might give thanks to thee, but us hast thou blessed with spiritual food and drink and eternal light through thy Child.</q></p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">Above all we give thanks to thee for that thou art mighty. To thee be glory for ever.</q></p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">Remember, Lord, thy Church, to deliver it from all evil and to make it perfect in thy love, and gather it together in its holiness from the four winds to thy kingdom which thou hast prepared for it. For thine is the power and the glory for ever.</q></p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">Let grace come and let this world pass away. Hosannah to the God of David. If any man be holy, let him come! if any man be not, let him repent: Maranatha,<note type="footnote" resp="editor">A transliteration of Aramaic words meaning <q>Our Lord! Come!</q></note> Amen.</q></p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p rend="indent">But suffer the prophets to hold Eucharist as they will.</p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Whosoever then comes and teaches you all<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Travelling teachers</note> these things aforesaid, receive him.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>But if the teacher himself be perverted and teach another doctrine to destroy these things, do not listen to him, but if his teaching be for the increase of righteousness and knowledge of the Lord, receive him as the Lord.</p></div><pb xml:id="p.327"/>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p rend="indent">And concerning the Apostles and Prophets,<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Apostles</note> act thus according to the ordinance of the Gospel.<note type="footnote" resp="editor">It is unknown to what ordinance the writer refers.</note></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Let every Apostle who comes to you be received as the Lord,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>but let him not stay more than one day, or if need be a second as well; but if he stay three days, he is a false prophet.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>And when an Apostle goes forth let him accept nothing but bread till he reach his night’s lodging; but if he ask for money, he is a false prophet.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p rend="indent">Do not test or examine any prophet who is speaking<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Prophets</note> in a spirit, <q>for every sin shall be forgiven, but this sin shall not be forgiven.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>But not everyone who speaks in a spirit is a prophet, except he have the behaviour of the Lord. From his behaviour, then, the false prophet and the true prophet shall be known.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>And no prophet who orders a meal in a spirit shall eat of it: otherwise he is a false prophet.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p>And every prophet who teaches the truth, if he do not what he teaches, is a false prophet.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p>But no prophet who has been tried and is genuine, though he enact a worldly mystery <note type="footnote" resp="editor">This passage has never been satisfactorily explained: it probably refers to a tendency among some prophets to introduce forms of worship, or of illustration of their teaching, of doubtful propriety, if so the reference below to the prophets of old is perhaps an allusion to Hosea (Hos. 1, 2 ff.).</note> of the Church, if he teach not others to do what he does himself, shall be judged by you: for he has his judgment with God, for so also did the prophets of old.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p>But whosoever shall say in a spirit ‘Give me money, or something else,’ you shall not listen to him; but if he tell you to give on behalf of others in want, let none judge him.</p></div></div>
    
    <pb xml:id="p.329"/>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let everyone who <q>comes in the Name of the<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Travelling Christians</note> Lord</q> be received; but when you have tested him you shall know him, for you shall have understanding of true and false.<note type="footnote" resp="editor">Literally, <q>right and left understanding.</q></note></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>If he who comes is a traveller, help him as much as you can, but he shall not remain with you more than two days, or, if need be, three.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And if he wishes to settle among you and has a craft, let him work for his bread.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>But if he has no craft provide for him according to your understanding, so that no man shall live among you in idleness because he is a Christian.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>But if he will not do so, he is making traffic of Christ; beware of such.</p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But every true prophet who wishes to settle<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Prophets who desire to remain</note> among you is <q>worthy of his food.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Likewise a true teacher is himself worthy, like the workman, of his food.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Therefore thou shalt take the firstfruit<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Their payment by firstfruits</note> of the produce of the winepress and of the threshing-floor and of oxen and sheep, and shalt give them as the firstfruits to the prophets, for they are your high priests.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>But if you have not a prophet, give to the poor.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>If thou makest bread, take the first-fruits, and give it according to the commandment.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Likewise when thou openest a jar of wine or oil, give the firstfruits to the prophets.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Of money also and clothes, and of all your possessions, take the firstfruits, as it seem best to you, and give according to the commandment.</p></div></div>
    
    <pb xml:id="p.331"/>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">On the Lord’s Day of the Lord come together,<note type="marginal" resp="editor">The Sunday worship</note> break bread and hold Eucharist, after confessing your transgressions that your offering may be pure;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>but let none who has a quarrel with his fellow join in your meeting until they be reconciled, that your sacrifice be not defiled.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For this is that which was spoken by the Lord, <q>In every place and time offer me a pure sacrifice, for I am a great king,</q> saith the Lord, <q>and my name is wonderful among the heathen.</q></p></div></div>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Appoint therefore for yourselves bishops and<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Bishops and Deacons</note> deacons worthy of the Lord, meek men, and not lovers of money, and truthful and approved, for they also minister to you the ministry of the prophets and teachers.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Therefore do not despise them, for they are your honourable men together with the prophets and teachers.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p rend="indent">And reprove one another not in wrath but in<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Mutual reproofs</note> peace as you find in the Gospel, and let none speak with any who has done a wrong to his neighbour, nor let him hear a word from you until he repents.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>But your prayers and alms and all your acts perform as ye find in the Gospel of our Lord.</p></div></div>
    
    <pb xml:id="p.333"/>
    
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent"><q>Watch</q> over your life: <q>let your lamps</q> be<note type="marginal" resp="editor">Warning that the end is at hand</note> not quenched <q>and your loins</q> be not ungirded, but be <q>ready,</q> for ye know not <q>the hour in which our Lord cometh.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>But be frequently gathered together seeking the things which are profitable for your souls, for the whole time of your faith shall not profit you except ye be found perfect at the last time;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>for in the last days the false prophets and the corrupters shall be multiplied, and the sheep shall be turned into wolves, and love shall change to hate;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>for as lawlessness increaseth they shall hate one another and persecute and betray, and then shall appear the deceiver of the world as a Son of God, and shall do signs and wonders and the earth shall be given over into his hands and he shall commit iniquities which have never been since the world began.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Then shall the creation of mankind come to the fiery trial and <q>many shall be offended</q> and be lost, but <q>they who endure</q> in their faith <q>shall be saved</q> by the curse itself.<note type="footnote" resp="editor">The meaning is obscure; but there seem to be other traces in early literature of a doctrine that each curse also contained the elements of a counterbalancing power to salvation. There is a valuable and long note on the subject in Rendel Harris’s edition of the Didache.</note></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>And <q>then shall appear the signs</q> of the truth. First the sign spread out in Heaven, then the sign of the sound of the trumpet, and thirdly the resurrection of the dead:</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>but not of all the dead, but as it was said, <q>The Lord shall come and all his saints with him.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>Then shall the world <q>see the Lord coming on the clouds of Heaven.</q></p></div></div>
  
</div>
</body></text></TEI>
