<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		

<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title>Euthydemus</title>
<author>Plato</author>
	<editor role="translator">W. R. M. Lamb</editor>
<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

</titleStmt>
	<publicationStmt>
		<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
		<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
		<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
		<date type="release">1996</date>
	</publicationStmt> 
	<notesStmt>
		<note anchored="true">Text was scanned at St. Olaf Spring, 1992.</note>
		<note>Perseus 2.0</note>
	</notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
	<monogr>
		<author>Plato</author>
		<title>Plato in Twelve Volumes, translated by W.R.M. Lamb.</title>
		
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
			<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
			<date>1924</date>
			<note>volumes renumbered in various printings</note>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<ref target="https://archive.org/details/L165PlatoIILachesProtagorasMenoEuthydemus">Internet Archive</ref>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>


</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
	<refsDecl n="CTS">
		<cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
			replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">           
			<p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
		</cRefPattern>
	</refsDecl>

<!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="text"/>
<state unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="text"/>
<state unit="page"/>
</refsDecl>-->
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
	<particDesc>
		<person><persName>Crito</persName></person>
		<person><persName>Socrates</persName></person>
		<person><persName>Euthydemus</persName></person>
		<person><persName>Dionysodorus</persName></person>
		<person><persName>Cleinias</persName></person>
		<person><persName>Ctesippus</persName></person>
	</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017-06-13" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion.</change>
<change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
<change when="1992-07-01" who="WPM">Tagged in conformance with Prose.e dtd.</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="eng">
		<body> 
			<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg021.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng"> 

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="271">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="271"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="271a"/>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Who was it, Socrates, that you were talking with yesterday at the Lyceum? Why, there was such a crowd standing about you that when I came up in the hope of listening I could hear nothing distinctly: still, by craning over I got a glimpse, and it appeared to me that it was a stranger with whom you were talking. Who was he?</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>About which are you asking, Crito? There were two of them, not one.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>The man whom I mean was sitting next but one to you, on your right: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="271b"/>between you was Axiochus’ boy; and he, Socrates, seemed to me to have grown a great deal, so as to look almost the same age as my Critobulus, who is rather puny whereas this boy has come on finely, and has a noble air about him.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Euthydemus is the person to whom you refer, Crito, and the one sitting on my left was his brother, Dionysodorus. He too takes part in our discussions.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Neither of them is known to me, Socrates. A pair of fresh additions, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="271c"/>I suppose, to our sophists. Where do they hail from, and what science do they profess?</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>By birth I believe they belong to these parts, that is to say, <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>; they went out as colonists to <placeName key="perseus,Thurii">Thurii</placeName>, but have been exiled thence and have spent a good many years now in various parts of this country. As to what you ask of their profession, it is a wonderful one, Crito. These two men are absolutely omniscient: I never knew before what <q type="emph">all-round sportsmen</q><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The phrase refers especially to a very vigorous sport which combined wrestling and boxing.</note> were. They are a pair of regular all-round fighters—not in the style of the famous all-round athletes, the two brothers of Acamania; <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="271d"/>they could fight with their bodies only. But these two, in the first place, are most formidable in body and in fight against all comers</p></said></div>
				
				
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="272">
<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>—for they are not only well skilled themselves in fighting under arms, 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="272"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="272a"/>but are able to impart that skill, for a fee, to another; and further, they are most competent also to fight the battle of the law-courts and teach others how to speak, or to have composed for them, such speeches as may win their suits. Formerly they had merely some ability for this; but now they have put the finishing touch to their skill as all-round sportsmen. The one feat of fighting yet unperformed by them they have now accomplished, so that nobody dares stand up to them for a moment; such a faculty they have acquired for wielding words as their weapons and confuting any argument as readily <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="272b"/>if it be true as if it be false. And so I, Crito, am minded to place myself in these two gentlemen’s hands; for they say it would take them but a little while to make anyone else clever in just the same way.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>What, Socrates! Are you not afraid, at your time of life, that you may be too old for that now?</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Not at all, Crito: I have enough proof and reassurance to the contrary. These same two persons were little less than old men at the time of their taking up this science, which I desire to have, of disputation. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="272c"/>Last year, or the year before, they were as yet without their science. The only thing I am afraid of is that I may bring the same disgrace upon our two visitors as upon Connus, son of Metrobius, the harper, who is still trying to teach me the harp; so that the boys who go to his lessons with me make fun of me and call Connus <q type="emph">the gaffers’ master.</q> This makes me fear that someone may make the same reproach to the two strangers; and, for aught I know, their dread of this very thing may make them unwilling to accept me. So, Crito, just as in the other case I have persuaded some elderly men to come and have lessons with me, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="272d"/>in this affair I am going to try and persuade another set. Now you, I am sure, will come with me to school; and we will take your sons as a bait to entice them, for I have no doubt that the attraction of these young fellows will make them include us also in the class.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>I have no objection, Socrates, if you think fit to do so. But first you must explain to me what is the science these men profess, that I may know what it is we are going to learn.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>You shall be told at once; for I cannot plead that I did not give them my attention, since I not only attended closely but remember and will try <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="272e"/>to expound the whole thing from the beginning. By some providence I chanced to be sitting in the place where you saw me, in the undressing-room,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This gymnasium (the Lyceum) was a public one, open to persons of all ages, and was a common resort of Socrates and the sophists.</note> alone, and was just intending to get up and go; but the moment I did so, there came my wonted spiritual sign.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Socrates believed that his conduct was occasionally guided by a spiritual voice or sign peculiar to himself. By Plato’s account it was always negative, but the present instance shows how Xenophon might have some reason for saying that it was sometimes positive.</note></p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="273"> <said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So I sat down again, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="273" /><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="273a"/>and after a little while these two persons entered—Euthydemus and Dionysodorus—and accompanying them, quite a number, as it seemed to me, of their pupils: the two men came in and began walking round inside the cloister.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The cloister ran round the central open court, and was reached by passing through the undressing-room.</note> Hardly had they taken two or three turns, when in stepped Cleinias, who you say has come on so much, and you are right: behind him was a whole troop of lovers, and among them Ctesippus, a young fellow from Paeania, of gentle birth and breeding, except for a certain insolence of youth. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="273b"/>So when Cleinias as he entered caught sight of me sitting there alone, he came straight across and sat beside me on my right, just as you say. Dionysodorus and Euthydemus, when they saw him, stood at first talking with each other, and casting an occasional glance at us—for my attention was fixed on them—but then one of them, Euthydemus, took a seat by the youth, and the other next to me on my left; the rest, where each happened to find one. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="273c"/> So I greeted the two brothers, as not having seen them for some time; after that I said to Cleinias: My dear Cleinias, these two men, you know, are skilled not in little things, but in great. For they understand all about war, that is, as much as is needful for him who is to be a good general; both the tactics and the strategy of armies, and all the teaching of troops under arms; and they can also enable one to get redress in the law courts for a wrong that one may have suffered. 
					<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When I had said this, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="273d"/>I saw they despised me for it, and they both laughed, looking at each other; then Euthydemus said: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">No, no, Socrates, we do not make those matters our business now; we deal with them as diversions.</said> 
					<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this I wondered and said: Your business must be a fine one, if such great matters are indeed diversions to you; so I beseech you, tell me what this fine business is. 
					<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Virtue, Socrates</said>, he replied, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">is what we deem ourselves able to purvey in a pre-eminently excellent and speedy manner.</said> 
					<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="273e"/> 
					<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Good heavens, I exclaimed, a mighty affair indeed! Where did you have the luck to pick it up? I was still considering you, as I remarked just now, to be chiefly skilled in fighting under arms, and so spoke of you in those terms: for when you visited, our city before, this, I recollect, was the profession you made.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="274">
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But if you now in truth possess this other knowledge, have mercy—you see I address you just as though you were a couple of gods, beseeching you to forgive my former remarks. 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="274"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="274a"/>But make sure, Euthydemus and Dionysodorus, that you spoke the truth: for the vastness of your promise gives me some excuse for disbelieving.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus #Dionysodorus">You may be sure, Socrates,</said> they replied, <said who="#Euthydemus #Dionysodorus">it is as we say.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then I congratulate you on your acquisition far more than I do the great king on his empire: only tell me whether you intend to exhibit this science of yours, or what you have determined to do.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus #Dionysodorus">We are here for the very purpose, Socrates, of exhibiting <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="274b"/>and expounding it to anyone who wishes to learn.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, I guarantee that all who do not possess it will wish to—myself to begin with, then Cleinias here and, besides us, Ctesippus and all these others, I said, showing him the lovers of Cleinias, who were by this time standing about us. For Ctesippus, as it happened, was sitting some way from Cleinias, I noticed; and by chance, as Euthydemus leant forward <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="274c"/>in talking to me he obscured Ctesipus’ view of Cleinias, who was between us. Then Ctesippus, desiring to gaze on his favorite and being also an eager listener, led the way by jumping up and placing himself opposite us; and this made the others, on seeing what he did, stand around us, both Cleinias’ lovers and the followers of Euthydemus and Dionysodorus. Pointing to these, I told Euthydemus that they were all ready to learn; to which Ctesippus assented with great eagerness, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="274d"/>and so did the rest; and they all joined in urging the two men to exhibit the power of their wisdom.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On this I remarked: My good Euthydemus and Dionysodorus, you must do your very best to gratify my friends and, for my sake also, to give us an exhibition. To do it in full, of course, would obviously be a lengthy performance: but tell me one thing—will you be able to make a good man of him only who is already convinced that he should learn of you, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="274e"/>or of him also who is not yet so convinced, owing to an absolute disbelief that virtue is a thing that can be learnt or that you are teachers of it? Come now, is it the business of this same art to persuade such a man that virtue is teachable and that you are the men of whom one may best learn it, or does this need some other art?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">No, this same one can do it, Socrates,</said> said Dionysodorus.</p></said></div>
						
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="275">
<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>


<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then you two, Dionysodorus, I said, would be the best persons now on earth to incite one to the pursuit of knowledge 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="275"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="275a"/>and the practice of virtue?

	<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">We think so, at least, Socrates.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then, please defer the display of all the rest to some other occasion, I said, and exhibit this one thing. You are to persuade this young fellow here that he ought to ensue wisdom and practise virtue, and so you will oblige both me and all these present. This youth happens to be in just the sort of condition I speak of; and I and all of us here are at this moment anxious for him to become as good as possible. He is the son of Axiochus, son of the former Alcibiades,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. the famous Alcibiades, who died in <date when="-0404">404</date> B.C. at the age of 44. The supposed time of this discussion must be a year or two before Socrates’ death (<date when="-0399">399</date> B.C.).</note> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="275b"/> and is own cousin to the Alcibiades that now is: his name is Cleinias. He is young; and so we have fears for him, as well one may for a young man, lest someone forestall us and turn his inclination to some other course of life, and so corrupt him. Hence your arrival now is most happy. Come now, if it is all the same to you, make trial of the lad and talk with him in our presence.

	<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When I had thus spoken, in almost these very words, Euthydemus answered in a tone both manly and dashing: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Oh, it is all the same to us, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="275c"/>Socrates, provided the youth is willing to answer us.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Why, in fact, I said, that is just what he is used to: these people here are constantly coming to him and asking him a number of questions and debating with him, so he is a fairly fearless answerer.

	<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What ensued, Crito, how am I to relate in proper style? For no slight matter it is to be able to recall in description such enormous knowledge as theirs. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="275d"/>Consequently, like the poets, I must needs begin my narrative with an invocation of the Muses and Memory. Well, Euthydemus set to work, so far as I remember, in terms very much the same as these: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Cleinias, which sort of men are the learners, the wise or the foolish?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this the young man, feeling the embarrassment of the question, blushed and glanced at me in his helplessness. So I, perceiving his confusion, said: Have no fear, Cleinias; answer bravely, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="275e"/>whichever you think it is: for perchance he is doing you the greatest service in the world.

	<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Meanwhile Dionysodorus leant over a little to me, with a broad smile on his face, and whispered in my ear: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Let me tell you, Socrates, beforehand that, whichever way the lad answers, he will be confuted.</said></p></said></div>
	
	<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="276"> 
		<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p> 

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>While he was saying this, Cleinias made his reply, so that I was unable even to advise 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="276"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="276a"/>the boy to be wary: he replied that it was the wise who were the learners.

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Euthydemus asked: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And are there persons whom you call teachers, or not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed that there were.

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And the teachers of the learners are teachers in the same way as your lute-master and your writing-master, I suppose, were teachers of you and the other boys, while you were pupils?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He assented.

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Now, of course, when you were learning, you did not yet know the things you were learning?</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="276b"/> 
			
			<milestone unit="para" ed="P"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">No,</said> he said.

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">So were you wise, when you did not know those things?</said>

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">No, to be sure, he said.</said>

				<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then if not wise, foolish?</said>

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Certainly.</said>

					<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">So when you learnt what you did not know, you learnt while being foolish.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To this the lad nodded assent.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Hence it is the foolish who learn, Cleinias, and not the wise, as you suppose.</said>

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When he had thus spoken, all those followers of Dionysodorus <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="276c"/>and Euthydemus raised a cheer and a laugh, like a chorus at the signal of their director; and before the boy could fairly and fully recover his breath Dionysodorus took up the cudgels and said: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well now, Cleinias, whenever your writing-master dictated from memory, which of the boys learnt the piece recited, the wise or the foolish?</said>

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">The wise,</said> said Cleinias.

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">So it is the wise who learn, and not the foolish: hence the answer you gave just now to Euthydemus was a bad one.</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="276d"/> 
				
			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Thereupon arose a great deal of laughter and loud applause from the pair’s adorers, in admiration of their cleverness; while we on our side were dismayed and held our peace. Then Euthydemus, observing our dismay, and seeking to astonish us still further, would not let the boy go, but went on questioning him and, like a skilful dancer, gave a twofold twist to his questions on the same point: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Now, do the learners learn what they know, he asked, or what they do not?</said>

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Dionysodorus whispered to me again softly: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="276e"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Here comes a second one, Socrates, just like the first.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Heavens! I replied: surely the first question served you well enough.

			<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">All our questions, Socrates, he said, are like that; they leave no escape.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And consequently, as it seems to me, I remarked, you have this high repute among your disciples.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="277"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p> 
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Meanwhile Cleinias answered Euthydemus, that learners learnt what they did not know; so he had to meet the same course of questions as before: 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="277"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="277a"/>
<said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Well then, asked the other, do you not know your letters?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Yes,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">All of them?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He admitted it.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Now when anyone dictates some piece or other, does he not dictate letters?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He admitted it.
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And he dictates things of which you know something, since you know all of them?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He admitted this too.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Well now,</said> said the other, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">surely you do not learn whatever such a person dictates; it is rather he who does not know his letters that learns?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">No,</said> he replied; <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I learn.</said>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then you learn what you know, since you know all your letters.</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="277b"/> 
						
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">So your answer was not correct,</said> he said.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The last word was hardly out of Euthydemus’ mouth when Dionysodorus caught, as it were, the ball of the argument and, aiming at the boy again, said: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Euthydemus is deceiving you, Cleinias. Tell me, is not learning the reception of knowledge of that which one learns?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Cleinias agreed.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And is not knowing, he went on, just having knowledge at the time?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He assented.

							<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">So that not knowing <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="277c"/>is not yet having knowledge?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed with him.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then are those who receive anything those who have it already, or those who have it not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Those who have it not.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And you have admitted that those who do not know belong also to this class of those who have it not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He nodded assent.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And the learners belong to the class of the receiving and not to that of the having?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

							<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Hence it is those who do not know that learn, Cleinias, and not those who know.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Euthydemus was proceeding to press the youth for the third fall, when I, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="277d"/>perceiving the lad was going under, and wishing to give him some breathing-space lest he should shame us by losing heart, encouraged him with these words: Cleinias, do not be surprised that these arguments seem strange to you; for perhaps you do not discern what our two visitors are doing to you. They are acting just like the celebrants of the Corybantic rites, when they perform the enthronement of the person whom they are about to initiate. There, as you know, if you have been through it, they have dancing and merrymaking: so here these two <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="277e"/>are merely dancing about you and performing their sportive gambols with a view to your subsequent initiation. You must now, accordingly, suppose you are listening to the first part of the professorial mysteries.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="278"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p> First of all, as Prodicus says, you have to learn about the correct use of words—the very point that our two visitors are making plain to you, namely, that you were unaware that learning is the name which people apply on the one hand to the case of a man who, having originally no knowledge about some matter, in course of time receives such knowledge; 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="278"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="278a"/>and on the other hand the same word is applied when, having the knowledge already, he uses that knowledge for the investigation of the same matter whether occurring in action or in speech. It is true that they tend rather to call it <q type="emph">understanding</q> than <q type="emph">learning</q>, but occasionally they call it learning too; and this point, as our friends are demonstrating, has escaped your notice—how the same word is used for people who are in the opposite conditions of knowing and not knowing. A similar point underlay the second question, where they asked you <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="278b"/>whether people learn what they know, or what they do not. Such things are the sport of the sciences—and that is why I tell you these men are making game of you; I call it sport because, although one were to learn many or even all of such tricks, one would be not a whit the wiser as to the true state of the matters in hand, but only able to make game of people, thanks to the difference in the sense of the words, by tripping them up and overturning them; just as those who slyly pull stools away from persons who are about to sit down <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="278c"/>make merry and laugh when they see one sprawling on one’s back. So far, then, you are to regard these gentlemen’s treatment of you as mere play: but after this they will doubtless display to you their own serious object, while I shall keep them on the track and see that they fulfil the promise they gave me. They said they would exhibit their skill in exhortation; but instead, I conceive, they thought fit to make sport with you first. So now, Euthydemus and Dionysodorus, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="278d"/>let us have done with your sport: I daresay you have had as much as you want. What you have next to do is to give us a display of exhorting this youth as to how he should devote himself to wisdom and virtue. But first I shall explain to you how I regard this matter and how I desire to hear it dealt with. If I strike you as treating it in a crude and ridiculous manner, do not laugh me to scorn; for in my eagerness <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="278e"/>to listen to your wisdom I shall venture to improvise in your presence. So both you and your disciples must restrain yourselves and listen without laughing; and you, son of Axiochus, answer me this:

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Do all we human beings wish to prosper? Or is this question one of the absurdities I was afraid of just now? For I suppose it is stupid merely to ask such things, since every man must wish to prosper.</p></said></div> 

				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="279"> 
						<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="279"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="279a"/>
					
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Everyone in the world, said Cleinias.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then, I asked, as to the next step, since we wish to prosper, how can we prosper? Will it be if we have many good things? Or is this an even sillier question than the other? For surely this too must obviously be so.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Come now, of things that are, what sort do we hold to be really good? Or does it appear to be no difficult matter, and no problem for an important person, to find here too a ready answer? Anyone will tell us that to be rich is good, surely?

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Quite true,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then it is the same with being healthy and handsome, and having the other bodily endowments <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="279b"/>in plenty?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Again, it is surely clear that good birth and talents and distinctions in one’s own country are good things.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He admitted it.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then what have we still remaining, I asked, in the class of goods? What of being temperate, and just, and brave? I bay you tell me, Cleinias, do you think we shall be right in ranking these as goods, or in rejecting them? For it may be that someone will dispute it. How does it strike you?

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">They are goods,</said> said Cleinias.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Very well, I went on, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="279c"/>and where in the troupe shall we station wisdom? Among the goods, or how?

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Among the goods.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then take heed that we do not pass over any of the goods that may deserve mention.

							<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I do not think we are leaving any out,</said> said Cleinias.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hereupon I recollected one and said: Yes, by Heaven, we are on the verge of omitting the greatest of the goods.

								<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">What is that?</said> he asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Good fortune, Cleinias: a thing which all men, even the worst fools, refer to as the greatest of goods.

									<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">You are right,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Once again I reconsidered and said: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="279d"/>We have almost made ourselves laughing-stocks, you and I, son of Axiochus, for our visitors.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">What is wrong now?</said> he asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Why, after putting good fortune in our former list, we have just been discussing the same thing again.

							<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">What is the point?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Surely it is ridiculous, when a thing has been before us all the time, to set it forth again and go over the same ground twice.

								<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">To what are you referring?</said> he asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Wisdom, I replied, is presumably good fortune: even a child could see that.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He wondered at this—he is still so young and simple-minded: then I, perceiving his surprise, went on: Can you be unaware, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="279e"/>Cleinias, that for success in flute-music it is the flute-players that have the best fortune?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed to this.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then in writing and reading letters it will be the schoolmasters.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="grc">γραμματισταί</foreign> were the schoolmasters who taught reading and writing and explained the difficulties of Homer in primary education.</note>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Certainly.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well now, for the dangers of a sea-voyage, do you consider any pilots to he more fortunate, as a general rule, than the wise ones?

							<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">No, to be sure.</said></p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="280"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, then, suppose you were on a campaign, with which kind of general would you prefer to share both the peril and the luck—a wise one, or an ignorant?

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">With a wise one.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then, supposing you were sick, with which kind of doctor would you like to venture yourself a wise one, or an ignorant?

							<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">With a wise one.</said> 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="280"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="280a"/> 
						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And your reason, I said, is this, that you would fare with better fortune in the hands of a wise one than of an ignorant one?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He assented.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So that wisdom everywhere causes men to be fortunate: since I presume she could never err, but must needs be right in act and result; otherwise she could be no longer wisdom.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>We came to an agreement somehow or other <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="280b"/>in the end that the truth in general was this: when wisdom is present, he with whom it is present has no need of good fortune as well; and as we had agreed on this I began to inquire of him over again what we should think, in this case, of our previous agreements. For we agreed, said I, that if many goods were present to us we should be happy and prosper.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Yes,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then would we be happy because of our present goods, if they gave us no benefit, or if they gave us some?

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">If they gave us benefit,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And would a thing benefit us if we merely had it <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="280c"/>and did not use it? For instance, if we had a lot of provisions, but did not eat them, or liquor, and did not drink it, could we be said to be benefited?

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Of course not,</said> he answered.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then, if every craftsman found the requisites for his particular work all ready prepared for him, and then made no use of them, would he prosper because of these acquisitions, as having acquired all the things necessary for a craftsman to have at hand? For example, if a carpenter were furnished with all his tools and a good supply of wood, but did no carpentry, is it possible he could be benefited <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="280d"/>by what he had got?

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">By no means,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well now, suppose a man had got wealth and all the goods that we mentioned just now, but made no use of them; would he be happy because of his possessing these goods?

							<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Surely not, Socrates.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So it seems one must not merely have acquired such goods if one is to be happy, but use them too; else there is no benefit gained from their possession.

								<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">True.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then have we here enough means, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="280e"/>Cleinias, for making a man happy—in the possession of these goods and using them?

									<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I think so.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Shall we say, I asked, if he uses them rightly, or just as much if he does not?

										<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">If rightly.</said></p></said></div>
						
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="281"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well answered, I said; for I suppose there is more mischief when a man uses anything wrongly than when he lets it alone. In the one case there is evil; in the other there is neither evil 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="281"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="281a"/>nor good. May we not state it so?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To proceed then: in the working and use connected with wood, is there anything else that effects the right use than the knowledge of carpentry? 
						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Surely not,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Further, I presume that in the working connected with furniture it is knowledge that effects the right work.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Yes,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then similarly, I went on, in the use of the goods we mentioned at first—wealth and health and beauty—was it knowledge that showed the way to the right use of all those advantages <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="281b"/>and rectified their conduct, or was it something else?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Knowledge,</said> he replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So that knowledge, it would seem, supplies mankind not only with good luck, but with welfare, in all that he either possesses or conducts.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then can we, in Heaven’s name, get any benefit from all the other possessions without understanding and wisdom? Shall we say that a man will profit more by possessing much and doing much when he has no sense, than he will if he does and possesses little? Consider it this way: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="281c"/>would he not err less if he did less; and so, erring less, do less ill; and hence, doing less ill, be less miserable?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In which of the two cases, when one is poor or when one is rich, will one be more likely to do less?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">When one is poor,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And when one is weak, or when one is strong?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Weak.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And when one has high position, or has none?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">None.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When one is brave and self-controlled, will one do less, or when one is a coward?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">A coward.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So too, when idle rather than busy?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And slow rather than quick, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="281d"/>and dim of sight and hearing rather than sharp?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>We agreed with each other as to these and all such cases.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To sum up then, Cleinias, I proceeded, it seems that, as regards the whole lot of things which at first we termed goods, the discussion they demand is not on the question of how they are in themselves and by nature goods, but rather, I conceive, as follows: if they are guided by ignorance, they are greater evils than their opposites, according as they are more capable of ministering to their evil guide; whereas if understanding and wisdom guide them, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="281e"/>they are greater goods; but in themselves neither sort is of any worth.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I think the case appears,</said> he replied, <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">to be as you suggest.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now what result do we get from our statements? Is it not precisely that, of all the other things, not one is either good or bad, but of these two, wisdom is good and ignorance bad? 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="282"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="282a"/> He agreed.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="282"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Let us consider then, I said, the further conclusion that lies before us. Since we are all eager to be happy, and since we were found to become so by not only using things but using them aright, while knowledge, we saw, was that which provided the rightness and good fortune, it seems that every man must prepare himself by all available means so that he may be as wise as possible. Is it not so?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Yes,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And if a man thinks, as well he may, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="282b"/>that he ought to get this endowment from his father much more than money, and also from his guardians and his ordinary friends, and from those who profess to be his lovers, whether strangers or fellow-citizens—praying and beseeching them to give him his share of wisdom; there is no disgrace, Cleinias, or reprobation in making this a reason for serving and being a slave to either one’s lover or any man, and being ready to perform any service that is honorable in one’s eagerness to become wise. Is not this your view? I asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I think you are <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="282c"/>perfectly right,</said> he replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, Cleinias, I went on, if wisdom is teachable, and does not present itself to mankind of its own accord—for this is a question that we have still to consider as not yet agreed on by you and me.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">For my part, Socrates,</said> he said, <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I think it is teachable.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this I was glad, and said: Well spoken indeed, my excellent friend! How good of you to relieve me of a long inquiry into this very point, whether wisdom is teachable or not teachable! So now, since you think it is both teachable and <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="282d"/>the only thing in the world that makes man happy and fortunate, can you help saying that it is necessary to pursue wisdom or intending to pursue it yourself?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Why,</said> said he, <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I do say so, Socrates, with all my might.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So I, delighted to hear this, said: There, Dionysodorus and Euthydemus, is my illustration of what I desire a hortatory argument to be—rough and ready, perhaps, and expressed at laborious length: now let either of you who wishes to do so give us an example of an artist’s handling of this same matter. If you do not wish to do that, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="282e"/>let your display begin where I left off, and show the lad whether he ought to acquire every kind of knowledge, or whether there is a single sort of it which one must obtain if one is to be both happy and a good man, and what it is. For as I was saying at the outset, it really is a matter of great moment to us that this youth should become 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="283"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="283a"/>wise and good.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="283"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>These were my words, Crito; and I set about giving the closest attention to what should follow, and observing in what fashion they would deal with the question, and how they would start exhorting the youth to practise wisdom and virtue. So then the elder of them, Dionysodorus, entered first upon the discussion, and we all turned our eyes on him expecting to hear, there and then, some wonderful arguments. And this result we certainly got; <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="283b"/>for wondrous, in a way, Crito, was the argument that the man then ushered forth, which is worth your hearing as a notable incitement to virtue.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Tell me, Socrates,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">and all you others who say you desire this youth to become wise, whether you say this in jest or truly and earnestly desire it.
</said>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this I reflected that previously, as it seemed, they took us to be jesting, when we urged them to converse with the youth, and hence they made a jest of it <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="283c"/>and did not take it seriously. This reflection therefore made me insist all the more that we were in deadly earnest.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Dionysodorus said: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Yet be careful, Socrates, that you do not have to deny what you say now.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I know what I am about, I said: I know I shall never deny it.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well now,</said> he proceeded; <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">you tell me you wish him to become wise?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Certainly.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And at present,</said> he asked, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">is Cleinias wise or not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He says he is not yet so—he is no vain pretender.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And you,</said> he went on, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="283d"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">wish him to become wise, and not to be ignorant?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>We agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">So you wish him to become what he is not, and to be no longer what he now is.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When I heard this I was confused; and he, striking in on my confusion, said: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Of course then, since you wish him to be no longer what he now is, you wish him, apparently, to be dead. And yet what valuable friends and lovers they must be, who would give anything to know their darling was dead and gone!</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="283e"/> 
						
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Ctesippus, on hearing this, was annoyed on his favorite’s account, and said: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Stranger of <placeName key="perseus,Thurii">Thurii</placeName>, were it not rather a rude thing to say, I should tell you, ill betide your design of speaking so falsely of me and my friends as to make out—what to me is almost too profane even to repeat—that I could wish this boy to be dead and gone!</said></p></said></div>
						
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="284"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>	
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Why, Ctesippus,</said> said Euthydemus, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">do you think it possible to lie?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">To be sure, I do,</said> he replied: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">I should be mad otherwise.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Do you mean, when one tells the thing about which 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="284"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="284a"/>one is telling, or when one does not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">When one tells it,</said> he said.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then if you tell it, you tell just that thing which you tell, of all that are, and nothing else whatever?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Of course,</said> said Ctesippus.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Now the thing that you tell is a single one, distinct from all the others there are.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Certainly.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then the person who tells that thing tells that which is?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">But yet, surely he who tells what is, and things that are, tells the truth: so that Dionysodorus, if he tells things that are, tells the truth and speaks no lie about you.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes,</said> said Ctesippus; <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="284b"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">but he who speaks as he did, Euthydemus, does not say things that are.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Euthydemus asked him: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And the things which are not, surely are not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">They are not.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then nowhere can the things that are not be?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Nowhere.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then is it possible for anyone whatever so to deal with these things that are not as to make them be when they are nowhere?
</said>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">I think not,</said> said Ctesippus.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Well now, when orators speak before the people, do they do nothing?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">No, they do something,</said> he replied.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then if they do, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="284c"/>they also make?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Now, is speaking doing and making?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed that it is.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">No one, I suppose, speaks what is not—for thereby he would be making something; and you have agreed that one cannot so much as make what is not—so that, by your account, no one speaks what is false, while if Dionysodorus speaks, he speaks what is true and is.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes, in faith, Euthydemus,</said> said Ctesippus; <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">but somehow or other he speaks what is, only not as it is.</said><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The quibbling throughout this passage is a willful confusion of the two very different uses of the verb <q type="emph">to be</q> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">εἶναι</foreign>), (a) in predication, where it has nothing to do with existence, and (b) by itself, as stating existence.</note>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">How do you mean, Ctesippus?</said> said Dionysodorus. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="284d"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Are there persons who tell things as they are?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Why surely,</said> he replied, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">there are gentlemen—people who speak the truth?</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well,</said> <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">he went on, good things are in good case, bad in bad, are they not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He assented.

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And you admit that gentlemen tell things as they are.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">I do.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then, Ctesippus, good people speak evil of evil things, if they speak of them as they are.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes, I can tell you, very much so, when for instance they speak of evil men; among whom, if you take my advice, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="284e"/>you will beware of being included, that the good may not speak ill of you. For, I assure you, the good speak ill<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Euthydemus seizes on the ambiguous use of <foreign xml:lang="grc">κακῶς</foreign> which may mean either <gloss>badly</gloss> or <gloss>injuriously.</gloss></note> of the evil.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And they speak greatly of the great,</said> asked Euthydemus, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">and hotly of the hot?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Certainly, I presume,</said> said Ctesippus: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">I know they speak frigidly of the frigid, and call their way of arguing frigid.</said>

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">You are turning abusive, Ctesippus,</said> said Dionysodorus, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">quite abusive!</said></p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="285"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Not I, on my soul, Dionysodorus, for I like you: I am only giving you a friendly hint, and endeavoring to persuade you never to say anything so tactless in my presence as 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="285"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="285a"/>that I wish these my most highly valued friends to be dead and gone.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So then I, observing that they were getting rather savage with each other, began to poke fun. at Ctesippus, saying: Ctesippus, my feeling is that we ought to accept from our visitors what they tell us, if they are so good as to give it, and should not quarrel over a word. For if they understand how to do away with people in such sort as to change them from wicked and witless to honest and intelligent, and that too whether they have discovered for themselves <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="285b"/>or learnt from somebody else this peculiar kind of destruction or undoing, which enables them to destroy a man in his wickedness and set him up again in honesty; if they understand this—and obviously they do; you know they said that their newly discovered art was to turn wicked men into good—let us then accord them this power; let them destroy the lad for us, and make him sensible, and all the rest of us likewise. If you young fellows are afraid, let the experiment be made on me <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="285c"/>as a <q type="foreign">corpus vile</q><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Lit. <gloss>a Carian slave.</gloss></note>; for I, being an elderly person, am ready to take the risk and put myself in the hands of Dionysodorus here, as if he were the famous Medea of <placeName key="tgn,7016642">Colchis</placeName>. Let him destroy me, and if he likes let him boil me down, or do to me whatever he pleases: only he must make me good.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Ctesippus said: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">I too, Socrates, am ready to offer myself to be skinned by the strangers even more, if they choose, than they are doing now, if my hide <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="285d"/>is not to end by being made into a wine-skin, like that of Marsyas,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This satyr was fabled to have challenged Apollo to a musical contest, and on his fluting being judged inferior to Apollo’s harping he was flayed alive by the god for his presumption, and his skin was hung up like a bag or bottle in a cave; cf. Herod. vii. 26.</note> but into the shape of virtue. And yet Dionysodorus here believes I am vexed with him. I am not vexed at all; I only contradict the remarks which I think he has improperly aimed at me. Come now, my generous Dionysodorus, do not call contradiction abuse: abuse is quite another thing.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On this Dionysodorus said: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">As though there were such a thing as contradiction! Is that the way you argue, Ctesippus?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes, to be sure,</said> he replied, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">indeed I do; and do you, Dionysodorus, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="285e"/>hold that there is not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well, you at any rate,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">could not prove that you had ever heard a single person contradicting another.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Is that so?</said> he replied: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">well, let us hear now whether I can prove a case of it—Ctesippus contradicting Dionysodorus.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Now, will you make that good?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="286"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
				

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well then,</said> proceeded the other, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">each thing that is has its own description?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Certainly.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then do you mean, 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="286"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="286a"/>as each is, or as it is not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">As it is.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Yes,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">for if you recollect, Ctesippus, we showed just now that no one speaks of a thing as it is not; since we saw that no one speaks what is not.
</said>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Well, what of that?</said> asked Ctesippus: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">are you and I contradicting any the less?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Now tell me,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">could we contradict if we both spoke the description of the same thing? In this case should we not surely speak the same words?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">But when neither of us speaks the description of the thing,</said> he asked, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="286b"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">then we should contradict? Or in this case shall we say that neither of us touched on the matter at all?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This also he admitted.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well now, when I for my part speak the description of the thing, while you give another of another thing, do we contradict then? Or do I describe the thing, while you do not describe it at all? How can he who does not describe contradict him who does?</said><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The argument is that, if we cannot speak what is not, or falsely, of a thing (this assumption being based on the old confusion of being with existence), there can be only one description of a thing in any given relation, and so there is no room for contradiction. This argument is commonly ascribed to Anthisthenes, the founder of the Cynic sect and opponent of Plato. It is not clear who exactly are meant by <q type="mentioned">the followers of Protagoras</q> or the <q type="mentioned">others before his time.</q></note>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this Ctesippus was silent; but I, wondering at the argument, said: How do you mean, Dionysodorus? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="286c"/>For, to be plain with you, this argument, though I have heard it from many people on various occasions, never fails to set me wondering—you know the followers of Protagoras made great use of it, as did others even before his time, but to me it always seems to have a wonderful way of upsetting not merely other views but itself also—and I believe I shall learn the truth of it from you far better than from anyone else. There is no such thing as speaking false—that is the substance of your statement, is it not? Either one must speak and speak the truth, or else not speak?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="286d"/> 
						
<milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Then shall we say that speaking false <q type="emph">is not,</q> but thinking false <q type="emph">is</q>?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">No, it is the same with thinking,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So neither is there any false opinion, I said, at all.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">No,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Nor ignorance, nor ignorant men; or must not ignorance occur, if it ever can, when we put things falsely?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But there is no such thing as this, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">No,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Is it merely to save your statement, Dionysodorus, that you state it so—just to say something startling—or is it really and truly your view that there is no such thing as an ignorant man? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="286e"/> 
						
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">But you,</said> he replied, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">are to refute me.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, does your argument allow of such a thing as refutation, if there is nobody to speak false?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">There is no such thing,</said> said Euthydemus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So neither did Dionysodorus just now bid me refute him? I asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">No, for how can one bid something that is not? Do you bid such a thing?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, Euthydemus, I said, it is because I do not at all understand these clever devices and palpable hits: I am only a dull sort of thinker. And so I may perhaps be going to say something rather clownish; but you must forgive me.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="287"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Here it is: 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="287"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="287a"/>if there is no such thing as speaking false or thinking false or being stupid, surely there can be no making a mistake either, when one does something. For in doing it there is no mistaking the thing that is done. You will state it so, will you not?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>My clownish question, I went on, is now already before you. If we make no mistake either in doing or saying or intending, I ask you what in Heaven’s name, on that assumption, is the subject you two set up to teach. Or did you not say just now that your speciality was to put any man who wished <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="287b"/>in the way of learning virtue?

						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Now really, Socrates,</said> interposed Dionysodorus, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">are you such an old dotard as to recollect now what we said at first, and will you now recollect what I may have said last year, and yet be at a loss how to deal with the arguments urged at the moment?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, you see, I replied, they are so very hard, and naturally so; for they fall from the lips of wise men; and this is further shown by the extreme difficulty of dealing with this last one you put forward. For what on earth do you mean, Dionysodorus, by saying I am at a loss how to deal with it? Or is it clear that <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="287c"/>you mean I am at a loss how to refute it? You must tell me what else your phrase can intend, <q type="mentioned">at a loss how to deal with the arguments</q>.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">But it is not so very hard to deal with that phrase<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. <foreign xml:lang="grc">νοεῖ</foreign>, <gloss>intend.</gloss></note> of yours,</said> he said. <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Just answer me.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Before you answer me, Dionysodorus? I protested.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">You refuse to answer?</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Is it fair?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Oh yes, it is fair enough,</said> he replied

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On what principle? I asked: or is it plainly on this one—that you present yourself to us at this moment as universally skilled in discussion, and thus can tell when an answer is to be given, and when not? So now you will not answer a word, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="287d"/>because you discern that you ought not to.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">What nonsense you talk, he said, instead of answering as you should. Come, good sir, do as I bid you and answer, since you confess to my wisdom.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then, I must obey, I said, and of necessity, it seems; for you are the master here. Now for your question.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then tell me, do things that <q type="emph">intend</q> have life when they intend, or do lifeless things do it too?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Only those that have life.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Now do you know any phrase that has life?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Upon my soul, I do not. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="287e"/> 
						
<milestone unit="para" ed="P"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Why then did you ask just now what my phrase intended?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Of course I made a great mistake, I said: I am such a dullard. Or perhaps it was not a mistake, and I was right in saying what I did, that phrases intend. Do you say I was mistaken or not?</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="288"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						If I was not, then you will not refute me, with all your skill, and you are at a loss how to deal with the argument; while if I was mistaken, you are in the wrong there, too, 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="288"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="288a"/>for you assert that there is no such thing as making a mistake; and what I say is not aimed at what you said last year. But it seems, I went on, Dionysodorus and Euthydemus, that our argument remains just where it was, and still suffers from the old trouble of knocking others down and then falling itself, and even your art has not yet discovered a way of avoiding this failure—in spite, too, of the wonderful show it makes of accurate reasoning.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Here Ctesippus exclaimed: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes, your way of discussion is marvellous, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="288b"/>you men of <placeName key="perseus,Thurii">Thurii</placeName> or <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. above, <bibl n="Plat. Euthyd. 271c">Plat. Euthyd. 271c</bibl>.</note> or wherever or however it is you are pleased to get your names; for you have no scruple about babbling like fools.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this I was afraid we might hear some abuse, so I soothed Ctesippus down once more, saying: Ctesippus, I repeat to you what I said to Cleinias just now, that you do not perceive the wonderful nature of our visitors’ skill. Only they are unwilling to give us a display of it in real earnest, but treat us to jugglers’ tricks in the style of Proteus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Hom. Od. 4.385">Hom. Od. 4.385 ff</bibl>. Proteus was an ancient seer of the sea who, if one could catch him as he slept on the shore and hold him fast while he transformed himself into a variety of creatures, would tell one the intentions of the gods, the fate of absent friends, etc.</note> the Egyptian adept. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="288c"/>So let us take our cue from Menelaus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Hom. Od. 4.456">Hom. Od. 4.456</bibl>.</note> and not leave hold of these gentlemen till they give us a sight of their own serious business. I believe something very fine will be found in them as soon as they begin to be serious. Come, let us beg and exhort and beseech them to let their light shine. For my part, then, I am minded to take the lead once more in showing what sort of persons I pray may be revealed in them: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="288d"/>starting from where I left off before, I shall try, as best I can, to describe what follows on from that, to see if I can rouse them to action and make them, in merciful commensuration of my earnest endeavor, be earnest themselves.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Will you, Cleinias, I asked, please remind me of the point at which we left off? Now, as far as I can tell, it was something like this: we ended by agreeing that one ought to pursue wisdom, did we not?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Euthyd. 282d">Plat. Euthyd. 282d</bibl>.</note>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Yes,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And this pursuit—called philosophy—is an acquiring of knowledge. Is it not so? I asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Yes,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then what knowledge should we acquire if we acquired it rightly? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="288e"/>Is it not absolutely clear that it must be that knowledge which will profit us?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now will it profit us at all, if we know how to tell, as we go about, where the earth has most gold buried in it?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Perhaps,</said> he said.</p></said></div>
				
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="289"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But yet, I went on, we refuted that former proposition, agreeing that even if without any trouble or digging the earth we got all the gold in the world, we should gain nothing, so that not if we knew how 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="289"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="289a"/>to turn the rocks into gold would our knowledge be of any worth. For unless we know how to use the gold, we found no advantage in it. Do you not remember? I asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Certainly I do,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Nor, it seems, do we get any advantage from all other knowledge, whether of money-making or medicine or any other that knows how to make things, without knowing how to use the thing made. Is it not so?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Nor again, if there is a knowledge <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="289b"/>enabling one to make men immortal, does this, if we lack the knowledge how to use immortality, seem to bring any advantage either, if we are to infer anything from our previous admissions.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On all these points we agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then the sort of knowledge we require, fair youth, I said, is that in which there happens to be a union of making and knowing how to use the thing made.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">Apparently,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So we ought, it seems, to aim at something far other than being lyre-makers <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="289c"/>or possessing that kind of knowledge. For in this case the art that makes and the art that uses are quite distinct, dealing in separation with the same thing; since there is a wide difference between the art of making lyres and that of harp-playing. Is it not so?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He agreed.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Nor again, obviously, do we require an art of flute-making; for this is another of the same kind.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He assented.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now in good earnest, I asked, if we were to learn the art of speech-making, can that be the art we should acquire if we would be happy?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I for one think not,</said> said Cleinias, interposing. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="289d"/> 
						
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On what proof do you rely? I asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I see,</said> he said, <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">certain speech-writers who do not know how to use the special arguments composed by themselves, just as lyre-makers in regard to their lyres: in the former case also there are other persons able to use what the makers produced, while being themselves unable to make the written speech. Hence it is clear that in speech likewise there are two distinct arts, one of making and one of using.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I think you give sufficient proof, I said, that this art of the speech-writers cannot be that whose acquisition would make one happy. And yet I fancied that somewhere about this point would appear the knowledge which we have been seeking all this while. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="289e"/>For not only do these speech-writers themselves, when I am in their company, impress me as prodigiously clever, Cleinias, but their art itself seems so exalted as to be almost inspired. However, this is not surprising; for it is a part of the sorcerer’s art, 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="290"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="290a"/>and only slightly inferior to that.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="290"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>The sorcerer’s art is the charming of snakes and tarantulas and scorpions and other beasts and diseases, while the other is just the charming and soothing of juries, assemblies, crowds, and so forth. Or does it strike you differently? I asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">No, it appears to me,</said> he replied, <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">to be as you say.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Which way then, said I, shall we turn now? What kind of art shall we try?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">For my part,</said> he said, <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I have no suggestion.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Why, I think I have found it myself, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">What is it?</said> said Cleinias. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="290b"/> 
						
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Generalship, I replied, strikes me as the art whose acquisition above all others would make one happy.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">I do not think so.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Why not? I asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">In a sense, this is an art of hunting men.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What then? I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">No part of actual hunting,</said> he replied, <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">covers more than the province of chasing and overcoming; and when they have overcome the creature they are chasing, they are unable to use it: the huntsmen or the fishermen hand it over to the caterers, and so it is too with the geometers, astronomers, and calculators— <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="290c"/>for these also are hunters in their way, since they are not in each case diagram-makers, but discover the realities of things<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. geometers etc. are not to be regarded as mere makers of diagrams, these being only the necessary and common machinery for their real business, the discovery of mathematical and other abstract truths.</note>—and so, not knowing how to use their prey, but only how to hunt, I take it they hand over their discoveries to the dialecticians to use properly, those of them, at least, who are not utter blockheads.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Very good, I said, most handsome and ingenious Cleinias; and is this really so?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">To be sure it is; and so, in the same way, with the generals. When they have hunted either a city or <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="290d"/>an army, they hand it over to the politicians—since they themselves do not know how to use what they have hunted—just as quail-hunters, I suppose, hand over their birds to the quail-keepers. If, therefore,</said> he went on, <said who="#Cleinias" direct="false">we are looking for that art which itself shall know how to use what it has acquired either in making or chasing, and if this is the sort that will make us blest, we must reject generalship, he said, and seek out some other.</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="290e"/></p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>What is this, Socrates? Such a pronouncement from that stripling!</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>You do not believe it is his, Crito?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>I should rather think not. For I am sure, if he spoke thus, he has no need of education from Euthydemus or anyone else.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But then, Heaven help me! I wonder if it was Ctesippus who said it, and my memory fails me.</p></said></div> 

				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="291"> 
						<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="291"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="291a"/>
					
					
<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Very like Ctesippus!</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well, of this at any rate I am certain, that it was neither Euthydemus nor Dionysodorus who said it. Tell me, mysterious Crito, was it some superior power that was there to speak it? For that speech I heard, I am sure.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Yes, I promise you, Socrates: I fancy it was indeed some superior power—very much so. But after that, did you go on looking for a suitable art? Did you find the one which you had as the object of your search, or not? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="291b"/></p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Find it, my good fellow! No, we were in a most ridiculous state; like children who run after crested larks, we kept on believing each moment we were just going to catch this or that one of the knowledges, while they as often slipped from our grasp. What need to tell you the story at length? When we reached the kingly art, and were examining it to see if we had here what provides and produces happiness, at this point we were involved in a labyrinth: when we supposed we had arrived at the end, we twisted about again <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="291c"/>and found ourselves practically at the beginning of our search, and just as sorely in want as when we first started on it.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>How did this happen to you, Socrates?</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>I will tell you. We took the view that the statesman’s and the monarch’s arts were one and the same.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Well, what then?</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>To this art, we thought, generalship and the other arts handed over the management of the productions of their own trades, as this one alone knew how to use them. So it seemed clear to us that this was the one we were seeking, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="291d"/>and was the cause of right conduct in the state, and precisely as Aeschylus’ line<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Aesch. Seven 2">Aesch. Seven 2</bibl> <quote>Whoso at helm of the state keeps watch upon affairs, guiding the tiller without resting his eyelids in sleep.</quote></note> expresses it, is seated alone at the helm of the city, steering the whole, commanding the whole, and making the whole useful.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>And surely your notion was a good one, Socrates?</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>You shall judge of that, Crito, if you care to hear what befell us thereafter. For later on we reconsidered it somewhat in this manner: Look now, does the monarch’s art, that rules over all, produce any effect <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="291e"/>or not? Certainly it does, of course, we said to one another. Would you not say so too, Crito?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>I would.</p></said></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="292"> 
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then what would you say is its effect? For instance, if I were to ask you whether medicine, in ruling over all that comes under its rule, has any effect to show; would you not say: Yes, health?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>I would.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And what about your art of agriculture? In ruling over all 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="292"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="292a"/>that comes under its rule, what effect does it produce? Would you not say that it supplies us with food from the earth?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>I would.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And what of the monarch’s art? In ruling over all that comes under its rule, what does it produce? Perhaps you are not quite ready with the answer.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>I am not indeed, Socrates.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Nor were we, Crito; yet so much you know, that if this is really the one we are seeking, it must be beneficial.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Certainly.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then surely it must purvey something good?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Necessarily, Socrates. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="292b"/></p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And you know we agreed with each other, Cleinias and I, that nothing can be good but some sort of knowledge.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Yes, so you told me.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And it was found that all effects in general that you may ascribe to statesmanship—and a great many of them there must be, presumably, if the citizens are to be made wealthy and free and immune from faction—all these things were neither bad nor good, while this art must make us wise and impart knowledge, if it really was to be the one which benefited us <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="292c"/>and made us happy.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>True: so at all events you agreed then, by your account of the discussion.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then do you think that kingship makes men wise and good?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Why not, Socrates?</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But does it make all men good, and in all things? And is this the art that confers every sort of knowledge—shoe-making and carpentry and so forth?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>No, I think not, Socrates. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="292d"/></p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well, what knowledge does it give ? What use can we make of it? It is not to be a producer of any of the effects which are neither bad nor good, while it is to confer no other knowledge but itself. Shall we try and say what it is, and what use we shall make of it? Do you mind if we describe it, Crito, as that whereby we shall make other men good?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>I quite agree.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And in what respect are we going to have these men good, and in what useful? Or shall we venture to say they are to make others so, and these again others? In what respect they can possibly be good is nowhere evident to us, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="292e"/>since we have discredited all the business commonly called politics, and it is merely a case of the proverbial <q type="soCalled">Corinthus Divine</q><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Pind. N. 7">Pind. N. 7</bibl>. <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>, a colony of <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, revolted, and when the Corinthians appealed to the sentiment attaching to <placeName key="tgn,7010734">Corinthus</placeName>, the mythical founder of <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>, the Megarians drove them off taunting them with using a <q type="emph">vain repetition.</q></note>; and, as I was saying, we are equally or even worse at fault as to what that knowledge can be which is to make us happy.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Upon my word, Socrates, you got yourselves there, it seems, into a pretty fix.</p></said></div>

				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="293"> 
				<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So then I myself, Crito, finding 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="293"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="293a"/>I had fallen into this perplexity, began to exclaim at the top of my voice, beseeching the two strangers as though I were calling upon the Heavenly Twins to save us, the lad and myself, from the mighty wave<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Lit. <gloss>the big wave that comes in every three.</gloss></note> of the argument, and to give us the best of their efforts, and this done, to make plain to us what that knowledge can be of which we must get hold if we are to spend the remainder of our lives in a proper way</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Well, did Euthydemus consent to propound anything for you?</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Why, certainly; and he began his discourse, my good friend, in this very lofty-minded fashion: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="293b"/> <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Would you rather, Socrates, that I instructed you as to this knowledge which has baffled you all this while, or propound that you have it?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>O gifted sir, I exclaimed, and have you the power to do this?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Certainly I have,</said> he replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then for Heaven’s sake, I cried, propound that I have it! This will be much easier than learning foraman of my age.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Come then, answer me this,</said> he said: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Do you know anything?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, indeed, I replied. and many things, though trifles.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">That is enough,</said> he said; <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">now do you think it possible that anything that is should not be just that which it actually is?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>On my soul, not I. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="293c"/> 
	
	<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Now you,</said> he said, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">know something?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I do.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then you are knowing, if you really know?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Certainly, in just that something.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">That makes no difference; you are not under a necessity of knowing everything, if you are knowing?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>No, to be sure, I replied; for there are many other things which I do not know.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then if you do not know something, you are not knowing?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Not in that thing, my dear sir, I replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Are you therefore any the less unknowing? Just now you said you were knowing; <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="293d"/>so here you are, actually the very man that you are, and again, not that man, in regard to the same matter and at the same time!</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Admitted, Euthydemus, I said: as the saying goes, <q type="spoken">well said whate’er you say.</q> How therefore do I know that knowledge which we were seeking? Since forsooth it is impossible for the same thing to be so and not be so; by knowing one thing I know all;—for I could not be at once both knowing and unknowing;—and as I know everything I have that knowledge to boot: is that your line of argument? Is this your wisdom? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="293e"/> 
	
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Yes, you see, Socrates,</said> he said, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">your own words refute you.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, but, Euthydemus, I continued, are you not in the same plight? I assure you, so long as I had you and this dear fellow Dionysodorus to share my lot, however hard, I should have nothing to complain of. Tell me, you both know some existent things, of course, and others you do not?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">By no means, Socrates,</said> said Dionysodorus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>How do you mean? I asked: do you then not know anything?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Oh yes, we do,</said> he said.</p></said></div> 

				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="294"> 
				<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="294"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="294a"/>
				<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So you know everything, I asked, since you know anything?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Everything,</said> he replied; <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">yes, and you too, if you know one thing, know all.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Good Heavens, I cried, what a wonderful statement! What a great blessing to boast of! And the rest of mankind, do they know everything or nothing?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Surely,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">they cannot know some things and not others, and so be at once knowing and unknowing.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But what then? I asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">All men,</said> he replied, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">know all things, if they know one.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In the name of goodness, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="294b"/>Dionysodorus, I said—for now I can see both of you are serious; before, I could hardly prevail on you to be so—do you yourselves really know everything? Carpentry, for instance, and shoe-making?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And you are good hands at leather-stitching?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Why yes, in faith, and cobbling,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And are you good also at such things as counting the stars, and the sand?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">can you think we would not admit that also?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Here Ctesippus broke in: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Be so good, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="294c"/>Dionysodorus, he said, as to place some such evidence before me as will convince me that what you say is true.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">What shall I put forward?</said> he asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Do you know how many teeth Euthydemus has, and does Euthydemus know how many you have?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Are you not content,</said> he rejoined, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">to be told that we know everything?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">No, do not say that,</said> he replied: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">only tell us this one thing more, and propound to us that you speak the truth. Then, if you tell us how many teeth each of you has, and you are found by our counting to have known it, we shall believe you thenceforth in everything else likewise.</said> 
					
					<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="294d"/> Well, as they supposed we were making fun of them, they would not do it: only they agreed that they knew all subjects, when questioned on them, one after the other, by Ctesippus; who, before he had done with them, asked them if they knew every kind of thing, even the most unseemly, without the least reserve; while they most valiantly encountered his questions, agreeing that they had the knowledge in each case, like boars when driven up to face the spears: so that I for my part, Crito, became quite incredulous,and had to ask in the end if Dionysodorus knew <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="294e"/>also how to dance. To which he replied: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Certainly.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I do not suppose, I said, that you have attained such a degree of skill as to do sword-dancing, or be whirled about on a wheel, at your time of life?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">There is nothing,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">that I cannot do.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then tell me, I went on, do you know everything at present only, or for ever?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">For ever too,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And when you were children, and were just born, you knew?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus #Euthydemus" direct="false">Everything,</said> they both replied together.</p></said></div> 

				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="295"> 
					<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="295"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="295a"/>
				
						<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Now, to us the thing seemed incredible: then Euthydemus said: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">You do not believe it, Socrates?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I will only say, I replied, that you must indeed be clever.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Why,</said> he said, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">if you will consent to answer me, I will propound that you too admit these surprising facts.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Oh, I am only too glad, I replied, to be refuted in the matter. For if I am not aware of my own cleverness, and you are going to show me that I know everything always, what greater stroke of luck than this could befall me in all my living days?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then answer me,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Ask: I am ready to answer. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="295b"/> 
							
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Well then, Socrates, he asked, have you knowledge of something, or not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I have.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And tell me, do you know with that whereby you have knowledge, or with something else?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>With that whereby I have knowledge: I think you mean the soul, or is not that your meaning?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Are you not ashamed, Socrates,</said> he said, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">to ask a question on your side when you are being questioned?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Very well, I said: but how am I to proceed? I will do just as you bid me. When I cannot tell what you are asking, is it your order that I answer all the same, without asking a question upon it?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Why,</said> he replied, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">you surely conceive <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="295c"/>some meaning in what I say?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I do, I replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Answer then to the meaning you conceive to be in my words.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, I said, if you ask a question with a different meaning in your mind from that which I conceive, and I answer to the latter, are you content I should answer nothing to the point?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">For my part,</said> he replied, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">I shall be content: you, however, will not, so far as I can see.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then I declare I shall not answer, I said, before I get it right.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">You refuse to answer,</said> he said, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">to the meaning you conceive in each case, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="295d"/>because you will go on driveling, you hopeless old dotard!</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Here I perceived he was annoyed with me for distinguishing between the phrases used, when he wanted to entrap me in his verbal snares. So I remembered Connus, how he too is annoyed with me whenever I do not give in to him, with the result that he now takes less trouble over me as being a stupid person. So being minded to take lessons from this new teacher, I decided that I had better give in, lest he should take me for a blockhead and not admit me to his classes. So I said: Well, if you think fit, Euthydemus, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="295e"/>to proceed thus, we must do so; in any case I suppose you understand debating better than I do—you are versed in the method, and I am but a layman. Begin your questions, then, over again.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Now, answer me once more,</said> he said: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">do you know what you know by means of something, or not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I do, I replied; by means of my soul.</p></said></div> 

				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="296"> 

						<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="296"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="296a"/>
					
						<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
							<said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">There he is again,</said> he said, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">answering more than he is asked. For I am not asking what the means is, but only whether you know by some means.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, I did again answer more than I ought, I said, through lack of education. But forgive me, and I will now simply reply that I know what I know by some means.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">By one and the same means always,</said> he asked, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">or sometimes by one and sometimes by another?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Always, whenever I know, I replied, it is by this means.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">There again,</said> he cried, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">you really must stop adding these qualifications.</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="296b"/> 

							<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But I am so afraid this word <q type="mentioned">always</q> may bring us to grief.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Not us,</said> he rejoined, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">but, if anyone, you. Now answer: do you know by this means always?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Always, I, replied, since I must withdraw the <q type="mentioned">whenever.</q>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then you always know by this means: that being the case, do you know some things by this means of knowing, and some things by another means, or everything by this?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Everything by this, I replied; everything, that is, that I know.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">There it comes again,</said> he cried; <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">the same qualification!</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, I withdraw my <q type="mentioned">that is, that I know.</q>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">No, do not withdraw a single word,</said> he said: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">I ask you for no concession. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="296c"/>Only answer me: could you know all things if you did not know everything?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It would be most surprising, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then he went on: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">You may therefore add on now whatever you please: for you admit that you know all things.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It seems I do, I replied, seeing that my <q type="mentioned">that I know</q> has no force, and I know everything.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Now you have also admitted that you know always by the means whereby you know, whenever you know—or however you like to put it. For you have admitted that you always know and, at the same time, everything. Hence it is clear that <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="296d"/>even as a child you knew, both when you were being born and when you were being conceived: and before you yourself came into being or heaven and earth existed, you knew all things, since you always know. Yes, and I declare,</said> he said, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">you yourself will always know all things, if it be my pleasure.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Oh, pray let it be your pleasure, I replied, most worshipful Euthydemus, if what you say is really true. Only I do not quite trust in your efficacy, if your pleasure is not to he also that of your brother here, Dionysodorus: if it is, you will probably prevail. And tell me, I went on, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="296e"/>since I cannot hope in a general way to dispute the statement that I know everything with persons so prodigiously clever—since it is your statement—how am I to say I know certain things, Euthydemus; for instance, that good men are unjust? Come, tell me, do I know this or not?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">You know it certainly,</said> he said. 
							
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What? I said. 
							
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">That the good are not unjust.</said></p></said></div>
							
							<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="297"> 
								<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
									

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Quite so, I said: I knew that all the time; but that is not what I ask: 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="297"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="297a"/>tell me, where did I learn that the good are unjust?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Nowhere,</said> said Dionysodorus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then I do not know this, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">You are spoiling the argument,</said> said Euthydemus to Dionysodorus, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">and we shall find that this fellow does not know, and is at once both knowing and unknowing.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this Dionysodorus reddened. But you, I said, what do you mean, Euthydemus. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="297b"/>Do you find that your brother, who knows everything, has not spoken aright?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">I a brother of Euthydemus?</said> quickly interposed Dionysodorus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Whereupon I said: Let me alone, good sir, till Euthydemus has taught me that I know that good men are unjust, and do not grudge me this lesson.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">You are running away, Socrates,</said> said Dionysodorus; <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">you refuse to answer.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, and with good reason, I said: for I am weaker than <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="297c"/>either one of you, so I have no scruple about running away from the two together. You see, I am sadly inferior to Hercules, who was no match for the hydra—that she-professor who was so clever that she sent forth many heads of debate in place of each one that was cut off; nor for another sort of, crab-professor from the sea— freshly, I fancy, arrived on shore; and, when the hero was so bothered with its leftward barks and bites, he summoned his nephew Iolaus to the rescue, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="297d"/>and he brought him effective relief. But if my Iolaus were to come, he would do more harm than good.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. any kinsman or helper I might summon would only add to the number of your victims.</note>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well, answer this,</said> said Dionysodorus, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">now you have done your descanting: Was Iolaus more Hercules’ nephew than yours?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I see I had best answer you, Dionysodorus, I said. For you will never cease putting questions—I think I may say I am sure of this—in a grudging, obstructing spirit, so that Euthydemus may not teach me that bit of cleverness.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then answer,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, I answer, I said, that Iolaus was Hercules’ nephew, but not mine, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="297e"/>so far as I can see, in any way whatever. For Patrocles, my brother, was not his father; only Hercules’ brother Iphicles had a name somewhat similar to his.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And Patrocles,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">is your brother?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Certainly, I said: that is, by the same mother, but not by the same father.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then he is your brother and not your brother.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Not by the same father, worthy sir, I replied. His father was Chaeredemus, mine Sophroniscus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">So Sophroniscus and Chaeredemus,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">were <q type="emph">father</q>?</said></p></said></div>
				
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="298"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Certainly, I said: the former mine, 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="298"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="298a"/>the latter his. 
						
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then surely,</said> he went on, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Chaeredemus was other than <q type="emph">father</q>?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Than mine, at any rate, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Why then, he was father while being other than father. Or are you the same as <q type="emph">the stone</q>?</said><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Gorg. 494a">Plat. Gorg. 494a</bibl>, where <quote>the life of a stone</quote> is given as a proverbial example of a life without pleasure or pain.</note>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I fear you may prove that of me, I said, though I do not feel like it.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then are you other than the stone?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Other, I must say.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then of course,</said> he went on, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">if you are other than stone, you are not stone? And if you are other than gold, you are not gold?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Quite so.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Hence Chaeredemus,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">being other than father, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="298b"/>cannot be <q type="emph">father.</q></said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It seems, I said, that he is not a father.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">No, for I presume,</said> interposed Euthydemus, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">that if Chaeredemus is a father Sophroniscus in his turn, being other than a father, is not a father; so that you, Socrates, are fatherless.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Here Ctesippus took it up, observing: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">And your father too, is he not in just the same plight? Is he other than my father?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Not in the slightest</said>, said Euthydemus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">What,</said> asked the other, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">is he the same?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">The same, to be sure.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">I should not like to think he was: but tell me, Euthydemus, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="298c"/>is he my father only, or everybody else’s too?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Everybody else’s too,</said> he replied; <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">or do you suppose that the same man, being a father, can be no father?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">I did suppose so,</said> said Ctesippus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Well,</said> said the other, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">and that a thing being gold could be not gold? Or being a man, not man?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Perhaps, Euthydemus,</said> said Ctesippus, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">you are knotting flax with cotton,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. treating two different things as the same.</note> as they say: for it is a strange result that you state, if your father is father of all.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">He is, though,</said> was the reply.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Of all men, do you mean?</said> asked Ctesippus, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">or of horses too, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="298d"/>and all other animals?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Of all,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">And is your mother a mother in the same way?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">My mother too.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">And is your mother a mother of sea-urchins?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Yes, and yours is also,</said> he replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">So then you are a brother of the gudgeons and whelps and porkers.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Yes, and so are you,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Then your father is a boar and a dog.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And so is yours,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Yes,</said> said Dionysodorus, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">and it will take you but a moment, if you will answer me, Ctesippus, to acknowledge all this. Just tell me, have you a dog?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes, a real rogue,</said> said Ctesippus. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="298e"/> 
						
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Has he got puppies?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes, a set of rogues like him.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then is the dog their father?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes, indeed; I saw him with my own eyes covering the bitch.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well now, is not the dog yours?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Thus he is a father, and yours, and accordingly the dog turns out to be your father, and you a brother of whelps.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hereupon Dionysodorus struck in again quickly, lest Ctesippus should get a word in before him: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Answer me just one more little point: do you beat this dog?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Ctesippus laughed and said: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">My word, yes; since I cannot beat you!</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">So you beat your own father?</said> 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="299"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="299a"/>he said.</p></said></div>
						
						<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="299"> 
							<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
								

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">There would be much more justice, though,</said> he replied, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">in my beating yours, for being so ill-advised as to beget clever sons like you. Yet I doubt,</said> Ctesippus went on, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">if your father, Euthydemus—the puppies’ father—has derived much good from this wisdom of yours.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Why, he has no need of much good, Ctesippus, neither he nor you.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">And have you no need either, yourself, Euthydemus?</said> he asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">No, nor has any other man. Just tell me, Ctesippus, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="299b"/>whether you think it good for a sick man to drink physic when he wants it, or whether you consider it not good; or for a man to go to the wars with arms rather than without them.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">With them, I think,</said> he replied: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">and yet I believe you are about to utter one of your pleasantries.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">You will gather that well enough,</said> he said: <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">only answer me. Since you admit that physic is good for a man to drink when necessary, surely one ought to drink this good thing as much as possible; and in such a case it will be well to pound and infuse in it a cart-load of hellebore?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To this Ctesippus replied: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Quite so, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="299c"/>to be sure, Euthydemus, at any rate if the drinker is as big as the Delphian statue.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then, further, since in war,</said> he proceeded, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">it is good to have arms, one ought to have as many spears and shields as possible, if we agree that it is a good thing?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes, I suppose,</said> said Ctesippus; <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">and you, Euthydemus, do you take the other view, that it should be one shield and one spear?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Yes, I do.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">What,</said> he said, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">and would you arm Geryon also and Briareus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Two fabulous giants (Geryon had three, Briareus fifty, pairs of arms).</note> in this way? I thought you more of an expert than that, considering you are a man-at-arms, and your comrade here too!</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this Euthydemus was silent; then Dionysodorus <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="299d"/>asked some questions on Ctesippus’ previous answers, saying: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well now, gold is in your opinion a good thing to have?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Certainly, and—here I agree—plenty of it too,</said> said Ctesippus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well then, do you not think it right to have good things always and everywhere?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Assuredly,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then do you admit that gold is also a good?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Why, I have admitted it,</said> he replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then we ought always to have it, and everywhere, and above all, in oneself? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="299e"/>And one will be happiest if one has three talents of gold in one’s belly, a talent in one’s skull, and a stater of gold in each eye?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Well, Euthydemus,</said> replied Ctesippus, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">they say that among the Scythians those are the happiest and best men who have a lot of gold in their own skulls—somewhat as you were saying a moment ago that <q type="emph">dog</q> is <q type="emph">father</q>; and a still more marvellous thing is told, how they drink out of their skulls when gilded, and gaze inside them, holding their own headpiece in their hands.</said></p></said></div>
				
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="300"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Tell me,</said> said Euthydemus, 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="300"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="300a"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">do the Scythians and men in general see things possible of sight, or things impossible?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Possible, I presume.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And you do so too?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">I too.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then you see our cloaks?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">And have they power of sight?</said><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The quibble is on the double meaning of <foreign xml:lang="grc">δυνατὰ ὁρᾶν</foreign>—(a)<gloss>possible,</gloss> and (b)<gloss>able to see.</gloss> So in what follows, <foreign xml:lang="grc">σιγῶντα λέγειν</foreign> may mean both <gloss>the speaking of a silent person,</gloss> or <gloss>speaking of silent things.</gloss></note>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Quite extraordinarily,</said> said Ctesippus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">What do they see?</said> he asked.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Nothing. Perhaps you do not think they see—you are such a sweet innocent. I should say, Euthydemus, that you have fallen asleep with your eyes open and, if it be possible to speak and at the same time say nothing, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="300b"/>that this is what you are doing.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Why,</said> asked Dionysodorus, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">may there not be a speaking of the silent?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">By no means whatever,</said> replied Ctesippus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Nor a silence of speaking?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Still less,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Now, when you speak of stones and timbers and irons, are you not speaking of the silent?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Not if I walk by a smithy, for there, as they say, the irons speak and cry aloud, when they are touched; so here your wisdom has seduced you into nonsense. But come, you have still to propound me your second point, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="300c"/>how on the other hand there may be a silence of speaking.</said> (It struck me that Ctesippus was specially excited on account of his young friend’s presence.)

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">When you are silent,</said> said Euthydemus, <said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">are you not making a silence of all things?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Yes,</said> he replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Then it is a silence of speaking things also, if the speaking are among all things.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">What,</said> said Ctesippus, <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">are not all things silent?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">I presume not,</said> said Euthydemus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">But then, my good sir, do all things speak?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Euthydemus" direct="false">Yes, I suppose, at least those that speak.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">But that is not what I ask,</said> he said: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">are all things silent or do they speak?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Neither and both,</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="300d"/>said Dionysodorus, snatching the word from him: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">I am quite sure that is an answer that will baffle you!</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At this Ctesippus, as his manner was, gave a mighty guffaw, and said: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Ah, Euthydemus, your brother has made the argument ambiguous with his <q type="mentioned">both,</q> and is worsted and done for.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then Cleinias was greatly delighted and laughed, so that Ctesippus felt his strength was as the strength of ten: but I fancy Ctesippus—he is such a rogue—had picked up these very words by overhearing the men themselves, since in nobody else of the present age is such wisdom to be found. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="300e"/> So I remarked: Why are you laughing, Cleinias, at such serious and beautiful things?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">What, have you, Socrates, ever yet seen a beautiful thing?</said> asked Dionysodorus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, I have, I replied, and many of them, Dionysodorus.</p></said></div>
				
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="301"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Did you find them different from the beautiful,</said> he said, 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="301"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="301a"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">or the same as the beautiful?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Here I was desperately perplexed, and felt that I had my deserts for the grunt I had made: however, I replied that they were different from the beautiful itself, though each of them had some beauty present with it.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">So if an ox is present with you,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">you are an ox, and since I am now present with you, you are Dionysodorus.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Heavens, do not say that! I cried.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">But in what way can one thing, by having a different thing present with it, be itself different?</said> 
						<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="301b"/> 
						
						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Are you at a loss there? I asked: already I was attempting to imitate the cleverness of these men, I was so eager to get it.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Can I help being at a loss,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">I and likewise everybody else in the world, in face of what cannot be?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What is that you say, Dionysodorus? I asked: is not the beautiful beautiful, and the ugly ugly?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Yes, if it seems so to me,</said> he replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then does it seem so?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Certainly,</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then the same also is the same, and the different different? For I presume the different cannot be the same; nay, I thought <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="301c"/>not even a child would doubt that the different is different. But, Dionysodorus, you have deliberately passed over this one point; though, on the whole, I feel that, like craftsmen finishing off each his special piece of work, you two are carrying out your disputation in excellent style.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well,</said> he asked, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">do you know what is each craftsman’s special piece of work? First of all, whose proper task is it to forge brass? Can you tell?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I can: a brazier’s.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well, again, whose to make pots?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A potter’s.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Once more, whose to slaughter and skin, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="301d"/>and after cutting up the joints to stew and roast?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A caterer’s, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Now, if one does one’s proper work,</said> he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">one will do rightly?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, to be sure.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And is it, as you say, the caterer’s proper work to cut up and skin? Did you admit this or not?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I did so, I replied, but pray forgive me.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">It is clear then,</said> he proceeded, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">that if someone slaughters the caterer and cuts him up, and then stews or roasts him, he will be doing his proper work; and if he hammers the brazier himself, and moulds the potter, he will be doing his business likewise.</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="301e"/> 
						
						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Poseidon! I exclaimed, there you give the finishing touch to your wisdom. I wonder if this skill could ever come to me in such manner as to be my very own.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Would you recognize it, Socrates,</said> he asked, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">if it came to be your own?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, if only you are agreeable, I replied, without a doubt.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Why,</said> he went on, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">do you imagine you perceive what is yours?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, if I take your meaning aright: for all my hopes arise from you, and end in Euthydemus here.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Greek works follow a usual form of prayer or hymn to the gods.</note></p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="302"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then tell me,</said> he asked, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">do you count those things yours which you control and are free to use as you please?

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="302"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="302a"/>For instance, an ox or a sheep,would you count these as yours, if you were free to sell or bestow them, or sacrifice them to any god you chose? And things which you could not treat thus are not yours?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hereupon, since I knew that some brilliant result was sure to bob up from the mere turn of the questions, and as I also wanted to hear it as quickly as possible, I said: It is precisely as you say; only such things are mine.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well now,</said> he went on: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">you call those things animals which have life?</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="302b"/> 
						
						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And you admit that only those animals are yours which you are at liberty to deal with in those various ways that I mentioned just now?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I admit that.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then—after a very ironical pause, as though he were pondering some great matter—he proceeded: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Tell me, Socrates, have you an ancestral Zeus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Zeus was the ancestral or tutelary god of the Dorians</note>?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Here I suspected the discussion was approaching the point at which it eventually ended, and so I tried what desperate wriggle I could to escape from the net in which I now felt myself entangled. My answer was: I have not, Dionysodorus.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">What a miserable fellow you must be,</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="302c"/>he said, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">and no Athenian at all, if you have neither ancestral gods, nor shrines, nor anything else that denotes a gentleman!</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Enough, Dionysodorus; speak fair words, and don’t browbeat your pupil! For I have altars and shrines, domestic and ancestral, and everything else of the sort that other Athenians have.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then have not other Athenians,</said> he asked, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">their ancestral Zeus?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>None of the Ionians, I replied, give him this title, neither we nor those who have left this city to settle abroad: they have an ancestral Apollo, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="302d"/>because of Ion’s parentage.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Eur. Ion 64">Eur. Ion 64-75</bibl>. Apollo begot Ion upon Creusa, daughter of Erechtheus.</note> Among us the name <q type="emph">ancestral</q> is not given to Zeus, but that of <q type="emph">houseward</q> and <q type="emph">tribal,</q> and we have a tribal Athena.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">That will do,</said> said Dionysodorus; <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">you have, it seems, Apollo and Zeus and Athena.
</said>
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Certainly, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then these must be your gods?</said> he said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>My ancestors, I said, and lords.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Well, at least, you have them,</said> he said: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">or have you not admitted they are yours?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I have admitted it, I replied: what else could I do?

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And are not these gods animals?</said> he asked: <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">you know you have admitted <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="302e"/>that whatever has life is an animal. Or have these gods no life?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>They have, I replied.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Then are they not animals?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Yes, animals, I said.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">And those animals,</said> he went on, <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">you have admitted to be yours, which you are free to bestow and sell and sacrifice to any god you please.</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I have admitted it, I replied; there is no escape for me, Euthydemus.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="303"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/><said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Come then, tell me straight off,</said> he said; <said who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">since you admit that Zeus and the other gods are yours, are you free to sell or 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="303"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="303a"/>bestow them or treat them just as you please, like the other animals?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, Crito, here I must say I was knocked out, as it were, by the argument, and lay speechless; then Ctesippus rushed to the rescue and—<said who="#Ctesippus">Bravo, Hercules!</said> he cried, <said who="#Ctesippus">a fine argument!</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Whereat Dionysodorus asked: <said  who="#Dionysodorus" direct="false">Now, do you mean that Hercules is a bravo, or that bravo is Hercules?</said>

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Ctesippus replied: <said who="#Ctesippus" direct="false">Poseidon, what a frightful use of words! I give up the fight: these two are invincible.</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="303b"/> 
						
						<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hereupon I confess, my dear Crito, that everyone present without exception wildly applauded the argument and the two men, till they all nearly died of laughing and clapping and rejoicing. For their previous successes had been highly acclaimed one by one, but only by the devotees of Euthydemus; whereas now almost the very pillars of the Lyceum took part in the joyful acclamations in honor of the pair. For myself, I was quite disposed to admit that never had I set eyes <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="303c"/>on such clever people, and I was so utterly enthralled by their skill that I betook myself to praising and congratulating them, and said: Ah, happy pair! What amazing genius, to acquire such a great accomplishment so quickly and in so short a time! Among the many fine points in your arguments, Euthydemus and Dionysodorus, there is one that stands out in particular magnificence—that you care not a jot for the multitude, or for any would-be important or famous people, but only for those of your own sort. And I am perfectly sure that there are but a few persons <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="303d"/>like yourselves who would be satisfied with these arguments: the rest of the world regard them only as arguments with which, I assure you, they would feel it a greater disgrace to refute others than to be refuted themselves. And further, there is at the same time a popular and kindly feature in your talk: when you say there is nothing either beautiful, or good, or white, and so on, and no difference of things at all, in truth you simply stitch up men’s mouths, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="303e"/>as you expressly say you do; while as to your apparent power of stitching up your own mouths as well, this is a piece of agreeable manners that takes off any offence from your talk. But the greatest thing of all is, that this faculty of yours is such, and is so skilfully contrived, that anyone in the world may learn it of you in a very short time; this fact I perceived myself by watching Ctesippus and observing how quickly he was able to imitate you on the spot.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="304"> 
					<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
						Now, in so far as your accomplishment can be quickly imparted, 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="304"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="304a"/>it is excellent; but for public discussions it is not suitable: if I may advise you, beware of talking before a number of people, lest they learn the whole thing in a trice and give you no credit for it. The best thing for you is to talk to each other by yourselves, in private; failing that, if a third person is present, it must be someone who will pay you a good fee. And if you are prudent <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="304b"/>you will give this same counsel to your pupils also—that they are never to converse with anybody except you and each other. For it is the rare, Euthydemus, that is precious, while water is cheapest, though best, as Pindar<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Pind. O. 1">Pind. O. 1</bibl>., which begins—<foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἄριστον μὲν ὕδωρ</foreign>.</note> said. But come, I said, see if you can admit both me and Cleinias here to your class.

<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This, Crito, was our conversation, and after exchanging a few more words we went off. Now you must arrange to join us in taking lessons from the pair; <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="304c"/>for they say they are able to teach anyone who is willing to pay good money, and that no sort of character or age—and it is well that you especially should be told that they promise that their art is no hindrance to money-making—need deter anyone from an easy acquisition of their wisdom.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Indeed, Socrates, I love listening, and would be glad to learn from them; but I am afraid I am one of the sort who are not like Euthydemus, but who, as you described them just now, would prefer being refuted <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="304d"/>to refuting with such arguments. Now, although I feel it is absurd to admonish you, I wish nevertheless to report to you what was told me just now. Do you know, one of the people who had left your discussion came up to me as I was taking a stroll—a man who thinks himself very wise, one of those who are so clever at turning out speeches for the law-courts<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The allusion is probably to Isocrates.</note>—and said: <said direct="false">Crito, do you take no lessons from these wise men?</said> No, in truth, I replied: there was such a crowd that, though I stood quite close, I was unable to catch what was said. <said direct="false">Well, let me tell you,</said> he said, <said direct="false">it was something worth hearing.</said> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="304e"/>What was it? I asked. <said direct="false">You would have heard the disputation of men who are the most accomplished of our day in that kind of speaking.</said> To this I replied: Well, what did they show forth to you? <said direct="false">Merely the sort of stuff,</said> he said, <said direct="false">that you may hear such people babbling about at any time—making an inconsequent ado about matters of no consequence</said> (in some such parlance he expressed himself). Whereupon—Well, all the same, I said, philosophy is a charming thing.</p></said></div>
				
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="305"> 
					<said who="#Crito" rend="merge"><label>Cri.</label> <p>
						<said direct="false">Charming is it, my dear innocent?</said> he exclaimed: 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="305"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="305a"/><said direct="false">nay, a thing of no consequence. Why, had you been in that company just now, you would have been filled with shame, I fancy, for your particular friend: he was so strangely willing to lend himself to persons who care not a straw what they say, but merely fasten on any phrase that turns up. And these, as I said just now, are the heads of their profession today. But the fact is, Crito,</said> he went on, <said direct="false">the business itself and the people who follow it are worthless and ridiculous.</said> Now, in my opinion, Socrates, he was not right in decrying the pursuit: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="305b"/>he is wrong, and so is anyone else who decries it: though I must say I felt he was right in blaming the readiness to engage in discussion with such people before a large company.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Crito, these people are very odd. But I do not yet know what answer I shall give you. Of which party was he who came up to you and blamed philosophy? Was he one of those who excel in the contests of the courts, an orator; or of those who equip the orators for the fray, a composer of the speeches they deliver in their contests? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="305c"/></p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Nothing of an orator, I dare swear, nor do I think he has ever appeared in court: only he is reputed to know about the business, so they declare, and to be a clever person, and compose clever speeches.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Now I understand: it was of these people that I was just now going to speak myself. They are the persons, Crito, whom Prodicus described as the border-ground between philosopher and politician, yet they fancy that they are the wisest of all mankind, and that they not merely are but are thought so by a great many people; and accordingly <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="305d"/>they feel that none but the followers of philosophy stand in the way of their universal renown. Hence they believe that, if they can reduce the latter to a status of no esteem, the prize of victory will by common consent be awarded to them, without dispute or delay, and their claim to wisdom will be won. For they consider themselves to be in very truth the wisest, but find that, when caught in private conversation, they are cut off short by Euthydemus and his set. This conceit of their wisdom is very natural, since they regard themselves as moderately versed in philosophy, and moderately too in politics, on quite reasonable grounds: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="305e"/>for they have dipped into both as far as they needed, and, evading all risk and struggle, are content to gather the fruits of wisdom.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Well, now, do you consider, Socrates, that there is anything in what they say? It is not to be denied that these men have some color for their statements.</p></said></div>

				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="306"> 
					
						<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Yes, that is so, Crito; color rather than truth. 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="306"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="306a"/>It is no easy matter to persuade them that either people or things, which are between two other things and have a certain share of both, if compounded of bad and good are found to be better than the one and worse than the other; but if compounded of two good things which have not the same object, they are worse than either of their components in relation to the object to which each of them is adapted; while if they are compounded of two bad things which have not the same object, and stand between them, this is the only case <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="306b"/>where they are better than either of the two things of which they have a share. Now if philosophy and the statesman’s business are both good things, and each of them has a different object, and if these persons, partaking of both, are between them, their claims are nought; for they are inferior to both: if one is good and the other bad, they are better than the one and worse than the other: while if both are bad, in this case there would be some truth in their statement, but in any other case there is none. Now I do not think they will admit <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="306c"/>either that both these things are bad, or that one is bad and the other good: the truth is that these people, partaking of both, are inferior to both in respect of the objects for which statesmanship and philosophy are important; and while they are really in the third place they seek to be accorded the first. However, we ought to be indulgent towards their ambition and not feel annoyed, while still judging them to be what they actually are. For we should be glad of anyone, whoever he may be, who says anything that verges on good sense, and labours steadily <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="306d"/>and manfully in its pursuit.</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Now I myself, Socrates, as I so often tell you, am in doubt about my sons, as to what I am to do with them. The younger is as yet quite small; but Critobulus is already grown up, and needs someone who will be of service to him. When I am in your company, the effect on me is such as to make me feel it is mere madness to have taken ever so much pains in various directions for the good of my children— <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="306e"/>first in so marrying that they should be of very good blood on their mother’s side; then in making money so that they might be as well off as possible; while I have neglected the training of the boys themselves. But when I glance at one of the persons who profess to educate people, I am dismayed, and feel that each one of them, when I consider them, is wholly unsuitable— 

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="307"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="307a"/>to tell you the truth between ourselves. So that I cannot see how I am to incline the lad towards philosophy.</p></said></div>

				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="307"> 
				<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>My dear Crito are you not aware that in every trade the duffers are many and worthless, whereas the good workers are few and worth any price? Why, do you not hold athletics, and money-making, and rhetoric, and generalship, to be fine things?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Certainly I do, of course. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="307b"/></p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well then, in each of these, do you not see most men making a ridiculous show at their respective tasks?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>Yes, I know: what you say is perfectly true.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then will you yourself on this account eschew all these pursuits, and not let your son have anything to do with them?</p></said>

<said who="#Crito"><label>Cri.</label> <p>No, there would be no good reason for that, Socrates.</p></said>

<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then avoid at least what is wrong, Crito: let those who practise philosophy have their way, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="307c"/>whether they are helpful or mischievous; and when you have tested the matter itself, well and truly, if you find it to be a poor affair, turn everyone you can away from it, not only your sons: but if you find it to be such as I think it is, pursue and ply it without fear, both you, as they say, and yours.</p></said></div>
			</div></body></text>

</TEI>