<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>Of the Epidemics</title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 20, 2003</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							              <date>1886</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="">English</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-29" who="Thibault Clérice">Bumped URN</change>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng"
              type="translation"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg006.perseus-eng3">
			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="book">
				           <head>BOOK I</head>
				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>Section I. -- First Constitution</head>

					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 1 </head>
						               <p>IN THASUS, about the autumn equinox, and under the Pleiades, the rains
							were abundant, constant, and soft, with southerly winds; the winter
							southerly, the northerly winds faint, droughts; on the whole, the winter
							having the character of spring. The spring was southerly, cool, rains
							small in quantity. Summer, for the most part, cloudy, no rain, the
							Etesian winds, rare and small, blew in an irregular manner. The whole
							constitution of the season being thus inclined to the southerly, and
							with droughts early in the spring, from the preceding opposite and
							northerly state, ardent fevers occurred in a few instances, and these
							very mild, being rarely attended with hemorrhage, and never proving
							fatal. Swellings appeared about the ears, in many on either side, and in
							the greatest number on both sides, being unaccompanied by fever so as
							not to confine the patient to bed; in all cases they disappeared without
							giving trouble, neither did any of them come to suppuration, as is
							common in swellings from other causes. They were of a lax, large,
							diffused character, without inflammation or pain, and they went away
							without any critical sign. They seized children, adults, and mostly
							those who were engaged in the exercises of the palestra and gymnasium,
							but seldom attacked women. Many had dry coughs without expectoration,
							and accompanied with hoarseness of voice. In some instances earlier, and
							in others later, inflammations with pain seized sometimes one of <pb n="p.101"/>the testicles, and sometimes both; some of these cases
							were accompanied with fever and some not; the greater part of these were
							attended with much suffering. In other respects they were free of
							disease, so as not to require medical assistance.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 2 </head>
						               <p>Early in the beginning of spring, and through the summer, and towards
							winter, many of those who had been long gradually declining, took to bed
							with symptoms of phthisis; in many cases formerly of a doubtful
							character the disease then became confirmed; in these the constitution
							inclined to the phthisical. Many, and, in fact, the most of them, died;
							and of those confined to bed, I do not know if a single individual
							survived for any considerable time; they died more suddenly than is
							common in such cases. But other diseases, of a protracted character, and
							attended with fever, were well supported, and did not prove fatal: of
							these we will give a description afterwards. Consumption was the most
							considerable of the diseases which then prevailed, and the only one
							which proved fatal to many persons. Most of them were affected by these
							diseases in the following manner: fevers accompanied with rigors, of the
							continual type, acute, having no complete intermissions, but of the form
							of the semi-tertians, being milder the one day, and the next having an
							exacerbation, and increasing in violence; constant sweats, but not
							diffused over the whole body; extremities very cold, and warmed with
							difficulty; bowels disordered, with bilious, scanty, unmixed, thin,
							pungent, and frequent dejections. The urine was thin, colorless,
							unconcocted, or thick, with a deficient sediment, not settling
							favorably, but casting down a crude and unseasonable sediment. Sputa
							small, dense, concocted, but brought up rarely and with difficulty; and
							in those who encountered the most violent symptoms there was no
							concoction at all, but they continued throughout spitting crude matters.
							Their fauces, in most of them, were painful from first to last, having
							redness with inflammation; defluxions thin, small and acrid; they were
							soon wasted and became worse, having no appetite for any kind of food
							throughout; no thirst; most persons delirious when near death. So much
							concerning the phthisical affections.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 3 </head>
						               <p>In the course of the summer and autumn many fevers of the <pb n="p.102"/>continual type, but not violent; they attacked persons who had been
							long indisposed, but who were otherwise not in an uncomfortable state.
							In most cases the bowels were disordered in a very moderate degree, and
							they did not suffer thereby in any manner worth mentioning; the urine
							was generally well colored, clear, thin, and after a time becoming
							concocted near the crisis. They had not much cough, nor it troublesome;
							they were not in appetite, for it was necessary to give them food (on
							the whole, persons laboring under phthisis were not affected in the
							usual manner). They were affected with fevers, rigors, and deficient
							sweats, with varied and irregular paroxysms, in general not
							intermitting, but having exacerbations in the tertian form. The earliest
							crisis which occurred was about the twentieth day, in most about the
							fortieth, and in many about the eightieth. But there were cases in which
							it did not leave them thus at all, but in an irregular manner, and
							without any crisis; in most of these the fevers, after a brief interval,
							relapsed again; and from these relapses they came to a crisis in the
							same periods; but in many they were prolonged so that the disease was
							not gone at the approach of winter. Of all those which are described
							under this constitution, the phthisical diseases alone were of a fatal
							character; for in all the others the patients bore up well, and did not
							die of the other fevers.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>Section II. -- Second Constitution</head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 1 </head>
						               <p>In Thasus, early in autumn, the winter suddenly set in rainy before the
							usual time, with much northerly and southerly winds. These things all
							continued so during the season of the Pleiades, and until their setting.
							The winter was northerly, the rains frequent, in torrents, and large,
							with snow, but with a frequent mixture of fair weather. These things
							were all so, but the setting in of the cold was not much out of season.
							After the winter solstice, and at the time when the zephyr usually
							begins to blow, severe winterly storms out of season, with much
							northerly wind, snow, continued and copious rains; the sky tempestuous
							and clouded; these things were protracted, and did not remit until the
							equinox. The spring was cold, northerly, rainy, and clouded;<pb n="p.103"/> the summer was not very sultry, the Etesian winds blew
							constant, but quickly afterwards, about the rising of Arcturus, there
							were again many rains with north winds. The whole season being wet,
							cold, and northerly, people were, for the most part, healthy during
							winter; but early in the spring very many, indeed, the greater part,
							were valetudinary. At first ophthalmies set in, with rheums, pains,
							unconcocted discharges, small concretions, generally breaking with
							difficulty, in most instances they relapsed, and they did not cease
							until late in autumn. During summer and autumn there were dysenteric
							affections, attacks of tenesmus and lientery, bilious diarrhoea, with
							thin, copious, undigested, and acrid dejections, and sometimes with
							watery stools; many had copious defluxions, with pain, of a bilious,
							watery, slimy, purulent nature, attended with strangury, not connected
							with disease of the kidneys, but one complaint succeeding the other;
							vomitings of bile, phlegm, and undigested food, sweats, in all cases a
							redundance of humors. In many instances these complaints were unattended
							with fever, and did not prevent the patients from walking about, but
							some cases were febrile, as will be described. In some all those
							described below occurred with pain. During autumn, and at the
							commencement of winter, there were phthisical complaints, continual
							fevers; and, in a few cases, ardent; some diurnal, others nocturnal,
							semi-tertians, true tertians, quartans, irregular fevers.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 2 </head>
						               <p>All the fevers which are described attacked great numbers. The ardent
							fevers attacked the smallest numbers, and the patients suffered the
							least from them, for there were no hemorrhages, except a few and to a
							small amount, nor was there delirium; all the other complaints were
							slight; in these the crises were regular, in most instances, with the
							intermittents, in seventeen days; and I know no instance of a person
							dying of causus, nor becoming phrenitic. The tertians were more numerous
							than the ardent fevers, and attended with more pain; but these all had
							four periods in regular succession from the first attack, and they had a
							complete crisis in seven, without a relapse in any instance. The
							quartans attacked many at first, in the form of regular quartans, but in
							no few cases a transition from other fevers and diseases into quartans
							took place; they were<pb n="p.104"/> protracted, as is wont with them,
							indeed, more so than usual. Quotidian, nocturnal, and wandering fevers
							attacked many persons, some of whom continued to keep up, and others
							were confined to bed. In most instances these fevers were prolonged
							under the Pleiades and till winter. Many persons, and more especially
							children, had convulsions from the commencement; and they had fever, and
							the convulsions supervened upon the fevers; in most cases they were
							protracted, but free from danger, unless in those who were in a deadly
							state from other complaints. Those fevers which were continual in the
							main, and with no intermissions, but having exacerbations in the tertian
							form, there being remissions the one day and exacerbations the next,
							were the most violent of all those which occurred at that time, and the
							most protracted, and occurring with the greatest pains, beginning
							mildly, always on the whole increasing, and being exacerbated, and
							always turning worse, having small remissions, and after an abatement
							having more violent paroxysms, and growing worse, for the most part, on
							the critical days. Rigors, in all cases, took place in an irregular and
							uncertain manner, very rare and weak in them, but greater in all other
							fevers; frequent sweats, but most seldom in them, bringing no
							alleviation, but, on the contrary, doing mischief. Much cold of the
							extremities in them, and these were warmed with difficulty.
							Insomnolency, for the most part, especially in these fevers, and again a
							disposition to coma. The bowels, in all diseases, were disordered, and
							in a bad state, but worst of all in these. The urine, in most of them,
							was either thin and crude, yellow, and after a time with slight symptoms
							of concoction in a critical form, or having the proper thickness, but
							muddy, and neither settling nor subsiding; or having small and bad, and
							crude sediments; these being the worst of all. Coughs attended these
							fevers, but I cannot state that any harm or good ever resulted from the
							cough.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 3 </head>
						               <p>The most of these were protracted and troublesome, went on in a very
							disorderly and irregular form, and, for the most part, did in a crisis,
							either in the fatal cases or in the others; for if it left some of them
							for a season it soon returned again. In a few instances the lever
							terminated with a crisis;<pb n="p.105"/> in the earliest of these about
							the eightieth day, and some of these relapsed, so that most of them were
							not free from the fever during the winter; but the fever left most of
							them without a crisis, and these things happened alike to those who
							recovered and to those who did not. There being much want of crisis and
							much variety as to these diseases, the greatest and worst symptom
							attended the most of them, namely, a loathing of all articles of food,
							more especially with those who had otherwise fatal symptoms; but they
							were not unseasonably thirsty in such fevers. After a length of time,
							with much suffering and great wasting, abscesses were formed in these
							cases, either unusually large, so that the patients could not support
							them, or unusually small, so that they did no good, but soon relapsed
							and speedily got worse. The diseases which attacked them were in the
							form of dysenteries, tenesmus, lientery, and fluxes; but, in some cases,
							there were dropsies, with or without these complaints. Whatever attacked
							them violently speedily cut them off, or again, did them no good. Small
							rashes, and not corresponding to the violence of the disease, and
							quickly disappearing, or swellings occurred about the ears, which were
							not resolved, and brought on no crisis. In some they were determined to
							the joints, and especially to the hip-joint, terminating critically with
							a few, and quickly again increasing to its original habit.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 4 </head>
						               <p>Perons died of all these diseases, but mostly of these fevers, and
							notably infants just weaned, and older children, until eight or ten
							years of age, and those before puberty. These things occurred to those
							affected with the complaints described above, and to many persons at
							first without them. The only favorable symptom, and the greatest of
							those which occurred, and what saved most of those who were in the
							greatest dangers, was the conversion of it to a strangury, and when, in
							addition to this, abscesses were formed. The strangury attacked, most
							especially, persons of the ages I have mentioned, but it also occurred
							in many others, both of those who were not confined to bed and those who
							were. There was a speedy and great change in all these cases. For the
							bowels, if they happened previously to have watery discharges of a bad
							character, became regular, they got an appetite for food, and the <pb n="p.106"/>fevers were mild afterwards. But, with regard to the
							strangury itself, the symptoms were protracted and painful. Their urine
							was copious, thick, of various characters, red, mixed with pus, and was
							passed with pain. These all recovered, and I did not see a single
							instance of death among them.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 5 </head>
						               <p>With regard to the dangers of these cases, one must always attend to the
							seasonable concoction of all the evacuations, and to the favorable and
							critical abscesses. The concoctions indicate a speedy crisis and
							recovery of health; crude and undigested evacuations, and those which
							are converted into bad abscesses, indicate either want of crisis, or
							pains, or prolongation of the disease, or death, or relapses; which of
							these it is to be must be determined from other circumstances. <hi rend="ital">The physician must be able to tell the antecedents, know
								the present, and foretell the future- must mediate these things, and
								have two special objects in view with regard to disease, namely, to
								do good or to do no harm. The art consists in three things- the
								disease, the patient, and the physician. The physician is the
								servant of the art, and the patient must combat the disease along
								with the physician.</hi>
                        <note> I need scarcely remark that this
								passage is of classical celebrity. Galen, in his Commentary, remarks
								that the first time he read it he thought it unworthy of Hippocrates
								to lay it down as a rule of practice, that "the physician should do
								good to his patient, or at least no harm;" but that, after having
								seen a good deal of the practice of other physicians, and observed
								how often they were justly exposed to censure for having bled, or
								applied the bath, or given medicines, or wine unseaonably, he came
								to recognize the propriety and importance of the rule laid down by
								Hippocrates. The practice of certain physicians, Galen remarks, is
								like playing at the dice, when what turns up may occasion the
								greatest mischief to their patients. The last clause of this passage
								is very forcibly put. Galen, however, informs us that in some of th
								MSS. instead of "art" he found "nature"; that is to say, that the
								physician is "the minister (<hi rend="ital">or</hi> servant) of
								nature." Either of the readings, he remarks, will agree very well
								with the meaning of the passage.</note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 6 </head>
						               <p>Pains about the head and neck, and heaviness of the same along with pain,
							occur either without fevers or in fevers. Convulsions occurring in
							persons attacked with frenzy, and having vomitings of verdigris-green
							bile, in some cases quickly prove fatal. In ardent fevers, and in those
							other fevers in which there is pain of the neck, heaviness of the
							temples, mistiness about the eyes, and distention about the
							hypochondriac region, not unattended with pain, hemorrhage from the nose
							takes place, but <pb n="p.107"/>those who have heaviness of the whole
							head, cardialgia and nausea, vomit bilious and pituitous matters;
							children, in such affections, are generally attacked with convulsions,
							and women have these and also pains of the uterus; whereas, in elder
							persons, and those in whom the heat is already more subdued, these cases
							end in paralysis, mania, and loss of sight.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>

				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>Section III. -- Third Constitution </head>

					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 1 </head>
						               <p>In Thasus, a little before and during the season of Arcturus, there were
							frequent and great rains, with northerly winds. About the equinox, and
							till the setting of the Pleiades, there were a few southerly rains: the
							winter northerly and parched, cold, with great winds and snow. Great
							storms about the equinox, the spring northerly, dryness, rains few and
							cold. About the summer solstice, scanty rains, and great cold until near
							the season of the Dog-star. After the Dog-days, until the season of
							Arcturus, the summer hot, great droughts, not in intervals, but
							continued and severe: no rain; the Etesian winds blew; about the season
							of Arcturus southerly rains until the equinox.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 2 </head>
						               <p>In this state of things, during winter, paraplegia set in, and attacked
							many, and some died speedily; and otherwise the disease prevailed much
							in an epidemical form, but persons remained free from all other
							diseases. Early in the spring, ardent fevers commenced and continued
							through the summer until the equinox. Those then that were attacked
							immediately after the commencement of the spring and summer, for the
							most part recovered, and but few of them died. But when the autumn and
							the rains had set in, they were of a fatal character, and the greater
							part then died. When in these attacks of ardent fevers there was a
							proper and copious hemorrhage from the nose, they were generally saved
							by it, and I do not know a single person who had a proper hemorrhage who
							died in this constitution. Philiscus, Epaminon, and Silenus, indeed, who
							had a trifling epistaxis on the fourth and fifth day, died. Most of
							those taken with had a rigor about the time of the crisis, and notably
							those who had no hemorrhage; these had also rigor associated.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 3 </head>
						               <p>Some were attacked with jaundice on the sixth day, but these were
							benefited <pb n="p.108"/>either by an urinary purgation, or a disorder
							of the bowels, or a copious hemorrhage, as in the case of Heraclides,
							who was lodged with Aristocydes: this person, though he had the
							hemorrhage from the nose, the purgation by the bladder, and disorder of
							the bowels, experienced a favorable crisis on the twentieth day, not
							like the servant of Phanagoras, who had none of these symptoms, and
							died. The hemorrhages attacked most persons, but especially young
							persons and those in the prime of life, and the greater part of those
							who had not the hemorrhage died: elderly persons had jaundice or
							disorder of the bowels, such as Bion, who was lodged with Silenus.
							Dysenteries were epidemical during the summer, and some of those cases
							in which the hemorrhage occurred, terminated in dysentery, as happened
							to the slave of Eraton, and to Mullus, who had a copious hemorrhage,
							which settled down into dysentery, and they recovered. This humor was
							redundant in many cases, since in those who had not the hemorrhage about
							the crisis, but the risings about the ears disappeared, after their
							disappearance there was a sense of weight in the left flank extending to
							the extremity of the hip, and pain setting in after the crisis, with a
							discharge of thin urine; they began to have small hemorrhages about the
							twenty-fourth day, and the swelling was converted into the hemorrhage.
							In the case of Antiphon, the son of Critobulus' son, the fever ceased
							and came to a crisis about the fortieth day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 4 </head>
						               <p>Many women were attacked, but fewer than of the men, and there were fewer
							deaths among them. But most of them had difficult parturition, and after
							labor they were taken ill, and these most especially died, as, for
							example, the daughter of Telebolus died on the sixth day after delivery.
							Most females had the menstrual discharge during the fever, and many
							girls had it then for the first time: in certain individuals both the
							hemorrhage from the nose and the menses appeared; thus, in the case of
							the virgin daughter of Daetharses, the menses then took place for the
							first time, and she had also a copinous hemorrhage from the nose, and I
							knew no instance of any one dying when one or other of these took place
							properly. But all those in the pregnant state that were attacked had
							abortions, as far as I observed. The urine in most cases was of the
							proper color, but thin, and having scanty sediments: in <pb n="p.109"/>most the bowels were disordered with thin and bilious dejections; and
							many, after passing through the other crises, terminated in dysenteries,
							as happened to Xenophanes and Critias. The urine was watery, copious,
							clear, and thin; and even after the crises, when the sediment was
							natural, and all the other critical symptoms were favorable, as I
							recollect having happened to Bion, who was lodged in the house of
							Silenus, and Critias, who lived with Xenophanes, the slave of Areton,
							and the wife of Mnesistratus. But afterwards all these were attacked
							with dysentery. It would be worth while to inquire whether the watery
							urine was the cause of this. About the season of Arcturus many had the
							crisis on the eleventh day, and in them the regular relapses did not
							take place, but they became comatose about this time, especially
							children; but there were fewest deaths of all among them.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 5 </head>
						               <p>About the equinox, and until the season of the Pleiades, and at the
							approach of winter, many ardent fevers set in; but great numbers at that
							season were seized with phrenitis, and many died; a few cases also
							occurred during the summer. These then made their attack at the
							commencement of ardent fevers, which were attended with fatal symptoms;
							for immediately upon their setting in, there were acute fever and small
							rigors, insomnolency, aberration, thirst, nausea, insignificant sweats
							about the forehead and clavicles, but no general perspiration; they had
							much delirious talking, fears, despondency, great coldness of the
							extremities, in the feet, but more especially in their hands: the
							paroxysms were on the even days; and in most cases, on the fourth day,
							the most violent pains set in, with sweats, generally coldish, and the
							extremities could not be warmed, but were livid and rather cold, and
							they had then no thirst; in them the urine was black, scanty, thin, and
							the bowels were constipated; there was an hemorrhage from the nose in no
							case in which these symptoms occurred, but merely a trifling epistaxis;
							and none of them had a relapse, but they died on the sixth day with
							sweats. In the phrenitic cases, all the symptoms which have been
							described did not occur, but in them the disease mostly came to a crisis
							on the eleventh day, and in some on the twentieth. In those cases in
							which the phrenitis did not begin immediately, but about the <pb n="p.110"/>third or fourth day, the disease was moderate at the
							commencement, but assumed a violent character about the seventh day.
							There was a great number of diseases, and of those affected, they who
							died were principally infants, young persons, adults having smooth
							bodies, white skins, straight and black hair, dark eyes, those living
							recklessly and luxuriously; persons with shrill, or rough voices, who
							stammered and were passionate, and women more especially died from this
							form. In this constitution, four symptoms in particular proved salutary;
							either a hemorrhage from the nose, or a copious discharge by the bladder
							of urine, having an abundant and proper sediment, or a bilious disorder
							of the bowels at the proper time, or an attack of dysentery. And in many
							cases it happened, that the crisis did not take place by any one of the
							symptoms which have been mentioned, but the patient passed through most
							of them, and appeared to be in an uncomfortable way, and yet all who
							were attacked with these symptoms recovered. All the symptoms which I
							have described occurred also to women and girls; and whoever of them had
							any of these symptoms in a favorable manner, or the menses appeared
							abundantly, were saved thereby, and had a crisis, so that I do not know
							a single female who had any of these favorably that died. But the
							daughter of Philo, who had a copious hemorrhage from the nose, and took
							supper unseasonably on the seventh day, died. In those cases of acute,
							and more especially of ardent fevers, in which there is an involuntary
							discharge of tears, you may expect a nasal hemorrhage unless the other
							symptoms be of a fatal type, for in those of a bad description, they do
							not indicate a hemorrhage, but death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 6 </head>
						               <p>Swellings about the ears, with pain in fevers, sometimes when the fever
							went off critically, neither subsided nor were converted into pus; in
							these cases a bilious diarrhoea, or dysentery, or thick urine having a
							sediment, carried off the disease, as happened to Hermippus of
							Clazomenae. The circumstances relating to crises, as far as we can
							recognize them, were so far similar and so far dissimilar. Thus two
							brothers became ill at the same hour (they were brothers of Epigenes,
							and lodged near the theatre), of these the elder had a crisis on the
							sixth day, and the younger on the seventh, <pb n="p.111"/>and both had a
							relapse at the same hour; it then left them for five days, and from the
							return of the fever both had a crisis together on the seventeenth day.
							Most had a crisis on the sixth day; it then left them for six days, and
							from the relapse there was a crisis on the fifth day. But those who had
							a crisis on the seventh day, had an intermission for seven days; and the
							crisis took place on the third day after the relapse. Those who had a
							crisis on the sixth day, after an interval of six days were seized again
							on the third, and having left them for one day, the fever attacked them
							again on the next and came to a crisis, as happened to Evagon the son of
							Daetharses. Those in whom the crisis happened on the sixth day, had an
							intermission of seven days, and from the relapse there was a crisis on
							the fourth, as happened to the daughter of Aglaidas. The greater part of
							those who were taken ill under this constitution of things, were
							affected in this manner, and I did not know a single case of recovery,
							in which there was not a relapse agreeably to the stated order of
							relapses; and all those recovered in which the relapses took place
							according to this form: nor did I know a single instance of those who
							then passed through the disease in this manner who had another
							relapse.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 7 </head>
						               <p>In these diseases death generally happened on the sixth day, as with
							Epaminondas, Silenus, and Philiscus the son of Antagoras. Those who had
							parotid swellings experienced a crisis on the twentieth day, but in all
							these cases the disease went off without coming to a suppuration, and
							was turned upon the bladder. But in Cratistonax, who lived by the temple
							of Hercules, and in the maid servant of Scymnus the fuller, it turned to
							a suppuration, and they died. Those who had a crisis on the seventh day,
							had an intermission of nine days, and a relapse which came to a crisis
							on the fourth day from the return of the fever, as was the case with
							Pantacles, who resided close by the temple of Bacchus. Those who had a
							crisis on the seventh day, after an interval of six days had a relapse,
							from which they had a crisis on the seventh day, as happened to
							Phanocritus, who was lodged with Gnathon the fuller. During the winter,
							about the winter solstices, and until the equinox, the ardent fevers and
							frenzies prevailed, and many died. The crisis, however, changed, and <pb n="p.112"/>happened to the greater number on the fifth day from the
							commencement, left them for four days and relapsed; and after the
							return, there was a crisis on the fifth day, making in all fourteen
							days. The crisis took place thus in the case of most children, also in
							elder persons. Some had a crisis on the eleventh day, a relapse on the
							fourteenth, a complete crisis on the twentieth; but certain persons, who
							had a rigor about the twentieth, had a crisis on the fortieth. The
							greater part had a rigor along with the original crisis, and these had
							also a rigor about the crisis in the relapse. There were fewest cases of
							rigor in the spring, more in summer, still more in autumn, but by far
							the most in winter; then hemorrhages ceased.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 8 </head>
						               <p>With regard to diseases, the circumstances from which we form a judgment
							of them are,- by attending to the general nature of all, and the
							peculiar nature of each individual,- to the disease, the patient, and
							the applications,- to the person who applies them, as that makes a
							difference for better or for worse,- to the whole constitution of the
							season, and particularly to the state of the heavens, and the nature of
							each country;- to the patient's habits, regimen, and pursuits;- to his
							conversation, manners, taciturnity, thoughts, sleep, or absence of
							sleep, and sometimes his dreams, what and when they occur;- to his
							picking and scratching;- to his tears;- to the alvine discharges, urine,
							sputa, and vomitings; and to the changes of diseases from the one into
							the other;- to the deposits, whether of a deadly or critical character;-
							to the sweat, coldness, rigor, cough, sneezing, hiccup, respiration,
							eructation, flatulence, whether passed silently or with a noise;- to
							hemorrhages and hemorrhoids;- from these, and their consequences, we
							must form our judgment.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 9 </head>
						               <p>Fevers are,- the continual, some of which hold during the day and have a
							remission at night, and others hold a remission during the day;
							semi-tertians, tertians, quartans, quintans, septans, nonans. The most
							acute, strongest, most dangerous, and fatal diseases, occur in the
							continual fever. The least dangerous of all, and the mildest and most
								protracted,<pb n="p.113"/> is the quartan, for it is not only such
							from itself, but it also carries off other great diseases. In what is
							called the semi-tertian, other acute diseases are apt to occur, and it
							is the most fatal of all others, and moreover phthisical persons, and
							those laboring under other protracted diseases, are apt to be attacked
							by it. The nocturnal fever is not very fatal, but protracted; the
							diurnal is still more protracted, and in some cases passes into
							phthisis. The septan is protracted, but not fatal; the nonan more
							protracted, and not fatal. The true tertian comes quickly to a crisis,
							and is not fatal; but the quintan is the worst of all, for it proves
							fatal when it precedes an attack of phthisis, and when it supervenes on
							persons who are already consumptive. There are peculiar modes, and
							constitutions, and paroxysms, in every one of these fevers; for
							example,- the continual, in some cases at the very commencement, grows,
							as it were, and attains its full strength, and rises to its most
							dangerous pitch, but is diminished about and at the crisis; in others it
							begins gentle and suppressed, but gains ground and is exacerbated every
							day, and bursts forth with all its heat about and at the crisis; while
							in others, again, it commences mildly, increases, and is exacerbated
							until it reaches its acme, and then remits until at and about the
							crisis. These varieties occur in every fever, and in every disease. From
							these observations one must regulate the regimen accordingly. There are
							many other important symptoms allied to these, part of which have been
							already noticed, and part will be described afterwards, from a
							consideration of which one may judge, and decided in each case, whether
							the disease be acute, and whether it will end in death or recovery; or
							whether it will be protracted, and will end in death or recovery; and in
							what cases food is to be given, and in what not; and when and to what
							amount, and what particular kind of food is to be administered.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 10 </head>
						               <p>Those diseases which have their paroxysms on even days have their crises
							on even days; and those which have their paroxysms on uneven days have
							their crises on uneven days. The first period of those which have the
							crisis on even days, is the 4th, 6th, 8th, 10th, 14th, 20th, 30th, 40th,
							60th, 80th, 100th; and the first period of those which have their crises
							on uneven<pb n="p.114"/> days, is the 1st, 3d, 5th, 7th, 9th, 11th,
							17th, 21th, 27th, 31st. It should be known, that if the crisis take
							place on any other day than on those described, it indicates that there
							will be a relapse, which may prove fatal. But one ought to pay
							attention, and know in these seasons what crises will lead to recovery
							and what to death, or to changes for the better or the worse. Irregular
							fevers, quartans, quintans, septans, and nonans should be studied, in
							order to find out in what periods their crises take place.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>

				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>Fourteen Cases of Disease </head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case I </head>
						               <p>Philiscus, who lived by the Wall, took to bed on the first day of acute
							fever; he sweated; towards night was uneasy. On the second day all the
							symptoms were exacerbated; late in the evening had a proper stool from a
							small clyster; the night quiet. On the third day, early in the morning
							and until noon, he appeared to be free from fever; towards evening,
							acute fever, with sweating, thirst, tongue parched; passed black urine;
							night uncomfortable, no sleep; he was delirious on all subjects. On the
							fourth, all the symptoms exacerbated, urine black; night more
							comfortable, urine of a better color. On the fifth, about mid-day, had a
							slight trickling of pure blood from the nose; urine varied in character,
							having floating in it round bodies, resembling semen, and scattered, but
							which did not fall to the bottom; a suppository having been applied,
							some scanty flatulent matters were passed; night uncomfortable, little
							sleep, talking incoherently; extremities altogether cold, and could not
							be warmed; urine, black; slept a little towards day; loss of speech,
							cold sweats; extremities livid; about the middle of the sixth day he
							died. The respiration throughout, like that of a person recollecting
							himself, was rare, and large, and spleen was swelled upon in a round
							tumor, the sweats cold throughout, the paroxysms on the even days.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 2 </head>
						               <p>Silenus lived on the Broad-way, near the house of Evalcidas. From
							fatigue, drinking, and unseasonable exercises, he was seized with fever.
							He began with having pain in the loins; he had heaviness of the head,
							and there was stiffness of the neck. On the first day the alvine
							discharges were bilious, unmixed, <pb n="p.115"/>frothy, high colored,
							and copious; urine black, having a black sediment; he was thirsty,
							tongue dry; no sleep at night. On the second, acute fever, stools more
							copious, thinner, frothy; urine black, an uncomfortable night, slight
							delirium. On the third, all the symptoms exacerbated; an oblong
							distention, of a softish nature, from both sides of the hypochondrium to
							the navel; stools thin, and darkish; urine muddy, and darkish; no sleep
							at night; much talking, laughter, singing, he could not restrain
							himself. On the fourth, in the same state. On the fifth, stools bilious,
							unmixed, smooth, greasy; urine thin, and transparent; slight absence of
							delirium. On the sixth, slight perspiration about the head; extremities
							cold and livid; much tossing about; no passage from the bowels, urine
							suppressed, acute fever. On the seventh, loss of speech; extremities
							could no longer be kept warm; no discharge of urine. On the eighth, a
							cold sweat all over; red rashes with sweat, of a round figure, small,
							like vari, persistent, not subsiding; by means of a slight stimulus, a
							copious discharge from the bowels, of a thin and undigested character,
							with pain; urine acrid, and passed with pain; extremities slightly
							heated; sleep slight, and comatose; speechless; urine thin, and
							transparent. On the ninth, in the same state. On the tenth, no drink
							taken; comatose, sleep slight; alvine discharges the same; urine
							abundant, and thickish; when allowed to stand, the sediment farinaceous
							and white; extremities again cold. On the eleventh, he died. At the
							commencement, and throughout, the respiration was slow and large; there
							was a constant throbbing in the hypochondrium; his age was about
							twenty.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 3 </head>
						               <p>Herophon was seized with an acute fever; alvine discharges at first were
							scanty, and attended with tenesmus; but afterwards they were passed of a
							thin, bilious character, and frequent; there was no sleep; urine black,
							and thin. On the fifth, in the morning, deafness; all the symptoms
							exacerbated; spleen swollen; distention of the hypochondrium; alvine
							discharges scanty, and black; he became delirious. On the sixth,
							delirious; at night, sweating, coldness; the delirium continued. On the
							seventh, he became cold, thirsty, was disordered in mind; at night
							recovered his senses; slept. On the eighth, was feverish;<pb n="p.116"/>
							the spleen diminished in size; quite collected; had pain at first about
							the groin, on the same side as the spleen; had pains in both legs; night
							comfortable; urine better colored, had a scanty sediment. On the ninth,
							sweated; the crisis took place; fever remitted. On the fifth day
							afterwards, fever relapsed, spleen immediately became swollen; acute
							fever; deafness again. On the third day after the relapse, the spleen
							diminished; deafness less; legs painful; sweated during the night;
							crisis took place on the seventeenth day; had no disorder of the senses
							during the relapse.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 4 </head>
						               <p>In Thasus, the wife of Philinus, having been delivered of a daughter, the
							discharge being natural, and other matters going on mildly, on the
							fourteenth day after delivery was seized with fever, attended with
							rigor; was pained at first in the cardiac region of the stomach and
							right hypochondrium; pain in the genital organs; lochial discharge
							ceased. Upon the application of a pessary all these symptoms were
							alleviated; pains of the head, neck, and loins remained; no sleep;
							extremities cold; thirst; bowels in a hot state; stools scanty; urine
							thin, and colorless at first. On the sixth, towards night, senses much
							disordered, but again were restored. On the seventh, thirsty; the
							evacuations bilious, and high colored. On the eighth, had a rigor; acute
							fever; much spasm, with pain; talked much, incoherently; upon the
							application of a suppository, rose to stool, and passed copious
							dejections, with a bilious flux; no sleep. On the ninth, spasms. On the
							tenth, slightly recollected. On the eleventh, slept; had perfect
							recollection, but again immediately wandered; passed a large quantity of
							urine with spasms, (the attendants seldom putting her in mind), it was
							thick, white, like urine which has been shaken after it has stood for a
							considerable time until it has subsided, but it had no sediment; in
							color and consistence, the urine resembled that of cattle, as far as I
							observed. About the fourteenth day, startings over the whole body;
							talked much; slightly collected, but presently became again delirious.
							About the seventeenth day became speechless, on the twentieth died.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 5 </head>
						               <p>The wife of Epicrates, who was lodged at the house<pb n="p.117"/> of
							Archigetes, being near the term of delivery, was seized with a violent
							rigor, and, as was said, she did not become heated; next day the same.
							On the third, she was delivered of a daughter, and everything went on
							properly. On the day following her delivery, she was seized with acute
							fever, pain in the cardiac region of the stomach, and in the genital
							parts. Having had a suppository, was in so far relieved; pain in the
							head, neck, and loins; no sleep; alvine discharges scanty, bilious,
							thin, and unmixed; urine thin, and blackish. Towards the night of the
							sixth day from the time she was seized with the fever, became delirious.
							On the seventh, all the symptoms exacerbated; insomnolency, delirium,
							thirst; stools bilious, and high colored. On the eighth, had a rigor;
							slept more. On the ninth, the same. On the tenth, her limbs painfully
							affected; pain again of the cardiac region of the stomach; heaviness of
							the head; no delirium; slept more; bowels constipated. On the eleventh,
							passed urine of a better color, and having an abundant sediment; felt
							lighter. On the fourteenth had a rigor; acute fever. On the fifteenth,
							had a copious vomiting of bilious and yellow matters; sweated; fever
							gone; at night acute fever; urine thick, sediment white. On the
							seventeenth, an exacerbation; night uncomfortable; no sleep; delirium.
							On the eighteenth, thirsty; tongue parched; no sleep; much delirium;
							legs painfully affected. About the twentieth, in the morning, had as
							light rigor; was comatose; slept tranquilly; had slight vomiting of
							bilious and black matters; towards night deafness. About the
							twenty-first, weight generally in the left side, with pain; slight urine
							thick, muddy, and reddish; when allowed to stand, had no sediment; in
							other respects felt lighter; fever not gone; fauces painful from the
							commencement, and red; uvula retracted; defluxion remained acrid,
							pungent, and saltish throughout. About the twenty-seventh, free of
							fever; sediment in the urine; pain in the side. About the thirty-first,
							was attacked with fever, bilious diarrhea; slight bilious vomiting on
							the fortieth. Had a complete crisis, and was freed from the fever on the
							eightieth day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 6 </head>
						               <p>Cleonactides, who was lodged above the Temple of Hercules, was seized
							with a fever in an irregular form; was pained <pb n="p.118"/>in the head
							and left side from the commencement, and had other pains resembling
							those produced by fatigue; paroxysms of the fevers inconstant and
							irregular; occasional sweats; the paroxysms generally attacked on the
							critical days. About the twenty-fourth was cold in the extremities of
							the hands, vomitings bilious, yellow, and frequent, soon turning to a
							verdigris-green color; general relief. About the thirtieth, began to
							have hemorrhage from both nostrils, and this continued in an irregular
							manner until near the crisis; did not loathe food, and had no thirst
							throughout, nor was troubled with insomnolency; urine thin, and not
							devoid of color. When about the thirtieth day, passed reddish urine,
							having a copious red sediment; was relieved, but afterwards the
							characters of the urine varied, sometimes having sediment, and sometimes
							not. On the sixtieth, the sediment in the urine copious, white, and
							smooth; all the symptoms ameliorated; intermission of the fever; urine
							thin, and well colored. On the seventieth, fever gone for ten days. On
							the eightieth had a rigor, was seized with acute fever, sweated much; a
							red, smooth sediment in the urine; and a perfect crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 7 </head>
						               <p>Meton was seized with fever; there was a painful weight in the loins.
							Next day, after drinking water pretty copiously, had proper evacuations
							from the bowels. On the third, heaviness of the head, stools thin,
							bilious, and reddish. On the fourth, all the symptoms exacerbated; had
							twice a scanty trickling of blood from the right nostril; passed an
							uncomfortable night; alvine discharges like those on the third day;
							urine darkish, had a darkish cloud floating in it, of a scattered form,
							which did not subside. On the fifth, a copious hemorrhage of pure blood
							from the left he sweated, and had a crisis. After the fever restless,
							and had some delirium; urine thin, and darkish; had an affusion of warm
							water on the head; slept and recovered his senses. In this case there
							was no relapse, but there were frequent hemorrhages after the
							crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 8 </head>
						               <p>Erasinus, who lived near the Canal of Bootes, was seized with fever after
							supper; passed the night in an agitated state. During the first day
							quiet, but in pain at night. On the second, symptoms all exacerbated; at
							night delirious. On the <pb n="p.119"/>third, was in a painful
							condition; great incoherence. On the fourth, in a most uncomfortable
							state; had no sound sleep at night, but dreaming and talking; then all
							the appearances worse, of a formidable and alarming character; fear,
							impatience. On the morning of the fifth, was composed, and quite
							coherent, but long before noon was furiously mad, so that he could not
							constrain himself; extremities cold, and somewhat livid; urine without
							sediment; died about sunset. The fever in this case was accompanied by
							sweats throughout; the sweats throughout; the hypochondria were in a
							state of meteorism, with distention and pain; the urine was black, has
							round substances floating in it, which did not subside; the alvine
							evacuations were not stopped; thirst throughout not great; much spasms
							with sweats about the time of death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 9 </head>
						               <p>Criton, in Thasus, while still on foot, and going about, was seized with
							a violent pain in the great toe; he took to bed the same day, had rigors
							and nausea, recovered his heat slightly, at night was delirious. On the
							second, swelling of the whole foot, and about the ankle erythema, with
							distention, and small bullae (phlyctaenae); acute fever; he became
							furiously deranged; alvine discharges bilious, unmixed, and rather
							frequent. He died on the second day from the commencement.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 10 </head>
						               <p>The Clazomenian who was lodged by the Well of Phrynichides was seized
							with fever. He had pain in the head, neck, and loins from the beginning,
							and immediately afterwards deafness; no sleep, acute fever, hypochondria
							elevated with a swelling, but not much distention; tongue dry. On the
							fourth, towards night, he became delirious. On the fifth, in an uneasy
							state. On the sixth, all the symptoms exacerbated. About the eleventh a
							slight remission; from the commencement to the fourteenth day the alvine
							discharges thin, copious, and of the color of water, but were well
							supported; the bowels then became constipated. Urine throughout thin,
							and well colored, and had many substances scattered through it, but no
							sediment. About the sixteenth, urine somewhat thicker, which had a
							slight sediment; somewhat better, and more collected. On the
							seventeenth, urine again thin; swellings about both his ears, with pain;
							no sleep, some incoherence; legs painfully affected. On the twenti-<pb n="p.120"/>eth, free of fever, had a crisis, no sweat, perfectly
							collected. About the twenty-seventh, violent pain of the right hip; it
							speedily went off. The swellings about the ears subsided, and did not
							suppurate, but were painful. About the thirty-first, a diarrhea attended
							with a copious discharge of watery matter, and symptoms of dysentery;
							passed thick urine; swellings about the ears gone. About the fortieth
							day, had pain in the right eye, sight dull. It went away.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 11 </head>
						               <p>The wife of Dromeades having been delivered of a female child, and all
							other matters going on properly, on the second day after was seized with
							rigor and acute fever. Began to have pain about the hypochondrium on the
							first day; had nausea and incoherence, and for some hours afterwards had
							no sleep; respiration rare, large, and suddenly interrupted. On the day
							following that on which she had the rigor, alvine discharges proper;
							urine thick, white, muddy, like urine which has been shaken after
							standing for some time, until the sediment had fallen to the bottom; it
							had no sediment; she did not sleep during the night. On the third day,
							about noon, had a rigor, acute fever; urine the same; pain of the
							hypochondria, nausea, an uncomfortable night, no sleep; a coldish sweat
							all over, but heat quickly restored. On the fourth, slight alleviation
							of the symptoms about the hypochondria; heaviness of the head, with
							pain; somewhat comatose; slight epistaxis, tongue dry, thirst, urine
							thin and oily; slept a little, upon awaking was somewhat comatose;
							slight coldness, slept during the night, was delirious. On the morning
							of the sixth had a rigor, but soon recovered her heat, sweated all over;
							extremities cold, was delirious, respiration rare and large. Shortly
							afterwards spasms from the head began, and she immediately expired.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 12 </head>
						               <p>A man, in a heated state, took supper, and drank more than enough; he
							vomited the whole during the night; acute fever, pain of the right
							hypochondrium, a softish inflammation from the inner part; passed an
							uncomfortable night; urine at the commencement thick, red, but when
							allowed to stand, had no sediment, tongue dry, and not very thirsty. On
							the fourth, acute fever, pains all over. On the fifth, urine smooth,
							oily, and<pb n="p.121"/> copious; acute fever. On the sixth, in the
							evening, very incoherent, no sleep during the night. On the seventh, all
							the symptoms exacerbated; urine of the same characters; much talking,
							and he could not contain himself; the bowels being stimulated, passed a
							watery discharge with lumbrici: night equally painful. In the morning
							had a rigor; acute fever, hot sweat, appeared to be free of fever; did
							not sleep long; after the sleep a chill, ptyalism; in the evening, great
							incoherence; after a little, vomited a small quantity of dark bilious
							matters. On the ninth, coldness, much delirium, did not sleep. On the
							tenth, pains in the limbs, all the symptoms exacerbated; he was
							delirious. On the eleventh, he died.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 13 </head>
						               <p>A woman, who lodged on the Quay, being three months gone with child, was
							seized with fever, and immediately began to have pains in the loins. On
							the third day, pain of the head and neck, extending to the clavicle, and
							right hand; she immediately lost the power of speech; was paralyzed in
							the right hand, with spasms, after the manner of paraplegia; was quite
							incoherent; passed an uncomfortable night; did not sleep; disorder of
							the bowels, attended with bilious, On the fourth, recovered the use of
							her tongue; spasms of the same parts, and general pains remained;
							swelling in the hypochondrium, accompanied with pain; did not sleep, was
							quite incoherent; bowels disordered, urine thin, and not of a good
							color. On the fifth, acute fever; pain of the hypochondrium, quite
							incoherent; alvine evacuations bilious; towards night had a sweat, and
							was freed from the fever. On the sixth, recovered her reason; was every
							way relieved; the pain remained about the left clavicle; was thirsty,
							urine thin, had no sleep. On the seventh trembling, slight coma, some
							incoherence, pains about the clavicle and left arm remained; in all
							other respects was alleviated; quite coherent. For three days remained
							free from fever. On the eleventh, had a relapse, with rigor and fever.
							About the fourteenth day, vomited pretty abundantly bilious and yellow
							matters, had a sweat, the fever went off, by coming to a crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 14 </head>
						               <p>Melidia, who lodged near the Temple of Juno, began to feel a violent pain
							of the head, neck, and chest. She <pb n="p.122"/>was straightway seized
							with acute fever; a slight appearance of the menses; continued pains of
							all these parts. On the sixth, was affected with coma, nausea, and
							rigor; redness about the cheeks; slight delirium. On the seventh, had a
							sweat; the fever intermitted, the pains remained. A relapse; little
							sleep; urine throughout of a good color, but thin; the alvine
							evacuations were thin, bilious, acrid, very scanty, black, and fetid; a
							white, smooth sediment in the urine; had a sweat, and experienced a
							perfect crisis on the eleventh day.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
			         </div>

			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="book">
				           <head>BOOK III</head>

				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>Section I </head>

					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 1 </head>
						               <p>Pythion, who lived by the Temple of the Earth, on the first day,
							trembling commencing from his hands; acute fever, delirium. On the
							second, all the symptoms were exacerbated. On the third, the same. On
							the fourth alvine discharges scanty, unmixed, and bilious. On the fifth,
							all the symptoms were exacerbated, the tremors remained; little sleep,
							the bowels constipated. On the sixth sputa mixed, reddish. On the
							seventh, mouth drawn aside. On the eighth, all the symptoms were
							exacerbated; the tremblings were again constant; urine, from the
							beginning to the eighth day, thin, and devoid of color; substances
							floating in it, cloudy. On the tenth he sweated; sputa somewhat
							digested, had a crisis; urine thinnish about the crisis; but after the
							crisis, on the fortieth day, an abscess about the anus, which passed off
							by a strangury. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It
							is probably that the great discharge of urine brought about the
							resolution of the disease, and the cure of the patient on the fortieth
							day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 2 </head>
						               <p>Hermocrates, who lived by the New Wall, was seized with fever. He began
							to have pain in the head and loins; an empty distention of the
							hypochondrium; the tongue at first was parched; deafness at the
							commencement; there was no sleep; not very thirsty; urine thick and red,
							when allowed to stand it did not subside; alvine discharge very dry, and
							not scanty. On the fifth, urine thin, had substances floating in it<pb n="p.123"/> which did not fall to the bottom; at night he was
							delirious. On the sixth, had jaundice; all the symptoms were
							exacerbated; had no recollection. On the seventh, in an uncomfortable
							state; urine thin, as formerly; on the following days the same. About
							the eleventh day, all the symptoms appeared to be lightened. Coma set
							in; urine thicker, reddish, thin substances below, had no sediment; by
							degrees he became collected. On the fourteenth, fever gone; had no
							sweat; slept, quite collected; urine of the same characters. About the
							seventeenth, had a relapse, became hot. On the following days, acute
							fever, urine thin, was delirious. Again, on the twentieth, had a crisis;
							free of fever; had no sweat; no appetite through the whole time; was
							perfectly collected; could not speak, tongue dry, without thirst; deep
							sleep. About the twenty-fourth day he became heated; bowels loose, with
							a thin, watery discharge; on the following days acute fever, tongue
							parched. On the twenty-seventh he died. In this patient deafness
							continued throughout; the urine either thick and red, without sediment,
							or thin, devoid of color, and, having substances floating in it: he
							could taste nothing. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi>
							It is probably that it was the suppression of the discharges from the
							bowels which occasioned death on the twenty-seventh day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 3 </head>
						               <p>The man who was lodged in the Garden of Dealces: had heaviness of the
							head and pain in the right temple for a considerable time, from some
							accidental cause, was seized with fever, and took to bed. On the second,
							there was a trickling of pure blood from the left nostril, but the
							alvine discharges were proper, urine thin, mixed, having small
							substances floating in it, like coarse barley meal, or semen. On the
							third, acute fever; stools black, thin, frothy, a livid sediment in the
							dejections; slight coma; uneasiness at the times he had to get up;
							sediment in the urine livid, and somewhat viscid. On the fourth, slight
							vomiting of bilious, yellow matters, and, after a short interval, of the
							color of verdigris; a few drops of pure blood ran from the left nostril;
							stools the same; urine the same; sweated about the head and clavicles;
							spleen enlarged, pain of the thigh on the same side; loose swelling of
							the right hypochondrium; at night <pb n="p.124"/>had no sleep, slight
							delirium. On the sixth, stools black, fatty, viscid, fetid; slept, more
							collected. On the seventh, tongue dry, thirsty, did not sleep; was
							somewhat delirious; urine thin, not of a good color. On the eighth,
							stools black, scanty, and compact; slept, became collected; not very
							thirsty. On the ninth had a rigor, acute fever, sweated, a chill, was
							delirious, strabismus of the right eye, tongue dry, thirsty, without
							sleep. On the tenth, much the same. On the eleventh, became quite
							collected; free from fever, slept, urine thin about the crisis. The two
							following days without fever; it returned on the fourteenth, then
							immediately insomnolency and complete delirium. On the fifteenth, urine
							muddy, like that which has been shaken after the sediment has fallen to
							the bottom; acute fever, quite delirious, did not sleep; knees and legs
							painful; after a suppository, had alvine dejections of a black color. On
							the sixteenth, urine thin, had a cloudy eneorema, was delirious. On the
							seventeenth, in the morning, extremities cold, was covered up with the
							bedclothes, acute fever, general sweat, felt relieved, more collected;
							not free of fever, thirsty, vomited yellow bile, in small quantities;
							formed faeces passed from the bowels, but soon afterwards black, scanty,
							and thin; urine thin, not well colored. On the eighteenth, not
							collected, comatose. On the nineteenth, in the same state. On the
							twentieth, slept; quite collected, sweated, free from fever, not
							thirsty, but the urine thin. On the twenty-first, slight delirium;
							somewhat thirsty, pain of the hypochondrium, and throbbing about the
							navel throughout. On sediment in the urine, quite collected.
							Twenty-seventh, pain of the right hip joint; urine thin and bad, a
							sediment; all the other symptoms milder. About the twenty-ninth, pain of
							the right eye; urine thin. Fortieth, dejections pituitous, white, rather
							frequent; sweated abundantly all over; had a complete crisis. </p>

						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is probable that,
							by means of the stools, the urine, and the sweat, this patient was cured
							in forty days. </p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>Section II </head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 4 </head>
						               <p>Case I. In Thasus, Philistes had headache of long continuance, and
							sometimes was confined to bed, with a tendency<pb n="p.125"/> to deep
							sleep; having been seized with continual fevers from drinking, the pain
							was exacerbated; during the night he, at first, became hot. On the first
							day, he vomited some bilious matters, at first yellow, but afterwards of
							a verdigris-green color, and in greater quantity; formed faeces passed
							from the bowels; passed the night uncomfortably. On the second,
							deafness, acute fever; retraction of the right hypochondrium; urine
							thin, transparent, had some small substances like semen floating in it;
							delirium ferox about mid-day. On the third, in an uncomfortable state.
							On the fourth, convulsions; all the symptoms exacerbated. On the fifth,
							early in the morning, died. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the
								characters.</hi> It is probable that the death of the patient on the
							fifth day is to be attributed to a phrenitis, with unfavorable
							evacuations.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 5 </head>
						               <p>Charion, who was lodged at the house of Demaenetus, contracted a fever
							from drinking. Immediately he had a painful heaviness of the head; did
							not sleep; bowels disordered, with thin and somewhat bilious discharges.
							On the third day, acute fever; trembling of the head, but especially of
							the lower lip; after a little time a rigor, convulsions; he was quite
							delirious; passed the night uncomfortably. On the fourth, quiet, slept
							little, talked incoherently. On the fifth, in pain; all the symptoms
							exacerbated; delirium; passed the night uncomfortably; did not sleep. On
							the sixth, in the same state. On the seventh had a rigor, acute fever,
							sweated all over his body; had a crisis. Throughout the alvine
							discharges were bilious, scanty, and unmixed; urine thin, well colored,
							having cloudy substances floating in it. About the eighth day, passed
							urine of a better color, having a white scanty sediment; was collected,
							free from fever for a season. On the ninth it relapsed. About the
							fourteenth, acute fever. On the sixteenth, vomited pretty frequently
							yellow, bilious matters. On the seventeenth had a rigor, acute fever,
							sweated, free of fever; had a crisis; urine, after the relapse and the
							crisis, well colored, having a sediment; neither was he delirious in the
							relapse. On the eighteenth, became a little heated; some thirst, urine
							thin, with cloudy substances floating in it; slight wandering in his
							mind. About the nineteenth, free of fever, had<pb n="p.126"/> a pain in
							his neck; a sediment in the urine. Had a complete crisis on the
							twentieth. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is
							probable that the patient was cured in twenty days, by the abundance of
							bilious stools and urine.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 6 </head>
						               <p>The daughter of Euryanax, a maid, was taken ill of fever. She was free of
							thirst throughout, but had no relish for food. Alvine discharges small,
							urine thin, scanty, not well colored. In the beginning of the fever, had
							a pain about the nates. On the sixth day, was free of fever, did not
							sweat, had a crisis; the complaint about the nates came to a small
							suppuration, and burst at the crisis. After the crisis, on the seventh
							day, had a rigor, became slightly heated, sweated. On the eighth day
							after the rigor, had an inconsiderable rigor; the extremities cold ever
							after. About the tenth day, after a sweat which came on, she became
							delirious, and again immediately afterwards was collected; these
							symptoms were said to have been brought on by eating grapes. After an
							intermission of the twelfth day, she again talked much incoherently; her
							bowels disordered with bilious, scanty, unmixed, thin, acrid discharges;
							she required to get frequently up. She died on the seventh day after the
							return of the delirium. At the commencement of the disease she had pain
							in the throat, and it red throughout, uvula retracted, defluxions
							abundant, thin, acrid; coughed, but had no concocted sputa; during the
							whole time loathed all kinds of food, nor had the least desire of
							anything; had no thirst, nor drank anything worth mentioning; was
							silent, and never spoke a word; despondency; had no hopes of herself.
							She had a congenital tendency to phthisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 7 </head>
						               <p>The woman affected with quinsy, who lodged in the house of Aristion: her
							complaint began in the tongue; speech inarticulate; tongue red and
							parched. On the first day, felt chilly, and afterwards became heated. On
							the third day, a rigor, acute fever; a reddish and hard swelling on both
							sides of the neck and chest, extremities cold and livid; and livid;
							respiration elevated; the drink returned by the nose; she could not
							swallow; alvine and urinary discharges suppressed. On the fourth, all of
							the symptoms were exacerbated. On the fifth she died of the quinsy.<pb n="p.127"/>
							                 <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is probable that
							the cause of death on the sixth day was the suppression of the
							discharges.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 8 </head>
						               <p>The young man who was lodged by the Liars' Market was seized with fever
							from fatigue, labor, and running out of season. On the first day, the
							bowels disordered, with bilious, thin, and copious dejections; urine
							thin and blackish; had no sleep; was thirsty. On the second all the
							symptoms were exacerbated; dejections more copious and unseasonable; he
							had no sleep; disorder of the intellect; slight sweat. On the third day,
							restless, thirst, nausea, much tossing about, bewilderment, delirium;
							extremities livid and cold; softish distention of the hypochondrium on
							both sides. On the fourth, did not sleep; still worse. On the seventh he
							died. He was about twenty years of age. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of
								the characters.</hi>It is probable that the cause of his death on
							the seventh day was the unseasonable practices mentioned above. An acute
							affection.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 9 </head>
						               <p>The woman who lodged at the house of Tisamenas had a troublesome attack
							of iliac passion, much vomiting; could not keep her drink; pains about
							the hypochondria, and pains also in the lower part of the belly;
							constant tormina; not thirsty; became hot; extremities cold throughout,
							with nausea and insomnolency; urine scanty and thin; dejections
							undigested, thin, scanty. Nothing could do her any good. She died.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 10 </head>
						               <p>A woman of those who lodged with Pantimides, from a miscarriage, was
							taken ill of fever. On the first day, tongue dry, thirst, nausea,
							insomnolency, belly disordered, with thin, copious, undigested
							dejections. On the second day, had a rigor, acute fever; alvine
							discharges copious; had no sleep. On the third, pains greater. On the
							fourth, delirious. On the seventh she died. Belly throughout loose, with
							copious, thin, undigested evacuations; urine scanty, thin. An ardent
							fever.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 11 </head>
						               <p>Another woman, after a miscarriage about the fifth month, the wife of
							Ocetes, was seized with fever. At first had sometimes coma and sometimes
							insomnolency; pain of the loins; heaviness of the head. On the second,
							the bowels were disordered, with scanty, thin, and at first unmixed
							dejections. On the third, more copious, and worse; at night did not
							sleep. On <pb n="p.128"/>the fourth was delirious; frights, despondency;
							strabismus of the right eye; a faint cold sweat about the head;
							extremities cold. On the fifth day, all the symptoms were exacerbated;
							talked much incoherently, and again immediately became collected; had no
							thirst; labored under insomnolency; alvine dejections copious, and
							unseasonable throughout; urine scanty, thin, darkish; extremities cold,
							somewhat livid. On the sixth day, in the same state. On the seventh she
							died. Phrenitis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 12 </head>
						               <p>A woman who lodged near the Liars' Market, having then brought forth a
							son in a first and difficult labor, was seized with fever. Immediately
							on the commencement had thirst, nausea, and cardialgia; tongue dry;
							bowels disordered, with thin and scanty dejections; had no sleep. On the
							second, had slight rigor, acute fever; a faint cold sweat about the
							head. On the third, painfully affected; evacuations from the bowels
							undigested, thin, and copious. On the fourth, had a rigor; all the
							symptoms exacerbated; insomnolency. On the fifth, in a painful state. On
							the sixth, in the same state; discharges from the bowels liquid and
							copious. On the seventh, had a rigor, fever acute; much thirst; much
							tossing about; towards evening a cold sweat over all; extremities cold,
							could no longer be kept warm; and again at night had a rigor;
							extremities could not be warmed; she did not sleep; was slightly
							delirious, and again speedily collected. On the eighth, about mid-day,
							she became warm, was thirsty, comatose, had nausea; vomited small
							quantities of yellowish bile; restless at night, did not sleep; passed
							frequently large quantities of urine without consciousness. On the
							ninth, all the symptoms gave way; comatose, towards evening slight
							rigors; small vomitings of bile. On the tenth, rigor; exacerbation of
							the fever, did not sleep at all; in the morning passed much urine having
							a sediment; extremities recovered their heat. On the eleventh, vomited
							bile of a verdigris-green color; not long after had a rigor, and again
							the extremities cold; towards evening a rigor, a cold sweat, much
							vomiting; passed a painful night. On the twelfth, had copious black and
							fetid vomitings; much hiccup, painful thirst. On the thirteenth,
							vomitings black, fetid, and copious; rigor about mid-day, loss of
							speech. On the four-<pb n="p.129"/>teenth, some blood ran from her nose,
							she died. In this case the bowels were loose throughout; with rigors:
							her age about seventeen. An ardent fever.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>Section III -- Constitution 2</head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 1 </head>
						               <p>The year was southerly, rainy; no winds throughout. Droughts having
							prevailed during the previous seasons of the year, the south winds
							towards the rising of Arcturus were attended with much rain. Autumn
							gloomy and cloudy, with copious rains. Winter southerly, damp, and soft.
							But long after the solstice, and near the equinox, much wintery weather
							out of season; and when now close to the equinox, northerly, and
							winterly weather for no long time. The spring again southerly, calm,
							much rain until the dog-days. Summer fine and hot; great suffocating
							heats. The Etesian winds blew small and irregular; again, about the
							season of Arcturus, much rains with north winds.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 2 </head>
						               <p>The year being southerly, damp, and soft towards winter, all were
							healthy, except those affected with phthisis, of whom we shall write
							afterwards.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 3 </head>
						               <p>Early in spring, along with the prevailing cold, there were many cases of
							erysipelas, some from a manifest cause, and some not. They were of a
							malignant nature, and proved fatal to many; many had sore-throat and
							loss of speech. There were many cases of ardent fever, phrensy, aphthous
							affections of the mouth, tumors on the genital organs; of ophthalmia,
							anthrax, disorder of the bowels, anorexia, with thirst and without it;
							of disordered urine, large in quantity, and bad in quality; of persons
							affected with coma for a long time, and then falling into a state of
							insomnolency. There were many cases of failure of crisis, and many of
							unfavorable crisis; many of dropsy and of phthisis. Such were the
							diseases then epidemic. There were patients affected with every one of
							the species which have been mentioned, and many died. The symptoms in
							each of these cases were as follows:</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 4 </head>
						               <p>In many cases erysipelas, from some obvious cause, such as an accident,
							and sometimes from even a very small wound, broke out all over the body,
							especially, in persons about sixty<pb n="p.130"/> years of age, about
							the head, if such an accident was neglected in the slightest degree; and
							this happened in some who were under treatment; great inflammation took
							place, and the erysipelas quickly spread all over. in the most of them
							abscessed ended in suppurations, and there were great fallings off
							(sloughing) of the flesh, tendons, and bones; and the defluxion which
							seated in the part was not like pus, but a sort of putrefaction, and the
							running was large and of various characters. Those cases in which any of
							these things happened about the head were accompanied with falling off
							of the hairs of the head and chin, the bones were laid bare and
							separated, and there were excessive runnings; and these symptoms
							happened in fevers and without fevers. But these things were more
							formidable in appearance than dangerous; for when the concoction in
							these cases turned to a suppuration, most of them recovered; but when
							the inflammation and erysipelas disappeared, and when no abscess was
							formed, a great number of these died. In like manner, the same things
							happened to whatever part of the body the disease wandered, for in many
							cases both forearm and arm dropped off; and in those cases in which it
							fell upon the sides, the parts there, either before or behind, got into
							a bad state; and in some cases the whole femur and bones of the leg and
							whole foot were laid bare. But of all such cases, the most formidable
							were those which took place about the pubes and genital organs.<note>The
								classical reader will here call to his recollection a striking
								passage in the celebrated description of the Plague of Athens, as
								given by Thucydides: "For the mischief, being at first seated in the
								head, spread over the whole body, and if one survived the most
								formidable symptoms, an attack on the extremities manifested itself;
								for it was determined to the genital organs and to the hands and
								feet, and many escaped with losing them, and some with the loss of
								their eyes." (ii., 49.)</note> Such was the nature of these cases
							when attended with sores, and proceeding from an external cause; but the
							same things occurred in fevers, before fevers, and after fevers. But
							those cases in which an abscess was formed, and turned to a suppuration,
							or a seasonable diarrhea or discharge of good urine took place, were
							relieved thereby: but those cases in which none of these symptoms
							occurred, but they disappeared without a crisis, proved fatal. The
							greater number of these erysipelatous cases <pb n="p.131"/>took place in
							the spring, but were prolonged through the summer and during autumn.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 5 </head>
						               <p>In certain cases there was much disorder, and tumors about the fauces,
							and inflammations of the tongue, and abscesses about the teeth. And many
							were attacked with impairment or loss of speech; at first, those in the
							commencement of phthisis, but also persons in ardent fever and in
							phrenitis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 6 </head>
						               <p>The cases of ardent fever and phrenitis occurred early in spring after
							the cold set in, and great numbers were taken ill at that time, and
							these cases were attended with acute and fatal symptoms. The
							constitution of the ardent fevers which then occurred was as follows: at
							the commencement they were affected with coma, nausea, and rigors; fever
							acute, not much thirst, nor delirium, slight epistaxis, the paroxysms
							for the most part on even days; and, about the time of the paroxysms,
							forgetfulness, loss of strength and of speech, the extremities, that is
							to say, the hands and feet, at all times, but more especially about the
							time of the paroxysms, were colder than natural; they slowly and
							imperfectly became warmed, and again recovered their recollection and
							speech. They were constantly affected either with coma, in which they
							got no sleep, or with insomnolency, attended with pains; most had
							disorders of the bowels, attended with undigested, thin, and copious
							evacuations; urine copious, thin, having nothing critical nor favorable
							about it; neither was there any other critical appearance in persons
							affected thus; for neither was there any proper hemorrhage, nor any
							other of the accustomed evacuations, to prove a crisis. They died, as it
							happened, in an irregular manner, mostly about the crisis, but in some
							instances after having lost their speech for a long time, and having had
							copious sweats. These were the symptoms which marked the fatal cases of
							ardent fever; similar symptoms occurred in the phrenitic cases; but
							these were particularly free from thirst, and none of these had wild
							delirium as in other cases, but they died oppressed by a bad tendency to
							sleep, and stupor.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 7 </head>
						               <p>But there were also other fevers, as will be described. Many had their
							mouths affected with aphthous ulcerations. There were also many
							defluxions about the genital parts, and<pb n="p.132"/> ulcerations,
							boils (phymata), externally and internally, about the groins. Watery
							ophthalmies of a chronic character, with pains; fungous excrescences of
							the eyelids, externally and internally, called fig, which destroyed the
							sight of many persons. There were fungous growths, in many other
							instances, on ulcers, especially on those seated on the genital organs.
							There were many attacks of carbuncle (anthrax) through the summer, and
							other affections, which are called "the putrefaction" (<hi rend="ital">seps</hi>); also large ecthymata, and large tetters (<hi rend="ital">herpetes</hi>) in many instances.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 8 </head>
						               <p>And many and serious complaints attacked many persons in the region of
							the belly. In the first place, tenesmus, accompanied with pain, attacked
							many, but more especially children, and all who had not attained to
							puberty; and the most of these died. There were many cases of lientery
							and of dysentery; but these were not attended with much pain. The
							evacuations were bilious, and fatty, and thin, and watery; in many
							instances the disease terminated in this way, with and without fever;
							there were painful tormina and volvuli of a malignant kind; copious
							evacuations of the contents of the guts, and yet much remained behind;
							and the passages did not carry off the pains, but yielded with
							difficulty to the means administered; for in most cases purgings were
							hurtful to those affected in this manner; many died speedily, but in
							many others they held out longer. In a word, all died, both those who
							had acute attacks and those who had chronic, most especially from
							affections of the belly, for it was the belly which carried them all
							off.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 9 </head>
						               <p>All persons had an aversion to food in all the afore-mentioned complaints
							to a degree such as I never met with before, and persons in these
							complaints most especially, and those recovering from them, and in all
							other diseases of a mortal nature. Some were troubled with thirst, and
							some not; and both in febrile complaints and in others no one drank
							unseasonably or disobeyed injunctions.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 10 </head>
						               <p>The urine in many cases was not in proportion to the drink administered,
							but greatly in excess; and the badness of the urine voided was great,
							for it had not the proper thickness, nor concoction, nor purged
							properly; for in many cases purgings<pb n="p.133"/> by the bladder
							indicate favorably, but in the greatest number they indicated a melting
							of the body, disorder of the bowels, pains, and a want of
								crisis.<note>It will readily be understood that a colliquative
								diabetes would prove a very unfavorable complication of these
								complaints.</note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 11 </head>
						               <p>Persons laboring under phrenitis and causus were particularly disposed to
							coma; but also in all other great diseases which occurred along with
							fever. In the main, most cases were attended either by heavy coma, or by
							short and light sleep.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 12 </head>
						               <p>And many other forms of fevers were then epidemic, of tertian, of
							quartan, of nocturnal,<note>By nocturnal fevers, according to Galen, was
								meant quotidians, which had their paroxysms during the night.</note>
							of continual, of chronic, of erratic, of fevers attended with nausea,
							and of irregular fevers. All these were attended with much disorder, for
							the bowels in most cases were disordered, accompanied with rigors,
							sweats not of a critical character, and with the state of the urine as
							described. In most instances the disease was protracted, for neither did
							the deposits which took place prove critical as in other cases; for in
							all complaints and in all cases there was difficulty of crisis, want of
							crisis, and protraction of the disease, but most especially in these. A
							few had the crisis about the eightieth day, but in most instances it
							(the disease?) left them irregularly. A few of them died of dropsy
							without being confined to bed. And in many other diseases people were
							troubled with swelling, but more especially in phthisical cases.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 13 </head>
						               <p>The greatest and most dangerous disease, and the one that proved fatal to
							the greatest number, was consumption. With many persons it commenced
							during the winter, and of these some were confined to bed, and others
							bore up on foot; the most of those died early in spring who were
							confined to bed; of the others, the cough left not a single person, but
							it became milder through the summer; during the autumn, all these were
							confined to bed, and many of them died, but in the greater number of
							cases the disease was long protracted. Most of these were suddenly
							attacked with these diseases, having frequent rigors, often continual
							and acute fevers; unseasonable, copious,<pb n="p.134"/> and cold sweats
							throughout; great coldness, from which they had great difficulty in
							being restored to heat; the bowels variously constipated, and again
							immediately in a loose state, but towards the termination in all cases
							with violent looseness of the bowels; a determination downwards of all
							matters collected about the lungs; urine excessive, and not good;
							troublesome melting. The coughs throughout were frequent, and copious,
							digested, and liquid, but not brought up with much pain; and even when
							they had some slight pain, in all cases the purging of the matters about
							the lungs went on mildly. The fauces were not very irritable, nor were
							they troubled with any saltish humors; but there were viscid, white,
							liquid, frothy, and copious defluxions from the head. But by far the
							greatest mischief attending these and the other complaints, was the
							aversion to food, as has been described. For neither been described. For
							neither had they any relish for drink along with their food, but
							continued without thirst. There was heaviness of the body, disposition
							to coma, in most cases swelling, which ended in dropsy; they had rigors,
							and were delirious towards death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 14 </head>
						               <p>The form of body peculiarly subject to phthisical complaints was the
							smooth, the whitish, that resembling the lentil; the reddish, the
							blue-eyed, the leucophlegmatic, and that with the scapulae having the
							appearance of wings: and women in like manner, with regard to the
							melancholic and subsanguineous, phrenitic and dysenteric affections
							principally attacked them. Tenesmus troubled young persons of a
							phlegmatic temperament. Chronic diarrhoea, acrid and viscid discharges
							from the bowels, attacked those who were troubled with bitter bile.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 15 </head>
						               <p>To all those which have been described, the season of spring was most
							inimical, and proved fatal to the greatest numbers: the summer was the
							most favorable to them, and the fewest died then; in autumn, and under
							the Pleiades, again there died great numbers. It appears to me,
							according to the reason of things, that the coming on of summer should
							have done good in these cases; for winter coming on cures the diseases
							of summer, and summer coming on removes the diseases of winter. And yet
							the summer in question was not of itself well constituted, for<pb n="p.135"/> it became suddenly hot, southerly, and calm; but, not
							withstanding, it proved beneficial by producing a change on the other
							constitution.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
						               <head>Part 16 </head>
						               <p>I look upon it as being a great part of the art to be able to judge
							properly of that which has been written. For he that knows and makes a
							proper use of these things, would appear to me not likely to commit any
							great mistake in the art. He ought to learn accurately the constitution
							of every one of the seasons, and of the diseases; whatever that is
							common in each constitution and disease is good, and whatever is bad;
							whatever disease will be protracted and end in death, and whatever will
							be protracted and end in recovery; which disease of an acute nature will
							end in death, and which in recovery. From these it is easy to know the
							order of the critical days, and prognosticate from them accordingly. And
							to a person who is skilled in these things, it is easy to know to whom,
							when, and how aliment ought to be administered.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>Section 17 -- Sixteen Cases </head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case I </head>
						               <p>In Thasus, the Parian who lodged above the Temple of Diana was seized
							with an acute fever, at first of a continual and ardent type; thirsty,
							inclined to be comatose at first, and afterwards troubled with
							insomnolency; bowels disordered at the beginning, urine thin. On the
							sixth day, passed oily urine, was delirious. On the seventh, all the
							symptoms were exacerbated; had no sleep, but the urine of the same
							characters, and the understanding disordered; alvine dejections bilious
							and fatty. On the eighth, a slight epistaxis; small vomiting of
							verdigris-green matters; slept a little. On the ninth, in the same
							state. On the tenth, all the symptoms gave way. On the eleventh, he
							sweated, but not over the whole body; he became cold, but immediately
							recovered his heat again. On the fourteenth, acute fever; discharges
							bilious, thin, and copious; substances floating in the urine; he became
							incoherent. On the seventeenth, in a painful state, for he had no sleep,
							and the fever was more intense. On the twentieth, sweated all over;
							apyrexia, dejections bilious; aversion to food, comatose. On the
							twenty-fourth, had a relapse.<pb n="p.136"/> On the thirty-fourth,
							apyrexia; bowels not confined; and he again recovered his heat.
							Fortieth, apyrexia, bowels confined for no long time, aversion to food;
							had again slight symptoms of fever, and throughout in an irregular form;
							apyrexia at times, and at others not; for if the fever intermitted, and
							was alleviated for a little, it immediately relapsed again; he used much
							and improper food; sleep bad; about the time of the relapse he was
							delirious; passed thick urine at that time, but troubled, and of bad
							characters; bowels at first confined, and again loose; slight fevers of
							a continual type; discharges copious and thin. On the hundred and
							twentieth day he died. In this patient the bowels were constantly from
							the first either loose, with bilious, liquid, and copious dejections, or
							constipated with hot and undigested faeces; the urine throughout bad;
							for the most part coma, or insomnolency with pain; continued aversion to
							food. Ardent fever. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi>
							It is probable that the weakness produced by the fever, the phrenitis,
							and affection of the hypochondrium caused death on the hundred and
							twentieth day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 2 </head>
						               <p>In Thasus, the woman who lodged near the Cold Water, on the third day
							after delivery of a daughter, the lochial discharge not taking place,
							was seized with acute fever, accompanied with rigors. But a considerable
							time before delivery she was feverish, confined to bed, and loathed her
							food. After the rigor which took place, continual and acute fevers, with
							rigors. On the eighth and following days, was very incoherent, and
							immediately afterwards became collected; bowels disordered, with
							copious, thin, watery, and bilious stools; no thirst. On the eleventh
							was collected, but disposed to coma; urine copious, thin, and black; no
							sleep. On the twentieth, slight chills, and immediately afterwards was
							warm; slight incoherence; no sleep; with regard to the bowels, in the
							same condition; urine watery, and copious. On the twenty-seventh, free
							from fever; bowels constipated; not long afterwards violent pain of the
							right hip-joint for a considerable time; fevers afterwards supervened;
							urine watery. On the fortieth, complaints about the hip-joint better;
							continued coughs, with copious, watery sputa; bowels constipated;
							aversion to food; urine the same; fever not leaving<pb n="p.137"/> her
							entirely, but having paroxysms in an irregular form, sometimes present,
							sometimes not. On the sixtieth, the coughs left her without a crisis,
							for no concoction of the sputa took place, nor any of the usual
							abscesses; jaw on the right side convulsively retracted; comatose, was
							again incoherent, and immediately became collected; utter aversion to
							food; the jaw became relaxed; alvine discharges small, and bilious;
							fever more acute, affected with rigors; on the following days lost her
							speech, and again became collected, and talked. On the eightieth she
							died. In this case the urine throughout was black, thin, and watery;
							coma supervened; there was aversion to food, despondency, and
							insomnolency; irritability, restlessness; she was of a melancholic turn
							of mind. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is
							probable that the suppression of the lochial discharge caused death on
							the day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 3 </head>
						               <p>In Thasus, Pythion, who was lodged above the Temple of Hercules, from
							labor, fatigue, and neglected diet, was seized with strong rigor and
							acute fever; tongue dry, thirsty, and bilious; had no sleep; urine
							darkish, eneorema floating on the top of the urine, did not subside. On
							the second day, about noon, coldness of the extremities, especially
							about the hands and head; loss of speech and of articulation; breathing
							short for a considerable time; recovered his heat; thirst; passed the
							night quietly; slight sweats about the head. On the third, passed the
							day in a composed state; in the evening, about sunset, slight chills;
							nausea, agitation; passed the night in a painful state; had no sleep;
							small stools of compact faeces passed from the bowels. On the fourth, in
							the morning, composed; about noon all the symptoms became exacerbated;
							coldness, loss of speech, and of articulation; became worse; recovered
							his heat after a time; passed black urine, having substances floating in
							it; the night quiet; slept. On the fifth, seemed to be lightened, but a
							painful weight about the belly; thirsty, passed the night in a painful
							state. On the sixth, in the morning, in a quiet state; in the evening
							the pains greater; had a paroxysm; in the evening the bowels properly
							opened by a small clyster; slept at night.<pb n="p.138"/> On the
							seventh, during the day, in a state of nausea, somewhat disturbed;
							passed urine of the appearance of oil; at night, much agitation, was
							incoherent, did not sleep. On the eighth, in the morning, slept a
							little; but immediately coldness, loss of speech, respiration small and
							weak; but in the evening recovered his heat again; was delirious, but
							towards day was somewhat lightened; stools small, bilious, and unmixed.
							On the ninth, affected with coma, and with nausea when roused; not very
							thirsty; about sunset he became restless and incoherent; passed a bad
							night. On the tenth, in the morning, had become speechless; great
							coldness; acute fever; much perspiration; he died. His sufferings were
							on the even days. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It
							is probable that the excessive sweats caused death on the tenth day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 4 </head>
						               <p>The patient affected with phrenitis, having taken to bed on the first
							day, vomited largely of verdigris-green and thin matters; fever,
							accompanied with rigors, copious and continued sweats all over;
							heaviness of the head and neck, with pain; urine thin, substances
							floating in the urine small, scattered, did not subside; had copious
							dejections from the bowels; very delirious; no sleep. On the second, in
							the morning, loss of speech; acute fever; he sweated, fever did not
							leave him; palpitations over the whole body, at night, convulsions. On
							the third, all the symptoms exacerbated; he died. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is probable that the sweats
							and convulsions caused death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 5 </head>
						               <p>In Larissa, a man, who was bald, suddenly was seized with pain in the
							right thigh; none of the things which were administered did him any
							good. On the first day, fever acute, of the ardent type, not agitated,
							but the pains persisted. On the second, the pains in the thigh abated,
							but the fever increased; somewhat tossed about; did not sleep;
							extremities cold; passed a large quantity of urine, not of a good
							character. On the third, the pain of the thigh ceased; derangement of
							the intellect, confusion, and much tossing about. On the fourth, about
							noon, he died. An acute disease.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 6 </head>
						               <p>In Abdera, Pericles was seized with a fever of the<pb n="p.139"/> acute,
							continual type, with pain; much thirst, nausea, could not retain his
							drink; somewhat swelled about the spleen, with heaviness of the head. On
							the first day, had hemorrhage from the left nostril, but still the fever
							became more violent; passed much muddy, white urine, which when allowed
							to stand did not subside. On the second day, all the symptoms were
							exacerbated, yet the urine was thick, and more inclined to have a
							sediment; the nausea less; he slept. On the third, fever was milder;
							abundance of urine, which was concocted, and had a copious sediment;
							passed a quiet night. On the fourth, had a copious and warm sweat all
							over about noon; was free of fever, had a crisis, no relapse. An acute
							affection.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 7 </head>
						               <p>In Abdera, the young woman who was lodged in the Sacred Walk was seized
							with an ardent fever. She was thirsty, and could not sleep; had
							menstruation for the first time. On the sixth, much nausea, flushing,
							was chilly, and tossed about. On the seventh, in the same state; urine
							thin,but of a good color; no disturbance about the bowels. On the
							eighth, deafness, acute fever, insomnolency, nausea, rigors, became
							collected; urine the same. On the ninth, in the same state, and also on
							the following days; thus the deafness persisted. On the fourteenth,
							disorder of the intellect; the fever abated. On the seventeenth, a
							copious hemorrhage from the nose; the deafness slightly better; and on
							the following days, nausea, deafness, and incoherence. On the twentieth,
							pain of the feet; deafness and delirium left her; a small hemorrhage
							from the nose; sweat, apyrexia. On the twenty-fourth, the fever
							returned, deafness again; pain of the feet remained; incoherence. On the
							twenty-seventh, had a copious sweat, apyrexia; the deafness left her;
							the pain of her feet partly remained; in other respects had a complete
							crisis. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is
							probable that the restoration of health on the twentieth day was the
							result of the evacuation of urine.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 8 </head>
						               <p>In Abdera, Anaxion, who was lodged near the Thracian Gates, was seized
							with an acute fever; continued pain of the right side; dry cough,
							without expectoration during the<pb n="p.140"/> first days, thirst,
							insomnolency; urine well colored, copious, and thin. On the sixth,
							delirious; no relief from the warm applications. On the seventh, in a
							painful state, for the fever while the pains did not abate, and the
							cough was troublesome, and attended with dyspnoea. On the eighth, I
							opened a vein at the elbow, and much blood, of a proper character,
							flowed; the pains were abated, but the dry coughs continued. On the
							eleventh, the fever diminished; slight sweats about the head; coughs,
							with more liquid sputa; he was relieved. On the twentieth, sweat,
							apyrexia; but after the crisis he was thirsty, and the expectorations
							were not good. On the twenty-seventh the fever relapsed; he coughed, and
							brought up much concocted sputa: sediment in the urine copious and
							white; he became free of thirst, and the respiration was good. On the
							thirty-fourth, sweated all over, apyrexia general crisis. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is probable that
							the evacuation of the sputa brought about the recovery on the
							thirty-fourth day. </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 9 </head>
						               <p> In Abdera, Heropythus, while still on foot, had pain in the head, and
							not long afterwards he took to bed; he lived near the High Street. Was
							seized with acute fever of the ardent type; vomitings at first of much
							bilious matter; thirst; great restlessness; urine thin, black,
							substances sometimes floating high in it, and sometimes not; passed the
							night in a painful state; paroxysms of the fever diversified, and for
							the most part irregular. About the fourteenth day, deafness; the fever
							increased; urine the same. On the twentieth and following days, much
							delirium. On the thirtieth, copious hemorrhage from the nose, and became
							more collected; deafness continued, but less; the fever diminished; on
							the following days, frequent hemorrhages, at short intervals. About the
							sixtieth, the hemorrhages ceased, but violent pain of the hip-joint, and
							increase of fever. Not long afterwards, pains of all the inferior rule,
							that either the fever and deafness increased, or, pains of the inferior
							parts were increased. About the eightieth day, all the complaints gave
							way, without leaving any behind; for the urine was of a good color, and
							had a copious sediment, while the delirium<pb n="p.141"/> became less.
							About the hundredth day, disorder of the bowels, with copious and
							bilious evacuations, and these continued for a considerable time, and
							again assumed the dysenteric form with pain; but relief of all the other
							complaints. On the whole, the fevers went off, and the deafness ceased.
							On the hundred and twentieth day, had a complete crisis. Ardent fever.
								<hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is probable
							that the bilious discharge brought about the recovery on the hundred and
							twentieth day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 10 </head>
						               <p>In Abdera, Nicodemus was seized with fever from venery and drinking. At
							the commencement he was troubled with nausea and cardialgia; thirsty,
							tongue was parched; urine thin and dark. On the second day, the fever
							exacerbated; he was troubled with rigors and nausea; had no sleep;
							vomited yellow bile; urine the same; passed a quiet night, and slept. On
							the third, a general remission; amelioration; but about sunset felt
							again somewhat uncomfortable; passed an uneasy night. On the fourth,
							rigor, much fever, general pains; urine thin, with substances floating
							in it; again a quiet night. On the fifth, all the symptoms remained, but
							there was an amelioration. On the sixth, some general pains; substances
							floating in the urine; very incoherent. On the seventh, better. On the
							eighth, all the other symptoms abated. On the tenth, and following days,
							there were pains, but all less; in this case throughout, the paroxysms
							and pains were greater on the even days. On the twentieth, the urine
							white and thick, but when allowed to stand had no sediment; much sweat;
							seemed to be free from fever; but again in the evening he became hot,
							with the same pains, rigor, thirst, slightly incoherent. On the
							twenty-fourth, urine copious, white, with an abundant sediment; a
							copious and warm sweat all over; apyrexia; the fever came to its crisis.
								<hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is probable
							that the cure was owing to the bilious evacuations and the sweats.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 11 </head>
						               <p>In Thasus, a woman, of a melancholic turn of mind, from some accidental
							cause of sorrow, while still going about, became affected with loss of
							sleep, aversion to food, and had thirst and nausea. She lived near the
							Pylates, upon the Plain. On the first, at the commencement of night,
							frights, much <pb n="p.142"/>talking, despondency, slight fever; in the
							morning, frequent spasms, and when they ceased, she was incoherent and
							talked obscurely; pains frequent, great and continued. On the second, in
							the same state; had no sleep; fever more acute. On the third, the spasms
							left her; but coma, and disposition to sleep, and again awaked, started
							up, and could not contain herself; much incoherence; acute fever; on
							that night a copious sweat all over; apyrexia, slept, quite collected;
							had a crisis. About the third day, the urine black, thin, substances
							floating in it generally round, did not fall to the bottom; about the
							crisis a copious menstruation.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 12 </head>
						               <p>In Larissa, a young unmarried woman was seized with a fever of the acute
							and ardent type; insomnolency, thirst; tongue sooty and dry; urine of a
							good color, but thin. On the second, in an uneasy state, did not sleep.
							On the third, alvine discharges copious, watery, and greenish, and on
							the following days passed such with relief. On the fourth, passed a
							small quantity of thin urine, having substances floating towards its
							surface, which did not subside; was delirious towards night. On the
							sixth, a great hemorrhage from the nose; a chill, with a copious and hot
							sweat all over; apyrexia, had a crisis. In the fever, and when it had
							passed the crisis, the menses took place for the first time, for she was
							a young woman. Throughout she was oppressed with nausea, and rigors;
							redness of the face; pain of the eyes; heaviness of the head; she had no
							relapse, but the fever came to a crisis. The pains were on the even
							days.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 13 </head>
						               <p>Apollonius, in Abdera, bore up (under the fever?) for some time, without
							betaking himself to bed. His viscera were enlarged, and for a
							considerable time there was a constant pain about the liver, and then he
							became affected with jaundice; he was flatulent, and of a whitish
							complexion. Having eaten beef, and drunk unseasonably, he became a
							little heated at first, and betook himself to bed, and having used large
							quantities of milk, that of goats and sheep, and both boiled and raw,
							with a bad diet otherwise, great mischief was occasioned by all these
							things; for the fever was exacerbated, and of the food taken scarcely
							any portion worth mentioning was passed from the bowels; the urine was
							thin and scanty; no sleep; troublesome <pb n="p.143"/>meteorism; much
							thirst; disposition to coma; painful swelling of the right
							hypochondrium; extremities altogether coldish; slight incoherence,
							forgetfulness of everything he said; he was beside himself. About the
							fourteenth day after he betook himself to bed, had a rigor, became
							heated, and was seized with furious delirium; loud cries, much talking,
							again composed, and then coma came on; afterwards the bowels disordered,
							with copious, bilious, unmixed, and undigested stools; urine black,
							scanty, and thin; much restlessness; alvine evacuations of varied
							characters, either black, scanty, and verdigris-green, or fatty,
							undigested, and acrid; and at times the dejections resembled milk. About
							the twenty-fourth, enjoyed a calm; other matters in the same state;
							became somewhat collected; remembered nothing that had happened since he
							was confined to bed; immediately afterwards became delirious; every
							symptom rapidly getting worn. About the thirtieth, acute fever; stools
							copious and thin; was delirious; extremities cold; loss of speech. On
							the thirty-fourth he died. In this case, as far as I saw, the bowels
							were disordered; urine thin and black; disposition to coma;
							insomnolency; extremities cold; delirious throughout. Phrenitis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 14 </head>
						               <p>In Cyzicus, a woman who had brought forth twin daughters, after a
							difficult labor, and in whom the lochial discharge was insufficient, at
							first was seized with an acute fever, attended with chills; heaviness of
							the head and neck, with pain; insomnolency from the commencement; she
							was silent, sullen, and disobedient; urine thin, and devoid of color;
							thirst, nausea for the most part; bowels irregularly disordered, and
							again constipated. On the sixth, towards night, talked much
							incoherently; had no sleep. About the eleventh day was seized with wild
							delirium, and again became collected; urine black, thin, and again
							deficient, and of an oily appearance; copious, thin, and disordered
							evacuations from the bowels. On the fourteenth, frequent
							convulsions;extremities cold; not in anywise collected; suppression of
							urine. On the sixteenth loss of speech. On the seventeenth, she died.
							Phrenitis. <hi rend="ital">Explanation of the characters.</hi> It is
							probable that death was caused, on the seventeenth day, by the affection
							of the brain consequent upon her accouchement.</p>
					             </div>
					             <pb n="p.144"/>
					             <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 15 </head>
						               <p>In Thasus, the wife of Dealces, who was lodged upon the Plain, from
							sorrow was seized with an acute fever, attended with chills. From first
							to last she wrapped herself up in her bedclothes; still silent, she
							fumbled, picked, bored, and gathered hairs (from them); tears, and again
							laughter; no sleep; bowels irritable, but passed nothing; when directed,
							drank a little; urine thin and scanty; to the touch of the hand the
							fever was slight; coldness of the extremities. On the ninth, talked much
							incoherently, and again became composed and silent. On the fourteenth,
							breathing rare, large, at intervals; and again hurried respiration. On
							the sixteenth, looseness of the bowels from a stimulant clyster;
							afterwards she passed her drink, nor could retain anything, for she was
							completely insensible; skin parched and tense. On the twentieth, much
							talk, and again became composed; loss of speech; respiration hurried. On
							the twenty-first she died. Her respiration throughout was rare and
							large; she was totally insensible; always wrapped up in her bedclothes;
							either much talk, or completely silent throughout. Phrenitis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
						               <head>Case 16 </head>
						               <p>In Meliboea, a young man having become heated by drinking and much
							venery, was confined to bed; he was affected with rigors and nausea;
							insomnolency and absence of thirst. On the first day much faeces passed
							from the bowels along with a copious flux; and on the following days he
							passed many watery stools of a green color; urine thin, scanty, and
							deficient in color; respiration rare, large, at long intervals; softish
							distention of the hypochondrium, of an oblong form, on both sides;
							continued palpitation in the epigastric region throughout; passed urine
							of an oily appearance. On the tenth, he had calm delirium, for he was
							naturally of an orderly and quiet disposition; skin parched and tense;
							dejections either copious and thin, or bilious and fatty. On the
							fourteenth, all the symptoms were exacerbated; he became delirious, and
							talked much incoherently. On the twentieth, wild delirium, On the
							twentieth, wild delirium, jactitation, passed no urine; small drinks
							were retained. On the twenty-fourth he died. Phrenitis.<pb n="p.145"/>
                     </p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
			         </div>


		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
