<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>EPIDEMICS I AND III </title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 1, 2005</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							              <date>1923</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="">English</language>
				        <language ident="">Greek</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-29" who="Thibault Clérice">Bumped URN</change>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng"
              type="translation"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg006.perseus-eng4">
			         <pb n="p.147"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="book">
				           <head>EPIDEMICS I</head>
				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>F<hi rend="sc">IRST</hi> C<hi rend="sc">ONSTITUTION</hi>
                  </head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 1 </head>
						               <p>I. I<hi rend="sc">N</hi> Thasos during autumn, about the time of the
							equinox to near the setting of the Pleiades,<note>
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">U(PD</foreign> in expressions denoting time seems
								in Hippocrates to mean "about" or "during." The period is roughly
								from September 21 to November 8.</note> there were many rains,
							gently continuous, with southerly winds. Winter southerly,<note>That is,
								the winds were generally from the south, and such north winds as
								blew were light.</note> north winds light, droughts ; on the whole,
							the winter was like a spring. Spring southerly and chilly ; slight
							showers. Summer in general cloudy. No rain. Etesian winds few, light and
							irregular.</p>
						               <p>The whole weather proved southerly, with droughts, but early in the
							spring, as the previous constitution had proved the opposite and
							northerly, a few patients suffered from ardent fevers, and these very
							mild, causing hemorrhage in few cases and no deaths. Many had swellings
							beside one ear, or both ears, in most cases unattended with
								fever,<note>Or, punctuating after <foreign xml:lang="grc">=(WTA</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">PLEI/S1TOIS1IN</foreign>, "There were swellings beside the
								ears, in many cases on one side, but in most on both." The epidemio
								was obviously mumps.</note> so that confinement to bed was
							unnecessary. In some cases there was slight heat, but in all the
							swellings subsided without causing harm ; in no case was there
							suppuration such as attends swellings of other origin. This was the
							character of them :--flabby, big, spreading, with neither inflammation
							nor pain ; in every case they</p>
						               <pb n="p.149"/>
						               <p>disappeared without a sign.<note>That is, with no symptoms indicative of
								a crisis.</note> The sufferers were youths, young men, and men in
							their prime, usually those who frequented the wrestling school and
							gymnasia. Few women were attacked. Many had dry coughs which brought up
							nothing when they coughed, but their voices were hoarse. Soon after,
							though in some cases after some time, painful inflammations occurred
							either in one testicle or in both, sometimes accompanied with fever, in
							other cases not. Usually they caused much suffering. In other respects
							the people had no ailments requiring medical assistance.<note>That is,
								nobody was ill enough to make a visit to the physician's surgery
									(<foreign xml:lang="grc">I(HTREI=ON</foreign>)
							necessary.</note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 2 </head>
						               <p>II. Beginning early in the summer, throughout the summer and in winter
							many of those who had been ailing a long time took to their beds in a
							state of consumption, while many also who had hitherto been doubtful
							sufferers at this time showed undoubted symptoms. Some showed the
							symptoms now for the first time ; these were those whose constitution
							inclined to be consumptive. Many, in fact most of these, died ; of those
							who took to their beds I do not know one who survived even for a short
							time. Death came more promptly than is usual in consumption, and yet the
							other complaints, which will be described presently, though longer and
							attended with fever, were easily supported and did not prove fatal. For
							consumption was the worst of the diseases that occurred, and alone was
							responsible for the great mortality.</p>
						               <p>In the majority of cases the symptoms were these. Fever with shivering,
							continuous, acute, not completely intermitting, but of the semitertian
							type ; remitting during one day they were exacerbated on the next,
							becoming on the whole more acute. Sweats</p>
						               <pb n="p.151"/>
						               <p>were continual, but not all over the body. Severe chill in the
							extremities, which with difficulty recovered their warmth. Bowels
							disordered, with bilious, scanty, unmixed, thin, smarting stools,
							causing the patient to get up often. Urine either thin,
								colourless,<note>Throughout <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi>
								                   <foreign xml:lang="grc">A\)XRWS2</foreign> may mean, not merely
								"without colour," but "of bad colour." It certainly has this meaning
								in <hi rend="ital">Airs Waters Places</hi>, VII, l. ii. See p.
								85.</note> unconcocted and scanty, or thick and with a slight
							deposit, not settling favourably, but with a crude and unfavourable
							deposit. The patients frequently coughed up small, concocted sputa,
							brought up little by little with difficulty. Those exhibiting the
							symptoms in their most violent form showed no concoction at all, but
							continued spitting crude sputa. In the majority of these cases the
							throat was throughout painful from the beginning, being red and
							inflamed. Fluxes slight, thin, pungent. Patients quickly wasted away and
							grew worse, being throughout averse to all food and experiencing no
							thirst. Delirium in many cases as death approached. Such were the
							symptoms of the consumption.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 3 </head>
						               <p>III. But when summer came, and during autumn occurred many continuous but
							not violent fevers, which attacked persons who were long ailing without
							suffering distress in any other particular manner ; for the bowels were
							in most cases quite easy, and hurt to no appreciable extent. Urine in
							most cases of good colour and clear, but thin, and after a time near the
							crisis it grew concocted. Coughing was slight, and caused no distress.
							No lack of appetite ; in fact it was quite possible even to give food.
							In general the patients did not sicken, as did the consumptives,</p>
						               <pb n="p.153"/>
						               <p>with shivering fevers, but with slight sweats, the paroxysms being
							variable and irregular.<note>The words omitted by Kéhlewein mean "not
								intermitting altogether, but with exacerbations after the manner of
								tertians."</note> The earliest crisis was about the twentieth day ;
							in most cases the crisis was about the fortieth day, though in many it
							was about the eightieth. In some cases the illness did not end in this
							way, but in an irregular manner without a crisis. In the majority of
							these cases the fevers relapsed after a brief interval, and after the
							relapse a crisis occurred at the end of the same periods as before. The
							disease in many of these instances was so protracted that it even lasted
							during the winter.</p>
						               <p>Out of all those described in this constitution only the consumptives
							showed a high mortality-rate ; for all the other patients bore up well,
							and the other fevers did not prove fatal.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>S<hi rend="sc">ECOND</hi>
						               <hi rend="sc">C</hi>ONSTITUTION</head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 4 </head>
						               <p>IV. In Thasos early in autumn occurred unseasonable wintry storms,
							suddenly with many north and south winds bursting out into rains. These
							conditions continued until the setting of the Pleiades and during their
							season. Winter was northerly ; many violent and abundant rains ; snows ;
							generally there were fine intervals. With all this, however, the cold
							weather was not exceptionally unseasonable. But immediately after the
							winter solstice, when the west wind usually begins to blow, there was a
							return of severe wintry weather, much north wind, snow and</p>
						               <pb n="p.155"/>
						               <p>copious rains continuously, sky stormy and clouded. These conditions
							lasted on, and did not remit before the equinox. Spring cold, northerly,
							wet, cloudy. Summer did not turn out excessively hot, the Etesian winds
							blowing continuously. But soon after, near the rising of Arcturus, there
							was much rain again, with northerly winds.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 5</head>
						               <p>V. The whole year having been wet, cold and northerly, in the winter the
							public health in most respects was good, but in early spring many, in
							fact most, suffered illnesses. Now there began at first inflammations of
							the eyes, marked by rheum, pain, and unconcocted discharges. Small gummy
							sores, in many cases causing distress when they broke out ; the great
							majority relapsed, and ceased late on the approach of autumn. In summer
							and autumn dysenteric diseases, tenesmus and lientery ; bilious
							diarrhœa, with copious, thin, crude, smarting stools ; in some cases it
							was also watery. In many cases there were also painful, bilious
							defluxions, watery, full of thin particles, purulent and causing
							strangury. No kidney trouble, but their various symptoms succeeded in
							various orders. Vomitings of phlegm, bile, and undigested food. Sweats ;
							in all cases much moisture over all the body. These complaints in many
							cases were unattended with fever, and the sufferers were not confined to
							bed ; but in many others there was fever, as I am going to describe.
							Those who showed all the symptoms mentioned above were consumptives who
							suffered pain. When autumn came, and during winter, continuous
							fevers--in some few cases ardent--day fevers, night fevers,
							semitertians, exact tertians, quartans, irregular fevers. Each of the
							fevers mentioned found many victims.</p>
						               <pb n="p.157"/>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 6</head>
						               <p>VI. Now the ardent fevers attacked the fewest persons, and these were
							less distressed than any of the other sick. There was no bleeding from
							the nose, except very slight discharges in a few cases, and no delirium.
							All the other symptoms were slight. The crises of these diseases were
							quite regular, generally in seventeen days, counting the days of
							intermission, and I know of no ardent fever proving fatal at this time,
							nor of any phrenitis. The tertians were more numerous than the ardent
							fevers and more painful. But all these had four regular periods from the
							first onset, had complete crises in seven, and in no case relapsed. But
							the quartans, while in many instances they began at first with quartan
							periodicity, yet in not a few they became quartan by an abscession from
							other fevers or illnesses.<note>There are often mixed infections in
								malaria. If the quartan be one of these, being the longest it
								outlasts the others. So the disease appears to have turned into a
								quartan.</note> They were protracted, as quartans usually are, or
							even more protracted than usual. Many fell victims to quotidians, night
							fevers, or irregular fevers, and were ill for a long time, either in bed
							or walking about. In most of these cases the fevers continued during the
							season of the Pleiades or even until winter. In many patients,
							especially children, there were convulsions and slight feverishness from
							the beginning ; sometimes, too, convulsions supervened upon fevers.
							Mostly these illnesses were protracted, but not dangerous, except for
							those who from all other causes were predisposed to die.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 7</head>
						               <p>VII. But those fevers which were altogether continuous and never
							intermitted at all, but in all cases</p>
						               <pb n="p.159"/>
						               <p>grew worse after the manner of semitertians, with remission during one
							day followed by exacerbation during the next, were the most severe of
							all the fevers which occurred at this time, the longest and the most
							painful. Beginning mildly, and on the whole increasing always, with
							exacerbation, and growing worse, they had slight remissions followed
							quickly after an abatement by more violent exacerbations, generally
							becoming worse on the critical days. All patients had irregular rigors
							that followed no fixed law, most rarely and least in the
								semitertians,<note>I take the pronoun <foreign xml:lang="grc">AU)=TOS2</foreign> throughout this chapter to refer to the
								remittent semitertian, or to sufferers from it.</note> but more
							violent in the other fevers. Copious sweats, least copious in the
							semitertians ; they brought no relief, but on the contrary caused harm.
							These patients suffered great chill in the extremities, which grew warm
							again with difficulty. Generally there was sleeplessness, especially
							with the semitertians, followed afterwards by coma. In all the bowels
							were disordered and in a bad state, but in the semitertians they were
							far the worst. In most of them urine either (<hi rend="ital">a</hi>)
							thin, crude, colourless, after a time becoming slightly concocted with
							signs of crisis, or (<hi rend="ital">b</hi>) thick enough but turbid, in
							no way settling or forming sediment, or (<hi rend="ital">c</hi>) with
							small, bad, crude sediments, these being the worst of all. Coughs
							attended the fevers, but I cannot say that either harm or good resulted
							from the coughing on this occasion.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 8</head>
						               <p>VIII. Now the greatest number of these symptoms continued to be
							protracted, troublesome, very disordered, very irregular, and without
							any critical signs, both in the case of those who came very near
							death</p>
						               <pb n="p.161"/>
						               <p>and in the case of those who did not. For even if some patients enjoyed
							slight intermissions, there followed a quick relapse. A few of them
							experienced a crisis, the earliest being about the eightieth day, some
							of the latter having a relapse, so that most of them were still ill in
							the winter. The greatest number had no crisis before the disease
							terminated. These symptoms occurred in those who recovered just as much
							as in those who did not. The illnesses showed a marked absence of crisis
							and a great variety ; the most striking and the worst symptom, which
							throughout attended the great majority, was a complete loss of appetite,
							especially in those whose general condition exhibited fatal signs, but
							in these fevers they did not suffer much from unseasonable thirst. After
							long intervals, with many pains and with pernicious wasting, there
							supervened abscessions either too severe to be endured, or too slight to
							be beneficial, so that there was a speedy return of the original
							symptoms, and an aggravation of the mischief.<note>That is, the
								abscessions did not carry off the morbid humours, which spread again
								throughout the system.</note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 9</head>
						               <p>IX. The symptoms from which these patients suffered were dysenteries and
							tenesmus, lienteries also and fluxes. Some had dropsies also, either
							with or without these. Whenever any of these attacked violently they
							were quickly fatal, or, if mild, they did no good. Slight eruptions,
							which did not match the extent of the diseases and quickly disappeared
							again, or swellings by the ears that grew smaller<note>
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">MWLUO/MENA</foreign> would mean "remained
								crude."</note> and</p>
						               <pb n="p.163"/>
						               <p>signified nothing, in some cases appearing at the joints, especially the
							hip-joint, in few instances leaving with signs of crisis, when they
							quickly re-established themselves in their original state.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 10</head>
						               <p>X. From all the diseases some died, but the greatest number from these
								fevers,<note>It is not clear to what <foreign xml:lang="grc">PA/NTWN</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">TOU/TWN</foreign>
								refer. Probably <foreign xml:lang="grc">PA/NTWN</foreign> refers to
								all the semitertians, and <foreign xml:lang="grc">TOU/TWN</foreign>
								to the special type of them described in Chapter IX.</note>
							especially children--those just weaned, older children of eight or ten
							years, and those approaching puberty. These victims never suffered from
							the latter symptoms without the first I have described above, but often
							the first without the latter. The only good sign, the most striking that
							occurred, which saved very many of those who were in the greatest
							danger, was when there was a change to strangury, into which abscessions
							took place. The strangury, too, came mostly to patients of the ages
							mentioned, though it did happen to many of the others, either without
							their taking to bed or when they were ill. Rapid and great was the
							complete change that occurred in their case. For the bowels, even if
							they were perniciously loose, quickly recovered ; their appetite for
							everything returned, and hereafter the fever abated. But the strangury,
							even in these cases, was long and painful. Their urine was copious,
							thick, varied, red, mixed with pus, and passed with pain. But they all
							survived, and I know of none of these that died.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 11</head>
						               <p>XI. In all dangerous cases you should be on the watch for all favourable
							coctions of the evacuations from all parts, or for fair and critical
							abscessions. Coctions signify nearness of crisis and sure recovery</p>
						               <pb n="p.165"/>
						               <p>of health, but crude and unconcocted evacuations, which change into bad
							abscessions, denote absence of crisis, pain, prolonged illness, death,
							or a return of the same symptoms. But it is by a consideration of other
							signs that one must decide which of these results will be most likely.
							Declare the past, diagnose the present, foretell the future ; practise
							these acts. As to diseases, make a habit of two things--to help, or at
							least to do no harm. The art has three factors, the disease, the
							patient, the physician. The physician is the servant of the art. The
							patient must co-operate with the physician in combating the disease.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 12</head>
						               <p>XII. Pains about the head and neck, and heaviness combined with pain,
							occur both without and with fever. Sufferers from phrenitis have
							convulsions, and eject verdigris-coloured vomit ; some die very quickly.
							But in ardent and the other fevers, those with pain in the neck,
							heaviness of the temples, dimness of sight, and painless tension of the
							hypochondrium, bleed from the nose ; those with a general heaviness of
							the head, cardialgia, and nausea, vomit afterwards bile and phlegm.
							Children for the most part in such cases suffer chiefly from the
							convulsions. Women have both these symptoms and pains in the womb. Older
							people, and those whose natural heat is failing, have paralysis or
							raving or blindness.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>T<hi rend="sc">HIRD</hi> C<hi rend="sc">ONSTITUTION</hi>
                  </head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 13</head>
						               <p>XIII. In Thasos a little before and at the season of Arcturus many
							violent rains with northerly winds. About the equinox until the setting
							of the Pleiades</p>
						               <pb n="p.167"/>
						               <p>slight, southerly rains. Winter northerly, droughts, cold periods,
							violent winds, snow. About the equinox very severe storms. Spring
							northerly, droughts, slight rains, periods of cold. About the summer
							solstice slight showers, periods of great cold until near the Dog Star.
							After the Dog Star, until Arcturus, hot summer. Great heat, not
							intermittent but continuous and severe. No rain fell. The Etesian winds
							blew. About Arcturus southerly rains until the equinox.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 14</head>
						               <p>XIV. In this constitution during winter began paralyses which attacked
							many, a few of whom quickly died. In fact, the disease was generally
							epidemic. In other respects the public health continued good. Early in
							spring began ardent fevers which continued until the equinox and on to
							summer. Now those who began to be ill at once, in spring or the
							beginning of summer, in most cases got well, though a few died ; but
							when autumn and the rains came the cases were dangerous, and more
							died.</p>
						               <p>As to the peculiarities of the ardent fevers, the most likely patients to
							survive were those who had a proper and copious bleeding from the nose,
							in fact I do not know of a single case in this constitution that proved
							fatal when a proper bleeding occurred, For Philiscus and Epaminon and
							Silenus, who died, had only a slight epistaxis on the fourth and fifth
							days. Now the majority of the patients had rigors near the</p>
						               <pb n="p.169"/>
						               <p>crisis, especially such as had no epistaxis, but these had sweats also as
							well as rigors.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 15</head>
						               <p>XV. Some had jaundice on the sixth day, but these were benefited by
							either a purging through the bladder or a disturbance of the bowels or a
							copious hemorrhage, as was the case with Heraclides, who lay sick at the
							house of Aristocydes. This patient, however, who had a crisis on the
							twentieth day, not only bled from the nose, but also experienced
							disturbance of the bowels and a purging through the bladder. Far
							otherwise was it with the servant of Phanagoras, who had none of these
							symptoms, and died. But the great majority had hemorrhage, especially
							youths and those in the prime of life, and of these the great majority
							who had no hemorrhage died. Older people had jaundice or disordered
							bowels, for example Bion, who lay sick at the house of Silenus.
							Dysenteries also were general in summer, and some too of those who had
							fallen ill, and also suffered from hemorrhage, finally had dysentery ;
							for example, the slave of Erato and Myllus, after copious hemorrhage,
							lapsed into dysentery. They recovered.</p>
						               <p>This humour,<note>That is, blood.</note> then, especially was in great
							abundance, since even those who had no hemorrhage near the crisis, but
							swellings by the ears which disappeared--and after their disappearance
							there was a heaviness along the left flank up to the extremity of the
							hip--after the crisis had pain and passed thin urine, and then began to
							suffer slight hemorrhage about the twenty-fourth day, and</p>
						               <pb n="p.171"/>
						               <p>abscessions into hemorrhage occurred. In the case of Antipho, son of
							Critobulus, the illness ceased and came to a complete crisis about the
							fortieth day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 16</head>
						               <p>XVI. Though many women fell ill, they were fewer than the men and less
							frequently died. But the great majority had difficult childbirth, and
							after giving birth they would fall ill, and these especially died, as
							did the daughter of Telebulus on the sixth day after delivery. Now
							menstruation appeared during the fevers in most cases, and with many
							maidens it occurred then for the first time. Some bled from the nose.
							Sometimes both epistaxis and menstruation appeared together ; for
							example, the maiden daughter of Daitharses had her first menstruation
							during fever and also a violent discharge from the nose. I know of no
							woman who died if any of these symptoms showed themselves properly, but
							all to my knowledge had abortions if they chanced to fall ill when with
							child.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 17</head>
						               <p>XVII. Urine in most cases was of good colour, but thin and with slight
							sediments, and the bowels of most were disordered with thin, bilious
							excretions. Many after a crisis of the other symptoms ended with
							dysentery, as did Xenophanes and Critias. I will mention cases in which
							was passed copious, watery, clear and thin urine, even after a crisis in
							other respects favourable, and a favourable sediment : Bion, who lay
							sick at the house of Silenus, Cratis, who lodged with Xenophanes, the
							slave of Areto, and the wife of Mnesistratus. Afterwards all these
							suffered from dysentery.</p>
						               <p>About the season of Arcturus many had crisis on</p>
						               <pb n="p.173"/>
						               <p>the eleventh day, and these did not suffer even the normal relapses.
							There were also comatose fevers about this time, usually in children,
							and of all patients these showed the lowest mortality.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 18</head>
						               <p>XVIII. About the equinox up to the setting of the Pleiades, and during
							winter, although the ardent fevers continued, yet cases of phrenitis
							were most frequent at this time, and most of them were fatal. In summer,
							too, a few cases had occurred. Now the sufferers from ardent fever, when
							fatal symptoms attended, showed signs at the beginning. For right from
							the beginning there was acute fever with slight rigors, sleeplessness,
							thirst, nausea, slight sweats about the forehead and collar-bones, but
							in no case general, much delirium, fears, depression, very cold
							extremities, toes and hands, especially the latter. The exacerbations on
							the even days ; but in most cases the pains were greatest on the fourth
							day, with sweat for the most part chilly, while the extremities could
							not now be warmed again, remaining livid and cold ; and in these cases
							the thirst ceased. Their urine was scanty, black, thin, with
							constipation of the bowels. Nor was there hemorrhage from the nose in
							any case when these symptoms occurred, but only slight epistaxis. None
							of these cases suffered relapse, but they died on the sixth day, with
							sweating. The cases of phrenitis had all the above symptoms, but the
							crises generally occurred on the eleventh day. Some had their crises on
							the twentieth day, namely those in whom the phrenitis did not begin at
							first, or began about the third or fourth day, but</p>
						               <pb n="p.175"/>
						               <p>though these fared tolerably at the beginning, yet the disease assumed an
							acute form about the seventh day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 19</head>
						               <p>XIX. Now the number of illnesses was great. And of the patients there
							died chiefly striplings, young people, people in their prime, the
							smooth, the fair-skinned, the straight-haired, the black-haired, the
							black-eyed, those who had lived recklessly and care-lessly, the
							thin-voiced, the rough-voiced, the lispers, the passionate. Women too
							died in very great numbers who were of this kind. In this constitution
							there were four symptoms especially which denoted recovery :--a proper
							hemorrhage through the nostrils ; copious discharges by the bladder of
							urine with much sediment of a proper character ; disordered bowels with
							bilious evacuations at the right time ; the appearance of dysenteric
							characteristics. The crisis in many cases did not come with one only of
							the symptoms described above, but in most cases all symptoms were
							experienced, and the patients appeared to be more distressed ; but all
							with these symptoms got well. Women and maidens experienced all the
							above symptoms, but besides, whenever any took place properly, and
							whenever copious menstruation supervened, there was a crisis therefrom
							which resulted in recovery ; in fact I know of no woman who died when
							any of these symptoms took place properly. For the daughter of Philo,
							who died, though she had violent epistaxis, dined rather unseasonably on
							the seventh day.</p>
						               <p>In acute fevers, more especially in ardent fevers, when involuntary
							weeping occurs, epistaxis is to be</p>
						               <pb n="p.177"/>
						               <p>expected it the patient have no fatal symptoms besides ; for when he is
							in a bad way such weeping portends not hemorrhage but death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 20</head>
						               <p>XX. The painful swellings by the ears in fevers in some cases neither
							subsided nor suppurated when the fever ceased with a crisis. They were
							cured by bilious diarrhœa, or dysentery, or a sediment of thick urine
							such as closed the illness of Hermippus of Clazomenæ. The circumstances
							of the crises, from which too I formed my judgments, were either similar
							or dissimilar ; for example, the two brothers, who fell sick together at
							the same time, and lay ill near the bungalow of Epigenes. The elder of
							these had a crisis on the sixth day, the younger on the seventh. Both
							suffered a relapse together at the same time with an intermission of
							five days. After the relapse both had a complete crisis together on the
							seventeenth day. But the great majority had a crisis on the sixth day,
							with an intermission of six days followed by a crisis on the fifth day
							after the relapse. Those who had a crisis on the seventh day had an
							intermission of seven days, with a crisis on the third day after the
							relapse. Others with a crisis on the seventh had an intermission of
							three days, with a crisis on the seventh day after the relapse. Some who
							had a crisis on the sixth day had an intermission of six and a relapse
							of three, an intermission of one and a relapse of one, followed by a
							crisis ; for example, Euagon the son of Daitharses. Others with a crisis
							on the sixth had an intermission of seven days, and after the relapse a
							crisis on the fourth ; for example, the daughter of Aglai+das. Now most
							of those who fell ill in this constitution went through their illness in
							this manner, and none of</p>
						               <pb n="p.179"/>
						               <p>those who recovered, so far as I know, failed to suffer the relapses
							which were normal in these cases, but all, so far as I know, recovered
							if their relapses took place after this fashion. Further, I know of none
							who suffered a fresh relapse after going through the illness in the
							manner described above.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 21</head>
						               <p>XXI. In these diseases most died on the sixth day, as did Epaminondas,
							Silenus and Philiscus the son of Antagoras. Those who had the swellings
							by the ears had a crisis on the twentieth day, but these subsided in all
							cases without suppuration, being diverted to the bladder. There were two
							cases of suppuration, both fatal, Cratistonax, who lived near the temple
							of Heracles, and the serving-maid of Scymnus the fuller. When there was
							a crisis on the seventh day, with an intermission of nine days followed
							by a relapse, there was a second crisis on the fourth day after the
							relapse--in the case of Pantacles, for example, who lived by the temple
							of Dionysus. When there was a crisis on the seventh day, with an
							intermission of six days followed by a relapse, there was a second
							crisis on the seventh day after the relapse--in the case of Phanocritus,
							for example, who lay sick at the house of Gnathon the fuller.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 22</head>
						               <p>XXII. During winter, near the time of the winter solstice, and continuing
							until the equinox, the ardent fevers and the phrenitis still caused many
							deaths, but their crises changed. Most cases had a crisis on the fifth
							day from the outset, then intermitted four days, relapsed, had a crisis
							on the fifth day after the relapse, that is, after thirteen days
							altogether. Mostly children experienced crises thus, but older people
							did so too. Some had a crisis</p>
						               <pb n="p.181"/>
						               <p>on the eleventh day, a relapse on the fourteenth, and a complete crisis
							on the twentieth. But if rigor came on about the twentieth day the
							crisis came on the fortieth. Most had rigors near the first crisis, and
							those who had rigors at first near the crisis, had rigors again in the
							relapses at the time of the crisis. Fewest experienced rigors in the
							spring, more in summer, more still in autumn, but by far the most during
							winter. But the hemorrhages tended to cease.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 23</head>
						               <p>XXIII. The following were the circumstances attending the diseases, from
							which I framed my judgments, learning from the common nature of all and
							the particular nature of the individual, from the disease, the patient,
							the regimen prescribed and the prescriber--for these make a diagnosis
							more favourable or less ; from the constitution, both as a whole and
							with respect to the parts, of the weather and of each region ; from the
							custom, mode of life, practices and ages of each patient ; from talk,
							manner, silence, thoughts, sleep or absence of sleep, the nature and
							time of dreams, pluckings, scratchings, tears ; from the exacerbations,
							stools, urine, sputa, vomit, the antecedents and consequents of each
							member in the successions of diseases, and the abscessions to a fatal
							issue or a crisis, sweat, rigor, chill, cough, sneezes, hiccoughs,
							breathing, belchings, flatulence, silent or noisy, hemorrhages, and
							hemorrhoids. From these things must we consider what their consequents
							also will be.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 24</head>
						               <p>XXIV. Some fevers are continuous, some have an access during the day and
							an intermission during the night, or an access during the night and an
							intermission during the day ; there are semitertians,</p>
						               <pb n="p.183"/>
						               <p>tertians, quartans, quintans, septans, nonans. The most acute diseases,
							the most severe, difficult and fatal, belong to the continuous fevers.
							The least fatal and least difficult of all, but the longest of all, is
							the quartan. Not only is it such in itself, but it also ends other, and
							serious, diseases. In the fever called semitertian, which is more fatal
							than any other, there occur also acute diseases, while it especially
							precedes the illness of consumptives, and of those who suffer from other
							and longer diseases. The nocturnal is not very fatal, but it is long.
							The diurnal is longer still, and to some it also brings a tendency to
							consumption. The septan is long but not fatal. The nonan is longer still
							but not fatal. The exact tertian has a speedy crisis and is not fatal.
							But the quintan is the worst of all. For if it comes on before
							consumption or during consumption the patient dies.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 25 </head>
						               <p>XXV. Each of these fevers has its modes, its constitutions and its
							exacerbations. For example, a continuous fever in some cases from the
							beginning is high and at its worst, leading up to the most severe stage,
							but about and at the crisis it moderates. In other cases it begins
							gently and in a suppressed manner, but rises and is exacerbated each
							day, bursting out violently near the crisis. In some cases it begins
							mildly, but increases and is exacerbated, reaching its height after a
							time ; then it declines again until the crisis or near the crisis. These
							characteristics may show themselves in any fever and in any disease. It
							is necessary also to consider the patient's mode of life and to take
							it</p>
						               <pb n="p.185"/>
						               <p>into account when prescribing. Many other important symptoms there are
							which are akin to these, some of which I have described, while others I
							shall describe later. These must be duly weighed when considering and
							deciding who is suffering from one of these diseases in an acute, fatal
							form, or whether the patient may recover ; who has a chronic, fatal
							illness, or one from which he may recover ; who is to be prescribed for
							or not, what the prescription is to be, the quantity to be given and the
							time to give it.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 26 </head>
						               <p>XXVI. When the exacerbations are on even days, the crises are on even
							days. But the diseases exacerbated on odd days have their crises on odd
							days. The first period of diseases with crises on the even days is the
							fourth day, then the sixth, eighth, tenth, fourteenth, twentieth,
							twenty-fourth, thirtieth, fortieth, sixtieth, eightieth, hundred and
							twentieth. Of those with a crisis on the odd days the first period is
							the third, then the fifth, seventh, ninth, eleventh, seventeenth,
							twenty-first, twenty-seventh, thirty-first. Further, one must know that,
							if the crises be on other days than the above, there will be relapses,
							and there may also be a fatal issue. So one must be attentive and know
							that at these times there will be the crises resulting in recovery, or
							death, or a tendency for better or worse. One must also consider in what
							periods the crises occur of irregular fevers, of quartans, of quintans,
							of septans and of nonans.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <pb n="p.187"/>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>FOURTEEN CASES</head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> I </head>
						               <p>Philiscus lived by the wall. He took to his bed with acute fever on the
							first day and sweating ; night uncomfortable.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> General exacerbation, later a small
							clyster moved the bowels well. A restful night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Early and until mid-day he appeared to
							have lost the fever ; but towards evening acute fever with sweating ;
							thirst ; dry tongue ; black urine. An uncomfortable night, without sleep
							; completely out of his mind.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> All symptoms exacerbated ; black urine ;
							a more comfortable night, and urine of a better colour.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> About mid-day slight epistaxis of unmixed
							blood. Urine varied, with scattered, round particles suspended in it,
							resembling semen ; they did not settle. On the application of a
							suppository the patient passed, with flatulence, scanty excreta. A
							distressing night, snatches of sleep, irrational talk ; extremities
							everywhere cold, and would not get warm again ; black urine ; snatches
							of sleep towards dawn ; speechless ; cold sweat ; extremities livid.
							About mid-day on the sixth day the patient died. The breathing
							throughout, as though he were recollecting to do it,<note>The patient
								seemed to forget the necessity of breathing, and then to remember it
								and to breathe consciously.</note> was rare and large. Spleen raised
							in a round swelling ; cold sweats all the time. The exacerbations on
							even days.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> II </head>
						               <p>Silenus lived on Broadway near the place of Eualcidas. After
							over-exertion, drinking, and exercises</p>
						               <pb n="p.189"/>
						               <p>at the wrong time he was attacked by fever. He began by having pains in
							the loins, with heaviness in the head and tightness of the neck. From
							the bowels on the first day there passed copious discharges of bilious
							matter, unmixed, frothy, and highly coloured. Urine black, with a black
							sediment ; thirst ; tongue dry ; no sleep at night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> Acute fever, stools more copious,
							thinner, frothy ; urine black ; uncomfortable night ; slightly out of
							his mind.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> General exacerbation ; oblong
								tightness<note>The word <foreign xml:lang="grc">U(POLA/PAROS2</foreign> is often applied to <foreign xml:lang="grc">S1U/NTAS1IS2</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)/NTAS1IS2</foreign> of the hypochondria. Galen (see Littré on
									<hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> III, Case <hi rend="sc">II</hi>,
								Vol. III, p. 34) says that it means "without bulk," or "without
								swelling." This is possible if the word is etymologically connected
								with <foreign xml:lang="grc">LAPA/ZW</foreign>. The translators are
								not very precise. Littré has "sans beaucoup de rénitence," "sans
								tumeur," "sans gonflement," "sans grand gonflement ;" Adams has
								"empty," "loose," "softish." In <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> I,
								Case <hi rend="sc">XII</hi>, occurs the phrase <foreign xml:lang="grc">FLEGMONH\ U(POLA/PAROS2 E)K TOU= E)/S1W
									ME/REOS2</foreign>, from which it seems that the prefix <foreign xml:lang="grc">U(PO</foreign>- means "underneath," not "rather."
								"Empty underneath" seems the primary meaning, and suggests a
								tightness, or inflammation, with nothing hard and bulky immediately
								beneath the surface to cause the tightness or inflammation. Perhaps
								the word also suggests the tenderness often found in the
								hypochoudria of malaria patients.</note> of the hypochondrium, soft
							underneath, extending on both sides to the navel ; stools thin, blackish
							; urine turbid, blackish ; no sleep at night ; much rambling, laughter,
							singing ; no power of restraining himself.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Same symptoms.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Stools unmixed, bilious, smooth, greasy ;
							urine thin, transparent ; lucid intervals.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Slight sweats about the head ;
							extremities cold and livid ; much tossing ; nothing passed from the
							bowels ; urine suppressed ; acute fever.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Speechless ; extremities would no
							longer get warm ; no urine.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> Cold sweat all over ; red spots with
							sweat, round, small like acne, which persisted without subsiding. From
							the bowels with slight stimulus</p>
						               <pb n="p.191"/>
						               <p>there came a copious discharge of solid stools, thin,<note>I take
									<foreign xml:lang="grc">LEPTO/S2</foreign> here to mean "thinner
								than usual, than might have been expected," a meaning it has once or
								twice in the Hippocratic <hi rend="ital">Corpus.</hi> It might also
								mean "consisting of small pieoes." See on <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> III, Case <hi rend="sc">II</hi> (first
								series).</note> as it were unconcocted, painful. Urine painful and
							irritating. Extremities grow a little warmer ; fitful sleep ; coma ;
							speechlessness ; thin, transparent urine.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Same symptoms.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> Took no drink ; coma ; fitful sleep.
							Discharges from the bowels similar ; had a copious discharge of thickish
							urine, which on standing left a farinaceous, white deposit ; extremities
							again cold.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Death.</p>
						               <p>From the beginning the breath in this case was throughout rare and large.
							Continuous throbbing of the hypochondrium ; age about twenty years.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> III </head>
						               <p>Herophon had acute fever ; scanty stools with tenesmus at the beginning,
							afterwards becoming thin, bilious and fairly frequent. No sleep ; urine
							black and thin.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Deafness early in the day ; general
							exacerbation ; spleen swollen ; tension of the hypochondrium ; scanty
							black stools ; delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Wandering talk ; at night sweat and chill
							; the wandering persisted.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh Day.</hi> Chill all over ; thirst ; out of his
							mind. During the night he was rational, and slept.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> Fever ; spleen lessened ; quite rational
							; pain at first in the groin, on the side of the spleen ; then the pains
							extended to both legs. Night comfortable ; urine of a better colour,
							with a slight deposit.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Sweat, crisis, intermission.</p>
						               <pb n="p.193"/>
						               <p>On the fifth day after the crisis the patient relapsed. Immediately the
							spleen swelled ; acute fever ; return of deafness. On the third day
							after the relapse the spleen grew less and the deafness diminished, but
							there was pain in the legs. During the night he sweated. The crisis was
							about the seventeenth day. There was no delirium during the relapse.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> IV </head>
						               <p>In Thasos the wife of Philinus gave birth to a daughter. The lochial
							discharge was normal, and the mother was doing well when on the
							fourteenth day after delivery she was seized with fever attended with
							rigor. At first she suffered in the stomach and the right hypochondrium.
							Pains in the genital organs. The discharge ceased. By a pessary these
							troubles were eased, but pains persisted in the head, neck and loins. No
							sleep ; extremities cold ; thirst ; bowels burnt ; scanty stools ; urine
							thin, and at first colourless.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Much delirium at night, followed by
							recovery of reason.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Thirst ; stools scanty, bilious, highly
							coloured. </p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> Rigor ; acute fever ; many painful
							convulsions ; much delirium. The application of a suppository made her
							keep going to stool, and there were copious motions with a bilious flux.
							No sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Convulsions.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> Lucid intervals.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Slept ; complete recovery of her
							memory, followed quickly by renewed delirium.</p>
						               <pb n="p.195"/>
						               <p>A copious passing of urine with convulsions--her attendants seldom
							reminding her--which was white and thick, like urine with a sediment and
							then shaken ; it stood for a long time without forming a sediment ;
							colour and consistency like that of the urine of cattle. Such was the
							nature of the urine that I myself saw.</p>
						               <p>About the fourteenth day there were twitchings over all the body ; much
							wandering, with lucid intervals followed quickly by renewed delirium.
							About the seventeenth day she became speechless.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> V </head>
						               <p>The wife of Epicrates, who lay sick near the founder,<note>
                           <hi rend="ital">I. e.</hi> near the statue of the founder of the
								city, or near the temple of the god who presided over the founding
								of the city.</note> when near her delivery was seized with severe
							rigor without, it was said, becoming warm, and the same symptoms
							occurred on the following day. On the third day she gave birth to a
							daughter, and the delivery was in every respect normal. On the second
							day after the delivery she was seized with acute fever, pain at the
							stomach and in the genitals. A pessary relieved these symptoms, but
							there was pain in the head, neck and loins. No sleep. From the bowels
							passed scanty stools, bilious, thin and unmixed. Urine thin and
							blackish. Delirium on the night of the sixth day from the day the fever
							began.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> All symptoms exacerbated ;
							sleeplessness ; delirium ; thirst ; bilious, highly-coloured stools.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> Rigor ; more sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> The same symptoms.</p>
						               <pb n="p.197"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> Severe pains in the legs ; pain again at
							the stomach ; heaviness in the head ; no delirium ; more sleep ;
							constipation.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Urine of better colour, with a thick
							deposit ; was easier.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourteenth day.</hi> Rigor ; acute fever.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifteenth day.</hi> Vomited fairly frequently bilious,
							yellow vomit ; sweated without fever ; at night, however, acute fever ;
							urine thick, with a white sediment.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixteenth day.</hi> Exacerbation ; an uncomfortable night
							; no sleep ; delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighteenth day.</hi> Thirst ; tongue parched ; no sleep ;
							much delirium ; pain in the legs.</p>
						               <p>About the twentieth day. Slight rigors in the early morning ; coma ;
							quiet sleep ; scanty, bilious, black vomits ; deafness at night.</p>
						               <p>About the twenty-first day. Heaviness all over the left side, with pain ;
							slight coughing ; urine thick, turbid, reddish, no sediment on standing.
							In other respects easier ; no fever. From the beginning she had pain in
							the throat ; redness ; uvula drawn back ; throughout there persisted an
							acrid flux, smarting, and salt.</p>
						               <p>About the twenty-seventh day. No fever ; sediment in urine ; some pain in
							the side.</p>
						               <p>About the thirty-first day. Attacked by fever ; bowels disordered and
							bilious.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fortieth day.</hi> Scanty, bilious vomits.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eightieth day.</hi> Complete crisis with cessation of
							fever.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VI </head>
						               <p>Cleanactides, who lay sick above the temple of Heracles, was seized by an
							irregular fever. He had</p>
						               <pb n="p.199"/>
						               <p>at the beginning pains in the head and the left side, and in the other
							parts pains like those caused by fatigue. The exacerbations of the fever
							were varied and irregular ; sometimes there were sweats, sometimes there
							were not. Generally the exacerbations manifested themselves most on the
							critical days.</p>
						               <p>About the twenty-fourth day. Pain in the hands ; bilious, yellow vomits,
							fairly frequent, becoming after a while like verdigris ; general
							relief.</p>
						               <p>About the thirtieth day. Epistaxis from both nostrils began, and
							continued, irregular and slight, until the crisis. All the time he
							suffered no thirst, nor lack of appetite or sleep. Urine thin, and not
							colourless.</p>
						               <p>About the fortieth day. Urine reddish, and with an abundant, red deposit.
							Was eased. Afterwards the urine varied, sometimes having, sometimes not
							having, a sediment.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixtieth day.</hi> Urine had an abundant sediment, white
							and smooth ; general improvement ; fever intermitted ; urine again thin
							but of good colour.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventieth day.</hi> Fever, which intermitted for ten
							days.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eightieth day.</hi> Rigor ; attacked by acute fever ;
							much sweat ; in the urine a red, smooth sediment. A complete crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VII </head>
						               <p>Meton was seized with fever, and painful heaviness in the loins.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> After a fairly copious draught of water
							had his bowels well moved.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Heaviness in the head ; stools thin,
							bilious, rather red.</p>
						               <pb n="p.201"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> General exacerbation ; slight epistaxis
							twice from the right nostril. An uncomfortable night ; stools as on the
							third day ; urine rather black ; had a rather black cloud floating in
							it, spread out, which did not settle.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Violent epistaxis of unmixed blood from
							the left nostril ; sweat ; crisis. After the crisis sleeplessness ;
							wandering ; urine thin and rather black. His head was bathed ; sleep ;
							reason restored. The patient suffered no relapse, but after the crisis
							bled several times from the nose.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VIII </head>
						               <p>Erasinus lived by the gully of Boétes. Was seized with fever after supper
							; a troubled night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Quiet, but the night was painful.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> General exacerbation ; delirium at
							night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Pain and much delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Very uncomfortable ; no sleep at night ;
							dreams and wandering. Then worse symptoms, of a striking and significant
							character ; fear and discomfort.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Early in the morning was composed, and in
							complete possession of his senses. But long before mid-day was madly
							delirious ; could not restrain himself ; extremities cold and rather
							livid ; urine suppressed ; died about sunset.</p>
						               <p>In this patient the fever was throughout accompanied by sweat ; the
							hypochondria were swollen, distended and painful. Urine black, with
							round, suspended particles which did not settle. There were solid
							discharges from the bowels. Thirst</p>
						               <pb n="p.203"/>
						               <p>throughout not very great. Many convulsions with sweating about the time
							of death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> IX </head>
						               <p>Crito, in Thasos, while walking about, was seized with a violent pain in
							the great toe. He took to bed the same day with shivering and nausea ;
							regained a little warmth ; at night was delirious.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> Swelling of the whole foot, which was
							rather red about the ankle, and distended ; black blisters ; acute fever
							; mad delirium. Alvine discharges unmixed, bilious and rather frequent.
							He died on the second day from the commencement.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> X </head>
						               <p>The man of Clazomenae, who lay sick by the well of Phrynichides, was
							seized with fever. Pain at the beginning in head, neck and loins,
							followed immediately by deafness. No sleep ; seized with acute fever ;
							hypochondrium swollen, but not very much ; distension ; tongue dry.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Delirium at night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Painful.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> All symptoms exacerbated.</p>
						               <p>About the eleventh day slight improvement. From the beginning to the
							fourteenth day there were from the bowels thin discharges, copious, of a
							watery biliousness ; they were well supported by the patient. Then the
							bowels were constipated. Urine throughout thin, but of good colour. It
							had much cloud spread through it, which did not settle in a sediment.
							About the sixteenth day the urine was a little thicker, and had a slight
							sediment.</p>
						               <pb n="p.205"/>
						               <p>The patient became a little easier, and was more rational.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventeenth day.</hi> Urine thin again ; painful
							swellings by both ears. No sleep ; wandering ; pain in the legs.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> A crisis left the patient free from
							fever ; no sweating ; quite rational. About the twenty-seventh day
							violent pain in the right hip, which quickly ceased. The swellings by
							the ears neither subsided nor suppurated, but continued painful. About
							the thirty-first day diarrhéa with copious, watery discharges and signs
							of dysentery. Urine thick ; the swellings by the ears subsided.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fortieth day.</hi> Pain in the right eye ; sight rather
							impaired ; recovery.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XI </head>
						               <p>The wife of Dromeades, after giving birth to a daughter, when everything
							had gone normally, on the second day was seized with rigor ; acute
							fever. On the first day she began to feel pain in the region of the
							hypochondrium ; nausea ; shivering ; restless ; and on the following
							days did not sleep. Respiration rare, large, interrupted at once as by
							an inspiration.<note>As we might say, "with a catch in it."</note>
                     </p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day from rigor.</hi> Healthy action of the bowels.
							Urine thick, white, turbid, like urine which has settled, stood a long
							time, and then been stirred up. It did not settle. No sleep at
							night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> At about mid-day rigor ; acute fever ;
							urine similar ; pain in the hypochondrium ; nausea ; an uncomfortable
							night without sleep ; a cold sweat all over the body, but the patient
							quickly recovered heat.</p>
						               <pb n="p.207"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Slight relief of the pains about the
							hypochondrium ; painful heaviness of the head ; somewhat comatose ;
							slight epistaxis ; tongue dry ; thirst ; scanty urine, thin and oily ;
							snatches of sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Thirst ; nausea ; urine similar ; no
							movement of the bowels ; about mid-day much delirium, followed quickly
							by lucid intervals ; rose, but grew somewhat comatose ; slight
							chilliness ; slept at night ; was delirious.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> In the morning had a rigor ; quickly
							recovered heat ; sweated all over ; extremities cold ; was delirious ;
							respiration large and rare. After a while convulsions began from the
							head, quickly followed by death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XII </head>
						               <p>A man dined when hot and drank too much. During the night he vomited
							everything ; acute fever ; pain in the right hypochondrium ;
							inflammation, soft underneath, from the inner part<note>See note, p.
								188.</note>; an uncomfortable night ; urine at the first thick and
							red ; on standing it did not settle ; tongue dry ; no great thirst.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Acute fever ; pains all over.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Passed much smooth, oily urine ; acute
							fever.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> In the afternoon much delirium. No sleep
							at night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> General exacerbation ; urine similar ;
							much rambling ; could not restrain himself ; on stimulation the bowels
							passed watery, disturbed discharges, with worms. An uncomfortable night,
							with rigor in the morning. Acute fever. Hot sweat, and the patient
							seemed to lose his fever ;</p>
						               <pb n="p.209"/>
						               <p>little sleep, followed by chilliness ; expectoration. In the evening much
							delirium, and shortly afterwards he vomited black, scanty, bilious
							vomits.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Chill ; much wandering ; no sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> Legs painful ; general exacerbation ;
							wandering.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XIII </head>
						               <p>A woman lying sick by the shore, who was three months gone with child,
							was seized with fever, and immediately began to feel pains in the
							loins.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Pain in the neck and in the head, and in
							the region of the right collar-bone. Quickly she lost her power of
							speech, the right arm was paralyzed, with a convulsion, after the manner
							of a stroke ; completely delirious. An uncomfortable night, without
							sleep ; bowels disordered with bilious, unmixed, scanty stools.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Her speech was recovered, but was
							indistinct ; convulsions ; pains of the same parts remained ; painful
							swelling in the hypochondrium ; no sleep ; utter delirium ; bowels
							disordered ; urine thin, and not of good colour.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Acute fever ; pain in the hypochondrium ;
							utter delirium ; bilious stools. At night sweated ; was without
							fever.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Rational ; general relief, but pain
							remained about the left collar-bone ; thirst ; urine thin ; no
							sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Trembling ; some coma ; slight delirium
							; pains in the region of the collar-bone and left upper arm remained ;
							other symptoms</p>
						               <pb n="p.211"/>
						               <p>relieved ; quite rational. For three days there was an intermission of
							fever.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Relapse ; rigor ; attack of fever. But
							about the fourteenth day the patient vomited bilious, yellow matter
							fairly frequently ; sweated ; a crisis took off the fever.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XIV </head>
						               <p>Melidia, who lay sick by the temple of Hera, began to suffer violent pain
							in the head, neck and chest. Immediately she was attacked by acute
							fever, and there followed a slight menstrual flow. There were continuous
							pains in all these parts.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Coma ; nausea ; shivering ; flushed
							cheeks ; slight delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Sweat ; intermittence of fever ; the
							pains persisted ; relapse ; snatches of sleep ; urine throughout of good
							colour but thin ; stools thin, bilious, irritating, scanty, black and of
							bad odour ; sediment in the urine white and smooth ; sweating.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Perfect crisis.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
			         </div>
			         <pb n="p.213"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="3c" subtype="book">
				           <head>EPIDEMICS III: THE CHARACTERS </head>
				           <p>S<hi rend="sc">OME</hi> MSS., the most important being V, have certain characters
					at the end of the medical histories in Book III of the <hi rend="ital">Epidemics.</hi> These characters were known to Galen, who wrote, or
					contemplated writing, a treatise about them. There is no doubt, therefore, that
					they are ancient ; Galen indeed in his commentary tells us that his predecessors
					had been much exercised over them. Zeuxis, he says, had written a history of
					them in which they were traced back to Mnemon, who either added them to a
					manuscript in the Library at Alexandria or else brought to the Library a copy
					with the characters inserted.</p>
				           <p>These characters are of no real value for the interpretation of the text, but
					they bear witness to the interest taken in the "medical histories" from very
					early times. Somebody or other invented a shorthand script in order to summarize
					these histories, or rather the main teaching of them. For some reason they were
					only applied to the histories of the third book, and Galen says that the older
					manuscripts of his time had no characters inserted until the seventh case (woman
					with angina).</p>
				           <p>Galen gives the following explanation of the characters :--</p>
				           <p>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">*(HGEI=TAI ME\N OU)=N</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">W(S2 E)/FHN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">A(PA/NTWN TO\ TH\N
						DIA/METRON GRAMMH\N E)/XON *P</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">S1HMAI=NON
						A)EI\ TO\ PIQANO/N</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">TELEUTAI=ON
						D/</foreign>
               </p>
				           <pb n="p.214"/>
				           <p>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">H)/TOI TO\ *U GRA/MMA FAI/NETAI GEGRAMME/NON H)\ TO\
						*Q</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ ME\N U(GEI/AN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ QA/NATON S1HMAI=NON</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)/MPROS1QEN D' AU)TW=N O( TW=N H(MERW=N
					A)RIQMO/S2</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)N AI)=S2 E)NO/S1HS1EN H)\
						A)PE/QANEN O( KA/MNWN</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">OI( DE\ E)N TW=|
						METACU\ TOU/TWN XARAKTH=RES2 A)/PANTES2 ME/N EI)S1I DIA\ TW=N
						GRAMMA/TWN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">A(\ S1HMAI/NEI TA\ S1TOIXEI=A
						TH=S2 FWNH=S2</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">PLH\N TOU= KA/TWQEN
						A)PES1TIGME/NOU DE/LTA</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">TI/NA DE\
						DIA/NOIAN E(/KAS1TOS2 AU)TW=N E)/XEI</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">DHLW/S1W</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">MEMNHME/NWN OU)\N
						H(MW=N</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">O(/TI TA\ PRO\ TOU= TELEUTAI/OU
						TW=N XARAKTH/RWN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">U(F' OU(= QA/NATON H)\
						U(GEI/AN E)/FAMEN DHLOU=S1QAI</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">GEGRAMME/NA
						TO\N A)RIQMO\N TW=N H(MERW=N S1HMAI/NEI</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">PERI\ TW=N A)/LLWN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">O)/S1A METACU\
						TOU/TWN TE KAI\ TH=S2 A)RXH=S2 GE/GRAPTAI</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">POIH/S1OMAI TO\N LO/GON</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ ME\N *A
						DHLOI= A)POFQORA(N</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)PW/LEIAN</foreign>,
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *G GONOEIDE\S2 OU)=RON</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ D) A)PES1TIGME/NON</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">OI)A/PER E)/S1TIN A(\ KA/TWQEN E)/XEI</foreign>,<note>This sentence is
						evidently corrupt.</note>
					             <foreign xml:lang="grc">TRO/PW| TOIW=|DE GEGRAMME(NON *D| DIAXWROU/MENA DI)
						I(DRW/TWN KAI\ DIA/RROIAN KAI\ DIAFO/RHS1IN</foreign>
                  <note>Littré would read
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">DIAXW/RHS1IN</foreign>.</note>
					             <foreign xml:lang="grc">KAI\ S1UNELO/NTI FA/NAI KE/NWS1IN H(NTINAOU=N
						S1HMAI/NEIN *BOU/LONTAI</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *E
						E)POXH/N</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)/DRAN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *Z CH/THMA</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\
						*Q QA/NATON</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">W(S2 PROEI/RHTAI</foreign>,
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\</foreign> I <foreign xml:lang="grc">I(DRW=TA</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *K KRI/S1IN H)\
						KOILIAKH\N DIA/QES1IN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *M MANI/AN
						H)\ MH/TRAN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *N NEO/THTA KAI\
						NE/KRWS1IN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *C CANQH\N XOLH\N KAI\
						CE/NON TI KAI\ S1PA/NION KAI\ CUS1MO\N KAI\ CHRO/THTA</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *O O)DU/NAS2 H)\ OU)=RON</foreign>--<foreign xml:lang="grc">E)/NIOI DE/ FAS1IN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">O)/TAN
						E)PIKEI/MENON A)/NWQEN E)/XH| TO\ *U</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO/TE S1HMAI/NEIN TO\ OU)\RON AU)TO/</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">GRAFO/MENON W(S2 EI)W/QAS1I TO\ OU)/TWS1 GRA/FEIN</foreign>--, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\</foreign> II <foreign xml:lang="grc">PLH=QOS2 H)\
						PTU/ELON H)\ PURO\N</foreign>
                  <note>Littré would read ??<foreign xml:lang="grc">URRO/N</foreign>.</note>
					             <foreign xml:lang="grc">H)\ PURETO\N H)\ PNEU/MONOS2 PA/QOS2</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\</foreign> [<foreign xml:lang="grc">*P</foreign>] <foreign xml:lang="grc">D' E)N AU(TW=| ME/S1ON E)/XON TO\</foreign> I, <foreign xml:lang="grc">KAQO/TI PROEI/RHTAI</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\
						PIQANO\N DHLOI=</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *R R(U/S1IN H)\
						R(I=GOS2</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *F FRENI=TIN H)\
						FQI/S1IN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *S S1PAS1MO\N H)\
						S1TOMA/XON KA/KWS1IN H)\ S1TO/MATOS2</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\
						DE\ *T TO/KON</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *U U(GEI/AN H)\
						U(POXO/NDRION</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *X XOLH\N H)\
						XOLW=DES2</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *Y YU/CIN</foreign>,
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\ DE\ *W W)MO/THTA</foreign>.</p>
				           <p>Kéhn XVII, A 611-613.</p>
				           <pb n="p.215"/>
				           <p>Now the first character, as I said, is always the letter II with the intersecting
					line, meaning in all cases "probable." At the end we see written either <foreign xml:lang="grc">*U</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="grc">*Q</foreign>, meaning
					"recovery" and "death" respectively. Before them is the number of the days at
					the end of which the patient recovered or died. The characters in the middle are
					in all cases (except the delta with a mark below it) the letters indicating the
					elements of the word.<note>That is, each middle character except one is a letter
						of the alphabet, and that letter is significant, being the initial of a
						word, or of several alternative words.</note> I will now state the meaning
					of each. Remember that the last character was said to signify recovery or death,
					and the last but one the number of the days, and I will now give a list of the
					others written between the number and the beginning. A signifies "miscarriage,"
					"destruction"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*G</foreign> "urine like semen"; the
					letter with the mark underneath,<note>The text is probably mutilated, but the
						general meaning is clear.</note> written thus <foreign xml:lang="grc">*D</foreign>, means "evacuations by sweats," "diarrhoea" and
						"perspiration,"<note>Surely this is wrong. Littré's suggestion ("stools")
						may possibly be correct.</note> and in general any evacuation ; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*E</foreign> "retention," "seat"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*Z</foreign> "object of search"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*Q</foreign>
					"death," as I said before ; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*I</foreign> "sweat";
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">*K</foreign> "crisis" or "condition of the bowels";
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">*M</foreign> "madness" or "womb"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*N</foreign> "youth" or "mortification"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*C</foreign> "yellow bile," "something strange and rare,"
					"irritation," "dryness"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*O</foreign> "pains" or
					"urine," though some say it means urine only when it has the <foreign xml:lang="grc">*U</foreign> placed above, written as the word <foreign xml:lang="grc">OU(/TWS2</foreign> is generally written ; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*P</foreign> means "abundance," "sputum," "wheat,"<note>This
						again can surely not be correct. Littré's emendation is unconvincing.</note>
					"fever,"</p>
				           <pb n="p.216"/>
				           <p>"affection of the lung"; with a vertical stroke in the centre it means as
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">*I</foreign> said "probable"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*R</foreign> means "flux," "rigor"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*F</foreign> "phrenitis" or "consumption"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*S</foreign> "convulsion" or "morbid condition of oesophagus or mouth";
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">*T</foreign> "delivery"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*U</foreign> "recovery of health" or "hypochondrium"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*X</foreign> "bile" or "bilious"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*Y</foreign> "chill"; <foreign xml:lang="grc">*W</foreign> "crudity."</p>
				           <p>For more information about the characters see Littré, III. pp. 28-33, and various
					notes at the end of the cases, and also Ilberg in Kéhlewein's edition, p.
					245.</p>
				           <p>As might have been expected, there is considerable doubt as to the right readings
					of these characters. Thus in V the characters at the end of Case <hi rend="sc">I</hi> (first series) are :--</p>
				           <p>
                  <hi rend="center">?? <foreign xml:lang="grc">*Z*S*M*O*N</foreign>
                  </hi>
               </p>
				           <p>where the first character is obviously another form of Galen's ??. Ilberg emends
					to :--</p>
				           <p>
                  <hi rend="center">?? <foreign xml:lang="grc">*Z*S*M*O*N</foreign>
                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">*U</foreign>&gt;</hi>
               </p>
				           <p>Galen reads :--</p>
				           <p>
                  <hi rend="center">?? <foreign xml:lang="grc">*P*O*U*M*U</foreign>
                  </hi>
               </p>
				           <p>
                  <hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi>
					             <foreign xml:lang="grc">PIQANO/N</foreign>.</p>
				           <p>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">PLH=QOS2</foreign>.</p>
				           <p>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">OU)=RA</foreign>.</p>
				           <p>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">TES1S1ARA/KONTA</foreign>.</p>
				           <p>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">U(GI/EIA</foreign>.</p>
				           <p>"It is probable that abundance of urine caused recovery in forty days."</p>
				           <p>Galen's reading makes it necessary to take the words of the text, <foreign xml:lang="grc">META\ DE\ KRI/S1IN</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TES1S1ARA/KONTA</foreign>
               </p>
				           <pb n="p.217"/>
				           <p>
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">H(ME/RH|S1IN U(=S1TERON</foreign>, in the unnatural sense
					of "after the crisis, forty days from the beginning of the illness." So Littré
					and Adams, but the Greek scarcely allows it.</p>
				           <p>It appears certain that there were varieties of this shorthand, and that Galen's
					account deals with one only.</p>
			         </div>
			         <pb n="p.219"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="book">
				           <head>EPIDEMICS III</head>
				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="chapter">
					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> I </head>
						               <p>Pythion<note>The third book of the <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> has
								always been regarded as a continuation of the first book. Even a
								casual glance will convince any reader that the two books are really
								one work. The Paris manuscript called A, which breaks off after the
								opening words of <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> III, nevertheless
								joins these words without interruption to the end of the first
								book.</note>, who lived by the temple of Earth, was seized with
							trembling which began in the hands.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Acute fever ; wandering.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> General exacerbation.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Same symptoms.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Stools scanty, uncompounded and
							bilious.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> General exacerbation ; fitful sleep ;
							constipation.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Varied, reddish sputa.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Mouth drawn awry.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> General exacerbation ; tremblings
							persisted ; urine from the beginning to the eighth day thin, colourless,
							with a cloudy substance floating in it.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> Sweat ; sputa somewhat concocted ; crisis
							; urine somewhat thin about the time of the crisis. After the crisis,
							forty days subsequent to it, abscess in the seat, and an abscession
							through strangury.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> II </head>
						               <p>Hermocrates, who lay sick by the new wall, was seized with fever. He
							began to feel pain in the head and loins ; tension of the hypochondrium
							without</p>
						               <pb n="p.221"/>
						               <p>swelling<note>But see note on p. 188.</note>; tongue at the beginning
							parched ; deafness at once ; no sleep ; no great thirst ; urine thick,
							red, with no sediment on standing ; stools not scanty, and burnt.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Urine thin, with particles floating in
							it, without sediment ; at night delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Jaundice ; general exacerbation ; not
							rational.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Discomfort ; urine thin, and as before.
							The following days similar. About the eleventh day there seemed to be
							general relief ; coma began ; urine thicker, reddish, thin<note>Galen
								says that the meaning of <foreign xml:lang="grc">LEPTA\</foreign> is
								here "small," <hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> he thinks that there wore
								small particles at the bottom. Such is not the meaning of the word
								in Hippocrates when applied to urine.</note> at the bottom, without
							sediment ; by degrees grew more rational.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourteenth day.</hi> No fever ; no sweat ; sleep ; reason
							quite recovered ; urine as before.</p>
						               <p>About the seventeenth day there was a relapse, and the patient grew hot.
							On the following days there was acute fever ; urine thin ; delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> A fresh crisis ; no fever ; no sweat.
							All the time the patient had no appetite ; was perfectly collected but
							could not talk ; tongue dry ; no thirst ; snatches of sleep ; coma.
							About the twenty-fourth day he grew hot ; bowels loose with copious,
							thin discharges. On the following days acute fever ; tongue parched.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-seventh day.</hi> Death.</p>
						               <p>In this case deafness persisted throughout ; urine thick, red, without
							settling, or thin, colourless, with substances floating in it. The
							patient had no power to take food.</p>
					             </div>
					             <pb n="p.223"/>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> III </head>
						               <p>The man lying sick in the garden of Delearces had for a long time
							heaviness in the head and pain in the right temple. From some exciting
							cause he was seized with fever, and took to his bed.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> Slight flow of unmixed blood from the
							left nostril. The bowels were well moved ; urine thin and varied, with
							particles in small groups, like barley-meal or semen, floating in
							it.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Acute fever ; stools black, thin, frothy,
							with a livid sediment in them ; slight stupor ; getting up caused
							distress ; in the urine a livid, rather viscous sediment.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Vomited scanty, bilious, yellow vomits,
							and after a short interval, verdigris-coloured ones ; slight flow of
							unmixed blood from the left nostril ; stools unaltered and urine
							unaltered ; sweat about the head and collar-bones ; spleen enlarged ;
							pain in the direction of the thigh ; tension, soft under-neath, of the
							right hypochondrium ;<note>See note, p. 188.</note> no sleep at night ;
							slight delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Stools more copious, black, frothy ; a
							black sediment in the stools ; no sleep at night ; delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Stools black, oily, viscid, foul-smelling
							; slept ; was more rational.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Tongue dry ; thirsty ; no sleep ;
							delirium ; urine thin, not of a good colour.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> Stools black, scanty, compact ; sleep ;
							was collected ; not very thirsty.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Rigor, acute fever ; sweat ; chill ;
							delirium ; squinting of the right eye ; tongue dry ; thirsty ;
							sleepless.</p>
						               <pb n="p.225"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> Symptoms about the same.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Quite rational ; no fever ; slept,
							urine thin about the time of the crisis.</p>
						               <p>The patient remained free from fever for two days, relapsed on the
							fourteenth day, and immediately had no sleep at night and was completely
							delirious.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifteenth day.</hi> Urine muddy, like that which has been
							stirred up after settling ; acute fever ; completely delirious ; no
							sleep ; pain in knees and legs. On the application of a suppository,
							black, solid motions were passed.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixteenth day.</hi> Urine thin, with a cloudy substance
							floating in it ; delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventeenth day.</hi> Extremities cold in the early
							morning ; would wrap himself up ; acute fever ; sweated all over ; was
							relieved ; more rational ; some fever ; thirst ; vomited bilious
							matters, yellow and scanty ; solid motions from the bowels ; after a
							while they became black, scanty and thin ; urine thin, and not of a good
							colour.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighteenth day.</hi> Was not rational ; comatose.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Nineteenth day.</hi> The same symptoms.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Slept ; completely rational ; sweated
							; no fever ; no thirst ; urine thin.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-first day.</hi> Slightly delirious ; rather
							thirsty ; pain in the hypochondrium and throbbing about the navel
							continuously.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-fourth day.</hi> Sediment in urine ; completely
							rational.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-seventh day.</hi> Pain in the right hip, but in
							other respects very comfortable ; sediment in the urine.</p>
						               <p>About the twenty-ninth day pain in the right eye ; urine thin.</p>
						               <pb n="p.227"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fortieth day.</hi> Passed motions full of phlegm, white
							and rather frequent ; copious sweat all over ; a perfect crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> IV </head>
						               <p>Philistes in Thasos had for a long time pain in the head, and at last
							fell into a state of stupor and took to his bed. Heavy drinking having
							caused continuous fevers the pain grew worse. At night he grew hot at
							the first.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Vomited bilious matters, scanty, at first
							yellow, afterwards increasing and of the colour of verdigris ; solid
							motions from the bowels ; an uncomfortable night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> Deafness ; acute fever ; tension of the
							right hypochondrium, which fell inwards. Urine thin, transparent, with a
							small quantity of substance, like semen, floating in it. About mid-day
							became raving.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Uncomfortable.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Convulsions ; exacerbation.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Died early in the morning.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> V </head>
						               <p>Chaerion, who lay sick in the house of Demaenetus,<note>The variants
								indicate corruption. Can <foreign xml:lang="grc">*DHLI/AN</foreign>
								be "Delian goddess" or "Delias"? The form is not Ionic.</note> was
							seized with fever after drinking. At once there was painful heaviness of
							the head ; no sleep ; bowels disturbed with thin, rather bilious
							stools.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Acute fever, trembling of the head,
							particularly of the lower lip ; after a while rigor, convulsions,
							complete delirium ; an uncomfortable night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Quiet ; snatches of sleep ;
							wandering.</p>
						               <pb n="p.229"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Pain ; general exacerbation ; irrational
							talk ; uncomfortable night ; no sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> The same symptoms.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Rigor ; acute fever ; sweating all over
							; crisis.</p>
						               <p>This patient's stools were throughout bilious, scanty and uncompounded.
							Urine thin, not of a good colour, with a cloudy substance floating in
							it. About the eighth day the urine had a better colour, with a slight,
							white sediment ; quite rational and no fever ; an intermission.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Relapse.</p>
						               <p>About the fourteenth day acute fever.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixteenth day.</hi> Vomited bilious, yellow matters
							rather frequently.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventeenth day.</hi> Rigor ; acute fever ; sweating ;
							crisis ended the fever.</p>
						               <p>Urine after relapse and crisis of a good colour, with a sediment ; no
							delirium during the relapse.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighteenth day.</hi> Slight heat ; rather thirsty ; urine
							thin, with cloudy substance floating in it ; slight delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Nineteenth day.</hi> No fever ; pain in the neck ;
							sediment in urine.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Complete crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VI </head>
						               <p>The maiden daughter of Euryanax was seized with fever. Throughout the
							illness she suffered no thirst and had no inclination for food. Slight
							alvine discharges ; urine thin, scanty, and not of a good colour. At the
							beginning of the fever suffered pain in the seat. On the sixth day did
							not sweat, being</p>
						               <pb n="p.231"/>
						               <p>without fever ; a crisis. The sore near the seat suppurated slightly, and
							burst at the crisis. After the crisis, on the seventh day, she had a
							rigor ; grew slightly hot ; sweated. Afterwards the extremities always
							cold. About the tenth day, after the sweating that occurred, she grew
							delirious, but was soon rational again. They said that the trouble was
							due to eating grapes. After an intermission, on the twelfth day she
							again wandered a great deal ; the bowels were disturbed, with bilious,
							uncompounded, scanty, thin, irritating stools, which frequently made her
							get up. She died the seventh day from the second attack of delirium.
							This patient at the beginning of the illness had pain in the throat,
							which was red throughout. The uvula was drawn back. Many
								fluxes,<note>Here <foreign xml:lang="grc">R(EU/MATA POLLA\</foreign>
								must mean "many fluxes," but in <hi rend="ital">Epidemics</hi> III.
								iv. it means "copions fluxes."</note> scanty and acrid. She had a
							cough with signs of coction, but brought up nothing.<note>Or, with
								Galen's reading, "she had a cough, but brought up no concocted
								suptum."</note> No appetite for any food the whole time, nor did she
							desire anything. No thirst, and she drank nothing worth mentioning. She
							was silent, and did not converse at all. Depression, the patient
							despairing of herself. There was also some inherited tendency to
							consumption.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VII </head>
						               <p>The woman suffering from angina who lay sick in the house of Aristion
							began her complaint with indistinctness of speech. Tongue red, and grew
							parched.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Shivered, and grew hot.</p>
						               <pb n="p.233"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Rigor ; acute fever ; a reddish, hard
							swelling in the neck, extending to the breast on either side ;
							extremities cold and livid, breathing elevated ;<note>The ancient
								commentators did not know the meaning of this word when applied to
								respiration, and a modern can only guess.</note> drink returned
							through the nostrils--she could not swallow--stools and urine
							ceased.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> General exacerbation.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VIII </head>
						               <p>The youth who lay sick by the Liars' Market was seized with fever after
							unaccustomed fatigue, toil and running.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Bowels disturbed with bilious, thin,
							copious stools ; urine thin and blackish ; no sleep ; thirst.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> General exacerbation ; stools more
							copious and more unfavourable. No sleep ; mind disordered ; slight
							sweating.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Uncomfortable ; thirst ; nausea ; much
							tossing ; distress ; delirium ; extremities livid and cold ; tension,
							soft underneath, of the hypochondrium<note>See note, p. 188.</note> on
							both sides.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> No sleep ; grew worse.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Died, being about twenty years old.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> IX </head>
						               <p>The woman who lodged with Tisamenus was in bed with a troublesome attack
							of inflammation of the upper bowel. Copious vomits ; could not retain
							her drink. Pains in the region of the hypochondria. The pains were also
							lower, in the region of the bowels. Constant tormina. No thirst. She
							grew hot, though the extremities were cold all the time.</p>
						               <pb n="p.235"/>
						               <p>Nausea ; sleeplessness. Urine scanty and thin. Excreta crude, thin and
							scanty. It was no longer possible to do her any good, and she died.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> X </head>
						               <p>A woman who was one of the house of Pantimides after a miscarriage was
							seized with fever on the first day. Tongue dry ; thirst ; nausea ;
							sleeplessness. Bowels disordered, with thin, copious and crude
							stools.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> Rigor ; acute fever ; copious stools ;
							no sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> The pains greater.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Death.</p>
						               <p>The bowels were throughout loose, with copious, thin, crude stools. Urine
							scanty and thin.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XI </head>
						               <p>Another woman, after a miscarriage about the fifth month, the wife of
							Hicetas, was seized with fever. At the beginning she had alternations of
							coma and sleeplessness ; pain in the loins ; heaviness in the head.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> Bowels disordered with scanty, thin
							stools, which at first were uncompounded.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Stools more copious and worse ; no sleep
							at night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Delirium ; fears ; depression. Squinting
							of the right eye ; slight cold sweat about the head ; extremities
							cold.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> General exacerbation ; much wandering,
							with rapid recovery of reason ; no thirst ; no</p>
						               <pb n="p.237"/>
						               <p>sleep ; stools copious and unfavourable throughout ; urine scanty, thin
							and blackish ; extremities cold and rather livid.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Same symptoms.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XII </head>
						               <p>A woman who lay sick by the Liars' Market, after giving birth in a first
							and painful delivery to a male child, was seized with fever. From the
							very first there was thirst, nausea, slight pain at the stomach, dry
							tongue, bowels disordered with thin and scanty discharges, no sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> Slight rigor ; acute fever ; slight,
							cold sweating around the head.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> In pain ; crude, thin, copious discharges
							from the bowels.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Rigor ; general exacerbation ;
							sleepless.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> In pain.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> The same symptoms ; copious, fluid
							discharges from the bowels.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Rigor ; acute fever ; thirst ; much
							tossing ; towards evening cold sweat all over ; chill ; extremities
							cold, and would not be warmed. At night she again had a rigor ; the
							extremities would not be warmed ; no sleep ; slight delirium, but
							quickly was rational again.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> About mid-day recovered her heat ;
							thirst ; coma ; nausea ; vomited bilious, scanty, yellowish matters. An
							uncomfortable night ; no sleep ; unconsciously passed a copious
							discharge of urine.</p>
						               <pb n="p.239"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> General abatement of the symptoms ; coma.
							Towards evening slight rigor ; vomited scanty, bilious matters.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> Rigor ; exacerbation of the fever ; no
							sleep whatsoever. In the early morning a copious discharge of urine
							without sediment ; extremities were warmed.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Vomited bilious matters, of the colour
							of verdigris. A rigor shortly afterwards, and the extremities became
							cold again ; in the evening sweat, rigor and copious vomiting ; a
							painful night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twelfth day.</hi> Vomited copious, black, fetid matters ;
							much hiccoughing ; painful thirst.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Thirteenth day.</hi> Vomited black, fetid, copious
							matters ; rigor. About mid-day lost her speech.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourteenth day.</hi> Epistaxis ; death.</p>
						               <p>The bowels of this patient were throughout loose, and there were
							shivering fits. Age about seventeen.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="chapter">
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 2</head>
						               <p>
							                 <hi rend="center">C<hi rend="sc">ONSTITUTION</hi>
                        </hi>
                     </p>
						               <p>II. The year was southerly and rainy, with no winds throughout. About the
							rising of Arcturus, while during the immediately preceding period
							droughts had prevailed, there were now heavy rains, with southerly
							winds. Autumn dark and cloudy, with abundance of rain. The winter
							southerly, humid, and mild after the solstice. Long after the solstice,
							near the equinox, wintry weather returned, and at the actual equinoctial
							period there were northerly winds with snow, but not for long. The
							spring southerly again, with no winds ; many rains throughout until the
							Dog Star. The summer was clear and warm, with waves of stifling heat.
							The</p>
						               <pb n="p.241"/>
						               <p>Etesian winds were faint and intermittent. But, on the other hand, near
							the rising of Arcturus there were heavy rains with northerly winds.</p>
						               <p>The year having proved southerly, wet and mild, in the winter the general
							health was good except for the consumptives, who will be described in
							due course.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 3</head>
						               <p>III. Early in the spring, at the same time as the cold snaps which
							occurred, were many malignant cases<note>Or, "forms."</note> of
							erysipelas, some from a known exciting cause and some not. Many died,
							and many suffered pain in the throat. Voices impaired ; ardent fevers ;
							phrenitis ; aphthae in the mouth ; tumours in the private parts ;
							inflammations of the eyes ; carbuncles ; disordered bowels ; loss of
							appetite ; thirst in some cases, though not in all ; urine disordered,
							copious, bad ; long coma alternating with sleeplessness ; absence of
							crisis in many cases, and obscure crises ; dropsies ; many consumptives.
							Such were the diseases epidemic. There were patients suffering from each
							of the above types, and fatal cases were many. The symptoms in each type
							were as follow.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 4</head>
						               <p>IV. Many were attacked by the erysipelas all over the body when the
							exciting cause was a trivial accident or a very small wound ; especially
							when the patients were about sixty years old and the wound was in the
							head, however little the neglect might have been. Many even while
							undergoing treatment suffered from severe inflammations,<note>With
								Littré's punctuation the meaning is, "however slight the neglect,
								and even when a patient was actually undergoing treatment. There
								were severe inflammations," etc.</note> and the erysipelas would
							quickly spread widely in all directions. Most of the patients
							experienced abscessions ending in suppurations. Flesh, sinews and
							bones</p>
						               <pb n="p.243"/>
						               <p>fell away in large quantities. The flux which formed was not like pus,
							but was a different sort of putre-faction with a copious and varied
							flux. If any of these symptoms occurred in the head, there was loss of
							hair from all the head and from the chin ; the bones were bared and fell
							away, and there were copious fluxes. Fever was sometimes present and
							sometimes absent. These symptoms were terrifying rather than dangerous.
							For whenever they resulted in suppuration or some similar coction the
							cases usually recovered. But whenever the inflammation and the
							erysipelas disappeared without producing any such abscession, there were
							many deaths. The course of the disease was the same to whatever part of
							the body it spread. Many lost the arm and the entire forearm. If the
							malady settled in the sides there was rotting either before or behind.
							In some cases the entire thigh was bared, or the shin and the entire
							foot. But the most dangerous of all such cases were when the pubes and
							genital organs were attacked. Such were the sores which sprang from an
							exciting cause. In many cases, however, sores occurred in fevers, before
							a fever, or supervening on fevers. In some of these also, when an
							abscession took place through suppuration, or when a seasonable
							disturbance of the bowels occurred or a passing of favourable urine,
							this gave rise to a solution ; but when none of these events happened,
							and the symptoms disappeared without a sign, death resulted. It was in
							the spring that by far the greater number of cases of erysipelas
							occurred, but they continued throughout the summer and during
							autumn.</p>
						               <pb n="p.245"/>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 5</head>
						               <p>V. Much trouble was caused to some patients by the tumours in the throat,
							inflammations of the tongue and the abscesses about the teeth. Many had
							the symptom of impaired and muffled<note>The word so rendered has
								puzzled the commentators from very early times. See the full
								disoussion of Littré <hi rend="ital">ad loc.</hi> The ancients
								interpreted either "cooped up" or "altered," "faussée" (Littré). See
								Erotian <hi rend="ital">sub voce</hi>
								                   <foreign xml:lang="grc">FWNAI\ KATEI/LLOUS1AI</foreign>. I think
								that H. used a strange word metaphorically on purpose to describe a
								strange alteration in the voice, which was as it were "imprisoned"
								or (to borrow a motoring expression) "silenced."</note> voice, at
							first at the beginning of the cases of consumption, but also in the
							ardent fevers and in phrenitis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 6</head>
						               <p>VI. Now the ardent fevers and phrenitis began early in the spring after
							the cold snaps which occurred, and very many fell sick at that time.
							These suffered acute and fatal symptoms. The constitution of the ardent
							fevers that occurred was as follows. At the beginning coma, nausea,
							shivering, acute fever, no great thirst, no delirium, slight epistaxis.
							The exacerbations in most cases on even days, and about the time of the
							exacerbations there was loss of memory with prostration and
							speechlessness. The feet and hands of these patients were always colder
							than usual, most especially about the times of exacerbation. Slowly and
							in no healthy manner they recovered their heat, becoming rational again
							and conversing. Either the coma held them continuously without sleep, or
							they were wakeful and in pain. Bowels disordered in the majority of
							these cases, with crude, thin, copious stools. Urine copious, thin, with
							no critical or favourable sign, nor did any other critical sign appear
							in these patients. For there occurred neither favourable hemorrhage</p>
						               <pb n="p.247"/>
						               <p>nor any other of the usual critical abscessions. The manner of their
							dying varied with the individual ; it was usually irregular, at the
							crises, but in some cases after long loss of speech and in many with
							sweating. These were the symptoms attending the fatal cases of ardent
							fever, and the cases of phrenitis were similar. These suffered from no
							thirst at all, and no case showed the mad delirium that attacked others,
							but they passed away overpowered by a dull oppression of stupor.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 7</head>
						               <p>VII. There were other fevers also, which I shall describe in due course.
							Many had aphthae and sores in the mouth. Fluxes about the genitals were
								copious<note>Possibly "frequent," "common." So Littré. This is one
								of the most doubtful cases of those difficult words in a medical
								context, <foreign xml:lang="grc">POLU/S</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">O)LI/GOS</foreign> in the plural. See General
								Introduction, p. lxi.</note>; sores, tumours external and internal ;
							the swellings which appear in the groin.<note>A curious phrase. I
								suspect that <foreign xml:lang="grc">TA\</foreign> hides a
								corruption of the text.</note> Watery inflammations of the eyes,
							chronic and painful. Growths on the eyelids, external and internal, in
							many cases destroying the sight, which are called "figs." There were
							also often growths on other sores, particularly in the genitals. Many
							carbuncles in the summer, and other affections called "rot." Large
							pustules. Many had large tetters.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 8</head>
						               <p>VIII. The bowel troubles in many cases turned out many and harmful. In
							the first place many were attacked by painful tenesmus, mostly
							children--all in fact who were approaching puberty--and most of these
							died. Many lienteries. Cases of dysentery, but they too<note>
                           <hi rend="ital">I. c.</hi> as Galen suggests in his commentary, they
								were like the lienteries in not causing much pain. Lientery is not
								particularly painful.</note> were not very painful. Stools bilious,
							greasy, thin and watery. In many</p>
						               <pb n="p.249"/>
						               <p>cases this condition of the bowels constituted the disease itself, fever
							being sometimes absent and sometimes present.<note>Littré in a long and
								obscure note argues that only <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)/NEU
									PURETW=N</foreign> and not <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)N
									PURETOI=S1I</foreign> can belong to the preceding phrase,
								apparently because it is illogical to say that fever was present
								when the disease consisted merely of unhealthy stools. But the
								writer does not wish to exclude fever ; he merely wishes to exclude
								from this class of patient tenesmus, lientery and dysentery. The
								commentary of Galen, <foreign xml:lang="grc">POLLOI=S U=E/ FHS1IN
									AU)TO\ TOU=TO GENE/S1QAI TO\ NO/S1HMA</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TOUTE/S1TI TO\ DIAXWREI=N TA\ TOIAU=TA: KAI\ GA\R
									KAI\ XWRI\S PURETW=N E)NI/OIS TOU=TO GENE/S1QAI
								*FHS1I</foreign>, does not, as Littré supposes, support his
								contention. The phrase <foreign xml:lang="grc">KAI\ XWRI\S PURETW=N
									E)NI/OIS TOU=TO GENE/S1QAI FHS1I\</foreign> implies <foreign xml:lang="grc">KAI\ E)N PURETOI=S TOU=TO
								E)GE/NETO</foreign>.</note> Painful tormina and malignant colic.
							There were evacuations, though the bulk of the contents remained
								behind.<note>It is hard to separate <foreign xml:lang="grc">DIE/CODOI</foreign> from <foreign xml:lang="grc">TW=N
									POLLW=N</foreign>, yet the sense seems to require it. The next
								sentence states that these evacuations caused no relief, evidently
								because they did not clear the trouble from the bowel. Now if
									<foreign xml:lang="grc">DIE/CODOI</foreign> be taken with
									<foreign xml:lang="grc">TW=N POLLW=N</foreign>, the only
								possible translation is " evacuations of the many contents which
								were retained there," implying complete evacuation. Galen's comment
								(Kéhn XVII, Part I, p. 708) bears out the former interpretation :
									<foreign xml:lang="grc">TA\S DE\ DIECO/DOUS</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">TOUTE/S1TI\ TA\S KENW/S1EIS</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">AU)TOI=S S1UMBH=NAI</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">POLLW=N E)NO/NTWN KAI\ E)PIS1XO/NTWN</foreign> .
								. . . . <foreign xml:lang="grc">KAI\ DIA\ TOU=TO MHDE\ TOU\S PO/NOUS
									LU/EIN TA\ DIECIO/NTA</foreign>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">PW=S
									GAR O)=O/N TE LU/EIN AU)TA/</foreign>, <foreign xml:lang="grc">POLLW=N E)/TI TW=N E)PEXOME/NWN O/NTWN</foreign> ; It should be
								noticed that <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)PIS1XO/NTWN</foreign> is
								probably from <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)PI/S1XW</foreign> (Galen's
									<foreign xml:lang="grc">E)PEXOME/NWN</foreign>) and not from
									<foreign xml:lang="grc">E)PE/XW</foreign>, although I cannot
								find a parallel for intransitive <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)PI/S1XW</foreign> in this sense.</note> The evacuations did
							not take away the pains, and yielded with difficulty to the remedies
							administered. Purgings, in fact, did harm in most cases. Of those in
							this condition many died rapidly, though a few held out longer. In
							brief, all patients, whether the disease was prolonged or acute, died
							chiefly from the bowel complaints. For the bowels carried all off
								together.<note>The writer has not expressed himself clearly in this
								chapter, which seems to be the roughest of rough notes. The last two
								sentences apparently mean :-- <p>(<hi rend="ital">a</hi>) It was
									always the bowel complaints which caused most deaths. This was
									natural, since (<hi rend="ital">b</hi>) all attacked by bowel
									complaints died.</p>
                        </note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 9</head>
						               <p>IX. Loss of appetite, to a degree that I never met before, attended all
							the cases described above, but most especially the last, and of them,
							and of the others also, especially such as were fatally
								stricken.<note>The emendation of Blass permits the translator of
								this passage to harmonize both sense and grammar. Before it was
								impossible to do so.</note>
                     </p>
						               <pb n="p.251"/>
						               <p>Thirst afflicted some, but not others ; of the fever patients, as well as
							of the other cases, none were unseasonably affected, but as far as drink
							was concerned you could diet them as you pleased.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 10</head>
						               <p>X. The urine that was passed was copious, not in proportion to, but far
							exceeding, the drink administered. Yet the urine too that was passed
							showed a great malignancy. For it had neither the proper consistency,
							nor coction, nor cleansing powers ; it signified for most patients
							wasting, trouble,<note>Probably "disordered bowels," a common meaning of
									<foreign xml:lang="grc">TARAXH\</foreign> in the <hi rend="ital">Corpus.</hi>
                        </note> pains, and absence of crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 11</head>
						               <p>XI. Coma attended mostly the phrenitis and ardent fevers, without
							excluding, however, all the other diseases of the most severe sort that
							were accompanied by fever. Most patients throughout either were sunk in
							heavy coma or slept only in fitful snatches.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 12</head>
						               <p>XII. Many other forms also of fever were epidemic : -- tertians,
							quartans, night fevers, fevers continuous, protracted, irregular, fevers
							attended with nausea, fevers of no definite character. All these cases
							suffered severely from trouble.<note>See the preceding note.</note> For
							the bowels in most cases were disordered, with shivering fits. Sweats
							portended no crisis, and the character of the urine was as I have
							described. Most of these cases were protracted, for the abscessions too
							which took place did not prove critical as in other cases ; nay rather,
							in all cases all symptoms marked obscurity of crisis,<note>For <foreign xml:lang="grc">DU/S1KRITON</foreign> see Foes' <hi rend="ital">Oeconomia, sub voce.</hi> It means that it was hard to see when
								a crisis took place, or that the crisis was not a marked one.</note>
							or absence of crisis, or protraction of the disease, but most especially
							in the patients last described. A few</p>
						               <pb n="p.253"/>
						               <p>of these had a crisis about the eightieth day ; with most recovery
							followed no rule. A few of them died of dropsy, without taking to their
							bed ; many sufferers from the other diseases too were troubled with
							swellings, most particularly the consumptives.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 13</head>
						               <p>XIII. The severest and most troublesome disease, as well as the most
							fatal, was the consumption. Many cases began in the winter, and of these
							several took to their bed, though some went about ailing without doing
							so. Early in the spring most of those who had gone to bed died, while
							none of the others lost their cough, though it became easier in the
							summer. During autumn all took to bed and many died. Most of these were
							ill for a long time. Now most of these began suddenly to grow worse,
							showing the following symptoms :--frequent shivering ; often continuous
							and acute fever ; unseasonable, copious,<note>I am often doubtful as to
								the meaning of <foreign xml:lang="grc">POLLOI\</foreign> in
								instances like these ; does it refer to quantity or frequency ? In
								these two examples either meaning would give excellent sense. See
								General Introduction, p. lxi.</note> cold sweats throughout ; great
							chill with difficult recovery of heat ; bowels variously constipated,
							then quickly relaxing, and violently relaxing in all cases near the end
							; the humours about the lungs spread downwards ; abundance of
							unfavourable urine ; malignant wasting. The coughs throughout were
							frequent, bringing up copious,<note>I am often doubtful as to the
								meaning of <foreign xml:lang="grc">POLLOI\</foreign> in instances
								like these ; does it refer to quantity or frequency ? In these two
								examples either meaning would give excellent sense. See General
								Introduction, p. lxi.</note> concocted and liquid sputa, but without
							much pain ; but even if there was pain, in all cases the purging from
							the lungs took place very mildly. The throat did not smart very much,
							nor did salt humours cause any distress at all. The fluxes, however,
							viscid, white,</p>
						               <pb n="p.255"/>
						               <p>moist, frothy, which came from the head, were abundant. But by far the
							worst symptom that attended both these cases and the others was the
							distaste for food, as has been mentioned. They had no relish either for
							drink with nourishment, but they remained entirely without thirst.
							Heaviness in the body. Coma. In most of them there was swelling, which
							developed into dropsy. Shivering fits and delirium near death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 14</head>
						               <p>XIV. The physical characteristics of the consumptives were :--skin
							smooth, whitish, lentil-coloured, reddish ; bright eyes ;<note>It seems
								impossible to decide whether the adjective <foreign xml:lang="grc">XAROPO/S</foreign> refers here to the brightness of the eyes or
								to their colour (blue or grey).</note> a leucophlegmatic<note>See
								General Introduction, p. xlvi-li, on the humours. "Bitter bile" was
								the same as that sometimes called "yellow."</note> condition ;
							shoulder-blades projecting like wings. Women too so.<note>This brief
								phrase seems to mean that the same characteristics marked
								consumptive women as consumptive men.</note> As to those with a
								melancholic<note>See General Introduction, p. xlvi-li, on the
								humours. "Bitter bile" was the same as that sometimes called
								"yellow."</note> or a rather sanguine<note>See General Introduction,
								p. xlvi-li, on the humours. "Bitter bile" was the same as that
								sometimes called "yellow."</note> complexion, they were attacked by
							ardent fevers, phrenitis and dysenteric troubles. Tenesmus affected
							young, phlegmatic<note>See General Introduction, p. xlvi-li, on the
								humours. "Bitter bile" was the same as that sometimes called
								"yellow."</note> people ; the chronic diarrhoea and acrid, greasy
							stools affected persons of a bilious<note>See General Introduction, p.
								xlvi-li, on the humours. "Bitter bile" was the same as that
								sometimes called "yellow."</note> temperament.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 15</head>
						               <p>XV. In all the cases described spring was the worst enemy, and caused the
							most deaths ; summer was the most favourable season, in which fewest
							died. In autumn and during the season of the Pleiades, on the other
							hand, there were again deaths, usually on the fourth day. And it seems
							to me natural that the coming on of summer should have been helpful. For
							the coming on of winter resolves the diseases of summer, and the coming
							on of summer removes those of winter. And yet in</p>
						               <pb n="p.257"/>
						               <p>itself the summer in question was not healthful ;<note>"Of a good
								constitution."</note> in fact it was suddenly hot, southerly, and
							calm. But nevertheless the change from the other constitution proved
							beneficial.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
						               <head>PART 16</head>
						               <p>XVI. The power, too, to study correctly what has been written I consider
							to be an important part of the art of medicine. The man who has learnt
							these things and uses them will not, I think, make great mistakes in the
							art. And it is necessary to learn accurately each constitution of the
							seasons as well as the disease ; what common element in the constitution
							or in the disease is good, and what common element in the constitution
							or in the disease is bad ; what malady is protracted and fatal, what is
							protracted and likely to end in recovery ; what acute illness is fatal,
							what acute illness is likely to end in recovery. With this knowledge it
							is easy to examine the order of the critical days, and to prognosticate
							therefrom. One who has knowledge of these matters can know whom he ought
							to treat, as well as the time and method of treatment.<note>This chapter
								does not fit in with the context, and occurs again at the beginning
								of the book <foreign xml:lang="grc">PERI\ KRIS1I/MWN</foreign>.
								Ermerins brackets it.</note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>SIXTEEN CASES</head>
					             <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> I </head>
						               <p>XVII. In Thasos the Parian who lay sick beyond the temple of Artemis was
							seized with acute fever, which at the beginning was continuous and
							ardent. Thirst. At the beginning coma followed by sleeplessness. Bowels
							disordered at the beginning ; urine thin.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Oily urine ; delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> General exacerbation ; no sleep ;</p>
						               <pb n="p.259"/>
						               <p>urine similar and mind disordered ; stools bilious and fatty.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> Slight epistaxis ; vomited scanty
							matters of the colour of verdigris ; snatches of sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Same symptoms.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> General improvement.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Sweated all over ; grew chilly, but
							quickly recovered heat.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourteenth day.</hi> Acute fever ; stools bilious, thin,
							copious ; substance floating in urine ; delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventeenth day.</hi> In pain ; no sleep, while the fever
							grew worse.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Sweated all over ; no fever ; stools
							bilious ; aversion to food ; coma.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-fourth day.</hi> Relapse.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Thirty-fourth day.</hi> No fever ; no constipation ;
							recovered heat.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fortieth day.</hi> No fever ; bowels constipated for a
							short time ; aversion to food ; became slightly feverish again,
							throughout irregularly, the fever being sometimes absent, sometimes
							present ; for if the fever intermitted and was alleviated there was a
							relapse soon afterwards. He took little bits of food, and that of an
							unsuitable sort. Sleep bad ; delirium at the relapses. Urine at these
							times had consistency, but was troubled and bad. Bowels constipated, but
							afterwards relaxed. Continuous slight fevers. Stools thin and
							copious.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Hundred and twentieth day.</hi> Death.</p>
						               <p>In this case the bowels continuously from the first day loose with
							bilious, loose, copious stools, or</p>
						               <pb n="p.261"/>
						               <p>constipated with hot,<note>Lit. "seething" or "boiling." The reference is
								possibly not so much to heat as to the steaming, frothy nature of
								the stools.</note> undigested stools. Urine throughout bad ; mostly
							comatose ; painful sleeplessness ;<note>The meaning apparently is that
								the patient was generally in a state of coma ; if not comatose, he
								was in pain and could not sleep.</note> continued aversion to
							food.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> II </head>
						               <p>In Thasos the woman who lay sick by the Cold Water, on the third day
							after giving birth to a daughter without lochial discharge, was seized
							with acute fever accompanied by shivering. For a long time before her
							delivery she had suffered from fever, being confined to bed and averse
							to food. After the rigor that took place, the fevers were continuous,
							acute, and attended with shivering.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth and following days.</hi> Much delirium, quickly
							followed by recovery of reason ; bowels disturbed with copious, thin,
							watery and bilious stools ; no thirst.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> Was rational, but comatose. Urine
							copious, thin and black ; no sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Slight chills,<note>This sentence
								shows that <foreign xml:lang="grc">PERI/</foreign> in <foreign xml:lang="grc">PERIYU/XW</foreign> means not "very," but "all
								over." The phrase may mean "slight chilliness."</note> but heat
							quickly recovered ; slight wandering ; no sleep ; bowels the same ;
							urine watery and copious.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-seventh day.</hi> No fever ; bowels constipated ;
							not long afterwards severe pain in the right hip for a long time. Fevers
							again attended ; urine watery.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fortieth day.</hi> Pain in the hip relieved ; continuous
							coughing, with watery, copious sputa ; bowels constipated ; aversion to
							food ; urine the same. The fevers, without entirely intermitting, were
							exacerbated</p>
						               <pb n="p.263"/>
						               <p>irregularly, sometimes increasing and sometimes not doing so.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixtieth day.</hi> The coughing ceased without any
							critical sign ; there was no coction of the sputa, nor any of the usual
							abscessions ; jaw on the right side convulsed ; comatose ; wandering,
							but reason quickly recovered ; desperately averse to food ; jaw relaxed
							; passed small, bilious stools ; fever grew more acute, with shivering.
							On the succeeding days she lost power of speech, but would afterwards
							converse.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eightieth day.</hi> Death.</p>
						               <p>The urine of this patient was throughout black, thin and watery. Coma was
							present, aversion to food, despondency, sleeplessness, irritability,
							restlessness, the mind being affected by melancholy.<note>For
								"melancholy" see General Introduction, p. lviii.</note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> III </head>
						               <p>In Thasos Pythion, who lay sick above the shrine of Heracles, after
							labour, fatigue and careless living, was seized by violent rigor and
							acute fever. Tongue dry ; thirst ; bilious ; no sleep ; urine rather
							black, with a substance suspended in it, which formed no sediment.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> About mid-day chill in the extremities,
							especially in the hands and head ; could not speak or utter a sound ;
							respiration short for a long time ; recovered warmth ; thirst ; a quiet
							night ; slight sweats about the head.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> A quiet day, but later, about sunset,
							grew rather chilly ; nausea ; distress ;<note>Probably bowel trouble.
								See p. 250</note> painful night without sleep ; small, solid stools
							were passed.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Early morning peaceful, but about
							mid-day all symptoms were exacerbated ; chill ;</p>
						               <pb n="p.265"/>
						               <p>speechless and voiceless ; grew worse ; recovered warmth after a time ;
							black urine with a substance floating in it ; night peaceful ;
							slept.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> Seemed to be relieved, but there was
							heaviness in the bowels with pain ; thirst ; painful night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Early morning peaceful ; towards evening
							the pains were greater ; exacerbation ; but later a little clyster
							caused a good movement of the bowels. Slept at night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Nausea ; rather uneasy ; urine oily ;
							much distress<note>Probably bowel trouble. See p. 250.</note> at night ;
							wandering ; no sleep at all.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> Early in the morning snatches of sleep ;
							but quickly there was chill ; loss of speech ; respiration thin and weak
							; in the evening he recovered warmth again ; was delirious ; towards
							morning slightly better ; stools uncompounded, small, bilious.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Comatose ; nausea whenever he woke up.
							Not over-thirsty. About sunset was uncomfortable ; wandered ; a bad
							night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> In the early morning was speechless ;
							great chill ; acute fever ; much sweat ; death.</p>
						               <p>In this case the pains on even days.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> IV </head>
						               <p>The patient suffering from phrenitis on the first day that he took to bed
							vomited copiously thin vomits of the colour of verdigris ; much fever
							with shivering ; continuous sweating all over ; painful heaviness of
							head and neck ; urine thin, with small, scattered substances floating in
							it, which did not settle. Copious excreta at a single evacuation ;
							delirium ; no sleep.</p>
						               <pb n="p.267"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> In the early morning speechless ; acute
							fever ; sweating ; no intermission ; throbbing all over the body ;
							convulsions at night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> General exacerbation.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> V </head>
						               <p>In Larisa a bald man suddenly experienced pain in the right thigh. No
							remedy did any good.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Acute fever of the ardent type ; the
							patient was quiet, but the pains persisted.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> The pains in the thigh subsided, but the
							fever grew worse ; the patient was rather uncomfortable and did not
							sleep ; extremities cold ; copious and unfavourable urine was
							passed.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> The pain in the thigh ceased, but there
							was derangement of the intellect, with distress<note>Probably trouble in
								the bowels.</note> and much tossing.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Death about mid-day.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VI </head>
						               <p>In Abdera Pericles was seized with acute fever, continuous and painful ;
							much thirst ; nausea ; could not retain what he drank. There was slight
							enlargement of the spleen and heaviness in the head.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Epistaxis from the left nostril ; the
							fever, however, increased greatly. Copious urine, turbid and white. On
							standing it did not settle.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> General exacerbation ; the urine,
							however, had consistency, but there was some sediment ; the nausea was
							relieved and the patient slept.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> The fever went down ; abundance of urine,
							with concocted and copious sediment ; a quiet night.</p>
						               <pb n="p.269"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> About mid-day a hot, violent sweating
							all over ; no fever ; crisis ; no relapse.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VII </head>
						               <p>In Abdera the maiden who lay sick by the Sacred Way was seized with a
							fever of the ardent type. She was thirsty and sleepless. Menstruation
							occurred for the first time.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Much nausea ; redness ; shivering ;
							restlessness.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Same symptoms. Urine thin but of good
							colour ; no trouble in the bowels.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> Deafness ; acute fever ; sleeplessness ;
							nausea ; shivering ; was rational ; urine similar.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day</hi> Same symptoms, and also on the following
							days. The deafness persisted.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourteenth day.</hi> Reason disturbed ; the fever
							subsided.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventeenth day.</hi> Copious epistaxis ; the deafness
							improved a little. On the following days nausea and deafness, while
							there was also delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Pain in the feet ; deafness ; the
							delirium ceased ; slight epistaxis ; sweating ; no fever.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-fourth day.</hi> The fever returned, with the
							deafness ; pain in the feet persisted ; delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-seventh day.</hi> Copious sweating ; no fever ;
							the deafness ceased ; the pain in the feet remained, but in other
							respects there was a perfect crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> VIII </head>
						               <p>In Abdera Anaxion, who lay sick by the Thracian gate, was seized with
							acute fever. Continuous pain</p>
						               <pb n="p.271"/>
						               <p>in the right side ; a dry cough, with no sputa on the first days. Thirst
							; sleeplessness ; urine of good colour, copious and thin.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Delirium ; warm applications gave no
							relief.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> In pain, for the fever grew worse and
							the pains were not relieved, while the coughing was troublesome and
							there was difficulty in breathing.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> I bled him in the arm. There was an
							abundant, proper flow of blood ; the pains were relieved, although the
							dry coughing persisted.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eleventh day.</hi> The fever went down ; slight sweating
							about the head ; the coughing and the sputa more moist.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventeenth day.</hi> Began to expectorate small,
							concocted sputa ; was relieved.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Sweated and was free from fever ;
							after a crisis was thirsty, and the cleansings from the lungs were not
							favourable.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-seventh day.</hi> The fever returned ; coughing,
							with copious, concocted sputa ; copious, white sediment in urine ;
							thirst and difficulty in breathing disappeared.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Thirty-fourth day.</hi> Sweated all over ; no fever ;
							general crisis.<note>I am conscious of a slight change in diction and
								method in this part of the <hi rend="ital">Epidcmics.</hi> I mention
								four points :-- <p>(1) The frequent use of <foreign xml:lang="grc">PURETO\S</foreign> in the plural, which is unusual when it
									simply means "feverishness" (Cases <hi rend="sc">VIII</hi>, <hi rend="sc">IX</hi>, <hi rend="sc">XII</hi>, <hi rend="sc">XIII</hi>).</p>
								                   <p>(2) <foreign xml:lang="grc">KATABAI/NW</foreign> is used of
									evacuations (Cases <hi rend="sc">VII</hi>, <hi rend="sc">IX</hi>
									                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">OU)/RA</foreign> . . . <foreign xml:lang="grc">KATE/BAINEN</foreign>, <hi rend="sc">XII</hi>).</p>
								                   <p>(3) Treatment is mentioned (Case <hi rend="sc">VIII</hi>,
										<foreign xml:lang="grc">QERMA/S1MATA</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)GKW=NA E)/TAMON</foreign>, where note the
									personal touch).</p>
								                   <p>(4) <foreign xml:lang="grc">I(DRU/NOMAI</foreign> used of
									recovery of reason, = <foreign xml:lang="grc">KATANOW=</foreign>
									(Case <hi rend="sc">XV</hi>). The change is marked enough to
									lead one to suppose that these histories were composed at a
									different period in the writer's life.</p>
                        </note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> IX </head>
						               <p>In Abdera Heropythus had pain in the head without taking to bed, but
							shortly afterwards was</p>
						               <pb n="p.273"/>
						               <p>compelled to do so. He lived close to the Upper Road.<note>With Blass'
								reading, "Upper Market-place."</note> An acute, ardent fever seized
							him. Vomited at the beginning copious, bilious matters ; thirst ; great
							discomfort ; urine thin and black, sometimes with, sometimes without,
							substances suspended in it. Painful night, with fever rising now in this
							way, now in that, but for the most part irregularly. About the
							fourteenth day, deafness ; the fever grew worse ; urine the same.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Much delirium, also on the following
							days.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fortieth day.</hi> Copious epistaxis ; more rational ;
							some deafness, but less than before ; the fever went down. Frequent, but
							slight, epistaxis on the following days. About the sixtieth day the
							bleedings from the nose ceased, but there was violent pain in the right
							hip and the fever increased. Not long afterwards, pains in all the lower
							parts. It happened that either the fever was higher and the deafness
							great, or else, though these symptoms were relieved and less severe, yet
							the pains in the lower parts about the hips grew worse. But from about
							the eightieth day all the symptoms were relieved without any
							disappearing. The urine that was passed was of good colour and had
							greater deposits, while the delirious mutterings were less. About the
							hundredth day the bowels were disordered with copious, bilious stools,
							and copious evacuations of this nature were passed for a long time. Then
							followed painful symptoms of dysentery, with relief of the other
							symptoms. In brief, the fever disappeared and the deafness ceased.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Hundred and twentieth day.</hi> Complete crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <pb n="p.275"/>
					             <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> X </head>
						               <p>In Abdera Nicodemus after venery and drunkenness was seized with fever.
							At the beginning he had nausea and cardialgia ; thirst ; tongue parched
							; urine thin and black.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> The fever increased ; shivering ; nausea
							; no sleep ; bilious, yellow vomits ; urine the same ; a quiet night ;
							sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> All symptoms less severe ; relief. But
							about sunset he was again somewhat uncomfortable ; painful night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Rigor ; much fever ; pains every-where ;
							urine thin, with floating substance in it ; the night, on the other
							hand, was quiet.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fifth day.</hi> All symptoms present, but relieved.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Same pains everywhere ; substance
							floating in urine ; much delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventh day.</hi> Relief.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Eighth day.</hi> All the other<note>What other symptoms ?
								It is clear that some symptoms are excepted, but there is no hint
								what these are. As V has <foreign xml:lang="grc">TA\ D'
									A)/LLA</foreign>, " but all the other symptoms were relieved," I
								believe that after <foreign xml:lang="grc">0)GDO/H|</foreign> has
								fallen out a phrase containing the symptoms which were not
								relieved.</note> symptoms less severe.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day and following days.</hi> The pains were
							present, but all less severe. The exacerbations and the pains in the
							case of this patient tended through-out to occur on the even days.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Urine white, having consistency ; no
							sediment on standing. Copious sweating ; seemed to lose his fever, but
							towards evening grew hot again, with pains in the same parts ; shivering
							; thirst ; slight delirium.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-fourth day.</hi> Much white urine, with much
							sediment. Hot sweating all over ; the fever passed away in a crisis.</p>
					             </div>
					             <pb n="p.277"/>
					             <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XI </head>
						               <p>In Thasos a woman of gloomy temperament, after a grief with a reason for
							it, without taking to bed lost sleep and appetite, and suffered thirst
							and nausea. She lived near the place of Pylades on the plain.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> As night began there were fears, much
							rambling, depression and slight feverishness. Early in the morning
							frequent convulsions ; whenever these frequent convulsions intermitted,
							she wandered and uttered obscenities ; many pains, severe and
							continuous.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> Same symptoms ; no sleep ; fever more
							acute.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> The convulsions ceased, but were
							succeeded by coma and oppression, followed in turn by wakefulness. She
							would jump up ; could not restrain herself ; wandered a great deal ;
							fever acute ; on this night a copious, hot sweating all over ; no fever
							; slept, was perfectly rational, and had a crisis. About the third day
							urine black and thin, with particles mostly round floating in it, which
							did not settle. Near the crisis copious menstruation.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XII </head>
						               <p>In Larisa a maiden was seized with an acute fever of the ardent type.
							Sleeplessness ; thirst ; tongue sooty and parched ; urine of good
							colour, but thin.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Second day.</hi> In pain ; no sleep.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Third day.</hi> Copious stools, watery and of a yellowish
							green ; similar stools on the following days, passed without
							distress.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourth day.</hi> Scanty, thin urine, with a substance</p>
						               <pb n="p.279"/>
						               <p>suspended in it which did not settle ; delirium at night.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Violent and abundant epistaxis ; after a
							shivering fit followed a hot, copious sweating all over ; no fever ; a
							crisis. In the fever and after the crisis menstruation for the first
							time, for she was a young maiden. Throughout she suffered nausea and
							shivering ; redness of the face ; pain in the eyes ; heaviness in the
							head. In this case there was no relapse, but a definite crisis. The
							pains on the even days.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XIII </head>
						               <p>Apollonius in Abdera was ailing for a long time without being confined to
							bed. He had a swollen abdomen, and a continual pain in the region of the
							liver had been present for a long time ; moreover, he became during this
							period jaundiced and flatulent ; his complexion was whitish. After
							dining and drinking unseasonably cow's milk<note>
                           <foreign xml:lang="grc">FAGW\M</foreign> according to this translation has no expressed
								object. Furthermore, <foreign xml:lang="grc">BO/EION</foreign> is
								more naturally " beef." As the words stand the above version is the
								natural one, but I suspect that either <foreign xml:lang="grc">BO/EION</foreign> should be transposed to between <foreign xml:lang="grc">DE\</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">KAI/</foreign>, or else it is used <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)PO\ KOINOU=</foreign> and zengmatically with both <foreign xml:lang="grc">FAGW\N</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">PIW/N</foreign>, " after eating beef and drinking oow's milk."
								So Littré and, apparently, from his translation, Calvus.</note> he
							at first grew rather hot ; he took to his bed. Having drunk copiously of
							milk, boiled and raw, both goat's and sheep's, and adopting a thoroughly
							bad regimen,<note>Or, changing the comma at <foreign xml:lang="grc">PA/NTWN</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="grc">KAKH=</foreign>, "
								adopting a bad regimen, he suffered great harm in every way."</note>
							he suffered much therefrom. For there were exacerbations of the fever ;
							the bowels passed practically nothing of the food taken ; the urine was
							thin and scanty. No sleep. Grievous distension ; much thirst ; coma ;
							painful swelling of the right hypochondrium ; extremities all round
							rather cold ; slight delirious mutterings ; forgetfulness of every-thing
							he said ; he was not himself. About the</p>
						               <pb n="p.281"/>
						               <p>fourteenth day from his taking to bed, after a rigor, he grew hot ;
							wildly delirious ; shouting, distress,<note>Here perhaps not bowel
								trouble.</note> much rambling, followed by calm ; the coma came on
							at this time. Afterwards the bowels were disordered with copious stools,
							bilious, uncompounded and crude ; urine black, scanty and thin. Great
							discomfort. The evacuations showed varying symptoms ; they were either
							black, scanty and verdigris-coloured, or else greasy, crude and smarting
							; at times they seemed actually to be like milk. About the twenty-fourth
							day comfortable ; in other respects the same, but he had lucid
							intervals. He remembered nothing since he took to bed. But he quickly
							was again delirious, and all symptoms took a sharp turn for the worse.
							About the thirtieth day acute fever ; copious, thin stools ; wandering ;
							cold extremities ; speechlessness.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Thirty-fourth day.</hi> Death.</p>
						               <p>This patient throughout, from the time I had knowledge of the case,
							suffered from disordered bowels ; urine thin and black ; coma ;
							sleeplessness ; extremities cold ; delirious throughout.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XIV </head>
						               <p>In Cyzicus a woman gave birth with difficult labour to twin daughters,
							and the lochial discharge was far from good.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Acute fever with shivering ; painful
							heaviness of head and neck. Sleepless from the first, but silent, sulky
							and refractory. Urine thin and of no colour ; thirsty ; nausea generally
							; bowels irregularly disturbed with constipation following.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixth day.</hi> Much wandering at night ; no sleep.</p>
						               <pb n="p.283"/>
						               <p>About the eleventh day she went out of her mind and then was rational
							again ; urine black, thin, and then, after an interval, oily ; copious,
							thin, disordered stools.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourteenth day.</hi> Many convulsions ; extremities cold
							; no further recovery of reason ; urine suppressed.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Sixteenth day.</hi> Speechless.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventeenth day.</hi> Death.</p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XV </head>
						               <p>In Thasos the wife of Delearces, who lay sick on the plain, was seized
							after a grief with an acute fever with shivering. From the beginning she
							would wrap herself up, and throughout, without speaking a word, she
							would fumble, pluck, scratch, pick hairs, weep and then laugh, but she
							did not sleep ; though stimulated, the bowels passed nothing. She drank
							a little when the attendants suggested it. Urine thin and scanty ; fever
							slight to the touch ; coldness of the extremities.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Ninth day.</hi> Much wandering followed by return of
							reason ; silent.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourteenth day.</hi> Respiration rare and large with long
								intervals,<note>I take this, in apite of Galen, to mean " with extra
								long intervals between each breath." The phrase is rather care-less
								but scarcely tautological. " At intervals" or " after a long
								interval" are possible meanings, but inconsistent with <foreign xml:lang="grc">DIA\ TE/LEOS</foreign> later on.</note> becoming
							afterwards short.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Seventeenth day.</hi> Bowels under a stimulus passed
							disordered matters, then her very drink passed unchanged ; nothing
							coagulated. The patient noticed nothing ; the skin tense and dry.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Much rambling followed by recovery of
							reason ; speechless ; respiration short.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-first day.</hi> Death.</p>
						               <p>The respiration of this patient throughout was</p>
						               <pb n="p.285"/>
						               <p>rare and large ; took no notice of anything ; she constantly wrapped
							herself up ; either much rambling or silence throughout.<note>In many
								ways this case, though one of the most picturesque, is also one of
								the most carelessly written. Galen points out that <foreign xml:lang="grc">DIA\ *XPO/NON</foreign> is ambiguous, and that
								its possible meanings are inconsistent with the rest of the
								description. How can the respiration be <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)RAIO/N</foreign> throughout, when on both the fourteenth and
								the twentieth days the patient was <foreign xml:lang="grc">BRAXU/PNOOS2</foreign> ? It is strange that the writer
								specifies the fourteenth day as the day when the respiration was
								rare and large, seeing that it had these characteristics throughout.
								A similar remark applies to <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)NAIS1QH/TWS
									EI)XE PA/NTWN</foreign> of the seventeenth day. Further,
									<foreign xml:lang="grc">A)EI\ S1IGW=S1A</foreign> of the second
								sentence becomes strangely <foreign xml:lang="grc">H(\ LO/GOI
									XOLLOI\ H(\ S1IGW=S1A DIA\ TE/LEOS2</foreign> in the last. I
								conclude that this medical history was hastily written and never
								revised. A slight revision could easily have cleared away the
								inconsistencies, which are, as Galen seems to have seen, more
								apparent than real.</note>
                     </p>
					             </div>
					             <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
						               <head>C<hi rend="sc">ASE</hi> XVI </head>
						               <p>In Meliboea a youth took to his bed after being for a long time heated by
							drunkenness and sexual indulgence. He had shivering fits, nausea,
							sleeplessness, but no thirst.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">First day.</hi> Copious, solid stools passed in abundance
							of fluid, and on the following days the excreta were copious, watery and
							of a greenish yellow. Urine thin, scanty and of no colour ; respiration
							rare and large with long intervals ; tension, soft underneath, of the
								hypochondrium,<note>See note, p. 188.</note> extending out to either
							side ; continual throbbing throughout of the epigastrium ;<note>So
								Littré, following Galen. Perhaps, however, it means " heart," <hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> there was violent palpitation.</note>
							urine oily.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Tenth day.</hi> Delirious but quiet, for he was orderly
							and silent ;<note>Said by Galen, followed by Littré (who reads <foreign xml:lang="grc">H(/S1UXOS2</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">S1IGW=N</foreign>), to refer to the character of the young man
								when well, which interpretation to modern minds is rather
								inconsistent with the first sentence. They would paraphrase, " the
								delirium was really serious, but appeared slight because the patient
								was naturally self-controlled and calm." I take the meaning to be
								that though delirious he remained quiet and comparatively
								silent.</note> skin dry and tense ; stools either copious and thin
							or bilious and greasy.</p>
						               <pb n="p.287"/>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Fourteenth day.</hi> General exacerbation ; delirious
							with much wandering talk.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twentieth day.</hi> Wildly out of his mind ; much tossing
							; urine suppressed ; slight quantities of drink were retained.</p>
						               <p>
                        <hi rend="ital">Twenty-fourth day.</hi> Death.</p>
					             </div>
				           </div>
			         </div>


			         <pb n="p.291"/>
		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
