<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Charon, or the Inspectors</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor>Austin Morris Harmon, 1878-1950</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>OCRd, tagged and added initial corrections to  the text</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg001.1st1K-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1915</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.b000604154">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
<head>Charon, or the Inspectors
<note>
A presentation of the life of man as it appears to Charon the ferryman, who knows how it all ends. The world which Charon visits and comments on is that of the sixth century B.C., not that of Lucian’s day, for to Lucian as to most of his contemporaries the life that he found in books was more interesting and more real than that in which he lived and moved. What his satire loses in pungency on this account, it gains in universality of appeal.
</note>
</head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="1"><p>
<label>HERMES</label>
Wht are you laughing at, Charon, and why have
you left your ferry and come up here to our part of
the world? You are not at all in the habit of concerning yourself with affairs up above.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
I wanted to see what it is like in life, Hermes,
what men do in it, and what they lose that makes
them all grieve when they come down to us; for
none of them has ever made the crossing without a
tear. So, like the young Thessalian (Protesilaus), I
obtained shore leave from Hades for a single day and
came up to the sunlight, and I fancy that I have
been lucky to meet you, for you will surely go about
with me and guide me, and will show me everything, knowing all about it as you do.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
I haven't time, ferryman; I am on my way to
carry out a little commission among men for Zeus in
Heaven.<note n="v.2.p.397.n.1">Contrasted in thought with Zeus of the nether world; i.e. Pluto.</note> He is quick-tempered, and I fear that if
I am slow about it he will let me be yours altogether,
committing me to the nether gloom, or else that he
will treat me as he did Hephaestus the other day,
taking me.by the foot and throwing me from the

<pb n="v.2.p.399"/>

parapet of Heaven, so that I too may limp and make
them laugh as I fill their cups.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Then will you let me wander aimlessly above
ground, you who are a comrade and a shipmate and a
fellow guide of souls? Come now, son of Maea, you
would do well to remember this at least, that I have
never ordered you to bale or take an oar. On the
contrary, you stretch yourself out on deck and
snore, in spite of those broad shoulders of yours, or
if you find a talkative dead man, you chat with him
throughout the trip, while I, old as I am, row both
oars of my boat alone. Come, in your father’s name,
Hermie dear, don’t leave me stranded; be my guide
to everything in life, so that I may feel I have seen
something when I go back. If you leave me, I shall
be no better off than the blind, for they stumble and
reel about in the darkness, while I, to the contrary,
am dazed in the light. Be good to me, Cyllenian,
and I shall remember your kindness forever.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="2"><p>


<label>HERMES</label>
This business will stand me in a thrashing ; at any
rate I see even now that my pay for playing guide
will certainly include plenty of fisticufls. But I
must comply all the same, for what can a man do
when a friend insists ?</p>
<p>
For you to see everything minutely in detail is impossible, ferryman, since it would busy us for many
years. In that event Zeus would be obliged to have
me advertized by the crier, like a runaway slave, and
you yourself would be prevented from doing the

<pb n="v.2.p.401"/>

work of Death and compelled to embarrass the revenues of Pluto’s government by not bringing in aly
dead for a long time ; besides, Aeacus the toll-taker
would be angry if he did not make even an obol. We
must manage it so that you can see the principal
things that are going on.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
You must determine what is best, Hermes; I
know nothing at all about things above ground, being
a stranger.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
In a word, Charon, we want a high place of some
sort, from which you can look down upon everything.
If it were possible for you to go up into Heaven, we
should be in no difficulty, for you could see everything plainly from on high. But as it is not permissible for one who consorts always with shades to set
foot in the palace of Zeus, we must look about for a
high mountain.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="3"><p>

<label>CHARON</label>
You know, Hermes, what I am in the habit of
telling you and the others when we are on the water.
When we are close-hauled and the wind in a sudden
squall strikes the sail and the waves rise high, then
you all in your ignorance tell me to take the sail in
or slack the sheet off a bit or run before the wind ;
but I urge you to keep quiet, saying that I myself
know what is best. Just so in this case; you must
do whatever you think is right, for you are skipper
now, and I will sit in silence, as a passenger should,
and obey your orders in everything.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Quite right; I will see what is to be done, and

<pb n="v.2.p.403"/>

will find the proper coign of vantage. Well then,
will Caucasus do, or Parnassus, or Olympus yonder,
which is higher than either? But no, as I looked at
Olympus an idea came to me that is not half bad;
but you must bear a hand and help me out.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Give your orders ; I will help as much as I can,
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
The poet Homer says that the sons of Alocus, who,
like ourselves, were two in number, took a faney
once upon a time while they were still mere children
to pluck Ossa from its base and set it on Olympus,
and then to set Pelion on top of it, thinking that
this would give them a suitable ladder with which
to scale Heaven.<note n="v.2.p.403.n.1">Od. 11, 305.</note> Well, these two lads were
sacrilegious and they were punished for it; but we
two are not making this plan to harm the gods, so
why shouldn’t we build in the same way, rolling the
mountains one atop of another, in order to secure a
better view from a higher place?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="4">
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Shall we be able to lift Pelion or Ossa and heave
it up, Hermes, when there are only two of us ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Why not, Charon? Surely you don’t consider us
weaker than that pair of infants? Moreover, we are
gods.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
No, but the thing seems to me to involve an
incredible deal of work,

<pb n="v.2.p.405"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
Of course, for you are only a prosaic body, Charon,
and not a bit of a poet. Good Homer, however, has
made it possible for us to scale Heaven in a jiffy
with a pair of verses, for he puts the mountains
together as easily as that. I am surprised that you
think this miraculous, for, of course, you know Atlas,
who carries Heaven itself without any help, upholding us all. And no doubt you have heard about
my brother Heracles, how he himself once took the
place of Atlas and relieved him of his load for a
time by taking the burden on his own shoulders.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Yes, I have heard that; but whether it is true or
not, Hermes, you and the poets only know!
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
True as can be, Charon. Why should wise men
lie? So let us uproot Ossa first, according to
the directions of the poem and the master-builder,
Homer ;

<cit><quote><l>then upon Ossa</l>
<l>Pelion quivering-leaved.</l></quote>
<bibl>Od. 11, 305.</bibl></cit>


Don’t you see how easily and poetically we have
done the job? Come now, let me climb up and see
if this is enough or we shall have to add to the pile.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="5"><p>

Upon my word, we are still away down among the
foot-hills of Heaven! Toward the east I can only
just. see Ionia and Lydia, toward the west not beyond
Italy and Sicily, toward the north only the country
on this side the Danube, and in that direction Crete,
but not very plainly. Apparently we must move up


<pb n="v.2.p.407"/>

Oeta too, ferryman, and then Parnassus to top them
all.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Let’s do so. But take care that we don’t make
the structure too slender by heightening it beyond
all reason, and so tumble down with it and pay
bitterly for our experiment in Homeric building by
breaking our heads.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Never fear; everything will be secure. Move
Oeta over. Roll Parnassus this way. There now, I
am going up again. — It is all right, I see everything:
now come up yourself.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Put out your hand, Hermes. This is an uncommonly big piece of stage-machinery that you are
mounting me on.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Must be done, if you are bound to see everything,
Charon. One can’t see sights without taking
chances. Come, take hold of my right hand and
look out you don’t step where it is slippery.  Good,
you are up too, As Parnassus has two peaks, let us
each take a suminit for himself and sit on it. Now,
then, look round about you and inspect everything.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

<label>CHARON</label>
I see a quantity of land with a great lagoon encircling it, mountains, rivers bigger than Cocytus and
Pyriphlegethon, tiny little men, and things which
look like their hiding-places.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Those things which you take to be hiding-places
are cities.

<pb n="v.2.p.409"/>

<label>CHARON</label>
Do you know, Hermes, we haven’t accomplished
anything, but have moved Mount Parnassus, Castaly
and all, Mount Oeta and the rest of them for
nothing.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Why?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
I can’t see anything plainly from on high. What
I wanted was not just to look at cities and mountains
as in a picture, but to observe men themselves, what
they are doing and what they are saying. For
instance, when we first met and you saw me laughing
and asked what I was laughing at, I had heard something which amused me vastly.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
What was it?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
A man who had been invited to dinner, I take it,
by one of his friends for the next day replied
“Certainly I shall come,” and even as he spoke a tile
from the roof which someone had dislodged fell
on him and killed him. I had to laugh at him
because he did not keep his promise—I_ think
I shall go down a little, so as to see and_ hear
better.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="7"><p>

<label>HERMES</label>
Hold still ; I will remedy that for you too and will.
make you sharp-sighted in a minute by getting
a charm out of Homer for this purpose as well as the
other. When I say the verses remember not to ‘be
short-sighted any longer, but to sce everything
distinctly.

<pb n="v.2.p.411"/>

<label>CHARON</label>
Only say them!
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>

<cit><quote><l>Lo, from your eyes I have lifted a veil that before was upon them.</l>
<l>So that your sight may be sure to distinguish a god from a mortal.</l></quote>
<bibl>Iliad5, 127 ff.</bibl></cit>

"Lo, from your eyes I have lifted a veil that before was upon them.
So that your sight may be sure to distinguish a god from a mortal.” !
How about it? Do you see now ?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Marvellously! Lynceus was a blind man beside
me; so now give me the necessary instruction and
answer. my questions. But would you like me to
ask them in the language of Homer, so that you
may know that I myself am not unfamiliar with his
poetry?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
How can you know any of it when you are always
on shipboard and at the oar?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
See here, that is a libel on my calling! When I
set’ him over the ferry after his death, I leard him
recite a quantity of verses and still remember some
of them, although a good bit of a storm caught us
then. You see, he began to sing a song that was
not too auspicious for ‘the passengers, telling how
Poseidon brought the clouds together, stirred up the
deep by plunging in his trident as if it were a ladle,
excited all the gales and a lot more of it. Thus he
put the sea in a commotion with his verses, and a
black squall suddenly struck us and just missed
capsizing the boat. Then he became seasick and
jettisoned most of his lays, including Scylla and


<pb n="v.2.p.413"/>

Charybdis and the Cyclops; so that it wasn’t hard
for me to get a little salvage out of all that he let
go.<note n="v.2.p.413.n.1">Lucian appears to have borrowed this from a picture by Galato in which the indebtedness of the other poets to Homer was caricatured with more force than elegance.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
Tell me:

<cit><quote><l>Who is the burly man yonder, the hero so tall and so handsome,</l>
<l>Towering over the throng by a head and a broadpair of shoulders ?</l></quote>
<bibl>Parody on Iliad3, 226 (Ajax).</bibl></cit>


<label>HERMES</label>
That is Milo, the athlete from Croton. The
Greeks are clapping their hands at him because he
has lifted the bull and is carrying him through the
centre of the stadium.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
How much more fitting it would be, Hermes, if
they should applaud me ; for in a little while I shall
seize Milo himself and heave him aboard the boat,
when he comes to us after getting thrown by Death,
the most invincible of all antagonists, without even
knowing how he was tripped! Then we shall hear
him wail, depend upon it, when he remembers these
crowns of victory and this applause; but now he
thinks highly of himself because of the admiration he
is winning for carrying the bull. What! Are we to
think that he expects to die some day ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES </label>:
Why should he think of death now, when he is so
young and strong?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Never mind him; he will give us food for laughter


<pb n="v.2.p.415"/>

before long when he makes his voyage and is no
longer able to lift a mosquito, let alone a bull!
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
Tell
me,

<cit><quote><l>Who is the other man yonder, the haughty one?</l></quote>
<bibl>Iliad3, 226 served as a model for this line also.</bibl></cit>

Not a Greek, it seems, from his dress at least.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
That is Cyrus, Charon, the son of Cambyses, who
has already transferred to the Persians the empire
that once belonged to the Medes. Moreover, he
recently conquered the Assyrians and brought Babylon to terms, and now he appears to be meditating a
campaign against Lydia, with the idea of overthrowing Croesus and ruling the world.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
And Croesus, where is he ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Look over there towards the great acropolis with
the triple wall. That is Sardis, and now you see
Croesus himself sitting on a golden throne, talking
with Solon of Athens. Would you like to listen to
what they are saying ?<note n="v.2.p.415.n.1">The conversation that follows is based on Herodotus 1.29-33.</note>
<label>CHARON</label>
By all means.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="10"><p>

<label>CROESUS</label>
My friend from Athens, as you have seen my
riches, my treasuries, all the bullion that I have and
the rest of my splendor, tell me whom do you
consider the most fortunate man in the world ?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
What will Solon say to that?


<pb n="v.2.p.417"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
Never fear ; nothing ignoble, Charon.
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Fortunate men are few, Croesus, but I consider
that of all the men I know, the most fortunate are
Cleobis and Biton, the sons of the priestess at Argos,
who died together the other day when they had
harnessed themselves and drawn their mother to the
temple on the wagon.<note n="v.2.p.417.n.1">In Herodotus Tellus gets the first place.</note>
<label>CROESUS </label>.
Very well, let them have the first rank in good
fortune. But who would be the second? :
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Tellus of Athens, who lived happily and died for
his country.
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
But what about me, knave? Don’t you think I
am fortunate ?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
I do not know, Croesus, and shall not until you
come to the close of your life. Death is a sure test
in such matters, that and a fortunate life right up to
the end.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Thank you kindly, Solon, for not forgetting us,<note n="v.2.p.417.n.2">Himself and Pluto.</note>
but demanding the decision of such matters to be
made right at the ferry.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

But who are those men
whom Croesus is sending out, and what are they
carrying on their shoulders ?<note n="v.2.p.417.n.3">Compare Herodotus i. 50 ff. The conversation between Solon and Croesus on the subject of the ingots is Lucian’s own contribution.</note>
<pb n="v.2.p.419"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
He is making an offering of golden ingots to Apollo
at Delphi to pay for the prophecies which will bring
him to grief a little later on. The man is monstrously daft on divination.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Is that gold, the bright substance that shines, the
pale yellow substance with a cast of red? This is
the first time that I have seen it, though I am always
hearing of it.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
That is it, Charon, the name that they sing of and
fight for.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Really I don’t see what good there is about it,
except perhaps for one thing, that its bearers find it
heavy.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
You do not know how many wars there have been
on account of it, how many plots, perjuries, murders,
imprisonments, trading ventures, and enslavements.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
On account of this substance, not much different
from bronze? I know bronze, for, as you are aware,
I collect an obol from everyone who makes the
downward journey.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Yes, but bronze is plentiful, so that they do not
prize it very highly, while this is dug up by the
miners at a great depth in small quantities. It
comes from the earth, however, like lead and the
rest of the metals.


<pb n="v.2.p.421"/>

<label>CHARON</label>
Men are terribly stupid, by what you say, since
they have such a passion for a yellow, heavy
substance.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Well, at any rate Solon yonder does not seem to
love it, Charon, as you see, for he is laughing at
Croesus and his barbarian boastfulness, and to my
mind he wants to ask him a question. Let us listen,
then.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="12"><p>

<label>SOLON</label>
Tell me, Croesus, do you really think that Apollo
has any need of these ingots?
</p>
<p><label>CROE</label>sUS
Good Heavens, yes! He has nothing to match
them among the votive offerings at Delphi.
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Then you expect to make the god happy if he adds
ingots of gold to the rest of his possessions ?
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
Why not?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
They are very poor in Heaven from what you say,
since they have to send and get gold from Lydia
if they want it.
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
Why, where else can there be as much gold as
there is in our country ?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Tell me, is iron produced in Lydia ?
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
Not to any great extent.

<pb n="v.2.p.423"/>

<label>SOLON</label>
Then you are poor in the better metal.
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
In what way is iron better than gold ?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
If you will answer my questions without getting
angry, you will find out.
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
Ask them, Solon.
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Who is the better man, the one who saves a life or
the one who is saved by him ?
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
The one who saves a life of course.
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Then if Cyrus attacks the Lydians, as rumour has
it that he will, shall you get swords of gold made
for your army, or will iron be necessary in that case?
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
Iron, certainly.
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Yes, and if you should not provide iron, your gold
would go off to Persia in captivity.
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
Don’t speak of such a thing, man!
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
I pray it may not turn out that way; but you
clearly admit that iron is better than gold.
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
Then would you have me offer ingots of iron to
the god and call the gold back again ?

<pb n="v.2.p.425"/>

<label>SOLON</label>
He will have no need of iron either, not he!
Whether you offer bronze or gold, your offering will
be a boon and a blessing to ethers than he—to the
Phocians or the Boeotians or the Delphians themselves, or else to some tyrant or freebooter; but the
god takes little interest in your gold-work.
</p>
<p><label>CROESUS</label>
You are always at war with my wealth and
begrudge me it.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="13"><p>

<label>HERMES</label>
The Lydian cannot abide the outspokenness and
the truthfulness of his words, Charon; it seems
strange to him when a poor man does not cringe but
says frankly whatever occurs to him. But he will
remember Solon before long, when he has to be captured and put on the pyre by Cyrus. The other day
I heard Clotho reading out the fate that had been
spun for everyone, and among other things it had
been recorded there that Croesus was to be “captured
by Cyrus, and that Cyrus was to be slain by yonder
woman of the Massagetae. Do you see her, the
Scythian woman riding the white horse?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Indeed I do.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
That is Tomyris ; and after she has cut off Cyrus’
head she will plunge it into a wine-skin full of
blood. And do you see his son, the young man?
That is Cambyses ; he will be king after his father,
and when he has had no end of ill-luck in Libya and

<pb n="v.2.p.427"/>

Ethiopia he will at last go mad and die in consequence
of slaying Apis.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
How very funny! But now who would dare to
look at them, so disdainful are they of the rest of
the world? And who could believe that after a
little the one will be a prisoner and the other will
have his head in a sack of blood? </p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="14"><p>But who is that
man, Hermes, with the purple mantle about him, the
one with the crown, to whom the cook, who has just
cut open the fish, is giving the ring,

<cit><quote><l>All in a sea-girt island; a king he would have us
believe him</l></quote>
<bibl>The verse is composed of the beginning of Odyssey1, 50 and the end of Odyssey 1, 180.</bibl></cit>?<note n="v.2.p.427.n.1">Another allusion to a story in Herodotus (3, 39-43).</note>

<label>HERMES</label>
You are good at parody, Charon. The man whom
you see is Polycrates, the tyrant of Samos, who
considers himself wholly fortunate; yet the servant
who stands at his elbow, Maeandrius, will betray him
into the hands of the satrap Oroetes, and he will
be crucified, poor man, after losing his good fortune
inamoment’s time. This, too, I heard trom Clotho.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Well done, Clotho, noble lady that you are!
Burn them, gracious lady, cut off their heads and
crucify them, so that they may know they are
human. In the meantime let them be exalted,
only to have a sorrier fall from a higher place. For
my part I shall laugh when I recognize them aboard
my skiff, stripped to the skin, taking with them
neither purple mantle nor tiara nor throne of gold.

<pb n="v.2.p.429"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
<label>HERMES</label>
That is the way their lives will end. But do you
see the masses, Charon, the men voyaging, fighting,
litigating, farming, lending money, and begging ?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
I see that their activities are varied and their life
full of turmoil ; yes, and their cities resemble hives,
in which everyone has a sting of his own and stings
his neighbour, while some few, like wasps, harry
and plunder the meaner sort. But what is that
crowd of shapes that flies about them unseen ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Hope, Fear, Ignorance, Pleasure, Covetousness,
Anger, Hatred and their like. Of these, Ignorance
mingles with them down below and shares their
common life, and so do Hatred, Anger, Jealousy,
Stupidity, Doubt, and Covetousness; but Fear and
Hope hover up above, and Fear, swooping down
from time to time, terrifies them and makes them
cringe, while Hope, hanging overhead, flies up and
is off when they are most confident of grasping her,
leaving them in the lurch with their mouths open,
exactly as you have seen Tantalus served by the
water down below.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="16"><p>

If you look close, you will also
see the Fatés up above, drawing off each man’s
thread from the spindle to which, as it happens, one
and all are attached by slender threads. Do you see
cobwebs, if I may call them so, coming down to each
man from the spindles? .

<pb n="v.2.p.431"/>

<label>CHARON</label>
I see that each man has a very slender thread, and
it is entangled in most cases, this one with that and
that with another.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
With good reason, ferryman; it is fated for that
man to be killed by this man and this man by
another, and for this man to be heir to that one,
whose thread is shorter, and that man in turn to this
one. That is what the entanglement means. You
see, however, that they all hang by slender threads.
Furthermore, this man has been drawn up on high
and hangs in mid-air, and after a little while, when
the filament, no longer strong enough to hold his
weight, breaks and he falls to earth, he will make
a great noise; but this other, who is lifted but
little above the ground, will come down, if at all, so
noiselessly that even his neighbours will hardly hear
his fall.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
All this is very funny, Hermes.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="17"><p>

<label>HERMES</label>
Indeed, you cannot find words to tell how ridiculous it is, Charon, especially their inordinate ambition and the way in which they disappear from
the scene in the midst of their hopes, carried off
by our good friend Death. His messengers and
servants are very many, as you see—chills, fevers,
wasting sicknesses, inflammations of the lungs,
swords, pirate vessels, bowls of hemlock, judges, and
tyrants ; and no thought of any of these occurs to
them while they are prosperous, but when the
come to grief, many are the cries of “Oh!” and

<pb n="v.2.p.433"/>

“Ah!” and “O dear me!” If they had realized
at the very beginning that they were mortal, and
that after this brief sojourn in the world they
would go away as from a dream, taking leave of
everything above ground, they would live more
sanely and would be less unhappy after death.<note n="v.2.p.433.n.1">Most of the dead are unhappy, as Hermes and Charon well know. See the Downward Journey, and even Homer’s Achilles (Odyssey 11, 488).</note>
But as it is, they have imagined that what they
have now will be theirs forever, and so, when the
servant, standing at their bedside, summons them
and hales them off in the bonds of fever or consumption, they make a great to-do about it, for they
never expected to be torn away from their gear. For
example, that man who is busily building himself a
house and driving the workmen on; w hat would not
he do if he knew that although the house will be
finished, as soon as he gets the roof on, he himself will
depart and leave his heir the enjoyment of it without even dining in it, poor fellow? And as for the
man over there, who rejoices because his wife has
borne him a son and entertains his friends in
honour of the occasion and gives the boy his
father’s name, if he knew that the boy willdie atthe
age of seven, do you think he would rejoice over
his birth? No, it is because he sees yonder man
who is fortunate in his son, the father of the athlete
who has been victor at the Olympic games, but
does not see his next door neighbour, who is burying
his son, and does not know what manner of thread
his own son has been attached to. Again, take
those who quarrel about boundaries—you see how
numerous they are; likewise those who heap up

<pb n="v.2.p.435"/>

money and then, before enjoying it, receive a
summons from the messengers and servants that I
mentioned.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

<label>CHARON</label>
I see all this, and am wondering what pleasure
they find in life and what it is that they are distressed to lose. For example, if one considers their
kings, who are counted most happy, quite apart from
the instability and uncertainty of their fortune
which you allude to, one will find that the pleasures
which they have are fewer than the pains, for terrors,
alarums, enmities, plots, rage, and flattery are with
them always. I say nothing of sorrows, diseases,
and misadventures, which of course dominate them
without partiality ; but when their lot is hard, one is
driven to conjecture what the lot of common men
must be.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="19"><p>

Let me tell you, Hermes, what I think men and
the whole life of man resemble. You have noticed
bubbles in water, caused by a streamlet plashing
down—I mean those that mass to make foam?
Some of them, being small, burst and are gone in an
instant, while some last longer and as others join
them, become swollen and grow to exceeding great
compass ; but afterwards they also burst without fail
in time, for it cannot be otherwise. Such is the life
of men; they are all swollen with wind, some to
greater size, others to less; and with some the
swelling is short-lived and swift-fated, while with
others it is over as soon as it comes into being ; but
in any case they all must burst.
<pb n="v.2.p.437"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
Charon, your simile is every bit as good as Homer's,
who compares the race of man to leaves.<note n="v.2.p.437.n.1">Iliad 6, 146.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="20"><p>

<label>CHARON</label>
And although they are like that, Hermes, you see
what they do and how ambitious they are, vying
with each other for offices, honours, and possessions,
all of which they must leave behind them and come
down to us with but a single obol. As we are ina
high place, would you like me to call out in a great
voice and urge them to desist from their vain labours
and live always with death before their eyes, saying :
“Vain creatures, why have you set your hearts on
these things? Cease toiling, for your lives will not
endure forever. Nothing that is in honour here
is eternal, nor can a man take anything with him
when he dies; nay, it is inevitable that he depart
naked, and that his house and his land and his
money go first to one and then to another, changing
their owners.” If I should call to them out of a
commanding place and say all this and more, do you
not think that they would be greatly assisted in life
and made saner by far ?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="21">
<p><label>HERMES</label>
My dear fellow, you do not know how Ignorance
and Error have served them. Even a drill could not
penetrate their ears now, because these dames have
stopped them with such quantities of wax, like
Odysseus, who did this to his comrades for fear that
they might hear the Sirens. How could they hear,
then, even if you should crack your lungs with
bawling? What lies in the power of Lethe down

<pb n="v.2.p.439"/>

below is done by Ignorance here. However, there
are a few of them who have not admitted the wax
into their ears, who are devoted to truth, who look
keenly into things and know them for what they
are.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Then let us call to them at least.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
It would be superfluous to tell them what they
know. You see how they stand aloof from the
masses and laugh at what goes on ; they are not in
the least satisfied with it all, but are clearly planning
to make their escape from life to your own regions.
Indeed, they have reason, for they are disliked
because they expose the follies of man. ¢
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Well done, staunch souls! But they are very few,
Hermes.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Even these are enough. But let us go down now.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="22"><p>

<label>CHARON</label>
There is one thing more that I wanted to know
about, Hermes, and when you point it out to me you
will have done your full duty as guide; it is to see
the places where they stow the bodies, where they
bury them, I mean.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
They call such places vaults, tombs and graves.
Do you see those heaps of earth and slabs of stone
and pyramids in front of the cities? All those
are for the reception of corpses and the storage of
bodies.

<pb n="v.2.p.441"/>

<label>CHARON</label>
Why is it, then, that those people are putting
garlands on the stones and anointing them with
perfume ? There are others also who have built
pyres in front of the mounds and have dug trenches,
and now they are burning up those fine dinners and
pouring wine and mead, as far as one may judge,
into the ditches.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
I don’t know what good these things are to men
in Hades, ferryman; they are convinced, however,
that the souls, allowed to come up from below, get
their dinner as best they may by flitting about the
smoke and steam and drink the mead out of the
trench.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
What, they eat and drink, when their skulls are
dry as tinder? But it is silly for me to tell that to
you, who bring them down below every day; you
know whether they can come back to earth when
they have once gone under ground! I should be in
a fine predicament, Hermes, and should have no end
of trouble if I were obliged not only to bring them
down but to bring them up to drink ! What folly,
the idiots ! They do not know what an impassable
frontier divides the world of the dead from the
world of the living, and what it is like among us;
that

<cit><quote>

<l>Death maketh mortals alike, be they buried or lying unburied.</l>
<l>Equal is lrus the beggar in honour to King Agamemnon ;</l>
<l>Fair-haired Thetis’ son is no better a man than Thersites,</l>
<l>Aye, they are all of them nothing but skeleton relics of dead men,</l>
<l>Bare, dry bones that are scattered about in the asphodel meadow. </l>
</quote>
<bibl>A cento from Homer patched up out of Iliad9, 319-320 ; Odyssey10, 521; 11, 539, 573.</bibl></cit>



<pb n="v.2.p.443"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="23"><p>

<label>HERMES</label>
Heracles! What a lot of Homer you are baling
out! Now you have put me in mind of him, I want
to show you the tomb of Achilles. Do you see it,
there by the seaside ?_ Sigeum in Troy is over there,
and opposite to it Ajax lies buried on Rhoeteum.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
The tombs are not large, Hermes. But now show
me the prominent cities that we hear of down below,
Nineveh, the city of Sardanapalus, Babylon, Mycenae,
Cleonae, and Troy itself; I remember that I set a
great many from that place across the ferry, so that
for ten whole years I couldn’t dock my boat or dry
her out.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
As for Nineveh, ferryman, it is already gone and
there is nota trace of it left now; you couldn't even
say where it was. But there you have Babylon, the
city of the beautiful towers and the great wall, which
will itself soon have to be searched for like Nineveh.
I am ashamed to show you Mycenae and Cleonae,
and Troy above all; for I know right well that when
you go down-you will throttle Homer for the boastfulness of his poems. Yet they were once flourishing,
though now they too are dead ; cities die as well as
men, ferryman, and, what is more, even whole rivers.


<pb n="v.2.p.445"/>

In fact, even the grave of Inachus no longer survives
in Argos.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
That for your praises, Homer, and your adjectives
— “hallowed,” “wide-wayed”” Troy and “well-built” Cleonae!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg023.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

But while we are talking, who are
those people at war yonder, and why are they killing
each other?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
You are looking at the Argives and Spartans,
Charon, and over there is the dying general Othryadas, the one who is writing on the trophy in his
own blood.<note n="v.2.p.445.n.1">Three hundred Spartans fought an equal number of Argives for the possession of Thyreatis. Two Argives and a single dying Spartan survived the fight. The Argives hastened home to report their victory; but the Spartan managed to put up a trophy and write upon it 2 dedication to Zeus in his own blood. Herod. 1,82; Plut. Moral. 306 B.</note>
<label>CHARON</label>
What is their war about, Hermes ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
About the very plain in which they are fighting.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
What folly! They do not know that even if any
one of them should acquire the whole Peloponnese,
he could hardly get Aeacus to give him a foot of
space. And as for this plain, it will be tilled by one
race after another, and many a time they will turn
the trophy up out of the depths with the plough.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
True. But now let’s get down and replace the
mountains, and then go our ways, I on my crrand

<pb n="v.2.p.447"/>

and you to your ferry. I will follow vou soon with a
convoy of dead.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
I am much obliged to you, Hermes; you shall be
written down for ever as a benefactor. ‘Thanks to
you, I have had some profit from my journey. How
silly are the ways of unhappy mankind, with their
kings, golden ingots, funeral rites and battles—but
never a thought of Charon!

<pb n="v.2.p.449"/>



<pb n="v.2.p.451"/>
</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>
