<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Against Alcibiades from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
				<author>Andocides</author>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>


			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Andocides</author>
						<title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes 1, Antiphon Andocides, with an
							English translation by K. J. Maidment, M.A.</title>

						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
								Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1968</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="speech" delim="."/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English </language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek </language>
				<language ident="latin">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--
<change><date>3/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>redo tagging</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
	<change><date>5/27/09</date><respStmt><name>RS</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt>
		<item>  
			$Log: andoc_eng.xml,v $
			Revision 1.1  2009-10-09 19:49:16  rsingh04
			more reorganizing of texts module by collection

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/07 21:00:34  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.10  2009/06/22 19:33:09  student
			edited entity tags CEH

			Revision 1.9  2009/05/27 15:55:16  rsingh04
			added cvs log keyword

		</item>
	</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
			<change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="part" n="Intro">
				<div type="section" n="1">
					<p>This is not the first occasion upon which the perils of engaging in politics
						have come home to me; I regarded it as no less hazardous in the past, before
						I had concerned myself in any way with affairs of state. Yet I consider it
						the duty of the good citizen, not to withhold himself from public life for
						fear of making personal enemies, but to be ready to face danger for the
						benefit of the community. Those who think only of themselves contribute
						nothing to a state's advancement; it is to those who think of the state that
						its greatness and its independence are due. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="2">
					<p>I myself desired to be included in this number: and consequently I now find
						myself in the utmost peril. True, in yourselves I have an audience actively
						devoted to the public good, and that circumstance makes for my salvation;
						but I have innumerable enemies of the most dangerous kind, and by them I am
						being misrepresented. Nor is the contest in which I am engaged for the
						winning of a crown; it is to decide whether one who has done the state no
						wrong is to spend ten years in exile. The competitors for that prize are
						Alcibiades, Nicias, and myself. Upon one of us the blow must fall. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="3">
					<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now the legislator<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">Cleisthenes, in <date>510</date> B.C ., cf. <bibl
								n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 22">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 22</bibl>. <foreign
								xml:lang="greek">kai\ ga\r sune/bh tou\s me\n *so/lwnos no/mous
								a)fani/sai th\n turanni/da dia\ to\ mh\ xrh=sqai, kainou\s dÕ
								a)/llous qei=nai to\n *kleisqe/nhn stoxazo/menon tou= plh/qous, e)n
								oi(=s e)te/qh kai\ o( peri\ tou= o)strakismou= no/mos</foreign>. For
							the procedure cf. Philochorus frag. 79b, F.G.H. i. 396.</note>
						responsible for this deserves censure; for the law which he framed violates
						the oath of the People and Council. Under the terms of that oath you swear
						to exile no one, to imprison no one, to put no one to death, without trial;
						whereas on this present occasion, when the person ostracized is to be cut
						off from his country for so long, no accusation has been made, no defence
						allowed, and the voting is secret. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="4">
					<p>Moreover, at a time like this those who have political associates and
						confederates have an advantage over the rest, because the judges are not
						appointed by lot as in courts of law: in the present decision every member
						of the community has a voice. And not only that: the law appears to me to go
						both too far and not far enough; for wrongs done to individuals I consider
						such redress as this excessive: for wrongs done to the state I regard it as
						an insufficient and useless penalty, when you have the right to punish by
						fine, imprisonment, or death. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="5">
					<p>Furthermore, if a man is exiled because he is a bad citizen, his leaving
							<placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> will not cure him;
						wherever he lives, he will do this city harm and intrigue against her no
						less than hitherto—nay more so and with more justification than before his
						banishment. Today, too, above all days, your friends, I feel, are filled
						with sorrow and your enemies with joy, because they know that if you
						unwittingly banish your best citizen, <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName> will derive no benefit from him for ten years. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="6">
					<p>Then still another fact makes it easy to see that the law is a bad one: we
						are the only Greeks to observe it, and no other state is prepared to imitate
							us.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The evidence on the subject of
							ostracism in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> at large is
							too inconclusive to enable us either to accept or to reject this
							statement with confidence. It is known that the institution existed for
							a time at least at <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>
								(<bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 5.1302b.18">Aristot. Pol. 8.3, 1302b
								18</bibl>), at <placeName key="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>
							(Schol. <bibl n="Aristoph. Kn. 855">Aristoph. Kn. 855</bibl>), at
								<placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName> (ibid.), and at
								<placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> (<bibl
								n="Diod. 11.87.6">Dio. Sic. 11.87.6</bibl>). It was introduced at
								<placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> in
								<date>454</date> B.C. under the name of <foreign xml:lang="greek"
								>petalismo/s</foreign>, definitely in imitation of <placeName
								key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> Yet it is recognized
						that the best institutions are those which have proved most suited to
						democracy and oligarchy alike and which are the most generally favoured.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="7">
					<p>I see no reason for dwelling further on this subject, as, whatever the
						outcome, I should achieve nothing of immediate advantage. But I do ask you
						to preside over our speeches in a fair and impartial manner, and one and all
						to act as Archons.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Dalmeyda (Andoc., ed.
							Bude) is probably right in explaining this as a reference to the
							procedure observed when an <foreign xml:lang="greek"
								>o)strakismo/s</foreign> was held. According to the Scholiast on
								<bibl n="Aristoph. Kn. 855">Aristoph. Kn. 855</bibl>, the people met
							under the presidency of the Archons and the Boule, i.e. the Archons
							together with the Prytanes in office for the time being. These last
							would have one of their members as <foreign xml:lang="greek"
								>e)pista/ths</foreign> or president for the day. The speaker is
							therefore urging his audience to regard themselves as placed in the same
							responsible position as the Archons and <foreign xml:lang="greek"
								>e)pista/ths tw=n prutane/wn</foreign></note> Do not countenance
						abuse or undue flattery. Show yourselves kindly to him who desires to speak
						and to listen: show yourselves stern to him who is insolent and disorderly;
						for you will decide our fate all the better, if each of the cases to be laid
						before you is given a hearing.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="NarrProof" n="0">
				<div type="section" n="8">
					<p>It remains for me to make a brief reference to my hostility to the democracy
						and my membership of a political faction. Had I never appeared in court, you
						would have had some reason for listening to my accusers, and it would have
						been necessary for me to answer them on these points. But since I have been
						tried and acquitted four times, I do not consider any further discussion of
						the subject justified. Before a man is tried, it is difficult to know
						whether the charges made against him are false or true; but after his
						acquittal or conviction the matter is decided, and it is settled whether
						they are the one or the other. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="9">
					<p>Hence I cannot but think it strange that while defendants who are convicted
						by but a single vote<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. by a majority of
							one. If the jury was equally divided, the accused was acquitted. Cf.
								<bibl n="Antiph. 5.51">Antiph. 5.51</bibl>.</note> are put to death
						and have their property confiscated by you, those who win their case should
						have to face the same charges again: that while the court has the power to
						take away life, it should so clearly lack the authority to save it once and
						finally, especially as the laws forbid the same charge to be brought twice
						against the same defendant, and you have sworn to observe those laws. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="10">
					<p>I shall therefore say nothing of myself. I wish instead to remind you of the
						past of Alcibiades— although such is the multitude of his misdeeds that I am
						at a loss where to begin: there is not one of them that does not press for
						mention. Were I faced with the task of describing at length his career as an
						adulterer, as a stealer of the wives of others, as a perpetrator of acts of
						lawless violence in general, the time at my disposal would be all too short,
						and I should furthermore earn the ill-will of many of my fellows for making
						public the injuries which they have suffered. Of his conduct towards the
						state, however, and towards the members of his family and such citizens and
						foreigners as have crossed his path, I will give you some account. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="11">
					<p>To begin with, he persuaded you to revise the assessment of the tribute of
						the subject-states made with the utmost fairness by Aristeides.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In <date>478</date> B.C., at the formation
							of the Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>.
							According to Thucydides (<bibl n="Thuc. 1.96">Thuc. 1.96</bibl>), the
							tribute as assessed by Aristeides amounted to 460 talents. It is
							difficult to accept this statement, as the existing quota-lists show
							that even between <date>450</date> B.C. and <date when="-436">436</date>
							B.C., when the Confederacy was far larger and contributions of money had
							almost entirely superseded those of ships, the total sum collected never
							exceeded 455 talents. The original assessment of Aristeides cannot have
							produced much more than 250 talents.</note> Chosen with nine others to
						perform the task,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Nothing is known of this
							reassessment. In <date>425</date> B.C. the existing tribute had been
							practically doubled, probably at the instigation of Cleon (I.G. i1. 63);
							and the speaker may conceivably be making a mistaken reference to this,
							although Alcibiades would have been only about twenty-five at the time,
							and therefore too young to be concerned in it. A second attempt to
							increase the revenue was made c. 413, when a 5 per cent toll on maritime
							commerce was instituted in lieu of tribute (Thucyd. vii. 28).</note> he
						practically doubled the contribution of each member of the alliance, while
						by showing how formidable he was and how influential, he made the revenues
						of the state a means of procuring revenue for himself.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">i.e. he used his position to extort blackmail, under
							threat of an excessive assessment.</note> Now just consider: when our
						safety depends entirely upon our allies and those allies are acknowledged to
						be worse off today than in the past, how could anyone do greater mischief
						than by doubling the tribute of each? </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="12">
					<p>In fact, if you hold that Aristeides was a good Athenian and a just one, you
						can only regard Alcibiades as a scoundrel, since his policy towards the
						subject-states is the exact opposite of that of Aristeides. Indeed, because
						of his behaviour, many are leaving their homes as exiles and going off to
						settle at <placeName key="perseus,Thurii">Thurii</placeName><note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A colony founded in <date>453</date> B.C. on
							the site of <placeName key="perseus,Sybaris">Sybaris</placeName> in S.
							Italy. The bulk of the settlers were Athenian, although numbers came
							from all parts of the Greek world.</note>; while the bitter feeling of
						the allies will manifest itself directly there is a war at sea between
							<placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and ourselves. In my
						own opinion, he is a worthless statesman who considers only the present
						without also giving thought to the future, who advocates the policy which
						will best please the people and says nothing of that which their true
						interests require. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="13">
					<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I am astonished, furthermore, at those who are
						persuaded that Alcibiades is a lover of democracy, that form of government
						which more than any other would seem to make equality its end. They are not
						using his private life as evidence of his character, in spite of the fact
						that his greed and his arrogance are plain to them. On his marriage with the
						sister of Callias he received a dowry of ten talents; yet after
							Hipponicus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For Hipponicus and Callius
							cf. <bibl n="Andoc. 1.115">Andoc. 1.115</bibl>, 130.</note> had lost his
						life as one of the generals at <placeName key="tgn,6001700"
							>Delium</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In
								<date>424</date> B.C. Demosthenes and Hippocrates planned a joint
							invasion of <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>. The scheme
							miscarried; and the Athenians were heavily defeated at <placeName
								key="tgn,6001700">Delium</placeName>.</note> he exacted another ten,
						on the ground that Hipponicus had agreed to add this further sum as soon as
						Alcibiades should have a child by his daughter. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="14">
					<p>Then, after obtaining a dowry such as no Greek had ever obtained before, he
						behaved in so profligate a fashion, bringing mistresses, slave and free,
						into the bridal house, that he drove his wife, who was a decent woman, to
						present herself before the Archon, as she was legally entitled to do, and
						divorce him. At that he gave conspicuous proof of his power. He called in
						his friends, and carried off his wife from the Agora by force, showing the
						whole world his contempt for the magistrates, the laws, and his fellow
						Athenians in general. Nor was this one outrage enough for him. He went
						further. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="15">
					<p>In order to possess himself of Hipponicus' estate, he planned the
						assassination of Callias. Callias himself accused him of it before you all
						in the Assembly, and, for fear that his wealth would cost him his life, made
						over his property to the state in the event of his dying without issue.
						However, Callias neither lacks friends nor is he an easy victim. Thanks to
						his riches he can be sure of protection in plenty. None the less, when a man
						offers violence to his own wife and plots the death of his brother-in-law,
						how is he to be expected to behave towards such of his fellow-citizens as
						cross his path? Everyone has more regard for members of his own family than
						he has for strangers. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="16">
					<p>But most monstrous of all is the fact that a man of his character should talk
						as though he were a friend of the people, and call others oligarchs and foes
						of the democracy. Yes, although he himself deserves death for behaving as he
						does, he is chosen by you to proceed against any whose sympathies conflict
						with yours ; and he poses as guardian of the constitution, in spite of the
						fact that he refuses to be the equal of, or but little superior to, his
						fellows. So completely, indeed, does he despise you that he spends his time
						flattering you in a body and insulting you individually. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="17">
					<p>Why, there are no limits to his impudence. He persuaded Agatharchus, the
						artist, to accompany him home,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Plutarch
							also mentions this episode (<bibl n="Plut. Alc. 16">Plut. Alc.
							16</bibl>) but adds that Alcibiades sent Agatharchus away with a
							reward.</note> and then forced him to paint; and when Agatharchus
						appealed to him, stating with perfect truth that he could not oblige him at
						the moment because he had other engagements, Alcibiades threatened him with
						imprisonment, unless he started painting straight away. And he carried out
						his threat. Agatharchus only made his escape three months later, by slipping
						past his guards and running away as he might have done from the king of
							<placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>. But so shameless is
						Alcibiades that he went to Agatharchus and accused him of doing him a wrong;
						instead of apologizing for his violence, he uttered threats against him for
						leaving his work unfinished. Democracy, freedom went for nothing:
						Agatharchus had been put in chains exactly like any acknowledged slave. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="18">
					<p>It makes me angry to think that while you yourselves cannot place even
						malefactors under arrest without risk, because it is enacted that anyone who
						fails to gain one-fifth of the votes shall be liable to a fine of a thousand
						drachmae, Alcibiades, who imprisoned a man for so long and forced him to
						paint, went unpunished—nay, increased thereby the awe and the fear in which
						he is held. In our treaties with other states<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">For <foreign xml:lang="greek">su/mbola</foreign> see
								<bibl n="Antiph. 5.78">Antiph. 5.78</bibl> note 2.</note> we make it
						a condition that no free man shall be imprisoned or placed in durance, and a
						heavy fine is prescribed as the penalty for so doing. Yet when Alcibiades
						behaved as he did, no one sought satisfaction, whether for himself or for
						the state. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="19">
					<p>Obedience to the magistrates and the laws is to my mind the one safeguard of
						society; and anyone who sets them at nought is destroying at one blow the
						surest guarantee of security which the state possesses. It is hard enough to
						be made to suffer by those who have no conception of right and wrong; but it
						is far more serious when a man who knows what the public interest requires,
						acts in defiance of it. He shows clearly, as Alcibiades has done, that
						instead of holding that he ought himself to conform with the laws of the
						state, he expects you to conform with his own way of life. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="20">
					<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then again, remember Taureas<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 21.147">Dem. 21.147</bibl>.</note> who
						competed against Alcibiades as Choregus of a chorus of boys.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For the duties of such a Choregus see <bibl
								n="Antiph. 6.11">Antiph. 6.11-13</bibl>. Choruses of boys selected
							from each of the ten tribes competed against one another at all the
							major festivals of the Attic year.</note> The law allows the ejection of
						any member whatsoever of a competing chorus who is not of Athenian birth,
						and it is forbidden to resist any attempt at such ejection. Yet in your
						presence, in the presence of the other Greeks who were looking on, and
						before all the magistrates in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName>, Alcibiades drove off Taureas with his fists.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The speaker is not very clear. Apparently
							Taureas attempted to secure the ejection of a member of Alcibiades'
							chorus, but met with violent resistance from Alcibiades himself. Cf.
								<bibl n="Dem. 21.147">Dem. 21.147</bibl>
							<foreign xml:lang="greek">*taure/an e)pa/tace xorhgou=nt' e)pi\
								ko/rrhs</foreign></note> The spectators showed their sympathy with
						Taureas and their hatred of Alcibiades by applauding the one chorus and
						refusing to listen to the other at all. Yet Taureas was none the better off
						for that. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="21">
					<p>Partly from fear, partly from subservience, the judges pronounced Alcibiades
						the victor, treating him as more important than their oath. And it seems to
						me only natural that the judges should thus seek favour with Alcibiades,
						when they could see that Taureas, who had spent so vast a sum, was being
						subjected to insults, while his rival, who showed such contempt for the law,
						was all-powerful. The blame lies with you. You refuse to punish insolence;
						and while you chastise secret wrongdoing, you admire open effrontery. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="22">
					<p>That is why the young spend their days in the courts instead of in the
						gymnasia; that is why our old men fight our battles, while our young men
						make speeches— they take Alcibiades as their model, Alcibiades who carries
						his villainy to such unheard-of lengths that, after recommending that the
						people of <placeName key="tgn,7010922">Melos</placeName><note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">In <date>425</date> B.C. Melos refused to pay the
							increased tribute demanded of her, and during the years which followed
							displayed a general defiance of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
								>Athens</placeName>. <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
								>Athens</placeName> finally acted in the summer of 416. A fleet
							attacked the island, the male population was massacred, and the women
							and children sold as slaves. See <bibl n="Thuc. 5.1">Thuc.
							5</bibl>.</note> be sold into slavery, he purchased a woman from among
						the prisoners and has since had a son by her, a child whose birth was more
						unnatural than that of Aegis—thus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Son of
							Thyestes by his own daughter, Pelopeia. He was exposed as a child, but
							saved by shepherds. His uncle, Atreus, then brought him up as his own
							son. Later he murdered Atreus and placed Thyestes on his throne.</note>
						since he is sprung from parents who are each other's deadliest enemies, and
						of his nearest kin the one has committed and the other has suffered the most
						terrible of wrongs. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="23">
					<p>Indeed it would be well to make such shamelessness still plainer. He got
						himself a child by the very woman whom he had turned from a free citizen
						into a slave, whose father and kinsfolk he had put to death and whose city
						he had made a waste, that he might thereby make his son the deadly enemy of
						himself and of this city; so inevitably is the boy driven to hate both. When
						you are shown things of this kind on the tragic stage, you regard them with
						horror; but when you see them taking place in <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you remain unmoved—and yet you
						are uncertain whether the tales of tragedy are founded on the truth or
						spring merely from the imagination of the poets; whereas you well know that
						these other lawless outrages, which you accept with indifference, have
						occurred in fact. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="24">
					<p>In addition to all this, some dare to say that the like of Alcibiades has
						never been before. For my part, I believe that <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> will meet with terrible
						calamities at his hands, that he will be deemed responsible hereafter for
						disasters so awful that no one will remember his past misdeeds; for it is
						only to be expected that one who has begun his life in such a fashion will
						make its close no less portentous. Men of sense should beware of those of
						their fellows who grow too great, remembering that it is such as they who
						set up tyrannies. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="25">
					<p>I imagine that Alcibiades will make no reply to this, but will talk instead
						of his victory at <placeName key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName>,<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Plut. Alc. 13">Plut. Alc.
								13</bibl> ff.</note> and that he will seek to defend himself on any
						grounds rather than those on which he has been charged. But I will use the
						very facts upon which he relies to prove that he deserves death rather than
						acquittal. Let me explain. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="26">
					<p>Diomedes took a chariot-team to <placeName key="perseus,Olympia"
							>Olympia</placeName>. He was a man of moderate means, but desired to win
						a garland for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and for his
						family with such resources as he had, since he held that the chariot-races
						were for the most part decided by chance. Diomedes was no casual competitor,
						but a citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Or possibly: “Diomedes was a citizen of
								<placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and a person of
							some distinction.”</note> Yet thanks to his influence with the Masters
						of the Games<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Properly known as <foreign
								xml:lang="greek">*(ellanodi/kai</foreign>. In the time of Pausanias
							they numbered eight. They were appointed by lot from the whole body of
							Eleans and had the general superintendence of the Games.</note> at
							<placeName key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName>, Alcibiades deprived him
						of his team and competed with it himself. What would he have done, may we
						ask, had one of your allies arrived with a team? </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="27">
					<p>I imagine he would have been all eagerness to let him compete against
						himself, considering that he had forcibly ousted an Athenian rival and then
						had the impudence to contest the race with another man's horses—after he
						had, in fact, warned the Greeks in general that they must not be surprised
						at his offering violence to any of them, seeing that he does not treat his
						own fellow Athenians as his equals, but robs them, strikes them, throws them
						into prison, and extorts money from them, yes, shows the democracy to be
						nothing better than a sham, by talking like a champion of the people and
						acting like a tyrant, since he has found out that while the word “tyranny”
						fills you with concern, the thing for which leaves you undisturbed. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="28">
					<p>Indeed, so different is he from the Spartans that whereas the Spartans accept
						defeat even at the hands of their allies, when they compete against them,
						Alcibiades will not endure it even at the hands of his fellow-citizens; in
						fact, he has openly stated that he will brook no rivals. It is inevitable
						that such behaviour should cause the states within our confederacy to feel
						sympathy for our enemies and loathing for us. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="29">
					<p>In order to make it clear, however, that he was insulting <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> as a whole in addition to
						Diomedes, he asked the leaders of the Athenian deputation to lend him the
						processional vessels, alleging that he intended to use them for a
						celebration of his victory on the day before the sacrifice; he then abused
						the trust placed in him and refused to return them, as he wanted to use the
						golden basins and censers next day before <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName> did so. Naturally, when those strangers who did not
						know that they belonged to us saw the state-procession taking place after
						that of Alcibiades, they imagined that we were using his vessels: while
						those who had either heard the truth from the Athenians present or else knew
						the ways of Alcibiades, laughed at us when they saw one man showing himself
						superior to our entire community. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="30">
					<p>Then again, look at the arrangements which he made for his stay at <placeName
							key="perseus,Olympia">Olympia</placeName> as a whole. For Alcibiades the
						people of <placeName key="perseus,Ephesos">Ephesus</placeName> erected a
						Persian pavilion twice as large as that of our official deputation:
							<placeName key="perseus,Chios City">Chios</placeName> furnished him with
						beasts for sacrifice and with fodder for his horses: while he requisitioned
						wine and everything else necessary for his maintenance from <placeName
							key="tgn,7002672">Lesbos</placeName>. And so lucky is he that although
						the Greek people at large can testify to his lawlessness and corruption, he
						has gone unpunished. While those who hold office within a single city have
						to render account of that office, </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="31">
					<p>Alcibiades, whose authority extends over all our allies and who receives
						monies from them, is not liable to answer for any of his public acts; on the
						contrary, after behaving as I have described, he was rewarded with free
						entertainment in the Prytaneum<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign
								xml:lang="greek">si/thsis e)n *prutanei/w|</foreign> was the usual
							reward for a victory at the games or signal service to the state. The
							same privilege was granted Diocleides in 415, after his information in
							the matter of the Hermae. Cf. <bibl n="Andoc. 1.45">Andoc.
							1.45</bibl>.</note>; and not content with that, he is for ever taking
						credit for his victory, as though he had not so much brought <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> into disgrace as won her a
						garland of honour. Only reflect, and you will find that men who have given
						way even temporarily to any single one of the excesses in which Alcibiades
						has indulged time and again, have brought ruin upon their houses; yet
						Alcibiades, whose entire life is devoted to extravagance, has doubled his
						wealth. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="32">
					<p>You regard as misers those who are niggardly and close-fisted; but you are
						mistaken. It is the spendthrift, with his endless wants, who stoops lowest
						to fill his pockets. In fact, it will be a public disgrace, if you show
						tolerance towards a man who has achieved his success only with the help of
						your money, when in ostracizing Callias, son of Didymius, who won victories
						at all the great games by his personal prowess, you took no account
						whatsoever of his achievement, although it was by his own efforts that he
						brought glory to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="33">
					<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then again, remember how steadfast, how true
						to their principles your fathers showed themselves, when they ostracized
						Cimon for breaking the law by taking his own sister to wife<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">The story is mentioned by Plutarch (<bibl
								n="Plut. Cim. 15">Plut. Cim. 15</bibl>), who, however, gives the
							correct reason for C.'s ostracism—the failure of his pro-Spartan policy.
							He was ostracized almost immediately after his return in disgrace from
								<placeName key="perseus,Ithome">Ithome</placeName> in 461.</note>;
						and yet not only was Cimon himself an Olympic victor; his father, Miltiades,
						had been one likewise. Nevertheless, they took no account of his victories;
						for it was not by his exploits at the games, but by his manner of life that
						they judged him. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="34">
					<p>Furthermore, if account is to be taken of our families, I on my side cannot
						claim any acquaintance with ostracism. No one could show that any kinsman of
						mine has ever had the misfortune to suffer it. Alcibiades, on the other
						hand, knows more of it than any other member of the community. His mother's
						father, Megacles, and his father's father, Alcibiades, were both ostracized
						twice; so it will be neither surprising nor unnatural if he receives the
						same treatment as his ancestors. Indeed, not even Alcibiades himself would
						venture to maintain that they, the worst miscreants of their time though
						they were, did not have more regard for decency and honesty than he himself;
						for no one in the world could frame an accusation which would do justice to
						his misdeeds. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="35">
					<p>Moreover, the legislator who instituted ostracism appears to me to have had
						the following intention. Observing that whenever members of the community
						are more powerful than the magistrates and the laws, it is impossible for an
						individual to obtain redress from them, he arranged that punishment for
						their misdeeds should be exacted by the state. Now I myself have been
						publicly tried four times, and have never prevented any private person who
						so desired from bringing me to justice. On the other hand, Alcibiades, who
						has worked such mischief, has never yet dared to answer for it in any way
						whatsoever. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="36">
					<p>So forbidding is he that instead of punishing him for the wrongs which he has
						done already, men fear him for what he will do hereafter; and while it pays
						his victims to suffer in silence, he himself is not satisfied unless he can
						work his will in the future also. Yet I hardly deserve to be ostracized,
						gentlemen, if I do not deserve to be put to death<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">A quibble. The speaker tries to argue that if he was
							acquitted when tried for his life, he must similarly be acquitted when
							the penalty in question is exile for ten years.</note>; and if I was
						acquitted when brought to trial, I cannot deserve to be sent into exile when
						no trial has taken place; nor after vindicating myself so many times in
						court can I be thought to merit banishment on the same grounds of accusation
						again. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="37">
					<p>It may be objected that when I was prosecuted, the attack made upon me was a
						weak one, that my accusers were unimpressive, or that the case was conducted
						by casual enemies instead of by those who excel both as speakers and as men
						of action and who, in fact, brought about the death of two of the persons
						charged with the same offences as myself. I answer that justice requires you
						to banish, not those whom, after repeated inquiry, you have found to be
						innocent, but those who refuse to render to the state an account of their
						past. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="38">
					<p>Indeed what seems strange to me is this. If one sought to vindicate persons
						who have been put to death by showing that they met their end unjustly, such
						an attempt would not be tolerated. If, on the other hand, those who have
						been declared innocent should once more be accused on the same charge—is it
						not only right that you should behave in the case of the living as you would
						in the case of the dead? </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="39">
					<p>It is characteristic of Alcibiades to pay no attention to laws or oaths
						himself, and to try to teach you to disregard them as well, and while he is
						ruthless in bringing about the banishment and the death of others, to have
						recourse to heartrending tears and appeals for mercy on his own account. Nor
						does such behaviour surprise me—he has done much that calls for tears. But
						whose goodwill will he gain by his entreaties, I wonder? That of the young,
						upon whom he has brought the disfavour of the people by his insolence, by
						his emptying of the gymnasia, and by behaviour which his years do not
						warrant? Or that of the old, whose ways are the exact opposite of his own,
						and whose mode of life he has treated with contempt? </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="40">
					<p>However, it is not the mere exaction of punishment from wrongdoers themselves
						that should be your object; you should seek also to render everyone else
						more upright and more self-controlled by the sight of that punishment. If,
						then, you send me into exile, you will strike fear into all men of worth.
						If, on the other hand, you punish Alcibiades, you will inspire a greater
						respect for the law in those whose insolence is uncontrolled. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="41">
					<p>I wish, further, to remind you of what I have done. I have been sent on
						missions to <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>, to <placeName
							key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, to Molossia, to <placeName
							key="tgn,7002709">Thesprotia</placeName>, to Italy, and to <placeName
							key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>. In the course of them I have
						reconciled such as had quarrelled with you, others I have won over to
						friendship, others I have detached from your enemies. If every
						representative of yours had done the same, you would have few foes, and you
						would have gained many an ally.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="part" n="Concl">
				<div type="section" n="42">
					<p>Of my public services I do not intend to speak. I will say only this: the
						expenditure required of me I meet, not from monies belonging to the state,
						but from my own pocket. And yet I have in fact gained victories in the
						contest of physique,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See Harpocration,
							s.v., and Athenaeus 13.565f. The <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)gw\n
								eu)andri/as</foreign> was held at the Panathenaea.</note> in the
						torch-race, and at the tragic competitions without striking rival Choregi,
						and without feeling shame at my possessing less power than the laws.
						Citizens of this kind, it seems to me, deserve to remain in <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> far more than to be sent into
						exile.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
