<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against the Sophists from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg008.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If all who are engaged in the profession of education were willing to state the facts
          instead of making greater promises than they can possibly fulfill, they would not be in
          such bad repute with the lay-public. As it is, however, the teachers who do not scruple to
          vaunt their powers with utter disregard of the truth have created the impression that
          those who choose a life of careless indolence are better advised than those who devote
          themselves to serious study. Indeed, who can fail to abhor, yes to contemn, those
          teachers, in the first place, who devote themselves to disputation,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Captious argumentation in the field of ethics. He is not thinking of Socrates,
            who did not teach for pay, nor of Plato's dialectic, which was not yet famous, but of
            the minor Socratics, especially Antisthenes and Eucleides, who taught for money while
            affecting contempt for it. In general he is thinking of such quibblers as are later
            shown up in Plato's <title>Euthydemus</title>. See General Introd. pp. xxi ff.</note>
          since they pretend to search for truth, but straightway at the beginning of their
          professions attempt to deceive us with lies?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Theirs is a
            cloud morality, not truth to live by on earth. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 13.20">Isoc.
              13.20</bibl>. See General Introd. p. xxii.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I think it is manifest to all that foreknowledge of future events is not vouchsafed
          to our human nature, but that we are so far removed from this prescience<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">There is, according to Isocrates, no “science” which can teach
            us to do under all circumstances the things which will insure our happiness and success.
            Life is too complicated for that, and no man can foresee exactly the consequences of his
            acts—“the future is a thing unseen.” All that education can do is to develop a sound
            judgement (as opposed to knowledge) which will meet the contingencies of life with
            resourcefulness and, in most cases, with success. This is a fundamental doctrine of his
            “philosophy” which he emphasizes and echoes again and again in opposition to the
            professors of a “science of virtue and happiness.” See General Introd. pp. xxvii
            ff.</note> that Homer, who has been conceded the highest reputation for wisdom, has
          pictured even the gods as at times debating among themselves about the future<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Hom. Il. 16.431">Hom. Il. 16.431 ff.</bibl> and
              <bibl n="Hom. Il. 16.652">Hom. Il. 16.652 ff.</bibl>; <bibl n="Hom. Il. 22.168">Hom.
              Il. 22.168 ff.</bibl></note>—not that he knew their minds but that he desired to show
          us that for mankind this power lies in the realms of the impossible. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But these professors have gone so far in their lack of scruple that they attempt to
          persuade our young men that if they will only study under them they will know what to do
          in life and through this knowledge will become happy and prosperous. More than that,
          although they set themselves up as masters and dispensers of goods so precious, they are
          not ashamed of asking for them a price of three or four minae!<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Socrates (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 20b">Plat. Apol. 20b</bibl>) speaks with the
            same sarcasm of a sophist named Evenus, who professed to teach all the virtues necessary
            to a good man and a good citizen for five minae.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Why, if they were to sell any other commodity for so trifling a fraction of its worth
          they would not deny their folly; nevertheless, although they set so insignificant a price
          on the whole stock of virtue and happiness, they pretend to wisdom and assume the right to
          instruct the rest of the world. Furthermore, although they say that they do not want money
          and speak contemptuously of wealth as “filthy lucre,” they hold their hands out for a
          trifling gain and promise to make their disciples all but immortal!<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">That is, to make them all but gods.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But what is most ridiculous of all is that they distrust those from whom they are to get
          this money—they distrust, that is to say, the very men to whom they are about to deliver
          the science of just dealing—and they require that the fees advanced by their students be
          entrusted for safe keeping<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For their security, they
            required that the fees charged to their students be deposited with third parties until
            the end of the discourse.</note> to those who have never been under their instruction,
          being well advised as to their security, but doing the opposite of what they preach. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it is permissible to those who give any other instruction to be exacting in matters
          open to dispute, since nothing prevents those who have been made adept in other lines of
          training from being dishonorable in the matter of contracts. But men who inculcate virtue
          and sobriety—is it not absurd if they do not trust in their own students before all
            others?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. the same ridicule in <bibl
              n="Plat. Gorg. 519c">Plat. Gorg. 519c</bibl>, <bibl n="Plat. Gorg. 460e">Plat. Gorg.
              460e</bibl>.</note> For it is not to be supposed that men who are honorable and
          just-dealing with others will be dishonest with the very preceptors who have made them
          what they are. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When, therefore, the layman puts all these things together and observes that the
          teachers of wisdom and dispensers of happiness are themselves in great want<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See the close of the <bibl n="Isoc. 4">Isoc. 4</bibl>.</note>
          but exact only a small fee from their students, that they are on the watch for
          contradictions in words<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The aim of “eristic” ( <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">e(/ris</foreign> means contention) is to show up the contradictions
            in the accepted morality.</note> but are blind to inconsistencies in deeds, and that,
          furthermore, they pretend to have knowledge of the future </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but are incapable either of saying anything pertinent or of giving any counsel regarding
          the present, and when he observes that those who follow their judgements are more
          consistent and more successful<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 13.2"
              >Isoc. 13.2</bibl>, note; <bibl n="Isoc. 12.9">Isoc. 12.9</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 10.5"
              >Isoc. 10.5</bibl>.</note> than those who profess to have exact knowledge, then he
          has, I think, good reason to contemn such studies and regard them as stuff and nonsense,
          and not as a true discipline of the soul. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But it is not these sophists alone who are open to criticism, but also those who profess
          to teach political discourse.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The whole field of
            “deliberative” oratory, but the most “useful” branch of it in “litigious Athens” was the
            forensic.</note> For the latter have no interest whatever in the truth,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Their interest was not in the triumph of justice but in making
            the “worse reason appear the better.” See General Introd. p. xxii.</note> but consider
          that they are masters of an art if they can attract great numbers of students by the
          smallness of their charges and the magnitude of their professions and get something out of
          them. For they are themselves so stupid and conceive others to be so dull that, although
          the speeches which they compose are worse than those which some laymen improvise,
          nevertheless they promise to make their students such clever orators that they will not
          overlook any of the possibilities which a subject affords. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>More than that, they do not attribute any of this power either to the practical
          experience or to the native ability of the student, but undertake to transmit the science
          of discourse as simply as they would teach the letters of the alphabet,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introd. p. xxii.</note> not having taken trouble
          to examine into the nature of each kind of knowledge, but thinking that because of the
          extravagance of their promises they themselves will command admiration and the teaching of
          discourse will be held in higher esteem—oblivious of the fact that the arts are made
          great, not by those who are without scruple in boasting about them, but by those who are
          able to discover all of the resources which each art affords. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For myself, I should have preferred above great riches that philosophy had as much power
          as these men claim; for, possibly, I should not have been the very last in the profession
          nor had the least share in its profits. But since it has no such power, I could wish that
          this prating might cease. For I note that the bad repute which results therefrom does not
          affect the offenders only, but that all the rest of us who are in the same profession
          share in the opprobium.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.168">Isoc.
              15.168</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I marvel when I observe these men setting themselves up as instructors of youth who
          cannot see that they are applying the analogy of an art with hard and fast rules to a
          creative process. For, excepting these teachers, who does not know that the art of using
          letters remains fixed and unchanged, so that we continually and invariably use the same
          letters for the same purposes, while exactly the reverse is true of the art of
            discourse?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, mechanical formulas are not
            sufficient. There must be inventiveness, resourcefulness, in a word, creative
            imagination.</note> For what has been said by one speaker is not equally useful for the
          speaker who comes after him; on the contrary, he is accounted most skilled in this art who
          speaks in a manner worthy of his subject and yet is able to discover in it topics which
          are nowise the same as those used by others. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the greatest proof of the difference between these two arts is that oratory is good
          only if it has the qualities of fitness for the occasion,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A
            fundamental requisite. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.9">Isoc. 4.9</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 10.11"
              >Isoc. 10.11</bibl>.</note> propriety of style, and originality of treatment, while in
          the case of letters there is no such need whatsoever. So that those who make use of such
          analogies ought more justly to pay out than to accept fees, since they attempt to teach
          others when they are themselves in great need of instruction. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> However, if it is my duty not only to rebuke others, but also to set forth my own views,
          I think all intelligent people will agree with me that while many of those who have
          pursued philosophy have remained in private life,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates
            himself.</note> others, on the other hand, who have never taken lessons from any one of
          the sophists have become able orators and statesmen. For ability, whether in speech or in
          any other activity, is found in those who are well endowed by nature and have been
          schooled by practical experience.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates insists that
            the requisites of a good orator are first natural ability, second practical experience,
            and third formal training. See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.186">Isoc. 15.186-188</bibl> and
            General Introd. p. xxvii, Vol. I., L.C.L.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Formal training makes such men more skilfull and more resourceful in discovering the
          possibilities of a subject; for it teaches them to take from a readier source the topics
          which they otherwise hit upon in haphazard fashion. But it cannot fully fashion men who
          are without natural aptitude into good debaters or writers, although it is capable of
          leading them on to self-improvement and to a greater degree of intelligence on many
          subjects. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I desire, now that I have gone this far, to speak more clearly on these matters. For
          I hold that to obtain a knowledge of the elements out of which we make and compose all
          discourses is not so very difficult if anyone entrusts himself, not to those who make rash
          promises, but to those who have some knowledge of these things. But to choose from these
          elements those which should be employed for each subject, to join them together, to
          arrange them properly, and also, not to miss what the occasion demands but appropriately
          to adorn the whole speech with striking thoughts and to clothe it in flowing and melodious
            phrase<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Prose should have the same finish and charm as
            poetry. See General Introd. p. xxiv.</note>— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>these things, I hold, require much study and are the task of a vigorous and imaginative
            mind:<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Unmistakably this phrase is parodied in <bibl
              n="Plat. Gorg. 463a">Plat. Gorg. 463a</bibl>: <foreign xml:lang="greek">dokei= toi/nun
              moi, w)= *gorgia, ei)=nai ti e)pith/deuma texniko\n me\n ou)/, yuxh=s de\ stoxastikh=s
              kai\ a)ndrei/as kai\ fu/sei deinh=s prosomilei=n toi=s a)nqrw/pois</foreign></note>
          for this, the student must not only have the requisite aptitude but he must learn the
          different kinds of discourse and practice himself in their use; and the teacher, for his
          part, must so expound the principles of the art with the utmost possible exactness as to
          leave out nothing that can be taught, and, for the rest, he must in himself set such an
          example of oratory </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>that the students who have taken form under his instruction and are able to pattern after
          him will, from the outset, show in their speaking a degree of grace and charm which is not
          found in others. When all of these requisites are found together, then the devotees of
          philosophy will achieve complete success; but according as any one of the things which I
          have mentioned is lacking, to this extent must their disciples of necessity fall below the
          mark. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now as for the sophists who have lately sprung up and have very recently embraced these
            pretensions,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The sophist before mentioned. The teaching
            of the older sophists is discussed in <title>Antidosis</title>.</note> even though they
          flourish at the moment, they will all, I am sure, come round to this position. But there
          remain to be considered those who lived before our time and did not scruple to write the
          so-called arts of oratory.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Especially the first to write
            such treatises, Corax and Tisias of <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse"
              >Syracuse</placeName>. <foreign xml:lang="greek">te/xnh</foreign>, like
              <term>ars</term> in Latin, was the accepted term for a treatise on rhetoric.</note>
          These must not be dismissed without rebuke, since they professed to teach how to conduct
          law-suits, picking out the most discredited of terms,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Again
            and again Isocrates expresses his repugnance to this kind of oratory, and in general it
            was in bad odor. The precepts of Corax (Crow), for example, were called “the bad eggs of
            the bad Corax.”</note> which the enemies, not the champions, of this discipline might
          have been expected to employ— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and that too although this facility, in so far as it can be taught, is of no greater aid
          to forensic than to all other discourse. But they were much worse than those who dabble in
          disputation; for although the latter expounded such captious theories that were anyone to
          cleave to them in practice he would at once be in all manner of trouble, they did, at any
          rate, make professions of virtue and sobriety in their teaching, whereas the former,
          although exhorting others to study political discourse, neglected all the good things
          which this study affords, and became nothing more than professors of meddlesomeness and
            greed.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The same complaint is made by <bibl
              n="Aristot. Rh. 1.10">Aristot. Rh. 1.10</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And yet those who desire to follow the true precepts of this discipline may, if they
          will, be helped more speedily towards honesty of character<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >For the kind of political discourse which Isocrates extols, and its ethical influence
            see <bibl n="Isoc. 15.275">Isoc. 15.275</bibl> and General Introd. p. xxiv.</note> than
          towards facility in oratory. And let no one suppose that I claim that just living can be
            taught;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.274">Isoc. 15.274
              ff.</bibl></note> for, in a word, I hold that there does not exist an art of the kind
          which can implant sobriety and justice in depraved natures. Nevertheless, I do think that
          the study of political discourse can help more than any other thing to stimulate and form
          such qualities of character. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But in order that I may not appear to be breaking down the pretensions of others while
          myself making greater claims than are within my powers, I believe that the very arguments
          by which I myself was convinced will make it clear to others also that these things are
          true.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
