<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Ancient Medicine </title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>

			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1923</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>

			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Aph.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=intro">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Epid.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="section" n="1">
				<head>PART 1 </head>
				<p>I. A<hi rend="sc">LL</hi> who, on attempting to speak or to write on medicine,
					have assumed for themselves a postulate as a basis for their discussion--heat,
					cold, moisture, dryness, or anything else that they may fancy--who narrow down
					the causal principle of diseases and of death among men, and make it the same in
					all cases, postulating one thing or two, all these obviously blunder in many
					points even of their statements,<note>Or, reading <foreign xml:lang="grc"
							>KAINOI=S1I</foreign>
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">K</foreign>.<foreign xml:lang="grc"
							>T</foreign>.<foreign xml:lang="grc">L</foreign>., "of their
						novelties."</note> but they are most open to censure because they blunder in
					what is an art, and one which all men use on the most important occasions, and
					give the greatest honours to the good craftsmen and practitioners in it. Some
					practitioners are poor, others very excellent ; this would not be the case if an
					art of medicine did not exist at all, and had not been the subject of any
					research and discovery, but all would be equally inexperienced and unlearned
					therein, and the treatment of the sick would be in all respects haphazard. But
					it is not so ; just as in all other arts the workers vary much in skill and in
						knowledge,<note>Or "manual skill" and "intelligence."</note> so also is it
					in the case of medicine. Wherefore I have deemed that it has</p>
				<pb n="p.15"/>
				<p>no need of an empty postulate,<note>Or, reading <foreign xml:lang="grc"
							>XAINH=S2</foreign>, "a novel postulate." But the writer's objection is
						not that the postulate is novel, but that it <hi rend="ital">is</hi> a
						postulate. A postulate, he says, is "empty" in a sphere where accurate and
						verifiable knowledge is possible. Only in regions where science cannot
						penetrate are <foreign xml:lang="grc">U(POQE/S1EIS2</foreign> legitimate.
						For this reason I read <foreign xml:lang="grc">KENH=S2</foreign>.</note> as
					do insoluble mysteries, about which any exponent must use a postulate, for
					example, things in the sky or below the earth. If a man were to learn and
					declare the state of these, neither to the speaker himself nor to his audience
					would it be clear whether his statements were true or not. For there is no test
					the application of which would give certainty.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="2">
				<head>PART 2 </head>
				<p>II. But medicine has long had all its means to hand, and has discovered both a
					principle and a method, through which the discoveries made during a long period
					are many and excellent, while full discovery will be made, if the inquirer be
					competent, conduct his researches with knowledge of the discoveries already
					made, and make them his starting-point. But anyone who, casting aside and
					rejecting all these means, attempts to conduct research in any other way or
					after another fashion, and asserts that he has found out anything, is and has
					been the victim of deception.<note>Or, with the reading suggested, "both
						deceives and is deceived."</note> His assertion is impossible ; the causes
					of its impossibility I will endeavour to expound by a statement and exposition
					of what the art is.<note>Or, reading <foreign xml:lang="grc">O(/TI
							E)/S1TIN</foreign>, "that the art really is an art, really
						exists."</note> In this way it will be manifest that by any other means
					discoveries are impossible. But it is particularly necessary, in my opinion, for
					one who discusses this art to discuss things familiar to ordinary folk. For the
					subject of inquiry and discussion is simply and solely the sufferings of these
					same</p>
				<pb n="p.17"/>
				<p>ordinary folk when they are sick or in pain. Now to learn by themselves how their
					own sufferings come about and cease, and the reasons why they get worse or
					better, is not an easy task for ordinary folk ; but when these things have been
					discovered and are set forth by another, it is simple. For merely an effort of
					memory is required of each man when he listens to a statement of his
					experiences. But if you miss being understood by laymen, and fail to put your
					hearers in this condition, you will miss reality. Therefore for this reason also
					medicine has no need of any postulate.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="3">
				<head>PART 3 </head>
				<p>III. For the art of medicine would never have been discovered to begin with, nor
					would any medical research have been conducted--for there would have been no
					need for medicine--if sick men had profited by the same mode of living and
					regimen as the food, drink and mode of living of men in health, and if there had
					been no other things for the sick better than these. But the fact is that sheer
					necessity has caused men to seek and to find medicine, because sick men did not,
					and do not, profit by the same regimen as do men in health. To trace the matter
					yet further back, I hold that not even the mode of living and nourishment
					enjoyed at the present time by men in health would have been discovered, had a
					man been satisfied with the same food and drink as satisfy an ox, a horse, and
					every animal save man, for example the products of the earth--fruits, wood and
					grass. For on these they are nourished, grow, and live without pain, having no
					need at all of any other kind of living. Yet I am of opinion that to begin with
					man also used this sort of nourishment. Our present ways of living have, I
					think, been</p>
				<pb n="p.19"/>
				<p>discovered and elaborated during a long period of time. For many and terrible
					were the sufferings of men from strong and brutish living when they partook of
					crude foods, uncompounded and possessing great powers<note>Or "strong
						qualities."</note>--the same in fact as men would suffer at the present day,
					falling into violent pains and diseases quickly followed by death. Formerly
					indeed they probably suffered less, because they were used to it, but they
					suffered severely even then. The majority naturally perished, having too weak a
					constitution, while the stronger resisted longer, just as at the present time
					some men easily deal with strong foods, while others do so only with many severe
					pains. For this reason the ancients too seem to me to have sought for
					nourishment that harmonised with their constitution, and to have discovered that
					which we use now. So from wheat, after steeping it, winnowing, grinding and
					sifting, kneading, baking, they produced bread, and from barley they produced
					cake. Experimenting with food they boiled or baked, after mixing, many other
					things, combining the strong and uncompounded with the weaker components so as
					to adapt all to the constitution and power of man, thinking that from foods
					which, being too strong, the human constitution cannot assimilate when eaten,
					will come pain, disease, and death, while from such as can be assimilated will
					come nourishment, growth and health. To this discovery and research what juster
					or more appropriate name</p>
				<pb n="p.21"/>
				<p>could be given than medicine, seeing that it has been discovered with a view to
					the health, saving and nourishment of man, in the place of that mode of living
					from which came the pain, disease and death?</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="4">
				<head>PART 4 </head>
				<p>IV. That it is not commonly considered an art is not unnatural, for it is
					inappropriate to call anyone an artist in a craft in which none are laymen, but
					all possess knowledge through being compelled to use it. Nevertheless the
					discovery was a great one, implying much investigation and art. At any rate even
					at the present day those who study gymnastics and athletic exercises are
					constantly making some fresh discovery by investigating on the same method what
					food and what drink are best assimilated and make a man grow stronger.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="5">
				<head>PART 5 </head>
				<p>V. Let us consider also whether the acknowledged art of medicine, that was
					discovered for the treatment of the sick and has both a name and artists, has
					the same object as the other art,<note><hi rend="ital">I.e.</hi> that of dieting
						in health. See Chapter VII.</note> and what its origin was. In my opinion,
					as I said at the beginning, nobody would have even sought for medicine, if the
					same ways of life had suited both the sick and those in health. At any rate even
					at the present day such as do not use medical science, foreigners and some
					Greeks, live as do those in health, just as they please, and would neither forgo
					nor restrict the satisfaction of any of their desires. But those who sought for
					and discovered medicine, having the same intention as the men I discussed above,
					in the first place, I think, lessened the bulk of the foods, and, without
					altering their character, greatly diminished their quantity. But they found that
					this treatment was</p>
				<pb n="p.23"/>
				<p>sufficient only occasionally, and although clearly beneficial with some patients,
					it was not so in all cases, as some were in such a condition that they could not
					assimilate even small quantities of food. As such patients were thought to need
					weaker nutriment, slops were invented by mixing with much water small quantities
					of strong foods, and by taking away from their strength by compounding and
					boiling. Those that were not able to assimilate them were refused even these
					slops, and were reduced to taking liquids, these moreover being so regulated in
					composition and quantity as to be moderate, and nothing was administered that
					was either more or less, or less compounded, than it ought to be.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="6">
				<head>PART 6 </head>
				<p>VI. It must be clearly understood that some are not benefited in disease by
					slops, but when they take them, their fever and pain grow manifestly worse, and
					it is plain that what is taken proves nourishment and increase to the disease,
					but wears away and enfeebles the body. Any men who in this condition take dry
					food, barley-cake or bread, even though it be very little, will be hurt ten
					times more, and more obviously, than if they take slops, simply and solely
					because the food is too strong for their condition ; and a man to whom slops are
					beneficial, but not solid food, will suffer much more harm if he eat more than
					if he eat little, though he will feel pain even if he eat little. Now all the
					causes of the pain can be reduced to one, namely, it is the strongest foods that
					hurt a man most and most obviously, whether he be well or ill.</p>
				<pb n="p.25"/>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="7">
				<head>PART 7 </head>
				<p>VII. What difference then can be seen between the purpose of him we call
					physician, who is an acknowledged handicraftsman, the discoverer of the mode of
					life and of the nourishment suitable for the sick, and his who discovered and
					prepared originally nourishment for all men, which we now use, instead of the
					old savage and brutish mode of living ? My own view is that their reasoning was
					identical and the discovery one and the same. The one sought to do away with
					those things which, when taken, the constitution of man in health could not
					assimilate because of their brutish and uncompounded character, the other those
					things which the temporary condition of an individual prevented him from
					assimilating. How do the two pursuits differ, except in their scope<note>Or
						"appearance." The two pursuits are really one, but they appear to a
						superficial observer to differ.</note> and in that the latter is more
					complex and requires the greater application, while the former is the starting
					point and came first in time ?</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="8">
				<head>PART 8 </head>
				<p>VIII. A consideration of the diet of the sick, as compared with that of men in
					health, would show that the diet of wild beasts and of animals generally is not
					more harmful, as compared with that of men in health.<note>The text here is very
						uncertain ; I have combined that of Littré with that of Kéhlewein so as to
						give a good sense : "The diet of men in health is as injurious to the sick
						as the diet of wild beasts is to men in health."</note> Take a man sick of a
					disease which is neither severe and desperate nor yet altogether mild, but
					likely to be pronounced under wrong treatment, and suppose that he resolved to
					eat bread, and meat, or any other food that is beneficial to men in health, not
					much of it, but far less than he could have taken had he been well ; take again
					a man in health, with a constitution neither altogether weak nor altogether</p>
				<pb n="p.27"/>
				<p>strong, and suppose he were to eat one of the foods that would be beneficial and
					strength-giving to an ox or a horse, vetches or barley or something similar, not
					much of it, but far less than he could take. If the man in health did this he
					would suffer no less pain and danger than that sick man who took bread or
					barley-cake at a time when he ought not. All this goes to prove that this art of
					medicine, if research be continued on the same method, can all be
					discovered.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="9">
				<head>PART 9 </head>
				<p>IX. If the matter were simple, as in these instances, and both sick and well were
					hurt by too strong foods, benefited and nourished by weaker foods, there would
					be no difficulty. For recourse to weaker food must have secured a great degree
					of safety. But as it is, if a man takes insufficient food, the mistake is as
					great as that of excess, and harms the man just as much. For abstinence has upon
					the human constitution a most powerful effect, to enervate, to weaken and to
					kill. Depletion produces many other evils, different from those of repletion,
					but just as severe. Wherefore the greater complexity of these ills requires a
					more exact method of treatment. For it is necessary to aim at some measure. But
					no measure, neither number nor weight, by reference to which knowledge can be
					made exact, can be found except bodily feeling. Wherefore it is laborious to
					make knowledge so exact that only small mistakes are made here and there. And
					that physician who makes only small mistakes would win my hearty praise.
					Perfectly exact truth is but rarely to be seen. For most physicians seem to me
					to be in the same</p>
				<pb n="p.29"/>
				<p>case as bad pilots ; the mistakes of the latter are unnoticed so long as they are
					steering in a calm, but, when a great storm overtakes them with a violent gale,
					all men realise clearly then that it is their ignorance and blundering which
					have lost the ship. So also when bad physicians, who comprise the great
					majority, treat men who are suffering from no serious complaint, so that the
					greatest blunders would not affect them seriously--such illnesses occur very
					often, being far more common than serious disease--they are not shown up in
					their true colours to laymen if their errors are confined to such cases ; but
					when they meet with a severe, violent and dangerous illness, then it is that
					their errors and want of skill are manifest to all. The punishment of the
					impostor, whether sailor or doctor, is not postponed, but follows speedily.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="10">
				<head>PART 10 </head>
				<p>X. That the discomforts a man feels after unseasonable abstinence are no less
					than those of unseasonable repletion, it were well to learn by a reference to
					men in health. For some of them benefit by taking one meal only each day, and
					because of this benefit they make a rule of having only one meal ; others again,
					because of the same reason, that they are benefited thereby, take lunch also.
					Moreover some have adopted one or other of these two practices for the sake of
					pleasure or for some other chance reason. For the great majority of men can
					follow indifferently either the one habit or the other, and can take lunch or
					only one daily meal. Others again, if they were to do anything outside what is
					beneficial, would not get off easily, but if they</p>
				<pb n="p.31"/>
				<p>change their respective ways for a single day, nay, for a part of a single day,
					they suffer excessive discomfort. Some, who lunch although lunch does not suit
					them, forthwith become heavy and sluggish in body and in mind, a prey to
					yawning, drowsiness and thirst ; while, if they go on to eat dinner as well,
					flatulence follows with colic and violent diarrhœa. Many have found such action
					to result in a serious illness, even if the quantity of food they take twice a
					day be no greater than that which they have grown accustomed to digest once a
					day. On the other hand, if a man who has grown accustomed, and has found it
					beneficial, to take lunch, should miss taking it, he suffers, as soon as the
					lunch-hour is passed, from prostrating weakness, trembling and faintness.
					Hollowness of the eyes follows ; urine becomes paler and hotter, and the mouth
					bitter ; his bowels seem to hang ; there come dizziness, depression and
					listlessness. Besides all this, when he attempts to dine, he has the following
					troubles : his food is less pleasant, and he cannot digest what formerly he used
					to dine on when he had lunch. The mere food, descending into the bowels with
					colic and noise, burns them, and disturbed sleep follows, accompanied by wild
					and troubled dreams. Many such sufferers also have found these symptoms the
					beginning of an illness.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="11">
				<head>PART 11 </head>
				<p>XI. It is necessary to inquire into the cause why such symptoms come to these
					men. The one who had grown accustomed to one meal suffered, I think, because he
					did not wait sufficient time, until his digestive organs had completely digested
					and assimilated the food taken the day before, and until they had become empty
					and quiet, but had taken fresh</p>
				<pb n="p.33"/>
				<p>food while the organs were still in a state of hot turmoil and ferment. Such
					organs digest much more slowly than others, and need longer rest and quiet. The
					man accustomed to take lunch, since no fresh nourishment was given him as soon
					as his body needed nourishment, when the previous meal was digested and there
					was nothing to sustain him, naturally wastes and pines away through want. For I
					put down to want all the symptoms which I have said such a man shows. And I
					assert furthermore that all other men besides, who when in good health fast for
					two or three days, will show the same symptoms as I have said those exhibit who
					do not take their lunch.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="12">
				<head>PART 12 </head>
				<p>XII. Such constitutions, I contend, that rapidly and severely feel the effects of
					errors, are weaker than the others. A weak man is but one step removed from a
					sickly man, but a sickly man is weaker still, and is more apt to suffer distress
					whenever he misses the due season. And, while the art can admit of such nice
					exactness, it is difficult always to attain perfect accuracy. But many
					departments of medicine have reached such a pitch of exactness, and I will speak
					about them later. I declare, however, that we ought not to reject the ancient
					art as non-existent, or on the ground that its method of inquiry is faulty, just
					because it has not attained exactness in every detail, but much rather, because
					it has been able by reasoning to rise from deep ignorance to approximately
					perfect accuracy, I think we ought to admire the discoveries as the work, not of
					chance, but of inquiry rightly and correctly conducted.</p>
				<pb n="p.35"/>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="13">
				<head>PART 13 </head>
				<p>XIII. But I want to return to the theory of those who prosecute their researches
					in the art after the novel fashion, building on a postulate. For if there be
					such a thing as heat, or cold, or dryness, or moistness, which injures a man, it
					necessarily follows that the scientific healer will counteract cold with hot,
					hot with cold, moist with dry and dry with moist. Now suppose we have a man
					whose constitution is not strong, but weaker than the average. Let this man's
					food be wheat straight from the threshing-floor, unworked and uncooked, and raw
					meat, and let his drink be water. The use of this diet will assuredly cause him
					much severe suffering ; he will experience pains and physical weakness, his
					digestion will be ruined and he will not be able to live long. Well, what remedy
					should be prepared for a man in this condition ? Heat or cold or dryness or
					moistness ? One of these, plainly ; for, according to the theory of the new
					school, if the injury was caused by one of the opposites, the other opposite
					ought to be a specific. Of course the most obvious as well as the most reliable
					medicine would be to abandon his old diet, and to give him bread instead of
					wheat, boiled meat instead of raw meat, and besides these things, a little wine
					to drink. This change must restore him to his health, unless indeed it has been
					entirely ruined by long continuance of the diet. What then shall we say ? That
					he was suffering from cold, and that the taking of these hot things benefited
					him ? Or shall we say the opposite ? I think that I have nonplussed my opponent.
					For is it the heat of the wheat, or the cold, or the dryness, or the moistness,
					that the baker took away from it ? For a thing which has been</p>
				<pb n="p.37"/>
				<p>exposed to fire and to water, and has been made by many other things, each of
					which has its own individual property<note>Or "power."</note> and nature, has
					lost some of its qualities and has been mixed and combined with others.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="14">
				<head>PART 14 </head>
				<p>XIV. Of course I know also that it makes a difference to a man's body whether
					bread be of bolted or of unbolted flour, whether it be of winnowed or of
					unwinnowed wheat, whether it be kneaded with much water or with little, whether
					it be thoroughly kneaded or unkneaded, whether it be thoroughly baked or
					underbaked, and there are countless other differences. Barley-cake varies in
					just the same way. The properties<note>Or "powers."</note> too of each variety
					are powerful, and no one is like to any other. But how could he who has not
					considered these truths, or who considers them without learning, know anything
					about human ailments ? For each of these differences produces in a human being
					an effect and a change of one sort or another, and upon these differences is
					based all the dieting of a man, whether he be in health, recovering from an
					illness, or suffering from one. Accordingly there could surely be nothing more
					useful or more necessary to know than these things, and how the first
					discoverers, pursuing their inquiries excellently and with suitable application
					of reason to the nature of man, made their discoveries, and thought the art
					worthy to be ascribed to a god, as in fact is the usual belief. For they did not
					consider that the dry or the moist or the hot or the cold or anything else of
					the kind injures a man, or that he has need of any such thing, but they
					considered that it is the strength of each thing, that which, being too powerful
					for the human constitution, it cannot assimilate, which causes harm, and</p>
				<pb n="p.39"/>
				<p>this they sought to take away. The strongest part of the sweet is the sweetest,
					of the bitter the most bitter, of the acid the most acid, and each of all the
					component parts of man has its extreme. For these they saw are component parts
					of man, and that they are injurious to him ; for there is in man salt and
					bitter, sweet and acid, astringent and insipid,<note>Or "flat," the opposite of
						"sharp."</note> and a vast number of other things, possessing properties of
					all sorts, both in number and in strength. These, when mixed and compounded with
					one another are neither apparent nor do they hurt a man ; but when one of them
					is separated off, and stands alone, then it is apparent and hurts a man.
					Moreover, of the foods that are unsuitable for us and hurt a man when taken,
					each one of them is either bitter, or salt, or acid, or something else
					uncompounded and strong, and for this reason we are disordered by them, just as
					we are by the secretions separated off in the body. But all things that a man
					eats or drinks are plainly altogether free from such an uncompounded and potent
					humour, <hi rend="ital">e.g.</hi> bread, cake, and suchlike, which men are
					accustomed constantly to use in great quantity, except the highly seasoned
					delicacies which gratify his appetite and greed. And from such foods, when
					plentifully partaken of by a man, there arises no disorder at all or isolation
					of the powers<note>Or "properties."</note> resident in the body, but strength,
					growth and nourishment in great measure arise from them, for no other reason
					except that they are well compounded, and have nothing undiluted and strong, but
					form a single, simple whole.</p>
				<pb n="p.41"/>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="15">
				<head>PART 15 </head>
				<p>XV. I am at a loss to understand how those who maintain the other view, and
					abandon the old method to rest the art on a postulate, treat their patients on
					the lines of their postulate. For they have not discovered, I think, an absolute
					hot or cold, dry or moist, that participates in no other form. But I think that
					they have at their disposal the same foods and the same drinks as we all use,
					and to one they add the attribute of being hot, to another, cold, to another,
					dry, to another, moist, since it would be futile to order a patient to take
					something hot, as he would at once ask, " What hot thing ? " So that they must
					either talk nonsense or have recourse to one of these known substances. And if
					one hot thing happens to be astringent, and another hot thing insipid, and a
					third hot thing causes flatulence (for there are many various kinds of hot
					things, possessing many opposite powers), surely it will make a difference
					whether he administers the hot astringent thing, or the hot insipid thing, or
					that which is cold and astringent at the same time (for there is such a thing),
					or the cold insipid thing. For I am sure that each of these pairs produces
					exactly the opposite of that produced by the other, not only in a man, but in a
					leathern or wooden vessel, and in many other things less sensitive than man. For
					it is not the heat which possesses the great power, but the astringent and the
					insipid, and the other qualities I have mentioned, both in man and out of man,
					whether eaten or drunk, whether applied externally as ointment or as
					plaster.</p>
				<pb n="p.43"/>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="16">
				<head>PART 16 </head>
				<p>XVI. And I believe that of all the powers<note>Or "properties."</note> none hold
					less sway in the body than cold and heat. My reasons are these. So long as the
					hot and cold in the body are mixed up together, they cause no pain. For the hot
					is tempered and moderated by the cold, and the cold by the hot. But when either
					is entirely separated from the other, then it causes pain. And at that season,
					when cold comes upon a man and causes him some pain, for that very reason
					internal heat first is present quickly and spontaneously, without needing any
					help or preparation. The result is the same, whether men be diseased or in
					health. For instance, if a man in health will cool his body in winter, either by
					a cold bath or in any other way, the more he cools it (provided that his body is
					not entirely frozen) the more he becomes hotter than before when he puts his
					clothes on and enters his shelter. Again, if he will make himself thoroughly hot
					by means of either a hot bath of a large fire, and afterwards wear the same
					clothes and stay in the same place as he did when chilled, he feels far colder
					and besides more shivery than before. Or if a man fan himself because of the
					stifling heat and make coolness for himself, on ceasing to do this in this way
					he will feel ten times the stifling heat felt by one who does nothing of the
					sort.</p>
				<p>Now the following is much stronger evidence still. All who go afoot through snow
					or great cold, and become over-chilled in feet, hands or head, suffer at</p>
				<pb n="p.45"/>
				<p>night very severely from burning and tingling when they come into a warm place
					and wrap up ; in some cases blisters arise like those caused by burning in fire.
					But it is not until they are warmed that they experience these symptoms. So
					ready is cold to pass into heat and heat into cold. I could give a multitude of
					other proofs. But in the case of sick folk, is it not those who have suffered
					from shivering in whom breaks out the most acute fever? And not only is it not
					powerful, but after a while does it not subside, generally without doing harm
					all the time it remains, hot as it is? And passing through all the body it ends
					in most cases in the feet, where the shivering and chill were most violent and
					lasted unusually long. Again, when the fever disappears with the breaking out of
					the perspiration, it cools the patient so that he is far colder than if he had
					never been attacked at all. What important or serious consequence, therefore,
					could come from that thing on which quickly supervenes in this way its exact
					opposite, spontaneously annulling its effect?<note>Or "power."</note> Or what
					need has it of elaborate treatment?</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="17">
				<head>PART 17 </head>
				<p>XVII. An opponent may retort, "But patients whose fever comes from ardent
							fevers,<note><foreign xml:lang="grc">kau=sos</foreign> was almost
						certainly a form of remittent malaria. See my <hi rend="ital">Malaria and
							Greek Hist<foreign xml:lang="grc">S1</foreign>ry</hi> (index).</note>
					pneumonia, or other virulent disease, do not quickly get rid of their
					feverishness, and in these cases the heat and cold no longer alternate." Now I
					consider that herein lies my strongest evidence that men are not feverish merely
					through heat, and that it could not be the sole cause of the harm ; the truth
					being that one and the same thing is both bitter and hot, or acid and</p>
				<pb n="p.47"/>
				<p>hot, or salt and hot, with numerous other combinations, and cold again combines
					with other powers.<note>Or "properties."</note> It is these things which cause
					the harm. Heat, too, is present, but merely as a concomitant, having the
					strength of the directing factor which is aggravated and increases with the
					other factor, but having no power<note>Or "effect."</note> greater than that
					which properly belongs to it.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="18">
				<head>PART 18 </head>
				<p>XVIII. That this is so is plain if we consider the following pieces of evidence.
					First we have the more obvious symptoms, which all of us often experience and
					will continue so to do. In the first place, those of us who suffer from cold in
					the head, with discharge from the nostrils, generally find this discharge more
					acrid than that which previously formed there and daily passed from the nostrils
					; it makes the nose swell, and inflames it to an extremely fiery heat, as is
					shown if you put your hand upon it.<note>Or, with the MSS. reading, "And if you
						keep putting your hand to it, and the catarrh last a long time," etc.</note>
					And if the disease be present for an unusually long time, the part actually
					becomes ulcered, although it is without flesh and hard. But in some way the heat
					of the nostril ceases, not when the discharge takes place and the inflammation
					is present, but when the running becomes thicker and less acrid, being matured
					and more mixed than it was before, then it is that the heat finally ceases. But
					in cases where the evil obviously comes from cold alone, unaccompanied by
					anything else, there is always the same change, heat following chill and chill
					heat, and these supervene at once, and need no coction. In all other
					instances,</p>
				<pb n="p.49"/>
				<p>where acrid and unmixed humours come into play, I am confident that the cause is
					the same, and that restoration results from coction and mixture.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="19">
				<head>PART 19 </head>
				<p>XIX. Again, such discharges as settle in the eyes, possessing powerful, acrid
					humours of all sorts, ulcerate the eyelids, and in some cases eat into the parts
					on to which they run, the cheeks and under the eyes ; and they rupture and eat
					through the covering of the eyeball. But pains, burning and intense inflammation
					prevail until the discharges are concocted and become thicker, so that rheum is
					formed from them. This coction is the result of mixture, compounding and
					digestion. Secondly, the discharges that settle in the throat, giving rise to
					soreness, angina, erysipelas and pneumonia, all these at first emit salt, watery
					and acrid humours, whereby the diseases are strengthened. But when they become
					thicker and more matured, and throw off all trace of their acridness, then the
					fevers too subside with the other symptoms that distress the patient. We must
					surely consider the cause of each complaint to be those things the presence of
					which of necessity produces a complaint of a specific kind, which ceases when
					they change into another combination. All conditions, then, resulting from heat
					or cold pure and simple, with no other power<note>Or "quality."</note> as a
					factor, must cease when heat changes into cold or cold into heat. This change
					takes place in the manner I have described above. Moreover, all other complaints
					to which man is liable arise from powers.<note>Or "qualities."</note> Thus, when
					there is an out-pouring of the bitter principle, which we call yellow</p>
				<pb n="p.51"/>
				<p>bile, great nausea, burning and weakness prevail. When the patient gets rid of
					it, sometimes by purgation, either spontaneous or by medicine, if the purging be
					seasonable he manifestly gets rid both of the pains and of the heat. But so long
					as these bitter particles are undissolved, undigested and uncompounded, by no
					possible means can the pains and fevers be stayed. And those who are attacked by
					pungent and acrid acids suffer greatly from frenzy, from gnawings of the bowels
					and chest, and from restlessness.<note>Or "distress."</note> No relief from
					these symptoms is secured until the acidity is purged away, or calmed down and
					mixed with the other humours. But coction, alteration, thinning or thickening
					into the form of humours through other forms of all sorts (wherefrom crises also
					and fixing their periods derive great importance in cases of illness)--to all
					these things surely heat and cold are not in the least liable. For neither could
					either ferment or thicken. †For what shall we call it? Combinations of humours
					that exhibit a power<note>Or "property."</note> that varies with the various
						factors.<note>There are many reasons for supposing that this sentence is
						either (<hi rend="ital">a</hi>) in its wrong place, or (<hi rend="ital"
							>b</hi>) an interpolation. It seems quite irrelevant, and <foreign
							xml:lang="grc">AU)TW=N</foreign> should grammatically refer to <foreign
							xml:lang="grc">TO\ QERMO\N</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO\
							YUXRO/N</foreign>, but there is <hi rend="ital">not</hi> a crasis of
						these, but only of <foreign xml:lang="grc">XUMOI/</foreign>. Hot and cold
						mixed produce only hot or cold, not a crasis. The sentence might be more
						relevantly placed at the end of Chapter XVIII, as an explanation of the
						process <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)POKAQI/S1TAS1QAI PEFQE/NTA KAI\
							KRHQE/NTA</foreign>. But transposition will not remove the other
						difficulties of the sentence. What is <foreign xml:lang="grc"
							>AU)TO/</foreign>? Health or disease? If health, then there is but <hi
							rend="ital">one</hi> crasis producing it, not "many, having various
						properties." If disease, then it cannot be a crasis at all, but <foreign
							xml:lang="grc">A)KRAS1I/A</foreign>. Finally, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
							>A)/LLHN PRO\S2 A)/LLHLA</foreign> is dubious Greek. The whole sentence
						looks like an interpolation, though it is hard to say why it was introduced.
						The scribe of M seems to have felt the difficulties, for he wrote <foreign
							xml:lang="grc">KRH=S1IS2, PLH\N</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc"
							>A)/LLHN</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="grc"
						>E)/XOUS1A</foreign>.</note>† Since the hot will give up its heat only when
					mixed with the cold, and the cold can be</p>
				<pb n="p.53"/>
				<p>neutralized only by the hot. But all other components of man become milder and
					better the greater the number of other components with which they are mixed. A
					man is in the best possible condition when there is complete coction and rest,
					with no particular power<note>Or "property."</note> displayed. About this I
					think that I have given a full explanation.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="20">
				<head>PART 20 </head>
				<p>XX. Certain physicians and philosophers assert that nobody can know medicine who
					is ignorant what a man is ; he who would treat patients properly must, they say,
					learn this. But the question they raise is one for philosophy ; it is the
					province of those who, like Empedocles, have written on natural
						science,<note>About "nature," how the universe was born and grew out of
						primal elements. We might almost trauslate <foreign xml:lang="grc"
							>FU)S1IS2</foreign> by "evolution."</note> what man is from the
					beginning, how he came into being at the first, and from what elements he was
					originally constructed. But my view is, first, that all that philosophers or
					physicians have said or written on natural science no more pertains to medicine
					than to painting.<note>Or, perhaps, "pertains even less to medicine than to
						literature."</note> I also hold that clear knowledge about natural science
					can be acquired from medicine and from no other source, and that one can attain
					this knowledge when medicine itself has been properly comprehended, but till
					then it is quite impossible--I mean to possess this information, what man is, by
					what causes he is made, and similar points accurately. Since this at least I
					think a physician must know, and be at great pains to know, about natural
					science, if he is going to perform aught of his duty, what man is in relation to
					foods and drinks,</p>
				<pb n="p.55"/>
				<p>and to habits generally, and what will be the effects of each on each individual.
					It is not sufficient to learn simply that cheese is a bad food, as it gives a
					pain to one who eats a surfeit of it ; we must know what the pain is, the
					reasons for it, and which constituent of man is harmfully affected. For there
					are many other bad foods and bad drinks, which affect a man in different ways. I
					would therefore have the point put thus :--"Undiluted wine, drunk in large
					quantity, produces a certain effect upon a man." All who know this would realise
					that this is a power of wine, and that wine itself is to blame,<note>See
						Appendix on p. 64.</note> and we know through what parts of a man it chiefly
					exerts this power. Such nicety of truth I wish to be manifest in all other
					instances. To take my former example, cheese does not harm all men alike ; some
					can eat their fill of it without the slightest hurt, nay, those it agrees with
					are wonderfully strengthened thereby. Others come off badly. So the
					constitutions of these men differ, and the difference lies in the constituent of
					the body which is hostile to cheese, and is roused and stirred to action under
					its influence. Those in whom a humour of such a kind is present in greater
					quantity, and with greater control over the body, naturally suffer more
					severely. But if cheese were bad for the human constitution without exception,
					it would have hurt all. He who knows the above truths will not fall into the
					following errors.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="21">
				<head>PART 21 </head>
				<p>XXI. In convalescence from illness, and also in protracted illnesses, many
					disturbances occur, some spontaneously and some from things casually</p>
				<pb n="p.57"/>
				<p>administered. I am aware that most physicians, like laymen, if the patient has
					done anything unusual near the day of the disturbance--taken a bath or a walk,
					or eaten strange food, these things being all beneficial--nevertheless assign
					the cause to one of them, and, while ignorant of the real cause, stop what may
					have been of the greatest value. Instead of so doing they ought to know what
					will be the result of a bath unseasonably taken or of fatigue. For the trouble
					caused by each of these things is also peculiar to each, and so with surfeit or
					such and such food. Whoever therefore fails to know how each of these
					particulars affects a man will be able neither to discover their consequences
					nor to use them properly.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="22">
				<head>PART 22 </head>
				<p>XXII. I hold that it is also necessary to know which diseased states arise from
					powers and which from structures. What I mean is roughly that a "power" is an
					intensity and strength of the humours, while "structures" are the conformations
					to be found in the human body, some of which are hollow, tapering<note>Or
						"contracting."</note> from wide to narrow ; some are expanded, some hard and
					round, some broad and suspended, some stretched, some long, some close in
					texture, some loose in texture and fleshy, some spongy and porous. Now which
					structure is best adapted to draw and attract to itself fluid from the rest of
					the body, the hollow and expanded, the hard and round, or the hollow and
					tapering? I take it that the best adapted is the broad hollow that tapers. One
					should learn this thoroughly from unenclosed objects<note><hi rend="ital">i.
							e.</hi> objects that are not concealed, as are the internal
						organs.</note> that can be</p>
				<pb n="p.59"/>
				<p>seen. For example, if you open the mouth wide you will draw in no fluid ; but if
					you protrude and contract it, compressing the lips, and then insert a tube, you
					can easily draw up any liquid you wish. Again, cupping instruments, which are
					broad and tapering, are so constructed on purpose to draw and attract blood from
					the flesh. There are many other instruments of a similar nature. Of the parts
					within the human frame, the bladder, the head, and the womb are of this
					structure. These obviously attract powerfully, and are always full of a fluid
					from without. Hollow and expanded parts are especially adapted for receiving
					fluid that has flowed into them, but are not so suited for attraction. Round
					solids will neither attract fluid nor receive it when it has flowed into them,
					for it would slip round and find no place on which to rest. Spongy, porous
					parts, like the spleen, lungs and breasts, will drink up readily what is in
					contact with them, and these parts especially harden and enlarge on the addition
					of fluid. They will not be evacuated every day, as are bowels, where the fluid
					is inside, while the bowels themselves contain it externally ; but when one of
					these parts drinks up the fluid and takes it to itself, the porous hollows, even
					the small ones, are every-where filled, and the soft, porous part becomes hard
					and close, and neither digests nor discharges. This happens because of the
					nature of its structure. When wind and flatulence are produced in the body,
					the</p>
				<pb n="p.61"/>
				<p>rumbling noise naturally occurs in the hollow, broad parts, such as the bowels
					and the chest. For when the flatulence does not fill a part so as to be at rest,
					but moves and changes its position, it cannot be but that thereby noise and
					perceptible movements take place. In soft, fleshy parts occur numbness and
					obstructions, such as happen in apoplexy. And when flatulence meets a broad,
					resisting body, and rushes on it, and this happens by nature to be neither
					strong so as to endure its violence without harm, nor soft and porous so as to
					give way and admit it, but tender, fleshy, full of blood, and close, like the
					liver, because it is close and broad it resists without yielding, while the
					flatulence being checked increases and becomes stronger, dashing violently
					against the obstacle. But owing to its tenderness and the blood it contains, the
					part cannot be free from pain, and this is why the sharpest and most frequent
					pains occur in this region, and abscesses and tumours are very common. Violent
					pain, but much less severe, is also felt under the diaphragm. For the diaphragm
					is an extended, broad and resisting substance, of a stronger and more sinewy
					texture, and so there is less pain. But here too occur pains and tumours.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="23">
				<head>PART 23 </head>
				<p>XXIII. There are many other structural forms, both internal and external, which
					differ widely from one another with regard to the experiences of a patient and
					of a healthy subject, such as whether the head be large or small, the neck thin
					or thick, long or short, the bowels long or round, the chest and</p>
				<pb n="p.63"/>
				<p>ribs broad or narrow, and there are very many other things, the differences
					between which must all be known, so that knowledge of the causes of each thing
					may ensure that the proper precautions are taken.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="24">
				<head>PART 24 </head>
				<p>XXIV. As I have said before, we must examine the powers of humours, and what the
					effect of each is upon man, and how they are related to one another. Let me give
					an example. If a humour that is sweet assumes another form, not by admixture,
					but by a self-caused change, what will it first become, bitter, or salt, or
					astringent, or acid? I think acid. Therefore where sweet humour is the least
					suitable of all, acid humour is the next least suitable to be
						administered.<note>Because :-- <p>(1) Health is a <hi rend="ital"
								>crasis</hi> of all the humours, none being in excess ;</p>
						<p>(2) Sweet humour passes readily into acid ;</p>
						<p>(3) Therefore, when sweet is the least suitable as a remedy (there being
							an excess of it already), acid (which is likely to be reinforced from
							the sweet) is the next least suitable.</p>
						<p>Kéhlewein's text makes sense only if we transpose <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>O)CU/S2</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">GLUKU/S2</foreign>.
							If you want <foreign xml:lang="grc">O)CU\S XUMO/S1</foreign> for <hi
								rend="ital">crasis</hi> you can get it best by adding <foreign
								xml:lang="grc">O)CU/S2</foreign>, next best by adding <foreign
								xml:lang="grc">GLUKU/S</foreign>, which naturally turns into
								<foreign xml:lang="grc">O)CU/S2</foreign>.</p></note> If a man can
					in this way conduct with success inquiries outside the human body, he will
					always be able to select the very best treatment. And the best is always that
					which is farthest removed from the unsuitable.</p>
			</div>
			<pb n="p.64"/>
			<div type="chapter">
				<head>APPENDIX </head>
				<p><hi rend="center">A<hi rend="sc">PPENDIX ON</hi> C<hi rend="sc">HAPTER</hi> XX,
						p. 54.</hi></p>
				<p><foreign xml:lang="grc">OI)NOS A)/KRHTOS POLLO\S2 POQEI\S2 DIATI/QHS1I/ PWS2 TO\N
						A)/NQRWPON: KAI\ PA/NTES2 A)/N AI( EI)DO/TES2 TOU=TO GNOI/HS1AN, O(/TI
						AU(/TH DU/NAMIS2 OI)\NOU KAI\ AU\TO\S2 AI)/TIOS2</foreign>.</p>
				<p>So A ; other MSS. have <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)S1QENE/A</foreign> after
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">A)/NQRWPON, I)DO/NTES2</foreign> for <foreign
						xml:lang="grc">OI( EI)DO/TES2, H(</foreign> after <foreign xml:lang="grc"
						>AU(/TH</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)S1TIN</foreign> after
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">AU)TO/S2</foreign>.</p>
				<p>This passage contradicts the general argument, which is that in medicine
					statements about foods must not be made <foreign xml:lang="grc"
						>A(PLW=S2</foreign>. Cheese is not bad food ; it is only bad in certain
					conditions, and in certain ways, and at certain times. In these circumstances
					cheese has a <foreign xml:lang="grc">DU/NAMIS</foreign> which does not belong to
					cheese in itself, but is latent until certain conditions call it forth. The
					error, says the writer, is not made in the case of wine. Everybody knows that in
					itself wine is not bad ; it is drinking to excess, or at wrong times, which is
					mischievous.</p>
				<p>Now the reading of A (in fact any MS. reading) makes the writer say that wine
					itself <hi rend="ital">is</hi> to blame (<foreign xml:lang="grc">AU)TO\S2
						AI)/TIOS2</foreign>)--an obvious contradiction of the general argument. My
					colleague the Rev. H. J. Chaytor most ingeniously suggests that <foreign
						xml:lang="grc">AU)TO/S2</foreign> refers not to wine but to the man. He
					would therefore translate "this <foreign xml:lang="grc">DU/NAMIS</foreign> of
					wine and the man himself are to blame." But not only is it more natural for
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">AU)TO/S2</foreign> to refer to wine, but the
					writer's whole point is that in and by itself <hi rend="ital">no</hi> food is
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">AI)/TIOS2</foreign>. A food is a cause only in
					certain conditions, or, rather, certain conditions call forth certain <foreign
						xml:lang="grc">DUNA/MEIS2</foreign>.</p>
				<p>I think, therefore, that the right reading is <foreign xml:lang="grc">O(/TI
						TOIAU/TH DU/NAMIS2 OI(/NOU KAI\ OU)K AU)TO\S2 AI(/TIOS2</foreign>. "Such and
					such a <foreign xml:lang="grc">DU/NAMIS</foreign> of wine (<hi rend="ital">i.
						e.</hi> a <foreign xml:lang="grc">DU/NAMIS2</foreign> caused by excess of
					wine acting upon the human <foreign xml:lang="grc">FU/SIIS2</foreign>) is to
					blame and not mere wine by itself." <foreign xml:lang="grc">O(/TI
						TOIAU/TH</foreign> might easily turn into <foreign xml:lang="grc">O(/TI
						AU(/TH</foreign>, and the omission of <foreign xml:lang="grc">OU)</foreign>
					by scribes is not uncommon.</p>
				<p>There is an attractive vigour about the reading <foreign xml:lang="grc"
						>I)DO/NTES2</foreign> for <foreign xml:lang="grc">OI( EI)DO/TES2</foreign>,
					and it may be correct. "Anybody can see at a glance that in the case of wine it
					is excess, etc., and not merely wine itself which is to blame."</p>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
