<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Androtion</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>Gentlemen of the jury, Euctemon finding himself wronged by Androtion, thinks it
                    his duty to obtain satisfaction for himself and at the same time to up hold the
                    constitution; and that is what I also shall essay to do, if I am equal to the
                    task. As a matter of fact the outrages that Euctemon has endured, many and
                    serious and utterly illegal as they were, are slighter than the trouble that
                    Androtion has caused me. Euctemon was the object of a plot to get money out of
                    him and to eject him unfairly from an office of your appointment; but if the
                    charges that Androtion trumped up against me had been accepted in your courts,
                    not a single living man would have opened his door to me, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>for he accused me of things that anyone would have shrunk from mentioning, unless
                    he were a man of the same stamp as himself, saying that I had killed my own
                    father. He also concocted a public indictment for impiety, not against me
                    directly, but against my uncle, whom he brought to trial, charging him with
                    impiety for associating with me, as though I had committed the alleged acts, and
                    if it had ended in my uncle's conviction, who would have suffered more
                    grievously at the defendant's hands than I? For who, whether friend or stranger,
                    would have consented to have any dealings with me? What state would have
                    admitted within its borders a man deemed guilty of such impiety? Not a single
                    one.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>Of these charges, then, I cleared myself in your court, not by a narrow margin
                    but so completely that my accuser failed to obtain a fifth of the votes; and
                    upon Androtion I shall endeavor, with your help, to avenge myself today and on
                    every other occasion.I shall pass over a great deal that I might say about
                    private matters; but there are other matters on which you are now going to give
                    your votes, including not a few injuries which the defendant has done you in
                    dealing as a citizen with public affairs, and these, which Euctemon chose to
                    pass over, but which it is better for you to understand, I shall now try to
                    explain briefly. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>If I could see any straightforward defence that he could offer to these charges,
                    I would not make any reference to them; but I am quite certain that he cannot
                    have any simple and honest plea to put forward, but will try to hoodwink you,
                    inventing malicious answers to each charge and so leading you astray. For he is
                    a skillful rhetorician, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, and has devoted all his life to that one study.
                    Therefore, that you may not be deceived and persuaded to vote contrary to the
                    spirit of your oath and to acquit a man whom you have every reason to punish,
                    pray attend to what I shall say, so that when you have heard me, you may have
                    the right reply to every argument that he will advance. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>There is one plea which he thinks a clever defence of the omission of the
                    preliminary decree. There is a law, he says, that if the Council by its
                    performance of its duties seems to deserve a reward, that reward shall be
                    presented by the people. That question, he says, the chairman of the Assembly
                    put, the people voted, and it was carried. In this case, he says, there is no
                    need of a preliminary decree, because what was done was in accordance with law.
                    But I take the exactly contrary view-and I think you will agree with me—that the
                    preliminary decrees should only be proposed concerning matters prescribed by the
                    laws, because, where no laws are laid down, surely no proposal whatever is
                    admissible. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>Now he will say that all the Councils that have ever received a reward from you,
                    have received it in this way, and that in no case has a preliminary decree ever
                    been passed. But I think—or rather, I am certain—that this statement is untrue.
                    Even if it were absolutely true, yet surely where the law says the opposite, we
                    ought not to transgress the law now because it has often been transgressed
                    before; on the contrary we ought to enforce the observance of the law, beginning
                    with you, Androtion, first. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>You must not tell us that this has often been done before; you must show us that
                    it is right to do it. If the practice has at any time been contrary to the laws
                    and you have only followed precedent, you cannot in fairness escape, but ought
                    all the more to be convicted; for if any of the former delinquents had been
                    condemned, you would never have proposed the resolution, and in the same way, if
                    you are punished now, no one else will propose it in the future. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>Coming now to the law which explicitly denies to the Council the right to ask a
                    reward, if they have not built the warships, it is worth while to hear the
                    defence that he will set up, and to get a clear view of the shamelessness of his
                    behavior from the arguments that he attempts to use. The law, he says, forbids
                    the Council to ask for the reward, if they have not built the ships. But, he
                    adds, the law nowhere prohibits the Assembly from giving it. “If I gave it at
                    their request, my motion was illegal, but if I have never mentioned the ships in
                    the whole of my decree, but give other grounds for granting a crown to the
                    Council, where is the illegality of my motion?” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>It is surely not difficult for the jury to find the right answer to this: that in
                    the first place the Committee of the Council and the chairman, who puts these
                    proposals to the vote, duly put the question and called for a show of
                    hands—“those who are of opinion that the Council have deserved a reward, to vote
                    aye; on the contrary, no.” Yet surely men who neither ask nor expect a reward
                    should never have put the question at all. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>Besides this, when Meidias and others brought certain accusations against the
                    Council, the Councillors fairly leaped up on to the platform and begged not to
                    be robbed of their reward. There is no need for me to tell the jury this, for
                    you were present in the Assembly and know what happened there. So when he says
                    that the Council did not ask for it, have that answer ready for him. But I will
                    also prove to you that the people are forbidden by the law to give the reward,
                    if the Council have not built the ships. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>For the law, that the Council should not ask for the reward if they have not
                    built the war ships, was framed in that way, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to prevent the possibility of the
                    people being influenced or misled. The legislator held that the question should
                    not depend on the abilities of the speakers, but that whatever he could devise
                    that was at once just and expedient for the people, should be fixed by law. “You
                    have not built the ships? Then don't ask for the reward.” Where the law does not
                    permit the asking, does it not absolutely forbid the giving? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>Now there is another question, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, which is worth going into. Why is it that when the
                    Council have performed all their other duties satisfactorily, and no one has any
                    complaint to make, yet, if they have not built the ships, they are not allowed
                    to ask for the reward? You will find that this stringent enactment is in the
                    interests of the people. For I suppose no one would deny that all that has
                    happened to our city, in the past or in the present, whether good or otherwise—I
                    avoid an unpleasant term—has resulted in the one case from the possession, and
                    in the other from the want, of warships. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>Many instances might be given, ancient and modern, but of those that are most
                    familiar to your ears, take if you please this. The men who built the Propylaea
                    and the Parthenon, and decked our other temples with the spoils of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, trophies in which we take a natural
                    pride,—you know of course from tradition that after they abandoned the city and
                    shut themselves up in <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, it was
                    because they had the war galleys that they won the sea-fight and saved the city
                    and all their belongings, and made themselves the authors for the rest of the
                    Greeks of many great benefits, of which not even time can ever obliterate the
                    memory. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Well, you say, but that is ancient history. But take something that you have all
                    seen. You know that lately you sent help to the Euboeans within three days and
                    got rid of the Thebans by an armistice.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In
                        357.</note> Could you have done all this so promptly, if you had not had new
                    vessels to convey your force? You would have found it impossible. Many other
                    successes might be mentioned that have resulted from our being provided with
                    these ships in sound condition. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Yes, and how many disasters from unsound ships? I will pass over most of them;
                    but in the Decelean war<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The last stage of the
                        Peloponnesian War, 413 to 404.</note>—I am reminding you of a bit of old
                    history which you all know better than I do—though many serious disasters befell
                    our city, she did not succumb till her fleet was destroyed. But why need me cite
                    ancient instances? You know how it stood with our city in the last war with the
                        Lacedaemonians<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Terminated by the peace of
                        Callias in 371.</note> when it seemed unlikely that you could dispatch a
                    fleet. You know that vetches were sold for food. But when you did dispatch it,
                    you obtained peace on your own terms. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>Therefore, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, seeing that
                    warships have such weight in either scale, you nave done rightly to set this
                    strict limit to the Council's claim to the reward. For if they should discharge
                    all their other duties satisfactorily, but fail to build these ships, by which
                    we gained our power at the first and by which we retain it today, all their
                    other services are of no avail, for it is the safety of the whole State that
                    must be ensured for the people before every thing. Now the defendant is so
                    obsessed with the idea that he can make any speech or proposal he wishes, that
                    though the Council has discharged its other duties in the way that you have
                    heard, but has not built the warships, he moved to grant them their reward. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>That this is not a violation of the law, he could not possibly assert nor could
                    you be brought to believe it. But I understand that he will put before you some
                    such plea as this—that the Council was not to blame for the shortage of ships,
                    but the treasurer of the shipbuilders, who absconded with two and a half
                    talents, and so the business ended in a fiasco. But I must first express my
                    surprise that he should have demanded a crown for the Council to reward a
                    fiasco. I thought such honors were reserved for successes. Next, I have another
                    consideration to put before you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>I submit that it is not fair to combine the two pleas, that the gift was not
                    illegal and that the Council are not responsible for the lack of ships. For if
                    it is right to give them the reward even when they have not built the ships,
                    what need is there to say who is responsible for the omission? But if it is not
                    right, why were the Council any the more entitled to it, because he can point to
                    this or that man as responsible for the shortage? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>Apart from that, it seems to me that such arguments offer you a choice, whether
                    you think you ought to hear excuses and pleas from men who have done you harm,
                    or whether you ought to have some ships. For if you accept the defendant's plea,
                    it will be clear to every future Council that their business is to find you
                    plausible excuses, not to build you ships, with the result that your money will
                    be spent, but there will be no ships for you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>But if, as the law says and as your oath enjoins, you sternly and absolutely
                    reject their excuses, and make it clear that you have withheld the reward
                    because they have not built the ships, then every Council, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, will deliver to you the ships duly
                    built, because they will see that in your eyes everything else is of less
                    consequence than the law. Now I shall show you clearly that no other human being
                    is responsible for the shortage of ships; for the Council, having made the law
                    null and void, elected this treasurer themselves.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The treasurer should have been elected by the people; the
                        Council, by appointing him illegally, made themselves responsible for his
                        defalcations. The corruption of this passage is as old as Harpocration. Mss.
                        have <foreign xml:lang="grc">a(uth=|</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >a(uth/n</foreign> . With the latter and a comma after <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">tou=ton</foreign>, editors have tried to translate
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)xeipoto/nhsen</foreign> “voted itself guilty.”
                        Jurinus was the first to suggest <foreign xml:lang="grc">au)th\</foreign>
                        and to refer <foreign xml:lang="grc">tou=ton</foreign> to the
                        treasurer.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Again, with regard to the law<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The little that is
                        known of this law is derived from Aeschines' speech against Timarchus<bibl
                            n="Aeschin. 1">Aeschin. 1</bibl></note> of prostitution, he tries to
                    make out that we are insulting him and attacking him with baseless calumnies. He
                    says too that if we believed the charges true, we ought to have faced him in the
                    Court of the Thesmothetae, and asked a fine of a thousand drachmas if our
                    charges had been proved false; as it is, we are trying to hoodwink you by
                    accusations and idle abuse, and are confusing you by matters outside your
                    jurisdiction. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>But I think you ought first of all to reflect in your own minds that abuse and
                    accusation are very far removed from proof. It is an accusation when one makes a
                    bare statement without supplying grounds for believing it; it is proof when one
                    at the same time demonstrates the truth of one's statements. Those, therefore,
                    who are proving a case must supply evidence sufficient to establish its
                    credibility with you, or must advance reasonable arguments, or must produce
                    witnesses. Of some facts it is impossible to put eye-witnesses in the box, but
                    if one can establish any of these tests, you rightly consider in every case that
                    you have a sufficient proof of the truth. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>We then base our proof, not on probabilities nor on circumstantial evidence, but
                    on a witness from whom the defendant may easily obtain satisfaction—a man who
                    has prepared a document containing an account of the defendant's life, and who
                    makes himself responsible for this evidence. So that when Androtion says that
                    this is mere abuse and accusation, reply that this is proof, but that abuse and
                    accusation describe his own performance; and when he says that we ought to have
                    denounced him to the Thesmothetae, reply that we intend to do so, and that we
                    are now quite properly citing this statute. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>For if we were bringing these charges against him in any other kind of trial, he
                    could have just cause of complaint; but if the present trial is one that
                    concerns illegal proposals, and if men who have led a life like his are
                    forbidden by the laws to make even a legal proposal, and if we prove that he has
                    not only made an illegal proposal but has also led an illegal life, then is it
                    not proper to cite this law which determines his illegal status? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Moreover you should grasp this fact, that Solon,
                    who framed these and most of our other laws, was a very different kind of
                    legislator from the defendant, and provided not one, but many modes of procedure
                    for those who wish to obtain redress for various wrongs. For he knew, I think,
                    that for all the citizens to be equally clever, or bold, or moderate folk, was
                    impossible. If, then, he was going to frame the laws to satisfy the moderate
                    man's claim to redress, many rascals, he reflected, would get off scot-free, but
                    if he framed them in the interests of the bold and the clever speakers, the
                    plain citizen would not be able to obtain redress in the same way as they would.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>But he thought that no one should be debarred from obtaining redress in whatever
                    way he can best do so. How then will this be ensured? By granting many modes of
                    legal procedure to the injured parties. Take a case of theft. Are you a strong
                    man, confident in yourself? Arrest the thief; only you are risking a thousand
                    drachmas. Are you rather weak? Guide the Archons to him, and they will do the
                    rest. Are you afraid even to do this? Bring a written indictment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>Do you distrust yourself, and are you a poor man, unable to find the thousand
                    drachmas? Sue him for theft before a public arbitrator, and you will risk
                    nothing. In the same way for impiety you can arrest, or indict, or sue before
                    the Eumolpidae, or give information to the King-Archon. And in the same way, or
                    nearly so, for every other offence. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>Now just suppose that a man, instead of rebutting the charge of crime or impiety
                    or whatever else he may be tried for, should claim his acquittal on these
                    grounds-in the case of an arrest, that you might have brought an action before
                    an arbitrator and that you ought to have indicted him, or, if he is defendant in
                    an arbitrator's court, that you ought to have arrested him, so that you might
                    risk a fine of a thousand drachmas. Surely that would be a farce. A defendant,
                    if innocent, need not dispute the method by which he is brought.to justice: he
                    ought to prove hat he is innocent. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>In just the same way, if you, Androtion, propose a decree after having been
                    guilty of prostitution, do not imagine that you ought to escape punishment
                    because we might also have denounced you to the Thesmothetae, but either prove
                    that you are innocent or submit to punishment for any decrees that you have
                    proposed, being what you are; or you have no right to propose them. If we do not
                    punish you by every process that the laws allow, be grateful to us for those
                    that we omit: do not on that ground claim to pay no penalty at all. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>Now it is worth your while, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, to study too the character of Solon, who framed this
                    law, and to observe what care he took of the constitution in all the laws, how
                    much more zealous indeed he was for the constitution than for the matter on
                    which he was legislating. This may be seen in many ways, but especially from
                    this law, which forbids persons guilty of prostitution to make speeches or to
                    propose measures. For he saw that the majority of you do not avail yourselves of
                    your right to speak, so that the prohibition seemed no great hardship, and he
                    could have laid down many harsher penalties, if his object had been the
                    chastisement of these offenders. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>But that was not his aim; he imposed this disability in the interests of you and
                    of the State, for he knew—I say, he knew that of all states the most
                    antagonistic men of infamous habits is that in which every man is at liberty to
                    publish their shame. And what state is that? A democracy. He thought it would be
                    dangerous if there ever happened to coexist a considerable number of men who
                    were bold and clever speakers, but tainted with such disgraceful wickedness.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>For the people may be led astray by them to make many mistakes, and such men may
                    attempt either to overthrow the democracy completely,—for in an oligarchy, even
                    if there are viler livers than Androtion, no one may speak evil of dignities—or
                    to debauch the people, so that they may be as nearly as possible like
                    themselves. He therefore absolutely forbade such men to take any share in the
                    counsels of the State, lest the people should be deluded into some error.
                    Disregarding all this, our honorable gentleman here thought fit not only to make
                    speeches and proposals, though not entitled to do so, but even ventured to make
                    illegal ones. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Again, with regard to the law which forbids him to
                    speak or move resolutions, because his father owed money to the exchequer and
                    has never paid it, you have a fair and reasonable answer to him, if he says that
                    we ought to have laid an information against him. We will do that later,
                    certainly not now, Androtion, when you have to render an account of your other
                    crimes, but when it is proper to do so according to the law. For the present, we
                    are content to prove that the law does not permit you to move resolutions, not
                    even such as every other citizen may move. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>Prove, therefore, that your father was not a defaulter, or that he left the
                    prison, not by running away, but by paying his debts. If you cannot prove that,
                    then you had no right to move your resolution; for the law makes you a partner
                    in the disqualification of your father, and being disqualified you had no right
                    either to speak or move. Also with regard to the laws which we have cited in
                    court, I think that if he tries to cheat and mislead you, gentlemen, you must
                    give him the reply that I have indicated. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>On other points also he has arguments admirably calculated to deceive you, and it
                    is better that you should be told of them beforehand. One of them runs like
                    this: “Do not steal the reward from five hundred of yourselves, nor involve them
                    in disgrace; they are on their trial, not I.” But, had you been going to deprive
                    them of something without otherwise benefiting the State, I should not have
                    asked you to show any great keenness in the matter; but if by this action you
                    are going to convert more than ten thousand others into better citizens, what a
                    far finer thing it is to make so many men honest than to confer an unjust favour
                    on five hundred. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>But I am in a position to assert that the question does not concern the whole
                    Council, but only Androtion and some others, who are the cause of the mischief.
                    For should the Council receive no crown, who suffers disgrace, if he makes no
                    speech and moves no resolution himself, and perhaps even does not attend most of
                    the meetings? No one surely. The disgrace attaches to him who moves resolutions
                    and meddles with politics and tries to impose his wishes on the Council; because
                    it is through such men that the deliberations of the Council have proved
                    undeserving of the crown. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>And yet, even if we grant freely that the whole Council is on its trial, reflect
                    how much more advantage you will gain if you condemn Androtion, than if you do
                    not. If you acquit him, the talkers will rule in the Council chamber, but if you
                    convict him, the ordinary members. For when the majority see that they have lost
                    the crown through the misconduct of the orators, they will not leave the
                    transaction of business in their hands, but will depend on themselves for the
                    best advice. If this comes to pass, and if you are once rid of the old gang of
                    orators, then, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you
                    will see everything done as it ought to be. For this, if for no other, reason
                    you ought to convict. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now attend to another point that must not escape
                    you. Perhaps Philippus will get up and defend the Council; perhaps too Antigenes
                    and the checking-clerk<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">a)ntigrafeu\s th=s bou;h=s</foreign> checked all
                        financial transactions with which the Council was concerned. He must be
                        distinguished from the <foreign xml:lang="grc">grammateu/s</foreign> , who
                        dealt with the decrees. The two men named are unknown.</note> and some
                    others, who along with the defendant kept the Council-chamber as their private
                    preserve, and who are the cause of the present discontents. Now you must all
                    observe that their pretence is that they are supporting the cause of the
                    Council, but really they will be fighting for their own interests, to support
                    the audit which they have to render of their official acts. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>For the case stands thus. If you dismiss this impeachment, they are all acquitted
                    and not a single one of them will pay the penalty, for who henceforth would give
                    his verdict against them when you have crowned the Council of which they were
                    the leading spirits? But if you convict, in the first place you will have kept
                    your judicial oath; and further, when you have each of these men before you at
                    their audit, anyone whom you think guilty you will punish; and anyone who is
                    not, then will be the time to acquit him. Do not, therefore, accept their words
                    as spoken on behalf of the Council and of the general public, but be incensed
                    against them as impostors defending their own interests. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>Again, I expect that Archias, of the deme of Cholargas,—for he too was a
                    Councillor last year-will plead on their behalf in his character of respectable
                    citizen. But I suggest that you should meet his plea in some such way as this.
                    Ask him whether the conduct with which the Council are charged seems to him
                    honorable or the reverse, and if he says “honorable,” pay him no longer the
                    attention due to a respectable man; if he says “dishonorable,” ask him a second
                    question: why did he let it pass, if he claims to be a respectable man? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>If he says that he spoke against it but could persuade no one, surely it is
                    ridiculous for him now to defend this Council that rejected all his excellent
                    advice; but if he says that he held his tongue, is he not guilty of an injustice
                    if he neglected his chance of dissuading them from the offence they were
                    contemplating, and yet ventures now to say that having actually done so much
                    evil they deserve to be crowned? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>I expect too that Androtion will not refrain from pleading that all this has come
                    upon him because of his success in collecting on your behalf large arrears of
                    taxes, which a few citizens (so he will tell you) shamelessly neglected to pay;
                    and he will denounce these men—undertaking an easy task, I think—[;for not
                    paying their property-tax];, and will prophesy complete impunity for all who do
                    not pay, if you give your verdict against him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>But I must first ask you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, to reflect that the question you are sworn to decide is
                    not this, but whether his proposal was in accordance with the laws. Next reflect
                    that it is outrageous in one who charges others with violating the constitution
                    to claim exemption from punishment for his own more serious violations; because
                    it is obviously more serious to propose an unconstitutional decree than to fail
                    to pay the property-tax. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>Then even if it were certain that after this man's conviction no one would pay
                    the tax or be willing to collect it, even so you must not acquit him, as you
                    will see from this consideration. Upon the property-taxes from the archonship of
                    Nausinicus—say three hundred talents or a trifle more<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This figure is probably corrupt, being too large for a
                        single year, and too small for the twenty-three years from the archonship of
                        Nausinicus (378-377) to the date of this speech.</note>—you have a deficit
                    of fourteen talents, of which he levied seven; but I am assuming that he levied
                    the whole amount. Now you do not need Androtion to deal with the willing payers,
                    but with the defaulters. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>So you have now to consider whether that is the value that you put on the
                    constitution, the existing laws, and your regard for your oath;for if you acquit
                    him, though his proposal was manifestly illegal, everyone will conclude that you
                    have preferred this sum of money to the laws and to your good faith. Why, even
                    if a man gave you this sum out of his own pocket, it would not be worth taking,
                    much less if it has to be exacted from others. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>Therefore, when he uses this argument, remember your oath, and reflect that this
                    indictment concerns not the collection of taxes, but the sovereignty of the
                    laws. And as to all this—how he will try to hoodwink you by distracting you from
                    the subject of this law, and what points you must bear in mind so as not to give
                    way to him—though I might say more on these subjects, I will refrain, as I think
                    that this will suffice. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>I desire also to subject the politics of this honorable gentleman to a scrutiny,
                    from which it will be clear that he has not stopped short of the utmost limits
                    of depravity; for I shall prove him to be shameless and reckless, a thief and a
                    bully, fit for anything rather than to play a public part in a democracy. And
                    first of all let us examine this levying of taxes, on which he chiefly prides
                    himself. Without paying any attention to his boasts, let us look at the facts in
                    their true light. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>He said that Euctemon was retaining your taxes, and he undertook to prove the
                    charge or pay the sum out of his own pocket. On that pretext he got you to vote
                    for the dismissal of an official appointed by lot, and so wormed his way into a
                    collectorship. He delivered sundry harangues on the subject, telling you that
                    you had a choice of three courses, either to break up the sacred plate, or to
                    impose a fresh tax, or to squeeze the money out of the defaulters; and you
                    naturally chose the last. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>Having you under his thumb, thanks to his promises, and having liberty of action
                    owing to the state of affairs at the time, he did not think it necessary to
                    employ the existing laws for his purpose, nor to make new laws, if he considered
                    the old ones inadequate; but he proposed in your Assembly monstrous and
                    unconstitutional decrees, by means of which he created a job for himself and has
                    stolen a great deal that belongs to you, putting in a clause that the Eleven
                    should attend on him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>Then, with the Eleven, he led the way to the homes of his fellow-citizens.
                    Against Euctemon he could prove nothing, though he had said that he would get
                    the taxes out of him or pay them himself; but it was from you that he levied
                    them, as if his motive was hostility, not to Euctemon, but to you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>Let no one understand me to say that the money ought not to have been wrung from
                    the defaulters. It ought; but how? Even as the law enjoins, for the benefit of
                    the other citizens. That is the spirit of democracy. For what you, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, have gained by the
                    exaction of such paltry sums of money in this way, is nothing to what you have
                    lost by the introduction of such habits into political life. If you care to
                    inquire why a man would sooner live under a democracy than under an oligarchy,
                    you will find that most obvious reason is that in a democracy everything is more
                    easy-going. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>I shall not, then, trouble to show that the defendant has proved himself more
                    brutal than any oligarchy anywhere in the world. But here, in our own city, at
                    what period were the most outrageous things done? You will all say, “Under the
                    Thirty Tyrants.” Now under the Thirty, as we are informed, no man forfeited the
                    power to save his life who could hide himself at home; what we denounce the
                    Thirty for is that they arrested men illegally in the market-place. This man
                    displayed a brutality so far in excess of theirs that he, a public man under a
                    democracy, turned every man's private house into a jail by conducting the Eleven
                    into your homes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>But what do you think of this, Athenians? What if a poor man, or a rich man for
                    that matter who has spent much money and is naturally perhaps rather short of
                    cash, should have to climb over the roof to a neighbor's house or creep under
                    bed, to avoid being caught and dragged off to jail, or should degrade himself in
                    some other fashion, fit for slaves and not for freemen, and should be seen thus
                    acting by his own wife, whom he espoused as a freeman and a citizen of our
                    state? And what if the cause of all this was Androtion, a man who is debarred by
                    his own conduct and mode of life from seeking redress for himself, much more for
                    the State? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>Yet if he were asked whether the taxes are due from our property or from our
                    persons, he would admit, if he cared to speak the truth, that they are due from
                    our property; it is from property that our contributions come. Then why did you
                    drop the sequestration and scheduling of lands and houses, and proceed to
                    imprison and insult Athenian citizens and the unfortunate resident aliens, whom
                    you have treated with more insolence than your own slaves? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>Indeed, if you wanted to contrast the slave and the freeman, you would find the
                    most important distinction in the fact that slaves are responsible in person for
                    all offences, while freemen, even in the most unfortunate circumstances, can
                    protect their persons. For it is in the shape of money that in the majority of
                    cases the law must obtain satisfaction from them; but Androtion on the contrary
                    exacted vengeance from their persons, as if they had been bond-slaves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>So corrupt and selfish was his attitude towards you that he thought that his own
                    father, imprisoned by the State for moneys due, had a right to escape, without
                    payment and without trial, but that any other citizen, not having the means to
                    pay, might be dragged from his own home to prison. And then, on the top of all
                    this, as though he could do whatever he liked, he distrained upon Sinope and
                    Phanostrate, who were prostitutes certainly, but owed no property-tax. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>Should anyone possibly think that those women were fitting people to suffer, yet
                    assuredly it was not a fitting procedure—that men should be so puffed up by a
                    chance opportunity as to march into houses and carry off the furniture of people
                    who are not in debt. For one could point to many who are and have been “fitting
                    persons” for such treatment. But surely such is not the language of the statutes
                    or of the principles of the constitution, which it is your duty to uphold. In
                    them we find pity, pardon, everything that becomes free citizens. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>To all such feelings the defendant is of course a stranger by birth and breeding.
                    Many are the outrages and insults that he has had to submit to when consorting
                    with men who had no love for him but could pay his price. For such insults,
                    Androtion, it would have been right to vent your spite, not on the next citizen
                    you meet, not on the women who follow your own profession, but on the father who
                    gave you such a bringing up. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>Now that these are serious offences, contrary to every statute, he will not be
                    able to deny; but he is so impudent that in the Assembly, contriving always an
                    anticipation of his defence against this indictment, he dared to say that it was
                    in your interests and for your sake that he had drawn down enmity on himself and
                    was now in desperate peril. But I want to prove to you, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that he has never suffered, nor is
                    likely to suffer, any inconvenience at all through his services to you, but that
                    for his abominable and monstrous wickedness he has hitherto not paid the
                    penalty, but will pay it now, if you on your part do what is right. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>Consider this point. What did he undertake to do for you, and what did you
                    appoint him to do? To collect moneys. Anything else besides? Not a single thing!
                    Very well; I will remind you of the items of his accounts. He collected from
                    Leptines of Coele thirty-four drachmas, from Theoxenus of Alopece seventy
                    drachmas or a trifle more, and from Callicrates, the son of Eupherus, and from
                    the young son of Telestes, whose name I cannot give you—but without going into
                    details, of all those from whom he collected money, I doubt if anyone owed more
                    than a mina. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
                <p>Then do you suppose that all these men are his inveterate enemies merely because
                    he collected this money from them? Is it not rather because he said of one of
                    them, in the hearing of all of you in the Assembly, that he was a slave and born
                    of slaves and ought by rights to pay the contribution of one-sixth with the
                    resident aliens<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The metoeci paid tax on
                        one-sixth of their capital; but possibly, as Mr. Wayte has suggested, they
                        paid the same quotas as the citizen, plus an additional charge of
                        one-sixth.</note>; and of another that he had children by a harlot; of this
                    man that his father had prostituted himself; of that man that his mother had
                    been on the streets; that he was making an inventory of one man's peculations
                    from the start of his career, that another had done this or that, and that a
                    third had committed every conceivable crime—slandering them all in turn? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
                <p>I feel sure that of all whom he has abused in his cups, each one looked upon the
                    tax as a necessary item of expenditure, but has been deeply wounded by all these
                    indignities and insults. I feel sure too that he was elected by you to collect
                    money due, and not to reproach every man with his private misfortunes and so
                    make them public. For if the charges were true, Androtion (and we all have our
                    undesirable experiences), you had no right to publish them; and if you invented
                    them without any authority, is any punishment too light for you? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
                <p>Here is yet another proof that will convince you that they all hate him, not
                    because of the collection, but for his acts of drunken insolence. Satyrus, the
                    superintendent of the dock-yards, collected for you not seven, but thirty-four
                    talents from these very same men, and used the money to equip the ships that
                    were put in commission; and he can tell you that he has made no enemies in
                    consequence, and that none of those from whom he levied the taxes is at open war
                    with him. Naturally! He, I suppose, simply discharged the duty assigned to him,
                    but you in your wanton, headstrong effrontery, being armed with authority,
                    thought fit to terse with foul and lying reproaches men who had spent large sums
                    on the State, better men than yourself and of better birth. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="section">
                <p>After this, are the jury to believe that you did it all for their sakes? Are they
                    to make themselves responsible for your acts of callous wickedness? They ought
                    in justice to detest you all the more for this rather than protect you. For the
                    man who is acting for the State ought to imitate the spirit of the State, and
                    you, Athenians, ought to encourage such men and hate men like the defendant. For
                    though you are probably aware of it, I must none the less tell you this:
                    whatever sort of men you are seen to honor and protect, you will be thought to
                    be like them yourselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
                <p><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The rest of this speech is almost entirely
                        repeated in that against Timocrates, <bibl n="Dem. 24.172">Dem.
                            24.172-186</bibl>.</note> However, I will make it quite clear to you
                    without more ado that he did not carry out these exactions for your benefit at
                    all. If he were asked whether, in his opinion, the greater injury is done to the
                    common wealth by tillers of the soil, who live frugally, but, because of the
                    cost of maintaining their children, or of household expenses, or of other public
                    burdens, are behindhand with their taxes, or by people who plunder and squander
                    the money of willing taxpayers and the revenue that comes from our allies, I am
                    sure that, for all his hardihood, he would never have the audacity to reply that
                    those who fail to contribute their own money are worse transgressors than those
                    who embezzle public money. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="section">
                <p>What is the reason, you abominable wretch, that though you have taken part in
                    public life for more than thirty years, and though during that time many
                    commanders have defrauded the commonwealth, and many politicians as well, who
                    have been tried in this court, and though some of them have suffered death for
                    their crimes, and others have slipped away into exile, you never once appeared
                    as prosecutor of any of them or expressed any indignation at the wrongs of the
                    city, bold and clever speaker though you are, but made your first exhibition of
                    anxiety for our welfare on an occasion that called for harsh treatment of a
                    great many people? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="section">
                <p>Do you wish me to tell you the reason, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>? [;He has his share in the proceeds of certain
                    iniquities, and he also gets his pickings from the collection of revenue. In his
                    insatiable greed he reaps a double harvest from the State. Now it is not an
                    easier matter to make enemies of a multitude of petty offenders than of a few
                    big offenders; neither of course is it a more popular thing to have an eye for
                    the sins of the many than for the sins of the few. However, the reason is what I
                    am telling you.]; He knows indeed that he is one of them, one of the criminals,
                    but he thought you beneath his notice; and that was why he treated you in this
                    way. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="section">
                <p>If you had confessed, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    that you are a nation of slaves and not of men who claim empire over others, you
                    would never have put up with the insults which he repeatedly offered you in the
                    marketplace, binding and arresting aliens and citizens alike, bawling from the
                    platform in the Assembly, calling men slaves and slave-born who were better men
                    than himself and of better birth, and asking if the jail was built for no
                    object. I should certainly say it was, if your father danced his way out of it,
                    fetters and all, at the procession of the Dionysia. All his other outrages it
                    would be impossible to relate; they are too numerous. For all of them taken
                    together you must exact vengeance today, and make an example of him to teach the
                    rest to behave with more restraint. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="section">
                <p>Yes, it may be said, this is the sort of man he was in his public conduct, but
                    there are other things which he has managed with credit. On the contrary, in
                    every respect his behavior towards his fellow-citizens has been such that the
                    story you have heard is the least of the reasons you have for hating him. What
                    do you wish me to mention? How he “repaired” the processional ornaments? How he
                    broke up the crowns? His success as a manufacturer of saucers? Why, for those
                    performances alone, though he had committed no other fraud on the city, it seems
                    to me he deserves not one but three sentences of death; for he is guilty of
                    sacrilege, of impiety, of embezzlement, of every monstrous crime. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="section">
                <p>The greater part of the speech by which he threw dust in your eyes I will leave
                    unnoticed; but, by alleging that the leaves of the crowns were rotten with age
                    and falling off,—as though they were violet-leaves or rose-leaves, not leaves
                    made of gold—he persuaded you to melt them down. And then, in providing for the
                    collection of taxes, he had put in a clause that the public accountant should
                    attend. That was very honest of him; only every taxpayer was certain to check
                    the accounts. But in dealing with the crowns that he was to break up, he left
                    out that very proper regulation; one and the same man was orator, goldsmith,
                    business manager, and auditor of accounts. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="section">
                <p>Now if you, sir, had claimed our entire confidence in all your public business,
                    your dishonesty would not have been equally manifest; but, seeing that in the
                    matter of the taxes you laid down the just principle that the city must trust,
                    not you, but her own servants, and then, when you took up another job and were
                    tampering with the consecrated plate, some of it dedicated before we were born,
                    you forgot to provide the precaution that was taken at your own instance in
                    respect of the tax collection, is it not perfectly clear what you were aiming
                    at? Of course it is. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="section">
                <p>Again, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, consider those
                    glorious and enviable inscriptions that he has obliterated for all time, and the
                    strange and blasphemous inscriptions that he has written in their stead. You
                    all, I suppose, used to see the words written under the circlets of the crowns:
                    “The Allies to the Athenian People for valor and righteousness,” or “The Allies
                    to the Goddess of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, a prize of
                    victory”; or, from the several states of the alliance, “Such-and-such a City to
                    the People by whom they were delivered,” or, “The liberated Euboeans,” for
                    example, “crown the People”; or again,
                        “<persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> from the sea-fight with the
                    Lacedaemonians.” Such, I say, were the inscriptions of the crowns. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="section">
                <p>They were tokens of emulation and honorable ambition; but now they have vanished
                    with the destruction of the crowns, and the saucers which that lewd fellow has
                    had made in their place bear the inscription, “Made by direction of Androtion.”
                    And so the name of a man whom the laws forbid to enter our temples in person
                    because of his prostitution, has been inscribed on the cups in those temples.
                    Just like the old inscriptions, is it not? and an equal incentive to ambition?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="section">
                <p>[;You may, then, mark three scandalous crimes committed by these persons. They
                    have robbed the Goddess of her crowns. They have extinguished in the city that
                    spirit of emulation that sprang from the achievements which the crowns, while in
                    being, commemorated. They have deprived the donors of a great honor,—the credit
                    of gratitude for benefits received. After this long series of evil deeds they
                    have grown so callous and so audacious that they recall those crimes as
                    admirable examples of their administration, so that one of them expects you to
                    acquit him for the sake of the other, and the other sits by his side and does
                    not sink into the ground for shame at his conduct.]; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="section">
                <p>Not only is he lost to shame when money is in question, but he is so dull-witted
                    that he cannot see that crowns are a symbol of merit, but saucers and the like
                    only of wealth; that every crown, how ever small, implies the same regard for
                    honor as if it were large. that drinking-cups and censers, if very numerous,
                    attach to their owners a sort of reputation for wealth, but that, if a man takes
                    pride in trifles, instead of winning some honor by them, he is disdained as a
                    man of vulgar tastes. This man, then, has destroyed the possessions of honor,
                    and made the possessions of wealth mean and unworthy of your dignity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="section">
                <p>There is another thing that he did not understand, that the Athenian democracy,
                    never eager to acquire riches, coveted glory more than any other possession in
                    the world. Here is the proof: once they possessed greater wealth than any other
                    Hellenic people, but they spent it all for love of honor; they laid their
                    private fortunes under contribution, and recoiled from no peril for glory's
                    sake. Hence the People inherits possessions that will never die; on the one hand
                    the memory of their achievements, on the other, the beauty of the memorials set
                    up in their honor, yonder Propylaea, the Parthenon, the porticoes, the
                    docks,—not a couple of jugs, or three or four bits of gold plate, weighing a
                    pound apiece, which you, Androtion, will propose to melt down again, whenever
                    the whim takes you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="section">
                <p>To dedicate those buildings they did not tithe themselves, nor fulfil the
                    imprecations of their enemies by doubling the income-tax, nor was their policy
                    ever guided by such advisers as you. No; they conquered their enemies, they
                    fulfilled the prayers of every sound-hearted man by establishing concord
                    throughout the city; and so they have bequeathed to us their imperishable glory,
                    and excluded from the market-place men whose habits of life were what yours have
                    always been. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="section">
                <p>But you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, have grown so
                    extremely good-natured and pliable, that, with those examples ever before you,
                    you do not imitate them, and Androtion is the repairer of your processional
                    plate. Androtion! Gracious Heavens! Do you think impiety could go further than
                    that? I hold that the man who is to enter the sacred places, to lay hands on the
                    vessels of lustration and the sacrificial baskets, and to become the director of
                    divine worship, ought not to be pure for a prescribed number of days only; his
                    whole life should have been kept pure of the habits that have polluted the life
                    of Androtion.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
