<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Panathenaicus from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg021.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When I was younger, I elected not to write the kind of discourse which deals with
            myths<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introduction p. 22. Yet he deals with
            the legend of Demeter in <bibl n="Isoc. 4">Isoc. 4</bibl> and with that of Heracles in
              <bibl n="Isoc. 5">Isoc. 5</bibl>, and, half playfully, he goes into the stories of
            Helen and Busiris in the discourses devoted to them. See General Introduction.</note>
          nor that which abounds in marvels and fictions,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 10.4">Isoc. 10.4 ff.</bibl>, Vol. III., L.C.L.</note> although the majority
          of people are more delighted with this literature than with that which is devoted to their
          welfare and safety;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.1">Isoc.
              7.1</bibl>.</note> nor did I choose the kind which recounts the ancient deeds and wars
          of the Hellenes, although I am aware that this is deservedly praised,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">One of his pupils, Theopompus, was a historian. For Isocrates' attitude to the
            historians see Blass, <title>Die attische Beredsamkeit</title> 2. p. 49.</note> nor,
          again, that which gives the impression of having been composed in a plain and simple
          manner and is lacking in all the refinements of style,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For
            the plain style affected by the forensic orators, notably Lysias, see Jebb, <title>Attic
              Orators</title>1. pp. 159 ff. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4">Isoc. 4</bibl>.</note> which those
          who are clever at conducting law-suits urge our young men tocultivate, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>especially if they wish to have the advantage over their adversaries.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates despised this kind of writing. See General
            Introduction.</note> No, I left all these to others and devoted my own efforts to giving
          advice on the true interests of Athens and of the rest of the Hellenes,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introduction.</note> writing in a style rich in
          many telling points, in contrasted and balanced phrases not a few,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The Gorgian figures, <term>antithesis</term> and <term>parisosis</term>, which
            Dionysius of <placeName key="tgn,7016142">Halicarnassus</placeName> complained (<bibl
              n="D.H. Isoc. 14">Dion. Hal. Isoc. 14</bibl>) were excessively used in the <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.71">Isoc. 4.71-81</bibl>.</note> and in the other figures of speech which
          give brilliance to oratory<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introduction.</note>
          and compel the approbation and applause of the audience. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now, however, I have completely given up these devices of rhetoric.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">An exaggeration. They abound in this discourse, but his earlier efforts were
            more ornate. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 5.27">Isoc. 5.27-28</bibl>, and <bibl n="Isoc. 15.195"
              >Isoc. 15.195</bibl>.</note> For I do not think it is becoming to the ninety-four
          years which I have lived nor, in general, to men whose hair has at length turned to
            grey<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An echo of <bibl n="Plat. Apol. 17">Plat. Apol.
              17</bibl>.</note> to continue to speak in this fashion, but rather in the manner which
          every man, should he so desire, would hope to command, although no man can easily attain
          it without hard work and close application. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have said this at the beginning in order that if the discourse which is now about to
          be presented to the public should appear to some to be more feeble<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. same apology in <bibl n="Isoc. 5.149">Isoc. 5.149</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.9">Isoc. 15.9</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. L. 6.6">Isoc. Letter
            6.6</bibl>.</note> than those which have been published in former years, they may not
          compare it in the matter of rhetorical variety and finish to my former compositions but
          may judge it in relation to the subject matter which I have deemed appropriate to the
          present occasion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I intend to discuss the achievements of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> and the virtues of our ancestors, although I shall not begin with
          them but with a statement of my personal experience, since it is more urgent, I think, to
          begin with this. For notwithstanding that I strive to live in a manner above reproach and
          without offence to others, I am continually being misrepresented by obscure and worthless
          sophists and being judged by the general public, not by what I really am, but by what they
          hear from others.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.4">Isoc.
              15.4-8</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I wish, therefore, to preface my discussion with a word about myself and about those who
          have this attitude towards me, in order that, if only it lies within my power to do so, I
          may put an end to the abuse of my calumniators and give to the public a clear
          understanding of the work to which I am devoted. For if I succeed in setting forth a true
          picture of this in my discourse, I hope not only that I myself may pass the rest of my
          days free from annoyance but that my present audience will give better attention to the
          discourse which is about to be delivered. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I am not going to hesitate to tell you frankly of the confusion which now comes into my
          thoughts, of the strangeness of my feelings on the present occasion, and of my perplexity
          as to whether I am doing anything to the purpose. For I have had my share of the greatest
          goods of life—the things which all men would pray the gods to have as their portion:<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For the “greatest goods” cf. <bibl n="Plat. Laws 631c">Plat.
              Laws 631c</bibl>; <bibl n="Aristot. Rh. 1.5">Aristot. Rh. 1.5</bibl>; and Herrick's
            rendering of the famous Greek skolion: “Health is the first good lent to men;/A gentle
            disposition then;/Next, to be rich by no by-wayes;/Lastly, with friends t'enjoy our
            dayes.”</note> first of all, I have enjoyed health both of body and of soul, not in
          common degree, but in equal measure with those who have been most blessed in these
            respects;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Bacchyl. Ep. 1.27">Bacchyl. 1.27
              ff.</bibl> (<bibl n="Bacchyl. Ep. 1.55">Bacchyl. 1.55 ff.</bibl>, Jebb's edition):
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">ei) d' u(giei/gas qnato\s e)w\n e)/laxen, zw/ein t' a)p'
              oi)kei/wn e)/xei, prw/tois e)ri/zei</foreign>.</note> secondly, I have been in
          comfortable circumstances, so that I have not lacked for any of the moderate satisfactions
          nor for those that a sensible man would desire; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and, lastly, I have been ranked, not among those who are despised or ignored, but among
          those whom the most cultivated of the Hellenes will recall and talk about as men of
          consequence and worth. And yet, although I have been blessed with all these gifts, some in
          surpassing, others in sufficient measure, I am not content to live on these terms; on the
          contrary, my old age is so morose and captious and discontented that I have oftentimes
          before this found fault with my nature, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>which no other man has contemned, and have deplored my fortune, although I have had no
          complaint against it other than that the philosophy which I have chosen to pursue has been
          the object of unfortunate and unscrupulous attacks.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Such as
            are described at the beginning of the <bibl n="Isoc. 15.">Isoc. 15.</bibl>.</note> As to
          my nature, however, I realized that it was not robust and vigorous enough for public
          affairs and that it was not adequate nor altogether suited to public discourse, and that,
          furthermore, although it was better able to form a correct judgement of the truth of any
          matter than are those who claim to have exact knowledge,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >See General Introduction; <bibl n="Isoc. 13.7">Isoc. 13.7 ff.</bibl></note> yet for
          expounding the truth before an assemblage of many people it was, if I may say so, the
          least competent in all the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I was born more lacking in the two things which have the greatest power in Athens—a
          strong voice and ready assurance<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 5.81"
              >Isoc. 5.81</bibl> and note; <bibl n="Isoc. L. 1.9">Isoc. Letter 1.9 ff.</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. L. 8.7">Isoc. Letter 8.7</bibl>; and <bibl n="Aristoph. Kn. 217">Aristoph.
              Kn. 217 ff.</bibl>: <foreign xml:lang="greek">ta\ d' a)/lla soi pro/sesti dhmagwgika/,
              fwnh\ miara/, ge/gonas kakw=s, a)go/raios ei)=: e)xeis a(/panta pro\s politei/an a(\
              dei=</foreign>.</note>—than, I dare say, any of my fellow-citizens. And those who are
          not endowed with these are condemned to go about in greater obscurity so far as public
          recognition is concerned than those who owe money to the state;<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">An unpaid fine entailed disfranchisement in Athens.</note> for the latter have
          still the hope of paying off the fine assessed against them, whereas the former can never
          change their nature. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet I did not permit these disabilities to dishearten me nor did I allow myself to
          sink into obscurity or utter oblivion, but since I was barred from public life I took
          refuge in study and work and writing down my thoughts, choosing as my field, not petty
          matters nor private contracts, nor the things about which the other orators prate, but the
          affairs of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> and of kings and of
            states.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introduction.</note> Wherefore I
          thought that I was entitled to more honor than the speakers who come before you on the
          platform in proportion as my discourses were on greater and nobler themes than theirs. But
          nothing of the sort has come to pass. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet all men know that the majority of the orators have the audacity to harangue the
          people, not for the good of the state, but for what they themselves expect to gain,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.24">Isoc. 7.24</bibl> and note.</note>
          while I and mine not only abstain more than all others from the public funds but expend
          more than we can afford from our private means on the needs of the commonwealth;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.144">Isoc. 15.144-152</bibl> and
            notes.</note> and they know, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>furthermore, that these orators are either wrangling among themselves<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf., for this contrast between the other orators and himself,
              <bibl n="Isoc. 15.147">Isoc. 15.147-149</bibl>.</note> in the assemblies over deposits
          of money<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For this common cause of controversy see <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.188">Isoc. 4.188</bibl> and note. Such controversies were sometimes
            referred to the General Assembly and there debated and voted upon.</note> or insulting
          our allies<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 12.142">Isoc. 12.142</bibl>
            and <bibl n="Isoc. 15.318">Isoc. 15.318</bibl>.</note> or blackmailing<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.318">Isoc. 15.318</bibl>.</note>
          whosoever of the rest of the world chances to be the object of their attacks, while I, for
          my part, have led the way in discourses which exhort the Hellenes to concord among
          themselves and war against the barbarians </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and which urge that we all unite in colonizing a country so vast and so vulnerable that
          those who have heard the truth about it assert with one accord that if we are sensible and
          cease from our frenzy against each other we can quickly gain possession of it without
          effort and without risk and that this territory will easily accommodate all the people
          among us who are in want of the necessities of life.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            theme of <bibl n="Isoc. 4">Isoc. 4</bibl> and of <bibl n="Isoc. 5">Isoc.
            5</bibl>.</note> And these are enterprises than which, should all the world unite in the
          search, none could be found more honorable or more important or more advantageous to us
          all. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But in spite of the fact that myself and these orators are so far apart in our ways of
          thinking and that I have chosen a field so much more worthy, the majority of people
          estimate us, not in accordance with our merits, but in a confused and altogether
          irrational manner. For they find fault with the character of the popular orators and yet
          put them at the head of affairs and invest them with power over the whole state; and,
          again, they praise my discourses and yet are envious of me personally for no other reason
          than because of these very discourses which they receive with favor. So unfortunately do I
          fare at their hands. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But why wonder at those who are by nature envious of all superior excellence, when
          certain even of those who regard themselves as superior and who seek to emulate me and
          imitate my work are more hostile to me than is the general public? And yet where in the
          world could you find men more reprehensible—for I shall speak my mind even at the risk of
          appearing to some to discourse with more vehemence and rancor than is becoming to my
          age—where, I say, could you find men more reprehensible than these, who are not able to
          put before their students even a fraction of what I have set forth in my teaching but use
          my discourses as models and make their living from so doing, and yet are so far from being
          grateful to me on this account that they are not even willing to let me alone but are
          always saying disparaging things about me? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Nevertheless, as long as they confined themselves to abusing my discourses, reading them
          in the worst possible manner side by side with their own, dividing them at the wrong
          places, mutilating them, and in every way spoiling their effect, I paid no heed to the
          reports which were brought to me, but possessed myself in patience. However, a short time
          before the Great Panathenaia,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Panathenaic festival was
            celebrated in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> each year but with
            special magnificence every fourth year, when it was called the Great Panathenaia.</note>
          they stirred me to great indignation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For some of my friends met me and related to me how, as they were sitting together in the
            Lyceum,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A sacred enclosure on the right bank of the
              <placeName key="tgn,7010825">Ilissus</placeName>, dedicated to Apollo—a gymnasium and
            exercise ground, but was also frequented by philosophers. Here Aristotle and his pupils
            were wont to gather.</note> three or four of the sophists of no repute— men who claim to
          know everything and are prompt to show their presence everywhere—were discussing the
          poets, especially the poetry of Hesiod and Homer, saying nothing original about them, but
          merely chanting their verses and repeating from memory the cleverest things which certain
          others had said about them in the past.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Other sophists made
            much of the study and elucidation of the poets, but there is no evidence that Isocrates
            did. See Blass, <title>Die attische Beredsamkeit</title> 2, pp. 46 ff.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It seems that the bystanders applauded their performance, whereupon one of these
          sophists, the boldest among them, attempted to stir up prejudice against me, saying that I
          hold all such things in contempt and that I would do away with all the learning and the
          teaching of others, and that I assert that all men talk mere drivel except those who
          partake of my instruction. And these aspersions, according to my friends, were effective
          in turning a number of those present against me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now I could not possibly convey to you how troubled and disturbed I was on hearing that
          some accepted these statements as true. For I thought that it was so well known that I was
          waging war against the false pretenders to wisdom and that I had spoken so moderately, nay
          so modestly, about my own powers that no one could be credited for a moment who asserted
          that I myself resorted to such pretensions. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But in truth it was with good reason that I deplored at the beginning of my speech the
          misfortune which has attended me all my life in this respect. For this is the cause of the
          false reports which are spread about me, of the calumny and prejudice which I suffer, and
          of my failure to attain the reputation which I deserve—either that which should be mine by
          common consent or that in which I am held by certain of my disciples who have known me
          through and through. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>However, this cannot now be changed and I must needs put up with what has already come to
          pass. Many things come to my mind, but I am at a loss just what to do. Should I turn upon
          my enemies and denounce those who are accustomed always to speak falsely of me and do not
          scruple to say things which are repugnant to my nature? But if I showed that I took them
          seriously and wasted many words on men whom no one conceives to be worthy of notice I
          should justly be regarded as a simpleton. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Should I, then, ignore these sophists and defend myself against those of the lay public
          who are prejudiced against me, attempting to convince them that it is neither just nor
          fitting for them to feel towards me as they do? But who would not impute great folly to
          me, if, in dealing with men who are hostile to me for no other reason than that I appear
          to have discoursed cleverly on certain subjects, I thought that by speaking just as I have
          spoken in the past I should stop them from taking offence at what I say and should not
          instead add to their annoyance, especially if it should appear that even now at this
          advanced age I have not ceased from “speaking rubbish”? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But neither would anyone, I am sure, advise me to neglect this subject and, breaking off
          in the midst of it, to go on and finish the discourse which I elected to write in my
          desire to prove that our city had been the cause of more blessings to the Hellenes than
          the city of the Lacedaemonians. For if I should now proceed to do this without bringing
          what I have written to any conclusion and without joining the beginning of what is to be
          said to the end of what has been spoken, I should be thought to be no better than those
          who speak in a random, slovenly, and scattering manner whatever comes into their heads to
          say. And this I must guard against. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The best course, therefore, that I can take under all these conditions is to set before
          you what I think about the last attempts<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Obviously he
            resents bitterly some attack upon him in recent years. Possibly it came from the
            “Eristics,” to the value of whose teaching he makes a condescending concession in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.26">Isoc. 12.26</bibl>. These are not the “Eristics” mentioned in
              <title>Against the Sophists</title> (see <bibl n="Isoc. 13.1">Isoc. 13.1-8</bibl> and
            notes), who belong to an earlier period, but those referred to in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.258"
              >Isoc. 15.258</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. L. 5.3">Isoc. Letter 5.3 ff.</bibl>—namely
            Aristotle and his followers who had been hard on Isocrates (see Blass, <title>Die
              attische Beredsamkeit</title> ii. p. 65). This is supported by the fact that the
            critics here referred to frequented the Lyceum. Blass, however (ii. pp. 68, 69), thinks
            that Isocrates has here in mind especially Speusippus.</note> to arouse prejudice
          against me and then proceed to speak on the subject which I had in mind from the first.
          For I think that if I succeed by my writing in bringing out and making clear what my views
          are about education and about the poets, I shall stop my enemies from fabricating false
          charges and speaking utterly at random. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now in fact, so far from scorning the education which was handed down by our ancestors,
          I even commend that which has been set up in our own day—I mean geometry, astronomy, and
          the so-called eristic dialogues,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.265"
              >Isoc. 15.265</bibl> and note.</note> which our young men delight in more than they
          should, although among the older men not one would not declare them insufferable. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, I urge those who are inclined towards these disciplines to work hard and
          apply themselves to all of them, saying that even if this learning can accomplish no other
          good, at any rate it keeps the young out of many other things which are harmful. Nay, I
          hold that for those who are at this age no more helpful or fitting occupation can be found
          than the pursuit of these studies; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but for those who are older and for those who have been admitted to man's estate I assert
          that these disciplines are no longer suitable. For I observe that some of those who have
          become so thoroughly versed in these studies as to instruct others in them fail to use
          opportunely the knowledge which they possess, while in the other activities of life they
          are less cultivated<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introduction.</note> than
          their students—I hesitate to say less cultivated than their servants. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I have the same fault to find also with those who are skilled in oratory and those who
          are distinguished for their writings and in general with all who have superior attainments
          in the arts, in the sciences, and in specialized skill. For I know that the majority even
          of these men have not set their own house in order, that they are insupportable in their
          private intercourse, that they belittle the opinions of their fellow citizens, and that
          they are given over to many other grave offences. So that I do not think that even these
          may be said to partake of the state of culture of which I am speaking. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Whom, then, do I call educated, since I exclude the arts and sciences and specialties?
          First, those who manage well the circumstances which they encounter day by day, and who
          possess a judgement which is accurate in meeting occasions as they arise and rarely misses
          the expedient course of action;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introduction;
              <bibl n="Isoc. 13.3">Isoc. 13.3</bibl>, <bibl n="Isoc. 13.16">Isoc. 13.16</bibl>,
              <bibl n="Isoc. 13.17">Isoc. 13.17</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 15.184">Isoc. 15.184</bibl>,
              <bibl n="Isoc. 15.271">Isoc. 15.271</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>next, those who are decent and honorable in their intercourse with all with whom they
          associate, tolerating easily and good-naturedly what is unpleasant or offensive in others
          and being themselves as agreeable and reasonable to their associates as it is possible to
          be; furthermore, those who hold their pleasures always under control<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 1.21">Isoc. 1.21</bibl> and note; <bibl n="Isoc. 2.29"
              >Isoc. 2.29</bibl>.</note> and are not unduly overcome by their misfortunes,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 1.42">Isoc. 1.42</bibl> and note.</note>
          bearing up under them bravely and in a manner worthy of our common nature; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>finally, and most important of all, those who are not spoiled by successes and do not
          desert their true selves and become arrogant,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.196">Isoc. 12.196-197</bibl>.</note> but hold their ground steadfastly as
          intelligent men, not rejoicing in the good things which have come to them through chance
          rather than in those which through their own nature and intelligence are theirs from their
          birth. Those who have a character which is in accord, not with one of these things, but
          with all of them—these, I contend, are wise and complete men, possessed of all the
          virtues. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> These then are the views which I hold regarding educated men. As to the poetry of Homer
          and Hesiod and the rest, I would fain speak—for I think that I could silence those who
          chant their verses and prate about these poets in the Lyceum—but I perceive that I am
          being carried beyond the due limits which have been assigned to an introduction; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and it behoves a man of taste not to indulge his resourcefulness, when he has more to say
          on a given subject than the other speakers, but to preserve always the element of
          timeliness no matter on what subject he may have occasion to speak—a principle which I
          must observe. Therefore I shall speak on the poets at another time<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">A promise not fulfilled.</note> provided that my age does not first carry me
          off and that I do not have something to say on subjects more important than this. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I shall now proceed to discourse upon the benefactions of <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to the Hellenes, not that I have not sung the
          praises of our city more than all others put together who have written in poetry or
            prose.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.168">Isoc.
            15.168</bibl>.</note> I shall not speak, however, as on former occasions; for then I
          celebrated Athens incidentally to other matters, whereas now Athens herself shall be my
          theme. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But I do not fail to appreciate how great an undertaking this is for me at my time of
          life; on the contrary, I know full well, and have often said,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed"><bibl n="Isoc. 10.13">Isoc. 10.13</bibl>.</note> that while it is easy to
          magnify little things by means of discourse, it is difficult to find terms of praise to
          match deeds of surpassing magnitude and excellence. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, I may not desist on that account from my task, but must carry it through to
          the end, if indeed I am enabled to live to do so, especially since many considerations
          impel me to write upon this theme myself: first, is the fact that some are in the habit of
          recklessly denouncing our city; second, that while some have praised her gracefully, they
          have lacked appreciation of their theme and treated it inadequately; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>furthermore, that others have not scrupled rather to glorify her, not in human terms, but
          so extravagantly as to arouse the hostility of many against them; and, lastly, there is
          the fact of my present age, which is such as to deter others from such an undertaking. For
          I am hopeful that if I succeed I shall obtain a greater reputation than that which I now
          have, whereas if it turns out that I speak indifferently well, my hearers will make
          generous allowance for my years. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have now finished what I wished to say by way of prelude<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Rh. 3.14">Aristot. Rh. 3.14</bibl>, where he compares
            the prooemium of a speech to the prelude of a flute player.</note> about myself and
          others, like a chorus, as it were, before the contest. But I think that those who wish to
          be exact and just in praising any given state ought not to confine themselves alone to the
          state which they single out, but even as we examine purple and gold and test them by
          placing them side by side with articles of similar appearance and of the same estimated
          value, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>so also in the case of states one should compare, not those which are small with those
          which are great, nor those which are always subject to others with those which are wont to
          dominate others, nor those which stand in need of succor with those which are able to give
          it, but rather those which have similar powers, and have engaged in the same deeds and
          enjoyed a like freedom of action. For thus one may best arrive at the truth. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If, then, one views Athens in this light and compares her, not with any city chosen at
          random, but with the city of the Spartans, which most people praise moderately while
            some<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The oligarchical party in Athens, generally, admired
            Spartan institutions. Among writers, Xenophon especially (see <bibl
              n="Xen. Const. Lac. 1">Xen. Const. Lac.</bibl>) was emphatic in his praise of them.
            The Athenian philosophers, also, were wont to contrast the rigor and discipline of the
            Spartan with the slackness of the Athenian ways of life. See <bibl n="Isoc. 3.24">Isoc.
              3.24</bibl> and note.</note> extol her as though the demigods had there governed the
          state, then Athens, in her power, in her deeds and in her benefactions to the Hellenes,
          will be seen to have outdistanced <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> more
          than <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> the rest of the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Of the ancient struggles which they have undergone in behalf of the Hellenes, I shall
          speak hereafter.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">He does so in <bibl n="Isoc. 12.191">Isoc.
              12.191 ff.</bibl></note> Now, however, I shall begin with the time when the
          Lacedaemonians conquered the cities of <placeName key="tgn,7002733"
            >Achaea</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the northern <placeName
              key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>. For the Dorian Invasion of the <placeName
              key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> see Grote, <title>History of <placeName
                key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName></title> vol.2, pp. 2 ff. Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 6.16">Isoc. 6.16 ff.</bibl></note> and divided their territory with the
          Argives and the Messenians; for it is fitting to begin discussing them at this point. Now
          our ancestors will be seen to have preserved without ceasing the spirit of concord towards
          the Hellenes and of hatred towards the barbarians which they inherited from the Trojan War
          and to have remained steadfast in this policy. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>First they took the islands of the <placeName key="tgn,7011270"
            >Cyclades</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the campaigns of the so-called
            “Ionian Migration.” See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.34">Isoc. 4.34 ff.</bibl></note> about which
          there had been much contention during the overlordship of Minos of <placeName
            key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> and which finally were occupied by the Carians,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Hdt. 1.171">Hdt. 1.171</bibl>.</note> and, having
          driven out the latter, refrained from appropriating the lands of these islands for
          themselves, but instead settled upon them those of the Hellenes who were most lacking in
          means of subsistence. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And after this, they founded many great cities on both continents,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed"><placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and Asia—north and south of
            the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>.</note> swept the barbarians
          back from the sea, and taught the Hellenes in what way they should manage their own
          countries and against whom they should wage war in order to make <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> great. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The Lacedaemonians, on the other hand, about the same time were so far from carrying out
          the same policy as our ancestors—from waging war on the barbarians and benefiting the
          Hellenes—that they were not even willing to refrain from aggression, but although they
          held an alien city and a territory not only adequate but greater than any other city of
            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> possessed, they were not satisfied with
          what they had; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>on the contrary, having learned from the actual course of events that while according to
          law states and territories are deemed to belong to those who have duly and lawfully
          acquired them, in fact, however, they fall into the hands of those who are most practised
          in the art of warfare and are able to conquer their enemies in battle—thinking upon these
          things, they neglected agriculture and the arts and everything else and did not cease
          laying siege to the cities in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>
          one by one and doing violence to them until they overthrew them all with the exception of
            <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the
            Spartan Conquest of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> see Grote,
              <title>History of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> 2</title>, pp. 418
            ff.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And so it resulted from the policy which we pursued that <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName> waxed great, <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> became
          stronger than Asia, and, furthermore, the Hellenes who were in straitened circumstances
          received cities and lands, while the barbarians who were wont to be insolent were expelled
          from their own territory and humbled in their pride; whereas the results of the Spartan
          policy were that their city alone became strong, dominated all the cities in the
            <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, inspired fear in the other
          states, and was courted by them for her favor. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In justice, however, we should praise the city which has been the author of many
          blessings to the rest of the world but should reprehend the state which is ever striving
          to effect its own advantage; and we should cultivate the friendship of those who do by
          others just as they do by themselves, but should abhor and shun those who feel the utmost
          degree of self-love, while governing their state in a spirit inimical and hostile to the
          world at large. Such was the beginning made by each of these two states. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But at a later time, when the Persian War took place<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For
            conduct of Athens and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> in the Persian
            Wars, 49-52, compare <bibl n="Isoc. 4.71">Isoc. 4.71-74</bibl>, 85-98.</note>(Xerxes,
          who was then king, having gathered together a fleet of thirteen hundred triremes and a
          land force numbering five millions in all, including seven hundred thousand fighting men,
          and led this vast force<note anchored="true" resp="ed">“An innumerable army” in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.93">Isoc. 4.93</bibl>.</note> against the Hellenes), </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>the Spartans, although they were masters of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName>, contributed to the sea-fight which determined the issue of
          the whole war only ten triremes, whereas our ancestors, although they were homeless,
          having abandoned Athens<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.96">Isoc.
              4.96</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 6.43">Isoc. 6.43</bibl>.</note> because the city had not
          been fortified with walls at that time, furnished not only a greater number of ships, but
          ships with a greater fighting force, than all the rest combined who fought together in
          that battle.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.98">Isoc. 4.98</bibl>,
            note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Again, the Lacedaemonians contributed to this battle the leadership of Eurybiades, who,
          had he carried into effect what he intended to do, could have been prevented by nothing in
          the world from bringing destruction upon the Hellenes, whereas the Athenians furnished
          Themistocles, who, by the common assent of all, was credited with being responsible for
          the victorious outcome of that battle as well as for all the other successes which were
          achieved during that time.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.98">Isoc.
              4.98</bibl>. Erybiades and the Peloponnesians generally, including <placeName
              key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, favored the removal of the fleet from
              <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName> to the Isthmus of <placeName
              key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>. Themistocles thwarted this retreat. <bibl
              n="Hdt. 8.57">Hdt. 8.57 ff.</bibl> The account in <bibl n="Plut. Them. 1">Plut.
              Them.</bibl> is closer to that of Isocrates.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And the greatest proof of this is that those who then fought together took the hegemony
          away from the Lacedaemonians and conferred it upon our ancestors.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.72">Isoc. 4.72</bibl>.</note> And yet what more competent
          or trustworthy judges could one find of what then took place than those who had a part in
          those very struggles? And what benefaction could one mention greater than that which was
          able to save all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now after these events it came about that each of these cities in turn gained the empire
          of the sea<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For contrast between the empire of Athens and
            that of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, 53-61, compare <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.104">Isoc. 4.104 ff.</bibl></note>—a power such that whichever state
          possesses it holds in subjection most of the states of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.16">Isoc.
              4.16</bibl>.</note> As to their use of this power in general, I commend neither Athens
          nor <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>; for one might find many faults
          with both. Nevertheless, in this supervision<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Here is the
            inoffensive word <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)pime/leia</foreign>, supervision, to convey
            the feeling that the empire of Athens cared for the interests of the confederate
            states.</note> the Athenians surpassed the Lacedaemonians no less than in the deeds
          which I have just mentioned. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For our fathers tried to persuade their allies to establish the very same polity in their
          cities as they themselves had continually cherished;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
              <bibl n="Isoc. 4.104">Isoc. 4.104-106</bibl>.</note> and it is a sign of good will and
          friendship when any people urge it upon others to use those institutions which they
          conceive to be beneficial to themselves. The Lacedaemonians, on the other hand, set up in
          their subject states a polity which resembled neither that which obtained among themselves
          nor those which have existed anywhere else in the world; nay, they vested in ten men<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For these “decarchies” and their misrule see <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.110">Isoc. 4.110-114</bibl>.</note> alone the government of each of the
          states—men of such a character that were one to attempt to denounce them for three or four
          days without pause he would appear to have covered not a fraction of the wrongs which have
          been perpetrated by them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>To attempt to review these wrongs in detail were foolish; they are so many and so grave.
          Were I a younger man, I might perhaps have found means to characterize all of their crimes
          in a few words which would have stirred in my hearers an indignation commensurate with the
          gravity of the things which these men have done; but as it is, no such words occur to me
          other than those which are on the lips of all men, namely, that they so far outdid all
          those who lived before their time in lawlessness and greed that they not only ruined
          themselves and their friends and their own countries but also brought the Lacedaemonians
          into evil repute with their allies and plunged them into misfortunes so many and so grave
          as no one could have dreamed would ever be visited upon them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> You can see at once from this instance best of all how much milder and more moderate we
          were in our supervision over the affairs of the Hellenes, but you can see it also from
          what I shall now say. The Spartans remained at the head of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName> hardly ten years,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates elsewhere
            views the Spartan supremacy as lasting from the end of the Peloponnesian War, <date
              from="-0405" to="-0404">405-404 B.C.</date>, to the battle of Leuctra, <date
              when="-0371">371 B.C.</date> See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.47">Isoc. 5.47</bibl>. But later in
              <bibl n="Isoc. 5.63">Isoc. 5.63-64</bibl> he speaks of Conon's naval victory at the
            battle of <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>, <date when="-0394">394
              B.C.</date>, as the end of the Spartan rule, since it re-established the maritime
            influence of Athens. The latter is the version followed here. It is reasonable to say
            that <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>'s supremacy by sea ceased with
            the battle of <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName> and her supremacy by land
            with Leuctra.</note> while we held the hegemony without interruption for sixty-five
            years.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.106">Isoc. 4.106</bibl>,
            note.</note> And yet it is known to all that states which come under the supremacy of
          others remain loyal for the longest time to those under which they suffer the least degree
          of oppression. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now both Athens and <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> incurred the
          hatred of their subjects and were plunged into war and confusion, but in these
          circumstances it will be found that our city, although attacked by all the Hellenes and by
          the barbarians as well, was able to hold out against them for ten years,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The last decade of the Peloponnesian War, from what he terms
            the Decelean War, <date when="-0413">413 B.C.</date> (see <bibl n="Isoc. 8.37">Isoc.
              8.37</bibl>, 84, note.), to the fall of Athens <date from="-0404" to="-0403"
              >404-403 B.C.</date></note> while the Lacedaemonians, though still the leading
          power by land, after waging war against the Thebans alone and being defeated in a single
            battle,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Leuctra, <date when="-0371">371
            B.C.</date></note> were stripped of all the possessions which they had held and involved
          in misfortunes and calamities which were very similar to these which overtook
            ourselves.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.105">Isoc.
            8.105</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>More than that, our city recovered her power in less years than it took to overthrow it,
          while the Spartans after their defeat at Leuctra have not been able even in a period many
          times as long to regain the position from which they fell, but are even now<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Under the Peace of Antalcidas. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.115">Isoc.
              4.115</bibl>, note.</note> no better off than they were then. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Again, I must set forth how these two cities demeaned themselves toward the
            barbarians;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Compare the treatment of this topic in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.100">Isoc. 4.100-132</bibl>.</note> for this still remains to be done. In
          the time of our supremacy, the barbarians were prevented from marching with an army beyond
          the <placeName key="tgn,6002441">Halys river</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.144">Isoc. 4.144</bibl>.</note> and from sailing with their ships
          of war this side of Phaselis,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.118"
              >Isoc. 4.118</bibl>, <bibl n="Isoc. 7.80">Isoc. 7.80</bibl>, note.</note> but under
          the hegemony of the Lacedaemonians not only did they gain the freedom to march and sail
          wherever they pleased, but they even became masters over many Hellenic states. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Well then, does not the city which made the nobler and prouder covenants with the Persian
          king, which brought to pass the most and the greatest injuries to the barbarians and
          benefits to the Hellenes, which, furthermore, seized from her foes the sea-coast of Asia
          and much other territory besides and appropriated it to her allies, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>which put an end to the insolence of the barbarians and the poverty of the Hellenes, and
          which, besides, waged war in her own cause more capably than that city which is famed for
          her skill in warfare, and extricated herself from her misfortunes more quickly than these
          same Lacedaemonians—does not this city, I say, deserve to be praised and honored more than
          the state which has been outdistanced by her in all these respects? This, then, is what I
          had in mind to say on this occasion in comparing the achievements of Athens and <placeName
            key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> and the wars which they fought at the same time
          and against the same adversaries. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But I think that, while those who find these words distasteful to listen to will not deny
          that what I have said is the truth nor, again, will they be able to cite other activities
          of the Lacedaemonians through which they brought to pass many blessings to the Hellenes,
          yet they will attempt— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>as is ever their habit—to denounce our city, to recount the most offensive acts which
          transpired while she held the empire of the sea, to present in a false light the
          adjudication of lawsuits in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> for the
            allies<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Members of the Confederacy of <placeName
              key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> had to bring certain lawsuits, especially those
            which involved disloyalty to the league in any way, to Athens for trial. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.113">Isoc. 4.113</bibl>, note.</note> and her collection of tribute<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.2">Isoc. 7.2</bibl>, note.</note> from
          them, and above all to dwell on the cruelties suffered at her hands by the Melians and the
          Scionians and the Toronians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the treatment of
              <placeName key="tgn,7010922">Melos</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Scione"
              >Scione</placeName> see <bibl n="Isoc. 4.100">Isoc. 4.100</bibl>, note, and 109.
              <placeName key="perseus,Torone">Torone</placeName> was captured by Cleon in <date
              when="-0422">422 B.C.</date> The men of the town were sent as prisoners to Athens, and
            the women and children sold into slavery (<bibl n="Thuc. 5.3">Thuc. 5.3</bibl>).</note>
          thinking by these reproaches to sully the benefactions of Athens which I have just
          described. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now I, for my part, could not gainsay all the things which might justly be said against
          our city, nor would I attempt to do so; for I should be ashamed, as I have already said in
          another place,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In <bibl n="Isoc. L. 2.16">Isoc. Letter
              2.16</bibl>.</note> when all other men are of the opinion that not even the gods are
          free from guilt, were I to strain my conscience and attempt to persuade you that our
          commonwealth has never erred in any instance whatsoever. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, I think I shall do one thing, namely, show that the city of the Spartans,
          in handling situations such as I have mentioned, has been much more harsh and severe than
          Athens, and that those who seek to promote the reputation of the Spartans by calumniating
          us are short-sighted in the extreme and are themselves to blame for the bad repute which
          their own friends<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, the Spartans.</note> incur at
          our hands. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For whenever they make such charges against us, to which the Lacedaemonians are more open
          than ourselves, we do not find it difficult to cite against <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> a graver offence in each case than that which
          has been charged against <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. For example,
          in the present instance, if they bring up the fact that the law-suits of the allies were
          tried in Athens, is there anyone so slow of wit as not to find the ready retort that the
          Lacedaemonians have put to death without trial more of the Hellenes<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.113">Isoc. 4.113</bibl>, note.</note> than have ever been
          brought to trial and judgement here since the founding of our city? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And if they make any complaint about our collection of the tribute, we shall be ready
          with a like rejoinder. For we shall show that our ancestors far more than the
          Lacedaemonians acted for the advantage of the states which paid them tribute. For, in the
          first place, these states did this, not because we had so commanded, but because they
          themselves had so resolved at the very time when they conferred upon us the supremacy by
          sea. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In the next place, they paid their quotas, not to preserve Athens, but to preserve their
          own democratic polity and their own freedom and to escape falling into such great
          misfortunes, through the setting up of oligarchies, as were suffered under the decarchies
          and the domination of the Lacedaemonians. And, more than that, they paid these
          contributions, not from funds which they had treasured up through their own efforts, but
          from resources which they possessed through our aid.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            account here given of the Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos"
              >Delos</placeName> is a fair statement. It was in its origin a voluntary association
            of the Ionian Greeks, partly against <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>,
            but mainly against the Persian Empire, not for protection merely, but for the enrichment
            of its members at the expense of the barbarians. Each member contributed its quota to
            the common cause, the more powerful members in ships the weaker in money, <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">fo/ros</foreign>. The quotas appear to have been fixed by Aristides,
            although approved by the synod of the allies. See <bibl n="Thuc. 5.18">Thuc.
            5.18</bibl>; <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 23">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 23-24</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="69" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In return for these resources, had they reflected in the slightest degree, they should in
          all fairness have been grateful to us; for we took over their cities in some instances
          when they had been utterly destroyed, in others when they had been sacked and plundered by
          the barbarians, and advanced them to such a state of prosperity that although they
          contributed to us a slight proportion of the wealth which flowed in upon them, their
          estates were no less prosperous than those of the Peloponnesians who paid no tribute
          whatsoever. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="70" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Furthermore, as to the cities which were laid waste under the rule of each of these
          states—a matter for which certain men reproach the Athenians alone—we shall show that
          things much more reprehensible were done by those whom these men are never weary of
          extolling. For it happened that we offended against islets so small and insignificant that
          many of the Hellenes do not even know of their existence, whereas the Lacedaemonians laid
          waste the greatest cities of the Peloponnesus—states which in every way were eminent above
          the others— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="71" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and now hold for themselves the wealth of those states which, even supposing that in
          former times they possessed no merit, deserved the greatest possible rewards from the
          Hellenes because of the expedition against <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>
          in which they took the foremost place and furnished as its leaders men possessed not only
          of the virtues in which many of the common run of mankind have a part, but also of those
          in which no ignoble man may share. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="72" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> furnished Nestor, the wisest of
          all who lived in those times; <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>,
          Menelaus, who because of his moderation and his justice was the one man to be deemed
          worthy to become the son-in-law of Zeus;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Helen, the wife of
            Menelaus, was the daughter of Zeus. See <bibl n="Hom. Od. 4.569">Hom. Od. 4.569</bibl>
            and <bibl n="Isoc. 10.16">Isoc. 10.16</bibl>.</note> and <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
            >Argos</placeName>, Agamemnon, who was possessed, not of one or two of the virtues
          merely, but of all which anyone can name— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="73" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and these, not in moderate, but in surpassing degree. For we shall find that no one in
          all the world has ever undertaken deeds more distinctive, more noble, more important, more
          advantageous to the Hellenes, or deserving of higher praise. These are facts which, when
          thus barely enumerated, some may not unreasonably question, but when they have been
          supported in each instance by a few words, all men will acknowledge that I speak the
          truth. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="74" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> However, I am not able to see clearly, but am in doubt, with what words I may proceed
          without making an error of judgement. For, on the one hand, I am ashamed, after having
          said so much about the virtue of Agamemnon, to make no mention of the things which he
          accomplished and so to seem to my hearers no different from men who make empty boasts and
          say whatever comes into their heads. But I observe, on the other hand, that the discussion
          of things which lie outside the scope of the subject<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Digressions such as the praise of Theseus in <bibl n="Isoc. 10">Isoc. 10</bibl> and of
            Timotheus in <bibl n="Isoc. 15">Isoc. 15</bibl> are effective elements of variety. the
            praise of Agamemnon here seems awkwardly dragged in. It is commonly thought that
            Agamemnon is a masque for Philip of <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>.
            (See, for example, Blass, <title>Die attische Beredsamkeit 2</title>, pp. 331, 334.) The
            simplest explanation, however, is hinted at in <bibl n="Isoc. 12.76">Isoc. 12.76</bibl>.
            Agamemnon stood out in his mind as the first leader of all <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
              >Hellas</placeName> against the East—the first champion of the cause to which
            Isocrates dedicated his life.</note> is not approved but is thought rather to be
          confusing, and that while many misuse these digressions there are many more who condemn
          them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="75" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore I fear that I too may subject myself to some such criticism. Nevertheless, I
          elect to lend support to the man who has experienced the same misadventure as myself and
          many others and failed of the reputation he deserved, and who has been the author of the
          greatest services to the world of his time, albeit he is less praised than those who have
          done nothing worthy of mention. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="76" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For what element of glory did he lack who won a position of such exalted honor that,
          were all the world to unite on the search for a greater, no greater could be found? For he
          is the only man who was ever deemed worthy to be the leader of the armies of all
            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>. Whether he was elected by all or
          obtained this honor by himself, I am not able to say. But however this came about, he left
          no room for the rest of mankind who have in any wise won distinction since his time to
          surpass the glory which attaches to his name. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="77" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And when he obtained this power, he harmed no city of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>; nay, so far was he from injuring any one of them that, although he
          took command of the Hellenes when they were in a state of mutual warfare and confusion and
          great misfortune, he delivered them from this condition, and, having established concord
          among them, indifferent to all exploits which are extravagant and spectacular and of no
          benefit to others, he collected the Hellenes into an army and led them forth against the
          barbarians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="78" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And no one will be found, among those who rose to fame in his time or in later
          generations, to have accomplished an expedition more honorable than this or more
          advantageous to the Hellenes. But although he achieved all this and set this example to
          the rest of the world, he did not receive the fame which was his due, because of those who
          delight more in stage-play than in services and in fiction than in truth; nay, albeit he
          proved himself so great, he has a reputation which is less than that of men who have not
          ventured even to imitate his example. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="79" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But not for these things alone might one extol him, but also for the things he did at
          the same time. For he conceived of his mission in terms so lofty that he was not satisfied
          with making up his army from all the men in private station whom he desired to have from
          each of the cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, but even persuaded
          men of the rank of kings, who were accustomed to do in their own states whatsoever they
          pleased and to give orders to the world at large, to place themselves under his command,
          to follow him against whomsoever he might lead them, to obey his orders, to abandon their
          royal manner of living and to share the life of soldiers in the field, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="80" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and, furthermore, to imperil themselves and wage war, not for their own countries and
          kingdoms, but ostensibly for Helen, wife of Menelaus, though in reality for <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 10.51">Isoc. 10.51</bibl>.</note> that she might not again suffer such an
          outrage at the hands of the barbarians nor such as befell her before that time in the
          seizure of the entire <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> by Pelops or
          of <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> by Danaus or of <placeName
            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> by Cadmus.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >According to legend, Pelops, the Phrygian, settled in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
              >Peloponnesus</placeName> and gave his name to that territory; Cadmus, the Phoenician,
            founded <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>; Danaus, the Egyptian, became
            king of Argos—types of foreign invasion and conquest.</note> For what other man in the
          world will be found to have had forethought in these matters or to have taken measures to
          prevent any such misfortune in the future except one of Agamemnon's character and power?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="81" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> There is, moreover, connected with the above achievement one which, though less
          significant than those which I have mentioned, is more important and more deserving of
          mention than those which have been extolled again and again. For he commanded an army
          which had come together from all the cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>, a host whose size may be imagined since it contained many of the
          descendants of the gods and of the direct sons of the gods<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 10.52">Isoc. 10.52</bibl>.</note>—men who were not of the same
          temper as the majority of mankind nor on the same plane of thinking, but full of pride and
          passion and envy and ambition—, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="82" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and yet he held that army together for ten years, not by great bribes nor by outlays of
          money, by which means all rulers nowadays maintain their power,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Mercenary armies were now commonly relied upon even in <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.44">Isoc. 8.44
              ff.</bibl></note> but by the supremacy of his genius, by his ability to provide from
          the enemy subsistence for his soldiers, and most of all by his reputation of being better
          advised in the interest of others than others in their own interest. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="83" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But the final achievement by which he crowned all these is no less worthy of admiration.
          For he will be found to have done nothing unseemly or unworthy of these exploits which I
          have already described; on the contrary, although he waged war, ostensibly against a
          single city, but in reality not only against all the peoples who dwelt in <placeName
            key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> but also against many other races of the barbarians,
          he did not give up fighting nor depart for home before reducing to slavery the city of him
          who had offended against <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName><note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Paris, who carried off Helen, the wife of Menelaus.</note> and
          putting an end to the insolence of the barbarians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="84" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I am well aware of the space which I have given to the praises of Agamemnon's virtue; I
          am well aware also that if any of you should go over these one by one, many as they are,
          to see what might be rejected, no one would venture to subtract a single word, and yet I
          know that when they are read one after the other, all will criticize me for having said
          much more than I should. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="85" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For my part, if I inadvertently prolonged this topic I should be ashamed of being so
          lacking in perception when discoursing on a subject which no one has even ventured to
          discuss. But in fact I knew much better than those who will dare to take me to task that
          many will criticize this excess. I considered, however, that it would be less
          objectionable to be thought by some to disregard due measure in this part of my discourse
          than to leave out, in speaking of such a man, any of the merits which belong to him and
          which it behoves me to mention. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="86" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I thought also that I should be applauded by the most cultivated of my hearers if I could
          show that I was more concerned when discoursing on the subject of virtue about doing
          justice to the theme than about the symmetry of my speech and that too, knowing well that
          the lack of due proportion in my speech would detract from my own reputation, while just
          appreciation of their deeds would enhance the fame of those whose praises I sing.
          Nevertheless I bade farewell to expediency and chose justice instead. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="87" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And you will find that I am of this mind not only in what I am now saying but likewise
          upon all occasions, since it will be seen that I take more pleasure in those of my
          disciples who are distinguished for the character of their lives and deeds than in those
          who are reputed to be able speakers. And yet when they speak well, all men will assign the
          credit to me, even though I contribute nothing to what they say, whereas when they act
          right no man will fail to commend the doer of the deed even though all the world may know
          that it was I who advised him what to do.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">these last two
            paragraphs show striking use of antithesis and parisosis—devices of rhetoric which at
            the beginning of this discourse he pretends to have outgrown. See <bibl n="Isoc. 12.2"
              >Isoc. 12.2</bibl> and note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="88" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I do not know whither I am drifting.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For this
            rhetorical doubt cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.310">Isoc. 15.310</bibl>.</note> For, because I
          think all the time that I must add the point which logically follows what I have said
          before, I have wandered entirely from my subject. There is, therefore, nothing left for me
          to do but to crave indulgence to old age for my forgetfulness and prolixity—faults which
          are wont to be found in men of my years—and go back to the place from which I fell into
          this garrulous strain. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="89" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I think that I now see the point from which I strayed. I was speaking in reply to
          those who reproach us with the misfortunes of the Melians and of villages with like
          populations, not meaning that we had done no wrong in these instances, but trying to show
          that those who are the idols of these speakers have laid waste more and greater cities
          than the Athenians have done, in which connection I discussed the virtues of Agamemnon and
          Menelaus and Nestor, saying nothing that was not true, though passing, mayhap, the bounds
          of moderation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="90" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But I did this, supposing that it would be apparent that there could be no greater crime
          than that of those who dared lay waste the cities which bred and reared such great men,
          about whom even now one might say many noble things. But it is perhaps foolish to linger
          upon a single point, as if there were any lack, as if there were not, on the contrary, a
          superabundance of things to say about the cruelty and the harshness of the Lacedaemonians.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="91" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For the Lacedaemonians were not satisfied with wronging these cities and men of this
          character, but treated in the same way those who had set out with them from the same
          country, joined with them in the same expedition, and shared with them the same
            perils<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the Trojan War.</note>—I mean the Argives and
          the Messenians. For they determined to plunge these also into the very same misfortunes
          which had been visited upon their former victims.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            distinction—not altogether clear—is between the older and the later inhabitants.</note>
          They did not cease laying siege to the Messenians until they had driven them from their
          territory, and with the same object they are even now making war upon the Argives.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For the conquest of <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
              >Messene</placeName> see <bibl n="Isoc. 6.26">Isoc. 6.26 ff.</bibl> The Spartans and
            Argives were almost always at war. See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.51">Isoc. 5.51</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="92" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, it would be strange if, having spoken of these wrongs, I failed to mention
          their treatment of the Plataeans. It was on the soil of <placeName key="perseus,Plataea"
            >Plataea</placeName> that the Lacedaemonians had encamped with us and with the other
          allies, drawn up for battle against our enemies;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The battle
            of <placeName key="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName> was the final, decisive battle
            of the Persian Wars.</note> there they had offered sacrifices to the deities worshipped
          by the Plataeans;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Thuc. 2.71-72">Thuc.
              2.71-72</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="93" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and there we had won freedom, not only for the Hellenes who fought with us, but also for
          those who were compelled to be on the side of the Persians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The Greek cities on the Asiatic seaboard, which had been subject to <placeName
              key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>.</note> and we accomplished this with the help of
          the Plataeans, who alone of the Boeotians fought with us in that war.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The Thebans had “Medized.” The Plataeans in this battle acquitted themselves
            well; according to Plutarch (<bibl n="Plut. Arist. 20">Plut. Arist. 20</bibl>), they
            were awarded the meed of valor. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 14.57">Isoc. 14.57 ff.</bibl></note>
          And yet, after no great interval of time, the Lacedaemonians, to gratify <placeName
            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 14.62">Isoc. 14.62</bibl>.</note> reduced the Plataeans by siege and put them
          all to the sword with the exception of those who had been able to escape through their
            lines.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This was done by King Archidamus, who in the
            course of the Peloponnesian War besieged and took <placeName key="perseus,Plataea"
              >Plataea</placeName>, 427 b.c. The walls of the town were razed, the women and
            children sold into slavery, the defenders slain, excepting some two hundred who escaped
            and found refuge in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. See <bibl
              n="Thuc. 3.57">Thuc. 3.57 ff.</bibl></note> Little did Athens resemble <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> in the treatment of these peoples; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="94" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for, while the Lacedaemonians did not scruple to commit such wrongs both against the
          benefactors of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> and against their own
            kinsmen,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Fellow-Dorians.</note> our ancestors, on the
          other hand, gave the surviving Messenians a home in <placeName key="tgn,7011174"
            >Naupactus</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed">On the Corinthian gulf. For this
            event see <bibl n="Thuc. 1.103">Thuc. 1.103</bibl></note> and adopted the Plataeans who
          had escaped with their lives as Athenian citizens and shared with them all the privileges
          which they themselves enjoyed.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4">Isoc.
              4</bibl>, note.</note> So that if we had nothing else to say about these two cities,
          it is easy to judge from these instances what was the character of each and which of the
          two laid waste more and greater cities. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="95" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I perceive that my feelings are changing to the opposite of those which I described a
          little while ago. For then I fell into a state of doubt and perplexity and forgetfulness,
          but now I realize clearly that I am not keeping the mildness of speech which I had when I
          began to write my discourse; on the contrary, I am venturing to discuss matters about
          which I did not think that I should speak, I am more aggressive in temper than is my wont,
          and I am losing control over some of the things which I utter because of the multitude of
          things which rush into my mind to say. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="96" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Since, however, the impulse has come to me to speak frankly and I have removed the curb
          from my tongue, and since I took a subject which is of such a character that it is neither
          honorable nor possible to leave out the kind of facts from which it can be proved that our
          city has been of greater service to the Hellenes than <placeName key="tgn,7011065"
            >Lacedaemon</placeName>, I must not be silent either about the other wrongs which have
          not yet been told, albeit they have been done among the Hellenes, but must show that our
          ancestors have been slow pupils<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 12.101"
              >Isoc. 12.101</bibl>.</note> in wrong-doing, whereas the Lacedaemonians have in some
          respects been the first to point the way and in others have been the sole offenders. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="97" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now most people upbraid both cities because, while pretending that they risked the
          perils of war against the barbarians for the sake of the Hellenes, they did not in fact
          allow the various states to be independent and manage their own affairs in whatever way
          was expedient for each of them, but, on the contrary, divided them up, as if they had
          taken them captive in war, and reduced them all to slavery, acting no differently than
          those who rob others of their slaves, on the pretext of liberating them, only to compel
          them to slave for their new masters. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="98" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But it is not the fault of the Athenians that these complaints are made and many others
          more bitter than these, but rather of those who now in what is being said, as in times
          past in all that has been done, have been in the opposite camp from us. For no man can
          show that our ancestors during the countless years of our early history ever attempted to
          impose our rule over any city great or small, whereas all men know that the
          Lacedaemonians, from the time when they entered the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName>, have had no other object in their deeds or in their designs
          than to impose their rule if possible over all men but, failing that, over the peoples of
          the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="99" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And as to the stirring up of faction and slaughter and revolution in these cities, which
          certain critics impute both to Athens and to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
            >Sparta</placeName>, you will find that the Lacedaemonians have filled all the states,
          excepting a very few, with these misfortunes and afflictions,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.114">Isoc. 4.114</bibl>.</note> whereas no one would dare
          even to allege that our city, before the disaster which befell her in the <placeName
            key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At <placeName
              key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>, 405 b.c. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.119">Isoc.
              4.119</bibl>.</note> ever perpetrated such a thing among her allies. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="100" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But when the Lacedaemonians, after having been in the position of dictators over the
          Hellenes, were being driven from control of affairs—at that juncture, when the other
          cities were rent by faction, two or three of our generals (I will not hide the truth from
          you) mistreated some of them, thinking that if they should imitate the deeds of Spartans
          they would be better able to control them.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See, however,
            Isocrates' bitter attack upon the Athenian militaristic policy in <title>On the
              Peace</title>, especially <bibl n="Isoc. 8.44">Isoc. 8.44</bibl>. Among the Athenian
            generals, he is here thinking mainly of Chares (the enemy and opposite of his friend and
            pupil, Timotheus. See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.129">Isoc. 15.129</bibl> and note), who seems to
            have uniformly preferred force to persuasion or conciliation in the treatment of the
            Athenian allies. See Introduction to <bibl n="Isoc. 8">Isoc. 8</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="101" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore all may justly charge the Lacedaemonians with having been the instigators and
          teachers of such deeds, but may with good reason make allowance for us, as for pupils who
          have been deceived by the false promises of their tutors and disappointed in their
          expectations. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="102" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I come now finally to those offences which they alone and by themselves committed.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, conduct of the Spartans which has no parallel in
            Athenian history. Compare, for the contrast here drawn between <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and Athens in their feeling for the
            barbarians, <bibl n="Isoc. 4.156">Isoc. 4.156-159</bibl>, 120, 121.</note> Who does not
          know that the Spartans, notwithstanding that they and we harbor in common a feeling of
          hatred towards the barbarians and their kings, and notwithstanding that the Athenians,
          although beset by many wars and involved at times in great disasters, their territory
          being often ravaged and cut off by the enemy,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the
            Peloponnesian War.</note> never once turned their eyes towards friendship and alliance
          with the barbarians, but continued steadfastly to cherish a stronger hatred against them
          because of what they plotted against the Hellenes than we feel towards those who now seek
          to injure Athens— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="103" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>who does not know, I say, that the Spartans, although untroubled by any evil or even by
          any prospect or fear of evil, advanced to such a pitch of greed that they were not
          satisfied to hold the supremacy by land, but were so greedy to obtain also the empire of
          the sea that at one and the same time they were inciting our allies to revolt, undertaking
          to liberate them from our power, and were negotiating with the Persian king a treaty of
          friendship and alliance,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Treaty of <placeName
              key="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>, 412 b.c. See <bibl n="Thuc. 8.18">Thuc.
              8.18</bibl>.</note> promising to give over to him all the Hellenes who dwelt on the
          Asiatic coast? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="104" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet, after they had given these pledges both to our allies and to the King and had
          conquered us in war, they reduced those whom they had sworn to set free to a state of
          slavery worse than that of the Helots,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.111">Isoc. 4.111</bibl> and note.</note> and they returned the favour of
          the King in such wise that they persuaded Cyrus, his younger brother, to dispute the
          throne with him, and collected an army to support Cyrus, placing Clearchus at its head,
          and dispatched it against the King<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For this episode see
              <bibl n="Isoc. 8.98">Isoc. 8.98</bibl> and note.</note>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="105" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But having failed in this treachery and betrayed their purposes to the world and made
          themselves hated by all mankind, they were plunged into such a state of warfare and
          confusion as men should expect after having played false with both the Hellenes and the
          barbarians. I do not know what I need to take the time to say further about them except
          that after they had been defeated in the naval battle<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            battle of <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>, 394 b.c., in which the
            Spartan fleet was defeated by the joint fleets of Conon, the Athenian admiral, and
            Pharnabazus, the Persian satrap.</note> by the forces of the King and by the leadership
          of Conon they made a peace<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Peace of Antalcidas. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.115">Isoc. 4.115</bibl> and note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="106" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>of such a character that no one can point out in all history one more shameful, more
          reprehensible, more derogatory to the Hellenes, or more contradictory to what is said by
          certain eulogists of the virtue of the Lacedaemonians. For when the King had established
          them as masters over the Hellenes, they attempted to rob him of his kingdom and of all his
          good fortune, but when the King defeated them in battle on the sea and humbled them, they
          gave over to him, not a small contingent of the Hellenes, but all those who dwelt in
            <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, explicitly writing into the treaty that
          he should do with these according to his pleasure; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="107" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and they were not ashamed of entering into such covenants regarding men by whose help as
          allies they prevailed over us, became masters of the Hellenes, and expected to subdue the
          whole of Asia; on the contrary, they inscribed such covenants in their own temples<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.180">Isoc. 4.180</bibl>.</note> and
          compelled their allies to do the same. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="108" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now others will not care, I suppose, to hear about any further deeds, but will think
          that they have learned well enough from those which I have described what has been the
          character of each of these two states in their treatment of the Hellenes. I, however, do
          not share this feeling but consider that the subject which I undertook requires still many
          other arguments, and above all such as will show the folly of those who will attempt to
          refute what I have said, and these arguments I think I shall find ready at hand. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="109" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For of those who applaud all the actions of the Lacedaemonians, the best and the most
          discerning will, I think, commend the polity of the Spartans and remain of the same
          opinion about it as before, but will concede the truth of what I have said about the
          things which they have done to the Hellenes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="110" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Those, however, who are inferior not only to these but to the great majority of men and
          who could not speak tolerably about any other subject, albeit they are not able to keep
          silent about the Lacedaemonians, but expect that if they extol them extravagantly they
          will gain a reputation equal to those who are reputed abler and much better than
          themselves— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="111" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>these men, when they perceive that all the topics have been covered and find themselves
          unable to gainsay a single point which I have made, will, I think, turn their attention to
          the question of polities, comparing the institutions of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
            >Sparta</placeName> and of Athens, and especially their sobriety and discipline with our
          carelessness and slackness, and will eulogize the Spartans on these grounds. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="112" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If, however, they attempt anything of the sort, all intelligent men should condemn them
          as speaking beside the point. For I undertook my subject with the avowed purpose, not of
          discussing polities, but of proving that our city has been of much greater service to the
          Hellenes than has the city of the Lacedaemonians. If, then, they can overthrow any of
          these proofs or cite other achievements common to both these cities in which the Spartans
          have shown themselves superior to us, naturally they should be commended. But if they
          attempt to bring in matters of which I have made no mention, they will deserve the censure
          of all for their lack of perception. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="113" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, since I anticipate that they will inject the question of polities into the
          debate, I shall not shirk from discussing it. For I think that I shall prove that in this
          very matter our city has excelled more than in those which I have already mentioned. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="114" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And let no one suppose that I have said these things with reference to our present
          polity, which we were forced by circumstances to adopt, but rather with reference to the
          polity of our ancestors,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The democracy of Solon and
            Cleisthenes, much praised in the <bibl n="Isoc. 7.">Isoc. 7.</bibl>.</note> from which
          our fathers<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Beginning with Aristides and Themistocles,
            especially the latter, who made Athens a sea-power.</note> changed over to that which is
          now in force, not because they condemned the older polity—on the contrary, for the other
          activities of the state they preferred it as much superior—, but because they considered
          that for the exercise of supremacy by sea this polity was more expedient by adopting which
          and wisely administering it they were able to fend off both the plots of the Spartans and
          the armed forces of all the Peloponnesians, over whom it was of vital import to Athens,
          especially at that time, to have the upper hand in war. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="115" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So that no one could justly condemn those who chose our present polity.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">This making a virtue of necessity is inconsistent with
            Isocrates' uncompromising attitude toward the excesses of the later democracy in the
              <bibl n="Isoc. 7.">Isoc. 7.</bibl>, the <bibl n="Isoc. 8.">Isoc. 8.</bibl>, and even
            in this discourse.</note> For they were not disappointed in their expectations, nor were
          they at all blind to both the good and the bad features attached to either form of rule,
          but, on the contrary, saw clearly that while a land-power is fostered by order and
          sobriety and discipline and other like qualities,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.102">Isoc. 8.102</bibl>.</note> a sea-power is not augmented by these </p>
      </div>
      <div n="116" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but by the crafts which have to do with the building of ships and by men who are able to
          row them—men who have lost their own possessions and are accustomed to derive their
          livelihood from the possessions of others.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The homeless
            refugees who enlisted in the naval service of Athens for pay and the chance to pillage.
            See especially <bibl n="Isoc. 8.44">Isoc. 8.44 ff.</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. L. 9.9"
              >Isoc. Letter 9.9</bibl>.</note> Our fathers did not fail to foresee that with the
          introduction of these elements into the state the order and discipline of the former
          polity would be relaxed<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Eur. Hec. 607">Eur.
              Hec. 607</bibl>: <foreign xml:lang="greek">nautikh/ t' a)narxi/a</foreign>.</note> and
          that the good will of our allies would soon undergo a change when the Athenians should
          compel the Hellenes, to whom they had previously given lands and cities, to pay
          contributions and tribute to Athens in order that she might have the means to pay the kind
          of men whom I mentioned a moment ago. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="117" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, although they were not blind to any of the things which I have mentioned,
          they considered that it was both advantageous and becoming to a state so great in size and
          reputation to bear with all difficulties rather than with the rule of the Lacedaemonians.
          For having the choice between two policies, neither of them ideal, they considered it
          better to choose to do injury to others rather than to suffer injury themselves and to
          rule without justice over others rather than, by seeking to escape that reproach, to be
          subject unjustly to the Lacedaemonians— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="118" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>a course which all sensible men would prefer and desire for themselves,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">This cynicism accords ill with his plea for justice as a rule
            of conduct for states in <bibl n="Isoc. 8.28">Isoc. 8.28 ff.</bibl>, where he approaches
            the Platonic ideal that it is better to suffer than to do wrong (<bibl
              n="Plat. Gorg. 46c">Plat. Gorg. 46c ff.</bibl>). Here Isocrates inclines, for once, to
            the “practical” view of Demosthenes; that if all other states made justice the basis of
            their foreign policy it would be shameful for Athens not to observe it; but in a world
            where all other states are seeking the power to do injustice, for Athens alone to be
            governed by that ideal to her disadvantage would be “not justice but cowardice.” See
              <bibl n="Dem. 15.28">Dem. 15.28-29</bibl>.</note> albeit a certain few of those who
          claim to be wise men, were the question put to them, would not accept this view. These,
          then, are the reasons—I have perhaps gone into them at undue length—but, in any case,
          these are the reasons why they adopted the polity which is criticized by some in place of
          the polity which is commended by all. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="119" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I shall now proceed to speak about the polity which I took for my subject and about our
          ancestors, going back to the early times when neither the word oligarchy nor the word
          democracy was as yet in our speech, but when monarchies governed both the barbaric races
          and all the Hellenic states. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="120" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I have chosen to begin with a period rather remote for these reasons: first, because I
          consider that those who lay claim to superior excellence ought from the very beginning of
          their race to be distinguished above all others,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.25">Isoc. 4.25</bibl>.</note> and, second, because I should be ashamed if,
          having spoken at undue length of men who, though noble,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
              <bibl n="Isoc. 12.72">Isoc. 12.72 ff.</bibl></note> are nowise akin to me, I should
          not even briefly mention those of our ancestors who most excellently governed our city,
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="121" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>since they were as much superior to those who rule with absolute power as the wisest and
          gentlest of mankind may be said to excel the wildest and the most savage of the
            beasts.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Compare Montaigne, <title>Essays</title>, chapter
            42: “Plutarch says somewhere that he does not find so great a difference between beast
            and beast as he does between man and man; which he says in reference to the internal
            qualities and perfections of the soul. And, in truth, I find so vast a difference
            between Epaminondas, according to my judgement of him, and some that I know, who are yet
            men of good sense, that I would willingly enhance upon Plutarch, and say that there is
            more difference between such and such a man than there is between such aman and such a
            beast.”</note> For what among crimes that are unparalleled in their wickedness and
          cruelty shall we not find to have been perpetrated in the other states and especially in
          those which at the time of which I am speaking were considered the greatest and even now
          are so reputed? Has there not abounded in them murder of brothers and fathers and
          guest-friends; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="122" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>matricide and incest and begetting of children by sons with their own mothers; feasting
          of a father on the flesh of his own sons, plotted by those nearest of kin; exposure of
          infants by parents, and drownings and blindings<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Most of
            these horrors are taken from the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> legend
            of the house of Pelops and the Theban story of the house of Labdacus: from the former,
            Thyestes feasting unwittingly upon the flesh of his own sons, served up to him by his
            brother, Atreus; from the latter, Oedipus exposed as a child by his parents to perish in
            the mountains, the slaying of Laius, his father, by Oedipus, the marriage of Oedipus to
            his own mother, Jocasta, the death at each other's hands of the sons, Eteocles and
            Polyneices, who were born of that incestuous union, and the blinding of Oedipus.</note>
          and other iniquities so many in number that no lack of material has ever been felt by
          those who are wont each year to present in the theatre<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >These stories furnished largely the themes of the tragic poets.</note> the miseries
          which transpired in those days? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="123" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have recounted these atrocities with the desire, not of maligning these states, but of
          showing not only that nothing of the sort happened among the Athenians—for this would be a
          proof, not of their superior excellence, but merely that they were not of the same
          character as those who have proved themselves the most godless of men. However, those who
          undertake to praise any people in superlative terms must show, not only that they were not
          depraved, but that they excelled in all the virtues both those who lived at that time and
          those who are now living—which is the very claim that one may make for our ancestors. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="124" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For they administered both the affairs of the state and their own affairs as righteously
          and honorably as was to be expected of men who were descended from the gods,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">According to to one story it was from the seeds sown by
            Hephaestus on the soil of <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> that the
            Athenians were sprung. See <bibl n="Aesch. Eum. 13">Aesch. Eum. 13</bibl>.</note> who
          were the first to found a city and to make use of laws,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
              <bibl n="Isoc. 4.39">Isoc. 4.39-40</bibl> and notes.</note> who at all times had
          practised reverence in relation to the gods and justice in relation to mankind, who were
          neither of mixed origin nor invaders of a foreign territory but were, on the contrary,
          alone among the Hellenes, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="125" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>sprung from the soil itself,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.24"
              >Isoc. 4.24</bibl> and note.</note> possessing in this land the nurse of their very
          existence and cherishing it as fondly as the best of children cherish their fathers and
          mothers, and who, furthermore, were so beloved of the gods that—what is of all things in
          the world the most difficult and rare, namely, to find examples of royal houses or houses
          of absolute rulers remaining in power through four or five generations— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="126" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>this too transpired among our ancestors alone. For Erichthonius, the son of Hephaestus
          and Earth, took over from Cecrops, who was without male descent, his house and kingdom;
          and beginning with this time all those who came after him—not a few in number—handed down
          their possessions and their powers to their sons until the reign of Theseus. I would give
          much not to have spoken about the virtue and the achievements of Theseus on a former
            occasion,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 10.18">Isoc. 10.18
              ff.</bibl></note> for it would have been more appropriate to discuss this topic in my
          discourse about our city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="127" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But it was difficult, or rather impossible, to postpone the things which at that time
          occurred to me to say to the present occasion, which I could not foresee would come to me.
          Therefore I shall pass over this topic, since I have already exhausted it for my present
          purpose, and shall mention only a single course of action which, as it happens, has
          neither been discussed by anyone before nor been achieved by any other man but Theseus,
          and which is a signal proof of his virtue and wisdom. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="128" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For although he ruled over the securest and greatest of kingdoms<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Repeated from <bibl n="Isoc. 10.18">Isoc. 10.18</bibl>.</note> and in the
          exercise of this power had accomplished many excellent things both in war and in the
          administration of the state, he disdained all this and chose the glory which, in
          consequence of his labours and his struggles, would be remembered for all time in
          preference to the ease and felicity which, because of his royal power, were at his command
          for the term of his life. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="129" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And he did this, not after he had grown old and had taken his pleasure in the good things
          at hand, but in the prime of his manhood, it is said, he gave over the state to the people
          to govern,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For Theseus as the author of the spirit of the
            Athenian polity see <bibl n="Isoc. 10.35">Isoc. 10.35-37</bibl>.</note> while he himself
          risked his life without ceasing for the benefit of Athens and of the rest of the Hellenes.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="130" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have now touched upon the nobility of Theseus so far as I could on the present
          occasion, having formerly with some pains detailed his whole career. But as to those who
          took over the administration of the state, which he gave over to them, I am at a loss to
          know by what terms of praise I can adequately extol the genius of those men who, having no
          experience of governments, did not err in their choice of that polity which all the world
          would acknowledge to be not only the most impartial and the most just, but also the most
          profitable to all and the most agreeable to those who lived under it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="131" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For they established government by the people, not the kind which operates at haphazard,
          mistaking licence for liberty and freedom to do what one likes for happiness,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.20">Isoc. 7.20</bibl> and note.</note>
          but the kind which frowns upon such excesses and makes use of the rule of the best. Now
          the majority count the rule of the best,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Aristocracy.</note> which is the most advantageous of governments (just as they do
          government based upon a property qualification<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Timocracy.</note>), among the distinct kinds of polity, being mistaken, not because of
          ignorance, but because they have never taken any interest in the things which should claim
          their attention. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="132" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But I, for my part, hold that there are three types of polity and three only: oligarchy,
          democracy, and monarchy,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl n="Plat. Rep. 544c">Plat.
              Rep. 544c ff.</bibl>, distinguishes these three types: monarchy, which may be either a
            constitutional or an absolute rule; government by the few, which may be either an
            aristocracy or an oligarchy; and democracy. <bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 3.1281a">Aristot.
              Pol. 3.6 ff.</bibl>, recognizes three types: monarchy, aristocracy, and a republic,
            and, corresponding to them (aberrations from them), three debased forms, tyranny,
            oligarchy, and democracy. Isocrates' point is that any one of these forms may be an
            aristocracy; it is the spirit of the constitution which matters (<bibl n="Isoc. 12.138"
              >Isoc. 12.138</bibl>); that government is best (i.e. an aristocracy) where the best
            men rule.</note> and that of the people who live under these all who are wont to place
          in charge of their offices and of their affairs in general those of their fellow-citizens
          who are most competent and who will most ably and justly direct the affairs of state—all
          these, I hold, will govern well, under any type of polity, both in their domestic
          relations and in their relations to the rest of the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="133" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>On the other hand, when men employ in these positions of leadership those of their
          citizens who are the most brazen and the most depraved and who take no thought for the
          things which are advantageous to the commonwealth but are ready to go to any extreme to
          further their personal advantage, the character of their government will correspond to the
          depravity of the men at the head of their affairs. Again, all who are not of the latter
          class nor of that which I mentioned previously, but who, when they feel secure, honor
          before others those who speak for the gratification of the public and, when they are
          afraid, seek refuge in the best and wisest of their citizens—such men will fare now worse
          now better as the case may be. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="134" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> This, then, is the truth regarding the natures and powers of the several polities—a
          theme which will, I think, furnish to others material for much more extended discussion,
          although I must not speak further on the general subject but must confine myself to the
          polity of our ancestors. For I undertook to prove that this has been of greater worth and
          the source of greater benefits than the polity which obtains in <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="135" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And what I say on this head will prove, for those who would gladly hear me discuss an
          excellent polity, neither burdensome nor untimely but of due measure and in keeping with
          what I have said before; those, however, who take pleasure, not in the things which have
          been spoken in deep seriousness, but rather in the orators who rail at each other most of
          all at the public assemblies, or, if the speakers refrain from this madness, in those who
          deliver encomiums on the most trivial things<note anchored="true" resp="ed">It appears to
            have been a common practice for speakers to show off their oratorical powers by
            extolling such themes. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.">Isoc. 4.</bibl>close and note; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 10.12">Isoc. 10.12</bibl>.</note> or on the most lawless men who have ever
          lived—to these, I think, what I say will seem much longer than it should be. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="136" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I, however, have never concerned myself in the least with such auditors, any more than do
          other sensible men, but rather with those who will keep in mind what I said in preface to
          my whole discourse and at the same time will not frown upon the length of my speech, even
          though it extend through thousands upon thousands of words, but will realize that it lies
          in their power to read and peruse only such portion of it as they themselves desire; and
          most of all am I concerned with those who, in preference to any other, will gladly listen
          to a discourse which celebrates the virtues of men and the ways of a well-governed state.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="137" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For if any should have the wish and the power to pattern their lives upon such examples,
          they might themselves pass their days in the enjoyment of high repute and render their own
          countries happy and prosperous. Now I have expressed myself as to the kind of auditors I
          would pray that I might have for what I shall say, but I am afraid that were I given such
          an audience I might fall far below the subject upon which I am to speak. Nevertheless, in
          such manner as I can I shall attempt to discourse upon it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="138" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The fact, then, that our city was governed in those times better than the rest of the
          world I would justly credit to her kings, of whom I spoke a moment ago. For it was they
          who trained the multitude in the ways of virtue and justice and great sobriety and who
          taught through the manner of their rule the very truth which I shall be seen to have
          expressed in words after they had expressed it in their deeds, namely, that every polity
          is the soul of the state, having as much power over it as the mind over the body. For it
          is this which deliberates on all questions, seeking to preserve what is good and to avoid
          what is disastrous,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Repeated from <bibl n="Isoc. 7.14"
              >Isoc. 7.14</bibl>.</note> and is the cause of all the things which transpire in
          states. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="139" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Having learned this truth, the people did not forget it on account of the change in the
          constitution, but rather gave their minds to this one endeavor before all others: to
          obtain as their leaders men who were in sympathy with democracy, but were possessed of the
          same character as those who were formerly at the head of the state; and not unwittingly to
          place in charge of the whole commonwealth men to whom no one would entrust a single detail
          of his private interests;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 8.13">Isoc.
              8.13</bibl>, 133.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="140" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and not to permit men to approach positions of public trust who are notoriously depraved;
          and not even to suffer men to be heard<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.3">Isoc. 8.3</bibl> and note.</note> who lend their own persons to base
          practices but deem themselves worthy to advise others how they should govern the state in
          order to advance in sobriety and well-being, or who have squandered what they inherited
          from their fathers on shameful pleasures but seek to repair their own fortunes from the
          public treasury<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.124">Isoc.
              8.124</bibl> and note.</note>, or who strive always to speak for the gratification of
          their audience but plunge those who are persuaded by them into many distresses and
          hardships; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="141" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>on the contrary, they saw to it that each and everyone should look upon it as his duty to
          debar all such men from giving counsel to the public, and not only such men, but those
          also who assert that the possessions of the rest of the world belong to the state but do
          not scruple to plunder and rob the state of its legitimate property, who pretend to love
          the people but cause them to be hated by all the rest of mankind, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="142" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and who in words express anxiety for the welfare of the Hellenes but in fact outrage and
          blackmail and make them so bitter against us<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.318">Isoc. 15.318</bibl>.</note> that some of our states when pressed by
          war would sooner and more gladly open their gates to the besiegers than to a relief force
          from Athens. But one would grow weary of writing were he to attempt to go through the
          whole catalogue of iniquities and depravities. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="143" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Abhorring these iniquities and the men who practise them, our forefathers set up as
          counsellors and leaders of the state, not any and everyone, but those who were the wisest
          and the best and who had lived the noblest lives among them, and they chose these same men
          as their generals in the field<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 8.54"
              >Isoc. 8.54</bibl>.</note> and sent them forth as ambassadors, wherever any need
          arose, and they gave over to them the entire guidance of the state, believing that those
          who desired and were able to give the best counsel from the platform would, when by
          themselves, no matter in what regions of the world or on what enterprise engaged, be of
          the same way of thinking. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="144" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And in this they were justified by events. For because they followed this principle they
          saw their code of laws completely written down in a few days—laws, not like those which
          are established to-day, nor full of so much confusion and of so many contradictions that
          no one can distinguish between the useful and the useless, but, in the first place, few in
          number, though adequate for those who were to use them and easy to comprehend; and, in the
          next place, just and profitable and consonant with each other; those laws, moreover, which
          had to do with their common ways of life having been thought out with greater pains than
          those which had to do with private contracts, as indeed they should be in well regulated
            states.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.39">Isoc.
            7.39</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="145" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> At the same time they appointed to the magistracies those who had been selected
          beforehand by the members of their respective tribes<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Aristotle (<bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 8">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 8</bibl>) states that
            Solon enacted that the election to the offices should be by lot from candidates selected
            by each of the tribes. For example, each tribe selected then candidates for the nine
            archonships, and among these the lot was cast. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 7.22">Isoc.
              7.22</bibl>.</note> and townships,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The numerous “demes”
            into which <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> was divided.</note> having
          made of the offices, not prizes to fight for or to tempt ambition,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.24">Isoc. 7.24-25</bibl> and notes.</note> but
          responsibilities much more comparable to the liturgies,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
            Introduction to the <title>Antidosis</title>.</note> which are burdensome to those to
          whom they are assigned, although conferring upon them a kind of distinction. For the men
          who had been elected to office were required to neglect their own possessions and at the
          same time to abstain no less from the gratuities which are wont to be given to the offices
          than from the treasures of the gods. (Who under the present dispensation would submit to
          such restrictions?) </p>
      </div>
      <div n="146" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, those who proved conscientious in the performance of these duties, were
          moderately praised and then assigned to another similar responsibility, whereas those who
          were guilty of the slightest dereliction were involved in the deepest disgrace and the
          severest punishment. So that no one of the citizens felt about the offices as they now do,
          but they then sought to escape from them much more than they now seek to obtain them, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="147" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and all men were agreed that no truer democracy could be found, nor one more stable or
          more beneficial to the multitude, than that which gave to the people at the same time
          exemption from such cares and sovereign power to fill the offices and bring to justice
          those who offended in them<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.27">Isoc.
              7.27</bibl> and note.</note>—exactly the position which is enjoyed also by the most
          fortunate among despots. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="148" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And the greatest proof that they were even better satisfied with this regime than I say
          is this: we see the people at war with other polities which fail to please them,
          overturning them and slaying those at their head, but continuing to enjoy this polity for
          not less than a thousand years,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A very round number indeed.
            Tradition dated Theseus, whom Isocrates seems here to regard as the last of the kings,
            about 600 years before this time.</note> remaining loyal to it from the time when they
          received it down to the age of Solon and the tyranny of Pisistratus, who, after he had
          placed himself at the head of the people and done much harm to the city and driven out the
          best of her citizens as being partizans of oligarchy, brought an end to the rule of the
          people and set himself up as their master.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A pleasanter
            picture of the “tyranny” of Pisistratus is found in <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 14"
              >Aristot. Ath. Pol. 14 ff.</bibl></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="149" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But perhaps some may object—for nothing prevents breaking into my discourse—that it is
          absurd for me to presume to speak as though I had exact knowledge of events at which I was
          not present when they transpired. I, however, do not see anything unreasonable in this. I
          grant that if I were alone in relying on traditions regarding what happened long ago or
          upon records which have been handed down to us from those times I should with good reason
          be open to attack. But in fact many men—and men of discernment, too—will be seen to be in
          the same case with me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="150" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But apart from this, were I put to the test and the proof I could show that all men are
          possessed of more truth gained through hearing than through seeing and that they have
          knowledge of greater and nobler deeds which they have heard from others than those which
          they have witnessed themselves. Nevertheless it is wise for a speaker neither to ignore
          such false assumptions—for they might perhaps confuse the truth were no one to gainsay
          them—nor again to spend too much time refuting them, but only enough to indicate to the
          rest of the audience the arguments by which they might prove that the critics speak beside
          the mark, and then to go back and proceed with the speech from the point where he left
          off. And this is what I shall do. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="151" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have now sufficiently discussed the form of the polity as it was in those days and the
          length of time during which our people continued to enjoy it. But it remains for me to
          recount the actions which have resulted from the excellence of their government. For from
          these it will be possible to see still more clearly that our ancestors not only had a
          better and sounder polity than the rest of the world but also employed the kind of leaders
          and advisers which men of intelligence ought to select. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="152" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Yet I must not go on speaking even on this point, without first prefacing it with a word
          of explanation. For if, disdaining to take notice of the criticisms of people who are able
          to do nothing but find fault, I were to review one after the other not only the other
          achievements of our ancestors but also the ways and practices in warfare by which they
          prevailed over the barbarians and attained to glory among the Hellenes, inevitably some
          will say that I am really speaking of the ordinances which Lycurgus laid down and the
          Spartans follow. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="153" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I acknowledge that I am going to speak at length of the institutions of <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, not taking the view, however, that Lycurgus
          invented or conceived any of them, but that he imitated as well as he could the government
          of our ancestors,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.39">Isoc.
              4.39</bibl> and note.</note> establishing among the Spartans a democracy tempered with
          aristocracy—even such as existed in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>—,
          enacting that the offices be filled, not by lot, but by election, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="154" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>ordaining that the election of the Elders, who were to supervise all public affairs,
          should be conducted with the very same care as, they say, our ancestors also exercised
          with regard to those who were to have seats in the Areopagus, and, furthermore, conferring
          upon the Elders<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the Spartan Gerousia, Council of
            Elders, see Gilbert, <title>Greek Constitutional Antiquities</title> p. 47.</note> the
          very same power which he knew that the Council of the Areopagus also had in <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="155" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now that the institutions of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> were
          established after the manner of our own as they were in ancient times may be learned from
          many sources by those who desire to know the truth. But that skill in warfare is something
          which the Spartans did not practise earlier than our ancestors or employ to better
          advantage than they I think I can show so clearly from the struggles and the wars which
          are acknowledged to have taken place in those days that none will be able to contradict
          what I say—neither those who are blind worshippers of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
            >Sparta</placeName> nor those who at once admire and envy and strive to imitate the ways
          of Athens. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="156" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I am going to begin what I shall say on this topic with a statement which will perhaps
          be unpleasant for some to hear, although it will not be without profit to have it said.
          For if anyone were to assert that Athens and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
            >Sparta</placeName> had been the causes both of the greatest benefits and, after the
          expedition of Xerxes, of the greatest injuries to the Hellenes, without doubt he would be
          thought by those who know anything about the history of those times to speak the truth.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="157" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For they contended with the utmost possible bravery against the power of that King, but,
          having done this, although they ought then to have adopted sound measures also for the
          tasks which followed upon that achievement, they fell into such a degree, not of folly,
          but of madness, that they made peace with the man who had led an army against them and who
          had purposed to annihilate both these cities utterly and to enslave the rest of the
          Hellenes— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="158" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>with such a man, I repeat, although they could easily have conquered him on both land and
          sea, they drew up a peace<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Peace of Antalcidas.</note>
          for all time, as though he had been their benefactor, whereas, having grown jealous of
          each other's merits and fallen into mutual warfare and rivalry, they did not cease
          attempting to destroy each other and the rest of the Hellenes until they had placed their
          common enemy in a position to reduce Athens, through the power of the Lacedaemonians, and
          again <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, through the power of Athens, to
          a state of the utmost peril. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="159" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And although they were so far outstripped in shrewdness by the barbarian, they then
          experienced no such resentment as the things which they suffered should have provoked nor
          such as it behoved them to feel; nor at the present time are the greatest of the states of
            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> ashamed to vie with each other in
          fawning upon the wealth of the King; nay, <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>
          and <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> joined forces with him in the
          conquest of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.161">Isoc. 4.161</bibl>, note.</note> in order that he might be
          possessed of the greatest possible power to plot against the Hellenes, while we and the
          Spartans, although allied together, feel more hostile to each other than to those with
          whom we are each openly at war. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="160" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And of this we have a not insignificant proof. For in common we deliberate about nothing
          whatsoever, but independently we each send ambassadors to the King, expecting that the one
          of these two states to which he inclines in friendship will be invested with the place of
          advantage among the Hellenes,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General
            Introduction.</note> little realizing that those who court his favour he is wont to
          treat insolently while with those who oppose themselves to him and hold his power in
          contempt he endeavors by every means to come to terms.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. 4.154">Isoc. 4.154-155</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="161" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have gone into these matters,not without realizing that some will dare to say that I
          have here used an argument which lies beyond the scope of my subject. I, however, hold
          that never has an argument been advanced more pertinent than this to the foregoing
          discussion, neither is there any by which one can show more clearly that our ancestors
          were wiser in dealing with the greatest questions than were those who governed our city
          and the city of the Spartans after the war against Xerxes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="162" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it will be seen that these states in the times following that war made peace with the
          barbarians, that they were bent on destroying each other and the other Hellenic states,
          that at the present time they think themselves worthy to rule over the Hellenes, albeit
          they are sending ambassadors to the King, courting his friendship and alliance; whereas
          those who governed Athens before that time did nothing of the sort, but entirely the
          opposite; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="163" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for they were as firmly resolved to keep their hands off the states of <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> as were the devout to abstain from the treasures
          stored up in the temples of the gods, conceiving that, second only to the war which we
          carry on in alliance with all mankind against the savagery of the beasts, that war is the
          most necessary and the most righteous which we wage in alliance with the Hellenes against
          the barbarians, who are by nature our foes and are eternally plotting against us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="164" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The principle is not of my invention but is deduced from the conduct of our ancestors.
          For when they saw that the other states were beset by many misfortunes and wars and
          seditions, while their own city alone was well governed, they did not take the view that
          those who were wiser and more fortunate than the rest of the world were justified in
          caring nothing about the others or in permitting those states which shared the same
            stock<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The reference is to Athens, an Ionian state, as
            leader of the Ionian Colonization. The looseness of structure in this discourse is shown
            by his treatment of this theme in three places, in 42 ff. and in 190 ff. as well as
            here. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.34">Isoc. 4.34-37</bibl>.</note> with them to be destroyed,
          but rather that they were bound to take thought and adopt measures to deliver them all
          from their present misfortunes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="165" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Having determined upon this, they endeavored in the case of the less afflicted states to
          compose their quarrels by means of embassies and persuasion, but to the states which were
          more severely rent by factions they dispatched the most highly reputed of their citizens,
          who advised them regarding their present difficulties, and, associating themselves with
          the people who were unable to gain a livelihood in their own states or who had fallen
          below the requirements of the laws—a class which is generally destructive to ordered
            states<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.121">Isoc. 5.121
            ff.</bibl></note>—, they urged these to take the field with them and to seek to improve
          the conditions of their present life; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="166" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and when there proved to be many who were inclined and persuaded to take this course,
          they organized them into an army, conquered the peoples who occupied the islands of the
          barbarians and who dwelt along the coast of either continent, expelled them all, and
          settled in their stead those of the Hellenes who stood in greatest need of the necessities
          of life. And they continued doing this and setting this example to others until they
          learned that the Spartans, as I have related, had subjected to their power all the cities
          which are situated in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates regards the Ionian Colonization as contemporaneous
            with the Dorian Conquest of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName>.</note> After this they were compelled to center their
          thoughts upon their own interests. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="167" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> What, then, is the good which has resulted from the war which we waged and the trouble
          which we took in the colonization of the Hellenes? For this is, I think, a question which
          the majority would very much like to have answered. Well, the result was that the Hellenes
          found it easier to obtain subsistence and enjoyed a greater degree of concord after they
          had been relieved of so great a number of the class of people which I have described; that
          the barbarians were driven forth from their own territory and humbled in their pride; and
          that those who had brought these conditions to pass gained the fame and the name of having
          made <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> twice as strong as she was of old.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="168" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I could not, then, point out a greater service than this, rendered by our ancestors, nor
          one more generally beneficial to the Hellenes. But I shall, perhaps, be able to show one
          more particularly related to their conduct of war, and, at the same time, no less
          admirable and more manifest to all. For who does not himself know or has not heard from
          the tragic poets<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Aesch. Seven 1">Aesch.
              Seven</bibl>; <bibl n="Soph. Ant.">Soph. Ant.</bibl>; <bibl n="Eur. Phoen.">Eur.
              Phoen.</bibl></note> at the Dionysia of the misfortunes which befell Adrastus<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Compare the treatment of the Adrastus episode in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.54">Isoc. 4.54 ff.</bibl></note> at <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
            >Thebes</placeName>, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="169" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>how in his desire to restore to power the son of Oedipus, his own son-in-law, he lost a
          great number of his <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> soldiers in the battle
          and saw all of his captains slain, though saving his own life in dishonor, and, when he
          failed to obtain a truce and was unable to recover the bodies of his dead for burial, he
          came as a suppliant to Athens, while Theseus still ruled the city, and implored the
          Athenians not to suffer such men to be deprived of sepulture nor to allow ancient custom
          and immemorial law to be set at naught—that ordinance which all men respect without fail,
          not as having been instituted by our human nature, but as having been enjoined by the
          divine power?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.55">Isoc. 4.55</bibl>,
            note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="170" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>When our people heard this plea, they let no time go by but at once dispatched
          ambassadors to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> to advise her people
          that they be more reverent in their deliberations regarding the recovery of the dead and
          that they render a decision which would be more lawful than that which they had previously
          made, and to hint to them also that the Athenians would not countenance their
          transgression of the common law of all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="171" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Having heard this message, those who were then in authority at <placeName
            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> came to a decision which was in harmony neither
          with the opinion which some people have of them nor with their previous resolution; on the
          contrary, after both stating the case for themselves in reasonable terms and denouncing
          those who had invaded their country, they conceded to our city the recovery of the dead.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="172" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And let no one suppose that I fail to realize that I am giving a different version of
          these same events from that which I shall be found to have written in the
            <title>Panegyricus</title>. But I do not think that anyone of those who can grasp the
          meaning of these events is so obsessed by stupidity and envy as not to commend me and
          consider me discreet for the manner in which I have treated them then and now.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The version here is less offensive to the Thebans, perhaps
            because Athens is now cultivating friendlier relations with <placeName
              key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="173" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>On this topic, then, I know that I have written wisely and expediently. But how
          pre-eminent our city stood in war at that time—for it was with the desire to show this
          that I discussed what happened at <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>—is, I
          consider, clearly revealed to all by the circumstances which compelled the king of the
          Argives to become a suppliant of Athens and which so disposed the authorities at Thebes
          towards us </p>
      </div>
      <div n="174" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>that they chose of their own accord to accommodate themselves to the words dispatched to
          them by Athens more than to the laws ordained by the divine power. For our city would not
          have been in a position to settle properly any of those questions had she not stood far
          above the others both in reputation and in power. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="175" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Although I have many noble things to tell of in the conduct of our ancestors, I am
          debating in my mind in what manner to present them. Indeed I am more concerned about this
          than about any other thing. For I come now to that part of my subject which I reserved for
          the last—that part in which I promised to show that our ancestors excelled the Spartans
          much more in their wars and battles than in all other respects.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For the comparison of the early wars of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName> and Athens, 175-198, cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.51">Isoc.
            4.51-70</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="176" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>What I say on this topic will be counter to the opinions of the majority, but in equal
          degree it will appeal to the rest as the truth. A moment ago I was undecided whether I
          should first review the wars and battles of the Spartans or our own. Now, however, I elect
          to speak first of the perils and the battles of the Spartans, in order that I may close
          the discussion of this subject with struggles more honorable and more righteous. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="177" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>When, then, the Dorians who invaded the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName> divided into three parts both the cities and the lands which
          they had taken from their rightful owners, those of them who received <placeName
            key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
            >Messene</placeName> as their portions ordered their affairs very much as did the
          Hellenes in general. But the third division of them, whom we now call Lacedaemonians,
          were, according to close students of their history, more embroiled in factional strife
          than any other people of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>. Moreover, the
          party which looked down upon the multitude, having got the upper hand, did in no wise
          adopt the same measures regarding the issues of that conflict as the other Hellenes who
          had gone through a similar experience. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="178" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For the latter suffered the opposing party to live with them and share in all the
          privileges of the state, excepting the offices and the honors, whereas the intelligent
          class among the Spartans held that such men were foolish in thinking that they could live
          in the same city with those against whom they had committed the greatest wrongs and yet
          govern the state in security; they themselves did nothing of the sort, but instead set up
          amongst their own class the only kind of equality and democracy<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Those who enjoyed citizenship in <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName> are called by Aristotle (<bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 8.1341b">Aristot.
              Pol. 8.7</bibl>) <foreign xml:lang="greek">o(/moioi</foreign>, “equals.” Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 7.61">Isoc. 7.61</bibl>.</note> which is possible if men are to be at all
          times in complete accord, while reducing the mass of the people to the condition of
            Perioeci,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In historical times the population of
              <placeName key="tgn,7002745">Laconia</placeName>, the valley of the Eurotas river, was
            made up of the Spartans, who lived in the city of <placeName key="tgn,7011065"
              >Lacedaemon</placeName> (<placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> seems to
            have been a later name); the Helots, serfs bound to the soil, who worked the estates
            owned by the Spartans, paying a high rental, sometimes half the crop; and the Perioeci,
            free-holders of land, who were scattered in villages throughout theEurotas Valley—“the
            land of a hundred towns,” possessing apparently their own local governments, but under
            the general control and supervision of the Spartan state. These, like the Helots, were
            probably made up mainly of earlier inhabitants conquered by the Spartans. See Gilbert,
              <title>Greek Constitutional Antiquities</title> pp. 30 ff. Isocrates' picture of the
            driving out of the Perioeci from participation in the Spartan state as the result of a
            bitter factional fight seems to rest on a very doubtful tradition. See Grote's extended
            discussion of this passage, vol. 2, pp. 367 ff.</note> subjecting their spirits to a
          bondage no less abject than that endured by slaves. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="179" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And having done this, they disposed of the land, of which by right every man should have
          had an equal share, seizing for themselves—the few—not only the richest but more than any
          of the Hellenes possess, while to the mass of the people they apportioned only enough of
          the poorest land so that by working laboriously they could hardly gain their daily bread.
          Then they divided the multitude into the smallest groups possible and settled them upon
          many small tracts—groups who in name were spoken of as dwelling in cities, but in reality
          had less power than the townships with us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="180" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And, having despoiled them of all the rights which free men ought to share, they imposed
          upon them the greatest part in all dangers. For in the campaigns which were conducted by
          their kings they not only ranged them man for man side by side with themselves, but some
          they stationed in the first line, and whenever need arose to dispatch a relief-force
          anywhere and they themselves were afraid of the hardships or the dangers or the length of
          time involved, they sent them forth to take the brunt of the danger from all the rest.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="181" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But why make a long story by detailing all the outrages which were visited upon the
          common people? Why not, rather, mention the greatest of their misfortunes and refuse to be
          burdened with the rest? For over these people, who have from the beginning suffered evils
          so dreadful, but in present emergencies are found so useful, the Ephors have the power to
          put to death without trial as many as they please,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            Perioeci, like the Helots, were subject to military service more and more as the pure
            Spartan population declined; but Isocrates' complaint that they were made to take the
            brunt of danger is probably an exaggeration. However, the power of the Spartan
            magistrates, the Ephors, to condemn them to death without trial is well attested. See
            Gilbert, <title>Greek Constitutional Antiquities</title> p. 58.</note> whereas in the
          other states of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> it is a crime against the
          gods to stain one's hands with the blood of even the basest of slaves. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="182" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But the reason I have at some length gone into their domestic policy and the wrongs
          which they have committed against the common people is, that I may ask those who applaud
          all the actions of the Spartans whether they applaud these also and whether they look upon
          those struggles as righteous and honorable which have been carried on against these men.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="183" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I, for my part, regard them as having been great and terrible and the source of many
          injuries to the defeated and of many gains to the victors—gains for whose sake they are at
          all times continually waging war—but not, no, not as righteous or even as honorable or
          becoming to men who lay claim to excellence. I speak, not of excellence as that word is
          used in the arts or in many other activities, but of the excellence which in the hearts of
          good men and true is engendered in company with righteousness and justice. And it is this
          kind of excellence which is the subject of my whole discourse. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="184" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But depreciating this, some men heap praise upon those who have committed more crimes
          than all others and are not aware that they are betraying their own thoughts and showing
          that they would praise also men who, already possessing more wealth than they need, would
          not scruple to slay their own brothers and friends and associates so as to obtain their
          possessions also. For such crimes are parallel to the things which the Spartans have done.
          And those who applaud the latter cannot escape taking the same view also of the crimes
          which I have just mentioned. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="185" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I marvel that there are none who regard battles and victories won contrary to justice as
          more disgraceful and fraught with greater reproaches than defeats which are met without
          dishonor—and that too, knowing that great, but evil, powers prove often stronger than good
          men who choose to risk their lives for their country. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="186" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For such men are much more deserving of our praise than those who, while ready and
          willing to face death to gain the possessions of others, are yet in no wise different from
          hireling soldiers. For these are the acts of men depraved, and if men of honest purpose
          sometimes come off worse in the struggle than men who desire to do injustice, we may
          attribute this to negligence of the gods. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="187" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But I might apply this point also to the misfortune which befell the Spartans at
            <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName>, which all who have heard
          of it praise and admire more than the battles and victories which have been won over
          adversaries against whom wars ought never to have been waged,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 5.148">Isoc. 5.148</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 4.90">Isoc.
              4.90</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 6.99">Isoc. 6.99-100</bibl>.</note> albeit some are
          without scruple in extolling such successes, not realizing that nothing is either
          righteous or honorable which is not said or done with justice.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The high moral tone here is, like the plea for absolute justice as a principle
            of foreign policy in the Peace, inconsistent with the “practical” doctrine of <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.117">Isoc. 12.117-118</bibl>. See note on 118.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="188" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the Spartans have never given a thought to this truth; for they look to no other
          object than that of securing for themselves as many of the possessions of other peoples as
          they can. Our ancestors, on the other hand, have shown concern for nothing in the world so
          much as for a good name among the Hellenes; for they considered that there could be no
          truer or fairer judgement than that which is rendered by a whole race of people. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="189" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And they have been manifestly of this mind both in their government of the state in other
          respects and in the conduct of the greatest affairs. For in the three wars,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Three “wars,” with no attention to chronology: (1) that
            against Xerxes; (2) the warfare connected with the Ionian Colonization; (3) four
            campaigns summarized as one, all dealing with invasions: (a) that against Eumolpus and
            the Thracians; (b) that against the Scythians; (c) that against Eurystheus; (d) that
            against Dareius.</note> apart from the Trojan war, which were fought by the Hellenes
          against the barbarians—in all these they placed our city in the forefront of the fighting.
          Of these wars, one was the struggle against Xerxes,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
              <bibl n="Isoc. 12.49">Isoc. 12.49 ff.</bibl></note> in which they were as much
          superior to the Lacedaemonians in every crisis as were the latter to the rest of the
          Hellenes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="190" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Another was the war connected with the founding of the colonies,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 12.42">Isoc. 12.42 ff.</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 12.164"
              >Isoc. 12.164 ff.</bibl></note> in which none of the Dorians came to help them, but in
          which Athens, having been made the leader of those who were lacking in the means of
          subsistence and of all others who desired to join with her, so completely reversed the
          state of affairs that, whereas the barbarians had been wont in times past to seize and
          hold the greatest cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, she placed
          the Hellenes in a position where they were able to do what they had formerly suffered.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="191" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now as to the two wars, I have said enough earlier in this discourse.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In 49 ff., 42 ff., 164 ff.</note> I shall now take up the
          third, which took place when the other Hellenic cities had just been founded and while our
          own city was still ruled by kings. In those days there occurred at the same time very many
          wars and very great perils. I could neither ascertain nor set forth the history of all of
          them, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="192" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and I shall pass over the great bulk of the things which were then done, but do not now
          press upon us to be told, and shall endeavor to inform you as briefly as I can of the
          enemies who attacked our city, of the battles which deserve to be recalled and recounted,
          of their leaders, and, furthermore, of the pretexts which they alleged, and of the
          strength of the peoples who joined in their campaigns. For these details will be enough to
          discuss in addition to what we have said about our adversaries. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="193" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For our country was invaded by the Thracians, led by Eumolpus,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.68">Isoc. 4.68</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 6.42">Isoc.
              6.42</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 7.75">Isoc. 7.75</bibl>.</note> son of Poseidon, who
          disputed the possession of Athens with Erechtheus, alleging, that Poseidon had
          appropriated the city before Athena; also by the Scythians, led by the Amazons,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.68">Isoc. 4.68</bibl>.</note> the
          offspring of Ares, who made the expedition to recover Hippolyte,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">A queen of the Amazons, who, according to one legend, being enamored of
            Theseus, deserted her own people and followed him to Athens. In one tradition she meets
            her death fighting against the Amazons, who came to recover her. <bibl n="Paus. 1.2.1"
              >Paus. 1.2.1</bibl>.</note> since she had not only broken the laws which were
          established among them, but had become enamored of Theseus and followed him from her home
          to Athens and there lived with him as his consort; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="194" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>again, by the Peloponnesians, led by Eurystheus,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.58">Isoc. 4.58 ff.</bibl></note> who not only refused to make amends to
          Heracles for his ill-treatment of him but brought an army against our ancestors with the
          object of seizing by force the sons of Heracles, who had taken refuge with us. However, he
          met with the fate which was his due. For so far did he fail of getting our suppliants into
          his power that, having been defeated in battle and taken captive by our people, he became
          the suppliant of those whom he had come to demand of us, and lost his own life. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="195" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Later than Eurystheus, the troops dispatched by Dareius<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.71">Isoc. 4.71-72</bibl>, <bibl n="Isoc. 4.85">Isoc.
              4.85-87</bibl>.</note> to ravage <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>
          landed at Marathon, fell upon more misfortunes and greater disasters than they had hoped
          to inflict upon our city, and fled in rout from all <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="196" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> All these whom I have instanced, having invaded our country—not together nor at the same
          time, but as opportunity and self-interest and desire concurred in each case—our ancestors
          conquered in battle and put an end to their insolence. And yet they did not forsake their
          true selves<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See for the figure and the thought, <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.32">Isoc. 12.32</bibl>; General Introduction.</note> after they had
          achieved successes of such magnitude nor did they experience the same misadventure as
          those who, owing to the exercise of good and wise judgement, have attained great wealth
          and good reputation, but who, owing to excess of good fortune, have grown overweening,
          lost their senses, and have been brought down to lower and meaner circumstances than those
          which they enjoyed before. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="197" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>On the contrary, they escaped all such aberrations and remained steadfast in the
          character which they had because of the excellence of their government, taking more pride
          in their state of soul and in the quality of their minds than in the battles which had
          been fought, and being more admired by the rest of the world because of this self-control
          and moderation than because of the bravery displayed in their perils. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="198" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For all men saw that the fighting spirit is possessed by many even of those who outdo
          others in villainy, while that spirit which is beneficent in all things and is helpful to
          all men is not shared by the depraved, but is engendered only in men who are of good birth
          and breeding and education—even such as were those who then governed our city and brought
          to pass all the good things which I have described. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="199" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now I observe that the other orators close their discourses with the greatest and most
          memorable deeds, but, while I commend the wisdom of those who hold and practise this
          principle, yet I am not in a position to do this same thing, but am compelled to go on
          with my discourse. The reason why, I shall explain presently, after first saying just a
          word. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="200" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> After I had written out my discourse as far as what has been read, I was revising it
          with three or four youths who are wont to spend their time in my society. And when, on
          going over what I had written, it seemed to us to be good and to require only an ending,
          it occurred to me to send for one of those who had studied with me<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">It has been conjectured, with no degree of certainty, that the pupil here
            referred to was Theopompus, the historian.</note> but had lived under an oligarchy and
          had elected to extol the Lacedaemonians. I did this in order that, if any false statement
          had escaped me, he might detect it and point it out to me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="201" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>He came, upon being summoned, and, having read through my discourse (for why take up time
          in relating what happened in the interval?) he took no offence at anything which I had
          written but, on the contrary, praised the speech in the highest possible terms and
          expressed views on each part of it which were very similar to those which I held. And yet
          it was manifest that he was not pleased with what I had said about the Lacedaemonians.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="202" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And he showed it forthwith; for he made bold to say that if the Spartans had done no
          other service to the Hellenes, at any rate, they deserved the gratitude of all men because
          they had discovered the best ways of life and not only followed these ways themselves but
          had taught them to the rest of the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="203" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> This assertion, so brief and so brusque, furnished the reason why I did not close my
          speech at the point where I was inclined to end it. I thought that it would be shameful
          and reprehensible on my part to permit one who had been my pupil to make in my presence a
          statement which was unsound. With this in mind, I asked him whether he had no regard for
          his present auditors and was not ashamed of having said things which were impious and
          false and full of many contradictions. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="204" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>“You will realize,” I said, “that your assertion is such as I have declared it to be if
          you will ask any intelligent men, first what they think are the best ways of life, and
          next how long a time has passed since the Lacedaemonians settled in the <placeName
            key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>. For there is no one who, among the ways of
          life, will not give preference to the practice of reverence in relation to the gods and of
          justice in relation to mankind and of wisdom in relation to all activities in general, and
          they will tell you that the Spartans have lived in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName> not more than seven hundred years. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="205" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>These things being so, if you speak the truth when you assert that they were the
          discoverers of the best ways of life, then it must follow that those who lived many
          generations before the Spartans settled there had no part in them—neither those who made
          the expedition against <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> nor those who were
          of the generation of Heracles and Theseus or of Minos, son of Zeus, or Rhadamanthus or
            Aeacus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Minos, Rhadamanthus, and Aeacus are half-legendary
            kings famed for their virtues, and especially their justice. they are sometimes pictured
            as dispensing justice in the world of the dead. See <bibl n="Plat. Gorg. 523">Plat.
              Gorg. 523</bibl>.</note> or any of the others who are celebrated in song for the
          virtues which I have mentioned, but that all of them have in this respect a reputation
          which is false. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="206" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But if, on the other hand, you are speaking nonsense, and if it is fitting that men who
          were descended from gods should have cultivated these virtues more than all others and
          transmitted them to their successors as well, then you cannot escape being thought mad by
          all who hear you for being so reckless and unjust and undiscriminating in your praise.
          Furthermore, if you were praising them without having heard any of my speech, you would no
          less be speaking drivel, but you would not be manifestly contradicting yourself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="207" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But now, since you have commended my discourse, which proves that the Lacedaemonians have
          committed many outrages both against their own kinsmen and the rest of the Hellenes, how
          could you then say that those who are open to these charges have been the leaders in the
          best ways of life </p>
      </div>
      <div n="208" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “Moreover, this consideration also has escaped you, that the things which have been
          overlooked, whether in ways of living or in the arts or in all other activities, are not
          discovered by any and every one, but by men who have superior endowments and are both able
          to learn the most of what has been discovered before their time and willing more than all
          others to give their minds to the search for what is new. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="209" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But in these respects the Lacedaemonians are more backward than the barbarians. For you
          will find that the latter have been both pupils and teachers of many discoveries, while
          the Lacedaemonians have fallen so far behind our common culture and learning that they do
          not even try to instruct themselves in letters<note anchored="true" resp="ed">”Before the
            development of the body, that of the mind had completely to give way“ in <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. See <bibl n="Plut. Lyc. 16">Plut. Lyc.
              16</bibl>; Gilbert <title>GCA</title> p.64.</note>—a science which has so much power
          that those who understand and use it become apprized not only of the things which have
          been accomplished in their own time but also of the things which have come to pass in any
          age whatsoever. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="210" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, you have made bold to assert even of those who are ignorant of such matters
          that they have been the discoverers of the best ways of life, and that too when you know
          that they train their own boys in habits and practices by which they hope that, so far
          from becoming the benefactors of others, they will become most adept in doing injury to
          the Hellenes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="211" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “Were I to go through all of these practices, I should greatly fatigue both myself and
          my hearers, but if I mention only a single one—one which they cherish most and by which
          they set most store—I think that I can put before you their whole manner of life. For
          every day they send out their boys, from the very cradle, as it were, with such companions
          as each may prefer, ostensibly to hunt, but in reality to steal<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For this feature of their training see <bibl n="Plut. Lyc. 17">Plut. Lyc.
              17-18</bibl>; <bibl n="Xen. Const. Lac. 2.5">Xen. Const. Lac. 2.5 ff.</bibl>; Gilbert,
              <title>GCA</title> p. 64.</note> the property of the people who live in the country.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="212" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In this practice, those who are caught are punished with fines and blows, while those who
          have accomplished the greatest number of thefts and have been able to escape detection
          enjoy a higher esteem among their fellow-youths than the others, and when they attain to
          manhood, provided they remain true to the ways which they practised in youth, they are in
          line for the most important offices. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="213" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “If anyone can point out an education which is more cherished by them or by which they
          set greater store than this, I am willing to grant that there is not a word of truth in
          what I have said about anything whatsoever. And yet what is there in such conduct that is
          good or admirable and not, on the contrary, shameful? How can we fail to condemn the folly
          of those who extol men who have so far departed from our common laws and are in no respect
          of the same way of thinking as either the Hellenes or the barbarians? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="214" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For the rest of the world looks upon malefactors and thieves as more depraved than
          slaves, whereas the Lacedaemonians regard those who stand first in such crimes as the best
          among their youths and honor them the most. And yet who that is in his right mind would
          not prefer to die many times rather than be known as seeking through such practices to
          school himself in virtue?” </p>
      </div>
      <div n="215" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When he heard this, he did not answer arrogantly any of the things which I had said,
          neither, on the other hand, was he altogether silent, but remarked as follows:
          “You”—meaning myself—“have spoken as if I applauded all of the ways of <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and considered them good. But in fact I think
          that you are right in condemning the Spartans for the licence practised by their youth and
          for many other things as well, but wrong in attacking me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="216" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I was troubled on reading your speech by what you had said about the Lacedaemonians,
          but much more by my own inability to utter a single word in their defence against what you
          had written, accustomed as I had been at all other times to commend you. And when I found
          myself in this perplexity, I said the only thing I could, namely, that for this reason at
          least, if for no other, they deserved the gratitude of all of us, because they followed
          the best ways of life. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="217" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>However, I said this, not with any thought of reverence or justice or wisdom—the virtues
          which you mentioned<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See 204.</note>—but having in mind the
          athletic practices which have been instituted among them, their training in courage, their
          spirit of concord, and, in a word, their discipline for war. These all men will commend,
          and will concede that the Spartans practise them most of all.” </p>
      </div>
      <div n="218" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When he had said this, I accepted his explanation, feeling that it did not break down
          any of the criticisms which I had made but that it covered up, not without tact, nay, with
          good taste, the crudeness of his previous utterance, and that his defence on the other
          points showed greater moderation than his former brusque assertion. Nevertheless, though I
          dismissed that matter, I stated that with reference to these very claims which he made for
          the Spartans I had an attack which was much more damaging than what I had said on the
          subject of stealing among their youths. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="219" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>“For by that practice,” I said, “they ruined their own youths, and by these which you
          have just mentioned, they seek to destroy the Hellenes. And it is easy to see at a glance
          that this is so for I think that all men will agree that those men are the basest and
          deserve the severest punishment who take the discoveries which have been made for our
          benefit and use them for the injury, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="220" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>not of the barbarians nor of those who wrong them nor of those who invade their
          territory, but of those who are their nearest kin and share the same blood with them.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Perioeci, who, according to Isocrates, were of the Spartan
            blood, and their fellow-Dorians generally.</note> And this is what the Spartans have
          done. And yet with what conscience can we say that they make good use of their warlike
          practices who have at all times without ceasing sought to destroy those whom it behoved
          them to save? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="221" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “In truth, however, it is not you alone who fail to distinguish those who make good use
          of things, but, I might almost say, the great majority of the Hellenes. For whenever they
          see or hear from others that any people devote themselves zealously to what appear to be
          good practices, they extol them and make many speeches about them, without knowing what
          will be the effects of this devotion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="222" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>However, those who desire to form a correct judgement about such people should remain
          silent and have no opinion about them in the beginning, but when the time comes when they
          can observe them both speaking and taking action regarding both private and public
          affairs, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="223" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>then they should take accurate note of what they do in each case; and when men make good
          use of the things which they have practised, they should praise and honor them, but when
          they go wrong and do evil they should censure and abhor them and guard themselves against
          their ways, bearing in mind that things do not of their own nature either help or harm us,
          but that the manner in which they are used and employed by men is the cause of all the
          things which befall us.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 3.3">Isoc.
              3.3-4</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 15.251">Isoc. 15.251-252</bibl>.</note> One may grasp the
          truth of this from the following consideration: </p>
      </div>
      <div n="224" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>things which are in themselves always the same and never different are to some helpful
          and to others harmful. And yet it is not conceivable that each thing should have a nature
          which itself is contrary to itself and not the same. But, on the other hand, who that can
          reason correctly will not look upon it as natural that the consequences should be by no
          means the same in the case of those who act rightly and justly and in the case of those
          who act willfully and wickedly? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="225" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “This same argument applies also to the matter of concord; for this is not different in
          its nature from the things which I have discussed; on the contrary, we shall find that it
          is in some instances the cause of very many blessings, but in others of the greatest evils
          and misfortunes. And I contend that the concord of the Spartans is of the latter sort. For
          I shall speak the truth even at the risk of appearing to some to say what is quite
          contrary to the general opinion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="226" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For by being of one mind amongst themselves regarding the outside world they have always
          striven to set the Hellenes at variance with each other, reducing this practice, as it
          were, to a fine art and they have always looked upon the cruellest of evils which befell
          the other states as of all things in the world the greatest of boons to themselves; for
          when the states were in such stress, they found it possible to manage them as they
          pleased. So that no one could justly praise them because of their concord, any more than
          one could praise pirates or brigands or men given to other forms of injustice. For such
          men also enjoy concord among themselves<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For this concord
            “honor among thiefs” see <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 351c">Plat. Rep. 351c</bibl>.</note> and
          thereby seek to destroy all others. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="227" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But if I appear to some to use a comparison which is not in keeping with the reputation
          of the Spartans, I discard this and instance the Triballians,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See 50, note.</note> who, according to what all men say, are of one mind as
          are no other people on earth, but are bent on destroying not only those who border upon
          their territory and those who live in their neighborhood but also all others whom they are
          able to reach. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="228" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But men who pretend to excellence must not imitate their example but much rather the
          power of wisdom and of justice and of the other virtues. For these do not work for the
          benefit of their own natures,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See the argument between
            Socrates and Thrasymachus in <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 1">Plat. Rep. 1</bibl>.</note> but
          whomsoever they visit and abide with—these they bless with prosperity and happiness. But
          the Lacedaemonians do the very opposite: whomsoever they approach they seek to destroy and
          they are ever striving to appropriate all the good things which belong to the world at
          large.” </p>
      </div>
      <div n="229" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Having said these things, I silenced the man to whom I had addressed my remarks, albeit
          he was able and experienced in many things and had been trained in speaking no less than
          any of those who had been under my instruction. However, the youths who had been present
          at all this discussion did not form the same judgement as myself, but, while they
          applauded me both for having spoken more vigorously than they anticipated and for having
          debated well, they disparaged my opponent, although in fact they judged neither of us
          correctly </p>
      </div>
      <div n="230" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but missed the truth as to us both. For he went his way, having grown wiser and feeling
          chastened in spirit, as is becoming to men of intelligence he had experienced the force of
          the inscription at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> and come to know
          both himself and the nature of the Lacedaemonians better than before. I, on the other
          hand, remained, having perhaps debated effectively, but having because of this very fact
          shown less understanding, cherishing a greater pride than befits men of my age, and given
          over to youthful confusion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="231" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Manifestly I was in such a state of mind; for when I seized a moment of quiet, I did not
          cease until I had dictated to my boy<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The common term for a
            servant. Slaves were often employed as secretaries.</note> the speech which a short time
          before I had delivered with pleasure but which a little later was to cause me distress.
          For when, after three or four days had elapsed, I was reading and going over it, I found
          that, while I was not troubled about the things which I had said about Athens (for in
          everything which had reference to her I had written well and justly), </p>
      </div>
      <div n="232" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>yet I was distressed and uncomfortable about what I had said with reference to the
          Lacedaemonians. For it seemed to me that I had not spoken of them with moderation nor in
          the same manner as the rest of the world but with contempt and with extreme bitterness and
          altogether without understanding. The result was that I was often on the point of blotting
          out or burning what I had written and as often changed my mind when I thought with pity of
          my old age and of the labour which had been spent upon my discourse. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="233" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Since I was in this state of confusion, shifting frequently from one impulse to the
          other, I decided that the best thing for me to do was to call in those of my former
          disciples who lived in the city and take counsel with them as to whether my discourse was
          to be entirely destroyed or to be distributed among those who desired to have it, and to
          follow their judgement whatever it might be. Having so resolved, I lost no time; they whom
          I have mentioned were summoned at once; I announced to them beforehand the object of their
          coming together the speech was read aloud, was praised and applauded and accorded even
          such a reception as is given to successful declamations.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >“Epideictic” speeches—orations composed to display the powers of the speaker.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="234" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But when all this demonstration had come to an end, the others present began to talk
          among themselves, presumably about the discourse which had been read. But the man whom I
          had sent for at first to obtain his advice (the panegyrist of the Lacedaemonians, to whom
          I had spoken at greater length than I should), having remained silent in the meantime,
          turned to me and said that he was in doubt what to do in the present situation, for he
          desired neither to discredit the words which I had spoken nor was he able to credit them
          entirely. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="235" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>“For I wonder,” he continued, “whether you were as distressed and uncomfortable about the
          things which you had said concerning the Lacedaemonians as you allege—for I see nothing in
          what you have written to indicate such a feeling—and whether you really brought us
          together because you desired to get our advice about your discourse, since you knew well
          enough that we always commend whatever you say or do. Men of intelligence are accustomed
          to take common counsel with others regarding matters about which they are concerned,
          preferably with those who are wiser than themselves, but, at any rate, with those who will
          express their own judgement. But you have done the very opposite. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="236" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore I accept neither of these explanations but am rather of the opinion that you
          summoned us here and pronounced your encomium on Athens, not ingenuously nor for the
          reason you stated to us, but because you wanted to test us to see if we were true to the
          cultivated life, if we remembered what had been said to us under your tutelage, and if we
          could grasp at once the manner in which your speech was written— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="237" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>that you chose, and chose wisely, to eulogize your own city in order that you might
          gratify the multitude of your fellow-citizens and that you might win the acclaim of those
          who are friendly disposed towards you. But having so decided, you conceived that if you
          confined your discourse to Athens alone and repeated the fables about her which fall
          easily from the lips of everyone, your speech would appear no different from those which
          had been composed by the other orators (which would cause you extreme humiliation and
          distress), </p>
      </div>
      <div n="238" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>whereas if you discarded these fables and dealt with her acknowledged achievements, which
          have brought many blessings to the Hellenes, and compared these with the deeds of the
          Lacedaemonians, praising the achievements of your ancestors and censuring the things which
          have been done by the Lacedaemonians, not only would your discourse make a more striking
          impression upon your hearers but you yourself would lose no ground, and many would admire
          such a treatment of the theme more than what had been written by the other orators. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="239" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “At the first, then, so it appears to me, this was the manner in which you reviewed and
          thought upon your problem. But since you knew that you had praised the government of the
          Spartans more than any other man,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An exaggeration. But see
              <bibl n="Isoc. 6">Isoc. 6</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 7.7">Isoc. 7.7</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 3.24">Isoc. 3.24</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 8.142">Isoc. 8.142 ff.</bibl></note>
          you feared lest you might impress those who had heard this praise as no different from the
          orators who speak without conviction or principle, if, that is to say, you censured on the
          present occasion those whom you formerly were wont to praise above all others. Pondering
          this difficulty, you proceeded to study in what light you could represent each of these
          two cities in order that you might seem to speak the truth about them both and that you
          might be able to praise your ancestors, just as you purposed to do, and at the same time
          to appear to be censuring the Spartans in the eyes of those who have no liking for them,
          while in reality doing nothing of the sort but covertly praising them instead. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="240" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Seeking such an effect, you found without difficulty arguments of double meaning, which
          lend themselves no more to the purpose of those who praise than of those who blame, but
          are capable of being turned both ways and leave room for much disputation—arguments the
          employment of which, when one contends in court over contracts for his own advantage, is
          shameful and no slight token of depravity but, when one discourses on the nature of man
          and of things, is honorable and bespeaks a cultivated mind.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Surely this is ironical.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="241" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Even such is the discourse which has been read, in which you have represented your
          ancestors as devoted to peace and lovers of the Hellenes and champions of equality in the
          government of states, but have painted the Spartans as arrogant and warlike and
          self-seeking, as indeed they have been conceived by all men to be. “Such being the nature
          of each of these two cities, the Athenians are extolled by all men and are credited with
          being friendly to the masses, while the Spartans are envied and disliked by the majority
          of men. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="242" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>There are, however, those who praise them and admire them and make bold to say that they
          have greater advantages than were possessed by your ancestors. For arrogance partakes of
          dignity—a quality held in high esteem—and men of that character are regarded as more
          high-minded than those who champion equality, just as those who are warlike are regarded
          as superior to those who are peaceable. For the latter are neither seekers after what they
          do not have nor staunch guardians of what they possess, while the former are effective in
          both respects—both in seizing whatever they covet and in keeping whatever they have once
          made their own. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="243" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And this is what is done by those who are men in the complete sense.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Manifestly Isocrates in this passage imitates <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 344">Plat.
              Rep. 344</bibl>, where Thrasymachus, maintaining that “justice is the interest of the
            stronger,” bids Socrates not to mark the consequences of injustice practised on a petty
            scale but those of the “most complete injustice,” such as a despotism. Cf. <bibl
              n="Plat. Gorg. 483">Plat. Gorg. 483</bibl>.</note> But the eulogists of <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> think they have even a stronger plea for
          self-seeking than what I have said. For they do not consider that men who break contracts
          and cheat and falsify accounts deserve to be termed self-seeking; for because they are in
          bad repute with all men they come off worse in all circumstances, whereas the self-seeking
          of the Spartans and of kings and despots is a gift from heaven which all men crave. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="244" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It is true that those who hold such power are the objects of abuse and execration but no
          man is so constituted by nature that he would not pray to the gods to be granted this
          power, preferably for himself, but, failing that, for those nearest and dearest to him.
          And this fact makes it manifest that all men regard it as the greatest good in the world
          to have the advantage over others. “It was, then, with such thoughts, as it seems to me,
          that you planned the general scope of your discourse. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="245" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But if I believed that you would refrain from revising what has been said and would let
          this discourse stand without criticism, I would not myself attempt to speak further. As it
          is, however, I do not suppose that you will feel disturbed in the least because I did not
          speak out my opinion on the question about which I was called in to advise you, for even
          at the time when you called us together you did not seem to me to be really concerned
          about it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="246" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I suppose rather that you will object that, whereas you have deliberately chosen to
          compose a discourse which is not at all like any other, but which to those who read it
          casually will appear to be ingenuous and easy to comprehend, though to those who scan it
          thoroughly and endeavor to see in it what has escaped all others it will reveal itself as
          difficult and hard to understand, packed with history and philosophy, and filled with all
          manner of devices and fictions—not the kind of fictions which, used with evil intent, are
          wont to injure one's fellow-citizens, but the kind which, used by the cultivated mind, are
          able to benefit or to delight one's audience,— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="247" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>you will object, I say, that, whereas you have chosen to do this, yet I have not allowed
          any of this to stand as you resolved that it should, but that I fail to see that in
          seeking both to explain the force of your words and to expound your real thoughts I
          thereby lessen the reputation of the discourse in proportion as I make it more patent and
          intelligible to its readers; for by implanting understanding in those who are without
          knowledge I render the discourse naked and strip it of the honor which would otherwise
          attach to it through those who study hard and are willing to take pains. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="248" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “But, while I acknowledge that my own intelligence is vastly inferior to your own, yet
          as surely as I appreciate this fact so surely do I know that in times when your city
          deliberates on matters of the greatest import those who are reputed to be the wisest some
          times miss the expedient course of action, whereas now and then some chance person from
          the ranks of men who are deemed of no account and are regarded with contempt hits upon the
          right course and is thought to give the best advice. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="249" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It would not, then, be surprising if something of the sort has come to pass in the
          present instance, where you think that you will gain the greatest credit if you conceal
          for the longest possible time the purpose you had in mind when you worked out your
          discourse, whereas I think that you will best succeed if you can with the least possible
          delay publish the thought by which you were governed when you composed it to all the world
          and especially to the Lacedaemonians, whom you have often discussed, sometimes with
          fairness and dignity, but then again with recklessness and extreme captiousness. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="250" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “For if one were to show them a discourse of the latter sort before I had explained it
          to them, they would inevitably hate you and dislike you for having written in denunciation
          of them. As it is, I think that while most of the Lacedaemonians will continue to abide in
          the ways to which they have been faithful in past times and will pay no more attention to
          what is written in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> than to what is said
          beyond the Pillars of Heracles, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="251" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>yet the most intelligent among them, who possess and admire certain of your writings,
          will not misapprehend anything of what is said in this discourse if they can find someone
          who will interpret it to them, and if they can take the time to ponder over it by
          themselves; on the contrary, they will appreciate the praise given to their own city,
          which is based on proof, while they will dismiss with contempt the abuse, which is uttered
          at random with no regard to the facts, and is offensive only in the words employed; and
          they will think that envy slipped in the calumnies which are found in your treatise, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="252" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but that you have recorded the exploits and the battles in which they themselves take
          great pride and because of which they enjoy a high repute with the rest of the world, and
          that you have made these achievements memorable by collecting them all and placing them
          side by side with each other and so have brought it about that many of the Spartans long
          to read and peruse your accounts of them, not because they crave to hear of their own
          deeds, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="253" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but because they wish to hear how you have dealt with them. And as they think and dwell
          upon these deeds, they will not fail to recall also those ancient exploits through which
          you have glorified their ancestors,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See 239 note.</note>
          but will often talk of them amongst themselves; and first of all they will tell of the
          time when, being still Dorians, they saw their own cities to be inglorious and
          insignificant and in need of many things, and, feeling them to be unworthy, took the field
          against the leading states of the Peloponnesus—against Argos and <placeName
            key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
            >Messene</placeName>— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="254" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>conquered them in battle and drove the vanquished both from their cities and from their
          lands, and seized for themselves at that time all the possessions of the enemy and have
          continued to hold them to this day. And no man can point to a greater or a more marvellous
          achievement in those times nor to an enterprise more fortunate or more blessed of the gods
          than that which delivered those who engaged in it from their own poverty and placed them
          in possession of the prosperity of others. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="255" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “These were victories won with the aid of all who joined in that expedition. But after
          they had divided the territory with the Argives and the Messenians and for themselves had
          settled in Sparta—at this juncture, as you say, they were so proud that although they then
          numbered no more than two thousand men<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Spartans at the
            time of the Persian Wars numbered eight thousand according to <bibl n="Hdt. 7.234">Hdt.
              7.234</bibl>. Aristotle (<bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 2.1273b">Aristot. Pol. 2.9</bibl>)
            states that in his day there were hardly one thousand.</note> they considered themselves
          unworthy to live unless they could make themselves masters of all the cities in the
            <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="256" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In this state of mind, they undertook to wage war and did not cease, albeit they were
          involved in many misadventures and dangers, before they had reduced them all to
          subjection, except the city of the Argives. But when at length they held the greatest
          territory and the strongest power in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> and a
          reputation appropriate to men who had achieved such mighty things, they continued no less
          to pride themselves upon the fact that they could boast of a record unique and glorious:
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="257" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for they, alone of the Hellenes, could say that, albeit so few in number, they had never
          followed the lead or done the bidding of any one of the populous states, but had
          throughout been free and independent; and that they themselves in the war against the
          barbarians had held the place of leadership among all the Hellenes and had attained this
          honor, not without good reason, but because they had fought more battles than any other
          people in those times and had never been defeated in any one of them, when a king led them
          forth to battle, but had been victorious in all. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="258" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And no one could urge a stronger proof than this of their valor and their hardihood and
          of their concord amongst themselves, except that which I shall now mention: for of all the
          other Hellenic states, many as they are, no man could cite or find a single one which has
          not been involved in the misadventures which are wont to happen to states, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="259" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>whereas in the city of the Spartans no one can show an instance of civil faction or
          slaughter or unlawful exile, nor of seizure of property or outrage to women and children,
          nor even of revolution or abolition of debts or redistribution of lands, nor of any other
          of the irreparable ills.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Almost quoted from <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.127">Isoc. 15.127</bibl>.</note> And as the Spartans review these facts,
          they cannot fail to remember you also, who have collected them and discoursed upon them so
          ably, and to be most grateful to you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="260" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “But I do not now have the same feeling about you as I had formerly. For in time past I
          admired your natural endowments and the manner in which you ordered your life and your
          devotion to work and above all the truth of your teaching, but now I envy and congratulate
          you because of your good fortune. For it seems to me that during your lifetime you will
          gain a reputation, not greater than you deserve—for that would be difficult—but one more
          widely extended and more heartily acknowledged than that which you now possess, and that
          after you have ceased to live you will partake of immortality,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 1.38">Isoc. 1.38</bibl> and note; <bibl n="Isoc. 2.37"
              >Isoc. 2.37</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 5.134">Isoc. 5.134</bibl>.</note> not the
          immortality which the gods enjoy, but that which plants in future generations a
          remembrance of those who have distinguished themselves in any noble endeavor. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="261" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And you will deserve this reward; for you have extolled both these cities well and
          fittingly—Athens, according to the acclaim of the majority, which no man of note has ever
          disdained, while all men in their craving to obtain it are ready to submit themselves to
          any hazard whatsoever; but <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, according
          to the reasoning of those who endeavor to aim at the truth, whose good opinion some would
          choose in preference to that of all the rest of the world, even were mankind to number
          twice as many as now. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="262" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> “I am insatiable in my desire to speak on the present occasion and I still have many
          things which I might say concerning you and these two cities and your discourse, but I
          shall forgo these subjects and declare myself only upon the question about which, as you
          say, you called me in to advise you. I counsel you, then, not to burn or to suppress your
          discourse, but—if there be any need of so doing—to revise and supplement it and then give
          to those who desire it the benefit of all the time and pains which you have spent upon its
          composition, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="263" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>if indeed you wish to gratify the worthiest among the Hellenes—those who are in truth
          devoted to culture and do not merely pretend to it—and to annoy those who secretly admire
          your writings above all others but malign your discourses before the crowds at the
          national festivals, in which those who sleep outnumber those who listen;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 5.12">Isoc. 5.12</bibl>.</note> for these
          speakers hope that if only they can hoodwink such audiences their own compositions will
          rival yours in popular favour, little realizing that their work is farther below the level
          of yours than the poets who have essayed to compose in the manner of Homer fall short of
          his reputation.” </p>
      </div>
      <div n="264" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When he had said these things and had asked those present to express their opinion on
          the question about which they had been called in, they did not merely accord him the
          applause with which they were wont to greet a clever speech but signified by tumultuous
          shouts that he had spoken excellently; they crowded around him, praised him, envied him,
          congratulated him, and found nothing to add to what he had said or to subtract therefrom,
          but showed that they were of his opinion and advised me to do the very thing which he had
          urged. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="265" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nor did I, for my part, stand silently by; on the contrary, I praised both his native
          ability and his training, although beyond that I uttered not a word about the sentiments
          which he had expressed, as to how his conjecture had hit upon my purpose or missed the
          mark, but let him remain of the same opinion which he had formed for himself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="266" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now as to the subject which I undertook to discuss, I think that I have said enough; for
          to review in detail the points which have been made<note anchored="true" resp="ed">As at
            the close of the <title>Address to Philip</title>.</note> not in keeping with discourses
          such as this. But I do wish to relate my personal experiences in relation to its
          composition. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="267" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I entered upon it at the age which I have already stated at the beginning.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 12.3">Isoc. 12.3</bibl>.</note> But when I
          had written half of it, I was attacked by a malady which it is not decorous to name,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Coray conjectures that the malady was dysentery.</note> but
          which is powerful enough to carry off in the course of three or four days not only older
          people but many in the prime of life. I battled against this disease without respite for
          three years, and I passed every day of that time with such devotion to my work that those
          who knew of my industry as well as those who learned of it from them admired me more
          because of this fortitude than because of the things for which I had formerly been
          praised. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="269" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>When, however, I had at length given up my work both because of my illness and of my age,
          certain of those who were in the habit of paying me visits, and who had read again and
          again the portion of my discourse which I had written, begged and urged me not to leave it
          half-finished or incomplete, but to work upon it for a short time and to give my thoughts
          to what remained to be done. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="269a" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>They did speak as men do who perfunctorily acquit themselves of a duty, but praised
          extravagantly what I had written, saying about it such things that if any people had heard
          them who were not my personal friends and kindly disposed towards me, they could not
          possibly have failed to suppose that my visitors were trying to make a fool of me and that
          I had lost my wits and was altogether a simpleton if I allowed myself to be persuaded of
          what they said. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="270" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But, although I had this feeling about the things which they made bold to state, I did
          allow myself to be persuaded (for why make a long story of it?) to occupy myself with the
          completion of the discourse, at a time when I lacked but three years of having lived a
          century and when I was in a state of infirmity such that anyone else similarly afflicted,
          so far from undertaking to write a discourse of his own, would not even be willing to
          listen to one worked out and submitted by another. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="271" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Why, then, have I gone into these matters? Not because I think that I should ask
          indulgence for the things which I have discussed—for I do not feel that I have spoken of
          them in a manner to require this—but because I desire both to relate my personal
          experiences and to commend those among my hearers who not only applaud this speech but
          prefer, as more weighty and more worthy of serious study, discourses which are composed
          for instruction and, at the same time, with finished art<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Such as this discourse or the <title>Panegyricus</title>. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.11"
              >Isoc. 4.11</bibl>.</note> to others which are written for display or for the
            law-courts,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Speeches which were written for
            display—epideictic oratory—are composed with finish but are not instructive. See General
            Introduction. Speeches written for the law-courts, on the other hand, lack the
            refinements of style and aim to pervert the truth. See General Introduction.</note> and
          who prefer for the same reason discourses which aim at the truth to those which seek to
          lead astray the opinions of their auditors, and discourses which rebuke our faults and
            admonish<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Such as the <bibl n="Isoc. 8">Isoc. 8</bibl>.
            See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.62">Isoc. 15.62</bibl>.</note> us to those which are spoken for
          our pleasure and gratification.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.54"
              >Isoc. 2.54</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="272" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I desire, on the other hand, to warn those of my hearers who are of a mind contrary to
          these, in the first place, not to trust in their own opinions nor to regard as true the
          judgements which are pronounced by the lazy-minded and, in the second place, not to
          publish hastily their views on things which they do not understand, but to wait until they
          can find themselves in accord with men who have much experience of matters submitted to
          them for judgement;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Literally, “experience of things
            shown.” Others render “experience in epideictic oratory.”</note> for if they will so
          govern their thoughts, no one can fail to approve their discretion.</p>
      </div>
    </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
