<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Phormio</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>The request that I shall make of you, men of the jury, is a fair one, that you
                    should hear us with goodwill as we speak in our turn,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Others, less probably, render, “as we take our turns in
                        addressing you.”</note> knowing well that we are wholly without experience
                    in the art of speaking; and long as we have been frequenting your mart, and many
                    as are the merchants to whom we have made loans, we have never until now
                    appeared in any suit before you either as plaintiffs or as defendants. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>And you may be sure, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    that we should not even now have brought this action against Phormio, if we
                    believed that the money which we lent him had been lost on the ship that was
                    wrecked; we are not so shameless nor so unaccustomed to losses. But as many have
                    kept taunting us, and especially those who were in <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                        >Bosporus</placeName> with Phormio, who knew that he had not lost the money
                    together with the ship, we thought it a dreadful thing not to seek redress after
                    being wronged as we had been by this man. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>With reference to the special plea my argument is a brief one. For even the
                    defendants do not absolutely deny that a contract was made on your exchange<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The word rendered “exchange” or “market,” may
                        well designate merely the Peiraeus, which was in a very real sense the
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)mpo/rion</foreign> of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note>; but they claim that
                    there exists no longer any obligation on their part due to the contract, for
                    they have done nothing that contravenes the terms of the agreement. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>The laws, however, in accordance with which you sit as jurors, do not use this
                    language. They do indeed allow the production of a special plea when there has
                    been no contract at all at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> or
                    for the Athenian market; but if a man admits that a contract was made, yet
                    contends that he has done everything that the contract requires, they bid him to
                    make a defence on the merits of the case, and not to make the plaintiff a
                        defendant.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">As happened, of course, when a
                        plea in bar of action was introduced.</note> Not but that I hope to prove
                    from the facts of the case itself that this suit of mine is admissible. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>And I beg you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to
                    consider what is admitted by these men, and what is disputed; for in this way
                    you will best sift the question. They admit that they borrowed the money, and
                    that they had contracts made to secure the loan; but they claim that they have
                    paid the money to Lampis, the servant of Dio, in <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                        >Bosporus</placeName>. We, on our part, shall prove, not only that Phormio
                    did not pay it, but that it was actually impossible for him to pay it. But I
                    must recount to you a few of the things that happened at the outset. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>I, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, lent to this man,
                    Phormio, twenty minae for the double voyage to <placeName key="tgn,7016619"
                        >Pontus</placeName> and back, on the security of goods of twice that
                        value,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Such seems the most probable meaning
                        of the disputed phrase.</note> and deposited a contract with Cittus the
                    banker. But, although the contract required him to put on board the ship goods
                    to the value of four thousand drachmae, he did the most outrageous thing
                    possible. For while still in the Peiraeus he, without our knowledge, secured an
                    additional loan of four thousand five hundred drachmae from Theodorus the
                    Phoenician, and one of one thousand drachmae from Lampis the shipowner. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>And, whereas he was bound to purchase at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> a cargo worth one hundred and fifteen minae,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If the loans were all made on the same basis
                        (i.e. on the security of goods of a value twice as great as the loan) we
                        should have to read one hundred and fifty instead of one hundred and
                        fifteen, as the combined loans amounted to seventy-five minae. It is
                        possible, however, that Theodorus and Lampis, whose loans were for the
                        outward voyage only, and who sailed with Phormio, accepted a lower rate than
                        that demanded by Chrysippus and his partner, who remained in <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> if he was to perform for
                    all his creditors what was written in their agreements, he purchased only a
                    cargo worth five thousand five hundred drachmae, including the provisions; while
                    his debts were seventy-five minae. This was the beginning of his fraud, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; he neither furnished
                    security, nor put the goods on board the ship, although the agreement absolutely
                    bade him do so.Take the agreement, please.<quote n="Agreement">
                        <title>Agreement</title>
                    </quote>Now take also the entry made by the customs-officers and the
                        depositions.<quote n="Entry of the Customs">
                        <title>Entry of the Customs</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>When he came, then, to <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, having
                    letters from me, which I had given him to deliver to my slave, who was spending
                    the winter there, and to a partner of mine,—in which letter I had stated the sum
                    which I had lent and the security, and bade them, as soon as the goods should be
                    unshipped, to inspect them and keep an eye on them,—the fellow did not deliver
                    to them the letters which he had received from me, in order that they might know
                    nothing of what he was doing; and, finding that business in <placeName
                        key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName> was bad owing to the war which had
                    broken out between Paerisades<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The King of
                            <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>.</note> and the
                    Scythian, and that there was no market for the goods which he had brought, he
                    was in great perplexity; for his creditors, who had lent him money for the
                    outward voyage, were pressing him for payment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>When, therefore, the shipowner bade him put on board according to the agreement
                    the goods bought with my money, this fellow, who now alleges that he has paid
                    the debt in full, said that he could not ship the goods because his trash was
                    unsalable; and he bade him put to sea, saying that he himself would sail in
                    another ship as soon as he should dispose of the cargo</p>
                <p>Please take this deposition.<quote n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>After this, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, the
                    defendant was left in <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, while
                    Lampis put to sea, and was shipwrecked not far from the port; for although his
                    ship was already overloaded, as we learn, he took on an additional deck-load of
                    one thousand hides, which proved the cause of the loss of the vessel. He himself
                    made his escape in the boat with the rest of Dio's servants, but he lost more
                    than thirty<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The MS. reading is <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">triako/sia</foreign> (300), but it is most unlikely that
                        there were so many persons on board, unless this was a slave ship. Such an
                        aspiration, however, seems improbable, and does not accord well with the
                        statement that there was much mourning in <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                            >Bosporus</placeName> over the disaster.</note> lives besides the cargo.
                    There was much mourning in <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>
                    when they learned of the loss of the ship, and everybody deemed this Phormio
                    lucky in that he had not sailed with the others, nor put any goods on board the
                    ship. The same story was told by the others and by Phormio himself.Read me,
                    please, these depositions.<quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>Lampis himself, to whom Phormio declares he had paid the gold (pray note this
                    carefully), when I approached him as soon as he had returned to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> after the shipwreck and asked him
                    about these matters, said that Phormio did not put the goods on board the ship
                    according to our agreement, nor had he himself received the gold from him at
                    that time in <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>.Read, please, the
                    deposition of those who were present.<quote n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>Now, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, when this man
                    Phormio reached <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, after
                    completing his voyage in safety on another ship, I approached him and demanded
                    payment of the loan. And at the first, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, he did not in any instance make the statement which he
                    now makes, but always agreed that he would pay; but after he had entered into an
                    agreement with those who are now at his side and are advocates with him, he was
                    then and there different and not at all the same man. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>When I saw that he was trying to cheat me, I went to Lampis and told him that
                    Phormio was not doing what was right nor paying back the loan; and at the same
                    time I asked him if he knew where Phormio was, in order that I might summon him.
                    He bade me follow him, and we found the fellow at the perfumery shops; and I,
                    having witnesses with me, served the summons. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Lampis, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, was close at
                    hand when I did this, yet he never ventured to say that he had received the
                    money from Phormio, nor did he say, as he naturally would have done supposing
                    his story to be true, “Chrysippus, you are mad. Why do you summon this man? He
                    has paid me the money.” And not only did Lampis not say a word, but neither did
                    Phormio himself venture to say anything, although Lampis was standing by his
                    side, to whom he now declares he had paid the money. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Yet, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, it would surely
                    have been natural for him to say, “Why do you summon me, fellow? I have paid the
                    money to this man who is standing here ”—and at the same time to call upon
                    Lampis to corroborate his words. As it was, however, neither of them uttered a
                    syllable on an occasion so opportune.</p>
                <p>In proof that my words are true, take, please, the deposition of those who
                    witnessed the summons.<quote n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>Now take the complaint in the action which I commenced against him last year, for
                    this is the strongest possible proof that up to that time Phormio had never
                    stated that he had paid the money to Lampis.<quote n="Complaint">
                        <title>Complaint</title>
                    </quote>This action I commenced, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, basing my complaint upon nothing else than the report
                    of Lampis, who denied that Phormio had put the goods on board the ship or that
                    he himself had received the money. Do not imagine that I am so senseless, so
                    absolutely crazy, as to have drawn up a complaint like this, if Lampis (whose
                    words would prove my contention false) admitted that he had received the money.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>More than this, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, note
                    another fact. These very men entered a special plea last year, but dared not
                    assert in their plea that they had paid the money to Lampis.Now, pray take the
                    plea itself.<quote n="Special Plea">
                        <title>Special Plea</title>
                    </quote>You hear, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.
                    Nowhere in the plea is it stated that Phormio had paid the money to Lampis,
                    though I had expressly written in the complaint, which you heard a moment ago,
                    that Phormio had not put the goods on board the ship nor paid the money. For
                    what other witness, then, should you wait, when you have so significant a piece
                    of evidence from these men themselves? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>When the suit was about to come into court, they begged us to refer it to an
                    arbitrator; and we referred it by agreement to Theodotus, a privileged
                        alien<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The word is used of one who, though
                        an alien, paid only the taxes paid by citizens without the addition of the
                        special tax on aliens.</note> Lampis after that, thinking that it would now,
                    before an arbitrator, be safe for him to testify just as he pleased, divided my
                    money with this fellow Phormio, and then gave testimony the very opposite of
                    what he had stated before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>For it is not the same thing, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, to give false testimony while face to face with you and
                    to do so before an arbitrator. With you heavy indignation and severe penalty
                    await those who bear false witness; but before an arbitrator they give what
                    testimony they please without risk and without shame. When I expostulated and
                    expressed strong indignation, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, at the effrontery of Lampis, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>and produced before the arbitrator the same testimony as I now produce before
                    you—that, namely, of the persons who at the first went to him with me, when he
                    stated that he had not received the money from Phormio, and that Phormio had not
                    put the goods on board the ship—Lampis, being so plainly convicted of bearing
                    false witness and of playing the rogue, admitted that he had made the statement
                    to my partner here,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">I take the phrase <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">pro\s tou=ton</foreign> with <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >ei)rhke/nai</foreign>, assuming that the reference is to the partner of
                        Chrysippus, who apparently takes the latter's place as speaker at the
                        beginning of the next paragraph.</note> but declared that he was out of his
                    mind when he made it. Now read me this deposition.<quote n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">It is commonly assumed that the second speaker
                        begins with this paragraph. In <bibl n="Dem. 34.23">Dem. 34.23</bibl>
                        Chrysippus is referred to as <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou(=tos</foreign>, so
                        the fact of a change of speakers is patent.</note> Theodotus, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, after hearing us several
                    times, and being convinced that Lampis was giving false testimony, did not
                    dismiss the suit, but referred us to the court. He was loth to give an adverse
                    decision because he was a friend of this man Phormio, as we afterwards learned,
                    yet he hesitated to dismiss the suit lest he should himself commit perjury. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>Now, in the light of the facts themselves, consider in your own minds, men of the
                    jury, what means the man was likely to have for discharging the debt. He sailed
                    from this port without having put the goods on board the ship, and having no
                    adequate security; on the contrary, he had made additional loans on the credit
                    of the money lent by me. In <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName> he
                    found no market for his wares, and had difficulty in getting rid of those who
                    had lent money for the outward-voyage. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>My partner here had lent him two thousand drachmae for the double voyage on terms
                    that he should receive at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> two
                    thousand six hundred drachmae; but Phormio declares that he paid Lampis in
                        <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName> one hundred and twenty
                    Cyzicene staters<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The stater of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Cyzicus">Cyzicus</placeName> (a town on the south shore of
                        the Propontis, or sea of Marmora) was a coin made of electrum, an alloy of
                        approximately three-quarters gold and one-quarter silver. It was nearly
                        twice as heavy as the ordinary gold stater, which was worth twenty drachmae,
                        and had a value (as stated in the text) of twenty-eight drachmae. The
                        addition of the word “there” indicates that the value differed in different
                        places according to the rate of exchange.</note>(note this carefully) which
                    he borrowed at the interest paid on loans secured by real property. Now interest
                    on real security was sixteen and two-thirds percent, and the Cyzicene stater was
                    worth there twenty-eight Attic drachmae. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>It is necessary that you should understand how large a sum he claims to have
                    paid. A hundred and twenty staters amount to three thousand three hundred and
                    sixty drachmae, and the interest at the land rate of sixteen and two-thirds
                    percent on thirty-three minae and sixty drachmae is five hundred and sixty
                    drachmae, and the total amount comes to so much.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">That is, of course, the sum of the two items, or three
                        thousand nine hundred and twenty drachmae. The total is not mentioned here,
                        as it is given in the lines immediately following. Note that the speaker
                        inexactly speaks as if the whole sum (including the interest) had been paid
                        to Lampis (according to Phormio's claim). The argument is, however, valid,
                        as the sum represents the cost to Phormio of paying off the loan.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>Now, men of the jury, is there a man, or will the man ever be born, who, instead
                    of twenty-six hundred drachmae would prefer to pay thirty minae and three
                    hundred and sixty drachmae, and as interest five hundred and sixty drachmae by
                    virtue of his loan, both which sums Phormio says he has paid Lampis, in all
                    three thousand nine hundred and twenty drachmae? And when he might have paid the
                    money in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, seeing that it had
                    been lent for the double voyage, has he paid it in <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                        >Bosporus</placeName>, and too much by thirteen minae? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>And to the creditors who lent money for the outward voyage you had difficulty in
                    paying the principal, though they sailed with you and kept pressing you for
                    payment; yet to this man who was not present, you not only returned both
                    principal and interest, but also paid the penalties arising from the
                        agreement<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">We learn from <bibl
                            n="Dem. 34.33">Dem. 34.33</bibl> that the contract entailed a penalty of
                        five thousand drachmae in case a return cargo was not shipped, but of course
                        payment could not have been exacted in <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                            >Bosporus</placeName>. The speaker seems to identify the overpayment of
                        one thousand three hundred and twenty drachmae with this penalty; but the
                        “overpayment” represents almost exactly the amount of the money Lampis had
                        loaned to Phormio, plus the thirty percent interest. It is, of course,
                        possible that the penalty of five thousand drachmae was to be paid if
                        Phormio neither shipped the goods nor paid Lampis, and the lesser sum if
                        payment was made to Lampis without the shipment of a return cargo.</note>
                    though you were under no necessity of doing so? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>And you had no fear of those men, to whom their agreements gave the right of
                    exacting payment in <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, but
                    declare that you had regard for the claims of my partner, though you wronged him
                    at the outset by not putting on board the goods according to your agreement in
                    setting out from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>? And now
                    that you have come back to the port where the loan was made, you do not hesitate
                    to defraud the lender, though you claim to have done more than justice required
                    in <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, where you were not likely
                    to be punished? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>All other men who borrow for the outward and homeward voyage, when they are about
                    to set sail from their several ports, take care to have many witnesses present,
                    and call upon them to attest that the lender's risk begins from that moment<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, from the moment of sailing.</note>; but
                    you rely upon the single testimony of the very man who is your partner in the
                    fraud. You did not bring as a witness my slave who was in <placeName
                        key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName> or my partner, nor did you deliver to
                    them the letters which we gave into your charge, and in which were written
                    instructions that they should keep close watch on you in whatever you might do!
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>Why, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, what is there
                    which a man of this stamp is not capable of doing, who, after receiving letters,
                    did not deliver them in due and proper course? Or how can you fail to see that
                    his own acts prove his guilt? Surely (O Earth and the Gods) when he was paying
                    back so large a sum, and more than the amount of his loan, it was fitting that
                    he should make it a much talked of event on the exchange and to invite all men
                    to be present; but especially the servant and partner of Chrysippus. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>For you all know, I fancy, that men borrow with few witnesses, but, when they
                    pay, they take care to have many witnesses present, that they may win a
                    reputation for honesty in business dealings. But in your case, when you were
                    paying back both the debt and the interest on both voyages, though you had used
                    the money for the outward voyage only, and were adding thirteen minae besides,
                    should you not have caused many witnesses to be present? Had you done so, there
                    is not a single merchant who would have been held in higher esteem than you.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>But, as it was, instead of securing many witnesses to these acts you did
                    everything you could that none should know, as though you were committing some
                    crime! Again, had you been making payment to me, your creditor, in person, there
                    would have been no need of witnesses, for you would have taken back the
                    agreement and so got rid of the obligation; whereas in making payment, not to
                    me, but to another on my behalf, and not at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> but in <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                    >Bosporus</placeName>, when your agreement was deposited at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and with me, and when the man to
                    whom you paid the money was mortal and about to undertake a voyage over such a
                    stretch of sea, you called no one as a witness, whether slave or freeman. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>Yes, he says, for the agreement bade me pay the cash to the shipowner.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This is best explained by assuming that the
                        contract gave Phormio the right to pay the money to Lampis in <placeName
                            key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, if he did not ship a return
                        cargo to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> But it
                    did not prevent you from summoning witnesses, or from delivering the letters!
                    The parties here present<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The reference is not
                        wholly clear. It may be that others than Chrysippus and his partner had
                        contributed to the sum lent to Phormio.</note> drew up two agreements with
                    you in the matter of the loan, showing that they greatly distrusted you, but you
                    assert that without a single witness you paid the gold to the shipowner,
                    although you well know that an agreement against yourself was deposited at
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> with my colleague here!
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>He says that the agreement bids him pay back the money, “when the ship reaches
                    port in safety.” Yes, and it bids you also to put on board the ship the goods
                    purchased, or else to pay a fine of five thousand drachmae. You ignore this
                    clause in the agreement, but after having from the first violated its provisions
                    by failing to put the goods on board, you raise a dispute about a single phrase
                    in it, though you have by your own act rendered it null and void. For when you
                    state that you did not put the goods on board in <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                        >Bosporus</placeName>, but paid the cash to the shipowner, why do you still
                    go on talking about the ship? For you have had no share in the risk, since you
                    put nothing on board. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>At first, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, he seized
                    upon this excuse, pretending that he had shipped the goods; but when he saw that
                    the falsity of this claim was likely to be exposed in many ways,—by the entry
                    filed with the harbor-masters in <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                        >Bosporus</placeName>, and by the testimony of those who were staying in the
                    port at the same time—then he changes his tack, enters into a conspiracy with
                    Lampis, and declares that he has paid him the money in cash, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>finding a support for his plea in the fact that the agreement so ordered, and
                    thinking that we should not find it easy to get at the truth regarding all that
                    they did by themselves alone. And Lampis declares that all that he said to
                        me<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Either the speaker was with Chrysippus
                        at the time Lampis made this statement, or else Chrysippus is now again the
                        speaker.</note> before he was corrupted by this Phormio was spoken when he
                    was out of his head; but as soon as he got a share of my money, he declares that
                    he is in his right mind and remembers everything perfectly! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>Now, men of the jury, if it were toward myself only that Lampis were showing
                    contempt, it would be nothing to cause surprise; but in reality he has acted far
                    more outrageously than Phormio toward you all. For when Paerisades had published
                    a decree in <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName> that whoever
                    wished to transport grain to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
                    for the Athenian market might export it free of duty, Lampis, who was at the
                    time in <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, obtained permission
                    to export grain and the exemption from duty in the name of the state; and having
                    loaded a large vessel with grain, carried it to Acanthus<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">A town in Chalcidicê.</note> and there disposed of it,—he,
                    who had made himself the partner of Phormio here with our money. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>And he did this, men of the jury, though he was resident at Athens, and had a
                    wife and children here, and although the laws have prescribed the severest
                    penalties if anyone resident at Athens should transport grain to any other place
                    than to the Athenian market; besides, he did this at a critical time, when those
                    of you who dwelt in the city were having their barley-meal measured out to them
                    in the Odeum,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">We learn from <bibl
                            n="Aristoph. Wasps 1109">Aristoph. Wasps 1109</bibl>, that the Odeum,
                        built by Pericles as a music school, near the great theatre, was sometimes
                        used as a law-court, and <bibl n="Poll. 8.33">Pollux 8.33</bibl>, states
                        that suits concerning grain were decided there. Compare <bibl n="Dem. 59.52"
                            >Dem. 59.52</bibl>. It is easy, therefore, to assume that distribution
                        of grain may have been made there.</note> and those who dwelt in Peiraeus
                    were receiving their loaves at an obol each in the dockyard and in the
                        long-porch,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The long-porch was a warehouse
                        for grain in the Peiraeus.</note> having their meal measured out to them a
                        gallon<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Literally a half-sixth (i.e.
                        one-twelfth) of a medimnus, a measure containing about twelve
                        gallons.</note> at a time, and being nearly trampled to death.In proof that
                    my words are true, take, please, the deposition and the law.<quote
                        n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>Phormio, then, with the help of this fellow as his accomplice and witness, thinks
                    proper to rob us of our money—us, who have continually brought grain to your
                    market, and who in three crises which have come upon the state, during which you
                    put to the test those who were of service to the people, have not once been
                    found wanting. Nay, when Alexander entered Thebes,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">In <date when="-0355">355</date> B.C.</note> we made you a
                    free gift of a talent in cash; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>and when grain earlier advanced in price and reached sixteen drachmae, we
                    imported more than ten thousand medimni of wheat, and measured it out to you at
                    the normal price of five drachmae a medimnus, and you all know that you had this
                    measured out to you in the Pompeium.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was a
                        hall near the Dipylon, in which the dresses and other properties used in the
                        Panathenaic procession (<foreign xml:lang="grc">pomph/</foreign>) were
                        kept.</note> And last year my brother and I made a free gift of a talent to
                    buy grain for the people.Read, please, the depositions which establish these
                        facts.<quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>Surely, if any inference may be based upon these facts, it is not likely that we
                    should freely give such large sums in order to win a good name among you, and
                    then should bring a false accusation against Phormio in order to throw away even
                    the reputation for honorable dealing which we had won. It is right, therefore,
                    that you should come to our aid, men of the jury. I have shown you that Phormio
                    in the first place did not put on board the vessel goods to the value of all the
                    loans which he had secured at Athens, and that with the proceeds from the goods
                    sold in Bosporus he with difficulty satisfied his creditors who had lent money
                    for the outward voyage; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>further, that he was not well off, and not so foolish as to pay thirty-nine minae
                    instead of twenty-six hundred drachmae; and besides all this, that when, as he
                    says, he paid the money to Lampis he summoned neither my slave nor my partner,
                    who was at the time in Bosporus, as a witness. Again, Lampis himself is shown to
                    have testified to me, before he was corrupted by Phormio, that he had not
                    received the money. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>Yet,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The speaker is about to return to the
                        argument that the special plea was inadmissible. He says, in effect, I have
                        shown that Phormio is guilty. If he had been able to prove his case as
                        clearly (i.e. in the suit as instituted) it would have been his best
                        defence. He could not do so, and therefore had recourse to a special plea,
                        arguing that my suit could not be brought into court. This, however, is
                        inadmissible, and his course in entering it proves that he had no
                        defence.</note> if Phormio were thus to prove his case point by point, I do
                    not see what better defence he could have made. But that the action is
                    admissible the law itself solemnly declares, when it maintains that mercantile
                    actions are those for contracts made at Athens or for the Athenian market, and
                    not only those made at Athens, but all that are made for the purpose of a voyage
                    to Athens.Please take the laws.<quote n="Laws">
                        <title>Laws</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>That the contract has been entered into between Phormio and myself at Athens even
                    our opponents themselves do not deny, but they enter a special plea alleging
                    that the action is not admissible. But to what tribunal shall we come, men of
                    the jury, if not to you, since it was here in Athens that we made our contract?
                    It would be hard indeed that, if a wrong had been done me in connection with a
                    voyage to Athens, I should be able to get satisfaction from Phormio in your
                    court, but, when the contract has been made in your market, these men should say
                    that they will not be tried before you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>When we referred the case to Theodotus for arbitration, they admitted that my
                    action against them was admissible; but now they say what is the direct opposite
                    of what they have themselves before admitted; as if, forsooth, it were proper
                    that they should be tried before Theodotus, the privileged alien, without a
                    special plea, but, when we enter the Athenian court, the action should no longer
                    be admissible. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>I for my part am trying to conceive what in the world he would have written in
                    the special plea, if Theodotus had dismissed the suit, when now, after Theodotus
                    has decreed that we should go into court, he declares that the action is not one
                    that can be brought before you, to whom Theodotus bade us go.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">If, under the present circumstances, Phormio's insolence is
                        so great, who can say what it would have been, had the arbitrator decided in
                        his favor?</note> Surely I should suffer most cruel treatment if, when the
                    laws declare that suits growing out of contracts made at Athens shall be brought
                    before the Thesmothetae, you, who have sworn to decide according to the laws,
                    should dismiss the suit. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>That we lent the money is attested by the agreement, and by Phormio himself; that
                    it has been repaid is attested by no one except Lampis, who is an accomplice in
                    the crime. Phormio claims to prove the payment on the testimony of Lampis alone,
                    but I adduce Lampis and those who heard him declare that he had not received the
                    money. Further, Phormio is in a position to bring my witnesses to trial, if he
                    maintains that their testimony is false, but I have no means of dealing with his
                    witnesses, who say they know that Lampis testified that he had received the
                    money. If Lampis's own deposition had been put into court,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">When the arbitrator determined that the case before him
                        should be tried in court, he sealed in two jars, or boxes (<foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">e)xi=noi</foreign>), all documents bearing upon the case.
                        One of these was assigned to either party in the suit, and only such
                        depositions, citations of laws, or challenges, as were contained in them,
                        might be introduced at the trial.</note> these men would perhaps have said
                    that I ought to prosecute him for giving false testimony; but, as it is, I have
                    not this deposition, and Phormio thinks he should get off unscathed, since he
                    has left no valid security for the verdict which he urges you to pronounce.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Phormio relies upon the testimony of Lampis.
                        Under the circumstances it is impossible for me to sue Lampis for perjury,
                        in which case Phormio might be prosecuted for collusion. He therefore hopes
                        to get off scot-free.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>Would it not indeed be absurd if, when Phormio admits that he borrowed, but
                    alleges that he has made payment, you should make of none effect that which he
                    himself admits and by your vote give effect to what is under dispute? And if,
                    when Lampis, on whose testimony my opponent relies, after at first denying that
                    he had received the money, now testifies to the contrary, you should determine
                    that he has received it, although there are no witnesses to support the fact?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>And if you refuse to admit as proofs all that he truthfully stated, and should
                    count more worthy of belief the lies which he told after he had been corrupted?
                    Verily, men of Athens, it is far more just to draw conclusions from statements
                    made in the first instance than from those subsequently fabricated; for the
                    former he made truthfully, and not with ulterior purpose, while the later ones
                    are lies designed to further his interests. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>Remember, men of Athens, that even Lampis himself never denied saying that he had
                    not received the money; he admitted that he so stated, but declared he was not
                    in his right mind at the time. But would it not be absurd for you to accept as
                    worthy of credit that part of his testimony which favors the defrauding party,
                    and to discredit that which favors the party defrauded? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>Nay, men of the jury, I beg you, do not do this. You are the same persons who
                    punished with death, when he had been impeached before the assembly, a man who
                    obtained large additional loans on your exchange, and did not deliver to his
                    creditors their securities, though he was a citizen and the son of a man who had
                    been general. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>For you hold that such people not only wrong those who do business with them, but
                    also do a public injury to your mart; and you are right in holding this view.
                    For the resources required by those who engage in trade come not from those who
                    borrow, but from those who lend; and neither ship nor shipowner nor passenger
                    can put to sea, if you take away the part contributed by those who lend. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>In the laws there are many excellent provisions for their protection. It is your
                    duty to show that you aid the laws in righting abuses, and that you make no
                    concession to wrongdoers, in order that you may derive the greatest possible
                    benefit from your market. You will do so, if you protect those who risk their
                    money, and do not allow them to be defrauded by monsters such as these.I have
                    said all that it was in my power to say. But I am ready to call another of my
                    friends, if you so bid.</p>
            </div>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
