<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Pantaenetus </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>Inasmuch as the laws, men of the jury, have granted that a special plea be
                    entered in cases where a man, after having given a release and discharge,
                    nevertheless brings suit, and as both of these have been given me by Pantaenetus
                    here, I have pleaded, as you have just now heard, that his suit is not
                    admissible. I did not think that I should forgo this right, or that, after I had
                    proved among other things that the plaintiff had released me, and that I had got
                    rid of him, it should be open to him to declare that I was uttering a falsehood
                    and to try to employ the argument that, if any such release had been granted me,
                    I should have put in a special plea to bar his suit. No, I determined to come
                    before you relying on this plea and to prove both points—that I have never done
                    the plaintiff any wrong, and that he is suing me contrary to law. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>If Pantaenetus had suffered any of the wrongs with which he now charges me, he
                    would be found to have brought suit against me at the time when the contract
                    between us was made, for these actions must be decided within the month,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, within a month from the time of filing
                        the suit; “the object being that the mine-proprieter might not be too long
                        detained from his business.” (Boeckh, quoted by Sandys).</note> and both
                    Evergus and I were in town; since all men are wont to be most indignant at the
                    very time of their wrongs, and not after a period has intervened. Since,
                    however, the plaintiff, though he has suffered no wrong, as I know well you will
                    yourselves agree when you have heard the facts, elated by the success of his
                    suit against Evergus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Evergus and Nicobulus, as
                        stated in the Introduction, had leased the mining property to Pantaenetus.
                        As the lessee failed to pay the interest, Evergus, in the absence of
                        Nicobulus, who had gone abroad, took possession of the property and even
                        seized some silver which a slave of Pantaenetus was bringing to his master
                        that he might make a payment due to the state. Because of this Pantaenetus
                        became a debtor to the state and was required to pay double the amount due.
                        He then sued Evergus, and won a verdict of two talents damages.</note>
                    brings a malicious and baseless action, there is no other course left me, men of
                    the jury, than to prove in your court that I am guilty of no wrong whatever, to
                    produce witnesses in support of what I say, and to endeavor to save myself. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>I shall make a reasonable and fair request of you all, that you hear with
                    goodwill what I have to say regarding my special plea, and that you give your
                    attention to every aspect of the case. For, while hosts of cases have been tried
                    in Athens, I think it will be shown that no man has ever brought before you one
                    so marked by shamelessness and malice as this, which this fellow has had the
                    audacity to bring into your court. I shall with all possible brevity set before
                    you all the facts of the case. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>Evergus and I, men of the jury, lent to this man Pantaenetus one hundred and five
                    minae on the security of a mining property in Maroneia<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Maroneia was a small district in the mining area of Laurium
                        in Attica.</note> and of thirty slaves. Of this loan forty-five minae
                    belonged to me, and a talent to Evergus. It happened that the plaintiff also
                    owed a talent to Mnesicles of Collytus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Collytus
                        was a deme of the tribe Aegeïs.</note> and forty-five minae to Phileas of
                    Eleusis and Pleistor. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>The vendor to us of the mining property and the slaves was Mnesicles, for he had
                    purchased them for the plaintiff from Telemachus, the former owner; and the
                    plaintiff leased them from us at a rent equal to the interest accruing on the
                    money, a hundred and five drachmae a month. We drew up an agreement in which the
                    terms of the lease were stated, and the right was given the plaintiff of
                    redeeming these things from us within a given time. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>When these transactions had been completed in the month of Elaphebolion in the
                    archonship of Theophilus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, in March
                            <date when="-0347">347</date> B.C.</note> I at once sailed away for
                    Pontus, but the plaintiff and Evergus remained here. What transactions they had
                    with one another while I was away, I cannot state, for they do not tell the same
                    story, nor is the plaintiff always consistent with himself; sometimes he says
                    that he was forcibly ousted from his leasehold by Evergus in violation of the
                    agreement; sometimes that Evergus was the cause of his being inscribed as a
                    debtor to the state;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note on <bibl
                            n="Dem. 37.2">Dem. 37.2</bibl> and the Introduction.</note> sometimes
                    anything else that he chooses to say. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>But Evergus tells a plain and consistent story, that since he was not receiving
                    his interest, and the plaintiff was not performing any of the other things
                    stipulated in the agreement, he went and took from the plaintiff, with the
                    latter's consent, what was his own, and kept it; that after this the plaintiff
                    went away, but came back bringing men to make claim to the property; that he on
                    his own part did not give way in their favour, but made no objection to the
                    plaintiff's holding that for which he had given a lease, provided he should
                    observe the terms of the agreement. From these men, then, I hear stories of this
                    sort. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>This, however, I know well, that, if the plaintiff speaks the truth, and has been
                    outrageously treated, as he says, by Evergus, he has had satisfaction to the
                    amount at which he himself assessed his damages; for he came into your court and
                    won his suit against him; and surely he has no right to obtain damages for the
                    same wrongs both from the one who committed them and from me, who was not even
                    in Athens. But, if it is Evergus who speaks the truth, he has been made the
                    object, it appears, of a baseless and malicious charge; but even so there is no
                    ground for my being sued on the same charge.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To
                    prove, in the first place, that I am speaking the truth in this, I shall bring
                    before you the witnesses to establish these facts.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>That, therefore, the man who sold us the property was the man who had been the
                    original purchaser; that under the agreement the plaintiff rented the mining
                    establishment and the slaves, recognizing them as belonging to us; that I was
                    not present at the transactions which subsequently took place between the
                    plaintiff and Evergus, and indeed was not even in Athens; that he brought suit
                    against Evergus, and never made any charge against me,—all this, men of the
                    jury, you hear from the witnesses. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>Well, then, when I came back, having lost practically everything I had when I
                    sailed, I heard, and found it was true, that the plaintiff had given up the
                    property and that Evergus was in possession and control of what we had
                    purchased. I was distressed beyond words, seeing that the matter had got into an
                    awkward predicament; for it was now necessary for me either to enter into
                    partnership with Evergus for the working and management of the property, or have
                    him for a debtor instead of Pantaenetus, and draw up a new lease and enter into
                    a contract with him; and I liked neither of these alternatives. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>Being vexed at the matters of which I am telling you, and happening to see
                    Mnesicles, who had sold us the property, I came up to him, and reproached him,
                    telling what sort of a man he had recommended to me, and I questioned him
                    regarding the claimants, asking what this was all about. On hearing this, he
                    laughed at the claimants, but stated that they wished to have a conference with
                    us. He declared that he would bring us together, and that he would urge the
                    plaintiff to do all that was right in my regard, and he thought he would
                    persuade him to do so. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>When we had our meeting—what need is there to tell you all the details?—the men
                    came who claimed to have made loans to the plaintiff on the security of the
                    mining property and the slaves, which we bought from Mnesicles; and there was
                    nothing straightforward or honest about them. Then, when they were convicted of
                    falsehood in all their statements and Mnesicles confirmed our having bought the
                    property, they offered us a challenge, assuming that we should not accept it,
                    either to take all our money from them and withdraw, or to settle with them by
                    paying their claims; for the security which we held was, they claimed, worth far
                    more than the sums we had lent. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>When I heard this, on the spur of the moment and without even taking thought, I
                    agreed to take my money, and I persuaded Evergus to adopt the same course. But
                    when the time came for us to receive our money, the matter having been brought
                    to this conclusion, the people who had previously made the offer declared then
                    that they would not pay us unless we became vendors to them of the property, and
                    in this point anyway, men of Athens, they were prudent; for they saw in what
                    baseless and malicious charges we were involved by this fellow.To prove that I
                    am speaking the truth in this, take, please, these depositions also.<quote
                        type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>When the matter stood thus, and the people whom the plaintiff had introduced to
                    us would not give up the money, and it was clear that we were rightfully in
                    possession of what we had purchased, he begged, and implored, and besought us to
                    sell the property. As he made this demand and begged me most earnestly—there is
                    nothing he did not do—I gave way in this matter also. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>I saw, however, men of Athens, that he was a man of evil disposition, that at the
                    outset he had made charges to us against Mnesicles, and then had quarrelled with
                    Evergus, with whom he was on terms of closest friendship; that at the first,
                    when I returned from my voyage, he pretended that he was glad to see me, but
                    when the time came for him to do what was right, he became surly with me; that
                    he was a friend to all men until he got some advantage and attained what he
                    wanted, and thereafter became their foe and was at variance with them; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>I therefore thought it best, if I withdrew and assumed the position of vendor in
                    this man's interest, that I should obtain a full release and discharge from all
                    claims, and thus make a final settlement with him. This was agreed to, and he
                    gave me a release in full, while I, as he begged me to do, assumed the position
                    of vendor of the property, exactly as I had myself bought it from Mnesicles.
                    Having, then, recovered my money, and having done the plaintiff no wrong
                    whatsoever, I imagined, by the gods, that, no matter what should happen, he
                    would never bring a suit against me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>These, men of the jury, are the facts regarding which you are to cast your votes,
                    these are the grounds upon which I have entered the special plea that this
                    baseless and malicious suit is not maintainable. I shall bring forward witnesses
                    who were present when I was given a release and discharge by the plaintiff, and
                    shall then proceed to prove that under the law the suit is not
                    maintainable.Please read this deposition.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>Now, please, read the deposition of the purchasers, that you may be
                    assured that I sold the property at the bidding of the plaintiff and to the
                    persons to whom he bade me sell it.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>Not only have I these witnesses to prove that I have been released and am now the
                    object of a baseless and malicious charge, but Pantaenetus himself is a witness
                    also. For when, in bringing suit against Evergus, he left me out of the
                    question, he himself bore witness that he had no further claim against me. For
                    surely, assuming that he had the same charge to bring against both for the same
                    wrongdoing, he would not, when both were at hand, have passed over the one and
                    brought suit against the other. However, that the laws do not allow a fresh suit
                    to be brought regarding matters that have been thus settled you know, I presume,
                    even without my telling you.Nevertheless, read them this law also.<quote
                        type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>You hear the law, men of Athens, expressly stating that in cases where anyone has
                    given a release and discharge, there shall be no further action. And that both
                    these have been effected between the plaintiff and myself, you have heard from
                    the witnesses. One should not, of course, bring suit in any case when the law
                    forbids it, but least of all ought one in a case like this. For in regard to
                    sales made by the state, one might claim that it had made the sale unjustly, or
                    had sold what was not its own; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>and in regard to court decisions it might be claimed that the decision had been
                    rendered through error; and in all other cases where the law forbids action
                    exception might plausibly be taken to each one. But when anyone has himself
                    yielded to argument and given a release, he cannot in the very nature of the
                    case charge himself with having acted unjustly. Those who bring suit in defiance
                    of any other of these provisions fail to abide by what others have determined to
                    be just; but he who again brings suit in matters regarding which he has given a
                    release fails to abide by his own decision. Therefore, against all such your
                    anger should be particularly severe. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then, that he released me from all claims,
                    when I sold the slaves to him, I have proved to you; and that the laws do not
                    allow suits to be brought in such cases you have heard from the law which has
                    just been read. However, that no one of you, men of Athens, may suppose that it
                    is because I am at a disadvantage regarding the rights of the matters at issue
                    that I have recourse to this special plea, I propose to show you that in every
                    one of his charges against me his statements are false. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>Read the complaint itself, which he brings against me.<quote type="Complaint"
                            ><title>Complaint</title>Nicobulus has harmed me by laying a plot
                        against me and against my property, having ordered Antigenes, his slave, to
                        take away from my slave the silver which he was bringing to be paid to the
                        state for the mining property which I bought for ninety minae,<note
                            resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Presumably the amount due to the state for
                            the purchase of the mine, though the sum differs from the amount secured
                            by the mortgage.</note> and having also caused me to be inscribed as
                        debtor to the treasury for double that amount.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>Stop reading. All these charges which he has now lodged against me he previously
                    made against Evergus, and won his suit. Now evidence has been brought before you
                    in the opening of my speech that I was not in the country when these men
                    quarrelled with one another; but the fact is clear from the complaint itself.
                    For he nowhere stated that I have done any of these things, but, suggesting that
                    I laid a plot against him and against his property, he declares that I ordered
                    my slave to commit these acts; and in this he lies. For how could I have given
                    this order, seeing that at the time I set sail I could by no possibility have
                    had knowledge of what was going to happen here? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>And then how absurd when he says that I plotted to disenfranchise him and bring
                    him to utter ruin, to have written in the charge that I ordered a slave to do
                    this,—a thing which even a citizen could not do to another citizen.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, disenfranchisement could come only by
                        act of the state itself.</note> What, then, is the meaning of this? I
                    suppose that, being unable to refer to me the doing of any of these acts, but
                    wishing to go on with his malicious suit, he wrote in the complaint that I had
                    given the order. There was no sense in his charge, if he had not done this. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>Read what follows.<quote type="Complaint"><title>Complaint</title><milestone
                            ed="P" unit="para"/>And after I had become a debtor to the state, having
                        stationed his slave Antigenes in my mining property at Thrasyllus,<note
                            resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A site in Maroneia, so called from a
                            monument of Thrasyllus which stood there.</note> in full control of my
                        works, although I forbade him . . .</quote>Stop reading. In all this he will
                    again be convicted of falsehood by the facts themselves; for he has written in
                    the complaint that I stationed the slave and that he forbade me. But this was
                    impossible in the case of one who was not in the country. Neither did I station
                    anyone, seeing that I was in Pontus, nor did he forbid a man who was not in
                    Athens. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>How could he? What was it, then, that forced him to make this statement? I fancy
                    that Evergus, at the time he made the mistakes<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >A euphemism for the violence and lawlessness with which Evergus had been
                        charged by Pantaenetus.</note> for which he has paid the penalty, being on
                    friendly terms with me and well known, took the slave from my house and
                    stationed him at his own works to keep guard. If, then, he had written the
                    truth, it would have been ridiculous. For, if Evergus stationed the slave there,
                    wherein do I wrong you? It was to avoid this absurdity that he was compelled to
                    write as he did, that his charge might be directed against me.Read what
                        follows.<quote type="Complaint"><title>Complaint</title>And then having
                        persuaded my slaves to sit in the foundry<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >The precise meaning of <foreign xml:lang="grc">kegxrew/n</foreign>
                            cannot be determined. It seems to have denoted either the pit into which
                            the silver was run when melted, or the furnace in which it was
                            refined.</note> to my prejudice.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>This is out-and-out impudence. Not only from my challenging him to give up these
                    slaves for torture and from his refusing to do so, but from every circumstance
                    of the case its falsehood is manifest. Why, pray, should I have induced them to
                    do this? That, forsooth, I might get possession of them. But when the option was
                    given me either to keep the property or to recover my money, I chose to recover
                    my money; and of this you have heard the evidence.Nevertheless, read the
                        challenge.<quote type="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>Although he did not accept the challenge, but declined it, see what a charge he
                    makes immediately thereafter.Read what comes next.<quote type="Complaint"
                            ><title>Complaint</title>And having reduced the silver-ore which my
                        slaves had dug, and keeping the silver smelted from that ore.</quote>Again,
                    how could this have been done by me when I was not here?—things, too, for which
                    you won a judgement against Evergus? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Read the further charges.<quote type="Complaint"
                            ><title>Complaint</title>And having sold my mining property and the
                        slaves, contrary to the agreement which he had made with me.</quote>Stop
                    reading. This far outdoes all the rest. For in the first place he says,
                    “contrary to the agreement which he had made with me.” What agreement is this?
                    We leased our own property to this man, at a rent equal to the interest on the
                    loan; that was all. It was Mnesicles who sold it to us, in the presence of the
                    plaintiff and at his request. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>Afterwards in the same way we sold the property to others on the same terms upon
                    which we had ourselves bought it, and the plaintiff not only urged but actually
                    implored us to do so; for no one was willing to accept him as the vendor. What,
                    then, does the agreement to lease it have to do with the matter? Why, most
                    worthless of men, did you insert that clause?<milestone ed="P" unit="para"
                    />However, to prove that we resold the property at your request, and on the same
                    terms as those upon which we ourselves bought it, read the deposition.<quote
                        type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>You are yourself also a witness to this; for what we purchased for one hundred
                    and five minae, this you afterward sold for three talents and twenty-six hundred
                    drachmae. And yet who, if he had you<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The title
                        was not vested in Pantaenetus, but in the other claimants to whom it had
                        been transferred at his request.</note> as one to complete a final sale,
                    would have given a single drachma?To prove that I speak the truth in this, call,
                    please, the witnesses who establish the facts.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>He has, then, received the sum which he agreed to take for his property,—he even
                    begged me that I should assume the position of vendor for the sum which I had
                    advanced—yet this same man sues me for two talents more. And the rest of the
                    charges are even more outrageous.Read, please, the remainder of the
                        complaint.<quote type="Complaint">
                        <title>Complaint</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>Here he brings against me in one mass a host of dreadful charges; for he accuses
                    me of assault and battery, outrage, and of violent wrongs even against
                        heiresses.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl n="Dem. 37.45">Dem.
                            37.45</bibl>; and compare the oration against Meidias (<bibl
                            n="Dem. 21.79">Dem. 21.79</bibl>).</note> But for each of these
                    wrongdoings actions are separate; they do not come before the same magistrates
                    and they are not for the recovery of the same penalties. Assault and battery and
                    crimes of violence come before the Forty<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">“The
                        Forty” were circuit judges.</note>; cases of outrage before the
                    Thesmothetae; and all crimes against heiresses before the Archon.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, the chief archon.</note> And the laws
                    grant the filing of pleas to bar action also in case of charges brought before
                    magistrates who have not due competency.Read them this law.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>Although I had entered this exception in bar of action in addition to the other,
                    and although the Thesmothetae have not competency in the matters concerning
                    which Pantaenetus is bringing his suit, it has been erased, and is not found in
                    the plea as written. How this has come about it is for you to consider.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">He hints that the omission of the exception
                        filed by him was not an accident.</note> To me, so long as I am able to
                    produce the law itself, it makes not the slightest difference; for he will not
                    be able to erase from your minds your power to know and understand the right.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Take also the mining law. For I think I can show
                    you from this, too, that the action is not maintainable, and that I deserve
                    thanks rather than to be made the object of a baseless and malicious
                        charge.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Read.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>This law has clearly defined in what cases mining actions may properly
                    be brought. Observe—the law makes a man liable if he eject another from his
                    workings; but I, far from ejecting the plaintiff, gave over to him and put him
                    in possession of that of which another was seeking to deprive him; and I became
                    the vendor of it at his request. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>Yes, says he, but if one commit other wrongs concerning mines, for these, too,
                    actions may be brought. Certainly, Pantaenetus; but what are these? If one
                    smokes out another, if one makes an armed attack, if one makes cuttings which
                    encroach upon another's workings. These are the other cases; but I, of course,
                    have done nothing of this sort to you, unless you hold that people who seek to
                    recover what they had risked in a loan to you are making an armed attack. If you
                    hold that view, you have mining suits against all those who risk their own
                    money. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>But there is no justice in that. For consider—if a man purchases a mine from the
                    state, shall he disregard the general laws in accordance with which all men are
                    bound to render and obtain justice, and bring suit in a mining court, if he
                    borrows from another?—if he be evil spoken of?—if he be beaten?—if he charge one
                    with theft?—if he fail to recover money advanced for another's tax?—if, in
                    short, he has any other ground for action? I think not. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>Mining suits, in my judgement, are to be brought against those sharing in the
                    business of mining and those who have bored through into another's property,
                    and, in short, against those engaged in mining who do any of the things
                    mentioned in the law. But a man who has lent money to Pantaenetus, and by
                    persistently sticking to him has with difficulty got it back, is not also to be
                    made defendant in a mining suit; I should say not! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>That I have, therefore, done no wrong to the
                    defendant and that the suit is not admissible under the laws one may easily
                    determine from a consideration of these points. So, as he had not a single valid
                    argument to advance in support of his charges, but had even incorporated false
                    statements in his complaint, and was bringing suit regarding claims for which he
                    had given a release, last month, men of Athens, when I was on the point of
                    entering the court, and the court-rooms had already been allotted to the
                    jurymen, he came up to me and surrounded me with his minions (that gang of his
                    fellow-conspirators), and did a most outrageous thing. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>He read me a long challenge, demanding that a slave who, he claimed, was
                    acquainted with the facts, should be put to the torture; and that, if the facts
                    as alleged by him were true, I should have to pay him the damages charged
                    without adjustment by the jury; but if they were false, Mnesicles, the torturer,
                    should determine the value of the slave. When he had received sureties to this
                    agreement from me and I had sealed the challenge (not that I thought it fair;
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>for how could it be fair that it should depend upon the body and life of a slave,
                    whether I should be condemned to pay two talents, or the bringer of this
                    malicious suit get off scot-free? But I, wishing to prevail by a preponderance
                    of fair play, made this concession)—after this he again summoned me in the suit,
                    as soon as he had taken back his deposits;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >There is much obscurity here. The acceptance of the challenge by Nicobulus
                        should have put an end to the action. The plaintiff had then the right to
                        take back the sum deposited (as court-fees <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >prutanei=a</foreign>?) when the suit was brought.</note> so clear did
                    he make it at once that he would not abide by the conditions which he had
                    himself laid down. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>But when we had come before the torturer, instead of opening the challenge,
                    showing its contents, and proceeding in accordance with its terms to do what
                    seemed right (for on account of the turmoil at that time and the fact that the
                    case was about to be called, it was like this: I offer you this challenge.—I
                    accept it.—Let me have your ring.—Take it.—Who is your surety?—This man
                    here.—and I had taken no copy or anything else of that sort); instead of acting
                    in the way of which I speak, he had brought with him a different challenge,
                    insisting that he should himself torture the man, and he laid hold of him,
                    dragged him this way and that, and went beyond all bounds in blackguardly
                    action. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>On my part, men of the jury, I was led to reflect what gain there is in a life
                    molded to serve one's ends.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">His own desire to
                        live simply and naturally had caused him to be imposed upon, and to be
                        despised as one lacking in spirit. The passage is variously interpreted, and
                        the text is uncertain. The MSS. have <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >katapeplh=xqai</foreign>, which yields no satisfactory sense, unless
                        with Wolf we insert the negative <foreign xml:lang="grc">mh/</foreign>. The
                        meaning in that case would be that a life of ruthless self-assertion is a
                        “great gain.”</note> For it seemed to me that I was suffering this treatment
                    because I was despised as one who lived a simple and natural life, and that I
                    was paying a heavy penalty in having to submit to this.<milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/>However, to prove that I was compelled to give a
                    counter-challenge contrary to what I thought was right, that I offered to give
                    up the slave, and that I am speaking the truth in this, read the
                        challenge.<quote type="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>Since he refused this, and refused the challenge which he himself gave at the
                    first, I wonder what in the world he will have to say to you. But that you may
                    know who it is at whose hands he claims to have suffered these
                    indignities—behold him!<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Here the speaker
                        effectively brings before the jury the slave, Antigenes—a feeble, old
                        man.</note> This is the man who dispossessed Pantaenetus; this is the man
                    who was stronger than the friends of Pantaenetus, and stronger than the laws.
                    For I myself was not in Athens; even he does not make that charge. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>I wish to tell you also the means by which he misled the former jury, and
                    convicted Evergus, that you may realize that in this trial also there will be no
                    limit to his impudence and that he will shrink from no falsehoods. More than
                    this; in regard to his present suit against me, you will find my means of
                        defence<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Possibly, “the charges against
                        me.”</note> are the same as those of Evergus, which is the most convincing
                    proof that Evergus has been the victim of a malicious and baseless charge. For
                    in addition to all the other accusations the plaintiff charged that Evergus came
                    to his home in the country, and made his way into the apartments of his
                    daughters, who were heiresses, and of his mother; and he brought with him into
                    court the laws concerning heiresses. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>And yet up to this day he has never had the case examined before the Archon, whom
                    the law appoints to have charge of such matters, and before whom the wrongdoer
                    runs the risk of having punishment or fine adjudged against him, while by the
                    prosecutor redress is sought without risk;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Whereas in the court the plaintiff ran the risk of having to pay the heavy
                        penalty of the <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pwboli/a</foreign>, if he failed to
                        make good his case. See note on <bibl n="Dem. 27.67">Dem.
                        27.67</bibl>.</note> nor has he impeached either me or Evergus as
                    wrongdoers, but he made these charges in the court-room, and secured a verdict
                    for two talents. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>For, I take it, it would have been an easy matter for Evergus, if he had known in
                    advance (as under the laws he should have known) the charge on which he was
                    being tried, to set forth the truth of the matter and the justice of his cause,
                    and so win acquittal; but in a mining suit regarding matters concerning which he
                    could never have imagined that he would be accused, it was hard to find,
                    offhand, means to free himself from the false charges; and the indignation<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Due to the alleged intrusion into the women's
                        apartment.</note> of the jurymen, who were misled by the plaintiff, found
                    him guilty in the matter upon which they sat in judgement. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>And yet do you think that the man who deceived those jurymen will hesitate to try
                    to deceive you?—or that he comes into court with his confidence fixed upon the
                    facts, and not rather upon assertions and upon the witnesses who are in league
                    with him (that foul blackguard Procles, the tall fellow there, and Stratocles,
                    the smoothest-tongued of men and the basest), and in his readiness to weep and
                    wail without disguise or shame? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>But you are so far from deserving pity, that more than any man in the world you
                    should rightly be detested for the deeds you have wrought—you who, owing one
                    hundred and five minae and not being able to satisfy your creditors, and then
                    finding men who helped you to raise the money and enabled you to do what was
                    right by those who originally made the loan, are seeking, quite apart from the
                    wrongs you committed against them in regard to the loan itself, also to deprive
                    them of their civic rights. In the case of other men one may see borrowers
                    having to give up their property, but in your case it is the lender who has come
                    to this plight, and, having lent a talent, has been forced to pay two talents as
                    the victim of a baseless charge; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>and I, who lent forty minae, am defendant in this suit for two talents. Again, on
                    property on which you were never able to borrow more than one hundred minae, and
                    which you sold outright for three talents and two thousand drachmae,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, in round numbers. In <bibl
                            n="Dem. 37.31">Dem. 37.31</bibl> the sum is given as three talents,
                        twenty-six hundred drachmae.</note> you have, as it seems, sustained damages
                    to the amount of four talents! From whom? From my slave, you will say. But what
                    citizen would let himself be ousted from his own property by a slave? Or who
                    would say that it is right that my slave be held responsible for acts, for which
                    the plaintiff has brought action against Evergus and obtained a verdict? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>Besides all this, the plaintiff has himself given him a release from all charges
                    of this kind. He ought not to be stating these charges now, nor to have inserted
                    them in the challenge in which he demanded the slave for torture, but to have
                    instituted suit against him, and to have prosecuted me as his owner. As it is,
                    he has instituted suit against me, but accuses him. This the laws do not permit.
                    For whoever instituted suit against the master, and charged the facts against
                    his slave—as though the slave had any authority of his own? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>When anyone asks him, “What valid charges will you be able to make against
                    Nicobulus?” he says, “The Athenians hate money-lenders; Nicobulus is an odious
                    fellow; he walks fast,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Compare Oration <bibl
                            n="Dem. 45.77">Dem. 45.77</bibl>.</note> he talks loud, and he carries a
                    cane; and (he says) all these things count in my favor.” He is not ashamed to
                    talk in this way, and also fancies that his hearers do not understand that this
                    is the reasoning, not of one who has suffered wrong, but of a malicious
                    pettifogger. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>I, for my part, do not regard a money-lender as a wrongdoer, although certain of
                    the class may justly be detested by you, seeing that they make a trade of it,
                    and have no thought of pity or of anything else, except gain. Since I have
                    myself often borrowed money, and not merely lent it to the plaintiff, I know
                    these people well; and I do not like them, either but, by Zeus, I do not defraud
                    them, nor bring malicious charges against them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>But if a man has done business as I have, going to sea on perilous journeys, and
                    from his small profits has made these loans, wishing not only to confer favors,
                    but to prevent his money from slipping through his fingers without his knowing
                    it, why should one set him down in that class?—unless you mean this, that anyone
                    who lends money to you ought to be detested by the public.Read me, please, the
                    depositions, to show what manner of man I am to those who lend money, and to
                    those who need my help.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>Such am I, Pantaenetus, the fast walker, and such are you, who walk slowly.
                    However, regarding my gait and my manner of speech, I will tell you the whole
                    truth, men of the jury, with all frankness. I am perfectly aware—I am not blind
                    to the fact—that I am not one of those favored by nature in these respects, nor
                    of those who are an advantage to themselves. For if in matters in which I reap
                    no profit, I annoy others, surely I am to this extent unfortunate. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>But what is to come of it? If I lend money to so-and-so, am I for this reason
                    also to lose my suit? Surely not. The plaintiff cannot point out any baseness or
                    villainy attaching to me, nor does a single one among you, many as you are, know
                    any such thing against me. As to these other qualities, each one of us, I take
                    it, is as nature happened to make him; and to fight against nature, when one has
                    these characteristics, is no easy task (for otherwise we should not differ from
                    one another); though to recognize them in looking on another and to criticize
                    them is easy. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>But which one of these qualities has any bearing on my dispute with you,
                    Pantaenetus? You have suffered many grievous wrongs? Well, you have had
                    satisfaction. Not from me? No; for you were not wronged in any way by me.
                    Otherwise you would never have given me the release, nor, when you were making
                    up your mind to bring suit against Evergus, would you have passed me by; nor
                    would you have demanded that one who had done you many grievous wrongs should
                    undertake to be vendor of the property. Besides, how could I have wronged you,
                    when I was not present or even in the country? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>Well then, suppose<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The following passage is
                        repeated almost verbatim in the next oration, <bibl n="Dem. 38.21">Dem.
                            38.21-22</bibl>.</note> one should grant that Pantaenetus has suffered
                    the greatest possible wrongs, and that everything which he will now allege about
                    these matters is true, this, at least, I presume, you would all admit: that it
                    has happened to others ere now to have suffered many wrongs more serious than
                    pecuniary wrongs. For involuntary homicides, outrages on what is sacred, and
                    many other such crimes are committed; yet in all these cases the fact that they
                    have yielded to persuasion and given a release is appointed for the parties
                    wronged as a limit and settlement of the dispute. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>And this just principle is so binding among all men, that if anyone having
                    convicted another of involuntary homicide, and clearly shown him to be
                        polluted,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Homicide, even if accidental,
                        entailed pollution, which required expiation.</note> subsequently takes pity
                    on him and releases him, he has no longer the right to have the same person
                    driven into exile. Again, if the victim himself before his death releases the
                    murderer from bloodguiltiness, it is not lawful for any of the remaining kinsmen
                    to prosecute; but those whom the laws sentence to banishment and exile and
                    death, upon conviction, if they are once released, are by that word freed from
                    all evil consequences. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>If, then, when life and all that is most precious are at stake, a release has
                    this power and validity, shall it be without effect when money is at stake, or
                    claims of lesser importance? Surely not. For the thing most to be feared is, not
                    that I should fail to obtain justice in your court, but that you should now in
                    our day do away with a just practice, established from the beginning of
                    time.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
