<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - Haggai</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <editor role="editor">Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor role="editor">
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                  <!-- <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>-->
             <refState unit="chapter"/><refState unit="verse"/></refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>14-Oct-99</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <resp>markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial markup from flat ASCII text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>5/27/09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>RS</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: world.english.xml,v $
			Revision 1.2  2010-06-29 22:00:29  student
			fixing place tags - AD

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:10:56  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.3  2009/05/27 16:11:31  rsingh04
			added/fixed cvs log keyword
                </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="Haggai" type="book">
                <head>Haggai</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        In the second year of Darius the king, in the sixth month, in
the first day of the month, the Word of Yahweh came by Haggai, the
prophet, to Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to
Joshua, the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "This is
what Yahweh of Hosts says: These people say, 'The time hasn't yet come,
the time for Yahweh's house to be built.'"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Then the Word of Yahweh came by Haggai, the prophet, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        "Is it a time for you yourselves to dwell in your paneled houses,
while this house lies waste?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Now therefore this is what Yahweh of
Hosts says: Consider your ways.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        You have sown much, and bring in
little. You eat, but you don't have enough. You drink, but you aren't
filled with drink. You clothe yourselves, but no one is warm, and he
who earns wages earns wages to put them into a bag with holes in it."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        This is what Yahweh of Hosts says: "Consider your ways.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Go up to the mountain, bring wood, and build the house. I will take
pleasure in it, and I will be glorified," says Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        "You
looked for much, and, behold, it came to little; and when you brought
it home, I blew it away. Why?" says Yahweh of Hosts, "Because of my
house that lies waste, while each of you is busy with his own house.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Therefore for your sake the heavens withhold the dew, and the
earth withholds its fruit.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        I called for a drought on the land,
on the mountains, on the grain, on the new wine, on the oil, on that
which the ground brings forth, on men, on cattle, and on all the labor
of the hands."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Then Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, and Joshua, the son of
Jehozadak, the high priest, with all the remnant of the people, obeyed
the voice of Yahweh, their God, and the words of Haggai, the prophet,
as Yahweh, their God, had sent him; and the people feared Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Then Haggai, Yahweh's messenger, spoke in Yahweh's message to
the people, saying, "I am with you," says Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Yahweh stirred up the spirit of Zerubbabel, the son of
Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and the spirit of Joshua, the son of
Jehozadak, the high priest, and the spirit of all the remnant of the
people; and they came and worked on the house of Yahweh of Hosts, their
God,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        in the twenty-fourth day of the month, in the sixth month,
in the second year of Darius the king.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        In the seventh month, in the twenty-first day of the month,
the Word of Yahweh came by Haggai the prophet, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Speak now
to Zerubbabel, the son of Shealtiel, governor of Judah, and to Joshua,
the son of Jehozadak, the high priest, and to the remnant of the
people, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        'Who is left among you who saw this house in its
former glory? How do you see it now? Isn't it in your eyes as nothing?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Yet now be strong, Zerubbabel,' says Yahweh. 'Be strong, Joshua,
son of Jehozadak, the high priest. Be strong, all you people of the
land,' says Yahweh, 'and work, for I am with you,' says Yahweh of
Hosts.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        This is the word that I covenanted with you when you came
out of Egypt, and my Spirit lived among you. Don't be afraid.'
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        For this is what Yahweh of Hosts says: 'Yet once, it is a little while,
and I will shake the heavens, the earth, the sea, and the dry land;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        and I will shake all nations. The precious things of all nations
will come, and I will fill this house with glory, says Yahweh of Hosts.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        The silver is mine, and the gold is mine,' says Yahweh of Hosts.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        'The latter glory of this house will be greater than the former,'
says Yahweh of Hosts; 'and in this place will I give peace,' says
Yahweh of Hosts."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        In the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, in the second
year of Darius, the Word of Yahweh came by Haggai the prophet, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        "Thus says Yahweh of Hosts: Ask now the priests concerning the
law, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        'If someone carries holy meat in the fold of his
garment, and with his fold touches bread, stew, wine, oil, or any food,
will it become holy?'"

   The priests answered, "No."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Then Haggai said, "If one who is unclean by reason of a dead
body touch any of these, will it be unclean?"

   The priests answered, "It will be unclean."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Then Haggai answered, "'So is this people, and so is this
nation before me,' says Yahweh; 'and so is every work of their hands.
That which they offer there is unclean.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Now, please consider
from this day and backward, before a stone was laid on a stone in the
temple of Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Through all that time, when one came to a heap
of twenty measures, there were only ten. When one came to the wine vat
to draw out fifty, there were only twenty.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        I struck you with
blight, mildew, and hail in all the work of your hands; yet you didn't
turn to me,' says Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        'Consider, please, from this day and
backward, from the twenty-fourth day of the ninth month, since the day
that the foundation of Yahweh's temple was laid, consider it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Is
the seed yet in the barn? Yes, the vine, the fig tree, the pomegranate,
and the olive tree haven't brought forth. From this day will I bless
you.'"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        The Word of Yahweh came the second time to Haggai in the
twenty-fourth day of the month, saying,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        "Speak to Zerubbabel,
governor of Judah, saying, 'I will shake the heavens and the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        I will overthrow the throne of kingdoms. I will destroy the
strength of the kingdoms of the nations. I will overthrow the chariots,
and those who ride in them. The horses and their riders will come down,
everyone by the sword of his brother.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        In that day, says Yahweh
of Hosts, will I take you, Zerubbabel, my servant, the son of
Shealtiel,' says Yahweh, 'and will make you as a signet, for I have
chosen you,' says Yahweh of Hosts."
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
