<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Precepts </title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1868</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>		
		<encodingDesc>
			
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
				<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Aph.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=intro">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Epid.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader><text xml:lang="en"><body>
				<pb n="p.313"/>
				<div type="section" n="1"><head>PART 1</head><p>I. T<hi rend="sc">IME</hi> is that wherein there is opportunity, and
					opportunity is that wherein there is no great time.
					Healing is a matter of time, but it is sometimes
					also a matter of opportunity. However, knowing
					this, one must attend in medical practice not
					primarily to plausible theories,<note>The definition shows that in this
						passage <foreign xml:lang="grc">LOGIS1MO/S2</foreign> is a
						generalisation, like the <foreign xml:lang="grc">PRO/LHYIS2</foreign> of Epicurus, whose language
						is borrowed. But whereas <foreign xml:lang="grc">PRO/LHYIS2</foreign> corresponds to a general
						<hi rend="ital">term</hi> (<hi rend="ital">e. g.</hi> " man "), <foreign xml:lang="grc">LOGIS1MO/S2</foreign> here seems to mean a
						general
						<hi rend="ital">proposition</hi> (<hi rend="ital">e. g.</hi> " man is mortal "). Later on it means the
						use of <foreign xml:lang="grc">LOGIS1MOI/</foreign> in making <foreign xml:lang="grc">S1ULLOGIS1MOI/</foreign>, that is,
						deduction.
						" Theory " and "theorising " are the nearest equivalents I
						can think of.</note> but to experience
					combined with reason. For a theory is a
					composite memory of things apprehended with
					sense-perception. For the sense-perception, coming
					first in experience and conveying to the intellect
					the things subjected to it, is clearly imaged, and
					the intellect, receiving these things many times,
					noting the occasion, the time and the manner, stores
					them up in itself and remembers. Now I approve
					of theorising also if it lays its foundation in incident,
					and deduces its conclusions in accordance with phenomena.
					For if theorising lays its foundation in
					clear fact, it is found to exist in the domain of intellect,
					which itself receives from other sources each
					of its impressions. So we must conceive of our nature
					as being stirred and instructed under compulsion
					by the great variety of things ; and the intellect, as
					I have said, taking over from nature the impressions,
					leads us afterwards into truth. But if it</p>
					<pb n="p.315"/>
					<p>begins, not from a clear impression, but from a
						plausible fiction,<note><hi rend="ital">I. e.,</hi> if the general statement from which
							we deduce
							conclusions be a plausible but untrue hypothesis. Conclusions
							drawn from such hypotheses lead to nowhere.</note> it often induces a grievous
						and
						troublesome condition. All who so act are lost in a
						blind alley. Now no harm would be done if bad
						practitioners received their due wages. But as it is
						their innocent patients suffer, for whom the violence
						of their disorder did not appear sufficient without
						the addition of their physician's inexperience. I
						must now pass on to another subject.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="2"><head>PART 2</head><p>II. But conclusions which are merely verbal cannot
					bear fruit, only those do which are based on demonstrated
					fact. For affirmation and talk are deceptive
					and treacherous. Wherefore one must hold fast to
					facts in generalisations also,<note>Or, possibly, " even from beginning
						to end."</note> and occupy oneself with
					facts persistently, if one is to acquire that ready and
					infallible habit which we call " the art of medicine."
					For so to do will bestow a very great advantage
					upon sick folk and medical practitioners. Do not
					hesitate to inquire of laymen, if thereby there
					seems likely to result any improvement in treatment.
					For so I think the whole art has been set
					forth, by observing some part of the final end in
					each of many particulars, and then combining all
					into a single whole. So one must pay attention to
					generalities in incidents, with help and quietness
					rather than with professions and the excuses that
					accompany ill-success.</p>
					<pb n="p.317"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="3"><head>PART 3</head><p>III. Early determination of the patient's treatment--since
					only what has actually been administered
					will benefit ; emphatic assertion is of no
					use--is beneficial but complicated. For it is through
					many turns and changes that all diseases settle into
					some sort of permanence.<note>Because changes and turns are common in the
						early
						stages, to fix the proper treatment early is a complicated
						matter.</note></p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="4"><head>PART 4</head><p>IV. This piece of advice also will need our consideration,
					as it contributes somewhat to the whole.
					For should you begin by discussing fees, you will
					suggest to the patient either that you will go away
					and leave him if no agreement be reached, or that
					you will neglect him and not prescribe any immediate
					treatment. So one must not be anxious about fixing
					a fee. For I consider such a worry to be harmful
					to a troubled patient, particularly if the disease be
					acute. For the quickness of the disease, offering no
					opportunity for turning back,<note><hi rend="ital">I. e.</hi> from missed opportunities
						that have passed away
						while haggling over fees. It is possible that <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)NAS1TROFH/</foreign> has
						here the sense of <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)NAS1TRE/FEIN KARI/DAN</foreign> in Thucydides II. 49,
						" to upset." An acute disease is not the time to upset a
						patient with financial worries.</note> spurs on the good
					physician not to seek his profit but rather to lay
					hold on reputation. Therefore it is better to reproach
					a patient you have saved than to extort money from<note>Or, if Coray's
						emendation be adopted, " to tease."</note>
					those who are at death's door.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="5"><head>PART 5</head><p>V. And yet some patients ask for what is out of
					the way and doubtful, through prejudice, deserving
					indeed to be disregarded, but not to be punished.
					Wherefore you must reasonably oppose them, as
					they are embarked upon a stormy sea of change.</p>
					<pb n="p.319"/>
					<p>For, in heaven's name, who that is a brotherly<note>The word so
						translated is fairly common in the <hi rend="ital">Corpus</hi> in
						the sense of " related." Here it evidently means " a loyal
						member of the family of physicians."</note> physician
						practises with such hardness of heart as not at
						the beginning to conduct a preliminary examination
						of every illness<note>With Ermerins' reading, " all the illness."</note> and
						prescribe what will help towards
						a cure, to heal the patient and not to overlook the
						reward, to say nothing of the desire that makes a
						man ready to learn?</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="6"><head>PART 6</head><p>VI. I urge you not to be too unkind, but to consider
					carefully your patient's superabundance or
					means. Sometimes give your services for nothing,
					calling to mind a previous benefaction or present
					satisfaction.<note>Or, with <foreign xml:lang="grc">EU)DOKIMI/HN</foreign>, " your present
						reputation."</note> And if there be an opportunity of
					serving one who is a stranger in financial straits,
					give full assistance to all such. For where there is
					love of man, there is also love of the art. For some
					patients, though conscious that their condition is
					perilous, recover their health simply through their
					contentment with the goodness of the physician.
					And it is well to superintend the sick to make them
					well, to care for the healthy to keep them well, but
					also to care for one's own self, so as to observe what
					is seemly.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="7"><head>PART 7</head><p>VII. Now those who are buried in deep ignorance
					of the art cannot appreciate what has been said.
					In fact such men will be shown up as ignorant of</p>
					<pb n="p.321"/>
					<p>medicine, suddenly exalted yet needing good luck.
						For should wealthy men gain some remission of their
						trouble, these quacks win reputation through a
						double good fortune, and if a relapse occurs
						they stand upon their dignity, having neglected
						the irreproachable methods of the art, wherewith
						a good physician, a " brother of the art " as he is
						called, would be at his best. But he who accomplishes
						his cures easily without making a mistake
						would transgress none of these methods through want
						of power ;<note>He is trusted, and so can do as he likes. Therefore want
							of power to influence a patient never compels him to transgress
							the medical code.</note> for he is not distrusted on the ground of
						wickedness. For quacks do not attempt treatment
						when they see an alarming<note>It is quite uncertain whether
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">FLEBONW/DEA</foreign> is the correct
							reading, and equally uncertain what it means if it be correct.
							Erotian's note recognises two ancient readings, <foreign xml:lang="grc">FLEDONW/DEA</foreign>,
							explained as <foreign xml:lang="grc">TA\ META\ FLUARI/AS2 KAI\ PNEUMATW/DOUS2 TARAXH=S2
								E)KKRINO/MENA</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="grc">FLEBONW/DEA</foreign>, explained as <foreign xml:lang="grc">TA\ MET'
									A)LGH/MATOS2
									OI)DH/MATA</foreign>. But the general meaning must be " serious,"
							" alarming."</note> condition, and avoid
						calling in other physicians, because they wickedly
						hate help. And the patients in their pain drift on a
						sea of twofold wretchedness for not having intrusted
						themselves to the end to the fuller treatment that
						is given by the art. For a remission of a disease
						affords a sick man much relief. Wherefore wanting
						a healthy condition they do not wish always to submit
						to the same treatment, therein being in accord
						with a physician's versatility.<note>The reader must suspect that in the
							words <foreign xml:lang="grc">I)HTROU= POIKILI/H</foreign>
							is concealed an allusion to frequent changes of the medical
							attendant. " Changing their doctor every day." The
							version in the text means that the patients frequently
							change their minds as do quacks, or as doctors must be ready
							to change their treatment at a moment's notice.</note> For the patients</p>
					<pb n="p.323"/>
				<p>are in need through heavy expenditure, worshipping
						incompetence and showing no gratitude when they
						meet it ;<note>These patients <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)PORE/OUS1IN</foreign>, and so can scarcely be
							the same
							as the <foreign xml:lang="grc">EU)/POROI</foreign> of the earlier part of the chapter. Perhaps
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">OU)K</foreign> should be read before <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)XARIS1TE/ONTES2</foreign>, and the sense
							would
							then be, " they become poor by showing gratitude to quacks,
							when they might be well off by employing qualified men."</note> when they have
						the power to be well off,
						they exhaust themselves about fees, really wishing
						to be well for the sake of managing their investments
						or farms, yet without a thought in these matters to
						receive anything.<note>The greater part of this chapter is hopeless.
							There
							seems to be no connexion between the quack doctors of the
							first part and the wayward patients of the latter part. I
							suspect that an incongruous passage has been inserted here
							by some compiler, just as chapter fourteen was so inserted.
							Perhaps there are gaps in the text, the filling up of which
							would clear away the difficulty. Probably there is one after
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">EI(/NEKEN</foreign>. If the latter part be not an interpolation, the
							general meaning seems to be that when patients grow worse
							under quack treatment, they change their doctor and hire
							another quack. So they both grow worse and lose money.
							They really want to get well to look after their business,
							but do not think of the right way to return to work again,
							<hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> of employing a qualified medical man.</note></p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="8"><head>PART 8</head><p>VIII. So much for such recommendations. For
					remission and aggravation of a disease require respectively
					less or more medical assistance. A
					physician does not violate etiquette even if, being
					in difficulties on occasion over a patient and in the
					dark through inexperience, he should urge the calling
					in of others, in order to learn by consultation the
					truth about the case, and in order that there may
					be fellow-workers to afford abundant help. For
					when a diseased condition is stubborn and the evil
					grows, in the perplexity of the moment most things
					go wrong. So on such occasions one must be bold.<note>Or (reading
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">OU)</foreign>) " on such occasions one must not be
						self-confident."</note>
					For never will I lay it down that the art has been</p>
					<pb n="p.325"/>
				<p>condemned in this matter.<note><hi rend="ital">I. e.</hi> that because a consultant
						is necessary the fault lies
						with the art of medicine.</note> Physicians who meet
						in consultation must never quarrel, or jeer at one
						another. For I will assert upon oath, a physician's
						reasoning should never be jealous of another. To
						be so will be a sign of weakness. Those who act
						thus lightly are rather those connected with the
						business of the market-place. Yet it is no mistaken
						idea to call in a consultant. For in all abundance
						there is lack.<note>No matter how much help you have you can never have
							enough.</note></p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="9"><head>PART 9</head><p>IX. With all these things it will appear strong
					evidence for the reality of the art if a physician,
					while skilfully treating the patient, does not refrain
					from exhortations not to worry in mind in the
					eagerness to reach the hour of recovery. For we
					physicians take the lead in what is necessary for
					health. And if he be under orders the patient will
					not go far astray. For left to themselves patients
					sink through their painful condition, give up the
					struggle and depart this life. But he who has taken
					the sick man in hand, if he display the discoveries
					of the art, preserving nature, not trying to alter it,
					will sweep away the present depression or the distrust
					of the moment. For the healthy condition of
					a human being is a nature that has naturally attained
					a movement, not alien but perfectly adapted, having</p>
					<pb n="p.327"/>
				<p>produced it by means of breath, warmth and coction
						of humours, in every way, by complete regimen and
						by everything combined, unless there be some congenital
						or early deficiency. Should there be such a
						thing in a patient who is wasting, try to assimilate
						to the fundamental nature.<note><hi rend="ital">I. e.</hi> try to bring the patient
							back to his normal condition.</note> For the wasting, even
						of long standing, is unnatural.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="10"><head>PART 10</head><p>X. You must also avoid adopting, in order to gain a
					patient,<note>Apparently, in order to increase your practice by
						fastidiousness in the matter of dress. But the expression
						is very strange, and should mean, " in order to effect a cure."</note>
					luxurious headgear and elaborate perfume.
					For excess of strangeness will win you ill-repute, but
					a little will be considered in good taste, just as pain
					in one part is a trifle, while in every part it is serious.
					Yet I do not forbid your trying to please, for it is
					not unworthy of a physician's dignity.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="11"><head>PART 11</head><p>XI. Bear in mind the employment of instruments
					and the pointing out of significant symptoms, and
					so forth.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="12"><head>PART 12</head><p>XII. And if for the sake of a crowded audience
					you do wish to hold a lecture, your ambition is no
					laudable one, and at least avoid all citations from
					the poets, for to quote them argues feeble industry.
					For I forbid in medical practice an industry not
					pertinent to the art, and laboriously far-fetched,<note>See p. 308.</note>
					and which therefore has in itself alone an attractive
					grace. For you will achieve the empty toil of a
					drone and a drone's spoils.<note>See p. 308.</note></p>
					<pb n="p.329"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="13"><head>PART 13</head><p>XIII. A condition too is desirable free from the
					late-learner's faults. For his state accomplishes
					nothing that is immediate, and its remembrance
					of what is not before the eyes is but tolerable. So
					there arises a quarrelsome inefficiency, with headstrong
					outrage, that has no thought for what is
					seemly, while definitions, professions, oaths, great as
					far as the gods invoked are concerned,<note>That is, the oaths
						frantically appeal to all the great gods.</note> come from
					the physician in charge of the disease, bewildered
					laymen being lost in admiration of flowery language
					spoken in continuous reading and instruction,
					crowding together even before they are troubled by
					a disease.<note>The construction and translation are uncertain. I believe
						that <foreign xml:lang="grc">DRIS1MOI=S2</foreign> and the other datives are a Roman's efforts at
						rendering into Greek "ablatives of attendant circumstances,"
						but <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)K METAFORH=S2</foreign> is puzzling, and can hardly be taken with
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">LO/GONS2</foreign>. Perhaps it is a Latinism. Cf. "pastor ab Amphryso."</note>
					Wherever I may be in charge of a case,
					with no confidence should I call in such men to
					help as consultants. For in them comprehension of
					seemly learning is far to seek. Seeing then that they
					cannot but be unintelligent, I urge that experience
					is useful, the learning of opinions coming far after.
					For who is desirous and ambitious of learning truly
					subtle diversities of opinion, to the neglect of calm
					and practised skill? Wherefore I advise you to
					listen to their words but to oppose their acts.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="14"><head>PART 14</head><p>XIV. When regimen has been restricted you must</p>
					<pb n="p.331"/>
				<p>not suppress for long a long-standing desire of the
						patient.<note>Too strict a regimen may do harm by the patient's using
							up his strength in conquering his appetites. Some such verb
							as <foreign xml:lang="grc">KATE/XEIN</foreign> must be substituted for <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)GXEIREI=N</foreign>.</note> In a
						chronic disease indulgence too helps
						to set a man on his feet again, if one pay the
						necessary attention to one who is blind.<note><hi rend="ital">I. e.</hi> the patient
							does not know what is good for him.</note> As great
						fear is to be guarded against, so is excessive joy.
						A sudden disturbance of the air is also to be guarded
						against.<note><hi rend="ital">I. e.</hi> either (<hi rend="ital">a</hi>) a draught or (<hi rend="ital">b</hi>) a
							sudden change in
							the weather.</note> The prime of life has everything lovely,
						the decline has the opposite. Incoherence of speech
						comes from an affection, or from the ears, or from
						the speaker's talking of something fresh before he
						has uttered what was in his mind before, or from
						his thinking of fresh things before he has expressed
						what was in his thoughts before. Now this is a thing
						that happens without any "visible affection" socalled,
						mostly to those who are in love with their
						art. The power of youth, when the matter is
						trifling,<note>Possibly, "when the patient is not a big man."
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">U(POKEI/MENON</foreign>,
							can mean "patient" in later Greek.</note> is sometimes supremely great.
						Irregularity
						in a disease signifies that it will be a long one. A
						crisis is the riddance of a disease. A slight cause
						turns into a cure unless the affection be in a vital
						part. Because<note>Possibly, "for the same reason that."</note>
						fellow-feeling at grief causes distress,
						some are distressed through the fellow-feeling</p>
					<pb n="p.333"/>
				<p>of another. Loud talking is painful. Overwork
						calls for gentle dissuasion.<note><foreign xml:lang="grc">U(POPARAI/THS1IS2</foreign> is not found
							in the dictionaries, but may be
							correct.</note> A wooded<note><foreign xml:lang="grc">A)LUW/DHS2</foreign> is unmeaning, and I
								translate as though <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)LS1W/DHS2</foreign>
								were in the text.</note> district
								benefits.</p>
				</div>
			
			
			<pb n="p.337"/>
			</body></text></TEI>