<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Ignorant Book Collector</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor>Austin Morris Harmon, 1878-1950</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>OCRd, tagged and added initial corrections to  the text</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg001.1st1K-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1921</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202137">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">

<head>The Ignorant Book Collector<note>This too is a diatribe, an excellent illustration of that sort
of diatribe which made the word to us moderns synonymous
with invective. It is far from a school exercise, but was
directed against a real person, a Syrian (§19), evidently well
enough known to Lucian’s auditors. A scholiast (probably
Bishop Arethas, who was himself a book-collector) remarks :
“If I may guess, Lucian, you asked him for the loan of a
book, and when you did not get it, requited him with this
handsome token of your esteem!” It was written after the
death of Peregrinus Proteus and during the reign of Marcus
Aurelius, about170 A.D.</note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

Truly, what you are now doing is the reverse ot
what you are aiming to do. You expect to get a
reputation for learning by zealously buying up the
finest books, but the thing goes by opposites and in
a way becomes proof of your ignorance. Indeed,
you do not buy the finest ; you rely upon men who
bestow their praise hit-and-miss, you are a godsend to the people that tell such lies about books,
and a treasure-trove ready to hand to those who
traffic in them. Why, how can you tell what books
are old and highly valuable, and what are worthless
and simply in wretched repair<note n="v.3.p.175.n.1"><p>Not old, though they look old. </p></note>— unless you judge
them by the extent to which they are eaten into and
cut up, calling the book-worms into counsel to settle
the question ? As to their correctness and freedom
from mistakes, what judgement have you, and what
is it worth ?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

Yet suppose I grant you that you have selected the
very éditions de luxe that were prepared by Callinus
or by the famous Atticus with the utmost care.<note n="v.3.p.175.n.2"><p>Both Atticus and Callinus are mentioned again as scribes in this piece (24) ; Callinus is not elsewhere mentioned, but Atticus is supposed to be the “publisher” of the Atticiana, editions which had great repute in antiquity. It is hardly likely that he is Cicero’s friend.  </p></note>



<pb n="v.3.p.177"/>

What good, you strange person, will it do you to own
them, when you do not understand their beauty and
will never make use of it one whit more than a blind
man would enjoy beauty in favourites? To be sure you
look at your books with your eyes open and quite as
much as you like, and you read some of them aloud
with great fluency, keeping your eyes in advance of
your lips; but I do not consider that enough, unless
you know the merits and defects of each passage in
their contents, unless you understand what every
sentence means, how to construe the words, what
expressions have been accurately turned by the
writer in accordance with the canon of good use, and
what are false, illegitimate, and counterfeit.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="3"><p>

Come now, do you maintain that without instruction you know as much as we? How can you,
unless, like the shepherd of old,<note n="v.3.p.177.n.1"><p>Hesiod : see the Theogony29 ff. </p></note> you once received a
branch of laurel from the Muses? Helicon, which the
goddesses are said to haunt, you never even heard of,
I take it, and your haunts in your boyhood were not
the same as ours. That you should even mention
the Muses is impious. They would not have shrunk
from showing themselves to a shepherd, a hardbitten, hairy man displaying rich tan on his body,
but as for the like of you—in the name of your lady
of Lebanon<note n="v.3.p.177.n.2"><p>Aphrodite, perhaps, or Astarte; in later times there was a notorious cult of Aphrodite on Lebanon: Eusebius, Vit. Constantini 3, 53.   </p></note> dispense me for the present from giving
a full description of you in plain language !—they
would never have deigned, I am sure, to come near
you, but instead of giving you laurel they would have
scourged you with myrtle or sprays of mallow and
would have made you keep your distance from those



<pb n="v.3.p.179"/>

regions, so as not to pollute either Olmeios or
Hippocrene, whose waters only thirsty flocks or the
clean lips of shepherds may drink.</p>

<p>
No matter how shameless you are and how
courageous in such matters, you would never dare to
say that you have had an education, or that you ever
troubled yourself to associate intimately with books,
or that So-and-so was your teacher and you went to
school with So-and-so.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

You expect to make up for
all that now by one single expedient—by getting
many books. On that theory, collect and keep all
those manuscripts of Demosthenes that the orator
wrote with his own hand, and those of Thucydides
that were found to have been copied, likewise by
Demosthenes, eight times over, and even all the
books that Sulla sent from Athens to Italy.<note n="v.3.p.179.n.1"><p>Of the copies of his own works and those of Thucydides written by Demosthenes we have no other notice; Sulla took to Italy what was reported to have been the library of Aristotle : Plut. Sulla 26. </p></note> What
would you gain by it in the way of learning, even if
you should put them under your pillow and sleep
on them or should glue them together and walk
about dressed in them? “A monkey is always a
monkey,” says the proverb, “even if he has birthtokens of gold.”<note n="v.3.p.179.n.2"><p>These were trinkets put in the cradle or the clothing of a child when it was abandoned, as proof of good birth and as a possible means of identification later. Hyginus (187) calls them insignia ingenwitatis.   </p></note> Although you have a book in
your hand and read all the time, you do not understand a single thing that you read, but you are like
the donkey that listens to the lyre and wags his ears.</p>

<p>
If possessing books made their owner learned, they
would indeed be a possession of great price, and only
rich men like you would have them, since you could
buy them at auction, as it were, outbidding us poor




<pb n="v.3.p.181"/>

men. In that case, however, who could rival the
dealers and booksellers for learning, who possess and
sell so many books? But if you care to look into
the matter, you will see that they are not much
superior to you in that point; they are barbarous of
speech and obtuse in mind like you—just what one
would expect people to be who have no conception
of what is good and bad. Yet you have only two or
three books which they themselves have sold you,
while they handle books night and day.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="5"><p>

What good,
then, does it do you to buy them—unless you think
that even the book-cases are learned because they
contain so many of the works of the ancients !</p>

<p>
Answer me this question, if you will—or better,
as you are unable to answer, nod or shake your
head inreply. If a man who did not know how to
play the flute should buy the instrument of Timotheus
or that of Ismenias,<note n="v.3.p.181.n.1"><p>Famous Theban flute-players of the fourth century B.c. for Timotheus, see also Lucian’s Harmonides.  </p></note> for which [smenias paid seven
talents in Corinth, would that make him able to play,
or would it do him no good to own it since he did
not know how to use it as a musician would? You
did well to shake your head. Even if he obtained the
flute of Marsyas or Olympus, he could not play without previous instruction. And what if a man should
get the bow of Heracles without being a Philoctetes
so as to be able to draw it and shoot straight ? What
do you think about him? That he would make any
showing worthy of an archer? You shake your head
at this, too. So, of course, with a man who does not
know how to steer, and one who has not practised
riding ; if the one should take the helm of a fine
vessel, finely constructed in every detail both for
beauty and for seaworthiness, and the other should


<pb n="v.3.p.183"/>

get an Arab or a “Centaur” or a “Koppa-brand,”<note n="v.3.p.183.n.1"><p>The “Centaur” horses probably came from Thessaly, the home of the Centaurs and a land of good horses. The “Koppa-brand” were marked ϙ, which in the alphabet of Corinth corresponded to K, and was used (on coins, for instance) as the abbreviation for Korinthos.  </p></note>
each would give proof, I have no doubt, that he did
not know what to do with his property. Do you
assent to this? Take my advice, now, and assent to
this also; if an ignorant man like you should buy
many books, would he not give rise to gibes at himself for his ignorance? Why do you shrink from
assenting to this also? To do so is a clear giveaway, I maintain, and everybody who sees it at once
quotes that very obvious proverb: “What has a dog
to do with a bath ?”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

Not long ago there was a rich man in Asia, both of
whose feet had been amputated in consequence of
an accident; they were frozen, I gather, when he
had to make a journey through snow. Well, this of
course was pitiable, and to remedy the mischance he
had had wooden feet made for him, which he used to
lace on, and in that way made shift to walk, leaning
upon his servants as he did so, But he did one thing
that was ridiculous: he used always to buy very
handsome sandals of the latest cut and went to the
utmost trouble in regard to them, in order that his
timber toes might be adorned with the most beautiful footwear! Now are not you doing just the same
thing? Is it not true that although you have a
crippled, fig-wood<note n="v.3.p.183.n.2"><p>The most worthless sort of wood.  </p></note> understanding, you are buying
gilt buskins which even a normal man could hardly
get about in?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="7"><p>

As you have often bought Homer among your
other books, have someone take the second book of
his Iliad and read it to you. Do not bother about



<pb n="v.3.p.185"/>

the rest of the book, for none of it applies to you ;
but he has a description of a man making a speech,
an utterly ridiculous fellow, warped and deformed
in body.<note n="v.3.p.185.n.1"><p>Iliad2,212. </p></note> Now then, if that man, Thersites, should
get the armour of Achilles, do you suppose that he
would thereby at once become both handsome and
strong ; that he would leap the river, redden its stream
with Trojan gore, and kill Hector—yes, and before
Hector, kill Lycaon and Asteropaeus—when he cannot even carry the “ash tree”
on his shoulders?<note n="v.3.p.185.n.2"><p>Cf, Iliad 19, 387 fi  </p></note>
You will hardly say so. No, he would make himself
a laughing-stock, limping under the shield, falling on
his face beneath the weight of it, showing those
squint eyes of his under the helmet every time he
looked up, making the corselet buckle up with the
hump on his back, trailing the greaves on the ground
—disgracing, in short, both the maker of the arms
and their proper owner. Do not you see that the
same thing happens in your case, when the roll that
you hold in your hands is very beautiful, with a slipcover of purple vellum and a gilt knob, but in
reading it you barbarize its language, spoil its beauty
and warp its meaning? Men of learning laugh at
you, while the toadies who live with you praise you
—and they themselves for the most part turn to one
another and laugh!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="8"><p>

I should like to tell you of an incident that took
place at Delphi. A man of Tarentum, Evangelus
by name, a person of some distinction in Tarentum,
desired to obtain a victory in the Pythian games. As
far as the athletic competition was concerned, at the
very outset that seemed to him to be impossible, as



<pb n="v.3.p.187"/>

he was not well endowed by nature either for
strength or for speed; but in playing the lyre and
singing he became convinced that he would win
easily, thanks to detestable fellows whom he had
about him, who applauded and shouted whenever he
made the slightest sound in striking up. So he came
to Delphi resplendent in every way; in particular,
he had provided himself with a gold-embroidered
robe and a very beautiful laurel-wreath of gold,
which for berries had emeralds as large as berries.
The lyre itself was something extraordinary for
beauty and costliness, all of pure gold, ornamented
with graven gems and many-coloured jewels, with
the Muses and Apollo and Orpheus represented
upon it in relief—a great marvel to all who saw it.<note n="v.3.p.187.n.1"><p>Compare the version of this story given in the Rhetorica ad Herennium 4, 47.  </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

When the day of the competition at last came,
there were three of them, and Evangelus drew
second place on the programme. So, after Thespis _
of Thebes had made a good showing, he came in all
ablaze with gold and emeralds and beryls and sapphires. The purple of his robe also became him
well, gleaming beside the gold. With all this he
bedazzled the audience in advance and filled his
hearers with wonderful expectations; but when at
Jength he had to sing and play whether he would or
no, he struck up a discordant, jarring prelude, breaking three strings at once by coming down upon the
lyre harder than he ought, and began to sing ‘in an
unmusical, thin voice, so that a burst of laughter
came from the whole audience, and the judges of the
competition, indignant at his presumption, scourged
him and turned him out of the theatre. Then indeed


<pb n="v.3.p.189"/>

that precious simpleton<note n="v.3.p.189.n.1"><p>The word χρυσοῦς, applied to a person, means “simpleton” (Lapsus1). Here, of course, it also has a punning turn.  </p></note> Evangelus cut a comical
figure with his tears as he was chivvied across the
stage by the scourgers, his legs all bloody from their
whips, gathering up the gems of the lyre—for they
had dropped out when it shared his flogging.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="10"><p>

After a moment’s delay, a man named Eumelus,
from Elis, came on, who had an old lyre, fitted with
wooden pegs, and a costume that, including the
wreath, was hardly worth ten drachmas; but as he
sang well and played skilfully, he had the best of it
and was proclaimed victor, so that he could laugh at
Evangelus for the empty display that he had made
with his lyre and his gems. Indeed, the story goes
that he said to him: “Evangelus, you wear golden
laurel, being rich; but I am poor and I wear the
laurel of Delphi! ‘However, you got at least this
much by your outfit: you are going away not only
unpitied for your defeat but hated into the bargain
because of this inartistic lavishness of yours.” There
you have your own living image in Evangelus, except
that you are not at all put out by the laughter of
the audience. 1
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

It would not be out of place to tell you another
story about something that happened in Lesbos
long ago. They say that when the women of Thrace
tore Orpheus to pieces, his head and his lyre fell
into the Hebrus, and were carried out into the
Aegean Sea; and that the head floated along on the
lyre, singing a dirge (so the story goes) over Orpheus,


<pb n="v.3.p.191"/>

while the lyre itself gave out sweet sounds as the
winds struck the strings. In that manner they came
ashore at Lesbos to the sound of music, and the
people there took them up, burying the head where
their temple of Dionysus now stands and hanging
up the lyre in the temple of Apollo, where it was
long preserved.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="12"><p>

In after time, however, Neanthus,
the son of Pittacus the tyrant, heard how the lyre
charmed animals and plants and stones, and made
music even after the death of Orpheus without anyone’s touching it; so he fell in love with the thing,
‘tampered with the priest, and by means of a generous
bribe prevailed upon him to substitute another similar
lyre, and give him the one of Orpheus. After
securing it, he did not think it safe to play it in the
city by day, but went out into the suburbs at night
with it under his cloak, and then, taking it in hand,
struck and jangled the strings, untrained and unmusical
lad that he was, expecting that under his touch the
lyre would make wonderful music with which he
could charm and enchant everybody, and indeed that
he would become immortal, inheriting the musical
genius of Orpheus. At length the dogs (there were
many of them there), brought together by the noise,
tore him to pieces; so his fate, at least, was like
that of Orpheus, and only the dogs answered his
call. By that it became very apparent that it was
not the lyre which had wrought the spell, but the
skill and the singing of Orpheus, the only distinctive
gifts that he had from his mother; while the lyre
was just a piece of property, no better than any
other stringed instrument.

<pb n="v.3.p.193"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
But why do I talk to you of Orpheus and Neanthus, when even in our own time there was and still
is, I think, a man who paid three thousand drachmas
for the earthenware lamp of Epictetus the Stoic:
He thought, I suppose, that if he should read by —
that lamp at night, he would forthwith acquire the
wisdom of Epictetus in his dreams and would be just
like that marvellous old man.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
And only a day or
two ago another man paid a talent for the staff which
Proteus the Cynic laid aside before leaping into the
fire ;<note n="v.3.p.193.n.1"><p>Peregrinus ; nicknamed Proteus because he changed his faith so readily. The story of his life and his voluntary death at Olympia is related in Lucian’s Peregrinus. </p></note> and he keeps this treasure and displays it just
as the Tegeans do the skin of the Calydonian boar,
the Thebans the bones of Geryon, and the Memphites the tresses of Isis. Yet the original owner
of this marvellous possession surpassed even you
yourself in ignorance and indecency. You see what
a wretched state the collector is in: in all conscience
he needs a staff—on his pate.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="15"><p>

They say that Dionysius<note n="v.3.p.193.n.2"><p>The Elder, Tyrant of Syracuse (431-367 B.C.). </p></note> used to write tragedy in
a very feeble and ridiculous style, so that Philoxenus<note n="v.3.p.193.n.3"><p>A contemporary poet,   </p></note>
was often thrown into the quarries on account of it,
not being able to control his laughter. Well, when
he discovered that he was being laughed at, he took
great pains to procure the wax-tablets on which
Aeschylus used to write, thinking that he too would
be inspired and possessed with divine frenzy in virtue
of the tablets. But for all that, what he wrote on
those very tablets was far more ridiculous than what
he had written before : for example,
<quote>
<l>Doris, the wife of Dionysius,</l>
<l>Is dead—</l>
</quote>






<pb n="v.3.p.195"/>

and again,
<quote><l>Alackaday, a right good wife I’ve lost!</l></quote>

—for that came from the tablet ; and so did this:
<quote><l>'Tis of themselves alone that fools make sport.<note n="v.3.p.195.n.1"><p>The few extant fragments of Dionysius’ plays are given by Nauck, rag. Graec. Fragm. pp. 793-796. Tzetzes (Chil. 5, 180) says that he repeatedly took second and third place in the competitions at Athens, and first with the ansom of Hector. Amusing examples of his frigidity are given by Athenaeus (iii. p. 98 D).  </p></note></l></quote>
The last line Dionysius might have addressed to
you with especial fitness, and those tablets of his
should have been gilded for it.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
 For what expectation do you base upon your books that you are
always unrolling them and rolling them up, glueing
them, trimming them, smearing them with saffron and
oil of cedar, putting slip-covers on them, and fitting
them with knobs, just as if you were going to derive
some profit from them? Ah yes, already you have
been improved beyond measure by their purchase,
when you talk as you do—but no, you are more dumb
than any fish !—and live in a way that cannot even
be mentioned with decency, and have incurred everybody’s savage hatred? as the phrase goes, for your
beastliness! If books made men like that, they
ought to be given as wide a berth as possible.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="17"><p>

Two
things can be acquired from the ancients, the ability
to speak and to act as one ought, by emulating the
best models and shunning the worst; and when a
man clearly fails to benefit from them either in the
one way or in the other, what else is he doing but
buying haunts for mice and lodgings for worms, and
excuses to thrash his servants for negligence?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

Furthermore, would it not be discreditable if someone, on seeing you with a book in your hand(youalways



<pb n="v.3.p.197"/>

have one, no matter what), should ask what orator
or historian or poet it was by, and you, knowing from
the title, should easily answer that question; and if
then—for such topics often spin themselves out to
some length in conversation—he should either commend or criticise something in its contents, and you
should be at a loss and have nothing to say? Would
you not then pray for the earth to open and swallow
you for getting yourself into trouble like Bellerophon
by carrying your book about?<note n="v.3.p.197.n.1"><p>The letter that Bellerophon carried to the King of Lycia contained a request that he be put to death : Iliad 6, 155-195. </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="19"><p>

When Demetrius, the Cynic, while in Corinth, saw
an ignorant fellow reading a beautiful book (it was
the Bacchae of Euripides, I dare say, and he was at
the place where the messenger reports the fate of
Pentheus and the deed of Agave),<note n="v.3.p.197.n.2"><p>1041 ff. </p></note> he snatched it
away and tore it up, saying: “It is better for
Pentheus to be torn to tatters by me once for all
than by you repeatedly.”</p>

<p>
Though I am continually asking myself the
question, I have never yet been able to discover why
you have shown so much zeal in the purchase of
books. Nobody who knows you in the least would
think that you do it on account of their helpfulness
or use, any more than a bald man would buy a comb,
or a blind man a mirror, or a deaf-mute a flute-player,
or an eunuch a concubine, or a landsman an oar, or a
seaman a plough. But perhaps you regard the matter
as a display of wealth and wish to show everyone
that out of your vast surplus you spepd money even
for things of no use to you? Come now, as far as I
know—and I too am a Syrian<note n="v.3.p.197.n.3"><p>The implication is: “And therefore ought to know about your circumstances, if anyone knows.”  </p></note>—if you had not




<pb n="v.3.p.199"/>

smuggled yourself into that old man’s will with all
speed, you would be starving to death by now, and
would be putting up your books at auction!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="20"><p>

The
only remaining reason is that you have been convinced by your toadies that you are not only handsome and charming but a scholar and an orator and
a writer without peer, and you buy the books to
prove their praises true. They say that you hold
forth to them at dinner, and that they, like stranded
frogs, make a clamour because they are thirsty, or
else they get nothing to drink if they do not burst
themselves shouting.</p>

<p>
To be sure, you are somehow very easy to lead by
the nose, and believe them in everything ; for once
you were even persuaded that you resembled a
certain royal person in looks, like the false Alexander, the false Philip (the fuller), the false Nero in
our grandfathers’ time, and whoever else has been
put down under the title “false.”<note n="v.3.p.199.n.1"><p>Balas, in the second century B.c., claimed to be the brother of Antiochus V. Eupator on account of a strong resemblance in looks, and took the name of Alexander. At about the same time, after the defeat of Perses, Andriscus of Adramyttium, a fuller, claimed the name of Philip. The false Nero cropped up some twenty years after Nero’s death, and probably in the East, as he had strong support from the Parthians, who refused to surrender him to Rome. </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="21"><p>

And what
wonder that you, a silly, ignorant fellow, were thus
imposed upon and appeared in public holding your
head high and imitating the gait and dress and
glance of the man whom you delighted to make
yourself resemble ? Even Pyrrhus of Epirus, a marvellous man in other ways, was once, they say, so
spoiled by toadies after the self-same fashion that he
believed he was like the famous Alexander. Yet (to
borrow a phrase from the musicians) the discrepancy


<pb n="v.3.p.201"/>

was a matter of two octaves; for I have seen the
portrait of Pyrrhus. But in spite of that he had
acquired the conviction that he was a perfect replica
of Alexander’s beauty. To be sure, I have been uncomplimentary to Pyrrhus in comparing you with him
in this matter, but what followed would be quite in
character with you. When Pyrrhus was in this state
of mind and had this conviction about himself, everyone without exception concurred with him and
humoured him until an old foreign woman in Larissa
told him the truth and cured him of drivelling.
Pyrrhus showed her portraits of Philip, Perdiccas,
Alexander, Cassander and other kings, and asked her
whom he resembled, quite certain that she would fix
upon Alexander ; but, after delaying a good while,
she said, “Batrachion, the cook’: and as a matter
of fact there was in Larissa a cook called Batrachion
who resembled Pyrrhus.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="22"><p>

As for you, I cannot say which of the profligates
that hang about the actors in the pantomimes you
resemble; I do know very well, however, that
everyone thinks you are still downright daft over
that likeness. It is no wonder, then, since you are
such a failure at likenesses, that you want to make
yourself resemble men of learning, believing those
who praise you so.</p>

<p>
But why do I talk beside the point? The reason
for your craze about books is patent, even if I in my
blindness failed to see it long ago. It is a bright
idea on your part (you think so, anyhow), and.you
base no slight expectations upon the thing in case
the emperor, who is a scholar and holds learning
in especial esteem, should find out about it; if he
should hear that you are buying books and making

<pb n="v.3.p.203"/>

a large collection, you think you will soon get all you
want from him.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="23"><p>

But do you suppose, you rotter,
that he is so steeped in mandragora as to hear that
and yet not know how you pass your time during the
day, what your drinking bouts are like, how you
spend your nights, and in whose company? Do not
you know that a monarch has many eyes and ears?
And your doings are so conspicuous that even the
blind and the deaf may know of them; for if you
but speak, if you but bathe in public—or, if you
choose, don’t even do that—if your servants but
bathe in public, do you not think that all your
nocturnal arcana will be known at once? Answer
me this question: if Bassus, that literary man who
belonged to your following, or Battalus the fluteplayer, or the cinaedus Hemitheon of Sybaris,
who wrote those wonderful regulations for you,
which say that you must use cosmetics and depilatories and so forth—if one of those fellows should
to-day walk about with a lion’s skin on his back and
a club in his hand, what do you suppose those who
saw him would think? That he was Heracles? Not
unless they were gravel-blind; for there are a
thousand things in their appearance that would give
the lie to their costume; the gait, the glance, the
voice, the thin neck, the white lead and mastich and
rouge that you beautify yourselves with ; in short, to
quote the proverb, it would be easier to conceal five
elephants under your arm than a single cinaedus.
Then if the lion’s skin would not have hidden such
as they, do you suppose that you will be undetected

<pb n="v.3.p.205"/>

behind a book? Impossible: the other earmarks of
your sort will betray and reveal you.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

You are completely unaware, it seems to me, that
good expectations are not to be sought from the
booksellers but derived from one’s self and one’s
daily life. Do you expect to find public advocates
and character-witnesses in the scribes Atticus and
Callinus? No: you will find them heartless fellows,
bent upon ruining you, if the gods so will it, and
reducing you to the uttermost depths of poverty.
Even now you ought to come to your senses, sell
these books to some learned man, and your new
house along with them, and then pay the slave
dealers at least a part of the large sums you owe
them.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
For mark this, you have had a tremendous passion
for two things, the acquisition of expensive books
and the purchase of well-grown, vigorous slaves, and
you are showing great zeal and persistence in the
thing; but being poor, you cannot adequately
manage both. See now what a precious thing
advice is! I urge you to drop what does not
concern you, cultivate your other weakness, and
buy those menials of yours, so that your household
may not be depleted and you may not for that
reason have to send out for free men, who, if they
do not get all they want, can safely go away and
tell what you do after your wine. For instance, only
the other day a vile fellow told a most disgraceful
story about you when he came away, and even
showed marks. I can prove by those who were there
at the time that I was indignant and came near
giving him a thrashing in my anger on your behalf,

<pb n="v.3.p.207"/>

especially when he called upon one after another to
corroborate his evidence and they all told the same
story. In view of this, my friend, husband and save
your money so that you may be able to misconduct
yourself at home in great security; for who could
persuade you now to change your ways? When a
dog has once learned to gnaw leather, he cannot
stop.<note n="v.3.p.207.n.1"><p>Cf. <cit><quote><l>ut canis a corio nunquam absterrebitur uncto.</l></quote><bibl>Horace, Satires, ii. 5,83.</bibl></cit></p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="26"><p>

The other way is easier, not to buy books any
longer. You are well enough educated ; you have
learning to spare ; you have all the works of antiquity
almost at the tip of your tongue; you know not only
all history but all the arts of literary composition, its
merits and defects, and how to use an Attic vocabulary ; your many books have made you wondrous
wise, consummate in learning. There is no reason
why I should not have my fun with you, since you
like to be gulled!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="27"><p>

As you have so many books, I should like to ask
you what you like best to read ? Plato? Antisthenes?
Archilochus ? Hipponax? Or do you scorn them and
incline to occupy yourself with the orators? Tell
me, do you read the speech of Aeschines against
Timarchus? No doubt you know it all and understand everything in it, but have you dipped into
Aristophanes and Eupolis? Have you read the
Baptae, the whole play?<note n="v.3.p.207.n.2"><p>The Baptae of Eupolie appears to have been a satire upon the devotees of Cotys (Cotytto), a Thracian goddess worshipped with orgiastic rites.  </p></note> Then did it have no
effect upon you, and did you not blush when you saw
the point of it? Indeed, a man may well wonder
above all what the state of your soul is when you




<pb n="v.3.p.209"/>

lay hold of your books, and of your hands when you
open them. When do you do your reading? In the
daytime ? Nobody ever saw you doing it. - At night,
then? When you have already given instructions
to your henchmen, or before you have talked with
them? Come, in the name of Cotys, never again
dare to do such a thing.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="28"><p>

Leave the books alone
and attend to your own affairs exclusively. Yet you
ought not to do that, either; you ought to be put
to shame by Phaedra in Euripides, who is indignant
at women and says:

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>They shudder not at their accomplice, night,</l>
    <l>Nor chamber-walls, for fear they find a voice.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Hippolytus417 f.</bibl>
</cit>




But if you have made up your mind to cleave to
the same infirmity at all costs, go ahead: buy books,
keep them at home under lock and key, and enjoy
the fame of your treasures—that is enough for you.
But never lay hands on them or read them or sully
with your tongue the prose and poetry of the
ancients, that has done you no harm.</p>

<p>

I know that in all this I am wasting words, and, as
the proverb has it, trying to scrub an Ethiop white.
You will buy them and make no use of them and
get yourself laughed at by men of learning who are
satisfied with the gain that they derive, not from the
beauty of books or their expensiveness, but from the
language and thought of their author.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="29"><p>

You expect
to palliate and conceal your ignorance by getting
a reputation for this, and to daze people by the
number of your books, unaware that you are doing
the same as the most ignorant physicians, who get
themselves ivory pill-boxes and silver cupping-glasses
and gold-inlaid scalpels ; when the time comes to use



<pb n="v.3.p.211"/>

them, however, they do not know how to handle
them, but someone who has studied his profession
comes upon the scene with a knife that is thoroughly
sharp, though covered with rust, and frees the patient
from his pain. But let me compare your case with
something still more comical. Consider the barbers
and you will observe that the master-craftsmen
among them have only a razor and a pair of shears
and a suitable mirror, while the unskilled, amateurish
fellows put on view a multitude of shears and huge
mirrors ; but for all that, they cannot keep their
ignorance from being found out. In fact, what
happens to them is as comical as can be—people
have their hair cut next door and then go to
their mirrors to brush it.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg028.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="30"><p>

So it is with you: you
might, to be sure, lend your books to someone else
who wants them, but you cannot use them yourself.
But you never lent a book to anyone; you act like
the dog in the manger, who neither eats the grain
herself nor lets the horse eat it, who can.</p>

<p>
I give myself the liberty of saying this much to
you for the present, just about your books ; about
your other detestable and ignominions conduct you
shall often be told in future.
<pb n="v.3.p.215"/>
</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>
