<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>On the Peace</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
          <date type="print">1929</date>
          <date type="reprint">1982</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg017.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> All those who come before you on this platform are accustomed to assert that the
          subjects upon which they are themselves about to advise you are most important and most
          worthy of serious consideration by the state.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. a similar
            statement in <bibl n="Dem. 24.4">Dem. 24.4</bibl>.</note> Nevertheless, if it was ever
          appropriate to preface the discussion of any other subject with such words, it seems to me
          fitting also to begin with them in speaking upon the subject now before us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For we are assembled here to deliberate about War and Peace, which exercise the greatest
          power over the life of man, and regarding which those who are correctly advised must of
          necessity fare better than the rest of the world. Such, then, is the magnitude of the
          question which we have come together to decide. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I observe, however, that you do not hear with equal favor the speakers who address you,
          but that, while you give your attention to some, in the case of others you do not even
          suffer their voice to be heard.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This expression is used in
            a similar connection in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.22">Isoc. 15.22</bibl>.</note> And it is not
          surprising that you do this; for in the past you have formed the habit of driving all the
          orators from the platform<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Plutarch (<bibl n="Plut. Phoc. 9"
              >Plut. Phoc. 9</bibl>) states that this happened in the case of Phocion.</note> except
          those who support your desires. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Wherefore one may justly take you to task because, while you know well that many great
            houses<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This term is used of estates in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.117">Isoc. 8.117</bibl>. Here it is used of both families and their
            estates. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 8.88">Isoc. 8.88</bibl>.</note> have been ruined<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">By the casualties and expenses of war.</note> by
            flatterers<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Demagogic leaders of the war party, later
            termed sycophants. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.121">Isoc. 8.121 ff.</bibl></note> and while in
          your private affairs you abhor those who practice this art, in your public affairs you are
          not so minded towards them; on the contrary, while you denounce those who welcome and
          enjoy the society of such men, you yourselves make it manifest that you place greater
          confidence in them than in the rest of your fellow citizens. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Indeed, you have caused the orators to practice and study, not what will be advantageous
          to the state, but how they may discourse in a manner pleasing to you. And it is to this
          kind of discourse that the majority of them have resorted also at the present time, since
          it has become plain to all that you will be better pleased with those who summon you to
          war than with those who counsel peace; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for the former put into our minds the expectation both of regaining our possessions in
          the several states and of recovering the power which we formerly enjoyed,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">As head of the Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos"
              >Delos</placeName>, which developed into the Athenian Empire. During the period of
            supremacy, which lasted from the close of the Persian Wars to the end of the
            Peloponnesian War, <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> frequently
            disciplined recalcitrant confederate states by expelling their citizens and settling
            Athenians on their lands. Such settlements were called cleruchies. When <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> formed the new naval confederacy in <date
              when="-0378">378 B.C.</date> it was expressly stipulated by her allies and agreed to
            by <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> that such abuse of power should
            not be repeated. But the jingoistic orators advocated nothing less than the restoration
            of the former empire with all its powers and practices.</note> while the latter hold
          forth no such hope, insisting rather that we must have peace and not crave great
          possessions contrary to justice,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The state which seizes and
            holds foreign possessions is a robber. Isocrates throughout this discourse proposes to
            make the moral code within the state the basis of her foreign policy.</note> but be
          content with those we have<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A proverbial tag. Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 1.29">Isoc. 1.29</bibl>.</note>—and that for the great majority of mankind is
          of all things the most difficult. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For we are so dependent on our hopes and so insatiate in seizing what seems to be our
          advantage that not even those who possess the greatest fortunes are willing to rest
          satisfied with them but are always grasping after more and so risking the loss of what
          they have. Wherefore we may well be anxious lest on the present occasion also we may be
          subject to this madness. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For some of us appear to me to be over zealously bent on war, as though having heard, not
          from haphazard counsellors, but from the gods, that we are destined to succeed in all our
          campaigns and to prevail easily over our foes. But people of intelligence, when dealing
          with matters about which they have knowledge, ought not to take counsel—for this is
          superfluous—but to act as men who are already resolved what to do, whereas, in dealing
          with matters about which they take counsel, they ought not to think that they have exact
          knowledge of what the result will be, but to be minded towards these contingencies as men
          who indeed exercise their best judgement, but are not sure what the future may hold in
            store.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This some what wordy passsage in which the orator
            becomes the philosopher reflects a fundamental idea of his pedagogy: There can be no
            exact science or knowledge of what to do in all contingencies and relations of life; the
            best that we can do is to develop sound, not infalliable, judgement in dealing with
            them. See General Introd. p. xxvii, Isocrates, Vol. I., L.C.L., and <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.184">Isoc. 15.184</bibl>, note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> You, however, do neither the one thing nor the other, but are in the utmost confusion of
          mind. For you have come together as if it were your business to select the best course
          from all that are proposed; nevertheless, as though you had clear knowledge of what must
          be done, you are not willing to listen to any except those who speak for your pleasure.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet, if you really desired to find out what is advantageous to the state, you ought
          to give your attention more to those who oppose your views than to those who seek to
          gratify you, knowing well that of the orators who come before you here, those who say what
          you desire are able to delude you easily—since what is spoken to win favor clouds your
          vision of what is best—whereas those who advise you without regard to your pleasure can
          affect you in no such way, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>since they could not convert you to their way of thinking until they have first made
          clear what is for your advantage. But, apart from these considerations, how can men wisely
          pass judgement on the past or take counsel for the future unless they examine and compare
          the arguments of opposing speakers, themselves giving an unbiased hearing<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.21">Isoc. 15.21</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Dem. 18.6">Dem. 18.6</bibl>.</note> to both sides? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I marvel that the older men no longer recall and that the younger have not been told
          by anyone that the orators who exhort us to cling fast to peace have never caused us to
          suffer any misfortune whatsoever, whereas those who lightly espouse war have already
          plunged us into many great disasters. However, we have no memory for these facts but are
          always ready, without in the least advancing our own welfare, to man triremes, to levy
          war-taxes, and to lend aid to the campaigns of others or wage war against them, as chance
          may determine, as if imperilling the interests, not of our own, but of a foreign state.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And the cause of this condition of affairs is that, although you ought to be as much
          concerned about the business of the commonwealth as about your own, you do not feel the
          same interest in the one as in the other; on the contrary, whenever you take counsel
          regarding your private business you seek out as counsellors men who are your superiors in
          intelligence, but whenever you deliberate on the business of the state you distrust and
          dislike men of that character and cultivate, instead, the most depraved<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The private morals of men like Eubulus, Callistratus (see
            Theopompus in <bibl n="Ath. 4.166e">Athen. 4.166e</bibl>), and Philocrates (see <bibl
              n="Aeschin. 2.52">Aeschin. 2.52</bibl>) apparently left much to be desired.</note> of
          the orators who come before you on this platform; and you prefer as being better friends
          of the people those who are drunk<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Aristotle (<bibl
              n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 34">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 34</bibl>) states that when, after the
            battle of Arginusae, <date when="-0406">406 B.C.</date>, the Spartans made overtures of
            peace the demagogue Cleophon came before the Assembly drunk and prevented the Athenians
            from accepting the terms. With this paragraph should be compared <bibl n="Isoc. 15.316"
              >Isoc. 15.316</bibl> and note.</note> to those who are sober, those who are witless to
          those who are wise, and those who dole out the public money<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The reference is particularly to Eubulus, who caused to be set aside a portion of the
            public revenues (the “surplus” mentioned in <bibl n="Isoc. 8.82">Isoc. 8.82</bibl>) as a
            “theoric” fund to be distributed to the people at the public festivals.</note> to those
          who perform public services<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.128">Isoc.
              8.128</bibl>, note.</note> at their own expense. So that we may well marvel that
          anyone can expect a state which employs such counsellors to advance to better things. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I know that it is hazardous to oppose your views<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
            Socrates in <bibl n="Plat. Apol. 31e">Plat. Apol. 31e</bibl>: “No man in the world can
            preserve his life if he honestly opposes himself to you or to any other people and
            attempts to prevent many unjust and lawless things from being done by the state.”</note>
          and that, although this is a free government, there exists no ‘freedom of speech’<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The pride of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName>. See <bibl n="Hdt. 5.78">Hdt. 5.78</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Eur. Hipp. 422">Eur. Hipp. 422</bibl>.</note> except that which is enjoyed in this
          Assembly by the most reckless orators, who care nothing for your welfare, and in the
          theater by the comic poets.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The poets of the old comedy
            exercised an incredible degree of license in ridiculing everything, divine or human,
            particularly the foibles of the state. These comedies were given at the festival of
            Dionysus, when many visitors from other states were in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName>. Aristophanes himself says (<bibl n="Aristoph. Ach. 500">Aristoph.
              Ach. 500 ff.</bibl>) that he was attacked by Cleon for “abusing <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in the presence of strangers.”</note> And,
          what is most outrageous of all, you show greater favor to those who publish the failings
          of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to the rest of the Hellenes than you
          show even to those who benefit the city, while you are as ill-disposed to those who rebuke
          and admonish you<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates resents their attitude towards
            himself in the opening remarks of the <title>Antidosis</title> (<bibl n="Isoc. 15">Isoc.
              15</bibl>).</note> as you are to men who work injury to the state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Nevertheless, in spite of these conditions, I shall not desist from what I had in mind
          to say. For I have come before you, not to seek your favor nor to solicit your votes, but
          to make known the views I hold, first, regarding the proposals which have been put before
          you by the Prytaneis,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Senate of the Five Hundred was
            divided into ten committees of 50, each serving a tenth part of the year. Such a
            committee was called a prytany and its members prytaneis. The prytany formulated
            measures to be brought before the General Assembly.</note> and, second, regarding the
          other interests of the state; for no good will come of the resolutions which have now been
          made regarding the peace<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See Introduction, p. 2, note
            c.</note> unless we are well advised also with regard to what remains to be done. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I maintain, then, that we should make peace, not only with the Chians, the Rhodians, the
          Byzantines and the Coans, but with all mankind, and that we should adopt, not the
          covenants of peace which certain parties<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Eubulus, whose
            terms of peace were, apparently, not broad enough.</note> have recently drawn up, but
          those which we have entered into<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Peace of Antalcidas.
            See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.115">Isoc. 4.115</bibl>, note a.</note> with the king of <placeName
            key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> and with the Lacedaemonians, which ordain that the
          Hellenes be independent, that the alien garrisons be removed from the several states, and
          that each people retain its own territory. For we shall not find terms of peace more just
          than these nor more expedient for our city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But if I leave off speaking at this point, I know that I shall appear to put <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> at a disadvantage, if, that is to say, the
          Thebans are to retain possession of <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName> and
            <placeName key="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
              <bibl n="Isoc. 6.27">Isoc. 6.27</bibl>, note.</note> and the other cities<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="tgn,7011034">Orchomenus</placeName> (<bibl
              n="Diod. 15.79">Dio. Sic. 15.79</bibl>), Oropus (<bibl n="Diod. 15.76">Dio. Sic.
              15.76</bibl>).</note> which they have seized contrary to their oaths,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">When they agreed to the Peace of Antalcidas.</note> while we
          are to retire, under no compulsion to do so, from the territory which we now hold. But if
          you will only listen to me and give me your attention to the end, I believe that you will
          all impute extreme folly and madness to those who think that injustice is advantageous and
          who would hold in subjection by force the cities of others, failing to reckon with the
          disasters which result from such a policy. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> On this point indeed I shall attempt to instruct you throughout my entire speech. But
          first let us discuss the question of peace and consider what we should desire for
          ourselves at the present juncture. For if we define this clearly and intelligently, we
          shall take better counsel in the light of this principle regarding our other
            interests<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Their foreign policy in general.</note> as
          well. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Let me ask, then, whether we should be satisfied if we could dwell in our city secure
          from danger, if we could be provided more abundantly with the necessities of life, if we
          could be of one mind amongst ourselves, and if we could enjoy the high esteem of the
          Hellenes. I, for my part, hold that, with these blessings assured us, <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> would be completely happy. Now it is the
            war<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Social War.</note> which has robbed us of all the
          good things which I have mentioned; for it has made us poorer;<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">In <bibl n="Isoc. 7.9">Isoc. 7.9</bibl>, he states that in the course of the
            war <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> had thrown away 1000 talents on
            mercenary soldiers alone. Demosthenes also bears witness to the poverty and
            embarrassment of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> at this time. See
              <bibl n="Dem. 20.24">Dem. 20.24</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 23.209">Dem.
            23.209</bibl>.</note> it has compelled many of us to endure perils; it has given us a
          bad name among the Hellenes; and it has in every way overwhelmed us with misfortune. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But if we make peace and demean ourselves as our common covenants<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Of the Peace of Antalcidas.</note> command us to do, then we shall dwell in
          our city in great security, delivered from wars and perils and the turmoil in which we are
          now involved amongst ourselves, and we shall advance day by day in prosperity, relieved of
          paying war-taxes, of fitting out triremes, and of discharging the other burdens<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.128">Isoc. 8.128</bibl> and note.</note>
          which are imposed by war, without fear cultivating our lands and sailing the seas and
          engaging in those other occupations which now, because of the war, have entirely come to
          an end.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. Aristophanes, <bibl n="Isoc. 8.29">Isoc. 8.292
              ff.</bibl></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nay, we shall see our city enjoying twice the revenues<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >According to Demosthenes (<bibl n="Dem. 10.37">Dem. 10.37-38</bibl>) <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> before the peace had an income of 130 talents;
            after the peace of 400 talents.</note> which she now receives, and thronged with
          merchants and foreigners and resident aliens,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Foreigners,
            whether merchants or not, had to pay nonresident fees, <foreign xml:lang="grc">cenika\
              te/lh</foreign>; resident aliens paid the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >metoi/kion</foreign> of 12 drachmas per man and 6 per woman.</note> by whom she is
          now deserted. And, what is most important of all, we shall have all mankind as our
          allies—allies who will not have been forced, but rather persuaded, to join with us, who
          will not welcome our friendship because of our power when we are secure only to abandon us
          when we are in peril,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The reference is to the allies who
            revolted from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> both during the
            Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> and during the New Naval
            League.</note> but who will be disposed towards us as those should be who are in very
          truth allies and friends. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Furthermore, what we are now unable to obtain through war and great outlay of money we
          shall readily secure for ourselves through peaceful embassies. For do not think that
          Cersobleptes will wage war with us over the <placeName key="tgn,7010345"
            >Chersonese</placeName>, or Philip<note anchored="true" resp="ed">These are singled out
            because both Cersobleptes, now virtually master of the Thracian Chersonnes, and Philip,
            with his growing empire in the north <placeName key="tgn,7002675">Aegean</placeName>,
            were giving <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> trouble at this
            time.</note> over <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See the opening of the <title>Address to Philip</title>, <bibl
              n="Isoc. 5">Isoc. 5</bibl>.</note> when they see that we do not covet any of the
          possessions of other peoples. It is true that as things are now they have good reason to
          be afraid to make <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> a near neighbor to
          their dominions; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for they see that we are not content with what we have but are always reaching out for
          more. If, however, we change our ways and gain a better reputation, they will not only
          withdraw from our territory but will give us besides territory of their own. For it will
          be to their advantage to cherish and support the power of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> and so be secure in the possession of their own kingdoms. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And, mark you, it will be possible for us to cut off from the region of <placeName
            key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> enough land<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This was
            done in 353 when the Athenians captured <placeName key="perseus,Sestos"
              >Sestos</placeName> and settled colonists in this territory. See <bibl
              n="Diod. 16.34.3">Dio. Sic. 16.34.3</bibl>.</note> so that we shall not only have
          abundance ourselves but shall also be able to furnish adequate means of subsistence to
          those of the Hellenes who are in need and, because of their poverty, are now wandering
          from place to place.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For these wandering refugees and the
            problem they presented see <bibl n="Isoc. 5.120">Isoc. 5.120</bibl> and note.</note> For
          where Athenodorus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An Athenian citizen, he was a private in
            the sense that he had no official post. He was a free-lance captain of mercenaries who
            took service in <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> and later in the
            Thracian Chersonnese. What colony he founded is not known.</note> and Callistratus,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">An Athenian orator who had much to do with the formation of
            the New Naval League, he was charged with treason and retired into exile to <placeName
              key="tgn,7001317">Thrace</placeName>, where he had a part in the recolonization of
            Datus.</note> the one a private, the other an exile, have been able to found cities,
          surely we could gain possession of many such places if we so desired. And those who claim
          the right to stand at the head of the Hellenes ought to become leaders of such enterprises
          much rather than of war and of hireling armies,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.44">Isoc. 8.44-46</bibl>.</note> which at the present time are the objects
          of our ambition. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now as to the promises held out by the ambassadors,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Probably from the former allies with whom <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> was now at war.</note> what I have said is enough, although one
          might perhaps add many things to what I have said. But I think we should not go forth from
          this assembly, having merely adopted resolutions in favor of the peace, without also
          taking counsel how we shall keep it, and not do what we are in the habit of doing—namely,
          getting ourselves involved again in the same disorders after a short interval of time<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 5.8">Isoc. 5.8</bibl>.</note>—and how we
          shall devise, not merely a postponement, but some means of permanent deliverance from our
          present ills. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But no such thing can come to pass until you are persuaded that tranquillity is more
          advantageous and more profitable than meddlesomeness,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Meddlesomeness, <foreign xml:lang="grc">h( polupragmosu/nh</foreign>, is used here
            and elsewhere in the speech as the opposite of <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >h(suxi/a</foreign> ( or <foreign xml:lang="grc">swfrosu/nh</foreign>, moderation,
            self-control). The latter contains the idea of quiet living and minding one's own
            business in private relations, and in foreign relations, of pursuing peace and avoiding
            aggression.</note> justice than injustice, and attention to one's own affairs than
          covetousness of the possessions of others. This is a theme on which none of the orators
          has ever made bold to address you. I, however, shall devote most of my discourse to this
          very subject. For I observe that happiness is to be found in these ways of life and not in
          those which we now follow. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But anyone who attempts to discourse on a subject out of the common and who desires to
          bring about a change in your opinions must needs touch upon many matters and speak
          somewhat at length, now reminding, now rebuking, now commending, and again counselling
          you. For hardly with all these aids can you be led to a better way of thinking. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For the matter stands thus. It seems to me that, while all men crave their advantage and
          desire to be better off than the rest, they do not all know the kind of conduct which
          leads to this end but differ from each other in judgement, some possessing a judgement
          which is sound and capable of hitting the right course of action,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 12.30">Isoc. 12.30</bibl>.</note> others one which
          completely misses their true advantage.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Advantage in the
            good sense, which works no disadvantage to others. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 3.2">Isoc.
              3.2</bibl>, Isocrates, Vol. I., L.C.L.; <bibl n="Isoc. 15.275">Isoc.
            15.275</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And this is the very thing which has happened to our city; for we think that, if we sail
          the sea with many triremes and compel the various states to pay contributions<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In the Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos"
              >Delos</placeName> the quotas paid to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> to support the league were termed <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >fo/roi</foreign>, which, when <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> made
            it compulsory, came to have the invidious meaning “tribute moneys.” In the New Naval
            League, the term <foreign xml:lang="grc">sunta/ceis</foreign>, contributions, was
            substituted. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.123">Isoc. 15.123</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 7.2"
              >Isoc. 7.2</bibl>.</note> and send representatives<note anchored="true" resp="ed">To
            the Common Council of the allies, <foreign xml:lang="grc">to\ koino\n sune/drion tw=n
              summa/xiwn</foreign>, which met in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName>.</note> to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, we
          have accomplished something to the purpose. But in fact, we have been completely misled as
          to the truth; for of the hopes which we cherished not one has been fulfilled; on the
          contrary, we have reaped from them hatreds and wars and great expense. And this was to be
          expected; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for in former times as the result of such meddlesomeness we were placed in the utmost
            peril,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At the end of the Peloponnesian War, which was the
            end of the Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> and of the
            Empire of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> while as the result
          of keeping our city in the path of justice and of giving aid to the oppressed and of not
          coveting the possessions of others we were given the hegemony by the willing consent of
          the Hellenes<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In <date when="-0478">478 B.C.</date>, when
            the Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> (see <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.67">Isoc. 12.67 ff.</bibl> and notes)was formed, Thucydides states that
            the Ionian Greeks came to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and asked
            her to take the hegemony. See i. 95, 96. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.72">Isoc.
            4.72</bibl>.</note>—considerations which now and for a long time past, without reason
          and with utter recklessness, we have treated with contempt. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For some have gone to such an extreme of folly as to hold the view that, while injustice
          is reprehensible, it is, nevertheless, profitable and advantageous in our lives day by
          day, and that, while justice is estimable, it is for all that disadvantageous and more
          capable of benefiting others than of helping those who practise it.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 3.59">Isoc. 3.59</bibl>; <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 392b">Plat.
              Rep. 392b</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>They fail to see that nothing in the world can contribute so powerfully to material gain,
          to good repute, to right action, in a word, to happiness, as virtue and the qualities of
            virtue.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Literally, virtue and its parts. The particular
            virtues mentioned by Isocrates are piety, justice, and moderation. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.63">Isoc. 8.63</bibl>.</note> For it is by the good qualities which we have
          in our souls that we acquire also the other advantages of which we stand in need.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.290">Isoc. 15.290</bibl>; Socrates in
              <bibl n="Plat. Apol. 30a">Plat. Apol. 30a-b</bibl>: “I go about doing nothing else
            than trying to persuade you, young and old, not to care for your bodies nor for your
            possesssions before nor even as much as you care for your soul that it may be the best
            possible, saying to you that not from your possessons does virtue spring, but from
            virtue spring possessions and all other good things to makind in private and in public
            life.” For this as a sound principle of foreign policy see <bibl n="Isoc. 12.185">Isoc.
              12.185 ff.</bibl></note> So that those who have no care for their own state of mind
          are unwittingly disparaging the means of attaining at the same time to greater wisdom and
          to greater well-being. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I marvel if anyone thinks that those who practise piety and justice remain constant
          and steadfast in these virtues because they expect to be worse off than the wicked and not
          because they consider that both among gods and among men<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 3.2">Isoc. 3.2</bibl>.</note> they will have the advantage over
          others. I, for my part, am persuaded that they and they alone gain advantage in the true
          sense, while the others gain advantage only in the baser sense of that term. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I observe that those who prefer the way of injustice, thinking it the greatest good
          fortune to seize something that belongs to others, are in like case with animals which are
          lured by a bait, at the first deriving pleasure from what they seize, but the moment after
          finding themselves in desperate straits, while those who live a life of piety and justice
          pass their days in security for the present and have sweeter hopes for all eternity.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 1.39">Isoc. 1.39</bibl> and note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But if this is not wont to happen in all cases, nevertheless it does, for the most part,
          come out in this way. And it behoves intelligent men, since they cannot see clearly what
          will always be to their advantage, to show to the world that they prefer that which is
          generally beneficial. On the other hand, they are of all men most afflicted with unreason
          who concede that justice is a way of life more noble and more pleasing to the gods than
          injustice but at the same time believe that those who follow it will live in worse case
          than those who have chosen the way of evil. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I could wish that, even as to praise virtue is a facile theme, so it were easy to
          persuade bearers to practice it. But as things are I am afraid that I may be expressing
          such sentiments to no purpose. For we have been depraved for a long time by men whose only
          ability is to cheat and delude—men who have held the people in such contempt that whenever
          they wish to bring about a state of war with any city, these very men who are paid<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, bribed to speak. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.50">Isoc.
              8.50</bibl> and note.</note> for what they say have the audacity to tell us that we
          should follow the example of our ancestors and not allow ourselves to be made a
          laughing-stock nor permit those Hellenes to sail the sea who are unwilling to pay us their
          contributions. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now I should be glad if they would inform me what ancestors they would have us imitate.
          Do they mean those who lived at the time of the Persian Wars<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See 75.</note> or those who governed the city before the Decelean War<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">This term is frequently used to denote the last decade of the
            Peloponnesian War, from the occupation of the fort of Decelea near <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by the Spartans in <date when="-0413">413
              B.C.</date> Cf. 84. During this period the affairs of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> went from bad to worse.</note>? If they mean the latter then they
          are simply advising us to run the risk once again of being enslaved<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">As at the end of the Peloponnesian War. Cf. 78.</note>; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but if they mean those who at Marathon conquered the barbarians, then they are of all men
          the most brazen, if, that is to say, they praise those who governed <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> at that time and in the same breath would
          persuade us to act in a manner contrary to theirs and to commit blunders so gross that I
          am at a loss what I should do—whether I should speak the truth as on all other occasions
          or be silent out of fear of making myself odious to you. For while it seems to me the
          better course to discuss your blunders, I observe that you are more resentful towards
          those who take you to task than towards those who are the authors of your misfortunes.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless I should be ashamed if I showed that I am more concerned about my own
          reputation than about the public safety. It is, therefore, my duty and the duty of all who
          care about the welfare of the state to choose, not those discourses which are agreeable to
          you, but those which are profitable for you to hear. And you, for your part, ought to
          realize, in the first place, that while many treatments of all kinds have been discovered
          by physicians for the ills of our bodies, there exists no remedy for souls which are
          ignorant of the truth and filled with base desires other than the kind of discourse<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Aesch. PB 378">Aesch. PB 378</bibl>: <foreign
              xml:lang="grc">yuxh=s nosou/shs ei)si\n i)atpoi\ lo/goi</foreign>.</note> which
          boldly rebukes the sins which they commit, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and, in the second place, that it is absurd to submit to the cauteries and cuttings of
          physicians in order that we may be relieved of greater pains and yet refuse to hear
          discourses before knowing clearly whether or not they have the power to benefit their
          hearers. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have said these things at the outset because in the rest of my discourse I am going to
          speak without reserve and with complete frankness. For suppose that a stranger from
          another part of the world were to come to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.133">Isoc.
              4.133</bibl>.</note> having had no time to be tainted with our depravity, but brought
          suddenly face to face with what goes on here, would he not think that we are mad and
          bereft of our senses, seeing that we plume ourselves upon the deeds of our ancestors and
          think fit to eulogize our city by dwelling upon the achievements of their time and yet act
          in no respect like them but do the very opposite? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For while they waged war without ceasing in behalf of the Hellenes against the
          barbarians, we removed from their homes those who derive their livelihood from Asia and
          led them against the Hellenes;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Athenian general Chares
            employed Asiatic mercenaries in the war against the Athenian allies.</note> and while
          they liberated the cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName><note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.83">Isoc. 4.83</bibl>.</note> and lent
          them their aid and so were adjudged worthy of the hegemony, we seek to enslave these
            cities<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By conquest of the revolting allies.</note> and
          pursue a policy the very opposite of theirs and then feel aggrieved that we are not held
          in like honor with them— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>we who fall so far short of those who lived in those days both in our deeds and in our
          thoughts that, whereas they brought themselves to abandon their country<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.96">Isoc. 4.96</bibl>.</note> for the
          sake of saving the other Hellenes and fought and conquered the barbarians both on the land
          and on the sea,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Especially the battles of Marathon and
              <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>.</note> we do not see fit to run any
          risk even for our own advantage; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>on the contrary, although we seek to rule over all men, we are not willing to take the
          field ourselves,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The same complaint is repeatedly made by
            Demosthenes in the <title>Philippics</title> and the <title>Olynthiacs</title>.</note>
          and although we undertake to wage war upon, one might almost say, the whole world,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Between <date from="-0363" to="-0355">363-355
              B.C.</date> Athens made war on Alexander of <placeName key="tgn,7001399"
              >Thessaly</placeName>, King Cotys in the Thracian Chersonnese, <placeName
              key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
              >Euboea</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>, <placeName
              key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>, and Potidaea—to mention only the chief
            campaigns.</note> we do not train ourselves for war but employ instead vagabonds,
          deserters, and fugitives who have thronged together here in consequence of other
            misdemeanors,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See Introduction to the
              <title>Panegyricus</title>, Vol. I. p. 117.</note> who, whenever others offer them
          higher pay, will follow their leadership against us.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            Athenian general Chares with his mercenary troops actually enlisted during the Social
            War in the service of the Persian Satrap Artabazus, who paid them well. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 7.8">Isoc. 7.8</bibl>, note; <bibl n="Dem. 4.24">Dem. 4.24</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But, for all that, we are so enamored of these mercenaries that while we would not
          willingly assume the responsibility for the acts of our own children if they offended
          against anyone, yet for the brigandage, the violence, and the lawlessness of these
            men,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introd. p. xxxix, Isocrates, Vol. I.,
            L.C.L.</note> the blame for which is bound to be laid at our door, not only do we feel
          no regret, but we actually rejoice whenever we hear that they have perpetrated any such
          atrocity. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And we have reached such a degree of imbecility that, although we are ourselves in need
          of the necessities of daily existence, we have undertaken to support mercenary troops and
          we do violence to our own allies and extort money from them in order to provide pay for
          the common enemies of all mankind.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">These troops, whose only
            thought was for pay or plunder, made no difference between foes and friends. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. L. 9.9">Isoc. Letter 9.9-10</bibl>. Demosthenes also (<bibl n="Dem. 23.139"
              >Dem. 23.139</bibl>) calls them <foreign xml:lang="grc">koinoi\ kata\ ka=san xw/ran
              e)xqroi/</foreign>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And so far are we inferior to our ancestors, both those who enjoyed the esteem of the
          Hellenes and those who incurred their hatred,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            distinction is between those who were awarded the hegemony and those who later turned
            the hegemony into an empire maintained by force.</note> that whereas they, when they
          resolved to wage war against any state, deemed it their duty, notwithstanding that the
          Acropolis was stored with silver and gold,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See 126.</note>
          to face danger in their own persons in support of their resolutions, we, on the other
          hand, not withstanding that we are in such extreme poverty<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >See19 and <bibl n="Isoc. 7.54">Isoc. 7.54</bibl>.</note> and are so many in number,
          employ, as does the great King, mercenary armies! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In those days, when they manned their triremes, they put on board crews of foreigners and
          slaves but sent out citizens to fight under heavy arms. Now, however, we use mercenaries
          as heavy-armed troops but compel citizens to row the ships,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.54">Isoc. 7.54</bibl>, note.</note> with the result that when they
          land in hostile territory these men, who claim the right to rule over the Hellenes,
          disembark with their cushions<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Pads for the rowers'
            benches.</note> under their arms, while men who are of the character which I have just
          described take the field with shield and spear! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> However, if one could see that the domestic policy of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> was well managed he might be of good cheer as to our other affairs.
          But is it not about this very thing that he would feel most aggrieved? For we assert that
          we are sprung from our very soil<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.23"
              >Isoc. 4.23-24</bibl>.</note> and that our city was founded before all others,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.37">Isoc. 4.37</bibl>.</note> but
          although we ought to be an example to all the world of good and orderly government, we
          manage our state in a worse manner and with more disorder than those who are just founding
          their cities. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>We glory and take great pride in being better born than the rest but we are readier to
          share this noble birth-right with any who desire it<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            Athenians were less conservative in the matter of citizenship than other states.
            Cleisthenes gave citizenship to the resident aliens in Athens at the time of his
            reforms. In 427 citizenship was conferred upon all the people of <placeName
              key="tgn,7011028">Plataeae</placeName>. From time to time numerous individuals were
            admitted to this privilege.</note> than are the Triballians or the Leucanians<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Triballians were a savage tribe in the interior of
              <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>(see <bibl n="Isoc. 12.227">Isoc.
              12.227</bibl>); the Lucanians a rude people, noted for their ferocity, in Southern
            Italy.</note> to share their ignoble origin. We pass a multitude of laws,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.40">Isoc. 7.40-41</bibl>.</note> but we
          care so little about them (for if I give you a single instance you will be able to judge
          of the others as well) that, although we have prescribed the penalty of death for anyone
          who is convicted of bribery, we elect men who are most flagrantly guilty of this crime as
          our generals<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This seems to be a covert attack upon Chares,
            who according to Theopompus (in Athenaeus xii. 532) paid money to the orators to
            advocate a war policy, especially to the orator Aristophon, who may be alluded to in 36
            and in this paragraph. Chares in the field and Aristophon on the rostrum were the
            leaders of Athenian jingoism at this time.</note> and we pick out the man who has been
          able to deprave the greatest number of our citizens and place him in charge of the most
          important affairs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>We are concerned about our polity no less than about the safety of the whole state and we
          know that our democracy flourishes and endures in times of peace and security while in
          times of war it has twice already been overthrown,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By the
            oligarchical revolution of <date when="-0411">411 B.C.</date>, when the government of
            the Four Hundred was established, and that of <date when="-0404">404 B.C.</date>, when
            the reign of the Thirty began.</note> but we are hostile to those who desire peace as if
          suspecting them of favoring oligarchy,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For example,
            Timotheus, who was no flatterer. See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.131">Isoc. 15.131 ff.</bibl> Cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. 15.318">Isoc. 15.318</bibl>.</note> while we are friendly to those who
          advocate war as if assured of their devotion to democracy. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>We are versed beyond all others in discourse and in the conduct of affairs, but we are so
          devoid of reason that we do not hold the same views about the same question on the same
          day; on the contrary, the things which we condemn before we enter the assembly are the
          very things which we vote for when we are in session, and again a little later when we
          depart to our homes we disapprove of the things which we resolved upon here.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Aristophanes (<bibl n="Aristoph. Ach. 630">Aristoph. Ach.
              630</bibl>) ridicules the Athenians for being quick in making up and in changing their
            minds. Cf.<bibl n="Aristoph. Eccl. 797">Aristoph. Eccl. 797</bibl>.</note> We pretend
          that we are the wisest of the Hellenes, but we employ the kind of advisers whom no one
          could fail to despise, and we place these very same men in control of all our public
          interests to whom no one would entrust a single one of his private affairs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But, what is most reprehensible of all, we regard those whom all would acknowledge to be
          the most depraved of our citizens<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.316">Isoc. 15.316 ff.</bibl> and notes; <bibl n="Aristoph. Frogs 730"
              >Aristoph. Frogs 730 ff.</bibl></note> as the most trustworthy guardians of our
          polity; and we judge the character of our alien residents by the kind of patrons<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Only through a citizen to represent him as his “patron” before
            the law could a foreign resident enjoy the protection of the state. The word for patron,
              <foreign xml:lang="grc">prosta/ths</foreign>, was also used for the leader of the
            General Assembly. Hence the play on the word, which can be reproduced only by a free
            rendering in English.</note> they select to represent them, but do not expect that we
          shall be judged by the character of those who represent us at the head of the state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So far are we different from our ancestors that whereas they chose the same men to
          preside over the city and to be generals in the field,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For
            example, Pericles, who personally led a number of expeditions.</note> since they
          believed that one who could give the best counsel on this platform would best take counsel
          with himself when alone, we ourselves do the very opposite; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for the men whose counsels we follow in matters of the greatest importance—these we do
          not see fit to elect as our generals, as if distrusting their intelligence, but men whose
          counsel no one would seek either on his own business or on that of the state—these we send
          into the field with unlimited authority,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Obviously a jibe
            at Chares (the enemy of Isocrates' pupil and friend Timotheus. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.116">Isoc. 15.116</bibl>, note) who was sent out as <foreign
              xml:lang="grc">strathgo\s au)tokra/twr</foreign>. See <bibl n="Dem. 23.173">Dem.
              23.173</bibl>.</note> as if expecting that they will be wiser abroad than at home and
          will find it easier to take counsel on questions pertaining to the Hellenes than on those
          which are proposed for consideration here. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I say these things, not with reference to all, but with reference to those only who are
          open to the charges which I have made. However, the remainder of the day would not suffice
          me if I should attempt to review all the errors which have crept into our conduct of
          affairs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But someone among those who are hard hit by my strictures might take offense and demand
          of me, “How is it, if indeed we are so badly advised, that we are safe and hold a power
          which is inferior to that of no other city?” I, for my part, would reply to this question
          that we have in our adversaries men who are no more prudent than ourselves. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For example, if the Thebans, after the battle which they won over the
            Lacedaemonians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Battle of Leuctra, <date when="-0371"
              >371 B.C.</date>, the end of the Spartan supremacy and the beginning of the Theban
            hegemony, which lasted but nine years.</note> had contented themselves with liberating
          the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> and making the other Hellenes
            independent<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.53">Isoc. 5.53
              ff.</bibl></note> and had thenceforth pursued peace, while we continued to make such
          blunders, then neither could this man have asked such a question nor could we ourselves
          have failed to realize how much better moderation is than meddlesomeness. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But now matters have taken such a turn that the Thebans are saving us and we them, and
          they are procuring allies for us and we for them.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Not
            intentionally, but by our mistakes.</note> So that if we were sensible we should supply
          each other with money for our general assemblies; for the oftener we meet to deliberate
          the more do we promote the success of our rivals. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But those among us who are able to exercise even a modicum of reason ought not to rest
          our hopes of safety upon the blunders of our enemies but upon our own management of
          affairs and upon our own judgement. For the good fortune which results to us from their
          stupidity might perhaps cease or change to the opposite, whereas that which comes about
          because of our own efforts will be more certain and more enduring. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now it is not difficult to reply to those who take us to task without reason. But if
          anyone among those who are more fair-minded were to confront me and object, while
          conceding that I speak the truth and am correct in condemning the things which are taking
          place, that we have a right to expect of those who seek to admonish us with friendly
          purpose that they should not only denounce what has been done<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See also <bibl n="Dem. 1.16">Dem. 1.16</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but should also counsel us what to abstain from and what to strive for in order to cease
          from this way of thinking and from making such blunders, his objection would place me at a
          loss, not for a true answer and one that would be profitable, but for one that would be
          acceptable to you. But since I have set out to speak openly I must not shrink from
          disclosing what I think on these matters also. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Well then, the qualities which we must possess as a foundation if we are to be happy and
          prosperous, namely, piety and moderation and justice and virtue in all its phases, I
          mentioned a moment ago.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See 31-35.</note> But as to the
          means by which we may most speedily be taught to attain to such a character, what I am
          going to say will probably seem repellent to you when you have heard it as well as far
          removed from the opinions held by the rest of the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I, for my part, consider that we shall manage our city to better advantage and be
          ourselves better men and go forward in all our undertakings if we stop setting our hearts
          on the empire of the sea. For it is this which plunged us into our present state of
          disorder, which overthrew that democratic government<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Established by Solon and Cleisthenes, who are much praised in the
              <title>Areopagiticus</title>, <bibl n="Isoc. 7">Isoc. 7</bibl>.</note> under which our
          ancestors lived and were the happiest of the Hellenes, and which is the cause, one might
          almost say, of all the ills which we both suffer ourselves and inflict upon the rest of
          the Hellenes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I know, however, that it is difficult for one who attempts to denounce that imperial
          power which all the world lusts after and has waged many wars to obtain to impress his
          hearers as saying anything which is not intolerable. Nevertheless, since you have endured
          the other things which I have said, which, although true, are offensive, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I beg you to be patient also with what I shall say upon this subject and not to impute to
          me the madness of having chosen to discourse to you on matters so contrary to the general
          opinion without having something true to say about them. Nay, I believe that I shall make
          it evident to all that we covet an empire which is neither just nor capable of being
          attained nor advantageous to ourselves. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now that it is not just I can show you by lessons which I have learned from yourselves.
          For when the Lacedaemonians held this power,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">After <date
              when="-0404">404 B.C.</date></note> what eloquence did we not expend in denouncing
          their rule, contending that it was just for the Hellenes to enjoy independence? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>What cities of repute did we not call upon to join the alliance<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">In 395, at <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, an
            anti-Spartan alliance was entered.</note> which was formed in this cause? How many
          embassies did we not dispatch to the great King<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That headed
            by Conon in <date when="-0395">395 B.C.</date> is known.</note> to convince him that it
          was neither just nor expedient for one state to dominate the Hellenes? Indeed we did not
          cease waging war and facing perils both by land and sea until the Lacedaemonians were
          willing to enter into the treaty which guaranteed our independence.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The Peace of Antalcidas.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="69" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> At that time, then, we recognized the principle that it is not just for the stronger to
          rule over the weaker,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, we recognized it as valid
            not only in our domestic relations but in our foreign policy.</note> even as now we
          recognize it in the nature of the polity which has been established amongst ourselves. But
          that we could not, if we would, attain to this empire by conquest I think I shall quickly
          prove. For when, with the help of ten thousand talents,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A
            round number. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.234">Isoc. 15.234</bibl>. In 126 he speaks of 8000.
            Thucydides (ii.13. 3) states that 9700 talents was the largest amount ever stored on the
            Acropolis.</note> we were not able to retain it, how can we acquire it in our present
          state of poverty, especially since we are now addicted, not to the ways of life by which
          we gained it, but to those by which we lost it? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="70" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, that it is not even for the advantage of the state to accept this empire, if
          it were offered to us, I think you will learn very quickly from what further I have to
          say. But first I want to say a word by way of leading up to this point, fearing that, on
          account of my many strictures, I may give the impression to some of you of having chosen
          to denounce our city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="71" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If I were attempting to discourse in this manner before any others, I should naturally
          lay myself open to this charge. But now I am addressing myself to you, not with the wish
          that I may prejudice you in the eyes of others, but with the desire that I may cause you
          to make an end of such a policy and that Athens and the rest of the Hellenes may form a
          lasting peace. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="72" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But those who admonish and those who denounce cannot avoid using similar words, although
          their purposes are as opposite as they can be.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.130">Isoc. 4.130</bibl>.</note> You ought not, therefore, to have the same
          feeling towards all who use the same language but, while abhorring those who revile you to
          your harm as inimical to the state, you ought to commend those who admonish you for your
          good and to esteem them as the best of your fellow-citizens, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="73" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and him most of all, even among them, who is able to point out most vividly the evils of
          your practices and the disasters which result from them. For such a man can soonest bring
          you to abhor what you should abhor and to set your hearts on better things. These, then,
          are the things which I have to say in defense of my harshness both in the words which I
          have spoken and those which I am about to speak. I will now resume at the place where I
          left off. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="74" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I was on the point of saying that you could best learn that it is not to your
          advantage to obtain the empire of the sea if you should consider what was the condition of
          Athens before she acquired this power and what after she obtained it. For if you will
          examine one condition in contrast with the other you will see how many evils this power
          has brought upon the city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="75" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now the polity as it was in the earlier time was as much better and stronger than that
          which obtained later as Aristides and Themistocles and Miltiades<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Demosthenes (<bibl n="Dem. 3.21">Dem. 3.21 ff.</bibl>) compares Aristides and
            Pericles with the present-day orators who say to the people:“What are your desires; what
            shall I propose; how can I please you?”</note> were better men than Hyperbolus<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Hyperbolus, successor to Cleon, the tanner. Aristophanes calls
            him <foreign xml:lang="grc">ponhro/s</foreign> (<bibl n="Aristoph. Peace 684"
              >Aristoph. Peace 684</bibl>); Thucydides, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >moxqhro/s</foreign> (<bibl n="Thuc. 8.73">Thuc. 8.73</bibl>).</note> and
            Cleophon<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For Cleophon see <bibl n="Isoc. 8.13">Isoc.
              8.13</bibl>, note.</note> and those who today harangue the people.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Aristophon and Eubulus.</note> And you will find that the
          people who then governed the state were not given over to slackness and poverty and empty
            hopes,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.“hopes from the platform,” <bibl n="Dem. 4.45"
              >Dem. 4.45</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="76" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but were able to conquer in battle all who invaded their territory;<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.86">Isoc. 4.86</bibl>.</note> that they were awarded the
          meed of valor<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.99">Isoc.
            4.99</bibl>.</note> in the wars which they fought for the sake of <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>; and that they were so trusted that most of the
          states of their own free will placed themselves under their leadership.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.72">Isoc. 4.72</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="77" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But, notwithstanding these advantages, in place of a polity which was admired by all men
          this power has led us on to a state of license which no one in the world could commend; in
          place of our habit of conquering those who took the field against us it has instilled into
          our citizens such ways that they have not the courage even to go out in front of the walls
          to meet the enemy;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A rhetorical point. It was Pericles'
            policy in the Peloponnesian War to meet the enemy only on the sea and to keep on the
            defensive on land. He was bitterly criticized for keeping the Athenians cooped up within
            their walls while the Spartans invaded and ravaged their lands.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="78" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and in place of the good will which was accorded us by our allies and of the good repute
          in which we were held by the rest of the Hellenes it brought us into such a degree of
          odium that Athens barely escaped being enslaved and would have suffered this fate had we
          not found the Lacedaemonians, who were at war with us from the first, more friendly than
          those who were formerly our allies<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.6"
              >Isoc. 7.6</bibl> and note.</note>— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="79" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>not that we can have any just complaint against the latter for being obdurate towards us;
          for they were not aggressors but on the defensive, and came to have this feeling after
          suffering many grievous wrongs at our hands. For who could have brooked the insolence of
          our fathers? Gathering together from all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>
          men who were the worst of idlers and men who had a part in every form of depravity and
          manning their triremes with them,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Mercenaries made up the
            crews at the beginning of the Peloponnesian War. See <bibl n="Thuc. 1.121">Thuc.
              1.121</bibl>.</note> they made themselves odious to the Hellenes,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Thuc. 2.9">Thuc. 2.9</bibl>.</note> driving into exile the best
          of the citizens in the other states<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The aristocratic
            families, in order to make room for the democratic faction. Isocrates evidently means
            that their property was confiscated and used to pay the mercenaries. See <bibl
              n="Thuc. 8.21">Thuc. 8.21</bibl>. The rhetorical point is the same as in 46.</note>
          and distributing their property among the most depraved of the Hellenes! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="80" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But if I were to make bold to go through in detail what took place in those times I
          might probably help you to be better advised regarding the present situation, but I should
          prejudice my own reputation; for you are wont to hate not so much those who are
          responsible for your mistakes as those who undertake to denounce them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="81" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I fear, therefore, since you are of such a mind, that if I attempt to benefit you I may
          myself reap a poor reward. Nevertheless, I am not going to refrain entirely from saying
          the things which I had in mind but shall pass over the most severe and, mayhap, the most
          painful to you and recall to your minds only the facts by which you will recognize the
          folly of the men who at that time governed the city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="82" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For so exactly did they gauge<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Ironical. He means that
            they mastered the science of making themselves unpopular.</note> the actions by which
          human beings incur the worst odium that they passed a decree to divide the surplus of the
          funds derived from the tributes of the allies into talents and to bring it on the
            stage,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, the theoric fund. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.13">Isoc. 8.13</bibl>, note. The point of the division into talents is
            obscure. Perhaps one talent was distributed at each festival.</note> when the theatre
          was full, at the festival of Dionysus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The “Greater
            Dionysia,” celebrated in March.</note>; and not only was this done but at the same time
          they led in upon the stage the sons of those who had lost their lives in the war,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The state brought them up at public expense until they were of
            age for citizenship, at which time they were led before the concourse of the people in
            the theatre and bidden God speed! See <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.154">Aeschin.
            3.154</bibl>.</note> seeking thus to display to our allies,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">It appears that the “tribute” money of the allies during the Confederacy of
              <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> was brought to Athens by their
            representatives at the time of the Dionysiac festival. See <bibl n="Aristoph. Ach. 505"
              >Aristoph. Ach. 505, 643</bibl>. Besides, the festival attracted many unofficial
            visitors from the other states.</note> on the one hand, the value of their own
            property<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, the value we attach to it—how we honor
            their contributions.</note> which was brought in by hirelings,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The text clearly means “brought in by paid men.” But <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >misqwtoi/</foreign> may be either paid servants or paid soldiers. The former meaning
            is generally preferred by the editors because only in a loose sense could it be said
            that the tribute was brought in by mercenaries; besides, the present tense is employed.
            Nevertheless the reader will think of the hirelings mentioned just before (in 79) with
            whom the Athenians manned their triremes and through whom they forced the payment of the
            tribute, and doubtless the author so intended.</note> and to the rest of the Hellenes,
          on the other, the multitude of the fatherless and the misfortunes which result from this
          policy of aggression. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="83" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And in doing this they themselves counted the city happy, while many of the simple-minded
          deemed it blessed, taking no thought whatsoever for future consequences but admiring and
          envying the wealth which flowed into the city unjustly and which was soon to destroy also
          that which justly belonged to it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="84" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For they reached such a degree of neglect of their own possessions and of covetousness of
          the possessions of other states that when the Lacedaemonians had invaded our territory and
          the fortifications at Decelea<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This strong position on the
            slope of Mt. Parnes in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> was seized and
            fortified by the Spartans as an outpost from which to raid Athenian territory in <date
              when="-0413">413 B.C.</date></note> had already been built, they manned triremes to
          send to <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            original expedition to <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> was dispatched in
              <date when="-0415">415 B.C.</date> Strong reinforcements were, however, sent at the
            time Decelea was fortified by the Spartans. See <bibl n="Thuc. 7.20">Thuc.
            7.20</bibl>.</note> and were not ashamed to permit their own country to be cut off and
            plundered<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.92">Isoc.
            8.92</bibl>.</note> by the enemy while dispatching an expedition against a people who
          had never in any respect offended against us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="85" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nay, they arrived at such a pitch of folly that at a time when they were not masters of
          their own suburbs<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Decelea was 14 miles from Athens, but the
            Athenians kept within their walls, and the Spartans ravaged thier territory almost at
            will. See <bibl n="Thuc. 7.19">Thuc. 7.19 ff.</bibl></note> they expected to extend
          their power over <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> and <placeName
            key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Carthage"
            >Carthage</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Thucydides makes Alcibiades voice
            the expectation of conquering first <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>,
            then <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName>, and then <placeName
              key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName>. See <bibl n="Thuc. 6.90">Thuc.
              6.90</bibl>.</note> And so far did they outdo all mankind in recklessness that whereas
          misfortunes chasten others and render them more prudent our fathers learned no lessons
          even from this discipline. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="86" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet they were involved in more and greater disasters in the time of the empire<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">So also <bibl n="Thuc. 1.23">Thuc. 1.23</bibl>.</note> than
          have ever befallen Athens in all the rest of her history. Two hundred ships which set sail
          for <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> perished with their crews,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">These were sent to aid Inarus of <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
              >Egypt</placeName> in his revolt against <placeName key="tgn,7000231"
              >Persia</placeName>, <date when="-0460">460 B.C.</date> See <bibl n="Thuc. 1.104"
              >Thuc. 1.104 ff.</bibl></note> and a hundred and fifty off the island of <placeName
            key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Thucydides (<bibl
              n="Thuc. 1.112">Thuc. 1.112</bibl>) speaks of a fleet of 200 ships of which 60 were
            sent to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, the remainder under Cimon laying
            siege to <placeName key="tgn,7016636">Citium</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
              >Cyprus</placeName>. This expedition, though expensive in the loss of men and money,
            was not disastrous like the former.</note> in the Decelean War<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The text is very uncertain. The reading of the <placeName key="tgn,7011781"
              >London</placeName> papyrus is at least preferable since the loss of 10,000 hoplites
            (unless a hopeless exaggeration) cannot be accounted for if the reading of <foreign
              xml:lang="grc">*g*e</foreign> or that of the other MSS. is adopted. See Laistner in
              <title>Classical Quarterly</title> xv. p. 81. At the beginning of the Peloponnesian
            War (according to <bibl n="Thuc. 2.13">Thuc. 2.13</bibl>), the Athenian heavy-armed
            troops numbered but 29,000. Later (according to <bibl n="Dem. 25.51">Dem. 25.51</bibl>),
            the whole body of Athenian citizens numbered but 20,000.</note> they lost ten thousand
          heavy armed troops of their own and of their allies, and in <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
            >Sicily</placeName> forty thousand men and two hundred and forty ships,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Diodorus (<bibl n="Diod. 13.21">Dio. Sic. 13.21</bibl>) gives
            the same number of men, but 200 ships. Thucydides gives the number of ships as 209 and
            the number of men as not less than 40,000, including heavy and light armed troops,
            crews, etc. See especially <bibl n="Thuc. 7.75.5">Thuc. 7.75.5</bibl>.</note> and,
          finally, in the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName> two hundred
            ships.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At the battle of <placeName key="tgn,6000070"
              >Aegospotami</placeName> in <date when="-0405">405 B.C.</date>, the denouement of this
            tragic history. Xenophon (<bibl n="Xen. Hell. 2.1.20">Xen. Hell. 2.1.20</bibl>) and
            Diodorus (<bibl n="Diod. 13.105">Dio. Sic. 13.105</bibl>) give 180 as the number of
            ships.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="87" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But of the ships which were lost in fleets of ten or five or more and of the men who were
          slain in armies of a thousand or two thousand who could tell the tale? In a word, it was
          at that time a matter of regular routine to hold public funerals<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.74">Isoc. 4.74</bibl>, note.</note> every year, which
          many both of our neighbors and of the other Hellenes used to attend, not to grieve with us
          for the dead, but to rejoice together at our misfortunes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="88" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And at last, before they knew it, they had filled the public burial-grounds<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Ceramicus.</note> with the bodies of their fellow citizens
          and the registers of the phratries and of the state<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. 8.50">Isoc. 8.50</bibl>. All citizens were duly enrolled in the phratry
            registers, <foreign xml:lang="grc">fratorika\ grammatei=a</foreign> and in the state
            registers, kept in each township, <foreign xml:lang="grc">lhciarxika\
              grammatei=a</foreign>.</note> with the names of those who had no claim upon the city.
          And you may judge of the multitude of the slain from this fact: The families of the most
          illustrious Athenians and our greatest houses, which survived the civil conflicts under
          the tyrants<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Pisitratus and his sons, Hippias and
            Hipparchus. See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 18">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 18</bibl>.</note> and
          the Persian Wars as well, have been, you will find, entirely wiped out<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 8.4">Isoc. 8.4</bibl>.</note> under this
          empire upon which we set our hearts. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="89" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So that if one desired to go into the question of what befell the rest of our citizens,
          judging by this instance, it would be seen that we have been changed, one might almost
          say, into a new people. And yet we must not count that state happy which without
          discrimination recruits from all parts of the world a large number of citizens but rather
          that state which more than all others preserves the stock of those who in the beginning
          founded it. And we ought not to emulate those who hold despotic power nor those who have
          gained a dominion which is greater than is just but rather those who, while worthy of the
          highest honors, are yet content with the honors which are tendered them by a free people.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="90" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For no man nor any state could obtain a position more excellent than this or more secure
          or of greater worth. And it was because they acquired just this position that our
          ancestors in the time of the Persian Wars did not live in the manner of freebooters, now
          having more than enough for their needs, again reduced to a state of famine and siege<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">They were virtually in a state of seige after the occupation
            of Decelea by the Spartans, who cut off their food supplies.</note> and extreme
            misfortune<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The terrible plague described by Thucydides
            (i. 23; ii. 48 ff.).</note>; on the contrary, while they lived neither in want nor in
          surfeit of the means of subsistence day by day, they prided themselves on the justice of
          their polity and on their own virtues, and passed their lives more pleasantly than the
          rest of the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="91" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But, heedless of these lessons, those who came after them desired, not to rule but to
            dominate<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, to rule by consent as against ruling by
            force—delegated as against irresponsible power. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.80">Isoc. 4.80
              ff.</bibl></note>—words which are thought to have the same meaning, although between
          them there is the utmost difference. For it is the duty of those who rule to make their
            welfare,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. L. 7.4">Isoc. Letter
              7.4</bibl>.</note> whereas it is a habit of those who dominate to provide pleasures
          for themselves through the labors and hardships of others. But it is in the nature of
          things that those who attempt a despot's course must encounter the disasters which befall
          despotic power<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Described in 111-113.</note> and be
          afflicted by the very things which they inflict upon others. And it is just this which has
          happened in the case of Athens; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="92" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for in place of holding the citadels of other states, her people saw the day when the
          enemy was in possession of the Acropolis<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A Spartan garrison
            occupied the Acropolis during the rule of the Thirty.</note>; in place of dragging
          children from their mothers and fathers and taking them as hostages,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">This the Athenians did at <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName> in
              <date when="-0440">440 B.C.</date> See <bibl n="Thuc. 1.115">Thuc.
            1.115</bibl>.</note> many of her citizens, living in a state of siege, were compelled to
          educate and support their children with less than was their due; and in place of farming
          the lands of other states,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The reference is to the
            cleruchies. See 6, note.</note> for many years<note anchored="true" resp="ed">From 413
            to <date when="-0404">404 B.C.</date></note> they were denied the opportunity of even
          setting eyes upon their own fields. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="93" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If, therefore, anyone were to ask us whether we should choose to see Athens in such
          distress as the price of having ruled so long a time,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">From
            478 to <date when="-0405">405 B.C.</date></note> who could answer yes, except some
          utterly abandoned wretch who cared not for sacred matters nor for parents nor for children
          nor for any other thing save for the term of his own existence? We, however, ought not to
          emulate the judgement of such men but rather that of those who exercise great forethought
          and are no less jealous for the reputation of the state than for their own—men who prefer
          a moderate competence with justice to great wealth unjustly gained. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="94" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For our ancestors,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.90">Isoc.
              8.90</bibl>.</note> proving themselves to be men of this character, handed on the city
          to their descendants in a most prosperous condition and left behind them an imperishable
          memorial of their virtue. And from this we may easily learn a double lesson: that our soil
          is able to rear better men than the rest of the world<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. 7.74">Isoc. 7.74</bibl>.</note> and that what we call empire, though in
          reality it is misfortune,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Eur. Alc. 802">Eur.
              Alc. 802</bibl>: <foreign xml:lang="grc">ou)bi/os a)lhqw=s o( bi/os, a)lla\
              sumfora/</foreign>.</note> is of a nature to deprave all who have to do with it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="95" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> We have a most convincing proof of this. For imperialism worked the ruin not only of
          Athens but of the city of the Lacedaemonians also, so that those who are in the habit of
          praising the virtues of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName><note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 12.200">Isoc. 12.200</bibl>.</note> cannot
          argue that we managed our affairs badly because of our democratic government whereas if
          the Lacedaemonians had taken over the empire the results would have been happy both for
          the rest of the Hellenes and for themselves. For this power revealed its nature much more
          quickly in their case.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Spartan supremacy lasted from
            404 to 371; the Athenian from 478 to <date when="-0405">405 B.C.</date></note> Indeed it
          brought it to pass that a polity which over a period of seven hundred years<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">From the reign of Eurysthenes and Procles, about 1072, to the
            battle of Leuctra, <date when="-0371">371 B.C.</date> For the stability of the Spartan
            constitution see <bibl n="Isoc. 12.257">Isoc. 12.257</bibl>.</note> had never, so far as
          we know, been disturbed by perils or calamities was shaken and all but destroyed in a
          short space of time. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="96" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For in place of the ways of life established among them it filled the citizens with
          injustice, indolence, lawlessness and avarice and the commonwealth with contempt for its
          allies, covetousness of the possessions of other states, and indifference to its oaths and
          covenants. In fact they went so far beyond our ancestors in their crimes against the
          Hellenes that in addition to the evils which already afflicted the several states they
          stirred up in them slaughter and strife,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.110">Isoc. 4.110 ff.</bibl></note> in consequence of which their citizens
          will cherish for each other a hatred unquenchable. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="97" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And they became so addicted to war and the perils of war that, whereas in times past they
          had been more cautious in this regard<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An example of this
            caution is the advice of King Archidamus at the beginning of the Peloponnesian War. See
              <bibl n="Thuc. 1.80">Thuc. 1.80</bibl>.</note> than the rest of the world, they did
          not refrain from attacking even their own allies and their own benefactors; on the
          contrary, although the great King had furnished them with more than five thousand
            talents<note anchored="true" resp="ed">So also Andocides, <bibl n="Isoc. 8.29">Isoc.
              8.29</bibl>.</note> for the war against us, and although the Chians<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName> revolted from
            Athens in 412 B. C. and supported <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>
            with her fleet until the end of the Peloponnesian War.</note> had supported them more
          zealously than any of their other allies by means of their fleet </p>
      </div>
      <div n="98" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and the Thebans<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
              >Thebes</placeName> was one of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>'s
            strongest allies against Athens. See <bibl n="Thuc. 4.93">Thuc. 4.93</bibl>.</note> had
          contributed a great number of troops to their land forces, the Lacedaemonians no sooner
          gained the supremacy than they straightway plotted against the Thebans,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Instanced by the treacherous seizure of the Theban citadel
            (the Cadmea) by the Spartan Phoebidas. See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.2.25">Xen. Hell. 5.2.25
              ff.</bibl></note> dispatched Clearchus with an army against the King,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 12.104">Isoc. 12.104</bibl>. The “ten
            thousand” mercenaries led by the Spartan Clearchus to support Cyrus against King
            Artaxerxes were not officially dispatched, although sanctioned, by <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. For the fortunes of this army see <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.145">Isoc. 4.145-149</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 5.90">Isoc. 5.90 ff.</bibl>;
            and <bibl n="Xen. Anab.">Xen. Anab.</bibl></note> and in the case of the Chians drove
          into exile<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An oligarchy was established there and 600 of
            the democratic faction were driven into exile. See <bibl n="Diod. 13.65">Dio. Sic.
              13.65</bibl>.</note> the foremost of their citizens and launched their battle-ships
          from their docks and made off with their whole navy.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This
            was done by Lysander in <date when="-0404">404 B.C.</date> See <bibl n="Diod. 13.70"
              >Dio. Sic. 13.70</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="99" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> However, they were not satisfied with perpetrating these crimes, but about the same time
          were ravaging the Asiatic coast,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Greek settlements in
              <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.144">Isoc.
              4.144</bibl>.</note> committing outrages against the islands,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For example, <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName> (<bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 2.3.6">Xen. Hell. 2.3.6</bibl>), by expelling the democratic faction and
            setting up “decarchis” there.</note> subverting the free governments in <placeName
            key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>,
          setting up despotisms in their stead,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> supported Dionysius the tyrant of <placeName
              key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> in extending his power over Greek cities
            in <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
              >Italy</placeName>. See Diodorus xiv. 10 and cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.126">Isoc.
              4.126</bibl>, which should be read in this connection.</note> overrunning the
            <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> and filling it with seditions and
          wars. For, tell me, against which of the cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName> did they fail to take the field? Which of them did they fail to
          wrong? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="100" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Did they not rob the Eleans of part of their territory,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >See <bibl n="Diod. 14.17">Dio. Sic. 14.17</bibl>.</note> did they not lay waste the
          land of the Corinthians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 4.5.19"
              >Xen. Hell. 4.5.19</bibl>.</note> did they not disperse the Mantineans from their
            homes,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.126">Isoc. 4.126</bibl>;
              <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.2.1">Xen. Hell. 5.2.1</bibl>.</note> did they not reduce the
          Phliasians by siege,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.3.21">Xen.
              Hell. 5.3.21 ff.</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 4.126">Isoc. 4.126</bibl>.</note> and did
          they not invade the country of the Argives,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 4.4.19">Xen. Hell. 4.4.19</bibl>.</note> never ceasing from their
          depredations upon the rest of the world and so bringing upon themselves the disaster at
          Leuctra? Some maintain that this disaster was the cause of the misfortunes which overtook
            <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, but they do not speak the truth. For
          it was not because of this that they incurred the hatred of their allies; it was because
          of their insolence in the time preceding that they were defeated in this battle and fell
          into peril of losing their own city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="101" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>We must not attribute the cause to any subsequent misfortunes but to their crimes in the
          beginning, as the result of which they were brought to such a disastrous end. So that
          anyone would be much more in accord with the truth if he should assert that they first
          became subject to the dominion of their present ills at the moment when they attempted to
          seize the dominion of the sea,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For this word-play cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 5.61">Isoc. 5.61</bibl>, note; also this discourse, <bibl n="Isoc. 8.105"
              >Isoc. 8.105</bibl>.</note> since they were seeking to acquire a power which was in no
          wise like that which they had before possessed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="102" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For because of their supremacy on land and of their stern discipline and of the self
          control which was cultivated under it, they readily obtained command of the sea, whereas
          because of the arrogance<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The best commentary upon the
            association here of self-control (moderation) with an inland power and of the opposite
            with a sea power is a very interesting passage of the <bibl n="Isoc. 12.115">Isoc.
              12.115-116</bibl>.</note> which was bred in them by that power they speedily lost the
          supremacy both on land and sea. For they no longer kept the laws which they had inherited
          from their ancestors nor remained faithful to the ways which they had followed in times
          past, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="103" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but conceived that they were licensed to do whatever they pleased and so were plunged
          into great confusion. For they did not know that this licence which all the world aspires
          to attain is a difficult thing to manage, that it turns the heads of those who are
          enamored by it, and that it is in its nature like courtesans, who lure their victims to
          love but destroy those who indulge this passion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="104" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet it has been shown clearly that it has this effect; for anyone can see that those
          who have been in the strongest position to do whatever they pleased have been involved in
          the greatest disasters, ourselves and the Lacedaemonians first of all. For when these
          states, which in time past had governed themselves with the utmost sobriety and enjoyed
          the highest esteem,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.80">Isoc.
              4.80-81</bibl>.</note> attained to this license and seized the empire, they differed
          in no respect from each other, but, as is natural in the case of those who have been
          depraved by the same passions and the same malady, they attempted the same deeds and
          indulged in similar crimes and, finally, fell into like disasters. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="105" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For we, being hated by our allies and standing in peril of being enslaved, were saved by
          the Lacedaemonians;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See 78.</note> and just so they, when
          all the rest wanted to destroy them, came to us for refuge and were saved through us.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.44">Isoc. 5.44</bibl>, note; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 7.7">Isoc. 7.7</bibl>, note.</note> And yet how can we praise a dominion
          which subjects us to so miserable an end? How can we fail to abhor and shun a power which
          has incited these two cities both to do and to suffer many abominable things? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="106" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But, after all, we should not be surprised that in the past all men have failed to see
          that this power is the cause of so many ills to those who hold it, nor should we wonder
          that it has been the bone of contention between us and the Lacedaemonians. For you will
          find that the great majority of mankind go astray in choosing a course of action and,
          being possessed of more desires for things evil than for things good, take counsel more in
          the interest of their foes than of themselves. You can observe this in matters of the
          greatest importance. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="107" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For when has it ever happened otherwise? Did we not choose to pursue a policy in
          consequence of which the Lacedaemonians became masters of the Hellenes? Did not they, in
          their turn, manage their supremacy so badly that not many years later we again got the
          upper hand and became the arbiters of their safety? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="108" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Did not the meddlesomeness of the partizans of Athens cause the various states to become
          partisans of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, and did not the insolence
          of the partisans of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> force these same
          states to become partisans of Athens? Did not the people themselves, because of the
          depravity of the popular orators, desire the oligarchy which was established under the
          Four Hundred? And have not we, all of us, because of the madness of the Thirty,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For the excesses of the Thirty see <bibl n="Isoc. 7.66">Isoc.
              7.66 ff.</bibl></note> become greater enthusiasts for democracy than those who
          occupied <placeName key="perseus,Phyle">Phyle</placeName>?<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Thrasybulus, the leader of the “people's party,” seized the fortress of <placeName
              key="perseus,Phyle">Phyle</placeName> on Mt. Parnes and held it against the Thirty
            until the democracy was restored. See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.64">Isoc. 7.64</bibl>,
            note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="109" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Indeed in matters of lesser importance and in our everyday life, one could show that the
          majority take pleasure in the foods and habits which injure both the body and the soul but
          consider laborious and irksome those from which both sides of our nature would benefit,
          and that those men are looked upon as austere who remain steadfast in habits which are
            beneficial.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.45">Isoc.
            2.45</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="110" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Since, therefore, in the circumstances in which they live every day and about which they
          are more directly concerned, men show that they prefer the worse to the better course, how
          can we be surprised if they lack insight regarding the empire of the sea and make war upon
          each other to possess a power regarding which they have never reflected in their lives?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="111" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Look at the one-man-rule which is established in various states and observe how many
          there are who aspire to it and are ready to undergo anything whatsoever to obtain it. And
          yet what that is dire and difficult is not its portion?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
            Pictures of the fate of despots in <bibl n="Isoc. 2.5">Isoc. 2.5</bibl>, <bibl
              n="Isoc. 10.32">Isoc. 10.32 ff.</bibl>, and <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 579">Plat. Rep.
              579</bibl>.</note> Is it not true that when men obtain unlimited power they find
          themselves at once in the coil of so many troubles </p>
      </div>
      <div n="112" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>that they are compelled to make war upon all their citizens, to hate those from whom they
          have suffered no wrong whatsoever, to suspect their own friends and daily companions, to
          entrust the safety of their persons to hirelings whom they have never even seen, to fear
          no less those who guard their lives than those who plot against them, and to be so
          suspicious towards all men as not to feel secure even in the company of their nearest
            kin?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. Cicero, <title>Laelius</title>15: “haec enim est
            tyrannorum vita nimirum in qua nulla fides, nulla caritas, nulla stabilis
            bennnevolentiae potest esse fiducia; omnia semper suspecta atque sollicita.”</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="113" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And naturally so; for they know well that those who held despotic power before them have
          been put out of the way, some by their parents,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Alexander
            of <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> by his mother.</note> some by their
            sons,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Astyages by Cyrus.</note> some by their
            brothers,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Acetas by Perdiccas; Jason of Pherae by
            Polydorus.</note> and some by their wives<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Alexander of
            Pherae.</note> and, furthermore, that the lineage of these rulers has been blotted out
          from the sight of men.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.108">Isoc.
              5.108</bibl>, note.</note> Nevertheless they willingly submit themselves to such a
          multitude of calamities.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. the saying of Periander (<bibl
              n="Hdt. 3.53">Hdt. 3.53</bibl>): <foreign xml:lang="grc">turanni\s xrh=ma sfalero/n:
              polloi\ d' au)th=s e)rastai/ ei)si</foreign>.</note> And when men who are of the
          foremost rank and of the greatest reputation are enamored of so many evils, is it any
          wonder that the rest of the world covets other evils of the same kind? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="114" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I do not fail to realize that while you accept readily what I say about the rule of
          despots, yet you hear with intolerance what I say about the empire of the sea. For you
          have fallen into a most shameful and careless way of thinking, since what you see clearly
          in the case of others, this you are blind to in your own case. And yet it is not the least
          important sign of whether men are possessed of intelligence if they are seen to recognize
          the same course of conduct in all cases that are comparable.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">That is, if they apply the same standard of judgement to all similar
            cases.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="115" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But you have never given this a thought; on the contrary, while you consider the power of
          a despot to be harsh and harmful not only to others but to those who hold it, you look
          upon the empire of the sea as the greatest good in the world, when in fact it differs
          neither in what it does nor in what it suffers from one-man-rule. And you think that the
          affairs of the Thebans are in a bad way because they oppress their neighbors,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Thespians and the Plataeans, whom the Thebans expelled
            from their territory.</note> but, although you yourselves are treating your allies no
          better than the Thebans treat the Boeotians, you believe that your own actions leave
          nothing to be desired. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="116" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If, then, you heed my advice you will stop taking counsel in your utterly haphazard
          fashion and give your attention to your own and the state's welfare; pondering and
          searching into these questions: What is it which caused these two states—Athens and
            <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> I mean—to rise, each one of them,
          from obscure beginnings to be the first power in <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName> and then to fall, after they had attained a power second to none,
          into peril of being enslaved? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="117" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>What are the reasons that the Thessalians, who inherited very great wealth and possess a
          very rich and abundant territory,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.155">Isoc. 15.155</bibl>; <bibl n="Thuc. 1.2">Thuc. 1.2</bibl>.</note>
          have been reduced to poverty, while the Megarians, who had small and insignificant
            resources<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Megarians were mere “nobodies” among the
            Greeks. Cf. <bibl n="Aristoph. Ach. 519">Aristoph. Ach. 519</bibl>, and the saying:
              <foreign xml:lang="grc">tw=n *megare/wn ou)dei\s lo/gos</foreign>. Isocrates could
            have ventured no more astounding paradox than in holding up the Megarians as an example
            to follow.</note> to begin with and who possess neither land nor harbors<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">He means no lands or harbors to speak of, for the Megarians
            had both, though very little land.</note> nor mines but are compelled to farm mere
          rocks, own estates which are the greatest<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Through
            commerce.</note> among the Hellenes? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="118" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Why is it that the Thessalians, with a cavalry of more than three thousand horse and
          light-armed troops beyond number,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 6.1.19">Xen. Hell. 6.1.19</bibl>.</note> have their fortresses occupied
          from time to time by certain other states<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By the
            Macedonians under Alexander II. and by the Thebans under Pelopidas.</note> while the
          Megarians, with only a small force, govern their city as they see fit? And, again, why is
          it that the Thessalians are always at war with each other while the Megarians, who dwell
          between the Peloponnesians on the one hand and the Thebans and the Athenians on the other,
          are continually in a state of peace?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An “unphilosophical”
            answer might be that no one coveted Megarian territory, whereas Thessalian resources
            were tempting. See a remark of <bibl n="Thuc. 1.2">Thuc. 1.2</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="119" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If you will go over these and similar questions in your minds, you will discover that
          arrogance and insolence have been the cause of our misfortunes while sobriety and self
          control have been the source of our blessings.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General
            Introd. pp. xxxii, xxxiii, Isocrates, Vol. I., L.C.L.</note> But, while you commend
          sobriety in individual men and believe that those who practice it enjoy the most secure
          existence and are the best among your fellow citizens, you do not think it fit to make the
          state practice it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="120" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet it behoves states much more than individuals to cultivate the virtues and to shun
            vices;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 545b">Plat. Rep.
              545b</bibl>.</note> for a man who is godless and depraved may die before paying the
          penalty for his sins, but states, since they are deathless, soon or late must submit to
          punishment at the hands both of men and of the gods. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="121" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> These considerations you should bear in mind and not pay heed to those who gratify you
          for the moment, while caring nothing for the future, nor to those who profess to love the
          people, but are in fact the bane of the whole state; since in times past also when men of
          this character took over the supremacy of the rostrum,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Obviously sarcastic: Their “supremacy” spells disaster to the state.</note> they led
          the city on to such a degree of folly that she suffered the fate which I described a
          moment ago. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="122" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And indeed what is most astonishing of all in your conduct is that you prefer as leaders
          of the people, not those who are of the same mind as the men who made <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> great, but those who say and do the same kind of
          things as the men who destroyed her power; and you do this albeit knowing full well that
          it is not alone in making the city prosperous that good leaders are superior to the base,
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="123" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but that our democracy itself under the leadership of the former remained unshaken and
          unchanged for many years,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A century, from the reforms of
            Cleisthenes in 510 to the revolution of <date when="-0411">411 B.C.</date></note>
          whereas under the guidance of these men it has already, within a short period of
            time,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In 411 and <date when="-0404">404
            B.C.</date></note> been twice overthrown, and that, furthermore, our people who were
          driven into exile under the despots and in the time of the Thirty were restored to the
          state, not through the efforts of the sycophants,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">False
            accusers, slanderers, professional blackmailers—a class of persons which sprang up like
            weeds in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> after the age of Pericles.
            Their favorite device was to extort money by threatening or instituting law-suits. But
            the word was applied indiscriminately by Isocrates and others to demagogues and
            politicians of the opposite party. See Lafberg, <title>Sycophancy in Athens</title>. Cf.
              <bibl n="Aristoph. Pl. 850">Aristoph. Pl. 850 ff.</bibl> The term “flatterers” is used
            in 4.</note> but through those leaders who despised men of that character and were held
          in the highest respect for their integrity.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Aristides
            restored the people after the rule of the Pisistratidae and Thrasybulus after the rule
            of the Thirty—both men of unblemished reputation.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="124" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Nevertheless, in spite of the many things which remind us how the city fared under both
          kinds of leadership, we are so pleased with the depravity of our orators that, although we
          see that many of our other citizens have been stripped of their patrimony because of the
          war and of the disorders which these sycophants have caused, while the latter, from being
          penniless, have become rich,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A frequent charge. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.140">Isoc. 12.140 ff.</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 23.208">Dem.
            23.208-209</bibl>. Aeschines (<bibl n="Aeschin. 3.173">Aeschin. 3.173</bibl>) makes it
            against Demosthenes himself: “he maintains himself, not from his private income, but
            from your perils.” The popular orators were in a strong position to make or break the
            fortunes or the reputations of men and of cities. Isocrates attributes the bad treatment
            of the general Timotheus by the Athenians to the latter's failure to court the favor of
            the orators, which other military leaders took pains to do. See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.136"
              >Isoc. 15.136</bibl>. Generals in the field found oportunities to enrich themselves
            and were prudent enough to “cultivate” the popular leaders at home. Chares,
            particularly, had the reputation of doing this. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.50">Isoc.
              8.50</bibl>, note. On the question of bribery at this time see Butcher,
              <title>Demosthenes</title> pp. 11 ff.</note> yet we are not aggrieved nor do we resent
          their prosperity </p>
      </div>
      <div n="125" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but remain patient with a condition of affairs wherein our city is reproached with doing
          violence to the Hellenes and extorting money from them,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
              <bibl n="Aristoph. Wasps 655-724">Aristoph. Wasps 655-724</bibl>.</note> while these
          men reap the harvest,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Aristoph. Wasps 1114"
              >Aristoph. Wasps 1114 ff.</bibl></note> and wherein our people, who are told by the
          sycophants that they ought to rule over the rest of the world, are worse off than those
          who are slaves to oligarchy,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.105"
              >Isoc. 4.105</bibl>.</note> while these men, who had no advantage to start with, have
          risen because of our folly from a mean to an enviable position. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="126" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet Pericles,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates' attitude towards Pericles is
            set forth at greater length in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.234">Isoc. 15.234</bibl>.</note> who
          was the leader of the people before men of this stamp came into favor, taking over the
          state when it was less prudent than it had been before it obtained the supremacy, although
          it was still tolerably well governed, was not bent upon his own enrichment,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Thucydides (ii. 65) calls him “incorruptible beyond
            suspicion.”</note> but left an estate which was smaller than that which he received from
          his father, while he brought up into the Acropolis eight thousand talents,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.69">Isoc. 8.69</bibl>, note; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.234">Isoc. 15.234</bibl>.</note> apart from the sacred treasures. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="127" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But these demagogues have shown themselves so different from him that they have the
          effrontery to say that because of the care they give to the commonwealth they are not able
          to give attention to their private interests, although in fact these “neglected” interests
          have advanced to a degree of affluence which they would never have even dreamed of praying
          to the gods that they might attain, whereas our people, for whom they pretend to care, are
          in such straits that not one of our citizens is able to live with pleasure or at ease; on
          the contrary, Athens is rife with lamentations. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="128" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For some are driven to rehearse and bewail amongst themselves their poverty and privation
          while others deplore the multitude of duties enjoined upon them by the state—the liturgies
          and all the nuisances connected with the symmories and with exchanges of property;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The burdens of state expense were theoretically carried by
            those best able to bear them. The twelve hundred richest citizens were divided in
            accordance with their wealth into twenty classes, called symmories. Special tax levies
            for war purposes were levied upon them in proportion to their means. Besides, men of the
            wealthiest class were called upon to perform the “liturgies” at their own expense. One
            of the most burdensome of these was the trierarchy—fitting out a battleship for service
            and maintaining it in fighting trim for one year. If a man called upon to undertake such
            a burden felt that another could better afford to stand the expense he had the right to
            demand that he do so or else exchange property with him. See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.145"
              >Isoc. 15.145</bibl>, note, and the introduction to that discourse.</note> for these
          are so annoying that those who have means find life more burdensome than those who are
          continually in want. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="129" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I marvel that you cannot see at once that no class is so inimical to the people as our
          depraved orators and demagogues. For, as if your other misfortunes were not enough, their
          chief desire is that you should be in want of your daily necessities, observing that those
          who are able to manage their affairs from their private incomes are on the side of the
          commonwealth and of our best counsellors, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="130" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>whereas those who live off the law-courts and the assemblies<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Three obols a day were paid for the attendance of jury-men and of members of
            the General Assembly. See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.24">Isoc. 7.24</bibl>, 54, and notes; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.152">Isoc. 15.152</bibl>.</note> and the doles derived from them are
          constrained by their need to be subservient to the sycophants and are deeply grateful for
          the impeachments and the indictments<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.314">Isoc. 15.314</bibl>, note.</note> and the other sharp practices which
          are due to the sycophants. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="131" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Wherefore these men would be most happy to see all of our citizens reduced to the
          condition of helplessness in which they themselves are powerful.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.241">Isoc. 15.241</bibl>.</note> And the greatest proof
          of this is that they do not consider by what means they may provide a livelihood for those
          who are in need, but rather how they may reduce those who are thought to possess some
          wealth to the level of those who are in poverty. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="132" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> What, then, is the way of escape from our present ills? I have already discussed most of
          the points which bear upon this question, not in sequence, but as each fell into its
          opportune place. But perhaps it will help you to hold them in memory if I attempt to bring
          together and review those which more than others press upon our attention. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="133" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The first way by which we can set right and improve the condition of our city is to
          select as our advisers on affairs of state the kind of men whose advice we should desire
          on our private affairs, and to stop thinking of the sycophants as friends of democracy and
          of the good men and true<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This term is almost technical for
            the aristocratic party, but is here used in a broader sense. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.316"
              >Isoc. 15.316</bibl>.</note> among us as friends of oligarchy,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.318">Isoc. 15.318</bibl>.</note> realizing that no man
          is by nature either the one or the other but that all men desire, in each case, to
          establish that form of government in which they are held in honor. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="134" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The second way is to be willing to treat our allies just as we would our friends and not
          to grant them independence in words, while in fact giving them over to our generals to do
          with as they please,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Aimed at Chares. Diodorus (xv. 95)
            says of him: <foreign xml:lang="grc">tou\s summa/xous a)dikw=n diete/lei</foreign>.
            Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Rh. 3.17">Aristot. Rh. 3.17</bibl>: <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >*)isokra/ths kathgorei= *xa/rhtos e)n tw=| summaxikw=|</foreign>.</note> and not to
          exercise our leadership as masters but as helpers,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. 4.80">Isoc. 4.80</bibl>.</note> since we have learned the lesson that
          while we are stronger than any single state we are weaker than all <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="135" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And the third way is to consider that nothing is more important, save only to show
          reverence to the gods, than to have a good name among the Hellenes. For upon those who are
          so regarded they willingly confer both sovereign power and leadership. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="136" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If, then, you will abide by the advice which I have given you, and if, besides, you will
          prove yourselves warlike by training and preparing for war but peaceful by doing nothing
          contrary to justice,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Repeated from <bibl n="Isoc. 2.24"
              >Isoc. 2.24</bibl>.</note> you will render not only this city but all the Hellenes
          happy and prosperous. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="137" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For no other of the states will dare to oppress them; on the contrary, they will hold
          back and studiously avoid aggression when they see the power of Athens on the alert and
          ready to go to the aid of the oppressed. But no matter what course the rest may take, our
          own position will be honorable and advantageous; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="138" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for if the foremost states resolve to abstain from acts of oppression, we shall have the
          credit for this blessing; but if, on the other hand, they attempt to oppress others, then
          all who fear them and suffer evil at their hands will come to us for refuge, with many
          prayers and supplications, offering us not only the hegemony but their own support. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="139" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So that we shall not lack for allies to help us to check the oppressors but shall find
          many ready and willing to join their forces to our own. For what city or what men will not
          be eager to share our friendship and our alliance when they see that the Athenians are at
          once the most just and the most powerful of peoples and are at the same time both willing
          and able to save the other states, while needing no help for themselves? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="140" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>What a turn for the better should you expect the affairs of our city to take when we
          enjoy such good will from the rest of the Hellenes? What wealth will flow into Athens when
          through her all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> is made secure? And who
          among men will fail to praise those who will have been the authors of blessings so many
          and so great? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="141" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I am not able because of my age<note anchored="true" resp="ed">He is now 81 years
            old.</note> to include in my speech all the things which I grasp in my thought, save
          that it is a noble enterprise for us, in the midst of the injustice and madness of the
          rest of the world, to be the first to adopt a sane policy and stand forth as the champions
          of the freedom of the Hellenes, to be acclaimed as their saviors, not their
            destroyers,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.80">Isoc.
            4.80</bibl>.</note> and to become illustrious for our virtues and regain the good repute
          which our ancestors possessed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="142" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I have yet to touch upon the chief consideration of all—that upon which centers
          everything that I have said and in the light of which we should appraise the actions of
          the state. For if we really wish to clear away the prejudice in which we are held at the
          present time, we must cease from the wars which are waged to no purpose and so gain for
          our city the hegemony for all time; we must abhor all despotic rule and imperial power,
          reflecting upon the disasters which have sprung from them; and we must emulate and imitate
          the position held by the kings of <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>:
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="143" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>they, it is true, have less freedom than their private citizens to do wrong,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Spartan kings were powerful in the field, but otherwise
            were subject to the Ephors, who could even have them put to death. See Gilbert,
              <title>Greek Consitituional Antiquities</title> pp. 46 ff. and 57 ff.</note> yet are
          much more enviable than those who hold despotic power by force; for those who take the
          lives of despots are given the highest rewards by their fellow citizens,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">He has in mind the honors shown by the Athenians to the
            “tyrannicides,” Harmodius and Aristogeiton.</note> whereas those Spartans who are not
          ready to lay down their lives for their kings in battle<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
              <bibl n="Isoc. 5.80">Isoc. 5.80</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. L. 2.6">Isoc. Letter
              2.6</bibl>.</note> are held in greater dishonor than men who desert their post and
          throw away their shields.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >r(iyaspis</foreign> was not only despised but suffered humiliations and penalties. In
            Athens, which was less rigorous than <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>,
            he lost his political rights.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="144" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>This, then, is the kind of leadership which is worth striving for. And this very position
          of honor which the kings of <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> have from
          their citizens we Athenians have it in our power to win from the Hellenes, if only they
          become convinced that our supremacy will be the instrument, not of their enslavement, but
          of their salvation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="145" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> My subject is not exhausted; there are many excellent things to be said upon it, but I
          am prompted by two considerations to stop speaking: the length of my discourse and the
          number of my years. But I urge and exhort those who are younger and more vigorous than I
          to speak and write the kind of discourses by which they will turn the greatest
          states—those which have been wont to oppress the rest—into the paths of virtue and
          justice, since when the affairs of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> are in
          a happy and prosperous condition, it follows that the state of learning and letters also
          is greatly improved.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A somewhat academic close, but the
            state of affairs and the state of learning are not dissociated in his mind; “philosophy”
            is the salvation of the state.</note></p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
