<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On His Return from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
				<author>Andocides</author>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>


			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Andocides</author>
						<title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes 1, Antiphon Andocides, with an
							English translation by K. J. Maidment, M.A.</title>

						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
								Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1968</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="speech" delim="."/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English </language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek </language>
				<language ident="latin">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--
<change><date>3/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>redo tagging</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
	<change><date>5/27/09</date><respStmt><name>RS</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt>
		<item>  
			$Log: andoc_eng.xml,v $
			Revision 1.1  2009-10-09 19:49:16  rsingh04
			more reorganizing of texts module by collection

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/07 21:00:34  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.10  2009/06/22 19:33:09  student
			edited entity tags CEH

			Revision 1.9  2009/05/27 15:55:16  rsingh04
			added cvs log keyword

		</item>
	</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
			<change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="part" n="Intro">
				<div type="section" n="1">
					<p>Had some other matter been at issue, gentlemen, I should have felt no
						surprise at finding a difference of opinion among the speakers who addressed
						you. But when the question is whether or not I, or anyone less worthy who so
						desires, should do this state a service, nothing seems to me more
						extraordinary than that contrary views should be held, instead of there
						being complete unanimity; for if the state is common to all who enjoy civic
						rights, the benefits which the state receives are likewise, I presume,
						common benefits.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="2">
					<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Such disagreement is a matter for alarm and
						astonishment; yet, as you can see, it has already been expressed by some,
						and will shortly be expressed by others. Indeed, I am completely at a loss
						to understand why the question of your receiving a benefit from me should
						cause such excitement among our friends here. They must either be the most
						stupid of mankind or the worst of public enemies. If they hold that when the
						state is prospering they are better off individually, they are showing
						extreme stupidity in advocating today a policy which directly conflicts with
						their own interests; </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="3">
					<p>while if they do not identify their interests as individuals with yours as a
						community, they can only be public enemies. Indeed when I secretly
						communicated to the Council a proposal which would be of the very greatest
						service to this city if carried into effect, and proved as much clearly and
						conclusively to the members present, such of my present critics as were
						among my audience found it as impossible as anyone else to show by argument
						that any of my statements was incorrect; yet they are now trying to impugn
						those statements. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="4">
					<p>This proves, then, that they are acting not on their own initiative—or they
						would have had no hesitation in opposing me originally—but on the
						instigation of others, of men such as are to be found in this city, who
						would not allow you to receive a benefit from me for all the money in the
						world. These others have not the courage to come into the open and make good
						their assertions in person, as they are afraid of letting their own possible
						shortcomings as patriots be examined too closely. Instead, they send
						substitutes to address you, men to whom effrontery is second nature, men who
						will utter or face the bitterest abuse with complete indifference. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="5">
					<p>The entire strength of their case against me, one finds, lies in their
						taunting me at every turn with my misfortunes; and that too when their
						listeners know better than they, so that not a word which they have uttered
						can bring them any true credit. </p>
					<p>To my mind, gentlemen, he was a wise man who first said that every human
						being is born to meet with good fortune and with bad; that to make a mistake
						is to meet with great ill fortune:</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="part" n="Narr">
				<div type="section" n="6">
					<p>and that while those who make the fewest mistakes are the luckiest, those who
						repent of them soonest show most good sense. Nor is this the peculiar lot of
						some men only; it is the common fate of humanity to make mistakes and suffer
						misfortune. So do but remember the frailty of man in passing judgement upon
						me, gentlemen, and your feelings for me will be more kindly. Indeed I do not
						deserve ill-will so much as sympathy for the past. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="7">
					<p>Owing to—shall I say my own youthful folly, or the influence of others who
						persuaded me into such a piece of madness?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>A clear indication that Andocides had been concerned to at least some
							extent in the mutilation of the Hermae.</note>—I was luckless enough to
						be forced to choose between two of the most painful alternatives imaginable.
						On the one hand, I could refuse to disclose the authors of the outrage. In
						that case I not only trembled for my own fate, but caused the death of my
						father, who was entirely innocent, as well as my own—he was inevitably
						doomed, if I refused to speak. On the other hand, I could purchase my own
						life and liberty and avoid becoming my father's murderer—and what would a
						man not bring himself to do to escape that?—but only by turning informer.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="8">
					<p>Of the alternatives before me, then, I chose that which meant years of sorrow
						for myself, but immediate release for you from the distress of the moment.
						Remember your peril: remember your helplessness: remember how you stood in
						such fear of one another that you ceased going abroad even into the Agora,
						because you each expected arrest.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl
								n="Andoc. 1.36">Andoc. 1.36</bibl>.</note> That such a state of
						things should have occurred at all proved to be due only in small part to
						me; that it ended, on the other hand, proved to be due to me alone.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="9">
					<p>Notwithstanding, I have never succeeded in being anything save the unluckiest
						man alive; for when <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> was
						heading for this disaster, no one came near suffering the sorrows which I
						suffered: and when she was once more regaining her security, I was of all
						men the most to be pitied. The desperate distress of <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> could be remedied only at the
						cost of my good name: so that your deliverance meant my own ruin. It is your
						gratitude, therefore, not your scorn that I deserve for my sufferings. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="10">
					<p>At the time I needed none to remind me of my plight—partly through my own
						folly, partly through the force of circumstances, nothing was wanting to
						complete my misery and my disgrace—and I saw that you would be best pleased
						were I to adopt that mode of life and that place of residence which would
						enable me to remain furthest from your sight.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">Andocides was not exiled under the actual terms of the
							decree of Isotimides. The decree made life at <placeName
								key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> so intolerable for him that
							he found it better to withdraw of his own accord.</note> Eventually,
						however, as was only natural, I was seized with a longing for the old life
						as a citizen among you which I had abandoned for my present place of exile;
						and I decided that I should be best advised either to have done with life or
						to render this city such a service as would dispose you to let me at last
						resume my rights as your fellow. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="11">
					<p>From that moment I have been reckless of both life and goods when called upon
						for a perilous venture. In fact, I at once proceeded to supply your forces
						in <placeName key="perseus,Samos City">Samos</placeName> with oar-spars—this
						was after the Four Hundred had seized power at <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>i.e. in 411.</note>—since Archelaus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>King of <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> from 413 to
							399 B.C.</note> had hereditary connexions with my family and offered me
						the right of cutting and exporting as many as I wished.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">The text of an Attic decree honouring Archelaus for
							supplying <foreign xml:lang="greek">cu/la kai\ kwpe/as</foreign> still
							survives (I.G. i 2 105). It may be consulted best in the restored
							version of B. D. Meritt; see <title>Classical Studies presented to
								Edward Capps</title>
							<placeName key="tgn,7016190">Princeton</placeName>, <date>1936</date>.
							Meritt would date it to <dateRange from="-407" to="-406"
							>407</dateRange>-406 B.C.</note> And not only did I supply the spars; I
						refused to charge more for them than they had cost me, although I might have
						obtained a price of five drachmae apiece. In addition, I supplied corn and
						bronze. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="12">
					<p>Thus equipped, the forces in <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>
						went on to defeat the Peloponnesians at sea<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>Most probably the battle of <placeName key="perseus,Cyzicus"
								>Cyzicus</placeName>, April 410. See Introd.</note>; and it was
						they, and they alone who saved <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName> at the time. Now if those heroes rendered you true
						service by their deed, I may fairly claim that that service was in no small
						degree due to me. Had that army not been furnished with supplies just then,
						they would have been fighting not so much to save <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> as to save their own lives. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="13">
					<p>In these circumstances, I was not a little surprised at the situation which I
						found at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. I returned
						thither fully expecting the congratulations of the city on the active way in
						which I had displayed my devotion to your interests. Instead, directly they
						learned of my arrival, certain of the Four Hundred sought me out, arrested
						me, and brought me before the Council.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e.
							their fellow-members of the Four Hundred. The Council proper had been
							superseded.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="14">
					<p>Whereupon Peisander<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For the career of
							Peisander see <bibl n="Andoc. 1.36">Andoc. 1.36</bibl> note.</note> at
						once came up, took his stand beside me, and cried: “Gentlemen, I hereby
						denounce this man as having supplied corn and oar-spars to the enemy.” Then
						he went on to tell the whole story. By this time, of course, it was clear
						that there had been a complete estrangement between the men on service and
						the Four Hundred. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="15">
					<p>I saw the uproar into which the meeting was breaking, and knew that I was
						lost; so I sprang at once to the hearth and laid hold of the sacred emblems.
						That act, and that alone, was my salvation at the time; for although I stood
						disgraced in the eyes of the gods,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Owing to
							his participation in the mutilation of the Hermae four years
							before.</note> they, it seems, had more pity on me than did men; when
						men were desirous of putting to death, it was the gods who saved my life. My
						subsequent imprisonment and the extent and nature of the bodily suffering to
						which I was subjected would take too long to describe. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="16">
					<p>It was then that I bewailed my lucklessness more bitterly than ever. When the
						people appeared to be hardly used, it was I who suffered in their stead; on
						the other hand, when they had been manifestly benefited by me, that act of
						service likewise threatened me with ruin.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>i.e. (a) Andocides put an end to the reign of terror which followed the
							mutilation of the Hermae, but at the cost of his own happiness. (b) He
							had helped <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> win a
							victory over <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> at sea,
							but had again suffered for it by imprisonment at the hands of the Four
							Hundred.</note> Indeed I no longer had either ways or means of
						sustaining my hopes; everywhere I turned I saw woe in store for me. However,
						disheartening though my reception had been, I was no sooner a free man than
						my every thought was again directed to the service of this city. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="17">
					<p>You must understand, gentlemen, how far such services as mine surpass
						ordinary services. When citizens who hold public office add to your
						revenues, are they not in fact giving you what is yours already? And when
						those who hold military command benefit their country by some fine exploit,
						is it not by exposing your persons to fatigue and danger and by spending
						public money in addition that they render you such service as they do?
						Again, if they make a mistake at some point, it is not they themselves who
						pay for their mistake; it is you who pay for the error which was due to
						them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="18">
					<p>Yet you bestow crowns on such persons and publicly proclaim them as heroes.
						And I will not deny that they deserve it; it is proof of signal merit to be
						able to render one's country a service in any way whatsoever. But you must
						see that that man is far the worthiest who has the courage to expose his own
						life and his own goods to danger in order to confer a benefit on his
						fellow-countrymen. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="19">
					<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>My past services must be known to almost all
						of you. But the services which I am about to render, which I have, in fact,
						already begun to render, have been revealed in secret to only five hundred
						of you [;,to the Council, that is to say<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>The words <foreign xml:lang="greek">h( boulh/</foreign> were rightly
							bracketed by Valckenaer as a gloss upon what precedes. The “secret
							proposal” placed before the Council must have been connected with the
							future corn-supply of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName>. Andocides was doubtless to use his influence in
								<placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> to ensure that it
							should not be interrupted.</note>];; they, I think, are likely to make
						far fewer mistakes than you would be, had you to debate the matter here and
						now immediately after listening to my explanations. Those five hundred are
						considering at leisure the proposal placed before them, and they are liable
						to be called to account and censured by the rest of you for any mistake
						which they may make; </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="20">
					<p>whereas you have none to hold you to blame, as you very rightly have the
						power of ordering your affairs wisely or foolishly at will. However, I will
						disclose to you such services as I can, such services as are not a secret,
						because they have already been performed. </p>
					<p>I need not remind you, I imagine, how you received news that no grain was to
						be exported to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> from
							<placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>. Now I was able to
						handle the situation with such effect that the persons who had formed the
						plot and put it into execution were frustrated. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="21">
					<p>It is of no importance that you should know how this was done; what I do wish
						you to know is that the ships on the point of putting in to the Peiraeus at
						this moment with a cargo of grain number no less than fourteen; while the
						remainder of the convoy which sailed from <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
							>Cyprus</placeName> will arrive in a body shortly after them. </p>
					<p>I would have given all the money in the world to be able to reveal to you
						with safety the secret proposal which I have placed before the Council, so
						that you might know at once what to expect. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="22">
					<p>Instead, you will only learn what it is when you begin to benefit by it, and
						that will not be until it is put into effect. However, if you would consent
						even as it is, gentlemen, to bestow on me what is only a small token of
						gratitude, and one which is both easily granted and just, nothing would give
						me more delight. That I am entitled to it you will see at once. I am asking
						of you only what you yourselves gave me in fulfilment of a solemn promise,
						but were afterwards persuaded to withdraw. If you are prepared to restore
						it, I ask it as a favour; if you are not, I claim it as my due. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="23">
					<p>I often see you bestowing civic rights and substantial grants of money upon
						both slaves and foreigners from every part of the world, if they prove to
						have done you some service. And you are acting wisely in making such gifts;
						they engender the greatest possible willingness to serve you. Now my own
						request is merely this. You decreed on the motion of Menippus that I should
						be granted immunity; restore me my rights under that decree. The herald
						shall read it to you, as it is lying even now among the records in the
						Council-chamber. <quote type="Decree"><title>Decree</title></quote>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="24">
					<p>This decree to which you have been listening, gentlemen, was passed by you in
						my favour, but afterwards revoked to oblige another.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">i.e. Peisander. Andocides meant that the decree of
							Menippus was effectively stultified by the decree of Isotimides, passed
							shortly afterwards at Peisander's instigation.</note> Be advised by me,
						then. If any of you feels prejudiced against me, let him rid himself of that
						prejudice. You will admit that men's persons are not to blame for the
						mistakes which spring from their opinions. Now my own person is still
						unchanged, and is free from guilt; whereas different opinions have replaced
						the old. Thus you are left without any just ground for prejudice.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A sophistry worthy of the
							Tetralogies.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="25">
					<p>In the case of my old blunder you maintained that you had to treat the
						indications furnished by conduct as decisive, and that therefore you were
						obliged to regard me as a criminal. Be consistent, then; use only the
						indications furnished by my present conduct to prove the genuineness of my
						present desire to serve you. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="26">
					<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Furthermore, my behaviour today is much more
						in keeping with my character than my behaviour then, just as it accords far
						more with the traditions of my family. I am not lying — no lie of this sort
						could deceive my older listeners — when I say that my father's grandfather,
						Leogoras, led a revolt of the people against the tyrants,<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Andoc. 1.106">Andoc. 1.106</bibl> and
							note.</note> and in spite of the opportunity of coming to terms with
						them, marrying into their house, and ruling the people of <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> at their side, chose to share
						the exile of the democrats and suffer the hardships of banishment rather
						than turn traitor to them. Thus the behaviour of my forefathers should be an
						additional inspiration to me to show affection for the people, if I have
						indeed regained my senses at last; and it also gives you a natural reason
						for accepting my services the more readily, if you see me to have your
						interests at heart.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="part" n="Concl">
				<div type="section" n="27">
					<p>The fact that you deprived me of the pardon which you had given me has never,
						I assure you, caused me to feel aggrieved. After those scoundrels had
						induced you to wrong your own selves so grossly as to change empire for
						slavery, and to replace democracy by despotism,<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">i.e. the Four Hundred.</note> why should it surprise any
						of you that you were induced to wrong me likewise? </p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="28">
					<p>However, I could wish that after reversing the policy of those who duped you
						in those matters which concern yourselves—as you did as soon as you were
						able—you would similarly render their purposes ineffective in the matter of
						that unfortunate measure which you were persuaded to pass with regard to me.
						Refuse, in fact, to side, on this or any other question, with those who are
						your worst enemies.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
