<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader>
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>Gallic History </title>
				        <author n="Appian">Appian</author>
				        <editor role="editor">Horace White</editor>
				        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>William Merrill</name>
               <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
               <name>David Smith</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
         </publicationStmt>
			
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <author>Appian</author>
						            <title>The Foreign Wars</title>
						            <editor role="editor">Horace White</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>THE MACMILLAN COMPANY</publisher>
							              <date>1899</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		
	  	<encodingDesc>
	  		<refsDecl n="CTS">
	  			<cRefPattern n="fragment" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
	  				<p>This pointer pattern extracts fragmentary quotes</p>
	  			</cRefPattern>
	  		</refsDecl>
	  	</encodingDesc>
		
		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="eng">English</language>
				        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
				        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
		
		
	  	<revisionDesc>
	  		<change when="2002-11-13" who="DMM">markup</change>
	  		
	  		
	  		<change when="2009-10-07" who="rsingh04">
	  			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files
	  		</change>
	  		<change when="2009-08-19" who="lcerrato">
	  			fixing Athenaeus refs</change>
	  		
	  		<change when="2009-07-06" who="student">
	  			edited entity tags CEH</change>
	  		
	  		<change when="2009-02-27" who="rsingh04">
	  			fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags</change>
	  		
	  		<change when="2009-01-29" who="rsingh04">
	  			fixed chunking scheme</change>
	  		
	  		<change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">
	  			places/dates now actually tagged</change>
	  		
	  		<change when="2004-08-10" who="amahoney">
	  			fix the XML files so they are valid, make the SGML obsolete so no one is confused
	  		</change>
	  		<change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
	  		<change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change> 
	  		<change when="2015-12-29" who="TDBuck">p4 to p5</change>
	  	</revisionDesc>
	
	
	
	
	  </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="en">
				  <body>
         <div xml:lang="grc" type="edition" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0551.tlg005.perseus-eng2">
					
					       <head>THE GALLIC HISTORY</head>
					       <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter">
						         <head>Fragments</head>
						         <div n="I" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>AN EPITOME OF APPIAN'S BOOK "DE REBUS GALLICIS"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 365</note>
								                <milestone unit="section" n="1"/>AT an early period the Gauls waged war against the <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. <date when="-0389">389</date>
                        </note> Romans, took Rome itself, except the Capitol, and burned it. Camillus, however, overcame and expelled them. At a later period, when they had made a second invasion, he overcame them again and enjoyed a triumph in consequence, being then in his eightieth year. A third army of Gauls which invaded Italy was destroyed by the Romans under Titus Quintius. Afterwards the Boii, the most savage of the Gallic tribes, attacked the Romans. Gaius Sulpicius, the dictator, marched against them, and is said to have used the following stratagem. He commanded those who were in the front line to discharge their javelins, and immediately crouch low; then the second, third, and fourth lines to discharge theirs, each crouching in turn so that they should not be struck by the spears thrown from the rear; then when the last line had hurled their javelins, all were to rush forward suddenly with a shout and join battle at close quarters. The hurling of so many missiles, followed by an immediate charge, would throw the enemy into confusion. The spears of the Gauls were not like javelins, but what the Romans called <foreign xml:lang="lat">,</foreign> four-sided, part wood and part iron, and not hard except at the pointed end. In this way the army of the Boii was completely destroyed by the Romans.
								<note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 404</note>
							              </p>
                     <milestone unit="section" n="2"/>
                     <p>Another Gallic force was defeated by Popillius, and <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. <date when="-0350">350</date>
                        </note> after this Camillus, son of the former Camillus, defeated the same tribe. Afterwards AEmilius Pappus won some trophies  from the Gauls. Shortly before the consulships of Marius  a most numerous and warlike horde of Celtic tribes, most formidable in bodily strength, made incursions into both <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 649</note> Italy and Gaul, and defeated some of the Roman consuls, <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. <date when="-0105">105</date>
                        </note> and cut their armies in pieces. Marius was sent against them and he destroyed them all. The latest and greatest war of the Romans against the Gauls was that waged under the command of Cæsar, for, in the ten years that he held command there, he fought with more than 4,000,000 barbarians, taken all together. Of these 1,000,000 were captured and as many more slain in battle. He reduced to subjection 400 tribes and more than 800 towns, which had either revolted from their allegiance or were conquered for the first time. Even before Marius, Fabius Maximus AEmilianus with a very small army killed 120,000 of them in one battle, losing only fifteen of his own men; and he did this although suffering from a recent wound, urging and encouraging his troops and showing them how to fight barbarians, now borne on a litter and now hobbling on foot leaning on the arms of others.
							</p>
                     <milestone unit="section" n="3"/>
                     <p>Cæsar began his war against them by gaining a victory over some 200,000 of the Helvetii and Tigurini. The latter at an earlier period had captured a Roman army commanded by Piso and Cassius and sent them under the yoke, as is related in the writings of Paulus Claudius. The Tigurini <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 696</note> were now overcome by Labienus, Cæsar's lieutenant, and <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. <date when="-0058">58</date>
                        </note> the others by Cæsar himself, together with the Tricorii, who were aiding them. He also overcame the Germans under Ariovistus, a people who excelled all others, even the largest men, in size; savage, the bravest of the brave, despising death because they believe they shall live hereafter, bearing heat and cold with equal patience, living on herbs in time of scarcity, and their horses browsing on trees. It seems that they were without patient endurance in their battles, and did not fight in a scientific way or in any regular order, but with a sort of high spirit simply made an onset like wild beasts, for which reason they were overcome by Roman science and endurance. For, although the Germans made a tremendous rush and pushed the legions back a short distance, the Romans kept their ranks unbroken, and outmanœuvred them, and eventually slew 800000 of them.
								<note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 697</note>
							              </p>
                     <milestone unit="section" n="4"/>
                     <p>Afterwards Cæsar fell upon the so-called Belgæ as  they were crossing a river, and killed so many of them that he crossed the stream on a bridge of their bodies. The  Nervii defeated him by falling suddenly upon his army as it <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0057">57</date>
                        </note> was getting itself into camp after a march. They made a very great slaughter, killing all of his tribunes and centurions. Cæsar himself took refuge on a hill with his bodyguard, and there he was surrounded by the enemy. The latter being assailed in the rear by the tenth legion were destroyed, although they were 60,00000 in number. The Nervii were the descendants of the Cimbri and Teutones. <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 699</note> Cæsar conquered the Allobroges also. He slaughtered <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0055">55</date>
                        </note> 400,000 of the Usipetes and Tenchteri, armed and unarmed together. The Sicambri with 500 horse put to flight 5000 of Cæsar's horse, falling upon them unexpectedly. They subsequently paid the penalty for this in a defeat.
							</p>
                     <milestone unit="section" n="5"/>
                     <p>Cæsar was also the first of the Romans to cross the Rhine. He also passed over to Britain, an island larger than a very large continent, and still unknown to the men of Rome. He crossed by taking advantage of the movement of the tide. As it rose the fleet was impelled by the waves, slowly at first, then more rapidly, until finally Cæsar was carried with great swiftness to Britain.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="II" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 364</note>
								In the 97th Olympiad, according to the Greek calendar,  a considerable part of the Gauls who dwelt along the Rhine moved off in search of new land, that which they occupied being insufficient for their numbers. Having scaled the Alps they fell upon the territory of Clusium, a fertile part of Etruria. The Clusians had made a league with the Romans not long before, and now applied to them for aid. So the three Fabii were sent with the Clusians as ambassadors to the Gauls to order them to vacate the country that was in alliance with Rome, and to threaten them if they did not obey. The Gauls replied that they feared no mortal man in threat or war, that they were in need of land, and that they had not yet meddled with the affairs of the Romans. The Fabii urged the Clusians to make an attack upon the Gauls while they were heedlessly plundering the country. They took part in the expedition themselves and slew an immense number of the Gauls whom they caught foraging. Quintus Fabius, one of the Roman embassy,  himself killed the chief of that band, stripped his body, and <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0390">390</date>
                        </note> carried his arms back to Clusium.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="III" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>After the Fabii had slain this large number of Gauls, Brennus, their king, though he had refused to recognize the Roman embassy, for the purpose of intimidating the Romans selected as ambassadors to them certain Gauls who exceeded all the others in bodily size as much as the Gauls exceeded other peoples, and sent them to Rome to complain that the Fabii, while serving as ambassadors, had joined in war against him, contrary to the law of nations. He demanded that they should be given up to him for punishment unless the Romans wished to make the crime their own. The Romans acknowledged that the Fabii had done wrong, but having great respect for that distinguished family, they urged the Gauls to accept a pecuniary compensation from them. As the latter refused, they elected the Fabii military tribunes for that year, and then said to the Gallic ambassadors that they could not do anything to the Fabii now because they were now holding office, but told them to come again next year if they were still in a bad humor. Brennus and the Gauls under him considered this an insult and took it hard. Accordingly they sent around to the other Gauls asking them to make common cause of war with them. When a large number had collected in obedience to this summons they broke camp and marched against Rome. <note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Livy, v. 36 <foreign>seq.</foreign>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="IV" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 365</note>
								He (Cædicius) promised to carry letters through the <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0389">389</date>
                        </note> enemy's ranks to the Capitol.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="V" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM PEIRESC</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>When Cædicius bore the decree of the Senate to Camillus, by which he was made consul, he exhorted him not to lay up against his country the injury it had done him. The  latter, interrupting him, said: "I could not have prayed to  the gods that the Romans might some time long for me if I had cherished any such feeling as that towards them. Now I pray the nobler prayer that I may render my country a service equal to the calamity that has befallen her."</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="VI" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM PEIRESC</bibl>
							           <quote>
							           	<p>
							           		When the Gauls could find no means for scaling the Capitol they remained quietly in camp in order to reduce the defenders by famine. A certain priest named Dorso went down from the Capitol to make a certain yearly sacrifice in the temple of Vesta, and passed safely, with the sacred utensils, through the ranks of the enemy, who were either awed by his courage or had respect for his piety and his venerable appearance. Thus he who had incurred danger for the sake of his holy office was saved by it. That this event occurred, as related, the Roman writer Cassius tells us.
							           		<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">
							           			This writer was L. Cassius Hemina, who lived about the beginning of the second century B.C. Schweighäuser refers to two passages in Pliny's
							           			<title>Natural History</title>
							           			(xiii. 37, and xxix. 1), where he is mentioned as one of the earliest Roman annalists; also to a passage in Aulus Gellius (xvii. 21), where his name appears. All the writings of Cassius Hemina have been lost except a few fragments preserved in the works of other authors.
							           		</note>
							           	</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="VII" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM SUIDAS AND PEIRESC</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>The Gauls filled themselves to repletion with wine and other luxuries, being intemperate by nature, and inhabiting a country which yielded only cereals, and was unfruitful and destitute of other productions. Thus their large bodies became delicate, distended with fatness, and heavy by reason of excessive eating and drinking, and quite incapable of running or hardship; and when any exertion was required of them they speedily became exhausted by perspiration and shortness of breath.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="VIII" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>He (Camillus) showed them naked to the Romans and said: "These are the creatures who assail you with such  terrible shouts in battle, and clash their arms and shake  their long swords and toss their hair. Behold their weakness of soul, their slothfulness and flabbiness of body, and gird yourselves to your work."</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="IX" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM THE SAME</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 394</note>
								The people beheld the battle from the walls, and constantly <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0360">360</date>
                        </note> sent fresh troops to take the place of the tired ones. But the tired Gauls having to engage with fresh opponents took to disorderly flight.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="X" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM THE SAME</bibl>
							           <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 405</note>
							           <quote>
                     <p>The Gaul, furious and exhausted with loss of blood, <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0349">349</date>
                        </note> pursued Valerius, hastening in order to grapple with him. As Valerius was all the time dodging just in front of him, the Gaul fell headlong. The Romans felicitated themselves on this second single combat with the Gauls.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XI" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 471</note>
								The Senones, although they had a treaty with the Romans,  nevertheless furnished mercenaries against them, wherefore the Senate sent an embassy to them to remonstrate against this infraction of the treaty. Britomaris, the Gaul, being incensed against them on account of his father, who had been killed by the Romans while fighting on the side of the Etruscans in this very war, slew the ambassadors while they held the caduceus in their hands, and wore the garments of their office. He then cut their bodies in small pieces and scattered them in the fields. The consul Cornelius, learning of this abominable deed while he was on the march, moved with great speed against the towns of the Senones by way of the Sabine country and Picenum, and ravaged them all with fire and sword. He reduced the women and children to slavery, killed all the adult males without exception, devastated the country in every possible way, and made it uninhabitable for anybody else. He carried off Britomaris alone as a prisoner for torture. A little later the Senones (who were serving as mercenaries), having no longer any homes to return  to, fell boldly upon the consul Domitius, and being <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0283">283</date>
                        </note> defeated by him killed themselves in despair. Such punishment was meted out to the Senones for their crime against the ambassadors.<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Cf. Excerpt VI., Samnite History, <foreign>supra.</foreign>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XII" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 633</note>
								The chiefs of the Salyi, a nation vanquished by the Romans, <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0121">121</date>
                        </note> took refuge with the Allobroges. When the Romans asked for their surrender and it was refused, they made war on the Allobroges, under the leadership of Cnæus Domitius. When he was passing through the territory of the Salyi, an ambassador of Bituitus, king of the Allobroges, met him, arrayed magnificently and followed by attendants likewise arrayed, and also by dogs; for the barbarians of this region use dogs also as body-guards. A musician was in the train who sang in barbarous fashion the praises of King Bituitus, and then of the Allobroges, and then of the ambassador himself, celebrating his birth, his bravery, and his wealth; for which reason chiefly their illustrious ambassadors usually take such persons along with them. But this one, although he begged pardon for the chiefs of the Salyi, accomplished nothing.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XIII" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 641</note>
								A numerous band of the Teutones bent on plunder invaded  the territory of Noricum. The Roman consul, Papirius Carbo, fearing lest they should make an incursion into Italy, occupied the Alps at a place where the pass is narrowest. As they made no attempt in this direction he attacked them, complaining that they had invaded the people of Noricum, who were foreign friends of the Romans. It was the practice of the Romans to make foreign friends of any people for whom they wanted to intervene on the score of friendship, without being obliged to defend them as allies. As Carbo was approaching, the Teutones sent word to him that they had not known anything about this relationship between Rome and Noricum, and that for the future they would keep hands off. He praised the ambassadors, and gave them guides for their homeward journey, but privately charged the guides to  take them by a longer route. He himself then marched by <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0113">113</date>
                        </note> a shorter one and fell unexpectedly upon the Teutones, though they were still desisting <note> of Livy (lxiii.) assigns this victory to the Cimbri.</note>
                     </p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XIV" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>He ordered them to leave the bodies of the Cimbri intact till daylight because he believed they were adorned with gold.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XV" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 696</note>
								Two nations, the Tigurini and the Helvetii, made an incursion <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0058">58</date>
                        </note> into the Roman province of Gaul. When Cæsar heard of this movement he built a wall along the river Rhone about a hundred and fifty stades in length to intercept them. When they sent ambassadors to him to endeavor to make a treaty, he ordered them to give him hostages and money. They replied that they were accustomed to receive these things, not to give them. As he wished to prevent them <note> 18) agrees with Appian that the victory over the Tigurini was won by Labienus. Cæsar himself does not mention Labienus. lie says that he himself marched about the third watch (midnight) and came upon the Tigurini on the bank of the river Arar, etc. (<title>Gallic War,</title> i. 12.)</note>
                     </p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XVI" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 695</note>
								Ariovistus, the king of the Germans beyond the Rhine, <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0059">59</date>
                        </note> crossed to this side before Cæsar's arrival and made war against the AEdui, who were friends of the Romans. But when the Romans commanded him to desist, he obeyed and moved away from AEdui and desired to be accounted a friend of the Roman people also, and this was granted, Cæsar being consul and voting for it.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XVII" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>Ariovistus, the king of the Germans, who had been voted a friend of the Roman people, came to Cæsar to have a colloquy. After they had separated he wished to have another. Cæsar refused it, but sent some of the leading men of the Gauls to meet him. Ariovistus cast them in chains, wherefore Cæsar threatened him and made war on him, but fear fell upon the army on account of the military reputation of the Germans.<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Cf. Cæsar's <title>Gallic War,</title> i. 42 <foreign>seq.</foreign>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XVIII" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 699</note>
								It is believed that the Usipetes and the Tenchteri, German  tribes, with 800 of their own horse, put to flight about 5000 of Cæsar's horse. When they sent ambassadors to Cæsar he held them as prisoners and made an attack on them, and took them so completely by surprise that 400,000 of them were cut to pieces. One writer says that Cato in the Roman Senate proposed that Cæsar should be surrendered to the barbarians for this deed of blood perpetrated while negotiations were pending. But Cæsar in his own diary says that when the Usipetes and Tenchteri were ordered to go back forthwith to their former homes, they replied that they had sent ambassadors to the Suevi, who had driven them away, and that they were waiting for their answer; that while these negotiations were pending, they set upon his men with 800 of their horse, and by the suddenness of the attack put to flight his 5000; and that when they sent another embassy to explain this violation of good faith  he suspected a similar deception, and made his attack before <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0055">55</date>
                        </note> giving his answer.<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Cæsar's <title>Gallic War,</title> iv. 1-5; Plutarch, <title>Life of Cæsar,</title> 22. The latter repeats Cato's proposal that Cæsar should be surrendered to the barbarians for his breach of faith.</note>
                     </p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XIX" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>Straightway they stirred up the Britons to violate the oath, complaining that while a treaty with them was in force the camp was still among them.</p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XX" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM SUIDAS</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>
                        <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 700</note>
								Cæsar apprehending an attack on [Quintus] Cicero turned <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0054">54</date>
                        </note> back.<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Cæsar's <title>Gallic War,</title> v. 38 <foreign>seq.</foreign>
                        </note>
                     </p>
                  </quote>
						         </cit></div>
						         <div n="XXI" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							           <bibl>FROM THE VATICAN MSS. OF CARDINAL MAI</bibl>
							           <quote>
                     <p>Britores seduced the AEdui from their Roman allegiance. When Cæsar reproached them for this, they said that an ancient alliance had the precedence.</p>
								             <p>[Here follow two fragments of only three words each.]</p>
							           </quote>
						         </cit></div>
					       </div>
				     </div>
      </body>
			</text>
			
			</TEI>