<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
            <title>The Martydom of Polycarp</title>
            <editor role="translator">Kirsopp Lake</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
                <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                <name/>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:Tufts">Tufts University</funder>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            <date type="release">2019</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
                <monogr>
                    <author>Hermas</author>
                    <title>The Apostolic Fathers with an English translation by Kirsopp Lake. In Two Volumes. Vol. II.</title>
                    <imprint>
                        <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                            Ltd.</publisher>
                        <date type="printing">1913</date>
                    </imprint>
                </monogr>
                <ref target="https://archive.org/details/apostolicfathers02lakeuoft/">Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
        </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
        <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
            <cRefPattern n="book" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
            </cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
            <refState unit="section"/>
        </refsDecl>
        <editorialDecl>
            <quotation marks="none"/>
            <correction method="silent" status="low"><p>Perseus OCR in house AbbyyFR; single pass proofreading</p></correction>
        </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
        <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
        </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
        <change when="2019-04-30" who="Lisa Cerrato">basic structural markup and single pass editing</change>
    </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
        <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg1484.tlg001.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
            <pb xml:id="p.313"/>
           <head>THE MARTYRDOM OF ST. POLYCARP, BISHOP OF SMYRNA</head>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="praef"><p>The Church of God which sojourns in Smyrna, to the Church of God which sojourns in Philomelium, and to all the sojournings of the Holy Catholic Church in every place. “Mercy, peace and love” of God the Father, and our Lord Jesus Christ be multiplied.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">We write to you, brethren, the story of the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Introduction</note> martyrs and of the blessed Polycarp, who put an ductlon end to the persecution by his martyrdom as though adding the seal.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">He was the last to suffer and thus might be regarded as being the seal to the <q type="emph">witness</q> or <q type="emph">testimony</q> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μαρτύριον</foreign>) of the Church. It is not clear whether  <foreign xml:lang="grc">μαρτυρία</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">μαρτύριον</foreign> ought to be translated <q type="translation">martyrdom</q> or <q type="translation">witness</q>: there is an untranslateable play on the words.</note> For one might almost say that all that had gone before happened in order that the Lord might show to us from above a martyrdom<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or perhaps <q type="translation">witness.</q></note> in accordance with the Gospel.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For he waited to be betrayed as also the Lord had done, that we too might become his imitators, “not thinking of ourselves alone, but also of our neighbours.” For it is the mark of true and steadfast love, not to wish that oneself may be saved alone, but all the brethren also.</p></div></div>
<pb xml:id="p.315"/>
            
 <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Blessed then and noble are all the martyrdoms<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The sufferings of the Martyrs</note> which took place according to the will of God, for we must be very careful to assign the power over all to God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For who would not admire their nobility and patience and love of their Master? For some were torn by scourging until the mechanism of their flesh was seen even to the lower veins and arteries, and they endured so that even the bystanders pitied them and mourned. And some even reached such a pitch of nobility that none of them groaned or wailed, showing to all of us that at that hour of their torture the noble martyrs of Christ were absent from the flesh, or rather that the Lord was standing by and talking with them. </p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And paying heed to the grace of Christ they despised worldly tortures, by a single hour purchasing everlasting life. And the fire of their cruel torturers had no heat for them, for they set before their eyes an escape from the fire which is everlasting and is never quenched, and with the eyes of their heart they looked up to the good things which are preserved for those who have endured, fwhich neither ear hath heard nor hath eye seen, nor hath it entered into the heart of man/ but it was shown by the Lord to them who were no longer men but already angels.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This passage, combined with Hermas Vis. II. ii. 7 and Sim. IX. xxv. 2, shows that the identification of the dead with angels existed in the second century in Christian circles.</note> <pb xml:id="p.317"/> </p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And in the same way also those who were condemned to the beasts endured terrible torment, being stretched on sharp shells and buffeted with other kinds of various torments, that if it were possible the tyrant might bring them to a denial by continuous torture. For the devil used many wiles against them.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But thanks be to God, for he had no power over<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Germanicus</note> any. For the most noble Germanicus encouraged their fears by the endurance which was in him, and he fought gloriously with the wild beasts. For when the Pro-Consul wished to persuade him and bade him have pity on his youth, he violently dragged the beast towards himself, wishing to be released more quickly from their unrighteous and lawless life. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>So after this all the crowd, wondering at the nobility of the God-loving and God-fearing people of the Christians, cried out: “Away with the Atheists; let Polycarp be searched for.”</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But one, named Quintus, a Phrygian lately come<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Quintus</note> from Phrygia, when he saw the wild beasts played the coward. Now it was he who had forced himself and some others to come forward of their own accord. Him the Pro-Consul persuaded with many entreaties to take the oath and offer sacrifice. For this reason, therefore, brethren, we do not commend those who give themselves up, since the Gospel does not give this teaching. <pb xml:id="p.319"/></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But the most wonderful Polycarp, when he<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Polycarp's retreat to the country</note> first heard it, was not disturbed, but wished to remain in the city; but the majority persuaded him to go away quietly, and he went out quietly to a farm, not far distant from the city, and stayed with a few friends, doing nothing but pray night and day for all, and for the Churches throughout the world, as was his custom. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And while he was praying he fell into a trance three days before he was arrested, and saw the pillow under his head burning with fire, and he turned and said to those who were with him: “ I must be burnt alive.”</p></div></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And when the searching for him persisted he<note resp="editor" type="marginal">His betrayal</note> went to another farm; and those who were searching for him came up at once, and when they did not find him, they arrested young slaves,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Literally ‘children,’ but constantly used for slaves; <sic>the South African use of ‘boy’ is an almost exact parallel.</sic></note> and one of them confessed under torture.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For it was indeed impossible for him to remain hid, since those who betrayed him were of his own house, and the police captain who had been allotted the very name, being called Herod,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The writer desires to bring out the points of resemblance to the Passion of Christ. The coincidences are remarkable, but none are in themselves at all improbable.</note> hastened to bring him to the arena <pb xml:id="p.321"/> that he might fulfil his appointed lot by becoming a partaker of Christ, while they who betrayed him should undergo the same punishment as Judas.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Taking the slave then police and cavalry<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The arrival of the police</note> went out on Friday<note resp="editor" type="footnote"><foreign xml:lang="grc">παρασκευή</foreign> is literally Preparation (i.e. for the Sabbath) and has always been used in the Greek Church for Friday.</note> about supper-time, with their usual arms, as if they were advancing against a robber.<note resp="editor" type="footnote"><q type="translation">robber</q> is the traditional translation: but <q type="translation">brigand</q> is nearer the real meaning.</note> And late in the evening they came up together against him and found him lying in an upper room. And he might have departed to another place, but would not, saying, “ the will of God be done.” </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>So when he heard that they had<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Their reception by Polycarp</note> arrived he went down and talked with them, while those who were present wondered at his age and courage, and whether there was so much haste for the arrest of an old man of such a kind. Therefore he ordered food and drink to be set before them at that hour, whatever they should wish, and he asked them to give him an hour to pray without hindrance. </p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>To this they assented, and he stood<note resp="editor" type="marginal">His prayer</note> and prayed—thus filled with the graqe of God— so that for two hours he could not be silent, and those who listened were astounded, and many repented that they had come against such a venerable old man.</p></div></div>

<pb xml:id="p.323"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Now when he had at last finished his prayer, after remembering all who had ever even come his way, both small and great, high and low, and the whole Catholic Church throughout the world, the hour came for departure, and they set him on an ass, and led him<note resp="editor" type="marginal">His arrival in Smyrna</note> into the city, on a “great Sabbath day.”<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This may have been the Jewish feast Purim, which, according to tradition, celebrates the triumph of the Jews in Persia over their enemies, as is related in the book of Esther, or else the Sabbath in the Passover week (see p. 311).</note></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And the police captain Herod and his father Niketas met him and removed him into their carriage, and sat by his side trying to persuade him and saying: "But what harm is it to say, 'Lord Caesar' and to offer sacrifice, and so forth, and to be saved?” But he at first did not answer them, but when they continued he said: “I am not going to do what you counsel me.” </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And they gave up the attempt to persuade<note resp="editor" type="marginal">And in the arena</note> him, and began to speak fiercely to him, and turned him out in such a hurry that in getting down from the carriage he scraped his shin; and without turning round, as though he had suffered nothing, he walked on promptly and quickly, and was taken to the arena, while the uproar in the arena was so great that no one could even be heard.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Now when Polycarp entered into the arena<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Polycarp’s examination</note> there came a voice from heaven: “Be strong, Polycarp, and play the man.” And no one saw the <pb xml:id="p.325"/> speaker, but our friends who were there heard the voice. And next he was brought forward, and there was a great uproar of those who heard that Polycarp had been arrested. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Therefore when he was brought forward the Pro-Consul asked him if he were Polycarp, and when he admitted it he tried to persuade him to deny, saying: “Respect your age,” and so forth, as they are accustomed to say  “Swear by the genius of Caesar, repent, say: 'Away with the Atheists’”; but Polycarp, with a stern countenance looked on all the crowd of lawless heathen in the arena, and waving his hand at them, he groaned and looked up to heaven and said: “Away with the Atheists.”</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>But when the Pro-Consul pressed him and said: “Take the oath and I let you go, revile Christ,” Polycarp said: “ For eighty and six years<note resp="editor" type="footnote">He was therefore probably a Christian born, unless we ascribe to him a quite improbable age.</note> have I been his servant, and he has done me no wrong, and how can I blaspheme my King<note resp="editor" type="footnote"><foreign xml:lang="grc">βασιλεύς</foreign> represents <q type="foreign" xml:lang="lat">imperator</q> not <q type="foreign" xml:lang="lat">rex,</q> and though it can hardly be translated <q type="gloss">Emperor,</q> the antithesis to Caesar is clearly implied.</note> who saved me?”</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But when he persisted again, and said: “Swear by the genius of Caesar,” he answered him: “If you vainly suppose that I will swear by the genius of Caesar, as you say, and pretend that you are ignorant who I am, listen plainly: I am a Christian. And if you wish to learn the doctrine of Christianity fix a <pb xml:id="p.327"/> day and listen.”</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>The Pro-Consul said: “Persuade the people.” And Polycarp said: “You I should have held worthy of discussion, for we have been taught to render honour, as is meet, if it hurt us not, to princes and authorities appointed by God. But as for those, I do not count them worthy that a defence should be made to them.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And the Pro-Consul said: “I have wild beasts,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The Pro-Consul’s threats</note> I will deliver you to them, unless you repent. And he said: “Call for them, for repentance from better to worse is not allowed us; but it is good to change from evil to righteousness.”</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And he said again to him: “I will cause you to be consumed by fire, if you despise the beasts, unless you repent.” But Polycarp said: “You threaten with the fire that burns for a time, and is quickly quenched, for you do not know the fire which awaits the wicked in the judgment to come and in everlasting punishment. But why are you waiting? Come, do what you will.”</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And with these and many other words he was filled with courage and joy, and his face was full of grace so that it not only did not fall with trouble at the things said to him, but that the Pro-Consul, on the other hand, was astounded and sent his herald into the midst of the arena to announce three <pb xml:id="p.329"/> times: “Polycarp has confessed that he is a Christian."</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>When this had been said by the herald, all the multitude of heathen and Jews living in Smyrna <note resp="editor" type="marginal">The anger of the Jews</note> cried out with uncontrollable wrath and a loud shout: “This is the teacher of Asia, the father of the Christians, the destroyer of our Gods, who teaches many neither to offer sacrifice nor to worship.” And when they said this, they cried out and asked Philip the Asiarch to let loose a lion on Polycarp. But he said he could not legally do this, since he had closed the Sports.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Literally <q type="translation">hunting,</q> the Latin <q type="foreign" xml:lang="lat">venatio.</q></note></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Then they found it good to cry out with one mind that he should burn Polycarp alive, for the vision which had appeared to him on his pillow must be fulfilled, when he saw it burning, while he was praying, and he turned and said prophetically to those of the faithful who were with him, “ I must be burnt alive.”</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">These things then happened with so great speed,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The preparations for burning him</note> quicker than it takes to tell, and the crowd came together immediately, and prepared wood and faggots from the work-shops and baths and the Jews were extremely zealous, as is their custom, in assisting at this.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Now when the fire wras ready he put off all his clothes, and loosened his girdle and tried also to take off his shoes, though he did not do this before, because each of the faithful was always zealous, which of them might the more quickly touch his flesh. For he had been treated with all respect because of his <pb xml:id="p.331"/> noble life,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Lit. “citizenship,” but it is used in a special sense of Christian life.</note> even before his martyrdom. </p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Immediately therefore, he was fastened to the instruments which had been prepared for the fire, but when they were going to nail him as well he said: “ Leave me thus, for He who gives me power to endure the fire, will grant me to remain in the flames unmoved even without the security you will give by the nails.”</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">So they did not nail him, but bound him, and he<note resp="editor" type="marginal">His last prayers</note> put his hands behind him and was bound, as a noble ram out of a great flock, for an oblation, a whole burnt offering made ready and acceptable to God; and he looked up to heaven and said: “ O Lord God Almighty, Father of thy beloved and blessed Child,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This use of <foreign xml:lang="grc">παῖς</foreign> as applied to Jesus is rare, and usually found in prayers; cf. <title>Ep. ad Diogn.</title> viii. 9. 11, ix. 1, Didache 9, 2, I Clement 59, 2 (the <q type="soCalled">Prayer</q>), and Acts 3, 13. 26. 4, 27. 30. Here it is clearly  <q type="translation">Child</q>: in Acts it may mean “<q type="translation">Servant</q> with reference to Is. 53, etc.</note> Jesus Christ, through Whom we have received full knowledge of thee, the God of Angels and powers, and of all creation, and of the whole family of the righteous, who live before thee!</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>I bless thee, that Thou hast granted me this day and hour, that I may share, among the number of the martyrs, in the cup of thy Christ, for the Resurrection to everlasting life, both of soul and body in the immortality of the Holy Spirit. And may I, to-day, be received among them before Thee, as a rich and acceptable sacrifice. <pb xml:id="p.333"/> as Thou, the God who lies not and is truth, hast prepared beforehand, and shown forth, and fulfilled.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For this reason I also praise Thee for all things, I bless Thee, I glorify Thee through the everlasting and heavenly high Priest, Jesus Christ, thy beloved Child, through whom be glory to Thee with him and the Holy Spirit, both now and for the ages that are to come. Amen.”</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Now when he had uttered his Amen and<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The fire is lighted</note> finished his prayer, the men in charge of the fire lit it, and a great flame blazed up and we, to whom it was given to see, saw a marvel. And we have been preserved to report to others what befell.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For the fire made the likeness of a room, like the sail of a vessel filled with wind, and surrounded the body of the martyr as with a wall, and he was within it not as burning flesh, but as bread that is being baked, or as gold and silver being refined in a furnace. And we perceived such a fragrant smell as the scent of incense or other costly spices.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">At length the lawless men, seeing that his<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Polycarp’s death</note> body could not be consumed by the fire, commanded an executioner to go up and stab him with a dagger, and when he did this, there came out a dove,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This no doubt points to the belief that the spirit appears at death in the form of a bird. Cf. Prudentius <title>Peristeph. Hymn.</title> iii. 33 (other references are also given by Lightfoot).</note> and <pb xml:id="p.335"/> much blood, so that the fire was quenched and all the crowd marvelled that there was such a difference between the unbelievers and the elect. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And of the elect was he indeed one, the wonderful martyr. Polycarp, who in our days was an apostolic and prophetic teacher, bishop of the Catholic<note resp="editor" type="footnote">If the reading “Catholic” be right, this and the instance on p. 322 are the earliest clear examples of this use of the word (but cf. Ignatius, <title>Symrn.</title> viii.).</note> Church in Smyrna. For every word which he uttered from his mouth both was fulfilled and will be fulfilled.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But the jealous and envious evil one who resists<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The treatment of the corpse</note> the family of the righteous, when he saw the greatness of his martyrdom, and his blameless career from the beginning, and that he was crowned with the crown of immortality, and had carried off the unspeakable prize, took care that not even his poor body should be taken away by us, though many desired to do this, and to have fellowship with his holy flesh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Therefore he put forward Niketas, the father of Herod, and the brother of Alee, to ask the Governor not to give his body, “ Lest,” he said, “ they leave the crucified one and begin to worship this man.” And they said this owing to the suggestions and pressure of the Jews, who also watched when we were going to take it from the fire, for they do not know that we shall not ever be able either to abandon Christ, who suffered for the salvation of those who are being <pb xml:id="p.337"/> saved in the whole world, the innocent for sinners, or to worship any other. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For him we worship as the Son of God, but the martyrs we love as disciples and imitators of the Lord; and rightly, because of their unsurpassable affection toward their own King and Teacher. God grant that we too may be their companions and fellow-disciples.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">When therefore the centurion saw the contentiousness<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The Christians take the ashes</note> caused by the Jews, he put the body in the midst, as was their custom, and burnt it.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Thus we, at last, took up his bones, more precious than precious stones, and finer than gold, and put them where it was meet.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>There the Lord will permit us to come together according to our power in gladness and joy, and celebrate the birthday of his martyrdom, both in memory of those who have already contested,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This is almost a technical term for martyrdom, cf. Ignatius’s epistle to Polycarp 1, 3.</note> and for the practice and training of those whose fate it shall be.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Such was the lot of the blessed Polycarp, who<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Conclusion</note> though he was, together with those from Philadelphia, the twelfth martyr in Smyrna, is alone especially remembered by all, so that he is spoken of in every place, even by the heathen. He was not only a famous teacher, but also a notable martyr, <pb xml:id="p.339"/> whose martyrdom all desire to imitate, for it followed the Gospel of Christ. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>By his endurance he overcame the unrighteous ruler, and thus gained the crown of immortality, and he is glorifying God and the Almighty Father, rejoicing with the Apostles and all the righteous, and he is blessing our Lord Jesus Christ, the Saviour of our souls, and Governor of our bodies, and the Shepherd of the Catholic Church throughout the world.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">You, indeed, asked that the events should be explained to you at length, but we have for the present explained them in summary by our brother Marcion<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Not of course to be identified with the famous heretic. If Marcianus be the right text, it is noteworthy that Irenaeus sent his treatise on the <q type="title">The Apostolic Preaching</q> to a certain Marcianus. But this was probably forty years later than Polycarp’s death.</note>;  therefore when you have heard these things, send the letter to the brethren further on, that they also may glorify the Lord, who takes his chosen ones from his own servants.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p rend="indent">And to him who is able to bring us all in his grace and bounty, to his heavenly kingdom, by his only begotten Child, Jesus Christ, be glory, honour, might, and majesty for ever. Greet all the saints. Those who are with us, and <pb xml:id="p.341"/> Evarestus, who wrote the letter, with his whole house, greet you.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Now the blessed Polycarp was martyred on the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The date</note> second day of the first half of the month of Xanthicus, the seventh day before the kalends of March,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">I. e. Feb. 23.</note> a great sabbath, at the eighth hour. And he was arrested by Herod, when Philip of Tralles was High Priest, when Statius Quadratus was Pro-Consul, but Jesus Christ was reigning<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This phrase is pointedly inserted instead of a reference to the reigning Emperor.</note> for ever, to whom be glory, honour, majesty and an eternal throne, from generation to generation. Amen.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">We bid you God-speed, brethren, who walk<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Notes by a later scribe</note> according to the Gospel, in the word of Jesus Christ (with whom be glory to God and the Father and the Holy Spirit), for the salvation of the Holy Elect, even as the blessed Polycarp suffered martyrdom, in whose footsteps may it be granted us to be found in the Kingdom of Jesus Christ.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p rend="indent">Gaius copied this from the writing of Irenaeus, a disciple of Polycarp, and he lived with Irenaeus, and I, Socrates, wrote it out in Corinth, from the copies of Gaius. Grace be with you all.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And I, <pb xml:id="p.343"/> again, Pionius, wrote it out from the former writings, after searching for it, because the blessed Polycarp showed it me in a vision, as I will explain in what follows,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">No explanation is given: probably because the <q type="soCalled">Pionian</q> text was part of a larger <q type="title">Acts of Polycarp.</q> Either these Acts have entirely disappeared except for this letter of the church of Smyrna, or a fragment preserved in p may perhaps belong to them.</note> and I gathered it together when it was almost worn out by age, that the Lord Jesus Christ may also gather me together with his elect into his heavenly kingdom, to whom be glory with the Father and the Holy Spirit, for ever and ever, Amen.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="alt_concl">
<head>ANOTHER CONCLUSION FROM THE MOSCOW MANUSCRIPT.</head>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p rend="indent">This account Gaius copied from the writings of Irenaeus, and he also had lived with Irenaeus, who was a disciple of the holy Polycarp. </p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For this Irenaeus, at the time of the martydom of the bishop Polycarp was in Rome, and taught many, and many most excellent and correct writings are extant, in which he mentions Polycarp,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Irenaeus <title>Haer.</title> iii. 3. 4, <title>Ep. ad Florinum</title> (in Eusebius <title>H.E.</title> v. 20) and <title>Ep. ad Victorem</title> (in Eusebius <title>H.E.</title> v. 24). The story of Marcion is in <title>Haer.</title> iii. 3. 4.</note> saying that he had been his pupil, and he ably refuted every heresy, and <pb xml:id="p.345"/> he also handed on the ecclesiastical and catholic rule, as he had received it from the saint. </p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And he also says this that once Marcion,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Marcion was the moat famous heretic of the second century. He was a native of Pontus and afterwards came to Rome. The main points of his teaching were the rejection of the Old Testament and a distinction between the Supreme God of goodness and an inferior God of justice, who was the Creator, and the God of the Jews. He regarded Christ as the messenger of the Supreme God.</note> from whom come the so-called Marcionites, met the holy Polycarp and said: “Recognise us, Polycarp,” and he said to Marcion, “I do recognise you, I recognise the first-born of Satan.” </p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And this is also recorded in the writings of Irenaeus, that at the day and hour when Polycarp suffered in Smyrna Irenaeus, who was in the city of Rome, heard a voice like a trumpet saying: “Polycarp has suffered martrydom.”
    </p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p rend="indent">From these papers of Irenaeus, then, as was stated above, Gaius made a copy, and Isocrates used in Corinth the copy of Gaius. And again I, Pionius, wrote from the copies of Isocrates, according to the revelation of the holy Polycarp, after searching for them, and gathering them together when they were almost worn out from age, that the Lord Jesus Christ may also gather me into his Heavenly Kingdom together with his Elect. To him be glory, with the Father and the Son and the Holy Spirit, for ever and ever, Amen.</p></div></div>
        </div></body></text></TEI>