<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Loukios, Or, the Ass</title>
 <author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Emily James Smith</editor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
 <respStmt>
  <persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
 <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date type="release">2023-08-01</date>
<publisher>Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr>
<title xml:lang="eng">Selections from Lucian</title>
  <editor role="translator">Emily James Smith</editor>
  <author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
  <imprint>
   <publisher>Harper and Brothers</publisher>
	<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
	<date>1892</date>
  </imprint>
 </monogr>
  <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/hvd.hw3j0n?urlappend=%3Bseq=257%3Bownerid=27021597767339600-275">The Hathi Trust</ref>
 </biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
 <p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
 <refsDecl n="CTS">
  <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
   replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
   <p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
  </cRefPattern>
 </refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2023-08-10" who="Alison Babeu">Updated URN and metadata</change>
<change when="2023-08-09" who="Greg Crane">Creation of initial translation file</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="eng">
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
<head>LOUKIOS; OR, THE ASS.
</head>
<head></head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="1"><p>

I once made a journey to Thessaly,
having a matter of business connected with my paternal estate to
arrange there with a man of that
country. A horse carried me and
my luggage, and a single servant accompanied
me. We followed the usual road, and fell in
with other travellers who happened to be going
to Hypata, a town in Thessaly in which they
lived. We joined company, made our provisions
common stock, and in this way achieved that laborious journey. When we were approaching the
town I asked the Thessalians whether they knew
a resident of Hypata named Hipparchos, for I
had a letter of introduction to him from home
and expected to lodge with him. They said they
did, and told me what part of the town he lived
in, and that, although he had plenty of money, his
household consisted solely of one maid-servant
and his wife. "For," said they, "he is a terrible
miser."
When we had come very near the town we saw
a garden with a tolerable cottage in it, and this
was where Hipparchos dwelt. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="2">
<p>So the others made


<pb n="v.1.p.240"/>



their adieux and rode on, and I went up to the
door and knocked. After a good deal of difficulty
and delay the woman managed to hear me, and
finally came to the door. I asked whether Hipparchos was at home.
"He is," said she; "but who are you and what
do you want to see him for?"
"I am the bearer of a letter from Dekrianos,
the sophist of Patrai.”
"Wait here," said she, and, closing the door,
she went away.
After a while she came back
and bade us enter. Accordingly, I went into the
house, saluted the master, and presented my letter. It happened that he was just beginning his
dinner, reclining on a narrow couch. His wife
sat near him, and a table stood before them with
nothing on it as yet. As soon as he had cast his
eye over the letter he said: "Dekrianos is my
dearest friend and the noblest Greek of them all.
I take it kindly of him that he sends his own
comrades to me with confidence. You see my
cottage, Loukios; it is small, but it is just the
right size to hold the owner; and you will transform it into a great house, if you will live in it
and put up with it."

Then he called the maid-servant. "Palaistra,
show the gentleman to a bed-chamber, and bring
him thither what luggage he has. And then direct
him to the bath: he has come a long journey."


<pb n="v.1.p.241"/>

At these words the girl Palaistra led the way
and showed a very pretty little sleeping-room.
"That is your bed," said she; "and for your servant I will set a couch alongside and put a pillow
on it." </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="3">
<p>When she had thus spoken we went off
to bathe, and I gave the girl money to buy a little barley for my horse. She carried in all my
belongings and deposited them in my room.
When we had bathed and come back to the
house we presented ourselves immediately, and
Hipparchos, shaking hands with me, bade me
recline beside him. The dinner was not too
frugal, and the wine was pleasant and old. After
dinner we sat talking over our wine-the usual
way of entertaining a guest. That whole evening we spent in drinking, and so to bed.
Next day Hipparchos asked me whither I purposed going next, or whether I was going to stay
there all the time. "I am going on to Larissa,"
said I, "but probably I shall spend four or five
days here." </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="4">
<p>This, however, was a subterfuge. I
had the greatest desire to remain there and
search out one of the women versed in sorcery,
and see some of their marvellous exhibitions—a
human being with wings, or turned into stone;
and I surrendered myself to my passion for such
a sight, and strolled about the town with no idea
how to begin the search, but strolling nevertheless. While I was thus employed I saw a woman



<pb n="v.1.p.242"/>



approaching, young still and well to do, as far as
I could judge from a casual meeting. She was
dressed in bright stuffs, had a number of attendants, and displayed an extravagance of gold.
When I came nearer, the lady greeted me and
I returned the salutation.

"My name is Abroia," she said. “You may
have heard your mother speak of me as a friend.
You, her children, are as dear to me as my own.
Why, then, my child, do you not come to me as
my guest?"

"Thank you very much," said I, "but I should
be ashamed to desert a friendly man's house when
I have no fault to find with him. But as far as
my inclination is concerned, dear madam, I would
lodge with you."
"Where do you lodge, then?" she asked.
"With Hipparchos."
"The miser?" cried she.
"Don't call him that, madam," said I. "He
has entertained me brilliantly and generously.
Actually, you might accuse him of extravagance."
But the lady smiled, and, taking me by the
hand, led me apart and said to me: "Pray, be
on your guard in every way against Hipparchos's
wife, for she is a powerful sorceress. She casts
a longing eye on all young men, and if one of
them rejects her advances she revenges herself
on him by her arts. Many a one has she turned


<pb n="v.1.p.243"/>


into an animal, and many a one destroyed outright. You, my child, are handsome as well as
young, so that you find favor with women at
once ; and you are a stranger, so that there is
no danger in dealing with you."
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="5">
<p>
When I heard that what I had been seeking
so long was living in the same house with me, I
paid no more heed to the lady. As soon as I
could take my leave I made off homeward, saying to myself as I went: "Come, now, you who
say you are eager to see this wonderful sight,
wake up and invent some sage plan to come at
what you want. Practise on Palaistra, the maidservant-for the wife of your host and friend is
sacred; wrestling with her, I assure you, you will
easily learn what you want, for servants know
everything about their masters, good and bad."
Talking thus with myself, I entered the house.
I did not find Hipparchos at home or his wife
either; but Palaistra was sitting by the fire preparing the dinner, and I opened my discourse
forthwith.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="6">
<p>
"Lovely Palaistra,” said I, “how gracefully
you turn and sway your body and the kettle at
the same time! My marrow melts at the sight.
He is a lucky man who dips his finger in that
dish."
The girl was of a very lively humor and full of
charming ways. "Fly, young man,” said she, “if


<pb n="v.1.p.244"/>



you are in your senses and want to live. I am
made of fire and smoke. If you should but touch
me you will sit here covered with blisters, burned
through by me.
No doctor will heal you, not even
a god, save only me who burned you. Strangest
of all, I will make you suffer the more, and you
will cherish the painful cure and cling to it, and
you would be stoned rather than escape from
your pleasant pain. Why do you laugh? You
see before you a scientific cook of men. These
trumpery eatables are not the only things I can
prepare; no, I know well how to butcher and
flay and carve that great and noble viand, man.
My dearest pleasure is to lay hold of his very
vitals and heart."
"You are perfectly right," I said; "for even
while I was at a distance, before I had come near
you, you not only burned me, by Heavens! but set
me all in a blaze. Through my eyes you flung
your
invisible fire into my vitals and are roasting
me, though I never did you any harm. So, heal
me, in the name of goodness, with those bittersweet remedies you speak of yourself. I am
butchered already; take me and flay me as you
will."

At this she burst into a peal of sweet laughter,
and after that she was a complete conquest.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="11">
<p>
I said to her one day, "My dear, get me sight of
your mistress practising her mysteries or changing


<pb n="v.1.p.245"/>


her shape. For a long time I have been eager to
see this curious thing. Or, better still, if you
know anything of the black art, exhibit it yourself, and show yourself to me in some other form
than your own. I have a notion that you are not
altogether ignorant of this science, and I know it
from my own heart, not from hearsay; for I used
to be adamantine, the women said, and I never
cast these eyes tenderly on any girl before; but
you laid hold of me by your arts and led me off,
after our loving contest, as the captive of your
spear."
"Stop making fun of me," said Palaistra.
"What incantation could charm Love, since he
is lord of all sorcery? No, sweetheart; I swear
by your head that I know nothing whatever of
these things. I have never learned so much as
my letters, and my mistress is very jealous of her
art. But if I should have a chance, I will try
to show her to you in the act of changing her
shape."
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="12">
<p>
A few days later Palaistra informed me that
her mistress was intending to put on the guise of
a bird and fly off to her lover.
"Now is your time, Palaistra," said I, "to do
me a kindness; for it is in your power to satisfy
the long-cherished desire of your suppliant."
"Never fear," said she. And when it was evening she came for me, and brought me to the door


<pb n="v.1.p.246"/>



of the chamber in which her master and mistress
slept, and bade me stand by a narrow chink in
the door and watch what was going on within.
Well, I saw the lady stripping off her clothes.
When she was naked she advanced to the lamp,
took two grains of incense and cast them on the
flame, and, standing still, addressed a long speech
to it. Then she opened a strong little chest with
a great many boxes in it, lifted one of them and
took it out. I do not know the nature of the
contents, but from its appearance I judged it was
oil. From this box she anointed herself completely, beginning with her finger-nails, and suddenly feathers sprang out on her, her nose grew
horny and curved, and she displayed all the other
properties and traits of a bird. She was nothing
else than a night-hawk. When she was completely feathered she gave a harsh cry like a hawk's,
stood up, and took her flight out of the window.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="13">
<p>
I thought I must be dreaming such a sight as
this, and rubbed my eyelids with my fingers, not
believing that I had seen with my own waking
eyes. When I had at length with difficulty convinced myself that I was not asleep, I forthwith
begged Palaistra to anoint me, too, with that drug,
and feather me and let me fly; for I wanted to
learn by experiment whether if my human shape
was altered I should have the mind, too, of a bird.
She stealthily opened the bedroom door and


<pb n="v.1.p.247"/>


brought the box. I had already made haste to
strip, and I anointed myself from head to toe.
But alas, alack! I did not become a bird! No;
a tail grew out on me behind, my fingers and toes
disappeared somehow, my nails reduced themselves to four and were nothing more nor less
than hoofs, my hands and feet became the feet
of a beast of burden, my ears grew long, and my
face enormous. When I surveyed myself all
over I saw that I was an ass, but I had no human voice left wherewith to blame Palaistra.
However, I stretched out my lower lip, and by
my shape itself and by my sidelong asinine glance
I reproached her as well as I could for having
made me an ass instead of a bird. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="14">
<p>She smote
her face with both hands. "Wretched girl that
I am," she cried, "what a dreadful thing I have
done! In my hurry I blundered, because the
boxes were so alike, and brought the wrong one,
not the one that makes feathers grow. But cheer
up, do, sweetheart! There is a very easy cure
for this. You have only to eat some roses, and
the beast will immediately fall from you and you
will give me back my lover. Only stay this one
night, dear, in the ass, and at daybreak I will run
and fetch you some roses, and you will eat them
and be cured."
While she spoke thus she stroked my ears and
the rest of my hide. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="15">
<p>I was an ass in all other


<pb n="v.1.p.248"/>



respects, but I had the heart and mind of a man
-the same Loukios, but not his voice. Well,
heaping silent reproaches on Palaistra for her
mistake, and chewing my lip, I went off to where
I knew my horse was stabled, together with another ass, a real one, belonging to Hipparchos.
When they saw me coming in to join them they
feared that I was going to share their feed, so
they put back their ears and made ready to defend their bellies with their heels. I grasped the
situation, and taking my stand at a distance from
the manger, burst into a laugh, but my laugh was
a bray. Then I said to myself: "Confound my
untimely curiosity! What if a wolf should come
in, too, or some other wild beast! The chances
are that I shall be killed, though I have done
nothing wrong." But though I reflected thus, I
had no idea, poor devil! of the evil that awaited
me.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="16">
<p>
When the night was already far advanced, with
its great silence and sweet sleep, there was a
noise from without as though the wall were being broken through, and so it was. There was a
hole already large enough to admit a man, and
one man after another made his way through it
promptly until a number were inside, swords in
hand. Then they tied up Hipparchos and Palaistra and my man in their rooms, and so stripped
the house fearlessly, carrying out the money and


<pb n="v.1.p.249"/>


the clothes and the furniture. When there was
nothing more left in it, they took me and the other ass and the horse, saddled us, and strapped all
they had stolen onto us. Laden with these heavy
loads, they drove us up the mountain by an untrodden road, beating us with clubs, and bent on
escaping. I am not able to describe the feelings
of the other beasts, but I, for my part-barefoot,
inexperienced, treading on sharp stones, and bearing so much stuff-was ready to die. Every now
and then I stumbled, but I was not at liberty to fall
down, for some one from behind would instantly
give me a blow across the haunches with a club;
and when I frequently longed to cry, "O Caesar!"
I could do nothing but bray. I could bring out
the "O" full and loud, but the "Caesar" would
not follow. And even for this they clubbed me,
because they thought my braying would betray
them. So, when I found that my cries were in
vain, I resolved to go on in silence, with the gain,
at least, of not being beaten.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="17">
<p>
After this day came, and we had already climbed
many mountains. They muzzled us so that we
might not browse along the road for our breakfasts and thus be caught; so for that day, too, I
remained an ass. At high noon we halted at a
sort of farm-house belonging to people who were
friends of the robbers, to judge from what happened, for they greeted each other with kisses,


<pb n="v.1.p.250"/>



and the owners of the house bade the others halt,
and set breakfast before them and gave us animals barley. The others breakfasted, but I fasted in misery. Since I had never at that time
breakfasted on raw barley, I looked around to
see what I could eat. I saw a garden there behind the court-yard, full of fine vegetables, and
above these I saw roses. In the house they were
all occupied with their breakfast, and I managed
to give them the slip and get to the garden, partly to eat my fill of raw vegetables, and partly for
the sake of the roses, for I calculated that if I ate
those flowers I should certainly become a man
again. When I had made my way into the garden I stuffed myself with lettuces, and radishes,
and parsley, such vegetables as men are wont to
eat raw; but those roses were not real ones, they
were such as grow on the wild laurel. The plant
is called rose-laurel, and it makes a poor breakfast for any ass or horse, for it is said that if they
eat it they die on the spot.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="18">
<p>
In the mean time the gardener perceived me,
snatched up a club, and ran into the garden.
When he saw the enemy, the destroyer of his
vegetables, he seized me as a severe master seizes
a thieving slave and pounded me with his club,
sparing neither ribs nor thighs. He even crushed
my ears and mangled my face. When I could
stand it no longer I kicked with both feet,


<pb n="v.1.p.251"/>


knocked him on his back on top of the vegetables, and ran for the mountain. Seeing me making off at a run he shouted that they were to loose
the dogs on my trail. The dogs were numerous
and large enough to fight with bears, and I knew
that if they caught me they would tear me to
pieces. So after I had made a short detour I
decided that the proverb is right, "better run
back than into trouble," and accordingly I started back and made my way to the farm again.
They captured the dogs who had been chasing
me, and tied them up, but me they beat and did
not stop until in my agony I had cast up all the
vegetables.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="19">
<p>
When it was time to take to the road again they
also heaped most of the booty and the heaviest
on me, and this having been arranged we set out.
I was soon exhausted, what with my beating and
with carrying my load, and my hoofs were crushed
by the road. At this point I made up my mind.
to fall down where I was and never get up again,
though they beat me to death, for I hoped great
gain from this if my plan should work. My idea
was that they would give up in despair, divide my
load between the horse and the mule, and leave
me to lie there for the wolves. But some jealous
divinity perceived my plans and made them work
just the other way. For the other ass followed the
same train of thought as mine and fell down in the


<pb n="v.1.p.252"/>



road. First they took to beating the poor wretch,
bidding him get up; but as he did not respond at
all to the blows, some of them took hold of his
ears and some of his tail and tried to rouse him.
When they were unsuccessful in this, and he lay
like a stone in the road, utterly worn out, they argued among themselves that their efforts were
useless, and that they were wasting their time for
escape sitting by a dead ass; so they took all the
gear he had been carrying and divided it between
me and the horse. As for the wretched partner
of my captivity and burdens, they laid hold of
him, cut the sinews of his legs with a sword, and
thrust him still quivering over the precipice, and
down he went, dancing the death-dance.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="20">
<p>
When I saw in the case of my fellow-traveller
the outcome of the plans I had formed I made
up my mind to bear my present plight bravely
and plod on with spirit, for I was in hopes that I
might chance on my roses at any turn, and by
their means be restored to myself. And I heard
the robbers saying our journey was almost done,
and that they would stay at their next haltingplace. Accordingly, we carried all that burden at
a quick pace, and before evening we came to their
house. An old woman was sitting inside, where
a great fire was burning. The robbers took all the
things we had been carrying and set them inside.
Then they asked the old woman, “Why in Heaven's

<pb n="v.1.p.253"/>

name are you sitting like this instead of getting our supper ready?"
"Why, everything is ready for you," said the
hag. "Plenty of bread, jars of old wine, and
some game that I have cooked for you.”
Then they fell to praising her, and, taking off
their clothes, anointed themselves before the fire.
There was a jar in the house full of warm water,
from which they drew and poured over themselves,
thus taking a hasty bath. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="21">
<p>A little later a number of young men arrived, bringing as much gold
and silver and clothing as they could carry, and a
great deal of jewelry, women's and men's. These
were accomplices of the others, and when they
had bestowed their booty within they, too, bathed
in the same manner. After this they had a bountiful supper, and there was a great deal of conversation among the cutthroats over their wine. The
old woman put barley before me and the horse,
and he set to and gulped it down in a hurry, fearing, probably, that I would share it.
But for my
part, whenever I saw the old woman go off I devoured the masters' bread.
The next day one young man was left behind
with the old woman, and all the others went off
on professional business. I bewailed my fate
and this strict guard, for I could despise the old
woman and run away under her very eyes, but the
young man was tall, and had a dangerous look,


<pb n="v.1.p.254"/>



moreover, and he always carried a sword and fastened the door every time he went out.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="22">
<p>
Three days after this, almost at midnight, the
robbers came back, bringing no gold or silver or
anything else except a very beautiful young girl.
She was in tears, and her clothes were torn and
her hair dishevelled. They deposited her in the
house on the mattresses, bade her cheer up, and
told the old woman to stay inside all the time,
and keep watch over her. The girl would neither eat nor drink; she did nothing but weep
and tear her hair, so that I myself, standing near
by at the manger, wept in sympathy with the beautiful maiden. In the mean time the robbers were
supping in the vestibule. Towards morning one
of the spies, who had been chosen by lot to watch
the roads, came and reported that a stranger was
going to pass that way carrying a great deal of
treasure. The robbers rose up just as they were,
armed themselves, saddled both me and the horse,
and drove us off. I, poor wretch, knew that we
were marching out to battle and murder, and I
advanced reluctantly, whereupon they beat me
with a stick to urge me on. When we came to
the road by which the stranger was to drive, the
robbers fell upon his carriages with one accord,
killed his servants, selected the most valuable articles, and placed them on the horse and me, and
hid the rest of the things there in the wood.


<pb n="v.1.p.255"/>


Then they drove us homeward thus laden, and I,
being urged on and beaten with a stick, struck
my foot on a sharp stone, and received a painful
wound from the blow, which made me limp as I
paced the rest of the journey. The robbers said.
to each other, "Why do we keep this ass who
stumbles on everything? Let us throw him over
the precipice, he brings us bad luck." "Yes," said
another, "let us throw him over to be a scapegoat for the gang." And they formed to attack
me. But I, hearing their talk, walked the rest of
the way on my wounded foot as though it belonged to somebody else, for the fear of death
made me insensible to the pain of it.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="23">
<p>

When we came to our abiding place they took
the booty from our shoulders and put it carefully
away. Then they fell to and dined, and when
night came they went off to secure the rest of the
things. "Why do we take this wretched ass?"
said one of them. "He is useless with his
wounded hoof. We will carry some of the things
and the horse the rest." So they went off, leading the horse. It was a bright moonlit night.
Then I said to myself: "You poor wretch, why
do you stay here any longer? Vultures and the
children of vultures will dine off you. Don't you
hear what they are plotting against you? Do you
want to be thrown over a precipice? It is night
now and there is a bright moon. The robbers


<pb n="v.1.p.256"/>



are off on the road. Fly, and save yourself from
these cutthroat masters."
While I was thus thinking to myself I perceived
that I was not even tied to anything, but that the
halter by which they led me on the road was hanging alongside. This added circumstance spurred
me to the greatest eagerness for flight, and I
emerged at a run and was making off; but when
the old woman saw me on the point of escaping
she seized me by the tail and held on. However, I
said to myself that if I were caught by an old woman I should deserve the precipice and any other
death, and I dragged her. But she shrieked with
all her might to the captive maiden to come out.
She ran forward, and when she saw the old woman
hanging on to the ass like a second Dirke she
found courage for a brave deed and worthy of
desperate youth. She sprang onto my back, seated
herself there, and urged me on. I, fired with love
of freedom and the girl, fled with all my might and
ran like a horse, leaving the old woman behind.
The girl prayed to the gods to grant her a safe
escape, and to me she said: "If you bring me to
my father, my pretty ass, I will free you from all
labor, and you shall have a bushel of barley every
day for breakfast." I ran on, quite forgetting my
wound in my eagerness to escape my murderers,
and the hope of getting plenty of assistance and
attention if I should save the maiden.


<pb n="v.1.p.257"/>

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="24">
<p>
But when we came to where the road split into
three the enemy met us on their homeward way.
They recognized their unhappy prisoners in the
moonlight while we were still at a distance, ran
up to us, and laid hold of me, saying: "Oho, my
fine madam, where are you going at this unseasonable hour, you poor, suffering thing? Aren't
you even afraid of ghosts? Come home with us
and we will hand you over to your friends." This
they said with a sardonic laugh, and they turned
me about and dragged me back. Then I remembered my lame foot and fell to limping. "What,"
said they, "are you lame now because you were
caught running away? When your mind was set
on flight you were sound and flew on wings,
swifter than a horse." These words were followed by the stick, and I got a wound on my
thigh at once as a warning.
When we turned into our lodging again we
found the old woman hanging from a stone by a
cord. Apparently she had been so afraid of her
masters when they should discover the girl's
flight that she had hanged herself. They spoke
admiringly of her courage, cut her down, and threw
her over the precipice with the cord round her
neck. The girl they tied up inside the house, and
then they supped and drank heavily.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="25">
<p> Meanwhile
they began at once to talk with each other about
the girl.



<pb n="v.1.p.258"/>



"What shall we do with the runaway?" asked
one of them.
"There is nothing to do," said another, "but
throw her down on top of our old woman.
She
has robbed us of as much treasure as she could,
and was on her way to betray our whole establishment. For be assured, my friends, that if she
had reached her kinsmen not one of us would
have been left alive, for our enemies would have
fallen on us with every preparation and captured
us all. So let us take our revenge on the foe,
but not by giving her such an easy death as falling onto the rock. Let us invent for her the
most painful and lingering death, and one that
will only kill her after keeping her a prisoner in
long torment."
Then they set themselves to think out a form
of death, and some one said, “I know you will
applaud my invention. We must kill the ass who
is a nuisance, and, moreover, pretends at present
to be lame, and helped and ministered to the girl's
flight into the bargain. Let us slaughter him,
then, early in the morning, cut open his belly,
take out all his vitals, and place this virtuous
maiden in the ass. We will let her head project
so that she may not be stifled at once, but all the
rest of her body shall be hidden inside. Then
we will stitch her securely in and throw them
both out to the vultures, preparing them a novel


<pb n="v.1.p.259"/>


breakfast. Note, my friends, the horror of the
torture: in the first place, to live in the dead body
of an ass, then to bake with the beast in the hottest sun of summer, and to die of lingering starvation, unable even to strangle herself. And,
finally, the vultures will make their way in through
the ass, and tear her flesh along with his while she
is yet alive."</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="27">
<p>
A general shout of applause greeted this monstrous idea as though it were something delightful; but I bewailed my lot. I was destined to be
slaughtered, and not even after death to lie a
peaceful corpse, but to serve as the tomb of an
unhappy and innocent girl.
But before day had fairly come a crowd of soldiers suddenly appeared who had come to attack
these villians, and they forthwith clapped them
all in irons and carried them off to the governor
of the country. And it happened that the girl's
fiancé came with them, for it was he that had given information as to the whereabouts of the robbers' headquarters. So he took charge of the girl,
set her on my back, and led her thus to her home.
When the villagers caught sight of us still at a
distance they knew the expedition was successful, for I brayed the good tidings to them, and
they ran to meet us, embraced us, and led us in.
The young girl had a great deal to say about
me, doing justice to her partner in captivity, in


<pb n="v.1.p.260"/>



flight, and in the danger of that common death.
And by my mistress's orders a breakfast was set
before me, consisting of a bushel of barley and
hay enough for a camel. But it was then most
of all that I cursed Palaistra for having changed
me into an ass by her art and not into a dog, for
I saw the dogs sneaking into the kitchen and
gorging themselves with plenty of food, such as
is served at the wedding-banquet of a wealthy
pair. A few days after the marriage my mistress
declared in her father's presence that she was indebted to me, and longed to make me a just return; whereupon he gave orders to turn me out to
grass in the pasture with the mares. "For if he
is at liberty," said he, "he will enjoy life." And
this recompense would have seemed perfectly just
if the matter had come before an ass as judge.
So he called one of the grooms and handed me
over to him, and I was delighted at the prospect
of doing no more work.
When we arrived at the farm the herdsman put
me with the mares, and led the drove of us into
the pasture. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="28">
<p>But even here it was fated that I
should have the same experience as Kandaules;
for the man in charge of the mares left me in
the possession of his wife, Megapole, for domestic service, and she harnessed me in the mill, and
made me grind wheat and barley at her bidding.
It is true that it was no great evil to a grateful ass


<pb n="v.1.p.261"/>

to turn a mill for his own masters, but the worthy
woman hired out my wretched neck to the other
peasants of the district, who were numerous, taking her pay in flour. And she would also roast
the barley allowed me for my breakfast, put it before me for me to grind, make cakes of it, and eat
them whole, leaving me to breakfast on the bran.
So I grew thin and ugly in a short time, for I had
no.comfort in-doors at the mill, nor out-of-doors
in the pasture, because my fellow-grazers fought
with me. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="29">
<p>Moreover, I was often sent up into
the mountain to fetch wood on my shoulders, and
this was the crown of my sorrows. In the first
place, there was a high mountain to be climbed
by a terribly straight road, and in the second
place, I was barefoot on a steep and stony path.
Besides this they sent with me as driver a wretch
of a small boy, who found a new way to torture
me every time. First he used to flog me even
when I was trotting faster than I should, and not
with a trimmed stick, but one covered with sharp
knots. He always used to strike the same spot
on my haunch, so that he opened a wound there
with his club, and he always aimed at the sore
place. His next idea was to lay a burden on me
that would have been too heavy for an elephant.
The descent from the mountain was steep, but
even there he used to flog me. And if he saw
that my load had slipped and was hanging to one


<pb n="v.1.p.262"/>



side, so that some of the sticks ought to be taken
off and added to the lighter side to make it balance, he would by no means proceed in this way.
No; he would lift great stones from the mountainside and put them on the side of my fardel that
was lighter and slipping up, and I would go on,
poor wretch, carrying in addition to the wood an
equal weight of useless stones. Moreover, there
was a stream that crossed the road and was never dry, and the boy, to save wetting his shoes, used
to perch on my back behind the wood, and thus
cross the river.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="30">
<p>
If ever I fell down, worn out with carrying my
load, that would be the occasion of unendurable
suffering. He who ought to have dismounted
and given me the assistance of his hand by raising me from the earth, and, if need were, taking
off my load, would neither get down nor lift a finger to help me, but from his seat he would batter
me with his stick, beginning at my head and ears,
until the blows aroused me. And he played an
even more intolerable trick on me than this. He
collected a fagot of the sharpest thorns, tied
them with a cord, and hung them behind on my
tail. As may be imagined, they dangled and fell
forward against me as I descended the mountain
and pricked my hind-quarters till they were covered with wounds. I was helpless to protect myself, for the source of my pain followed me at


<pb n="v.1.p.263"/>


each step, hanging from my own body. If I advanced gingerly to avoid the thorns I was halfkilled with the club; if I shunned the club then
that horror at my back attacked me sharply. In
fact, my
driver's one object in life was to kill me.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="31">
<p>
Once, when I could no longer bear my many
cruel sufferings, I let out at him with my heels,
and he never forgot that kick. He was ordered
one day to carry some tow from one village to
another, so he took me, collected a mass of tow,
tied it on my back, and made it fast with an additional and painful strap, brewing a fearful plot
against me as he adjusted the load. When it was
time to start he stole an ember still hot from the
hearth, and when we were at some distance from
the house he hid it in the tow. The tow immediately burst into flame-for what else would it
do?—and my load was nothing but a huge conflagration. I saw that I should be roasted in an
instant, and, coming upon a deep mud-hole in the
road, I flung myself into the wettest part of it.
There I rolled the tow, and twisted and turned
myself until I had sprinkled that hot and painful
burden with mud. Then I made the rest of the
journey with more safety, for the boy could not
set me on fire any more because the tow was
mixed with mud. And when he arrived he had
the impudence to tell this lie about me: that I
had plunged into the fireplace of my own accord


<pb n="v.1.p.264"/>



as I was passing it. Well, that time I survived
the tow, though I did not expect to; </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="32">
<p>but the villain of a boy invented something much worse
than this for me. He took me up the mountain
and put a great load of wood on me, but this he
sold to a neighboring farmer, and drove me home
with no load and no wood, and accused me falsely
to his master. "I don't see the good, sir," said
he, "of supporting this ass, for he is terribly lazy
and slow." </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="33">
<p>When the master heard this he said,
"Well, if he is willing neither to walk nor to carry a load, kill him and give his vitals to the dogs,
but save his flesh for the work-people, and if any
questions are asked as to the manner of his death
lay it to the wolf." The rascally boy, my driver,
was charmed, and was for killing me at once, </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="34">
<p>but
in the dead of night a messenger came from the
village to the farm, saying that the bride, the one
who was stolen by the robbers, had been walking
with her bridegroom late in the evening on the
sea-shore, when suddenly the sea rose, caught
them, and carried them out of sight, and that this
was the end of their happiness and their agony.
This news, that the house was bereft of its young
master and mistress, determined the farm-people
to live in slavery no longer. They laid their
hands on everything in the house and fled. The
master of the horses took me, too, collected all
the goods he could, and packed them on me and


<pb n="v.1.p.265"/>


the mares. I was put out at having to carry the
load of a real ass, but I was glad to accept this
trial in place of the knife.
We travelled all night over a painful road, and
in three days more we finished our journey and
came to Beroia, a large and populous town in
Macedonia. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="35">
<p>There our drivers determined to
settle us and themselves, and we beasts were sold
at auction by a loud-voiced crier in the middle
of the market-place. The by-standers wished to
open our mouths and look at them, and they saw
the age of each by his teeth. They bought the
others one by one, but I was left last of all, and
the auctioneer bade them take me home again.
"See," he said, "this fellow only has found no
master."

But fickle Nemesis who whirls our fortunes
constantly about brought a master even to me,
such as I should not have prayed for. He was
an old rascal of the sort who carry the Syrian
goddess around among the villages and farms,
and make her beg. This man bought me at the
handsome price of six dollars! </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="36">
<p>When we arrived
at Philebos's lodging—for this was my purchaser's name he shouted in a loud voice, just before the door, "Little girls, I have bought you a
slave, a handsome, stout Cappadocian." These
"little girls" were a crowd of abandoned men,
coadjutors of Philebos, and they all applauded in


<pb n="v.1.p.266"/>



answer to his shout, for they thought he had really made a human purchase. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="37">
<p>But when they saw
his slave was an ass they jeered Philebos and
burst out laughing.
The next day they got ready for work, as they
expressed it, prepared the goddess, and set her
on my back. Then we marched out of the city
and tramped about the country.
Whenever we
came into a village, I, the bearer of the goddess,
halted, the crowd of flute players blew a frenzied
strain, and the others, tearing off their Oriental
head-dresses, bending their heads and twisting
their necks, would cut their arms with their swords,
and each thrusting his tongue outside his teeth,
would cut that, too, so that in a moment they
would be covered with fresh blood. When I saw
these doings I at first stood trembling lest the
goddess might sometime have need of asses' blood,
too. But after they had mutilated themselves in
this way they collected coppers and small silver
coins from the surrounding spectators. Some one
might add figs and cheese and a jar of wine, or a
bushel of wheat or barley for the ass.
By these
means the company provided for their own maintenance and the service of the goddess whom I
carried.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="39">
<p>
Towards evening one day we halted at the
farm of a rich man. The master was at home,
received the goddess in his house with much


<pb n="v.1.p.267"/>


pleasure, and offered sacrifices to her. I am still
mindful of the terrible danger I was in at that
house, for the proprietor had received as a present from one of his friends a haunch of wild ass.
The cook took possession of it to dress it, but by
his carelessness it was lost, for a crowd of dogs
contrived to steal in where it was. The man was
so terrified at the storm of blows and the torture
he would get for the loss of the haunch that he
determined to hang himself by the neck. But
his wife, who was my heavy curse, said, "Nay,
dearest, don't take your own life or give way to
such despair. Be guided by me and all will go
well. Take these rascals' ass out to a lonely spot,
then kill him, cut off this quarter, the haunch,
bring it here, dress it and serve it to your master,
throwing the rest of the creature down some
precipice. They will think he has run away
somewhere and got lost. You see how fat he is,
and how much better in every way than that wild
one."

The cook praised the woman's idea. A happy
thought, wife," said he. “It is my only way to
escape a flogging, and it shall be done immediately." Thus did the wretch who was to be my
cook plot with his wife, standing in my presence.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="40">
<p>
But when I saw what was going to happen, I
made a strong resolve to save myself from the
knife; so, breaking the halter they led me by, I


<pb n="v.1.p.268"/>



leaped out and entered at a run the room where
the rascals were seated at table with the proprietor of the farm. Running in thither, I pranced
about and overturned everything, lamp and tables
together. I thought I had invented in this a
clever means of safety, and that the proprietor
would forthwith order me to be locked up where
I could be guarded safely as an unruly ass. But
this piece of cleverness brought me into the extremest danger. They thought I was mad, armed
themselves with plenty of swords and lances and
thick sticks, and got ready to kill me. When I
saw what great peril I was in, I ran past them into
the room where my masters were to sleep, and,
seeing this, they closed the doors carefully from
the outside.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="41">
<p>
As soon as day dawned I received the goddess
on my back again, and set out in company with
the begging priests, and we came to another village, large and populous, where they announced
something even more striking than usual in the
way of hocus-pocus-namely, that the goddess
would not stay in the house of a man, but would
occupy the temple of the most highly honored
local goddess they had. The people received the
foreign goddess very gladly, and lodged her with
their own.
To us they assigned lodgings with a
poor family. When my masters had made a long
stay here they desired to go on to the neighboring

<pb n="v.1.p.269"/>

city, and asked their goddess back from the
villagers. They entered the sacred precincts
themselves, brought her away, set her on my
back, and drove me off. But, as luck would have
it, the profane wretches had used the occasion of
entering this temple to steal a votive vessel of
gold, which they carried off hidden under the goddess. As soon as the villagers discovered what
had happened they gave chase; when they came
near they leaped down from their horses, arrested
them in the road, accused them of sacrilege and
temple-robbing, and demanded the stolen offering. Searching everywhere they found it in the
lap of the goddess. So they bound the wretches,
led them back, and cast them into prison. The
goddess whom I carried they took and placed in
another temple, and the golden vessel they restored to the local goddess.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="42">
<p>
The next day they decided to sell the prisoners' goods and me, and they disposed of me to a
stranger from a neighboring village, a baker by
trade. He took possession of me, bought ten
bushels of wheat, which he placed on my back,
and drove me home to his own house over a hard
road. When we arrived he led me into the mill,
where I beheld a great crowd of beasts, my fellow-slaves, and a great number of mills, all turned by them, and everything was covered with
flour. They left me there in idleness that day,


<pb n="v.1.p.270"/>



seeing that I was a new slave, and had come
over a hard road carrying a heavy burden. But
on the morrow they covered my eyes with a bandage, harnessed me to the shaft of the mill, and
then started me up. Although I knew how to
work a mill from much experience, I feigned ignorance; but my hopes were vain, for a number
of the millers seized clubs and surrounded me;
and when I was not expecting it—for I could not
see-they pounded me with one accord, and such
was the effect of their blows that I suddenly began to whirl round like a top. And I learned by
experiment that it will not do for a slave to wait
for the master's hand before he does his work.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="43">
<p>
Well, I grew very thin and weak in body, till
my master decided to sell me, and he disposed
of me to a man who was a market-gardener by
trade, for he had rented a garden to cultivate.
This was our daily work: My master would load
me with vegetables early in the morning, and take
them to the market. Having disposed of them
to the dealers, he would drive me back to the
garden. Then he would fall to digging and planting and watering, while I stood idle. Still this
life was terribly hard for me. In the first place,
when winter came my master could not afford
coverings for himself, and still less for me; and
I trod barefoot through the slimy mud and over
the hard, rough, frozen roads; and the only food


<pb n="v.1.p.271"/>


for man and beast alike was lettuces, hard and
bitter.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="44">
<p>
One day, when we were setting out for the
town, we happened upon a fine-looking man in a
soldier's uniform, who began to address us in the
Latin tongue, and asked the gardener whither he
was driving me, the ass. My master, not understanding the language, I suppose, made no reply.
The other grew angry at what he thought an insult, and struck with his whip at the gardener,
who thereupon closed with him, twirled him off
his legs, and stretched him in the road. As he
lay there he pounded him with hands and feet,
and a stone from the road. The soldier at first
resisted, and threatened that when he got on his
feet he would kill the gardener with his sword;
but my master, being thus instructed from the
very lips of his foe, chose the safer part, drew
the sword from him and hurled it to a distance.
Then he fell to pounding him again where he lay.
The soldier, seeing that his plight was already
past bearing, pretended to be killed by the blows.
This frightened the gardener, so that he left him
lying there just as he was, carried off the sword,
and rode away on me to the town.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="45">
<p>
When we were arrived there he confided the
charge of the garden to a partner of his, and,
fearing possible danger from the affair in the
road, he hid himself and me in the house of one


<pb n="v.1.p.272"/>



of his friends in the town. The next day they
laid their plans and acted as follows: my master
they concealed in a chest; me they hung by the
feet, and carried me up a ladder to the second
story, and shut me up there. The soldier, as we
heard afterwards, picked himself up out of the
road with difficulty when we were gone, and made
his way into the city, stunned with the beating he
had had. When he found the soldiers of his
company, he told them of the gardener's madness, and they, accompanying him, learned our
hiding-place. They brought the magistrates of
the city with them, who sent some of their people
into the house and bade all within come out.
When they appeared, the gardener was nowhere
to be seen. The soldiers, however, declared he
was in the house with me, his ass, but the people
of the house said no other creature was left inside, either man or ass. At this an uproar of vociferation rose in the narrow street, and I, in my
headstrong curiosity about everything, longed to
know who were shouting, so I peeped down from
above through the window. As soon as they saw
me they raised an outcry. The people of the
house were detected in their lie, and the magistrates, entering and ransacking everything, found
my master lying in the chest. Him they arrested
and packed off to prison, to give an account of
his desperate conduct, and me they brought down


<pb n="v.1.p.273"/>



and handed over to the soldiers. They all burst
into inextinguishable laughter at my having given.
information from the upper story and betrayed
my own master, and I was the origin, on this occasion, of the proverb about the "peeping ass."

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="46">
<p>
I do not know what happened the next day to
my master the gardener, but the soldier determined to sell me, and parted with me for five dollars. The purchaser was a servant to a very rich
man of Thessalonika, the largest town in Macedonia. His trade was to cook meats for his master, and he had a brother, a fellow-slave, who
understood bread - baking and the flavoring of
honey - cakes. These brothers were messmates
always, lodged in the same house, held the tools
of their trade as common property, and finally installed me, too, in their lodging. After the master's dinner these two used to bring home a quantity of fragments, the one of meats and fish, the
other of bread and cakes. They would shut me
in with these, leaving me the delightful task of
guarding them while they went to bathe. And I,
bidding farewell with all my heart to my portion
of barley, would devote myself to the skill and
earnings of my masters, and so for a long time
I revelled in human food. At first, when they
returned, they used to take no notice of my carnivorous tendency, because there was such a multitude of dishes, and because I still stole my dinner



<pb n="v.1.p.274"/>



with fear and discretion. But when at last
I perceived their unconsciousness, I used to eat
up the choicest morsels and a great deal beside.
Then they began to notice their loss, and each at
first looked suspiciously at the other, and called
him thief, robber of common goods, lost to all
sense of honor, and after that they both grew
careful, and counted the morsels.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="47">
<p>
The effect on me was that by living this pleasant and luxurious life I grew handsome again in
body from having my natural food, and my hide
shone with a fresh growth of hair. But my most
worthy masters, when they saw me growing fat
and sleek, although my barley was not consumed,
but remained of the same amount, began to suspect my audacity. So they went out as if going
to the bath, closed the doors, and applied their
eyes to a crack and watched what went on within. Innocent of the fraud, I forthwith advanced
and took my dinner. They first burst out laughing at sight of the incredible meal. Then they
called the other slaves to see me, and there was
a general laugh, so that the master himself heard
it, because it made such an uproar outside, and
asked what the joke was out there.
When he
heard he rose up from his wine, peeped in, and
saw me swallowing a bit of wild-boar. With a
shout of laughter he entered the room.
I was
greatly disturbed at being discovered by the master





<pb n="v.1.p.275"/>

as a thief and glutton in one, but he laughed
at me for a long time, and began by ordering me
to be led in to his supper-party. There he bade
them set a table for me, and put on it all sorts
of things, such as no other ass could eat-meats,
oysters, soup, fish—some dressed with caviare and
olive-oil, and some sprinkled with mustard. I,
when I saw fortune smiling sweetly on me, and
perceived that this foolery only could save me,
stood at the table and dined, though I had already made a hearty meal. The company shouted with laughter, and somebody said, "This ass
drinks wine, too, if any one will pour some out
for him." So the master ordered it, and I drank
what was offered me.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="48">
<p>
He perceived, as you may suppose, that I was
a remarkable creature, and ordered one of his
stewards to pay my price to the man who had
bought me, and as much again, and he handed
me over to a young freedman of his establishment, bidding him instruct me in whatever would
make me most diverting
him. The young
man found the task easy, for I obeyed instantly
every instruction. First he made me recline on
a couch, leaning on my elbow like a man. Then
he taught me to wrestle with him, and actually to
dance, standing upright on my hind-feet, and to
nod my head or shake it in answer to questions,
and a number of other things-all of which I


<pb n="v.1.p.276"/>



could have done even without teaching. And
the report spread far and wide that my master
had an ass who drank wine, wrestled, danced—
most surprising of all, nodded and shook his
head appropriately when spoken to, and, when he
was thirsty, summoned the butler by a movement
of his eyes. The spectators wondered at the
thing as a marvel, not knowing that a man was
shut up in the ass, and I made a fat living out
of their ignorance. I learned to amble and carry
my master on my back, galloping with a pace so
gentle that the rider hardly perceived the motion.
My harness was superb. I wore a purple saddlecloth, my bit was inlaid with gold and silver, and
I was hung with bells which made the sweetest
music.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="49">
<p>
As I have said, Menekles, our master, was from
Thessalonika, and had come to this place to
make arrangements for a spectacle he had promised his countrymen of men skilled to fight with
weapons in single combat. The gladiators were
by this time secured, and the party set out. We
started at early morning, and I carried my master
whenever a stretch of road was rough and hard
for the carriages to traverse. When we arrived
in Thessalonika every one was eager for the exhibition and for a sight of me, for my renown
had preceded me from afar, and the report of
my versatility and manlike gifts of dancing and


<pb n="v.1.p.277"/>


wrestling. My master displayed me to the most
distinguished of his townsmen over their wine,
and made those amazing frolics of mine an accessary of the dinner. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="52">
<p>But the man in charge of
me made an income of a good many dollars out
of me.
He used to lock me up in a room, and
when people wished to see me and my incredible
performances he would open the door on payment
of a fee. They used to bring in all sorts of eatables, particularly such as were considered revolting to an ass's stomach, but I ate them all, so
that in a few days, by dining with my master and
the townsfolk, I had already grown large and
terribly fat.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="53">
<p>
Finally that day arrived which was to bring
such distinction to my master. They decided to
exhibit me in the theatre, and this was the manner of my appearance. A large couch was prepared, wrought of Indian tortoise-shell fastened
with bolts of gold. I was laid on it, and in this
posture placed on a machine of some sort, transported to the theatre, and deposited in the middle
amid shouts of applause and a universal clapping
of hands. A table was spread for me, and many
dishes were set on it such as human epicures
have for dinner. Slave boys stood in attendance,
handsome cup-bearers who served me with wine
in a golden cup. The man in charge of me, who
was standing behind, bade me eat my dinner,


<pb n="v.1.p.278"/>

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="54">
<p>

But I was divided between shame at being exposed in the theatre and fear lest, perchance, a
bear or a lion should leap in.
At this moment some one passed by carrying
flowers, and among the others I saw the leaves
of freshly-gathered roses. Without an instant's
hesitation I sprang up and jumped from the
couch. The spectators thought I was getting up
to dance, but I fell upon the flowers, tore one
from another, selected the roses, and swallowed
them. And while the audience were still wondering at me, that beast's form fell from me and
vanished, the whilom ass disappeared, and to my
joy Loukios himself stood there naked. At this
incredible and most unexpected sight the company broke into great uproar in their terror, and
two opposing parties formed in the theatre. For
some thought I ought to be burned on the spot as
a master of unholy potions and a devil of many
shapes, but others said it was only fair to wait for
my account of myself and to hear the case first,
and then decide on it. For my part, I ran to the
governor of the province, who happened to be
present at the exhibition, and told him from below that the Thessalian serving-maid of a Thessalian woman had made an ass of me by anointing me with magic ointment, and I prayed him to
put me under guard until I should persuade him.
that I had told him my true history.


<pb n="v.1.p.279"/>

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="55">
<p>
"Tell us your name," said the governor, “and
the names of your parents and relatives, if you
have any, and your city."

"Sire," said I, my name is Loukios, and my
brother's name is Gaios. As to our family names,
we have the same. I am a writer of histories
and other works, and my brother is an elegiac
poet and a skilful diviner. Our birthplace is
Patrai, in Achaia."
When the magistrate heard this he cried, "You
are the son of a family who are very dear to me,
and my guest-friends. They have entertained me
in their house and given me presents, and I know
you tell the truth, since you are a child of theirs."
And he sprang from his seat, embraced me,
kissed me again and again, and conducted me to
his home. At this juncture my brother also
arrived, bringing me money and many other
things. Thereupon the governor declared me
free officially in the presence of the people, and
we went down to the sea, looked out a ship, and
put our luggage aboard.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0061.tlg001.perseus-eng1:" n="56">
<p>
Then we sailed away
from the city with a favorable wind, and a few
days later I arrived in my native land. There I
offered a sacrifice to the gods, my saviors, and
set up a votive offering, since I had been brought
home, and after long wanderings, and with great
difficulty, saved—not out of the lion's jaws, by
Heaven, but out of the curiosity of the ass.






<pb n="v.1.p.282"/>
</p></div>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>
