<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Judgement of the Goddesses</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1921</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianhar03luciuoft/page/384/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202137?urlappend=%3Bseq=396">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.3.p.385"/>

<head>The Judgement of the Goddesses<note xml:lang="eng"><p>The judgement of Paris, reviewed by Lucian.
Since the first edition, it has always been printed as the
twentieth of the Dialogues of the Gods, but in all the MSS.
it is a separate piece and has a separate caption of its own,
whereas in the Dialogues of the Gods the individual dialogues
are headed merely by the names of their interlocutors.
Then too it is longer than any of these, and although substantially of the same cloth, more markedly satirical than
most of them.</p>
<p>In connection with Lucian’s dialogue, it is well worth one’s
while to read Apuleius’ detailed description of a pantomime
on the same subject (Metamorphoses10, 232). The strong
contrast between the two treatments shows how little Lucian
was influenced by the contemporary theatre.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>
<label>ZEUS</label>
Hermes, take this apple; go to Phrygia, to Priam’s
son, the herdsman—he is grazing his flock in the
foothills of Ida, on Gargaron—and say to him:
“Paris, as you are handsome yourself, and also well
schooled in all that concerns love, Zeus bids you be
judge for the goddesses, to decide which of them is
the most beautiful. As the prize for the contest, let
the victor take the apple.” (To the Gopprsses) You
yourselves must now go and appear before your judge.
I refuse to be umpire because I love you all alike and
if it were possible, should be glad to see you all
victorious. Moreover, it is sure that if I gave the
guerdon of beauty to one, I should inevitably get into
the bad graces of the majority. For those reasons I
4am not a proper judge for you, but the young
Phrygian to whom you are going is of royal blood
and near of kin to our Ganymede; besides, he is
ingenuous and unsophisticated, and one cannot consider him unworthy of a spectacle such as this.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
<label>APHRODITE</label>
For my part, Zeus, even if you should appoint
Momus himself to be our judge, I would go and face
the inspection confidently, for what could he carp at
inme? The others, too, ought to be satisfied with
the man.

<pb n="v.3.p.387"/>

<label>HERA</label>
We are not afraid either, Aphrodite, not even if
the arbitration is turned over to your own Ares. We
accept this Paris, whoever he may be.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Is that your view too, daughter ? What do you
say? You turn away and blush? Of course, it is the
way of a maid like you to be bashful in such matters,
but you nod assent anyhow. Go, then, and do not
get angry at your judge, those of you who are
defeated, and do not inflict any harm on the lad. It
is not possible for all of you to be equally beautiful.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
<label>HERMES</label>
Let us make straight for Phrygia; I will lead the
way, and you follow me without delaying. Be of
good courage; I know Paris. He is young and
handsome and in every way susceptible to love ; just
the sort to decide such questions. He would not
judge amiss, not he.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
What you say is all to the good and in my favour,
that our judge is just. Is he unmarried, or does
some woman live with him?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Not quite unmarried, Aphrodite.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
What do you mean by that?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Apparently someone is living with him, a woman
from Mount Ida, well enough, but countrified and
terribly unsophisticated ; however, he does not seem .
to think much of her.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.387.n.1"><p>The reference is to Oenone.   </p></note> But why do you ask?


<pb n="v.3.p.389"/>

<label>APHRODITE</label>
It was just a casual question.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
<label>ATHENA</label>
I say, you are betraying your trust in talking to
her privately all this while.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
It was nothing alarming, Athena, or against you
and Hera; she asked me whether Paris is unmarried. ATHENA
Why was she inquisitive about that?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
I don’t know; she says, however, that she asked
because it came into her head casually, and not
because she had anything definite in view.
</p>
<p><label>ATHENA</label>
Well, what about it? Is he unmarried ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Apparently not.
</p>
<p><label>ATHENA</label>
Tell me, does he covet success in war and is he
fond of glory, or nothing but a herdsman ?.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
I can’t say for certain, but it is fair to suppose
that, being young, he yearns to acquire all that too,
and would like to be first in war.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
You see, I am not making any complaint or
reproaching you with talking confidentially to her ;
that is the way of fault-finders, not of Aphrodite !

<pb n="v.3.p.391"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
She herself asked me _ractically the same
questions ; so do not be ill-tempered or think you
are getting the worst of it if I answered her as I did
you, in a straightforward way.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>

But in the course of
our conversation we have already left the stars far
behind as we pressed on, and we are almost over
Phrygia. Indeed I can see Ida and the whole of
Gargaron plainly, and unless I am mistaken, even
Paris himself, your judge.
</p>
<p><label>HERA</label>
Where is he? I do not see him.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Look in this direction, Hera, to the left; not near
the mountain-top, but on the side, where the cavern is, near which you see the herd.
</p>
<p><label>HERA</label>
But I do not see the herd.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
What? Don’t you see tiny cattle over here in the
direction of my finger, coming out from among the
rocks, and someone running down from the cliff,
holding a crook and trying to prevent the herd from
scattering out ahead of him?
</p>
<p><label>HERA</label>
I see now—if that is really he.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Yes, itis he. As we are near now, let us alight
upon the earth and walk, if it is your pleasure, so
that we may not alarm him by flying suddenly down
from above.

<pb n="v.3.p.393"/>

<label>HERA</label>
You are right: let us do so... Now that we
have descended, it is in order, Aphrodite, for you to
go in front and lead the way for us. You are probably
acquainted with the countryside, since by common
report you often came down to visit Anchises.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
These jokes do not vex me greatly, Hera.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
<label>HERMES</label>
No matter: I will lead you, for I myself spent
some time on Ida when Zeus was in love with his
Phrygian lad, and I often came here when he sent
me down to watch the boy. Indeed, when he was
in the eagle, I flew beside him and helped him to lift
the pretty fellow, and if my memory serves me, it —
was from this rock just here that Zeus caught him
up. You see, he chanced to be piping to his flock
then, and Zeus, flying down behind him, grasped
him very delicately in his talons, held in his beak
the pointed cap which was on the boy’s head, and
bore him on high, terrified and staring at him with
his head turned backwards. So then I took the
syrinx, for he had let it fall in his fright—but here
is your umpire close by, so let us speak to him.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
 Good
day, herdsman.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
Good day to you also, young man. But who are
you, to have come here to see me, and who are these
women whom you have with you? They are not of a
sort to roam the mountains, being so beautiful.


<pb n="v.3.p.395"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
They are not women; it is Hera and Athena and
Aphrodite whom you see, Paris, and I am Hermes,
sent by Zeus—but why do you tremble and turn
pale? Don't be afraid; it is nothing terrible. He
bids you be judge of thelr beauty, saying that as you
are handsome yourself and also well schooled in all
that concerns love, he turns over the decision to you.
You will find out the prize for the contest if you
read the writing on the apple.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
Come, let me see what it says; “The fairest
may have me.”—How could I, Lord Hermes, a mere
mortal and a countryman, be judge of an extraordinary spectacle, too sublime for a herdsman? To
decide such matters better befits dainty, city-bred
folk. As for me, I could perhaps pass judgement as
an expert between two she-goats, as to which is the
more beautiful, or between two heifers;

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>

 but these
goddesses are all equally beautiful and I do not know
~ how a man could withdraw his eyes from one and
transfer them to another. They are not inclined to
come away readily, but wherever one directs them
first, they take firm hold and commend what is before
them; and if they pass over to something else, they
see that this too is beautiful and linger upon it,
mastered by what is near. In short, their beauty
encompasses and completely enthralls me, and I am
distressed that I cannot see with my whole body
as Argus did. I think I should pass a becoming
judgement if I should give the apple to them all.—
Another thing: one of them is Zeus’ sister and wife,

<pb n="v.3.p.397"/>

and the other two are his daughters! How, then,
could the decision help being hazardous from that
point of view also?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
I do not know; but it is impossible to escape
carrying out what Zeus has commanded.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
<label>PARIS</label>
Do me this one favour, Hermes: persuade them
not to be angry with me, the two that are defeated,
but to think that only my sight is at fault.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
They say they will do so, and now it is high time
for you to get your judging done.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
I shall try; what else can one do? But first I
want to know whether it will satisfy the requirements
to look them over just as they are, or must I have
them undress for a thorough examination ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
That is your affair, as you are the judge. Give
your orders as you will.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
As I will? I want to see them naked.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Undress, goddesses. Make your inspection, Paris.
I have turned my back.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
<label>APHRODITE</label>
Very well, Paris. I shall undress first, so that you
may discover that I am not just “white-armed”

<pb n="v.3.p.399"/>

and vain of “ox-eyes,” but that I am equally and
uniformly beautiful all over.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.399.n.1"><p>Aphrodite, vexed at Hera for twitting her about Anchises, makes fun of her by implying that she has no other beauties than those habitually commended in her by Homer. </p></note>
<label>ATHENA</label>
Do not let her undress, Paris, until she puts aside
her girdle, for she is an enchantress; otherwise
she may bewitch you with it.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.399.n.2"><p>See Iliad 14, 214 ff. </p></note> And indeed she ought
not to appear before you made up to that extent and
bedaubed with all those colours, as if she were a
courtesan in earnest: she ought to show her beauty
unadorned.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
They are right about the girdle, so lay it aside.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
Then why do not you take off your helmet, Athena,
and show your head bare, instead of tossing your
plumes at the judge and frightening him? Are you
afraid that you may be criticized for the green glare
of your eyes if it is seen without trappings that inspire
terror ?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.399.n.3"><p>The word with which Homer describes the eyes of Athena had an uncomplimentary sense in Lucian’s time. “Don’t let it trouble you that her eyes are very green (πανύ γλαυκούς), or that they squint and look at each other!” says a girl to her lover about a rival (Dial. Mer. 2,1). And Hephaestus finds Athena very beautiful, but must except her eyes: “To be sure, she has green eyes, but the helmet makes even that a mark of beauty” (Dial. Deor, 13 (vulg. 8)). So caesius in Latin ; cf. Lucretius 4, 1161. </p></note>
<label>ATHENA</label>
There is the helmet for.you: I have taken it off.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
There is the girdle for you.




<pb n="v.3.p.401"/>

<label>HERA</label>
Come, let us undress.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
<label>PARIS</label>
O Zeus, god of miracles! What a spectacle! What
beauty! What rapture! How fair the maiden is!
How royal and majestic and truly worthy of Zeus is
the matron’s splendour! How sweet and delicious
is the other’s gaze, and how seductively she smiled!
But I have more than enough of bliss already ; and if
you please, I should like to examine each of you
separately, for at present I am all at sea and do not
know what to look at; my eyes are ravished in every
direction.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
Let us do that.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
Then you two go away, and you, Hera, stay here.
</p>
<p><label>HERA</label>
Very well, and when you have examined me
thoroughly, you must further consider whether the
rewards of a vote in my favour are also beautiful in
your eyes. If you judge me to be beautiful, Paris,
you shall be lord of all Asia.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
My decisions are not to be influenced by rewards.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>

But go; I shall do whatever seems best. Come,
Athena.
</p>
<p><label>ATHENA</label>
I am at your side, and if you judge me beautiful,
Paris, you shall never leave the-field of battle

<pb n="v.3.p.403"/>

defeated, but always victorious, for I shall make you
a warrior and a conqueror.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
I have no use, Athena, for war and battle. As you
see, peace reigns at present over Phrygia and Lydia,
and my father’s realm is free from wars. But have
no fear ; you shall not be treated unfairly, even if my
judgement is not to be influenced by gifts. Dress
yourself now, and put on your helmet, for I have seen
enough. It is time for Aphrodite to appear.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
<label>APHRODITE</label>
Here I am close by; examine me thoroughly, part
by part, slighting none, but lingering upon each.
And if you will be so good, my handsome lad, let me
tell you this. I have long seen that you are young
and more handsome than perhaps anyone else whom
Phrygia nurtures. While I congratulate you upon
your beauty, I find’ fault with you because, instead
of abandoning these crags and cliffs and living in
town, you are letting your beauty go to waste in
the solitude. What joy can you get of the mountains? What good can your beauty do the kine?
Moreover, you ought to have married by this time—
not a country girl, however, a peasant, like the
women about Ida, but someone from Greece, either
from Argos or Corinth or a Spartan like Helen, who
is young and beautiful and not a bit inferior to me,
and above all, susceptible to love. If she but saw
you, I know very well that, abandoning everything
and surrendering without conditions, she would
follow you and make her home with you. No doubt
you yourself have heard something of her.


<pb n="v.3.p.405"/>

<label>PARIS</label>
Nothing, Aphrodite, but I should be glad to hear
you tell all about her now.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
<label>APHRODITE</label>
In the first place, she is the daughter of that
lovely Leda to whom Zeus flew down in the form of
a swan.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
What is her appearance ?
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
She is white, as is natural in the daughter of a
swan, and delicate, since she was nurtured in an eggshell, much given to exercise and athletics, and so
very much sought for that a war actually broke out
over her because Theseus carried her off while she was
still a young girl. Moreover, when she came to
maturity, all the noblest of the Achaeans assembled
to woo her, and Menelaus, of the line of Pelops, was
given the preferenee. If you like, I will arrange the
marriage for you.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
What do you mean? With a married woman?
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
You are young and countrified, but I know how
such things are to be managed.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
How? I too want to know.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
<label>APHRODITE</label>
You will go abroad on the pretext of seeing
Greece, and when you come to Sparta, Helen will
see you. From that time on it will be my look-out
that she falls in love with you and follows you.

<pb n="v.3.p.407"/>

<label>PARIS</label>
That is just the thing that seems downright
incredible to me, that she should be willing to
abandon her husband and sail away with a foreigner
and a stranger.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
Be easy on that score; I have two beautiful pages,
Desire and Love; these I shall give you to be your
guides on the journey. Love will enter wholly into
her heart and compel the woman to love you, while
Desire will encompass you and make you what he is
himself, desirable and charming. I myself shall be
there too, and I shall ask the Graces to go with me;
and in this way, by united effort, we shall prevail
upon her.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
How this affair will turn out is uncertain,
Aphrodite; but, anyhow, I am in love with Helen
already ; somehow or other I think I see her; I am
sailing direct to Greece, visiting Sparta, coming back
again with the woman—and it irks me not to be
doing all this now!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg032.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
<label>APHRODITE</label>
Do not fall in love, Paris, until you have requited
me, your match-maker and maid of honour, with the
decision. It would be only fitting that when I am
there with you, I too should be triumphant, and that
we should celebrate at the same time your marriage
and my victory. It is in your power to buy everything—her love, her beauty, and her hand—at the
price of this apple.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
I am afraid you may dismiss me from your mind
after the decision.

<pb n="v.3.p.409"/>

<label>APHRODITE</label>
Do you want me to take an oath?
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
Not at all; but promise once again.
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
I do promise that I will give you Helen to wife,
and that she shall follow you and come to your ©
people in Troy ; and I myself will be there and help
in arranging it all.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
And shall you bring Love and Desire and the
Graces ?
</p>
<p><label>APHRODITE</label>
Have no fear; I shall take with me Longing and
Wedlock as well.
</p>
<p><label>PARIS</label>
Then on these conditions I award you the apple:
take it on these conditions.



</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>

