<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>To Demonicus</title>
        
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor>George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <date type="print">1928</date>
          <date type="reprint">1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg007.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In many respects, Demonicus, we shall find that much disparity exists between the
          principles of good men and the notions of the base; but most of all by far have they
          parted company in the quality of their friendships.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the
            sentiment that bad men make poor friends cf. <bibl n="Thgn. 101">Theog. 101 ff.</bibl>,
            and <placeName key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName> in <bibl n="Xen. Mem. 2.6.19">Xen.
              Mem. 2.6.19</bibl>.</note> The base honor their friends only when they are present;
          the good cherish theirs even when they are far away; and while it takes only a short time
          to break up the intimacies of the base, not all eternity can blot out the friendships of
          good men. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So then, since I deem it fitting that those who strive for distinction and are ambitious
          for education should emulate the good and not the bad, I have dispatched to you this
          discourse as a gift, in proof of my good will toward you and in token of my friendship for
          Hipponicus; for it is fitting that a son should inherit his father's friendships even as
          he inherits his estate. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I see, moreover, that fortune is on our side and that the present circumstances are in
          league with us; for you are eager for education and I profess to educate; you are ripe for
            philosophy<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the meaning of “philosophy” in Isocrates
            see Introduction, pp. xxv. ff.</note> and I direct students of philosophy. Now those who
          compose hortatory discourses addressed to their own friends are, no doubt, engaged in a
          laudable employment; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>yet they do not occupy themselves with the most vital part of philosophy. Those, on the
          contrary, who point out to the young, not by what means they may cultivate skill in
          oratory, but how they may win repute as men of sound character, are rendering a greater
            service<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Hermogenes, <foreign xml:lang="greek">*peri\
              meqo/dou deino/thtos</foreign>, 25, refers to this introduction as an example of
            inoffensive self-laudation in the orators.</note> to their hearers in that, while the
          former exhort them to proficiency in speech, the latter improve their moral conduct.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For Isocrates' insistence on right conduct as the end of
            education see Introduction, p. xxv.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Therefore, I have not invented a hortatory<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This discourse
            is really hortatory in the general sense of that word, but Isocrates distinguishes it
            from hortatory (“protreptic”) discourses of the sophists, which were lectures to
            stimulate interest in whatever kind of learning they professed to teach, commonly
            oratory.</note> exercise, but have written a moral treatise; and I am going to counsel
          you on the objects to which young men should aspire and from what actions they should
          abstain, and with what sort of men they should associate and how they should regulate
          their own lives. For only those who have travelled this road in life have been able in the
          true sense to attain to virtue—that possession which is the grandest and the most enduring
          in the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For beauty is spent by time or withered by disease; wealth ministers to vice rather than
          to nobility of soul, affording means for indolent living and luring the young to pleasure;
          strength, in company with wisdom, is, indeed, an advantage, but without wisdom it harms
          more than it helps its possessors, and while it sets off the bodies of those who cultivate
          it, yet it obscures the care of the soul<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.1">Isoc. 4.1</bibl>.</note>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But virtue, when it grows up with us in our hearts without alloy, is the one possession
          which abides with us in old age; it is better than riches and more serviceable than high
          birth; it makes possible what is for others impossible; it supports with fortitude that
          which is fearful to the multitude; and it considers sloth a disgrace and toil an honor.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>This it is easy to learn from the labors of Heracles and the exploits of Theseus, whose
          excellence of character has impressed upon their exploits so clear a stamp of glory that
          not even endless time can cast oblivion upon their achievements. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Nay, if you will but recall also your father's principles, you will have from your own
          house a noble illustration of what I am telling you. For he did not belittle virtue nor
          pass his life in indolence; on the contrary, he trained his body by toil, and by his
          spirit he withstood dangers. Nor did he love wealth inordinately; but, although he enjoyed
          the good things at his hand as became a mortal, yet he cared for his possessions as if he
          had been immortal<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Bacchyl. Ep. 3.78">Bacchyl.
              3.78</bibl> (Jebb): “As a mortal thou must nourish each of two forebodings;—that
            to-morrow's sunlight will be the last that thou shalt see; or that for fifty years thou
            wilt live out thy life in ample wealth;” and <placeName key="tgn,2007838"
              >Lucian</placeName>, <title>Anthol. Pal</title> . x. 26: <foreign xml:lang="greek">w(s
              teqhnco/menos tw=n sw=n a)gaqw=n a)po/laue w(s de\ biwso/menos fei/deo sw=n
              ktea/wn</foreign>.</note>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Neither did he order his existence sordidly, but was a lover of beauty, munificent in his
          manner of life, and generous to his friends; and he prized more those who were devoted to
          him than those who were his kin by blood; for he considered that in the matter of
          companionship nature is a much better guide than convention, character than kinship, and
          freedom of choice than compulsion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But all time would fail us if we should try to recount all his activities. On another
          occasion I shall set them forth in detail;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This intention
            was not, so far as we know, carried out.</note> for the present however, I have produced
          a sample of the nature of Hipponicus, after whom you should pattern your life as after an
          example, regarding his conduct as your law, and striving to imitate and emulate your
          father's virtue; for it were a shame, when painters represent the beautiful among animals,
          for children not to imitate the noble among their ancestors. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nay, you must consider that no athlete is so in duty bound to train against his
          competitors as are you to take thought how you may vie with your father in his ways of
          life. But it is not possible for the mind to be so disposed unless one is fraught with
          many noble maxims; for, as it is the nature of the body to be developed by appropriate
          exercises, it is the nature of the soul to be developed by moral precepts. Wherefore I
          shall endeavor to set before you concisely by what practices I think you can make the most
          progress toward virtue and win the highest repute in the eyes of all other men. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> First of all, then, show devotion to the gods,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Thgn. 171">Theognis 171</bibl>
            <foreign xml:lang="greek">qeoi=s eu)xeu, qeoi=s e)stin e)/pi kra/tos</foreign>.</note>
          not merely by doing sacrifice, but also by keeping your vows; for the former is but
          evidence of a material prosperity, whereas the latter is proof of a noble character. Do
          honor to the divine power at all times, but especially on occasions of public worship; for
          thus you will have the reputation both of sacrificing to the gods and of abiding by the
          laws. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Conduct yourself toward your parents as you would have your children conduct themselves
          toward you.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates anticipates the golden rule.Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 3.61">Isoc. 3.61</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 2.24">Isoc. 2.24, 38</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.81">Isoc. 4.81</bibl>.</note> Train your body, not by the exercises which
          conduce to strength, but by those which conduce to health. In this you will succeed if you
          cease your exertions while you still have energy to exert yourself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Be not fond of violent mirth, nor harbor presumption of speech; for the one is folly,
          the other madness.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. Lord Chesterfield,
              <title>Letters</title> , 144: “Frequent and loud laughter is characteristic of folly
            and ill manners.”</note> Whatever is shameful to do you must not consider it honorable
          even to mention. Accustom yourself to be, not of a stern, but of a thoughtful, mien; for
          through the former you will be thought self-willed, through the latter, intelligent.
          Consider that no adornment so becomes you as modesty, justice, and self-control; for these
          are the virtues by which, as all men are agreed, the character of the young is held in
          restraint. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Never hope to conceal any shameful thing which you have done; for even if you do conceal
          it from others, your own heart will know. Fear the gods, honor your parents, respect your
          friends, obey the laws. Pursue the enjoyments which are of good repute; for pleasure
          attended by honor is the best thing in the world, but pleasure without honor is the
            worst.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 1.46">Isoc. 1.46</bibl></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Guard yourself against accusations, even if they are false; for the multitude are
          ignorant of the truth and look only to reputation. In all things resolve to act as though
          the whole world would see what you do; for even if you conceal your deeds for the moment,
          later you will be found out. But most of all will you have the respect of men, if you are
          seen to avoid doing things which you would blame others for doing.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Apparently borrowed form <placeName key="tgn,2716103">Thales</placeName>. See
              <bibl n="D. L. 1.36">Diog. Laert. 1.36</bibl>
            <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)a\n toi=s a)llois e)pitimw=men au)toi\ drw=men</foreign>.
            Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 1.14">Isoc. 1.14</bibl> and note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If you love knowledge, you will be a master of knowledge.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Sandys quotes from Ascham's <title>Scholemaster</title> : “Isocrates did cause to be
            written at the entrie of his schole, in golden letters, this golden sentence, <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">e)a\n h)=|s filomaqh/s, e)/sh| polumaqh/s</foreign>, which
            excellentlie said in Greek, is thus rudelie in English, ‘If thous lovest lerning, thou
            shalt attayne to moch learning.’” The words were in fact inscribed “in golden letters”
            over the portal to Shrewsbury School.</note> What you have come to know, preserve by
          exercise; what you have not learned, seek to add to your knowledge; for it is as
          reprehensible to hear a profitable saying and not grasp it as to be offered a good gift by
          one's friends and not accept it. Spend your leisure time in cultivating an ear attentive
          to discourse, for in this way you will find that you learn with ease what others have
          found out with difficulty. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Believe that many precepts are better than much wealth; for wealth quickly fails us, but
          precepts abide through all time; for wisdom alone of all possessions is imperishable. Do
          not hesitate to travel a long road<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Echoed unmistakably from
              <bibl n="Thgn. 71">Theog. 71-2</bibl>: <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)lla\ met' e)sqlo\n
              i)w\n bouleu/eo polla\ mogh/sas kai\ makrh\n possi/n, *ku/rn', o(do\n
              e)ktele/sas</foreign>.</note> to those who profess to offer some useful instruction;
          for it were a shame, when merchants cross vast seas in order to increase their store of
          wealth, that the young should not endure even journeys by land to improve their
          understanding. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Be courteous in your manner, and cordial in your address. It is the part of courtesy to
          greet those whom you meet; and of cordiality to enter into friendly talk with them. Be
          pleasant to all, but cultivate the best; thus you will avoid the dislike of the former and
          have the friendship of the latter. Avoid frequent conversations with the same persons, and
          long conversations on the same subject; for there is satiety in all things.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Hom. Il. 13.636">Hom. Il. 13.636</bibl>
            <foreign xml:lang="greek">pa/ntwn me\n ko/ros e)sti/</foreign>; <bibl
              n="Aristoph. Pl. 189">Aristoph. Pl. 189</bibl>
            <foreign xml:lang="greek">tw=n me\n ga\r a)/llwn e)sti\ pa/ntwn
            plhsmonh/</foreign>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Train yourself in self-imposed toils, that you may be able to endure those which others
          impose upon you.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">So also Democritus, Stobaeus,
              <title>Flor.</title> xxix. 63.</note> Practice self-control in all the things by which
          it is shameful for the soul to be controlled,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Greek
            ideal of freedom through self-control, See <placeName key="tgn,2674867"
              >Socrates</placeName> in <bibl n="Xen. Mem. 4.5">Xen. Mem. 4.5</bibl>. Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 3.29">Isoc. 3.29</bibl>.</note> namely, gain, temper, pleasure, and pain. You
          will attain such self-control if you regard as gainful those things which will increase
          your reputation and not those which will increase your wealth; if you manage your temper
          towards those who offend against you as you would expect others to do if you offended
          against them; if you govern your pleasures on the principle that it is shameful to rule
          over one's servants and yet be a slave to one's desires; and if, when you are in trouble,
          you contemplate the misfortunes of others and remind yourself that you are human. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Guard more faithfully the secret which is confided to you than the money which is
          entrusted to your care; for good men ought to show that they hold their honor more
          trustworthy than an oath. Consider that you owe it to yourself no less to mistrust bad men
          than to put your trust in the good. On matters which you would keep secret, speak to no
          one save when it is equally expedient for you who speak and for those who hear that the
          facts should not be published. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Never allow yourself to be put under oath save for one of two reasons—in order to clear
          yourself of disgraceful charges or to save your friends from great dangers. In matters of
          money, swear by none of the gods, not even when you intend to swear a true oath; for you
          will be suspected on the one hand of perjury, on the other of greed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Make no man your friend before inquiring how he has used his former friends;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Xen. Mem. 2.6.6">Xen. Mem. 2.6.6</bibl>.</note>
          for you must expect him to treat you as he has treated them. Be slow<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. Solon, quoted in <bibl n="D. L. 1.60">Diog. Laert. 1.60</bibl>: <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">fi/lous mh\ taxu\ ktw=: ou(\s d' a)\n kth/sh| mh\
              a)podoki/maze</foreign>.</note> to give your friendship, but when you have given it,
          strive to make it lasting; for it is as reprehensible to make many changes in one's
          associates as to have no friend at all. Neither test your friends to your own injury nor
          be willing to forgo a test of your companions. You can manage this if you pretend to be in
          want when really you lack nothing. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Confide in them about matters which require no secrecy as if they were secrets; for if
          you fail you will not injure yourself, and if you succeed you will have a better knowledge
          of their character. Prove your friends by means of the misfortunes of life and of their
          fellowship in your perils; for as we try gold in the fire, so we come to know our friends
          when we are in misfortune.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For both the figure and the
            sentiment cf. <bibl n="Thgn. 415">Theog. 415</bibl>.</note> You will best serve your
          friends if you do not wait for them to ask your help, but go of your own accord at the
          crucial moment to lend them aid. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Consider it equally disgraceful to be outdone by your enemies in doing injury and to be
          surpassed by your friends in doing kindness.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The “get even”
            standard of honor in popular thought. Cf. <bibl n="Thgn. 869">Theog. 869-72</bibl>:
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)/n moi e)/peita pe/soi me/gas ou)rano\s eu)ru\s u(/perqen
              xa/lkeos, a)nqrw/pwn dei=ma xamaigene/wn, ei) mh\ e)gw\ toi=sin me\n e)parke/sw oi(/
              me filou=sin, toi=s d' e)xqroi=s a)ni/n kai\ me/ga ph=m' e)/somai</foreign>. Even
              <placeName key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName> reflects this standard in <bibl
              n="Xen. Mem. 2.6.35">Xen. Mem. 2.6.35</bibl>. Not so Socrates in <placeName
              key="tgn,1023926">Plato</placeName>: see <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 335a">Plat. Rep.
              335a</bibl>.</note> Admit to your companionship, not those alone who show distress at
          your reverses, but those also who show no envy at your good fortune; for there are many
          who sympathize with their friends in adversity, but envy them in prosperity.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <placeName key="tgn,2674867">Socrates</placeName>'
            analysis of envy in <bibl n="Xen. Mem. 3.9.8">Xen. Mem. 3.9.8</bibl>.</note> Mention
          your absent friends to those who are with you, so that they may think you do not forget
          them, in their turn, when they are absent. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In matters of dress, resolve to be a man of taste, but not a fop. The man of taste is
          marked by elegance, the fop by excess. Set not your heart on the excessive acquisition of
          goods, but on a moderate enjoyment of what you have. Despise those who strain after
          riches, but are not able to use what they have; they are in like case with a man who,
          being but a wretched horseman, gets him a fine mount. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Try to make of money a thing to use as well as to possess; it is a thing of use to those
          who understand how to enjoy it, and a mere possession to those who are able only to
          acquire it. Prize the substance you have for two reasons—that you may have the means to
          meet a heavy loss and that you may go to the aid of a worthy friend when he is in
          distress; but for your life in general, cherish your possessions not in excess but in
          moderation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Be content with your present lot, but seek a better one. Taunt no man with his
          misfortune for fate is common to all and the future is a thing unseen. Bestow your favors
          on the good; for a goodly treasury is a store of gratitude laid up in the heart of an
          honest man. If you benefit bad men, you will have the same reward as those who feed stray
          dogs; for these snarl alike at those who give them food and at the passing stranger; and
          just so base men wrong alike those who help and those who harm them.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The same cynicism is expressed in <bibl n="Thgn. 105">Theog. 105-106</bibl>:
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">deilou\s eu)= e)/rdonti mataiota/th xa/ris e)sti/n: i)=son
              kai\ spei/rein po/nton a(lo\s polih=s</foreign>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Abhor flatterers as you would deceivers; for both, if trusted, injure those who trust
          them. If you admit to your friendship men who seek your favor for the lowest ends, your
          life will be lacking in friends who will risk your displeasure for the highest good. Be
          affable in your relations with those who approach you, and never haughty; for the pride of
          the arrogant even slaves can hardly endure, whereas when men are affable all are glad to
          bear with their ways. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But to be affable, you must not be quarrelsome, nor hard to please, nor always determined
          to have your way; you must not oppose harshly the angry moods of your associates, even if
          they happen to be angry without reason, but rather give way to them when they are in the
          heat of passion and rebuke them when their anger has cooled; you must avoid being serious
          when the occasion is one for mirth, or taking pleasure in mirth when the occasion is
          serious (for what is unseasonable is always offensive); you must not bestow your favors
          ungraciously as do the majority who, when they must oblige their friends, do it
          offensively; and you must not be given to fault-finding, which is irksome, nor be
          censorious, which is exasperating. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If possible avoid drinking-parties altogether,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For
            drinking-parties in <placeName key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName> see Isocrates'
            picture in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.286">Isoc. 15.286-7</bibl>.</note> but if ever occasion
          arises when you must be present, rise and take your leave before you become
            intoxicated;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Theognis gives the same advice, <bibl
              n="Thgn. 484">Theog. 484 ff.</bibl></note> for when the mind is impaired by wine it is
          like chariots which have lost their drivers; for just as these plunge along in wild
          disorder when they miss the hands which should guide them, so the soul stumbles again and
          again when the intellect is impaired.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This recalls the
            figure of the charioteer and the two horses in <bibl n="Plat. Phaedrus 247a">Plat.
              Phaedrus 247a-c</bibl>. There is an exact parallel in Libanius, xii. 40.</note>
          Cultivate the thoughts of an immortal by being lofty of soul, but of a mortal by enjoying
          in due measure the good things which you possess.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 1.9">Isoc. 1.9</bibl></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Consider culture to be a good so far superior to the lack of culture that while in
          general everyone derives gain from the practice of vice, boorishness<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The translation of this perplexing sentence takes <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >au)/th</foreign> to refer to <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)paiduesi/a</foreign>,
            following Sandys.</note> is the one vice which actually penalizes its possessors; for
          the latter are often punished in deed for the offences they give by their words. When you
          desire to make a friend of anyone, say good things about him to those who are wont to
          report them; for praise is the foundation of friendship, as blame is that of enmity. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In your deliberations, let the past be an exemplar for the future;<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.35">Isoc. 2.35</bibl>.</note> for the unknown may be
          soonest discerned by reference to the known.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The same idea
            is attributed to Cleobulus, Stob. <title>Flor.</title> 3.31 <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >ta\ a(fanh= toi=s faneroi=s tekmai/rou</foreign>.</note> Be slow in deliberation, but
          be prompt to carry out your resolves. Consider that as the best thing which we have from
          the gods is good fortune, so the best thing which we have in ourselves is good judgement.
          When there is anything of which you are ashamed to speak openly, but about which you wish
          to confer with some of your friends, speak as though it were another's affair; thus you
          will get at their opinion, and will not betray your own case. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Whenever you purpose to consult with anyone about your affairs, first observe how he has
          managed his own; for he who has shown poor judgement in conducting his own business will
          never give wise counsel about the business of others. The greatest incentive you can have
          to deliberation is to observe the misfortunes which spring from the lack of it; for we pay
          the closest attention to our health when we recall the pains which spring from disease.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Pattern after the character of kings, and follow closely their ways. For you will thus
          be thought to approve them and emulate them, and as a result you will have greater esteem
          in the eyes of the multitude and a surer hold on the favor of royalty. Obey the laws which
          have been laid down by kings, but consider their manner of life your highest law. For just
          as one who is a citizen in a democracy must pay court to the multitude, so also one who
          lives under a monarchy should revere the king.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates'
            defense of his advice to the young Nicocles in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.70">Isoc. 15.70</bibl>
            applies here. See <bibl n="Isoc. 2">Isoc. 2</bibl>, introduction.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When you are placed in authority, do not employ any unworthy person in your
          administration; for people will blame you for any mistakes which he may make. Retire from
          your public trusts, not more wealthy, but more highly esteemed; for the praise of a people
          is better than many possessions. Never support or defend a bad cause, for people will
          suspect that you yourself do the things which you aid others in doing. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Put yourself in a position in which you have the power to take advantage, but refrain
          when you have your fair share, so that men may think that you strive for justice, not from
          weakness, but from a sense of equity. Prefer honest poverty to unjust wealth;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Thgn. 145">Theog. 145-8</bibl>: <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">bou/leo d' eu)sebe/wn su\n xrh/masin oi)kei=n h)\ ploutei=n, a)di/kws
              xrhma/ta pasa/menos. e)n de\ dikaiosu/nh| sullh/bdhn pa=s' a)reth/ e)stin, pa=s de/ t'
              a)nh\r a)gaqo/s, *ku/rne, di/kaios e)w/n.</foreign>.</note> for justice is better than
          riches in that riches profit us only while we live, while justice provides us glory even
          after we are dead, and while riches are shared by bad men, justice is a thing in which the
          wicked can have no part.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.32">Isoc.
              2.32</bibl>; <bibl n="Thgn. 315">Theog. 315-18</bibl>: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >polloe/ toi ploutou=si kakoi/, a)gaqoi\ de\ pe/nontai: a)ll' h(mei=s tou/tois ou)
              diameiyo/meqa th=s a)reth=s to\n plou=tin, e)pei\ to\ me\n e)/mpedon ai)ei/, xrh/mata
              d' a)nqrw/pwn a)/llote a)/llos e)/xei.</foreign></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Never emulate those who seek to gain by injustice, but cleave rather to those who have
          suffered loss in the cause of justice; for if the just have no other advantage over the
          unjust, at any rate they surpass them in their high hopes.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >This suggests the noble passage on just living in <bibl n="Isoc. 8.34">Isoc.
              8.34</bibl>. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.28">Isoc. 4.28</bibl> and note. Life beyond this
            life is a “hope” in Isocrates; what he is sure of is the immortality of fame. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 5.134">Isoc. 5.134</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Give careful heed to all that concerns your life, but above all train your own
          intellect; for the greatest thing in the smallest compass is a sound mind in a human
            body.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">From Periander. See Stob. <title>Flor</title> .
            iii. 56: <foreign xml:lang="greek">*peri/andros e)rwthqei/s, ti/ me/giston e)n
              e)laxi/stw|, ei)=pe, fre/nes a)gaqai\ e)n sw/mati a)nqrw/pou</foreign></note> Strive
          with your body to be a lover of toil, and with your soul to be a lover of wisdom, in order
          that with the one you may have the strength to carry out your resolves, and with the other
          the intelligence to foresee what is for your good. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Always when you are about to say anything, first weigh it in your mind; for with many
          the tongue outruns the thought.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">From <placeName
              key="tgn,2078846">Chilo</placeName>. See Diog. Laert. i. 70: <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >h( glw=ssa/ sou mh\ protrexe/tw tou= nou=</foreign></note> Let there be but two
          occasions for speech—when the subject is one which you thoroughly know and when it is one
          on which you are compelled to speak. On these occasions alone is speech better than
          silence; on all others, it is better to be silent than to speak. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Consider that nothing in human life is stable;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 1.29">Isoc. 1.29</bibl>; <bibl n="Thgn. 585">Theog. 585</bibl>.</note> for
          then you will not exult overmuch in prosperity, nor grieve overmuch in adversity.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.39">Isoc. 2.39</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.30">Isoc. 12.30</bibl>; <bibl n="Thgn. 591">Theog. 591 ff.</bibl>:
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">tolma=n xrh/, ta\ didou=si qeoi\ qnhtoi=si brotoi=sin,
              r(hidi/ws de\ fe/rein a)mfote/rwn to\ la/xos, mh/to kakoi=sin a)sw=nta li/hn fre/na,
              mh/t' a)gaqoi=sin terfqe/nt' e)capi/nhs, pri\n te/los a)/kron i)dei=n</foreign>. and
              <placeName key="tgn,2075349">Kipling</placeName>: “If you can meet with triumph and
            disaster and treat these two imposters just the same.”</note> Rejoice over the good
          things which come to you, but grieve in moderation over the evils which befall you, and in
          either case do not expose your heart to others;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Thgn. 1162">Theog. 1162</bibl>.</note> for it were strange to hide away one's
          treasure in the house, and yet walk about laying bare one's feelings to the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Be more careful in guarding against censure than against danger; for the wicked may well
          dread the end of life, but good men should dread ignominy during life. Strive by all means
          to live in security,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.13">Isoc.
              2.13</bibl>.</note> but if ever it falls to your lot to face the dangers of battle,
          seek to preserve your life, but with honor and not with disgrace; for death is the
          sentence which fate has passed on all mankind, but to die nobly is the special honor which
          nature has reserved for the good. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Do not be surprised that many things which I have said do not apply to you at your
          present age. For I also have not overlooked this fact, but I have deliberately chosen to
          employ this one treatise, not only to convey to you advice for your life now, but also to
          leave with you precepts for the years to come; for you will then readily perceive the
          application of my precepts, but you will not easily find a man who will give you friendly
          counsel. In order, therefore, that you may not seek the rest from another source, but that
          you may draw from this as from a treasure-house, I thought that I ought not to omit any of
          the counsels which I have to give you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And I shall be most grateful to the gods if I am not disappointed in the opinion which I
          have of you. For, while we find that the great majority of other men seek the society of
          those friends who join them in their follies and not of those who admonish them, just as
          they prefer the most pleasant to the most wholesome food,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.42">Isoc. 2.42-45</bibl>.</note> you, I think, are minded
          otherwise, as I judge from the industry you display in your general education. For when
          one sets for himself the highest standard of conduct, it is probable that in his relation
          to others he will approve only of those who exhort him to virtue. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But most of all would you be spurred on to strive for noble deeds if you should realize
          that it is from them most of all that we also derive pleasure in the true sense. For while
          the result of indolence and love of surfeit is that pain follows on the heels of
            pleasure,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 1.16">Isoc. 1.16</bibl>;
              <bibl n="Plat. Phaedo 60b">Plat. Phaedo 60b</bibl></note> on the other hand, devoted
          toil in the pursuit of virtue, and self-control in the ordering of one's life always yield
          delights that are pure and more abiding. In the former case we experience pain following
          upon pleasure, in the latter we enjoy pleasure after pain. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In all our tasks we are not so much mindful of the beginning as we are sensible of the
          end; for we do most things in life not for themselves; it is rather for the sake of what
          results from them that we carry on our labors. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Bear in mind that while the base may be pardoned for acting without principle, since it
          is on such a foundation that from the first their lives have been built, yet the good may
          not neglect virtue without subjecting themselves to rebukes from many quarters; for all
          men despise less those who do wrong than those who have claimed to be respect able and yet
          are in fact no better than the common run; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and rightly, too, for when we condemn those who deceive us in words alone, how, pray, can
          we deny the baseness of those who in their whole lives belie their promise?<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 12.243">Isoc. 12.243</bibl>.</note> We
          should be right in judging that such men not only sin against themselves, but are traitors
          to fortune as well; for fortune places in their hands wealth and reputation and friends,
          but they, for their part, make themselves unworthy of the blessings which lie within their
          grasp. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And if a mortal may make conjecture of the thoughts of the gods, I think that they also
          have revealed very clearly in their treatment of their nearest kin how they are disposed
          to the good and base among men. For Zeus, who, as the myths relate and all men believe,
          was the father of Heracles and Tantalus, made the one immortal because of his virtue, and
          inflicted on the other the severest punishments because of his evil character. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> With these examples before you, you should aspire to nobility of character, and not only
          abide by what I have said, but acquaint yourself with the best things in the poets as
          well, and learn from the other wise men also any useful lessons they have taught.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.13">Isoc. 2.13</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For just as we see the bee settling on all the flowers, and sipping the best from each,
          so also those who aspire to culture ought not to leave anything untasted, but should
          gather useful knowledge from every source.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The figure is
            used by Lucretius in the same sense, <title>De rerum natura</title> iii. 11-12:
            floriferis ut apes in saltibus omnia libant,/omnia nos itidem depascimur aurea
            dicta.</note> For hardly even with these pains can they overcome the defects of
          nature.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
