<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Essays in Portraiture Defended</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1925</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianhar04luciuoft/page/298/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202129?urlappend=%3Bseq=306">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.4.p.299"/>
<head>Essays in Portraiture Defended<note xml:lang="eng"><p>Panthea justifies Lucian’s commendation of her modesty
by finding his praises too high for her and sending the piece
back to Be revised. Lucian could not comply if he would,
for it is already in circulation; so he defends it, and incidentally takes occasion to pay her still higher tribute.</p>

<p>
That Panthea really did object may be taken as certain.
If she had not done so, to say that she had, and to compliment her upon it, would have been an unpardonable affront.</p>

<p>
Nothing could be neater than the casual way in which he
alludes to the essential fact that the dialogue is already out
(c. 14), and hints that the only alternative to a defence of it
is a public recantation (c. 15).</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>


<label>POLYSTRATUS</label>
This is the lady’s reply: “Lycinus, I have discerned, to be sure, from what you have written that
your friendliness and esteem for me is great, for
nobody would bestow such high praise if he were
not writing in a friendly spirit. But my own attitude, please understand, is this. In general, I do
not care for people whose disposition inclines to
flattery, but consider such persons deceivers and not
at all generous in their natures. Above all, in the
matter of compliments, when anyone in praising me
employs vulgar and immoderate extravagances I
blush and almost stop my ears, and the thing seems
to me more like abuse than praise.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
For praise is
endurable only as long as the person who is being
praised recognizes that everything which is said is
appropriate to him, Whatever goes beyond that
is alien, and outright flattery.</p>

<p>
“Yet,” said she, “I know many who like it if, in
praising them, one bestows upon them qualities
which they do not possess; for example, if they are
old, congratulates them upon their youthfulness, or
if they are ugly, clothes them in the beauty of a
Nireus or a Phaon. They think that their appearance will be transformed by these compliments, and

<pb n="v.4.p.301"/>

that they will regain their youth afresh, as Pelias
thought to do.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
That, however, is not the case.
Praise would be highly valuable if it were possible
to derive any actual profit from it through such
extravagant employment. But as it is, those people
in my opinion are in the same case that an ugly
man would be in if someone should officiously put a
handsome mask upon him and he were to pride
himself greatly upon his beauty, regardless of the
fact that it was detachable and could be destroyed
by the first comer, in which event he would look
still more ridiculous when he stood revealed in
his own proper features and showed what ugliness
had been hidden behind that lovely mask. Or it
would be as if someone who was small should put on
the buskins of an actor and try to compete in height
with those who, on an even footing, overtop him by
a full cubit.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
She mentioned an instance in point. She said
that a woman of conspicuous position, who was
pretty and attractive in every other way, but small,
and far beneath the well-proportioned height, was
being lauded in song by a certain poet, not only
on all other grounds, but because she was fair
and tall; he likened her to a black poplar for
goodly stature and straightness! Well, she was
delighted with the compliment, just as if she were
going to grow to match the song, and lifted her
hand in approval. So the poet gave many encores,
seeing that she liked to be praised, until at last one
of the company leaned over to his ear and said:
“Have done with it, man—you might make her
stand up!”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
Something similar and much more comical was

<pb n="v.4.p.303"/>

done, she said, by Stratonice, the wife of Seleucus,
who set a competition for the poets, with a talent as
the prize, to see which of them could best praise
her hair, in spite of the fact that she was bald and
had not even a paltry few hairs of her own. Nevertheless, with her head in that pitiful state, when
everybody knew that a long illness had affected her
in that way, she listened to those rascally poets while
they called her hair hyacinthine, and platted soft
braids of it, and compared to wild parsley what did
not even exist at all!
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
She made fun of all such people as these, who
surrender themselves to flatterers, and she added,
too, that many wish to be similarly flattered and
cozened in portraits as well as in complimentary
speeches. “In fact,” said she, “they delight most
of all in those painters who make the prettiest
pictures of them. And there are some who even
direct the artists to take away a little of the nose,
or paint the eyes blacker, or give them any other
characteristic that they covet; and then, in their
blissful ignorance, they hang wreaths of flowers
upon portraits of other people, not in the least like
themselves!”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
That is about what she had to say; she commended most of the piece, but could not put up
with one feature of it, that you compared her to
goddesses, to Hera and Aphrodite. ‘Such praise,”
she said, “is too high for me; indeed, too high for
human kind. For my part I did not want you to
compare me even to those great ladies, Penelope
and Arete and Theano, let alone the noblest of the
goddesses. Besides, I am very superstitious and

<pb n="v.4.p.305"/>

timorous in all that concerns the gods. Consequently, I am afraid I may be thought to resemble
Cassiopeia<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.305.n.1"><p>The boastful mother of Andromeda, who would have had to surrender her daughter to the sea-monster except fur the timely intervention of Perseus. </p></note> if I accept such praise as yours; and yet
she, as a matter of fact, compared herself only to
the Nereids and was duly reverential toward Hera
and Aphrodite.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
In view of this, Lycinus, she said that you must
rewrite everything of that sort, or else for her part
she calls the goddesses to witness that you wrote it
without her consent, and says you know that the
book will annoy her if it circulates in the form in
which you have now couched it, which is not at all
reverential or pious in its allusions to the gods.
She thought, too, that it would be considered a
sacrilege and a sin on her own part if she should
allow herself to be said to resemble Cnidian Aphrodite, and Our Lady in the Gardens. Moreover, she
wanted to remind you of the remark that you made
about her at the end of the book. You said that
she was modest and free from vanity ; and that she
did not try to soar higher than a human being should,
but made her flight close to the earth. Yet the man
who said that sets the woman above the very stars,
even to the point of likening her to goddesses!
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
She did not want you to think her less intelligent
than Alexander. In his case, when the masterbuilder undertook to remodel the whole of Athos
and shape it into his likeness, so that the entire
mountain would become the image of the king,
holding a city in either hand, Alexander would not
agree to the monstrous proposal. Thinking the
project over-bold for him, he stopped the man from
modelling colossi on a scale that transcended convincingness, bidding him to let Athos alone and not


<pb n="v.4.p.307"/>

to diminish so great a mountain to similarity with a
tiny body. She praised Alexander for his greatness
of soul, and observed that thereby he had erected a
monument greater than Athos itself in the minds of
those who should think of him ever and anon in
time to come: for it took no little determination
to contemn so marvellous an honour.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.307.n.1"><p>The same story is in How to Write History, c. 12, where also the name of the architect is not mentioned. Plutarch says it was Stasicrates (Alea. 72; Moral. 335). In Strabo 14, p. 641, Cheirocrates seems to underlie the various readings. Vitruvius (ii, praef.) tells the tale quite differently and makes Dinocrates the hero of it. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
So it was with her, said she; while she commended your skill in modelling and the idea of the
portraits, she did not recognize the likeness. She
was not worthy of such compliments, not by a great
deal, nor was any other mere woman. Therefore she
absolves you from honouring her thus, and pays her
homage to your patterns and models. You may
praise her in the ordinary, human way, but do not
let the sandal be too large for her foot; “it might
hamper me,” she said, “when I walk about in it.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
Furthermore, she enjoined it upon me to tell you
this. “I hear many say (whether it is true or not,
you men know<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.307.n.2"><p>Women did not attend the Olympic games. </p></note>) that even at the Olympic games
the victors are not allowed to set up statues greater
than life-size, but the Hellanodicae take care that
not one of them shall exceed the truth, and the
scrutiny of the statues is more strict than the examination of the athletes. So be on your guard for
fear we incur the imputation of falsifying in the
matter of height, and then the Hellanodicae overturn our statue.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
That is what she said; and now it is for you,
Lycinus, to see how you can refurbish the book




<pb n="v.4.p.309"/>

and do away with everything of that sort; do not
offend against Heaven! Really, she took it very
ill, shuddered as it was read, and besought the
goddesses to be merciful to her. It is excusable,
too, that she should feel as a woman naturally
would. Indeed, if the truth must out, I myself
had somewhat the same opinion. To be sure, when
I heard it first I did not see a single fault in what
you had written, but now that she has pointed them
out, I myself begin to think as she does about it.
My experience in this matter has been just about
like that of us all when we look at things. If we
see. them too close, under our very eyes, we can
distinguish nothing accurately, but if we stand off
and look at them from the right distance, all the
points come out clearly, those that are good and
also those that are not.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
Truly, to liken a female human being to Aphrodite and to Hera, what else is it but outright
cheapening of the goddesses? In such matters the
less is not made greater by the comparison, but
rather the greater is lessened by being dragged
down to the lower level. If two people were walking together, one of whom was very tall and the
other quite humble in stature, and it should be
needful to equalize them so that the one would not
tower above the other, this could not be accomplished
by the shorter through stretching himself, however
much he were to raise himself on tiptoe. No, if
they are to look alike in size, the latter will stoop
and make himself appear shorter. Just so in such
comparisons ; it is not so true that a man becomes

<pb n="v.4.p.311"/>

greater if he is likened to a god, as that the divine
is inevitably minimized by being forced down to
match what is defective. If it were for lack of
earthly objects of comparison that one let one’s
speech range to those in Heaven, one would be less
open to the charge of acting impiously therein.
But in your case, though you had so many examples
of fair women at command, you made bold to liken
her to Aphrodite and Hera without any need.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
Do away, then, with all this that is excessive and
invidious, Lycinus—that sort of thing is not in
keeping with your character, for you have not as a
rule been ready and quick to praise. Now, however, you have somehow changed all at once and
are lavish with it; you who were so niggardly before
have become a spendthrift in compliments! Do not
be ashamed, either, to reshape the essay after it has
been put into circulation. Even Phidias, they say,
did that when he made the Zeus for the people of
Elis!<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.311.n.1"><p>The chryselephantine statue at Olympia. </p></note> He stood behind the door when he first
unveiled and exhibited his work, and listened to
those who criticized or commended any part. One
would criticize the nose as too thick, another the
face as too long, and so it went. Then, when the
spectators had left, Phidias locked himself up once
more, and corrected and reshaped the statue to suit
the opinion of the majority; for he did not think
that the advice of so many folk was trivial, but that
always of necessity the many could see better than
the one, even if that one were Phidias.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.311.n.2"><p>The story, which is patently apocryphal, occurs nowhere else. Lucian may have heard it from a guide at Olympia. For a similar story regarding Apelles, see Pliny, Nat. Hist. 35, 84-85. </p></note>



<pb n="v.4.p.313"/>

That is what she told me to tell you, and what I
myself recommend as your friend and well-wisher.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
<label>LYCINUS</label>
Polystratus, what an orator you have been all
along without my knowing it! You have delivered
such a long speech and such a weighty indictment
of my essay that you have not left me even a hope
of defence now. But see here! you have not dealt
fairly, the two of you, and especially you, in that
you have condemned the book without a hearing,
since its counsel was not in court. It is easy, I
take it, to win if you run alone, as the saying goes.
So it is no wonder that I was defeated when no
water was measured out for me and no chance to
defend myself offered. Indeed—and this is the
most extraordinary part of it all—you were judges
as well as plaintiffs!
Well, what is your wish? Shall I rest content
with the decision and hold my peace? Or, like the
poet of Himera,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.313.n.1"><p>Stesichorus, who after having maligned Helen, recanted in a palinode (the first), saying that Helen never went to Troy: it was but a wraith! Fable said that he recanted because Helen had struck him blind, and that afterwards he recovered his eyesight. </p></note> shall I compose a palinode? Or
will you give me an opportunity to plead my case on
appeal?
</p>
<p><label>POLYSTRATUS</label>
Yes, indeed, if you have any just plea to offer;
for it is not among opponents in court, as you say,
but among friends that you will make your defence.
For my part, I am even ready to associate myself
with you as joint defendant in the case.



<pb n="v.4.p.315"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
<label>LYCINUS</label>
But it is annoying, Polystratus, that she will not
be present when I make my speech. It would be
far better if she were. As it stands, I must plead
by proxy.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.315.n.1"><p>The phrase ἀπ᾽ ἐντολῆς means “by direction.” Strictly speaking, it is appropriate only to the action of an agent, but here it is transferred to that of the principal. Compare Aristides, vol. ii, p. 22 224-5 Dindorf, τὰ δὲ πλεῖστα ἐξ ἐντολῆς τῷ βασιλεῖ κατειργάζετο. </p></note> But if you are going to be as faithful in
carrying my message to her as you have been in
carrying hers to me, I shall make bold to cast
the die.
</p>
<p><label>POLYSTRATUS</label>
Never fear, Lycinus, as far as that goes! I shan’t
be at all bad, you will find, at delivering your plea,
if only you try to speak briefly, so that I may be
better able to fix it all in memory.
</p>
<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
But I really needed to speak at length in answering so forcible an accusation. Nevertheless, for
your sake I shall cut my plea short. Take, then,
this message from me to her—
</p>
<p><label>POLYSTRATUS</label>
No, no, Lycinus! Make your speech just as if
she herself were present, and then I will do her an
imitation of you.
</p>
<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
Well then, since that is the way you want it,
Polystratus, she is here and as the first speaker,
of course, has said all that you reported as her
messenger; and now it is for me to begin my
answer. However—for I shall not hesitate to tell
you the state of my feelings—somehow or other



<pb n="v.4.p.317"/>

you have made the thing more terrifying to me.
As you see, I am even now in a sweat and a tremble
and almost think I really see her, and the affair has
begotten great turmoil within me. But I will begin,
anyhow, for it isn’t possible to withdraw, with her
already here.
</p>
<p><label>POLYSTRATUS</label>
Yes, and she shows great friendliness in her expression, for she is radiant, as you see, and gracious.
So get on with your speech boldly.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
<label>LYCINUS</label>
Noblest of women, it is true I praised you, as you
say, highly and immoderately; but I do not see
what commendation I bestowed as great as the
encomium which you have pronounced upon yourself in extolling your reverence for the gods.
Really, this is more than all that I said about you,
and you ‘must forgive me that I did not add this trait
to your likeness; it escaped me because I did not
know about it, for there is no other which I should
have preferred to represent. So in that particular
at least I not only did not go beyond bounds, it
seems to me, with my praises, but actually said far
less than I should. Think what an important point
I omitted there—how very significant as evidence of
sterling character and sound judgement! For those
who assiduously reverence what pertains to the gods
will surely be above reproach in their relations with
mankind. So if the speech absolutely must be
revised and the portrait corrected, I should not
venture to take a single thing away from it, but
will add this detail to cap, as it were, and crown
the complete work.

<pb n="v.4.p.319"/>

There is one thing, however, for which I admit
that I am very grateful to you. After I had praised
the reasonableness of your character and the fact
that the present exalted state of your fortunes has
not engendered in you any arrogance or pride, you
confirmed the truth of my praise by censuring what
you did censure in my speech. Not to catch
greedily at such praise, but to blush for it and say
that it is too high for you betokens a reasonable and
unassuming disposition. But the more you manifest
that attitude toward praise itself, the more worth
of extravagant praise you prove yourself! Really
the thing, despite you, has come to a pass where
the remark of Diogenes applies. When he was
asked how one could become famous, he answered :
“If he were to scorn fame!” If I myself should
be asked: “Who are most worthy of praise?” I
should answer: “Those who are unwilling to be
praised !”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>
But all this, no doubt, is apart from the issue and
has nothing to do with the case ; and the charge to
which I must answer is that in making my sketch of
you I likened you in beauty to Cnidian Aphrodite
and Our Lady in the Gardens and Hera and Athena.
That seemed to you extravagant and presumptuous.
I shall address myself precisely to that point.</p>

<p>
It is an ancient saying, however, that poets and
painters are not to be held accountable ;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.319.n.1"><p><cit> <quote>     <l>Pictoribus atque poetis</l>     <l>Quidlibet audendi semper fuit aequa potestas.</l> </quote> <bibl>Horace, Ars Poet. 9 sq.</bibl> </cit> </p></note> still less,
I think, eulogists, even if they fare humbly afoot
like me, instead of being borne on the wings of
song. For praise is an unshackled thing, and has


<pb n="v.4.p.321"/>

ESSAYS IN PORTRAITURE DEFENDED
no limit, whether upper or lower, prescribed for it.
The only object that it ever has in view is to excite
high admiration and to maké its subject enviable.
Nevertheless, I shall not take this course, for fear
you may think that I do so for want of a better.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
This, however, I do say; the conditions that
govern us in these laudatory writings are such that
the eulogist must employ comparisons and similes,
and really the most important part of it is to make
successful comparisons. And success would be most
likely to be held attained, not if a man compares
like to like, or if he makes his comparison with
something that is inferior, but if he approximates, in
so far as he may, what he is praising to something
that surpasses it.</p>

<p>
For example, if in praising a dog someone were
to say that it was larger than a fox or a cat, does
it seem to you that he knows how to praise? You
will not say so! But even if he should say it was as
large as a wolf, he has not praised it generously.
Well, at what point will the special end of praise
be achieved? When the dog is said to resemble
a lion in size and in strength. So the poet who
praised Orion’s dog<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.321.n.1"><p>Pindar, frag. 74a (Schroeder). </p></note> called him “lion-daunting.”’
That, of course, in the case of a dog is perfect
praise.</p>

<p>
Again, if someone who wished to praise Milo of
Croton or Glaucus of Carystus or Polydamas<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.321.n.2"><p>Famous boxers ; see the Index. </p></note> should
say of any one of them that he was stronger than
a woman, do not you suppose that he would be
laughed at for the senselessness of his praise?



<pb n="v.4.p.323"/>

Indeed, if it had been said that he was better than
any single man, that would not have sufficed for
praise. Come, how did a famous poet? praise Glaucus
when he said : “Not even mighty Polydeuces” could
have held up his hands against that man, “nor yet
the iron-hard son of Alemene!” You see what gods
he likened him to—nay, actually avouched him
better than those gods themselves! And it cannot
be said either that Glaucus became indignant when
he was praised in opposition to the gods who are
the overseers of athletes, or that they punished
either Glaucus or the poet as guilty of sacrilege
in the matter of that praise. On the contrary, both
enjoyed good fame and were honoured by the
Greeks, Glaucus for his strength and the poet
especially for this very song!
</p>

<p>
Do not wonder then, that I myself, desiring to
make comparisons, as one who sought to praise
was bound to do, used an exalted counterfoil, since
my theme demanded it.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
Since you mentioned flattery, let me say that I
praise you for hating flatterers; I would not have
it otherwise. But I wish to make a distinction and
a difference for you between the achievement of
one who praises, and its exaggeration on the part of
one who flatters.</p>

<p>
The flatterer, since he praises for a selfish reason
and has little regard for truth, thinks that he must
praise everything to excess, telling falsehoods and
contributing a great deal on his own account, so
that he would not hesitate to declare Thersites had
a better figure than Achilles, and that of all who
took part in the expedition against Troy, Nestor
was the youngest; he would take his oath upon

<pb n="v.4.p.325"/>

it that the son of Croesus had sharper ears than
Melampus,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.325.n.1"><p>The son of Croesus was a deaf-mute (Herod. 1, 34 and 85) ; Melampus the seer could hear worms in the roof talking to each other (Apollodorus 1, 9, 12). </p></note> and Phineus sharper sight than Lynceus,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.325.n.2"><p>Phineus was blind ; Lynceus could see what was underground (Apoll. 3, 10, 3). </p></note> if only he hoped to gain something by the lie.
But the other, in praising the self-same object,
instead of telling any lie or adding any quality
that did not belong to it, would take the good
points that it had by nature, even if they were
not very great, and would amplify them and make
them greater. He would venture to say, when he
wished to praise a horse, which is the lightest of
foot and the best runner of all the animals that
we know.
<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Over the top of the flowers he ran without
bending them downward.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad20, 227, of the horses of Erichthonius, sired by Boreas.</bibl>
</cit>


And again he would not hesitate to speak of

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>the
swiftness of wind-footed horses.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Source unknown, if δρόμον is part of the quotation. But for “wind-footed horses,” see Hymn to Venus217, Pindar, frag. 221.</bibl>
</cit>


 And if he were
to praise a house that was beautiful and handsomely
furnished, he would say:

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Surely like this, inside, is the palace of Zeus on
Olympus.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Odyssey4, 74, said by Telemachus to his friend, admiring
the palace of Menelaus.</bibl>
</cit>

The flatterer, however, would express himself in
that way even about the swineherd’s hut, if only
he hoped to get something from the swineherd!
Take Cynaethus, the toady of Demetrius Poliorcetes ;
when he had used up all his means of flattery, he
praised Demetrius, who was troubled with a cough,
because he cleared his throat melodiously !



<pb n="v.4.p.327"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
That flatterers do not hesitate to lie for the sake
of pleasing the objects of their praise, whereas
those who really praise try to magnify what actually
exists, is not the only distinguishing mark of each.
They differ in a further point, and not a trivial one,
that flatterers use hyperbole to the full extent of
their powers, while those who really praise are
discreet in precisely that particular and remain
within their bounds.</p>

<p>
These are a few out of many earmarks of flattery
and of genuine praise which I give you so that you
may not suspect all who praise you, but may distinguish between them and gauge each by his
proper standard.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
Come then, apply, if you will, both canons to my
words, that you may discover whether they conform
to this one or the other. If it had been some ugly
woman whom I likened to the statue in Cnidos, I
might indeed be accounted a liar, and a worse
flatterer than Cynaethus. But since it was one
whose beauty is known to all, the venture was not
a salto mortale.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
Perhaps, then, you may say—indeed, you have
already said—that you concede my right to praise
you for your beauty, but that I should have made
my praise unexceptionable and should not have
compared a mortal woman with goddesses. As a
matter of fact (now she is going to make me speak
the truth!) it was not with goddesses I compared
you, my dear woman, but with masterpieces of good
craftsmen, made of stone or bronze or ivory; and
what man has made, it is not impious, I take it,


<pb n="v.4.p.329"/>

to compare with man. But perhaps you have
assumed that what Phidias fashioned is Athena,
and that what Praxiteles made in Cnidus not many
years ago is Heavenly Aphrodite ? Come now, would
it not be unworthy to hold such beliefs about the
gods, whose real images I for my part assume to
be unattainable by human mimicry ?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>
But if I had actually compared you, as much as
you will, with the very goddesses themselves, I
should not have been doing it on my own responsibility and should not have been the first to open
this road. No, there have been many good poets
ahead of me, and above all your fellow-citizen
Homer, whom I shall now call up to plead for me,
or else there is nothing for it but that he himself
will be convicted along with me!</p>

<p>
I shall therefore ask him, or, better, ask you in
his stead, since you know by heart—and it is greatly
to your credit—all the prettiest of the verses that
he composed, what you think of him when he says
of Briseis, the captive, that as she mourned for
Patroclus she resembled golden Aphrodite?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.329.n.1"><p>Iliad19, 282. </p></note> Then
after a bit, as if it were not enough that she should
be like Aphrodite only, he says :

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Then made answer, in tears, the maid as fair as
a goddess.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iiad19, 286</bibl>
</cit>

When he says that sort of thing, do you loathe him
and fling away the book, or do you permit him to
enjoy full freedom in his praise? Well, even if you
refuse permission, at all events Time in his long
flight has given it, and nobody has found fault with
Homer on that score, neither the man who made


<pb n="v.4.p.331"/>

bold to flog his statue nor the man who marked the
spurious lines by setting daggers beside them.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.331.n.1"><p>Respectively Zoilus the Homeromastix and Aristarchus of Alexandria, the grammarian. </p></note></p>

<p>
Then if he is to be permitted to compare a foreign
woman, and in tears at that, with golden Aphrodite,
for my part, not to speak of your beauty because
you will not listen, may not I compare with images
of the gods a radiant woman, usually smiling, a
trait which men have in common with the gods?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
In the case of Agamemnon, moreover, see how
parsimonious Homer was with the gods, and with
what propriety he doled out his comparisons! He
says that in eyes and head he was like to Zeus, in
waist to Ares, and in chest to Poseidon,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.331.n.2"><p>Iliad 2, 478-479. </p></note> dismembering the man for the sake of comparing
him with all those gods. Again, he says that
someone is a match for devastating Ares ;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.331.n.3"><p>Notably Hector, Iliad 11, 295; 13, 802. </p></note> and just
so with the rest of them—the Phrygian, the son
of Priam, is beautiful as a god,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.331.n.4"><p>Paris, Iliad 3, 16. </p></note> and the son of
Peleus is often godlike.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.331.n.5"><p>Achilles, Iliad 1, 131. </p></note>
But I will return to the parallels that concern
women. You know, naturally, that he says:

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Artemis she resembleth, or else Aphrodite the
golden,</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Odyssey17, 37 (19, 54), of Penelope.</bibl>
</cit>


also,

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Just so Artemis runneth adown the slope of a
mountain.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Odyssey6, 102, of Nausicaa.</bibl>
</cit>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
Moreover, he not only compares human beings
with gods, but likens the long hair of Euphorbus to






<pb n="v.4.p.333"/>

the Graces, and that too when it was soaked with
blood! In short, this sort of thing is so frequent
that there is no part of his poetry which is not well
adorned with comparisons of gods. Therefore you
must either expunge all that, or permit us to be
equally venturesome. So exempt from all accountability is the use of comparisons and similes that
Homer actually did not hesitate to derive praise for
the goddesses from things of lower degree. For
instance, he likened Hera’s eyes to those of kine.
And someone else called Aphrodite violet-browed.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.333.n.1"><p>The “Theban poet” of the preceding piece (p.271); i.e. Pindar. </p></note>
As for “rosy-fingered,” who that has even the
slightest acquaintance with Homer’s poetry does
not know it?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>
As far as personal appearance is concerned, it
signifies comparatively little if one is said to be
like a god. But how many there are who have
copied the very names of the gods, calling themselves Dionysius, Hephaestion, Zeno, Poseidonius,
Hermes! And there was a Leto, the wife of
Evagoras, king of Cyprus ; yet the goddess did not
take on about it, though she might have turned her
into stone as she did Niobe. The Egyptians I forbear to mention, who, though the most superstitious
people in the world, yet use the names of the gods
to their hearts’ content ; in fact, most of their names
are derived from Heaven.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>
It is not incumbent upon you, then, to be thus
timorous in respect of praise. If any offence at all
has been perpetrated against divinity in that essay,
you are not accountable for it—unless you think
that to listen makes one accountable ; it is I whom


<pb n="v.4.p.335"/>

the gods will punish, after first punishing Homer
and the other poets! But to this day they have
not punished the best of the philosophers for saying
that man was God’s image !<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.335.n.1"><p>Hardly Plato, though he has something similar in the Republic, 501. But to him the universe is God’s image ; see the end of the Timaeus. Perhaps Lucian means Diogenes, who said that good men were images of gods (Diog. Laert. 6, 51). </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg040.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>
Although I might say much more to you, I shall
stop for the sake of Polystratus here, so that he may
be able to repeat from memory what has been said.
</p>
<p><label>POLYSTRATUS</label>
I don’t know if that is any longer possible for me,
Lycinus. Even as it is, you have made a long
speech, far beyond your allowance of water. But
I shall try to remember it all the same ; and, as you
see, I am already making off to her with my ears
stopped for fear that something else may pop in
to confuse its outline, and then I may have the bad
luck to be hissed by my hearers!
</p>
<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
That is your concern, Polystratus, to act your part
to the best advantage. As for me, now that I have
once for all put the play into your hands, I shall
withdraw for the present; but when they announce
the votes of the judges, I shall be there in person to
see what will be the outcome of the contest.



</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>

