<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Fortune or the Virtue of Alexander I and II</title>
				<author>Plutarch</author>
				<editor role="translator">Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
					<name>Bridget Almas</name>
					<name>Angelia Hanhardt</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
				<date type="release">2010-12-13</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Plutarch</author>
						<title xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>
						<respStmt>
							<resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
							<name role="translator">Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
						</respStmt>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
							<publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date type="printing">1936</date>
						</imprint>
						<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
					</monogr>
					<ref target="https://archive.org/details/moraliainfifteen04plutuoft/page/378"
						>The Internet Archive</ref>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<quotation marks="none"/>
				<correction status="high" method="silent">
					<p>optical character recognition</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>
			<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
			<p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the
				CTS/CITE Architecture</p>
			<refsDecl n="CTS">
				<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
					replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts sections</p>
				</cRefPattern>
				<cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+)"
					replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts chapters</p>
				</cRefPattern>
				<!-- <state unit="section"/> -->
			</refsDecl>
			<!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>-->
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="eng">English</language>
				<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
				<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change who="RS" when="2010-05">tagged and parsed</change>
			<change who="1ucyP" when="2019-07-05">EpiDoc and CTS Conversion</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="eng">
		<body>
			
<div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg087.perseus-eng3"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="intro"><pb xml:id="v.4.p.380"/> 
	<head>ON THE FORTUNE OR THE VIRTUE OF ALEXANDER (<foreign xml:lang="lat">DE ALEXANDRI MAGNI FORTUNA AUT VIRTUTE</foreign>) I AND II</head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"> <head>INTRODUCTION</head><p rend="indent"> Again we have epideictic orations similar to the preceding and the following essays, and the conclusion again is abrupt, as if the speaker had been obliged to stop after a certain period of time had elapsed. Note, however, the very considerable difference in length between the first and the second part of the present work. </p><p rend="indent">We know nothing of the circumstances under which these orations were delivered, but it is quite possible that they were spoken at Rome to show the Romans what an educated Greek could do in the treatment of a controversial subject. </p><p rend="indent">The first oration deals mainly with the manner in which Fortune used Alexander; but much is also said of the manner in which he met the buffetings of Fortune and rose superior to them. In the second oration Fortune is by no means neglected, but rather more is said of Alexander’s Virtue; thus it is not surprising to find in Lamprias’s list of Plutarch’s works two entries: the first, No. 176, <title rend="italic" >Alexander’s Fortune</title> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">Περὶ τῆς Ἀλεξάνδρου τύχης </foreign>) and the second, No. 186, <title rend="italic">Alexander’s Virtue</title> (<foreign xml:lang="grc" >Περὶ τῆς Ἀλεξάνδρου άρετῆς</foreign>). </p><p rend="indent">Much that is included here is found also in Plutarch’s <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, in Arrian’s <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, and in other writers cited in the notes. <pb xml:id="v.4.p.381"/> </p><p rend="indent">The genuineness of the tradition which ascribes these works to Plutarch (for the attribution had been attacked by A. Schäfer and by L. Weber) has been brilliantly vindicated by W. Nachstädt in his dissertation, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">De Plutarchi Declamationibus quae sunt De Alexandri Fortuna (Berliner Beiträge für klassischen Philologie</title>, ii.), Karl Vogt, Berlin, 1895. This excellent work also contains a discussion of many of the problems which confront the editor of these essays and has been of great service. </p> </div> </div> <pb xml:id="v.4.p.383"/> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">This is Fortune’s discourse, who declares that Alexander is her own characteristic handiwork, and hers alone. But some rejoinder must be made on behalf of philosophy, or rather on Alexander’s behalf, who would be vexed and indignant if he should be thought to have received as a pure gift, even at the hands of Fortune, the supremacy which he won at the price of much blood and of wounds that followed one after another; and <quote rend="blockquote"> <l>Many a night did he spend without sleeping, </l> <l>Many a blood-stained day did he pass amid combats unceasing,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Adapted from Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title> ix. 325-326.</note> </l> </quote> against irresistible forces and innumerable tribes, against impassable rivers and mountain fastnesses whose summit no arrow could reach, furthered by wise counsels, steadfast purpose, manly courage, and a prudent heart. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p rend="indent">I think that if Fortune should try to inscribe her name on his successes, he would say to her, <q>Slander not my virtues, nor take away my fair fame by detraction. Darius was your handiwork: he who was <pb xml:id="v.4.p.385"/> a slave and courier of the king,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 340 c, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xviii. (674 d). Aelian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Varia Historia</title>, xii. 43, says that he was a slave; and Strabo, xv. 3. 24, Diodorus, xvii. 5, say that he was not of the royal family.</note> him did you make the mighty lord of Persia; and Sardar Lapalus, upon whose head you placed the royal diadem, though he spent his days in carding purple wool.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 336 c, <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra</foreign>.</note> But I, through my victory at Arbela,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">331 b.c.</note> went up to Susa, and Cilicia<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The battle of Issus, 333 b.c.</note> opened the way for me into the broad land of Egypt; but to Cilicia I came by way of the Granicus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">334 b.c.</note> which I crossed, using as a bridge the dead bodies of Mithridates and Spithridates. Adorn yourself, proud Fortune, and vaunt your dominion over kings that never felt a wound nor shed a drop of blood. For they have been Fortune’s favourites, men such as Ochus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true" >Artaxerxes III. (358-338 b.c.).</note> was and Artaxerses, whom at the very hour of their birth you placed upon the throne of Cyrus. But my body bears many a token of an opposing Fortune and no ally of mine. First, among the Illyrians,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">This wound is elsewhere unknown to history. For the wounds of Alexander see the excellent tables of Nachstädt, <emph>op. cit.</emph> pp. 38-44.</note> my head was wounded by a stone and my neck by a cudgel. Then at the Granicus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 341 a-c, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xvi. (673 a); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, i. 15. 7; Diodorus, xvii. 20.</note> my head was cut open by an enemy’s dagger, at Issus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">By Darius, according to Chares (341 c, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xx. (675 f)); but this is unknown to Arrian, Diodorus, Curtius, and Justin.</note> my thigh was pierced by the sword. Next at Gaza<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The text is probably corrupt; in Curtius, iv. 6, we hear of two wounds, and they are quite different ones. One wound is reported in 341 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xxv. (679 b); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, ii. 27. 2.</note> my ankle was wounded by an arrow, my shoulder was dislocated, and I whirled heavily round and round. Then at Maracandaf<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 341 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>; Arrian, <title rend="italic" >Anabasis</title>, iii. 30. 11; Curitus, vii. 6.</note> the bone of my leg was split open by an arrow. There awaited me towards the last also the buffetings I received among the Indians and the <pb xml:id="v.4.p.387"/> violence of famines.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxvi. (702 a-b); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, vi. 24-25.</note> Among the Aspasians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf. Ibid.</foreign>, iv. 23. 3; Curitus, viii. 3.</note> my shoulder was wounded by an arrow, and among the Gandridae<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true" >Nothing is known of this wound.</note> my leg. Among the Mallians,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 341 c, 343 e ff., <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra</foreign>; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxiii. (700 b ff.); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, vi. 9, 10; Diodorus, xvii. 98; Curtius, ix. 4, 5; Strabo, xv. 1. 33.</note> the shaft of an arrow sank deep into my breast and buried its steel; and I was struck in the neck by a cudgel, when the scaling-ladders which we had moved up to the walls were battered down; and Fortune cooped me up alone, favouring ignoble barbarians and not illustrious adversaries with such an exploit. But if Ptolemy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Peucestas in <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, and in Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>.</note> had not held his shield above me, and Limnaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Leonnatus according to Arrian (<title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, vi. 10. 2).</note> taking his stand before me had not fallen, a target for ten thousand shafts, and if my Macedonians had not overthrown the wall with spirit and main force, then that nameless village in a foreign land must needs have become the tomb of Alexander.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p rend="indent">Moreover, there were the trials of the campaign itself: storms, droughts, deep rivers, the heights of the Birdless Rock,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 181 c; Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, iv. 28; Diodorus, xvii. 85. Sir Aurel Stein has identified Aornos with the plateau of Pir-s’ar (<title rend="italic">On Alexander’s Track to the Indus</title>, Macmillan, 1929).</note> the monstrous shapes of savage beasts, an uncivilized manner of life, the constant succession of petty kings and their repeated treachery. Then there were also the difficulties before his expedition:<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xi. (670 b).</note> Greece was still gasping over Philip’s wars; Thebes, staggering to her feet after her fall, was shaking the dust of Chaeroneia from her arms, and Athens was stretching forth a helping hand to join with Thebes. All Macedonia was festering with revolt and looking toward Amyntas and the children <pb xml:id="v.4.p.389"/> of Aëropus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Very little is known of this faction. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diodorus, xiv. 37 and 89. Amyntas later joined Darius and met his death soon after the battle of Issus.</note>; the Illyrians were again rebelling, and trouble with the Scythians was impending for their Macedonian neighbours, who were in the throes of political change; Persian gold flowed freely through the hands of the popular leaders everywhere, and helped to rouse the Peloponnesus; Philip’s treasuries were bare of money, and in addition there was owing a loan of two hundred talents<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">£40,000 or $200,000.</note> (as Onesicritus records). In such poverty<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">For the varying accounts of the wealth and forces of Alexander <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 342 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra</foreign>; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xv. (672 a); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, i. 11. 3; and Alexander’s own account, according to Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, vii. 9. 6 ff.</note> and in circumstances fraught with such uncertainty, a stripling, scarcely older than a boy, had the daring to hope for Babylon and Susa; nay more, to conceive the project of dominion over all the world, relying only on the thirty thousand foot and four thousand cavalry which were his; for, according to Aristobulus, that was the full extent of their number. But King Ptolemy puts them at thirty thousand foot and five thousand horse, Anaximenes at forty-three thousand foot, fifty-five hundred horse. And the great and glorious war-chest which Fortune had ready for him was only seventy talents,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">£14,000 or $70,000.</note> as Aristobulus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 342 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> says, though Duris<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Müller, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Frag. Hist. Graec.</title> ii. p. 472.</note> says it was provision for only thirty days. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p rend="indent">Was, then, Alexander ill-advised and precipitate in setting forth with such humble resources to acquire so vast an empire? By no means. For who has ever put forth with greater or fairer equipment than he: greatness of soul, keen intelligence, selfrestraint, and manly courage, with which Philosophy <pb xml:id="v.4.p.391"/> herself provided him for his campaign? Yes, the equipment that he had from Aristotle his teacher when he crossed over into Asia was more than what he had from his father Philip. But although we believe those who record that Alexander once said that the <title rend="italic">Iliad</title> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chaps. viii. (p. 668 d) and xxvi. (679 c-d); Pliny, <title rend="italic">Natural History</title>, vii. 29. 108.</note> and the <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title> accompanied him as equipment for his campaigns, since we hold Homer in reverence, yet are we to contemn anyone who asserts that the works of Homer accompanied him as a consolation after toil and as a pastime for sweet hours of leisure, but that his true equipment was philosophic teaching, and treatises on Fearlessness and Courage, and Self-restraint also, and Greatness of Soul? For of course it is obvious that Alexander wrote nothing on the subject of either syllogisms or axioms, nor did he have the opportunity of sharing the walks in the Lyceum,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">That is, of occupying himself with Peripatetic (Aristotelian) philosophy.</note> or of discussing propositions in the Academy. For it is by these criteria that those define philosophy who regard it as a theoretical rather than a practical pursuit. And yet even Pythagoras wrote nothing at all, nor did Socrates, nor Arcesilaus, nor Carneades, who were all most notable among philosophers. Nor were these philosophers continuously occupied with such tremendous wars, nor with spreading civilization among foreign princes, nor in establishing Grecian cities among savage nations, nor did they go on and on, instructing lawless and ignorant tribes in the principles of law and peace; but, even though they had leisure, they relinquished the writing of philosophy to sophists. Whence, then, comes our belief that they were true philosophers? Surely from what they said, or from the <pb xml:id="v.4.p.393"/> manner of life which they led, or from the principles which they taught. By these criteria let Alexander also be judged! For from his words, from his deeds, and from the instruction which he imparted, it will be seen that he was indeed a philosopher. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p rend="indent">And first, if you will, consider a matter entirely contrary to the general belief, and compare Alexander’s pupils with those of Plato and Socrates. Plato and Socrates taught pupils of splendid natural endowment who spoke the same language; so that, even if the pupils understood nothing else, at least they understood the Greek tongue. And even so, Plato and Socrates did not win over many. But their pupils, such as Critias and Alcibiades and Cleitophon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">It is interesting to note that dialogues bearing the names of all these pupils have been handed down to us under the name of Plato, although some of them are thought to be spurious.</note> were prone to spew the good word forth, as a horse the curbing bit, and turned them to other ways. </p><p rend="indent">But if you examine the results of Alexander’s instruction, you will see that he educated the Hyrcanians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Wyttenbach in sadness doubts whether these ethnological remarks are the fruit of any research on the part of Plutarch. But they probably derive from a hazy recollection of such passages as Herodotus, i. 216 (of the Massagetae). Note, however, that Strabo supports Plutarch on this custom of the Persians (xv. 3. 20), which is easily explained by the fact that the young king inherited his father’s harem as well as his father’s stable, and that the father’s younger wives furnished the beginning of the son’s harem. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> also Sophocles, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Trachiniae</title>, 1221-1251. For other pleasant customs of the Hyrcanians <foreign xml:lang="lat" >Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" >Moralia</title>, 499 d.</note> to respect the marriage bond, and taught the Arachosians to till the soil, and persuaded the Sogdians to support their parents, not to kill them, and the Persians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Wyttenbach in sadness doubts whether these ethnological remarks are the fruit of any research on the part of Plutarch. But they probably derive from a hazy recollection of such passages as Herodotus, i. 216 (of the Massagetae). Note, however, that Strabo supports Plutarch on this custom of the Persians (xv. 3. 20), which is easily explained by the fact that the young king inherited his father’s harem as well as his father’s stable, and that the father’s younger wives furnished the beginning of the son’s harem. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> also Sophocles, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" >Trachiniae</title>, 1221-1251. For other pleasant customs of the Hyrcanians <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 499 d.</note> to revere their mothers and not to take them in wedlock. O wondrous power of Philosophic Instruction, that brought the Indians to worship Greek gods, and the Scythians to bury their dead, not to devour them! We admire Carneades’ power, which made Cleitomachus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diogenes Laertius, iv. 67; Athenaeus, 402 c.</note> formerly called Hasdrubal, and a Carthaginian by birth, adopt Greek ways. We admire the character of Zeno, which <pb xml:id="v.4.p.395"/> persuaded Diogenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Diogenes, from Seleucia in Mesopotamia (Strabo, xvi. 1. 16; Diogenes Laertius, vi. 81), was said to have been a pupil of Chrysippus, and thus was converted to the inheritance of Zeno, Stoicism.</note> the Babylonian to be a philosopher. But when Alexander was civilizing Asia, Homer was commonly read, and the children of the Persians, of the Susianians, and of the Gedrosians learned to chant, the tragedies of Sophocles and Euripides.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. viii. (p. 668 e).</note> And although Socrates, when tried on the charge of introducing foreign deities,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Plato, <title rend="italic" >Apology</title>, 24 b; Xenophon, <title rend="italic" >Memorabilia</title>, i. 1. 1.</note> lost his cause to the informers who infested Athens, yet through Alexander Bactria and the Caucasus learned to revere the gods of the Greeks. Plato wrote a book on the One Ideal Constitution, but because of its forbidding character he could not persuade anyone to adopt it; but Alexander established more than seventy cities among savage tribes, and sowed all Asia with Grecian magistracies, and thus overcame its uncivilized and brutish manner of living. Although few of us read Plato’s <title rend="italic" >Laws</title>, yet hundreds of thousands have made use of Alexander’s laws, and continue to use them. Those who were vanquished by Alexander are happier than those who escaped his hand; for these had no one to put an end to the wretchedness of their existence, while the victor compelled those others to lead a happy life. Therefore it is even more just to apply Themistocles’ saying<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 185 f, and the note there.</note> to the nations conquered by Alexander. For, when Themistocles in exile had obtained great gifts from Artaxerxes, and had received three cities to pay him tribute, one to supply his bread, another his wine, and a third his meat, he exclaimed, <q>My children, we should be ruined now, had we not been ruined before.</q> Thus Alexander’s new subjects would not have been civilized, had they not been vanquished; Egypt <pb xml:id="v.4.p.397"/> would not have its Alexandria, nor Mesopotamia its Seleuceia, nor Sogdiana its Prophthasia, nor India its Bucephalia, nor the Caucasus a Greek city<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Alexandria-in-the-Caucasus: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, iii. 28. 4; iv. 22. 4; v. 1. 5; Curtius, vii. 3. 23; Diodorus, xvii. 83. 1.</note> hard by; for by the founding of cities in these places savagery was extinguished and the worse element, gaining familiarity with the better, changed under its influence. If, then, philosophers take the greatest pride in civilizing and rendering adaptable the intractable and untutored elements in human character, and if Alexander has been shown to have changed the savage natures of countless tribes, it is with good reason that he should be regarded as a very great philosopher. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p rend="indent">Moreover, the much-admired <title rend="italic">Republic</title> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title rend="italic"> Cambridge Ancient History</title>, vol. vii. p. 225; <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 653 e; <title rend="italic">Life of Lycurgus</title>, xxxi. (59 a); Cicero, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">De Legibus</title>, i. 7-11 (21-32): <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">De Officiis</title>, i. 7 (22); Diogenes Laertius, vii. 32-34, 121, 129, 131.</note> of Zeno, the founder of the Stoic sect, may be summed up in this one main principle: that all the inhabitants of this world of ours should not live differentiated by their respective rules of justice into separate cities and communities, but that we should consider all men to be of one community and one polity, and that we should have a common life and an order common to us all, even as a herd that feeds together and shares the pasturage of a common field. This Zeno wrote, giving shape to a dream or, as it were, shadowy picture of a well-ordered and philosophic commonwealth; but it was Alexander who gave effect to the idea. For Alexander did not follow Aristotle’s<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Aristotle’s name is not elsewhere linked with this advice; <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> Strabo, i. 4. 9 (p. 66), or Aristotle, Frag. 658 (ed. V. Rose).</note> advice to treat the Greeks as if he were their leader, and other peoples as if he were their master; to have regard for the Greeks as for friends and kindred, but <pb xml:id="v.4.p.399"/> to conduct himself toward other peoples as though they were plants or animals; for to do so would have been to cumber his leadership with numerous battles and banishments and festering seditions. But, as he believed that he carne as a heaven-sent governor to all, and as a mediator for the whole world, those whom he could not persuade to unite with him, he conquered by force of arms, and he brought together into one body all men everywhere, uniting and mixing in one great loving-cup, as it were, men’s lives, their characters, their marriages, their very habits of life.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title rend="italic" >Anabasis</title>, vii. 11. 8-9.</note> He bade them all consider as their fatherland the whole inhabited earth, as their stronghold and protection his camp, as akin to them all good men, and as foreigners only the wicked; they should not distinguish between Grecian and foreigner by Grecian cloak and targe, or scimitar and jacket; but the distinguishing mark of the Grecian should be seen in virtue, and that of the foreigner in iniquity; clothing and food, marriage and manner of life they should regard as common to all, being blended into one by ties of blood and children. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p rend="indent">Now Demaratus the Corinthian, one of Philip’s intimate friends,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 70 c; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. ix. (669 c).</note> when he had seen Alexander in Susa, exclaimed with tears of joy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Ibid.</foreign> chaps. xxxvii. (687 a), lvi. (696 f); <title rend="italic">Life of Agesilaüs</title>, chap. xv. (604 a). </note> that all the Greeks who had died before that hour had been deprived of a great joy, since they had not seen Alexander seated on the throne of Darius. But I swear that for my part I feel no envy because of this spectacle toward them that saw it, for it was but the <pb xml:id="v.4.p.401"/> handiwork of Fortune, and the lot of other kings as well. But methinks I would gladly have been a witness of that fair and holy marriage-rite, when he brought together in one golden-canopied tent an hundred Persian brides and an hundred Macedonian and Greek bridegrooms, united at a common hearth and board.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxx. (703 e); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, vii. 4; Diodorus, xvii. 107. 6; Athenaeus, 538 b-e; Aelian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" >Varia Historia</title>, viii. 7; but the number is not elsewhere given as 100.</note> He himself, crowned with garlands, was the first to raise the marriage hymn as though he were singing a song of truest friendship over the union of the two greatest and most mighty peoples; for he, of one maid the bridegroom, and at the same time of all the brides the escort, as a father and sponsor united them in the bonds of wedlock. Indeed at this sight I should have cried out for joy, <q>O dullard Xerxes, stupid fool that spent so much fruitless toil to bridge the Hellespont! This is the way that wise kings join Asia with Europe; it is not by beams nor rafts, nor by lifeless and unfeeling bonds, but by the ties of lawful love and chaste nuptials and mutual joy in children that they join the nations together.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p rend="indent">Considering carefully this order of affairs, Alexander did not favour the Median raiment, but preferred the Persian, for it was much more simple than the Median. Since he deprecated the unusual and theatrical varieties of foreign adornment, such as the tiara and the full-sleeved jacket and trousers, he wore a composite dress adapted from both Persian and Macedonian fashion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xlv. (690 e-691 a); Diodorus, xvii. 77.</note> as Eratosthenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Presumably in the treatise referred to by Strabo, i. 4. 9 (p. 66).</note> has recorded. As a philosopher what he wore was <pb xml:id="v.4.p.403"/> a matter of indifference, but as sovereign of both nations and benevolent king he strove to acquire the goodwill of the conquered by showing respect for their apparel, so that they might continue constant in loving the Macedonians as rulers, and might not feel hate toward them as enemies. Conversely it were the mark of an unwise and vainglorious mind to admire greatly a cloak of uniform colour and to be displeased by a tunic with a purple border, or again to disdain those things and to be struck with admiration for these, holding stubbornly, in the manner of an unreasoning child, to the raiment in which the custom of his country, like a nurse, had attired him. When men hunt wild animals, they put on the skins of deer, and when they go to catch birds, they dress in tunics adorned with plumes and feathers; they are careful not to be seen by bulls when they have on red garments, nor by elephants when dressed in white;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 144 d.</note> for these animals are provoked and made savage by the sight of these particular colours. But if a great king, in taming and mollifying headstrong and warring nations, just as in dealing with animals, succeeded in soothing and stilling them by wearing a garb familiar to them and by following their wonted manner of life, thereby conciliating their rough natures and smoothing their sullen brows, can men impeach him? Must they not rather wonder at his wisdom, since by but a slight alteration of his apparel he made himself the popular leader of all Asia, conquering their bodies by his arms, but winning over their souls by his apparel? And yet men marvel at the disciple of Socrates, Aristippus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Horace, <title rend="italic" >Epistles</title>, i. 17. 23-29 <q> <foreign xml:lang="lat">personamque feret non inconcinnus utramque</foreign>.</q> </note> that whether he wore a threadbare <pb xml:id="v.4.p.405"/> cloak or a fine Milesian robe he retained his gentility in either; but they impeach Alexander because, although paying due respect to his own national dress, he did not disdain that of his conquered subjects in establishing the beginnings of a vast empire. For he did not overrun Asia like a robber nor was he minded to tear and rend it, as if it were booty and plunder bestowed by unexpected good fortune, after the manner in which Hannibal later descended upon Italy, or as earlier the Treres<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Strabo, i. 3. 21; xi. 8. 4.</note> descended upon Ionia and the Scythians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Herodotus, i. 15, 103-106.</note> upon Media. But Alexander desired to render all upon earth subject to one law of reason and one form of government and to reveal all men as one people, and to this purpose he made himself conform. But if the deity that sent down Alexander’s soul into this world of ours had not recalled him quickly, one law would govern all mankind, and they all would look toward one rule of justice as though toward a common source of light. But as it is, that part of the world which has not looked upon Alexander has remained without sunlight. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p rend="indent">Therefore, in the first place, the very plan and design of Alexander’s expedition commends the man as a philosopher in his purpose not to win for himself luxury and extravagant living, but to win for all men concord and peace and community of interests. </p><p rend="indent">And, in the second place, let us examine his sayings too, since it is by their utterances<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 172 d.</note> that the souls of other kings and potentates also best reveal their characters. The elder Antigonus remarked to a certain sophist who put in his hands a treatise on <pb xml:id="v.4.p.407"/> justice, <q>You are a fool to say anything about justice when you see me smiting other peoples cities.</q> The despot Dionysius remarked that one should trick children with dice, but men with oaths.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Attributed elsewhere to Lysander: <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic"> Moralia</title>, 229 b, and the note (Vol. III. p. 373).</note> Upon the tomb of Sardanapalus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign><title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">. Palatine Anthology</title>, vii. 325; xvi. 27: a full list of citations portraying Sardanapalus in ancient popular philosophy is given by W. Capelle, <title rend="italic" >Hermes</title>, lx. p. 394; see also W. Headlam, <title rend="italic">Journal of Philosophy</title>, xxvi. p. 98.</note> is written. <quote rend="blockquote">These are still mine - what I ate, and my wanton love - frolics.</quote> Who would not own that by these several sayings are revealed Sardanapalus’s love of pleasure, Dionysius’s impiety, and Antigonus’s injustice and greed? But if you subtract from Alexander’s sayings his crown, his relationship with Ammon, and his noble birth, they will appear to you as the utterances of a Socrates or a Plato or a Pythagoras. Let us, then, pay no heed to the proud boasts which the poets inscribed upon his portraits and statues, studying, as they were, to portray, not Alexander’s moderation, but his power: <quote rend="blockquote"> <l>Eager to speak seems the statue of bronze, up to Zeus as </l> <l>it gazes: <q>Earth I have set under foot; Zeus, keep Olympus yourself.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 335 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra</foreign>; T. Preger, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Inscriptiones Graecae Metricae</title> (1891), pp. 183-187. The epigram is more completely given in the <title rend="italic" >Anthology</title>, xvi. 120, where it is attributed to Archelaüs or Asclepiades. Probably, as Ouvre has seen, it belongs to the latter.</note> </l> </quote> And another man makes Alexander say, <q>I am the son of Zeus.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xxvii. (680 f).</note> These expressions, then, as I have said, the poets addressed to Alexander in flattery of his good fortune. </p><p rend="indent">But of the genuine sayings of Alexander we might first review those of his youth. Since he was the swiftest of foot of all the young men of his age,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 179 d; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. iv. (666 d).</note> his <pb xml:id="v.4.p.409"/> comrades urged him to enter the Olympic games. He asked if the competitors were kings, and when his friends replied that they were not, he said that the contest was unfair, for it was one in which a victory would be over commoners, but a defeat would be the defeat of a king. </p><p rend="indent">When the thigh of his father Philip had been pierced by a spear in battle with the Triballians, and Philip, although he escaped with his life, was vexed with his lameness, Alexander said, <q>Be of good cheer, father, and go on your way rejoicing, that at each step you may recall your valour.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Attributed to a Spartan woman in <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" >Moralia</title>, 241 e, where see the note.</note> Are not these the words of a truly philosophic spirit which, because of its rapture for noble things, already revolts against mere physical encumbrances? How, then, think you, did he glory in his own wounds, remembering by each part of his body affected a nation overcome, a victory won, the capture of cities, the surrender of kings? He did not cover over nor hide his scars, but bore them with him openly as symbolic representations, graven on his body, of virtue and manly courage. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p rend="indent">And in the same spirit if ever there chanced to be in hours of ease or at a banquet a comparison of the verses of Homer, each man choosing his favourite line, Alexander always judged this verse to be the greatest of all: <quote rend="blockquote">Both things is he: both a goodly king and a warrior mighty.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, iii. 179; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Xenophon, <title rend="italic" >Memorabilia</title>, iii. 2. 2.</note> </quote> This praise, which at the time it was written another had received, Alexander conceived to be a law for himself, so that he said of Homer that in this same verse he had honoured the manly courage of Agamemnon <pb xml:id="v.4.p.411"/> and prophesied that of Alexander. Accordingly when he had crossed the Hellespont, he went to see the site of Troy,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xv. (672 b); Aelian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Varia Historia</title>, ix. 38.</note> imagining to himself the heroic deeds enacted there; and when one of the natives of the country promised to give him the lyre of Paris, if he wished it, Alexander said, <q>Of his lyre I have no need; for I already possess Achilles’ lyre to the accompaniment of which, as he rested from his labours, <quote rend="blockquote">he sang the famed deeds of heroes.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title> ix. 189.</note> </quote> But the lyre of Paris gave forth an altogether weak and womanish strain to accompany his love songs.</q> Thus it is the mark of a truly philosophic soul to be in love with wisdom and to admire wise men most of all, and this was more characteristic of Alexander than of any other king. His attitude toward Aristotle has already been stated<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">327 f, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>; <foreign xml:lang="lat" >Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chaps. vii., viii. (668 a-f).</note>; and it is recorded by several authors that he considered the musician Anaxarchus the most valuable of all his friends, that he gave ten thousand gold pieces to Pyrrhon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Sextus Empiricus, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Adversus Mathematicos</title>, i. 282.</note> of Elis the first time he met him, that he sent to Xenocrates,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 333 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>, and <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" >Moralia</title>, 181 e.</note> the friend of Plato, fifty talents as a gift, and that he made Onesicritus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xiv. (671 d); Diogenes Laertius, vi. 32; Valerius Maximus, iv. 3. 4; Juvenal, xiv. 311-314. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> also <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 782 a-b.</note> the pupil of Diogenes the Cynic, chief pilot of his fleet. </p><p rend="indent">But when he came to talk with Diogenes g himself in Corinth, he was so awed and astounded with the life and the worth of the man that often, when remembrance of the philosopher came to him, he would <pb xml:id="v.4.p.413"/> say, <q>If I were not Alexander,I should be Diogenes,</q> that is to say: <q>If I did not actively practise philosophy, I should apply myself to its theoretical pursuit.</q> He did not say, <q>If I were not a king, I should be Diogenes,</q> nor <q>If I were not rich and an Argead</q>; for he did not rank Fortune above Wisdom, nor a crown and royal purple above the philosopher’s wallet and threadbare gown. But he said, <q>If I were not Alexander, I should be Diogenes</q>; that is to say: <q>If it were not my purpose to combine foreign things with things Greek, to traverse and civilize every continent, to search out the uttermost parts of land and sea, to push the bounds of Macedonia to the farthest Ocean, and to disseminate and shower the blessings of Greek justice and peace over every nation, I should not be content to sit quietly in the luxury of idle power, but I should emulate the frugality of Diogenes. But as things are, forgive me, Diogenes, that I imitate Heracles, and emulate Perseus, and follow in the footsteps of Dionysus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, iv. 10. 6; <title rend="italic">Rhein. Mus.</title> liv. 470.</note>the divine author and progenitor of my family,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 326 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> and desire that victorious Greeks should dance again in India and revive the memory of the Bacchic revels among the savage mountain tribes beyond the Caucasus. Even there it is said that there are certain holy men, a law unto themselves, who follow a rigid gymnosophy<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chaps. lxiv., lxv. (700 f-701 f) for Alexander’s dealing with the Gymnosophists.</note> and give all their time to God; they are more frugal than Diogenes since they have no need of a wallet. For they do not store up food, since they have it ever fresh and green from the earth; the flowing rivers give them drink and they have fallen leaves and grassy <pb xml:id="v.4.p.415"/> earth to lie upon. Because of me even those faraway sages shall come to know of Diogenes, and he of them. And I also, like Diogenes, must alter the standard of coinage<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diogenes Laertius, vi. 20, 21.</note> and stamp foreign states with the impress of Greek government.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p rend="indent">Very well. Do Alexander’s actions, then, reveal the caprice of Fortune, the violence of war, the might of conquest, or do they rather reveal the great courage and justice, the great restraint and mildness together with the decorous behaviour and intelligence, of one who did all things with sober and sane judgement? For, by Heaven, it is impossible for me to distinguish his several actions and say that this betokens his courage, this his humanity, this his selfcontrol, but everything he did seems the combined product of all the virtues; for he confirms the truth of that principle of the Stoics which declares that every act which the wise man performs is an activity in accord with every virtue; and although, as it appears, one particular virtue performs the chief role in every act, yet it but heartens on the other virtues and directs them toward the goal. Certainly one may observe that in Alexander the warlike is also humane, the mild also manly, the liberal provident, the irascible placable, the amatory temperate, his relaxation not idle, and his labours not without recreation. Who but he combined festivals with wars, campaigns with revels, Bacchic rites and weddings and nuptial songs with sieges and battle-fields? Who was ever more hostile to wrongdoers or kinder to the unfortunate? Who more stern to his opponents or more indulgent to petitioners? <pb xml:id="v.4.p.417"/> It occurs to me to introduce here an incident touching Porus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 181 e, and 458 b; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lx. (669 c); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, v. 19. 2.</note> For when Porus was brought as a captive before Alexander, the conqueror asked how he should treat him. <q>Like a king, Alexander,</q> said Porus. When Alexander asked again if there were nothing else, <q>No,</q> said he, <q>for everything is included in that word.</q> And it naturally occurs to me also to exclaim over each of Alexander’s deeds, <q>Like a philosopher!</q> For in this is included everything. He became enamoured of Roxanê,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 338 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xlvii. (691 e); Arrian, iv. 19; Curtius, viii. 4.</note> the daughter of Oxyartes, as she danced among the captive maidens; yet he did not offer any violence to her, but made her his wife. <q>Like a philosopher!</q> When he saw Darius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xliii. (690 b).</note> pierced through by javelins, he did not offer sacrifice nor raise the paean of victory to indicate that the long war had come to an end; but he took off his own cloak and threw it over the corpse as though to conceal the divine retribution that waits upon the lot of kings. <q>Like a philosopher!</q> Once when he was reading a confidential letter from his mother, and Hephaestion,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 180 d, and the note.</note> who, as it happened, was sitting beside him, was quite openly reading it too, Alexander did not stop him, but merely placed his own signet-ring on Hephaestion’s lips, sealing them to silence with a friend’s confidence. <q>Like a philosopher!</q> For if these actions be not those of a philosopher, what others are? </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p rend="indent">But let us compare the actions of men who are admitted to be philosophers. Socrates forbore when Alcibiades<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Plato, <title rend="italic" >Symposium</title>, 218 c; Diogenes Laertius, ii. 31.</note> spent the night with him. But when <pb xml:id="v.4.p.419"/> Philoxenus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 1099 d; <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xxii. (676 f).</note> the governor of the coast-lands of Asia Minor, wrote to Alexander that there was in Ionia a youth, the like of whom for bloom and beauty did not exist, and inquired in his letter whether he should send the boy on to him. Alexander wrote bitterly in reply, <q>Vilest of men, what deed of this sort have you ever been privy to in my past that now you would flatter me with the offer of such pleasures?</q> We admire Xenocrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 331 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> because he would not accept the gift of fifty talents which Alexander sent him. But shall we not admire the giving of it? Or do we think that he who does not welcome a gift and he who bestows it are not at one in their contempt for money? Because of philosophy Xenocrates had no need of wealth and because of philosophy Alexander had need of wealth that he might lavish it upon such men. How many times has Alexander said this when forcing an attack amid a shower of missiles?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true" >Alexander’s remark that he needed money to give to others may be compared to the remark which Plutarch quotes in his <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lx. (698 e), when Alexander was risking his life in crossing the swollen Hydaspes: <q>O Athenians, can you possibly believe what dangers I undergo, to win good repute among you?</q> Others think that the remark has been lost from the mss.</note> And yet we believe that all men are endowed with the capacity to form right judgements. For Nature of herself is prone to lead men toward the Good. But philosophers differ from common persons in having their powers of judgement strong and firm to face danger, since the common man is not fortified by conceptions such as these: <q>Best is one omen</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title> xii. 243 <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἷς οἰωνὸς ἄριστος ἀμύνεσθαε περὶ πάτρης</foreign>.</note> and <pb xml:id="v.4.p.421"/> <q>Death is the end for all men</q>;<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 166 f; Demosthenes, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">De Corona</title>, 97. W. Crönert, in a review of Bell-Crum, <title rend="italic">A Greek-Coptic Glossary</title> (<title rend="italic">Gnomon</title>, ii. p. 657), reconstructs, from the words of the Testament of the High Priest Fl. Phoebammon, trimeters of an Euripidean flavour: <quote xml:lang="grc" rend="blockquote"> <l>πέρας δὲ παντὸς τοῦ βροτησίου γένους</l> <l>ὁ θάνατος οὐδὲ δυνατόν ἐστιν ἐκφυκεὶν</l>.</quote> More likely here, however, would be such a line as <quote rend="blockquote"> <l><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ θάνατός ἐσθ᾽ἅπασιν ἀνθρώποις πέρας.</foreign></l>.</quote> Plutarch and Demosthenes may both be quoting from something of the sort.</note> but crises destroy all his calculations in the face of danger, and the fantastic imaginings of perils close at hand dispel his powers of judgement. For not only does <q>fear,</q> as Thucydides<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Thucydides, ii. 87.</note> says, <q>drive out memory,</q> but it also drives out every purpose and ambition and impulse, unless philosophy has drawn her cords about them. </p> </div> </div> <pb xml:id="v.4.p.423"/> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Yesterday we forgot, it seems, to remark that the age of Alexander had the good fortune to produce both many artistic achievements and many men of great talent. Perhaps, however, this was not part of Alexander’s good fortune, but rather that of the artists, to have obtained as witness and spectator of their achievements the man who was both best able to judge of their success and to reward them most liberally. At any rate, it is said that, when Archestratus, a poet of a later age, who, though an accomplished writer, was passing his days in poverty and neglect, someone remarked to him, <q>If you had been born in Alexander’s time, for every verse he would have given you a Cyprus or a Phoenicia.</q> And I think that the foremost of the artists of that age became so, not because they lived in Alexander’s day, but through what Alexander did for them. For a good climate and a lightness of the surrounding air produces a bountiful harvest; and likewise the favour, esteem, and benignity shown by a king evokes a rich increase in the arts and in men of talent. And, conversely, through jealousy <pb xml:id="v.4.p.425"/> and parsimony or emulous rivalry on the part of monarchs all artistic production is quenched and perishes. </p><p rend="indent">Thus the despot Dionysius,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 41 d-e.</note> as the story goes, while listening to a celebrated harper, engaged to give him a talent.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">£200, or $1000.</note> Next day, when the man asked for the fulfilment of the promise, Dionysius said, <q>Yesterday I was delighted with your performance, and during the time that you were singing I also delighted you with hopes! The result is that at that very time you were receiving full pay for the pleasure you gave by having your pleasure too!</q> Alexander,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign><title rend="italic">. Life of Pelopidas</title>, xxix. (293 f); Aelian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Varia Historia</title>, xiv. 40.</note> the tyrant of Pherae (this last should be his only appellation; he should not be permitted to disgrace the name of Alexander), as he watched a tragic actor, felt himself much moved to pity through enjoyment of the acting. He jumped up, therefore, and left the theatre at a rapid pace, exclaiming that it would be a dreadful thing, if, when he was slaughtering so many citizens, he should be seen to weep over the sufferings of Hecuba and Polyxena. And he came near visiting punishment upon the actor because the man had softened his heart, as iron in the fire. </p><p rend="indent">Archelaüs<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 177 b, and the note.</note> was thought to be somewhat niggardly in his favours, and Timotheus liked to hint at this by often chanting this refrain: <quote rend="blockquote" >Over the earth-born silver you rave.</quote> But Archelaüs, with some wit, chanted in reply: <quote rend="blockquote">That, however, is what you crave.</quote> <pb xml:id="v.4.p.427"/> </p><p rend="indent">Ateas, the Scythian king, took the flute-player Ismenias captive, and ordered him to play at a banquet. The rest were delighted, and applauded, but Ateas swore his horse’s neighing was sweeter to his ear.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 174 f, and the note.</note> So far from the Muses’ habitation did he allow his ears to dwell, and his soul he kept in the mangers,better attuned to hear, not horses’ neigh,but asses’ bray! At the court of monarchs such as these what advancement or esteem could there be for Art, or for Poetry and Music of excellence? Nor, again, could artistic endeavour flourish at the court of those who wish to be rival performers in these arts, and thus through malice and ill-will suppress the true artists. Such a prince was Dionysius (to use him again as an example), who threw the poet Philoxenus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Ibid.</foreign> 471 e; Cicero, <title rend="italic">Tusculan Disputations</title>, v. 22 (63); Aelian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Varia Historia</title>, xii. 44; Diodorus, xv. 6.</note> into the stone-quarries; for when Dionysius ordered him to correct a tragedy of his, Philoxenus cancelled the whole piece from the very beginning to the final flourish.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="lat">coronis</foreign> at the end of the roll.</note> </p><p rend="indent">Philip also was in these matters somewhat more petty and childish than became him, since he had acquired his knowledge late in life. Thus they tell the tale that Philip<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 67 f, 179 b, 634 d.</note> once argued with a certain harp-player about the technique of his instrument, and even thought he was confuting the man; but the harp-player smiled gently and said, <q>God forbid, your Majesty, that you should ever fall so low as to know more of these matters than I.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p rend="indent">But Alexander, knowing well in what matters he should be merely a spectator and listener, and in what he should play the chief role, trained himself <pb xml:id="v.4.p.429"/> always to be formidable in arms, and. in the words of Aeschylus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 317 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>, and the note.</note> <quote rend="blockquote">Sturdy contender in arms, baleful to all that oppose.</quote> This art he inherited from his ancestors, the Aeacidae, and from Heracles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. ii. (665 b).</note>; but upon the other arts he freely bestowed honour without jealousy according to their worth and artistic excellence; but he was not so easily carried away by the pleasure they give him as to try to imitate them. The tragic actors of his time were the group that centred about Thettalus and Athenodorus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Ibid.</foreign> chap. xxix. (681 d).</note> At the contest of these two, the kings of Cyprus defrayed the expenses of the performance and Alexander’s most celebrated generals served as judges. When Athenodorus won, <q>I would rather,</q> said Alexander, <q>have lost half my kingdom than see Thettalus defeated.</q> However, he did not intercede with the judges nor find fault with the judgement, since he felt that, while he must be superior to all men, yet he must submit to Justice. </p><p rend="indent">The comic actors of his time were the group that centred about Lycon of Scarpheia.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Ibid.</foreign> chap. xxix. (681 d).</note> When Lycon inserted in one of his comedies a begging verse, Alexander laughed and gave him ten talents. </p><p rend="indent">Various harp-players also were his friends, among them Aristonicus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title rend="italic" >Anabasis</title>, iv. 16. 7.</note> who came to Alexander’s aid in a certain battle, and was slain fighting gloriously. Therefore Alexander ordered to be made and set up at Delphi a bronze statue of him, with lyre in hand and spear advanced; thereby he not only honoured <pb xml:id="v.4.p.431"/> this particular man, but also paid tribute to Music herself, in the belief that she is a creator of true men and, in particular, that she filis with inspiration and impetuousness those who are truly her fosterchildren. For once Upon a time, when Antigenides was playing on his flute the Chariot Song,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 1133 e (= Edmonds, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Lyra Graeca</title>, i. pp. 4-8). See also Dio Chrysostom, <title rend="italic">Oration</title> i. 1-2, where Timotheus is the flute-player and the tune the Orthian.</note> Alexander became so transported, and his spirit so inflamed by the strains, that he leapt up and laid hands upon the weapons that lay near, and thus confirmed the testimony of the Spartans who used to sing,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true" >Attributed to Alcman in <title rend="italic">Life of Lycurgus</title>, chap. xxi. (53 d); <foreign xml:lang="lat" >Cf.</foreign>Bergk, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</title> iii. p. 51, or Edmonds, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Lyra Graeca</title>, i. p. 90.</note> <quote rend="blockquote">The noble playing of the lyre is meet to match the sword.</quote> </p><p rend="indent">Apelles the painter and Lysippus the sculptor also lived in the time of Alexander. The former painted <q>Alexander wielding the Thunderbolt</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. iv. (666 b); Pliny, <title rend="italic">Natural History</title>, xxxv. 10 (92).</note> so vividly and with so natural an expression, that men said that, of the two Alexanders, Alexander, son of Philip, was invincible, but the Alexander of Apelles was inimitable. And when Lysippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. iv. (666 b).</note> modelled his first statue of Alexander which represented him looking up with his face turned towards the heavens (as indeed Alexander often did look, with a slight inclination of his head to one side<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf. ibid.</foreign> and <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 53 d.</note>),someone engraved these verses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 331 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>, and the note.</note> on the statue, not without some plausibility, <quote rend="blockquote"> <l>Eager to speak seems the statue of bronze, up to Zeus as it gazes : </l> <l> <q>Earth I have set under foot: Zeus, keep Olympus yourself!</q></l> </quote> <pb xml:id="v.4.p.433"/> Wherefore Alexander gave orders that Lysippus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Pliny, <title rend="italic" >Natural History</title>, vii. 37 (125); Horace, <title rend="italic">Epistles</title>, ii. 1. 240; Valerius Maximus, viii. 11. 2; Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, i. 16. 4.</note> only should make statues of him. For Lysippus was, it seemed, the only one that revealed in the bronze Alexander’s character and in moulding his form portrayed also his virtues. The others wished to imitate the flexing of his neck and the melting and liquid softness of his eyes, but were unable to preserve his virile and leonine expression. </p><p rend="indent">Among the other artists at his court was Stasicrates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxxii. (705 a): the man is called Deinocrates by Vitruvius, ii. praef.; and Cheirocrates by the mss. of Strabo, xiv. 1. 23.</note> the master-sculptor, not seeking to make something flowery or pleasant or lifelike to look upon, but employing a magnificence in workmanship and design worthy of a king’s munificence. He followed Alexander into Asia and found fault with the paintings, sculptures, and moulded likenesses that had been made of him, on the ground that they were the works of timid and ignoble artists. <q>But I, your Majesty,</q> said he, <q>have conceived the project of placing your likeness in living and imperishable material, with roots that are everlasting and weight immovable and unshakable. For Mount Athos in Thrace, in that part where is its highest and most conspicuous summit, has well-proportioned surfaces and heights, limbs and joints and proportions that suggest the human form. When it has been properly carved and worked into shape, it can be called Alexander’s statue, and Alexander’s statue it will be; with its base set in the sea, in its left hand it will encompass and hold a city peopled with ten thousand <pb xml:id="v.4.p.435"/> inhabitants, and with its right pour from a bowl of libation an ever-flowing river down into the sea. But as for gold and bronze, ivory, wooden timbers, and dyes,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The reference is to the chryselephantine statues of Pheidias and his school with their inner frame-work of timbers, and painted without.</note> which make those paltry images that can be bought and sold, stolen, or melted down, let us reject them all!</q> Alexander listened to his words and admired but declined with thanks the lofty designs and the boldness of the artist. <q type="unspecified" >But,</q> said he, <q>let Athos remain as it is. It is enough that it be the memorial of the arrogance of one king<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Xerxes’ canal; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 342 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >infra</foreign>.</note>; but my imprint the Caucasus shall show and the Emodian<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">A range of north-western India, the Prakrit Haimota; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Indica</title>, 2. 3; 6. 4; Pliny, <title rend="italic">Natural History</title>, vi. 17 (56).</note> range and the Tanaïs and the Caspian Sea; these will be the image of my deeds. </q></p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p rend="indent">But imagine, pray, that such a work had been completed and made evident to men’s eyes. Is there anyone who could look upon it and suppose that the form, the arrangement, and the appearance were created by Fortune and Accident? No one, I think. What of Apelles’ <q type="unspecified" >Wielder of the Thunderbolt</q>?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 335 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra,</foreign> <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title> 360 d.</note> What of the statue which takes its name from the Spear?<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 335 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra,</foreign> <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 360 d.</note> Shall we admit, then, that greatness in a statue cannot, without the help of Art,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 99 b-c.</note> be created by Fortune’s profuse provision of gold and bronze and ivory and much rich material, but is it possible that a great man, or rather the greatest man of all that have ever lived, without the help of Virtue, was perfected through Fortunes supplying him with arms and money, foot and horse? But for him who has not learned how to use these things they are a danger, not a strength and enrichment, but a means of proving his weakness and pettiness. For Antisthenes <pb xml:id="v.4.p.437"/> was right when he said,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Stobaeus, <title rend="italic" >Florilegium</title>, lix. 41 (Hense, vol. iv. p. 362).</note> <q>We should pray that our enemies be provided with all good things, except courage; for thus these good things will belong, not to their owners, but to those that conquer them.</q> Therefore they say that Nature also for defence has caused horns, wonderful for their size and jagged points, to grow upon the deer, the most cowardly of all animals; and therein does Nature teach us that strength and arms are of no benefit to such as have not the courage to stand their ground. Thus also Fortune, by frequently bestowing on cowards and fools military forces and dominions, in which they disgrace themselves, emblazons and commends Virtue as the one quality that constitutes the greatness and beauty of man. For if indeed, as Epicharmus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">An oft-quoted line. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> G. Kaibel, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Comicorum Graec. Frag.</title> i. 137, Epicharmus, no. 249; <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 98 c, with the note; also Cicero, <title rend="italic">Tusculan Disp.</title> i. 20 (46); Maximus Tyrius, xi. 10.</note> says, <quote rend="blockquote">Mind has sight and Mind has hearing;</quote> but <quote rend="blockquote">All things else are deaf and blind;</quote> then it happens that these are really lacking in reason. For our perceptive faculties seem to respond to their own special stimuli; but the fact that it is mind which aids us and mind which emblazons our deeds, and it is mind that conquers and overpowers and plays the monarch, and that <q>all things else,</q> since they are <q>blind and deaf</q> and soulless, mislead and burden and disgrace their possessors, if Virtue be not present,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Plato, <title rend="italic" >Menexenus</title>, 246 e.</note> is a truth which may be gleaned from history. </p><p rend="indent">Now of the two monarchs Semiramis and Sardanapalus, in whose hands were placed the same power <pb xml:id="v.4.p.439"/> and dominion, Semiramis,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diodorus, ii. 4-20; Justin, i. 2.</note> though a woman, equipped great expeditions, armed her ranks, established the Babylonian Empire, and sailed about the Persian Gulf subduing the Ethiopians and Arabs. But Sardanapalus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 326 f, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>; Diodorus, ii. 21. 8 ff; Athenaeus, 528 f; W. K. Prentice, in <title rend="italic">Trans. Amer. Phil. Assoc.</title> liv. (1923) p. 79: but the theory rightly set forth, there, that this description comes from Ctesias’s <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Persica</title>, is as old as Hemsterhuys; see Wyttenbach’s note on this passage.</note> though born a man, spent his days at home carding purple wool, sitting with his knees drawn up in front of him among his concubines; and when he died, they made a stone statue of him dancing in a barbaric fashion and apparently snapping its fingers above its head. They engraved upon it: <q>Eat, drink, and sport with love; all else is naught.</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">See the note on 330 f, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> </p><p rend="indent">When Crates<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 401 a; Athenaeus, 591 b; Stobaeus, <title rend="italic">Florilegium</title>, vi. 39 (vol. iii. p. 296 Hense).</note> saw a golden statue of Phrynê the courtesan standing at Delphi, he cried out that it stood there as a monument to Greek licentiousness; and thus if one examine either the life or the tomb of Sardanapalus (for I think there is no difference between them), one would say that they are a monument to the bounty of Fortune. But if this be so, shall we allow Fortune to lay hold upon Alexander after Sardanapalus, and to lay claim to Alexander’s greatness and power? For what greater gift did she bestow on him than those which other monarchs received at her hands: arms, horses, missiles, money, guardsmen? Let Fortune endeavour to make an Aridaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 337 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> great by these, if she can, or an Ochus or Oarses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 337 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> or Tigranes the Armenian, or the Bithynian Nicomedes. Of these <pb xml:id="v.4.p.441"/> Tigranes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign><title rend="italic">. Life of Pompey</title>, chap. xxxiii. (637 a); <title rend="italic" >Comp. of Cimon and Lucullus</title>, iii. (522 e); Velleius Paterculus, ii. 37; Valerius Maximus, v. 1. 10.</note> cast down his crown before the feet of Pompey and ignominiously received back his kingdom, which had become the spoil of war. But Nicomedes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Plutarch has confused Nicomedes with his father Prusias; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Polybius, xxx. 19; Livy, xlv. 44; Diodorus, xxxi. 15; Appian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Mithridatica</title>, 2.</note> shaved his head and put on the freedman’s cap and proclaimed himself an emancipated slave of the Roman people. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p rend="indent">Shall we say, then, that Fortune makes men petty, timid, and abject in spirit? Yet it is not right for anyone to charge baseness to misfortune, or courage and intelligence to good fortune; but Fortune was magnified by Alexander’s reign, for in him she was illustrious, invincible, magnanimous, inoffensive, and humane. Then, immediately after Alexander’s decease, Leosthenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The saying is elsewhere attributed to Demades; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 181 f, and the note.</note> said that his forces, as they wandered here and there and fell foul of their own efforts, were like the Cyclops after his blinding, groping about everywhere with his hands, which were directed at no certain goal; even thus did that vast throng roam about with no safe footing, blundering through want of a leader. Or rather, in the manner of dead bodies, after the soul departs, when they are no longer held together by natural forces, but undergo dispersion and dissolution, and finally are dissipated and disappear altogether; even so Alexander’s forces, having lost him, maintained a gasping, agitated, and fevered existence through men like Perdiccas, Meleager, Seleucus, and Antigonus, who, as it were, provided still a warm breath of life and blood that still pulsed and circulated. But at length the host wasted away and perished, generating <pb xml:id="v.4.p.443"/> about itself maggots, as it were, of ignoble kings and rulers in their last death-struggle. This, then, it is likely that Alexander himself meant when he rebuked Hephaestion<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xlvii. (691 f-692 a).</note> for quarrelling with Craterus: <q>What</q> said he, <q>will be your power and your achievements if someone deprive you of Alexander?</q> Rut I, for my part, shall not hesitate to say this very thing to the Fortune that presided over Alexander’s career: <q>What is your greatness or your repute? Where is your power or your invincibility, if someone deprive you of Alexander?</q> That is to say, <q type="unspecified" >If someone deprive you of your skill in arms, your munificent use of riches, your self-restraint in expending them, your boldness against your foes in battle, your mildness toward the vanquished? Make another great, if you can; but one that shall not be generous with his substance, nor court danger in the front ranks, nor give honour to his friends, nor feel pity for his captives, nor be temperate in his pleasures, nor sleepless in crises, nor placable in his victories, nor humane amid his successes. What man is great in the exercise of power, if folly and wickedness attend him? Take away virtue from the fortunate man and in everything he is petty; in acts of generosity, through parsimony; in hard tasks, through softness; in religion, through superstition; towards the good, through envy; among men, through cowardice; among women, through wantonness.</q> Just as inexpert artisans, who construct large pedestals for petty offerings, make the smallness of the offerings noticeable, so Fortune, whenever she elevates a petty character by acts that have a certain pomp <pb xml:id="v.4.p.445"/> and circumstance, makes the more conspicuous and disgraceful the blundering and instability that result from a shallow character. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p rend="indent">Wherefore greatness lies, not in the possession of good things, but in our use of them, since even infant children inherit their fathers’ kingdoms and dominions, even as Charillus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign><title rend="italic">. Life of Lycurgus</title>, chap. iii. (41 a).</note> whom Lycurgus carried in his swaddling-clothes into the common dining-hall and proclaimed king of Sparta in place of himself. Assuredly it was not the child who was great, but he who surrendered to the child its paternal rights, and did not keep them for himself nor take them away. </p><p rend="indent">But who could have made Aridaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 791 e.</note> great, whom, differing no whit from a child, only that his swaddlingclothes were royal purple, Meleager set on the throne of Alexander? And indeed it was well that he did so, that for a few days it might be observed how it is that men rule by right of virtue and how by gift of Fortune. For in succession to a real competitor for sovereignty Meleager introduced a mere actor, or rather, did a mute figure wearing a crown parade across the stage, as it were, of the inhabited world. <quote rend="blockquote" >Even a woman can carry a burden if a man impose it upon her.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Aristophanes, <title rend="italic">Knights</title>, 1056; see Rogers’s note <foreign xml:lang="lat">ad loc.</foreign> </note> </quote> Conversely, however, one might affirm that it lies within the strength of even a woman or a child to take up and impose the gifts of power and wealth and sovereignty. The eunuch Bagoas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title rend="italic" >Anabasis</title>, ii. 14. 5; Aelian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Varia Historia</title>, vi. 8; Diodorus, xvii. 5.</note> took up the kingship of Persia and bestowed it upon Oarses and Darius.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 326 f, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> But the ability to sustain and administer <pb xml:id="v.4.p.447"/> great authority when one has once received it, and not to be crushed or turned from ones purpose by the weight and the magnitude of one’s activities, is the mark of a man who possesses virtue, sense, and intelligence. This virtue Alexander possessed, whom some accuse of drunkenness and a passion for wine I Rut he was truly a great man, for in his conduct of affairs he was sober, nor was he made drunk nor led to revelling by authority and power; but others, when they get but a small portion, or even a taste, of power are unable to control themselves: <quote rend="blockquote"> <l>Bad men, when gorged with wealth, or chancing on </l> <l>Some honours in the State, caper and prance </l> <l>When luck, unhoped for, to their house has come.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">From a much longer fragment of Euripides’ <title rend="italic" >Erechtheus</title>; Nauck, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Trag. Graec. Frag.</title> p. 471, Euripides, no. 362, 29-31.</note> </l> </quote> Cleitus,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diodorus, xviii. 15. 9. 72.</note> when he had scuttled three or four Greek triremes at Amorgos, caused himself to be proclaimed Poseidon and carried a trident. Demetrius, to whom Fortune added the little that she was able to subtract from Alexander’s power, allowed himself to be called <q>The Heaven-descended,</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <q>Avatar,</q> he that desceds from Heaven (in thunder and lightning), a common title of Zeus; <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf</foreign><title rend="italic">. Life of Demetrius</title>, chaps. x., xi. (893 d, e).</note> and the subject states did not send ambassadors to him, but <q>Sacred Deputies,</q> and his replies they spoke of as <q>Oracles.</q> Lysimacho, who obtained possession of the regions adjoining Thrace, the mere outskirts of the kingdom of Alexander, as it were, reached such a pitch of arrogance and boldness as to say, <q>The Byzantines now come to me when I am touching Heaven with my spear.</q> But Pasiades of Byzantium, who was present, said, <q>Let us be off, lest he make a hole in the sky with his spear-point!</q> <pb xml:id="v.4.p.449"/> </p><p rend="indent">And yet why should anyone mention these men who might have some legitimate ground for pride because of Alexander, when even Clearchus, after he became despot of Heracleia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">In Pontus: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Müller, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Frag. Hist. Graec.</title> iii. p. 526.</note> used to carry a thunderbolt,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">i.e.</foreign> a <foreign xml:lang="lat" >skepton</foreign>, instead of <foreign xml:lang="lat" >skeptron</foreign>, <q>sceptre.</q> </note> and named one of his sons Thunderer? And Dionysius the younger styled himself the son of Apollo in the inscription: <quote rend="blockquote">Sprung from a Dorian mother by union with Phoebus Apollo.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Bergk, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Poet. Lyr. Graec.</title> ii. p. 324.</note> </quote> And Dionysius’s father killed ten thousand or more citizens, and, led on by envy, betrayed his brother to the enemy, nor could he wait for his already aged mother to die a few days later, but strangled her<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Aelian, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Varia Historia</title>, xiii. 45.</note>; yet in one of his tragedies he wrote these words<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Nauck, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Trag. Graec. Frag.</title> p. 797, Dionysius, no. 7.</note>: <quote rend="blockquote">The mother of foul wrong is tyranny!</quote> Notwithstanding, of his daughters he named one Virtue, another Temperance, a third Justice.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign><title rend="italic">. Life of Dion</title>, chap. vi. (960 c).</note> And yet other persons publicly styled themselves Benefactors,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Probably Ptolemy Euergetes II. Physcon (<foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Athenaeus xii. 549 d), rather than Philopater (<foreign xml:lang="lat" >Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" >Moralia</title>, 56 e, Polybius v. 34), is alluded to.</note> Conquerors, Saviours, or The Great; but no one would be able to tell the tale of their marriages one after another, like the matings of horses, as they spent their days with no restraint amid herds of women, their corruption of boys, their beating of drums in the company of emasculated men, their daily dicing, their flute-playing in the public theatres, the night that was too short for them at their dinners, and the day at their breakfasts. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p rend="indent">But Alexander took his breakfast at daybreak <pb xml:id="v.4.p.451"/> seated<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xxiii. (677 d).</note>; he dined late in the evening; he drank only after sacrificing to the gods; he played dice with Medius when he had a fever<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Ibid.</foreign> chap. lxxvi. (706 d).</note>; he played games while travelling, at the same time also learning to wield a bow and mount a chariot. For himself he married Roxanê,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 332 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> the only woman he ever loved; but Stateira,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxx. (703 e); Diodorus, xvii. 107; Justin, xii. 10.</note> the daughter of Darius, he married for imperial and political reasons, since the union of the two races was highly advantageous. But as for the other Persian women, he was as much their superior in self-control as in valour he was superior to Persian men. For he looked at no woman against her will<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 97 d, 522 a; <title rend="italic" >Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xxi. (676 f).</note> and those that he looked at he passed by more readily than those that he did not look at; and although he bore himself humanely toward all other persons, it was toward fair youth alone that he conducted himself haughtily. He would not listen to a single word in praise of the beauty of the wife<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Ibid.</foreign> chap. xxii. (677 a); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, iv. 20; Athenaeus, xiii. 603 c; Quintus Curtius, <title rend="italic">Hist. Alexandri</title>, iv. 10.</note> of Darius, who was a very handsome woman; but when she died, he graced her funeral with such a royal pomp and bewailed her death so feelingly that his self-control was questioned amid his display of humanity, and his goodness incurred the charge of wrongdoing. For Darius<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xxx. (682 c-d).</note> was disturbed by suspicion of Alexander’s power and youth; for he also was still one of those who believed Alexander’s victory to be through Fortune. But when he had tested the matter from every angle, and recognized the truth, <q>Then,</q> said he, <q>the lot of the Persians is not so utterly wretched, nor will anyone say that we are altogether cowardly or unmanly in <pb xml:id="v.4.p.453"/> that we have been overcome by such a man. But for my part I pray the gods for fair fortune and for might in war, that I may surpass Alexander in bestowing favours; and I am possessed by an ambitious and emulous desire to prove myself more humane than Alexander. But if my power be spent, do thou, O Zeus, ancestral god of the Persians, and ye other gods that guard our kingship, grant that none other than Alexander take his seat upon the throne of Cyrus.</q> This was Darius’s way of adopting Alexander, invoking the gods as witnesses. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p rend="indent">Thus do men prevail through Virtue. Ascribe to Fortune, if you will, Arbela and the Cilician victory and his other deeds of violence and war : Fortune battered down the walls of Tyre<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xxv. (679 a); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, ii. 23.</note> for him; Fortune opened the way to Egypt<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 326 f, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note>; through Fortune Halicarnassus fell, and Miletus was captured, and Mazaeus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title rend="italic" >Anabasis</title>, iii. 7. 2.</note> left the Euphrates unguarded, and the Babylonian plain was strewn with corpses. But at least it was not in any way Fortune’s gift that he was temperate, nor was it because of Fortune that he was self-controlled, nor did Fortune lock his soul and keep it impregnable to pleasure and invulnerable to desire; in fact, these were the qualities by which he defeated Darius himself. The rest were but defeats of arms and horses, battles, slaughters, and routs of men. But the truly great and indisputable defeat Darius suffered: he yielded in virtue and greatness of soul, in prowess and Justice, and marvelled at Alexander’s invincibility in pleasure, in toil, in the bestowal of favours. It is true that Tarrias,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Tarrias is elsewhere unknown; the stories here related of him are told of Antigenes in <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxx. (703 e-f).</note> son of <pb xml:id="v.4.p.455"/> Deinomenes, and Antigenes of Pallenê, and Philo t as, the son of Parinenion, were also invincible at least amid shields, pikes, battle-cries, and the clash of arms; but towards pleasures and women and gold and silver they were no better than their captives. In fact, when Alexander was freeing the Macedonians from debt<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 343 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>; Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, vii. 5. 1-3.</note> and paying creditors for everybody, Tarrias said falsely that he was a debtor, and produced at the bank a person who asserted that he was Tarrias s creditor; later, when he was detected, he was ready to commit suicide had not Alexander, coming to know of this, exculpated him, and allowed him to keep the money; for the king remembered that when Philip was assaulting Perinthus, Tarrias, although his eye was pierced by a missile, would not submit nor suffer the shaft to be extracted until they had routed the enemy. </p><p rend="indent">Antigenes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Repeated in <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 181 a; but told of Eurylochus in <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xli. (689 b).</note> joined himself with those who were being sent back to Macedonia because of sickness or wounds,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxxi. (704 b).</note> and had himself enrolled among them; but when, however, it was discovered that he had nothing wrong with him, but was feigning some infirmity, and it was seen that he was a stout fighting man whose body was covered with wounds, the matter vexed Alexander. When he asked the reason for such conduct, Antigenes confessed that he was in love with Telesippa, and was accompanying her to the sea, since he could not be left behind if she went away. <q>Whose is she?</q> asked Alexander, <q>and to whom must we speak?</q> Antigenes replied that she was <pb xml:id="v.4.p.457"/> free-born. <q type="unspecified" >Then,</q> said Alexander, <q>let us persuade her with promises and presents to remain behind.</q> So ready was he with an excuse for every lover rather than for himself. </p><p rend="indent">And further, Philotas,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title rend="italic"> Life of Alexander</title>, chaps. xlviii., xlix. (692 a-693 a).</note> the son of Parmenion, had in his licentiousness the nurse, as it were, of all his ills. For among the captives taken at Damascus was a courtesan from Pella, by name Antigona. Ere this she had crossed over to Samothrace, and there had been taken captive by Autophradates. She was comely enough to look upon and, after Philotas had attached himself to her, she had complete possession of him. Indeed that man of iron<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The Doric form suggests quotation from some poem or drama.</note> was so softened that he was not in control of his reasoning powers amid his pleasures, but unlocked and brought forth many of his secrets for the woman: <q>What was that famed Philip, were it not for Parmenion? What was this Alexander, were it not for Philotas? Where his Ammon, and where his serpents,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">A reference, perhaps, to Ammon (<foreign xml:lang="lat">i.e.</foreign> Zeus) in the form of a serpent, seen with Olympias, as told in <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. iii. (665 d); or perhaps to the expedition to the oracle of Ammon, <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title rend="italic" >Anabasis</title>, iii. 3. 5.</note> if we do not wish it so?</q> These words Antigona reported to an intimate friend of hers among the women, and she reported them to Craterus; Craterus brought Antigona herself secretly to Alexander, who did not touch her person, but restrained himself and, working secretly through her, he discovered the whole of Philotas’s plans. And for a period of more than seven years Alexander never revealed his suspicion; not in his cups, the reputed drunkard I not in anger, this <pb xml:id="v.4.p.459"/> man of fiery temper! not to a friend, this man who trusted Hephaestion in everything and shared everything with him! In fact it is recorded<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 333 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> that once, when he had broken the seal of a confidential letter from his mother and was reading it silently<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <q>Silently,</q> for reading was generally done aloud.</note> to himself, Hephaestion quietly put his head beside Alexander’s and read the letter with him; Alexander could not bear to stop him, but took off his ring and placed the seal on Hephaestion’s lips. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p rend="indent">But one might grow weary in the enumeration of these matters by which Alexander is shown to have made the most honourable and the most regal use of his authority. And even though he became great through Fortune, he is even greater in that he made good use of his Fortune. And the more we praise his Fortune the more shall we exalt his Virtue by reason of which he became worthy of his Fortune. </p><p rend="indent">Now, however, I shall proceed at once to the first steps in his advancement and the beginnings of his power, and I shall examine in those matters the role played by Fortune, by reason of which men assert that Alexander became great through the instrumentality of Fortune. In Heaven’s name! Why do they not assert this of one that never felt a wound nor lost a drop of blood nor ever served in Avar, whom the neighing of a horse<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Herodotus, iii. 84 ff.</note> placed upon the throne of Cyrus, even as the first Darius, the son of Hystaspes? Or of Xerxes, whom a king, flattered by his wife, as Darius was flattered by Atossa,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Ibid.</foreign> vii. 3.</note> set upon the throne? Did the royal diadem come to Alexander’s doors, as <pb xml:id="v.4.p.461"/> to Oarses<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Artaxerxes: <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> 336 e, 337 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>, <title rend="italic">Life of Artaxerxes</title>, chap. i. (1012 a): Reiske conjectured <foreign xml:lang="grc">Ἄρσῃ</foreign> from Diodorus, xvii. 5, which may be right. But Bagoas also put Darius III. on the throne of Persia. <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 326 f, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> through the machinations of Bagoas, who stripped from him the garb of a courier and put upon him the royal raiment and the tiara that ever stands erect<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">For the upright tiara <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf. e.g.</foreign> Xenophon, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, ii. 5. 23; <title rend="italic" >Life of Themistocles</title>, chap. xxix. (126 e); <title rend="italic">Life of Artaxerxes</title>, chaps. xxvi., xxviii. (1024 e, 1025 e).</note>? Was he suddenly and unexpectedly chosen by lot and thus carne to rule the inhabited world, as at Athens the Thesmothetae and Archons attain their office? </p><p rend="indent">Would you learn how it is that men come to the throne by choice of Fortune? Once upon a time among the Argives the family of Heracleidae became extinct, from which family it was their ancestral custom to select the Argive kings. When in their search they made inquiry of the god at Delphi, he replied that an eagle would show them, and a few days later an eagle appeared on high and, swooping down, alighted on the house of Aegon, and Aegon was chosen king. </p><p rend="indent">Again in Paphos when the reigning king was seen to be unjust and wicked. Alexander expelled him and searched for another, since the family of Cinyradae appeared to be already passing away or extinct. However, they told him that there still survived one poor and obscure person, who eked out a forsaken existence in a certain garden. Men were sent to fetch him and, when they arrived, he was found watering his garden-plots; and he was much perturbed when the soldiers laid hands on him and ordered him to come with them. He was brought before Alexander and, dressed as he was in a single cheap garment, he was proclaimed king, and received the royal purple, and became one of those who are styled the king’s <q>Companions.</q> His name was <pb xml:id="v.4.p.463"/> Abdalonymus.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Cobet’s conjecture (Abdalonymus for Aralynomus) is only very partially supported by Diodorus, xvii. 46. 47. But <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> the references <foreign xml:lang="lat">ad loc.</foreign> in Fischer’s ed. (Leipzig 1906), especially Quintus Curtius, <title rend="italic">Hist. Alexandri</title>, iv. 1. 19.</note> Thus does shifting Fortune create kings, change their raiment, and quickly and easily alter the status of men who cxpect nothing of the sort, and do not even hope for it. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p rend="indent">But what greatness did Alexander acquire beyond his just merits, what without sweat, what without blood, what without a price, what without labour? He drank rivers fouled with blood, crossed streams bridged by dead bodies, through hunger ate the first grass that he saw, dug through nations buried in deep snow<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diodorus, xvii. 82; Quintus Curtius, <title rend="italic">Hist. Alexandri</title>, v. 3.</note> and cities built beneath the earth, sailed over a battling sea<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Arrian, <title rend="italic" >Anabasis</title>, vi. 19; Quintus Curtius, <title rend="italic" >Hist. Alexandri</title>, ix. 9.</note>; and as he traversed the parching strands of Gedrosia and Arachosia,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxvi. (702 a); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, vi. 22 ff; Quintus Curtius, <title rend="italic">Hist. Alexandri</title>, ix. 10.</note> it was in the sea, not on the land, that first he saw a living plant. </p><p rend="indent">If to Fortune, as to a human being, one might present Frankness in Alexander’s behalf, would she not say, <q>When and where did you ever vouchsafe a way for the exploits of Alexander? What fortress did he ever capture by your help without the shedding of blood? What city unguarded or what regiment unarmed did you deliver into his hands? What king was found to be indolent, or what general negligent, or what watchman asleep at the gate? But no river was easy to cross, no storm was moderate, no summer’s heat was without torment. Betake yourself to Antiochus, the son of Seleucus, or to Artaxerxes, the brother of Cyrus; depart to Ptolemy Philadelphus! Their fathers, while yet alive, proclaimed <pb xml:id="v.4.p.465"/> them kings; they won battles that did not cost a tear; they made merry all their lives in processions and theatres; and every one of them, because of good fortune, grew old upon the throne.</q> </p><p rend="indent"><q>But in the case of Alexander, though I were to mention nothing else, behold his body gashed with wounds<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">For the wounds of Alexander see the note on 327 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>, with the work of Nachstädt there referred to.</note> from tip to toe, bruised all over, smitten at the hands of his enemies <quote rend="blockquote">Now with the spear, now the sword, now with mighty masses of boulders.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true" >Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title> xi. 265, 541.</note> </quote> On the banks of the Granicus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 327 a, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>, and the notes.</note> his helmet was cleft through to his scalp by a sword; at Gaza his shoulder was wounded by a missile; at Maracanda his shin was so torn by an arrow that by the force of the blow the larger bone was broken and extruded. Somewhere in Hyrcania his neck was smitten by a stone, whereby his sight was dimmed, and for many days he was haunted by the fear of blindness. Among the Assacenians his ankle was wounded by an Indian arrow; that was the time when he smilingly said to his flatterers, ‘this that you see is blood, not <quote rend="blockquote">Ichor, that which flows from the wounds of the blessed immortals.’<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title> v. 340; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 180 e and the note.</note> </quote> At Issus he was wounded in the thigh with a sword, as Chares<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xx. (675 e-f).</note> states, by Darius the king, who had come into hand-to-hand conflict with him. Alexander himself wrote of this simply, and with complete truth, in a letter to Antipater: ‘I myself happened,’ he writes, ‘to be wounded in the thigh by a dagger. But nothing untoward resulted from the blow either <pb xml:id="v.4.p.467"/> immediately or later.’ Among the Mallians he was wounded in the breast by an arrow three feet long, which penetrated his breastplate, and someone rode up under him, arid struck him in the neck, as Aristobulus relates. When he had crossed the Taiiais against the Scythians and had routed them, he pursued them on horseback an hundred and fifty stades, though he was grievously distressed with diarrhoea.</q><note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xlv. (691 a); Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, iv. 4. 9; Quintus Curtius, <title rend="italic">Hist. Alexandri</title>, vii. 9, 13.</note> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p rend="indent"> <q>Well done. Fortune! You exalt Alexander and make him great by running him through from every side, by making him lose his footing, by laying open every portion of his body. Not like Athena before Menelaüs<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title> iv. 129.</note> did you guide the missile to the stoutest parts of his armour, and by breastplate, belt, and kilt take away the intensity of the blow, which only grazed his body with force enough to cause blood to flow; but you exposed to the missiles the vital portions of Alexander’s body unprotected, you drove home the blows through his very bones, you circled about his body, you laid siege to his eyes and his feet, you hindered him in pursuing his foes, you endeavoured to strip him of his victories, you upset his expectations.</q> </p><p rend="indent">No other king seems to me to have felt the hand of Fortune more heavily upon him, even though on many it has fallen harshly and malignantly. But like a thunderbolt it cut down the other rulers, and destroyed them; toward Alexander, however, Fortune’s ill-will became but contentious and quarrelsome and hard to overpower, even as it was toward Heracles. For what manner of Typhons or monstrous <pb xml:id="v.4.p.469"/> giants did she not raise up to oppose him? Whom of his foes did she not fortify with a vast supply of weapons or deep rivers or jagged cliffs or the might of beasts from foreign lands<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Presumably elephants.</note>? But if Alexander’s thought had not been set on high emprise, if it had not derived its impelling force from great Virtue, and had not refused to submit to defeat in its wrestling with Fortune, would he not have grown tired and weary of marshalling and arming his forces, weary of his sieges and pursuits amid unnumbered revolts, desertions, and riots of subject peoples, defections of kings, against Bactria, Maracanda, Sogdiana, as if he were cutting off the heads of a hydra which ever grew again in renewed wars among these faithless and conspiring peoples? </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p rend="indent">I shall be thought to be making a strange statement, yet what I shall say is true: it was because of Fortune that Alexander all but lost the repute of being the son of Ammon! For what offspring of the gods could have toiled through such hazardous, toilsome, and painful Labours save only Heracles, the son of Zeus? But it was one arrogant man who imposed upon Heracles the task of capturing lions, of pursuing wild boars, of frightening off birds so that he might not have time to go about performing greater deeds, such as punishing men like Antaeus and stopping creatures like Busiris<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 315 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign> and <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic" >Moralia</title> 857 a.</note> from their abominable murders. But upon Alexander it was Virtue who laid the kingly and god-like Labour, the end and aim of which was not gold, carried about by countless camels, nor Persian luxury, banquets, and women, nor the wine <pb xml:id="v.4.p.471"/> of Chalybon,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">A city in Syria; for the wine <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Strabo, xv. 3. 22 (p. 735); Athenaeus, 28 d; Suidas and Hesychius, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >s.v.</foreign> </note> nor the fish of Hyrcania, but to order all men by one law and to render them submissive to one rule and accustomed to one manner of life. The desire which he cherished to accomplish this task was implanted in him from childhood, and was fostered and increased with the years that passed. Once, when ambassadors carne from the Persian king to Philip, who was not at home, Alexander, while he entertained them hospitably,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. v. (666 e-f).</note> asked ho childish questions, as the others did, about the vine of gold,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Xenophon, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Hellenica</title>, vii. 1. 38; Diodorus, xix. 48.</note> or the Hanging Gardens, or how the Great King was arrayed; but he was completely engrossed with the most vital concerns of the dominion, asking how large was the Persian army; where the king stationed himself in battle (even as the famed Odysseus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title> x. 407.</note> asked <quote rend="blockquote">Where are his arms that he wields in the battle, and where are his horses?);</quote> and which roads were the shortest for travellers going inland from the sea - so that the strangers were astounded and said, <q>This boy is a ‘great king’; our king is only wealthy.</q> But after Philip’s end, when Alexander was eager to cross over and, already absorbed in his hopes and preparations, was hastening to gain a hold upon Asia, Fortune, seizing upon him, blocked his way, turned him about, dragged him back, and surrounded him with countless distractions and delays. First she threw into the utmost commotion the barbarian elements among his neighbours, and contrived wars with the Illyrians<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 327 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> and Triballians. By these wars he was drawn from his Asiatic projects as far away as the portion of Scythia that lies along <pb xml:id="v.4.p.473"/> the Danube; when, by sundry manoeuvres, he had subjugated all this territory with much danger and great struggles, he was again eager and in haste for the crossing. Again, however, Fortune stirred up Thebes against him, and thrust in his pathway a war with Greeks, and the dread necessity of punishing, by means of slaughter and fire and sword, men that were his kith and kin,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Heracles, a reputed ancestor of the Macedonian kings, was born in Thebes.</note> a necessity which had a most unpleasant ending.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The sack of Thebes and the enslaving of most of the surviving inhabitants; <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf</foreign><title rend="italic">. Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xi. (670 e), and Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, i. 8-9.</note> </p><p rend="indent">After this he crossed with provision for thirty days, as Phylarchus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Cited on the authority of Duris in 327 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> relates; but Aristobulus says,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 327 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> with seventy talents. He divided the greater part of his possessions at home and his royal revenues among his friends; Perdiccas<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xv. (672 b).</note> alone would take nothing when Alexander offered, but asked, <q>What, are you leaving for yourself, Alexander?</q> And when Alexander replied, <q>High hopes!</q>, <q type="unspecified" >Then,</q> said Perdiccas, <q>we also shall share in these; for it is not right to take your possessions, but right to wait in expectation of those of Darius.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p rend="indent">What, then, were the hopes on which Alexander relied when he crossed into Asia? Not a force counted by means of a wall that would hold a city of 10,000 men,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Xerxes counted his army, according to Herodotus vii. 60, by causing 10,000 men to fall in as compactly as possible; then a low wall was built around them; they then marched out, others marched in until the whole host (1,700,000 foot soldies) had been counted.</note> nor fleets that sailed through mountains,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">By Xerxes’ canal through Athos: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 335 e, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>; Herodotus, vii. 22, 23.</note> nor scourges or fetters, insane and barbaric implements for chastising the sea<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Again referring to Xerxes; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Herodotus, vii. 35.</note>; but externally they <pb xml:id="v.4.p.475"/> were the great ambition in his little army, mutual rivalry of hot youth, competition for repute and excellence among his Companions. And within himself he had his own high hopes, reverence for the gods, fidelity toward his friends, frugality, self-control, experience, fearlessness toward death, high courage, humanity, affability, integrity of character, constancy in counsel, quickness in execution, the height of good repute, and a disposition to gain his end in everything honourable. For not appropriately nor convincingly did Homer<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, ii. 478-479.</note> employ a combination of three similes in his comparison describing the fair appearance of Agamemnon: <quote rend="blockquote"> <l>Like in his eyes and his head unto Zeus who delighteth in thunder, </l> <l>Like unto Ares in waist, and in breadth of his chest to Poseidon.</l> </quote> But if the god who begat Alexander made his natural endowment an harmoniously joined combination of many virtues, may we not say that he possessed the high spirit of Cyrus, the discretion of Agesilaüs, the intelligence of Themistocles,the experience of Philip, the daring of Brasidas, the eloquence and statesmanship of Pericles? And, to compare him with the men of still more ancient days, he was more self-restrained than Agamemnon; for Agamemnon set a captive woman<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Chryseis: <title rend="italic" >Iliad</title>, i. 113.</note> above his wedded wife,but Alexander, even before his marriage, kept aloof from his captives. He was more magnanimous than Achilles; for Achilles<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, xxiv. 552-600.</note> gave back the body of Hector for a small ransom, but Alexander buried Darius at great expense; Achilles,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, xix. 140-147.</note> when he had become reconciled, <pb xml:id="v.4.p.477"/> accepted gifts and recompense from his friends to requite him for ceasing from his Wrath, but Alexander enriched his enemies by conquering them. He was more reverent than Diomedes<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <title rend="italic">Iliad</title>, v. 335-352, 855-861.</note>; for Diomedes was ready to fight with gods, but Alexander believed the gods to be the authors of all success. He was more deeply mourned by his relatives than was Odysseus; for Odysseus’<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <title rend="italic">Odyssey</title>, xi. 202-203.</note> mother died of grief, but the mother<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Sisygambis, the mother of Darius: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diodorus, xvii. 118. 3; Justin, xiii. 1; Quintus Curtius, <title rend="italic">Hist. Alexandri</title>, x. 5. 21.</note> of Alexander’s foe, for the goodwill she bore him, shared his death. </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p rend="indent">In short, if Solon’s statesmanship also was due to Fortune, and if Miltiades’ generalship, and Aristeides’<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 97 c.</note> justice were but the result of Fortune, then surely there is no work of Virtue in these men, but it is a name only, talk based on appearance, pervading their lives to no purpose, a figment of the sophists and legislators. But if every one of these men and of others like them became poor or rich, weak or strong, ugly or handsome, lived to a ripe old age or met an untimely death through Fortune, or if each one of them proved himself a great general, a great lawgiver, or great in government and statesmanship through Virtue and Reason, then consider Alexander and compare him with them all. Solon<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf</foreign>.<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Moralia</title>, 828 f; <title rend="italic">Life of Solon</title>, chaps. xv., xvi. (86 d, 87 d); Aristotle, <title rend="italic">Constitution of Athens</title>, 10. 1.</note> brought about a cancellation of debts in Athens which he called the <q>Relief from Burdens</q> (Seisachtheia); but Alexander himself paid the debts which his men owed to their creditors.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 339 c, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>, and the note.</note> Pericles collected tribute from the Greeks and with the money adorned the Acropolis <pb xml:id="v.4.p.479"/> with temples; but Alexander captured the riches of barbarians and sent them to Greece with orders that ten thousand talents<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true" >£2,000,000 or $10,000,000.</note> be used to construct temples for the gods.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Diodorus, xviii. 4. 4.</note> Brasidas’s<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Thucydides, ii. 25. 2.</note> dash along the shore to Methonê through the armed host of the enemy amid showers of missiles made him renowned in Greece; but that daring leap of Alexander in the country of the Oxydrachae,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">The Mallians: <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> 327 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat" >supra</foreign>.</note> incredible to them that hear of it and fearful to them that saw it, when he hurled himself down from the walls into the midst of the enemy, who received him with spears and arrows and naked swords-with what may one compare it, save with the levin bolt that breaks and flashes in the midst of a hurricane, like the apparition of Phoebus that darted down to earth,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> perhaps Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title> xv. 237; iv. 75-80.</note> gleaming round about with flaming armour. The enemy at first were amazed and affrighted and retired with trembling fear; but a moment later, when they saw that he was but one man attacking many, they made a stand against him. </p><p rend="indent">There indeed Fortune made manifest great and splendid results of her kindliness toward Alexander, when she cast him into an insignificant foreign town and shut him in and fenced him round about! And when his men wTere earnestly trying to bring help from without and were attempting to scale the wails, Fortune, by breaking and shattering their ladders, took away their foothold and hurled them from the walls. And of the three<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">327 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>, and <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxiii. (700 c) mention only two; but Plutarch here seems to follow the authority used by Arrian, <title rend="italic">Anabasis</title>, vi. 10, who gives the number as three; <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> also 344 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra</foreign>.</note> men who alone were quick enough to grasp the wall and, throwing themselves <pb xml:id="v.4.p.481"/> down inside, to take their stand beside the king, Fortune straightway snatched up one and made away with him before he could strike a blow; and a second, pierced through by many arrows, was only so far from death that he could see and perceive his king’s danger. But the charges and shouting of the Macedonians were unavailing for they had no machines nor siege engines with them; but in their zeal they tried to hack the walls with their swords, and were forced to break them off with their bare hands, and all but bite their way through. </p><p rend="indent">But the king, who was Fortune’s favourite, and was always guarded and personally protected by her, was caught within like a wild beast in the toils, alone and without succour; nor was he struggling for Susa or Babylon, nor to capture Bactriaj nor to vanquish the great Porus; for in great and glorious conflicts, even though men fail, disgrace, at least, can find no place. But so contentious and malicious was Fortune, so greatly did she favour barbarians and hate Alexander, that she tried to destroy not only his body and his life, but also, in so far as she could, to destroy his repute and to wipe out his fair fame. For it were not a terrible thing for Alexander to fall and lie buried beside the Euphrates or the Hydaspes, nor ignoble to meet death by coming into close combat with Darius or in confronting the horses and swords and battle-axes of the Persians as they fought to defend their king, nor to be overthrown while he bestrode the walls of Babylon and to fall from his high hope. Thus fell Pelopidas and Epameinondas; their death was a death belonging to Virtue, not to misfortune, engaged as they were in such a high emprise. But of what sort was the deed of Fortune, who is now <pb xml:id="v.4.p.483"/> under scrutiny? Was it not that on the farthest outposts of a land beside a foreign river within the walls of an obscure hamlet, which surrounded and hid away. from sight the lord and master of the inhabited world, he should perish, smitten and stricken by ignominious weapons and whatever else lay at hand? For his head was wounded through his helmet by an axe, and someone shot an arrow through his breastplate so that it penetrated the bones of his breast and was lodged there firmly, while the shaft protruded and hampered him and the iron point was four fingers broad and five fingers long.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Plutarch the rhetorician increases by one finger’s-breadth the dimensions of the arrow-point which are given by Plutarch the biographer in his <title rend="italic">Life of Alexander</title>, chap. lxiii. (700 e).</note> But - the extreme of all the dangers he confronted - while he was defending himself against those who attacked him in front, the archer who shot him had plucked up courage to approach him with a sword, but Alexander with his dagger was too quick for the man and knocked him down and killed him; but while he was thus occupied, someone ran out from a mill, and gave him a blow on the neck with a cudgel from behind; this confused his senses, and his head swam. But Virtue was by his side and in him she engendered daring, and in his companions strength and zeal. For men like Limnaeus and Ptolemy and Leonnatus and all those who had surmounted the wall or had broken through it took their stand before him and were a bulwark of Virtue, exposing their bodies in the face of the foe and even their lives for the goodwill and love they bore their king. Surely it is not due to Fortune that the companions of good kings risk their lives and willingly die for them; but this they do <pb xml:id="v.4.p.485"/> through a passion for Virtue, even as bees, as if under the spell of love-charms, approach and closely surround their sovereign. </p><p rend="indent">What spectator, then, who might without danger to himself have been present at that scene, would not exclaim that he was witnessing the mighty contest of Fortune and Virtue; that through Fortune the foreign host was prevailing beyond its deserts, but through Virtue the Greeks were holding out beyond their ability? And if the enemy gains the upper hand, this will be the work of Fortune or of some jealous deity or of divine retribution; but if the Greeks prevail, it will be Virtue and daring, friendship and fidelity, that will win the guerdon of victory? These were, in fact, the only support that Alexander had with him at this time, since Fortune had put a barrier between him and the rest of his forces and equipment, fleets, horse, and camp. </p><p rend="indent">Finally, the Macedonians routed the barbarians, and, when they had fallen, pulled down their city on their heads. But this was no help to Alexander; for he had been hurried from the field, arrow and all, and he had the shaft in his vitals; the arrow was as a bond or bolt holding his breastplate to his body. And when they tried forcibly to pull it out of the wound by the roots, as it were, the iron would not budge, since it was lodged in the bony part of the breast in front of the heart. They did not dare to saw off the protruding portion of the shaft, since they were afraid that the bone might be split by the jarring and cause excruciating pain, and that an internal haemorrhage might result. But when Alexander perceived their great perplexity and hesitation, he himself tried with his dagger to cut off the arrow <pb xml:id="v.4.p.487"/> close to his breastplate; but his hand was unsteady and affected by a torpid languor from the inflammation of the wound. Accordingly with encouraging words he urged those that were unwounded to take hold and not to be afraid; and he railed at some who were weeping and could not control themselves, others he branded as deserters, since they had not the courage to Come to his assistance. And he cried aloud to his Companions, <q>Let no one be fainthearted even for my sake! For it will not be believed that I do not fear death, if you fear death for me!</q> <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Some think the narrative closes abruptly, and that it should have been continued to include at least Alexander’s recovery, but the Greeks did not always insist on a happy ending narrated in full.</note> </p> </div> </div> </div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
