<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hymn 3 To Apollo</title>
            <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
            <editor role="translator">Hugh G. Evelyn-White</editor>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>William Merrill</name>
               <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
               <name>David Smith</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
         </publicationStmt>


         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
               <author>Anonymous</author>
               <title>The Homeric Hymns and Homerica with an English Translation by Hugh G. Evelyn-White.
            Homeric Hymns</title>
               <publisher>Cambridge, MA.,Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
               <date>1914</date>
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
        <refsDecl n="CTS">
          <cRefPattern n="line"
            matchPattern="(\\w+)"
            replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body//tei:l[@n=\'$1\'])">
            <p>This pointer pattern extracts line</p>
          </cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl>
          <refState unit="line"/>
        </refsDecl>
        <!--<refsDecl>
	<refState n="chunk" unit="card"/>
      </refsDecl>-->
    </encodingDesc>

      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            <!--<language ident="xgreek">Transliterated Greek</language>-->
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>

      <revisionDesc>
        <change when="1988-01-01" who="Bill Merrill">Text keyboarded in the Philippines.  Basic SGML tagging by Bill Merrill</change>
        <change when="1993-08-01" who="EM">Go over text, check cardbreaks, and change tags to be more TEI conformant.</change>
        <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
        <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        <change when="2015-12-11" who="Lisa Cerrato">fixing titles and headers</change>
        <change when="2016-01-06" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc conversion and CTS related changes</change>
      </revisionDesc>
    
    
    
    
    
    
    

  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
        <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0013.tlg003.perseus-eng2">
           <div type="textpart"><head>To Delian Apollo</head>
           <milestone n="1" unit="card"/><l n="1"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>I will remember and not be unmindful of Apollo who shoots afar. As he goes through
          the house of Zeus, the gods tremble before him and all spring up from their seats when he
          draws near, as he bends his bright bow. </l>
            <l n="5">But Leto alone stays by the side of Zeus who delights in thunder; and then she
          unstrings his bow, and closes his quiver, and takes his archery from his strong shoulders
          in her hands and hangs them on a golden peg against a pillar of his father's house. Then
          she leads him to a seat and makes him sit: </l>
            <l n="10">and the Father gives him nectar in a golden cup welcoming his dear son, while the
          other gods make him sit down there, and queenly Leto rejoices because she bare a mighty
          son and an archer. Rejoice, blessed Leto, for you bare glorious children, </l>
            <l n="15">the lord Apollo and Artemis who delights in arrows; her in Ortygia, and him in
          rocky <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>, as you rested against the great
              mass of the Cynthian hill hard by a palm-tree by the streams of Inopus. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>How, then, shall I
          sing of you who in all ways are a worthy theme of song? </l>
            <l n="20">For everywhere, O Phoebus, the whole range of song is fallen to you, both over the
          mainland that rears heifers and over the isles. All mountain-peaks and high headlands of
          lofty hills and rivers flowing out to the deep and beaches sloping seawards and havens of
          the sea are your delight. </l>
            <l n="25">Shall I sing how at the first Leto bare you to be the joy of men, as she rested
          against Mount Cynthus in that rocky isle, in sea-girt <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> —while on either hand a dark wave rolled on landwards driven by
          shrill winds —whence arising you rule over all mortal men? </l>
          <l n="30"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Among those who are in <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, and in the
          township of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and in the isle of
            <placeName key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, famous for ships, in <placeName key="perseus,Aegae">Aegae</placeName> and Eiresiae and Peparethus near the sea, in Thracian Athos and
            <placeName key="tgn,4008379">Pelion</placeName>'s towering heights and Thracian Samos
          and the shady hills of Ida, </l>
            <l n="35">in Scyros and <placeName key="tgn,7018000">Phocaea</placeName> and the high hill
          of Autocane and fair-lying Imbros and smouldering <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> and rich <placeName key="tgn,7002672">Lesbos</placeName>, home of
            <placeName key="tgn,1086655">Macar</placeName>, the son of Aeolus, and <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>, brightest of all the isles that lie in the sea, and
          craggy Mimas and the heights of Corycus </l>
            <l n="40">and gleaming Claros and the sheer hill of Aesagea and watered <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName> and the steep heights of Mycale, in <placeName key="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName> and Cos, the city of Meropian men, and steep
            <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidos</placeName> and windy <placeName key="tgn,7016628">Carpathos</placeName>, in <placeName key="tgn,7012053">Naxos</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7011023">Paros</placeName> and rocky Rhenaea — </l>
            <l n="45">so far roamed Leto in travail with the god who shoots afar, to see if any land
          would be willing to make a dwelling for her son. <milestone n="47" unit="card"/>But they
          greatly trembled and feared, and none, not even the richest of them, dared receive
          Phoebus, </l>
            <l n="50">until queenly Leto set foot on <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>
              and uttered winged words and asked her: <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote" -->“<placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>,
          if you would be willing to be the abode of my son Phoebus Apollo and make him a rich
          temple —; for no other will touch you, as you will find: and I think you will never be
          rich in oxen and sheep, </l>
            <l n="55">nor bear vintage nor yet produce plants abundantly. But if you have the temple of
          far-shooting Apollo, all men will bring you hecatombs and gather here, and incessant
          savour of rich sacrifice will always arise, and you will feed those who dwell in you </l>
          <l n="60">from the hand of strangers; for truly your own soil is not rich.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote" --> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>So spake Leto.
          And <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> rejoiced and answered and said:
            <!-- <milestone type="startquote" -->“Leto, most glorious daughter of great Coeus, joyfully would I receive your child the
          far-shooting lord; for it is all too true that I am ill-spoken of </l>
            <l n="65">among men, whereas thus I should become very greatly honored. But this saying I
          fear, and I will not hide it from you, Leto. They say that Apollo will be one that is very
          haughty and will greatly lord it among gods and men all over the fruitful earth. </l>
            <l n="70">Therefore, I greatly fear in heart and spirit that as soon as he sees the light of
          the sun, he will scorn this island —for truly I have but a hard, rocky soil —and overturn
          me and thrust me down with his feet in the depths of the sea; then will the great ocean
          wash deep above my head for ever, </l>
            <l n="75">and he will go to another land such as will please him, there to make his temple
          and wooded groves. So many-footed creatures of the sea will make their lairs in me and
          black seals their dwellings undisturbed, because I lack people. Yet if you will but dare
          to swear a great oath, goddess, </l>
            <l n="80">that here first he will build a glorious temple to be an oracle for men, then let
          him afterwards </l>
            <l n="81a">make temples and wooded groves amongst all men; for surely he will be greatly
              renowned.<!-- <milestone type="endquote" --> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>So said <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>. And Leto swear the
              great oath of the gods: <!-- <milestone type="startquote" -->“Now hear this, Earth and wide Heaven above, </l>
            <l n="85">and dropping water of Styx (this is the strongest and most awful oath for the
          blessed gods), surely Phoebus shall have here his fragrant altar and precinct, and you he
          shall honor above all.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote" --><milestone n="89" unit="card"/> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Now when Leto had sworn and ended
          her oath, </l>
            <l n="90">
               <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> was very glad at the birth of the
          far-shooting lord. But Leto was racked nine days and nine nights with pangs beyond wont. </l>
            <l n="95">And there were with her all the chiefest of the goddesses, Dione and Rhea and
          Ichnaea and Themis and loud-moaning Amphitrite and the other deathless goddesses save
          white-armed Hera, who sat in the halls of cloud-gathering Zeus. Only Eilithyia, goddess of
          sore travail, had not heard of Leto's trouble, for she sat on the top of <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> beneath golden clouds by white-armed Hera's </l>
            <l n="100">contriving, who kept her close through envy, because Leto with the lovely tresses
              was soon to bear a son faultless and strong. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>But the goddesses sent out Iris from the
          well-set isle to bring Eilithyia, promising her a great necklace strung with golden
          threads, nine cubits long. </l>
            <l n="105">And they bade Iris call her aside from white-armed Hera, lest she might
          afterwards turn her from coming with her words. When swift Iris, fleet of foot as the
          wind, had heard all this, she set to run; and quickly finishing all the distance she came
          to the home of the gods, sheer <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>, </l>
            <l n="110">and forthwith called Eilithyia out from the hall to the door and spoke winged
          words to her, telling her all as the goddesses who dwell on <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> had bidden her. So she moved the heart of Eilithyia in her dear
          breast; and they went their way, like shy wild-doves in their going. </l>
          <l n="115"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>And as soon as Eilithyia the goddess of sore travail set foot on <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>, the pains of birth seized Leto, and she longed to
          bring forth; so she cast her arms about a palm tree and kneeled on the soft meadow while
          the earth laughed for joy beneath. Then the child leaped forth to the light, and all the
          goddesses raised a cry. </l>
            <l n="120">Straightway, great Phoebus, the goddesses washed you purely and cleanly with
          sweet water, and swathed you in a white garment of fine texture, new-woven, and fastened a
          golden band about you. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Now Leto did not give Apollo, bearer of the golden blade, her
          breast; but Themis duly poured nectar and ambrosia </l>
            <l n="125">with her divine hands: and Leto was glad because she had borne a strong son and
          an archer. But as soon as you had tasted that divine heavenly food, O Phoebus, you could
          no longer then be held by golden cords nor confined with bands, but all their ends were
          undone. </l>
          <l n="130">Forth-with Phoebus Apollo spoke out among the deathless goddesses:<milestone n="131" unit="card"/><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“The lyre and the curved bow shall ever be dear to me, and I will
            declare to men the unfailing will of Zeus.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>So said Phoebus, the long-haired god who
          shoots afar and began to walk upon the wide-pathed earth; </l>
             <l n="135">and all the goddesses were amazed at him. Then with gold all <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> [<surplus reason="intrusive">was laden, beholding the child of Zeus and Leto,
          for joy because the god chose her above the islands and shore to make his dwelling in her:
          and she loved him yet more in her heart.</surplus>] blossomed as does a mountain-top with woodland
          flowers. </l>
          <l n="140"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>And you, O lord Apollo, god of the silver bow, shooting afar, now walked on
          craggy Cynthus, and now kept wandering about the islands and the people in them. Many are
          your temples and wooded groves, and all peaks and towering bluffs </l>
            <l n="145">of lofty mountains and rivers flowing to the sea are dear to you, Phoebus, yet in
            <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> do you most delight your heart; for
          there the long robed Ionians gather in your honor with their children and shy wives: with
          boxing and dancing and song, </l>
            <l n="150">mindful, they delight you so often as they hold their gathering. A man would say
          that they were deathless and unageing if he should then come upon the Ionians so met
          together. For he would see the graces of them all, and would be pleased in heart gazing at
          the men and well-girded women </l>
            <l n="155">with their swift ships and great wealth. And there is this great wonder besides
          —and its renown shall never perish —, the girls of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>, hand-maidens of the Far-shooter; for when they have praised Apollo
          first, and also Leto and Artemis who delights in arrows, </l>
            <l n="160">they sing a strain telling of men and women of past days, and charm the tribes of
          men. Also they can imitate the tongues of all men and their clattering speech: each would
          say that he himself were singing, so close to truth is their sweet song. </l>
          <l n="165"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>And now may Apollo be favorable and Artemis; and farewell all you maidens.
          Remember me in after time whenever any one of men on earth, a stranger who has seen and
          suffered much, comes here and asks of you: <!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Whom think ye, girls, is the sweetest singer
            that comes here, and in whom do you most delight?”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> </l>
          <l n="170">Then answer, each and all, with one voice: <!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“He is a blind man, and dwells in
            rocky <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>: his lays are evermore supreme.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> As
          for me, I will carry your renown as far as I roam over the earth </l>
            <l n="175">to the well-placed cities of man, and they will believe also; for indeed this
          thing is true. And I will never cease to praise far-shooting Apollo, god of the silver
          bow, whom rich-haired Leto bare.</l></div>

          
           
          
<div type="textpart">
<head>To Pythian Apollo</head>
            <milestone n="179" unit="card"/><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><l n="179">O Lord, <placeName key="tgn,7001294">Lycia</placeName> is yours and lovely
            <placeName key="tgn,7016631">Maeonia</placeName>
            </l>
            <l n="180">and <placeName key="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>, charming city by the
          sea, but over wave-girt <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> you greatly reign
              your own self. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Leto's all-glorious son goes to rocky <placeName key="tgn,7010770">Pytho</placeName>, playing upon his hollow lyre, clad in divine, perfumed garments; and
          his lyre,</l>
            <l n="185">at the touch of the golden key, sings sweet. Thence, swift as thought, he speeds
          from earth to <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>, to the house of Zeus, to
          join the gathering of the other gods: then straightway the undying gods think only of the
          lyre and song, and all the Muses together, voice sweetly answering voice, </l>
            <l n="190">hymn the unending gifts the gods enjoy and the sufferings of men, all that they
          endure at the hands of the deathless gods, and how they live witless and helpless and
          cannot find healing for death or defence against old age. Meanwhile the rich-tressed
          Graces and cheerful Seasons dance with </l>
            <l n="195">Harmonia and Hebe and Aphrodite, daughter of Zeus, holding each other by the
          wrist. And among them sings one, not mean nor puny, but tall to look upon and enviable in
          mien, Artemis who delights in arrows, sister of Apollo. </l>
            <l n="200">Among them sport Ares and the keen-eyed Slayer of Argus, while Apollo plays his
          lyre stepping high and featly and a radiance shines around him, the gleaming of his feet
          and close-woven vest. And they, </l>
            <l n="205">even gold-tressed Leto and wise Zeus, rejoice in their great hearts as they watch
              their dear son playing among the undying gods. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>How then shall I sing of you —though in all
          ways you are a worthy theme for song? Shall I sing of you as wooer and in the fields of
          love, how you went wooing the daughter of Azan </l>
            <l n="210">along with god-like Ischys the son of well-horsed Elatius, or with Phorbas sprung
          from Triops, or with Ereutheus, or with Leucippus and the wife of Leucippus<gap reason="lost"/>you on
          foot, he with his chariot, yet he fell not short of Triops. Or shall I sing how at the
          first </l>
            <l n="215">you went about the earth seeking a place of oracle for men, O far-shooting
          Apollo? To Pieria first you went down from <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> and passed by sandy Lectus and Enienae and through the land of the
          Perrhaebi. Soon you came to Iolcus and set foot on Cenaeum in <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, famed for ships: </l>
            <l n="220">you stood in the Lelantine plain, but it pleased not your heart to make a temple
          there and wooded groves. From there you crossed the Euripus, far-shooting Apollo, and went
          up the green, holy hills, going on to Mycalessus and grassy-bedded Teumessus,<milestone n="225" unit="card"/>
            </l>
            <l n="225">and so came to the wood-clad abode of Thebe; for as yet no man lived in holy
              Thebe, nor were there tracks or ways about Thebe's wheat-bearing plain as yet. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>And further
          still you went, O far-shooting Apollo, </l>
            <l n="230">and came to Onchestus, Poseidon's bright grove: there the new-broken colt
          distressed with drawing the trim chariot gets spirit again, and the skilled driver springs
          from his car and goes on his way. Then the horses for a while rattle the empty car, being
          rid of guidance; </l>
            <l n="235">and if they break the chariot in the woody grove, men look after the horses, but
          tilt the chariot and leave it there; for this was the rite from the very first. And the
          drivers pray to the lord of the shrine; but the chariot falls to the lot of the god.
              <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Further yet you went, O far-shooting Apollo, </l>
            <l n="240">and reached next Cephissus' sweet stream which pours forth its sweet-flowing
          water from Lilaea, and crossing over it, O worker from afar, you passed many-towered
          Ocalea and reached grassy Haliartus. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Then you went towards Telphusa: and there the
          pleasant place seemed fit for </l>
            <l n="245">making a temple and wooded grove. You came very near and spoke to her: <!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Telphusa,
          here I am minded to make a glorious temple, an oracle for men, and hither they will always
          bring perfect hecatombs, </l>
            <l n="250">both those who live in rich <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>
          and those of <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and all the wave-washed
          isles, coming to seek oracles. And I will deliver to them all counsel that cannot fail,
          giving answer in my rich temple.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>So said Phoebus Apollo, and laid out all the foundations </l>
            <l n="255">throughout, wide and very long. But when Telphusa saw this, she was angry in
              heart and spoke, saying: <!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Lord Phoebus, worker from afar, I will speak a word of counsel
          to your heart, since you are minded to make here a glorious temple to be an oracle for men
          who will always </l>
            <l n="260">bring hither perfect hecatombs for you; yet I will speak out, and do you lay up
          my words in your heart. The trampling of swift horses and the sound of mules watering at
          my sacred springs will always irk you, and men will like better to gaze at </l>
            <l n="265">the well-made chariots and stamping, swift-footed horses than at your great
          temple and the many treasures that are within. <milestone n="267" unit="card"/>But if you
          will be moved by me —for you, lord, are stronger and mightier than I, and your strength is
          very great —build at <placeName key="tgn,7018211">Crisa</placeName> below the glades of
            <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>: </l>
            <l n="270">there no bright chariot will clash, and there will be no noise of swift-footed
          horses near your well-built altar. But so the glorious tribes of men will bring gifts to
          you as Iepaeon (‘Hail-Healer’), and you will receive with delight rich sacrifices from the
          people dwelling round about.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> </l>
            <l n="275">So said Telphusa, that she alone, and not the Far-Shooter, should have renown
              there; and she persuaded the Far-Shooter. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Further yet you went, far-shooting Apollo, until
          you came to the town of the presumptuous Phlegyae who dwell on this earth </l>
            <l n="280">in a lovely glade near the Cephisian lake, caring not for Zeus. And thence you
          went speeding swiftly to the mountain ridge, and came to <placeName key="tgn,7018211">Crisa</placeName> beneath snowy <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>, a
          foothill turned towards the west: a cliff hangs over it from above, and a hollow, rugged
          glade runs under.</l>
            <l n="285">There the lord Phoebus Apollo resolved to make his lovely temple, and thus he
              said: <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“In this place I am minded to build a glorious temple to be an oracle for men, and
          here they will always bring perfect hecatombs, </l>
            <l n="290">both they who dwell in rich <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>
          and the men of <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and from all the
          wave-washed isles, coming to question me. And I will deliver to them all counsel that
          cannot fail, answering them in my rich temple.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>When he had said this, Phoebus Apollo laid
          out all the foundations </l>
            <l n="295">throughout, wide and very long; and upon these the sons of Erginus, Trophonius
          and Agamedes, dear to the deathless gods, laid a footing of stone. And the countless
          tribes of men built the whole temple of wrought stones, to be sung of for ever. </l>
            <l n="300"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>But near by was a sweet flowing spring, and there with his strong bow the lord,
          the son of Zeus, killed the bloated, great she-dragon, a fierce monster wont to do great
          mischief to men upon earth, to men themselves and to their thin-shanked sheep; for she was
          a very bloody plague.<milestone n="305" unit="card"/>
            </l>
            <l n="305">She it was who once received from gold-throned Hera and brought up fell, cruel
          Typhaon to be a plague to men. Once on a time Hera bare him because she was angry with
          father Zeus, when the Son of Cronos bare all-glorious Athena in his head. Thereupon
          queenly Hera was angry </l>
  <l n="310">and spoke thus among the assembled gods: <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Hear from me, all gods and goddesses,
          how cloud-gathering Zeus begins to dishonor me wantonly, when he has made me his
          true-hearted wife. See now, apart from me he has given birth to bright-eyed Athena </l>
            <l n="315">who is foremost among all the blessed gods. But my son Hephaestus whom I bare </l>
            <l n="317a">was weakly among all the blessed gods and shrivelled of foot, a shame and a
          disgrace to me in heaven, whom I myself took in my hands and cast out so that he fell in
          the great sea. But silver-shod Thetis the daughter of Nereus </l>
            <l n="320">took and cared for him with her sisters: would that she had done other service to
          the blessed gods! O wicked one and crafty! What else will you now devise? How dared you by
          yourself give birth to bright-eyed Athena? Would not I have borne you a child —I, who was
          at least called your wife </l>
            <l n="325">among the undying gods who hold wide heaven. </l>
            <l n="325a">Beware now lest I devise some evil thing for you hereafter: yes, now I will
          contrive that a son be born me to be foremost among the undying gods —and that without
          casting shame on the holy bond of wedlock between you and me. </l>
            <l n="330">And I will not come to your bed, but will consort with the blessed gods far off
              from you.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>When she had so spoken, she went apart from the gods, being very angry. Then
          straightway large-eyed queenly Hera prayed, striking the ground flatwise with her hand,
          and speaking thus: </l>
  <l n="335"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Hear now, I pray, Earth and wide Heaven above and you Titan gods who dwell
          beneath the earth about great Tartarus, and from whom are sprung both gods and men! Harken
          you now to me, one and all, and grant that I may bear a child apart from Zeus, no wit
          lesser than him in strength —nay, let him be as much stronger than Zeus as all-seeing Zeus
          than Cronos.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> </l>
            <l n="340">Thus she cried and lashed the earth with her strong hand. Then the life-giving
          earth was moved: and when Hera saw it she was glad in heart, for she thought her prayer
          would be fulfilled. And thereafter she never came to the bed of wise Zeus for a full year, </l>
            <l n="345">nor to sit in her carved chair as aforetime to plan wise counsel for him, but
          stayed in her temples where many pray, and delighted in her offerings, large-eyed queenly
            Hera.<milestone n="349" unit="card"/> But when the months and days were fulfilled </l>
            <l n="350">and the seasons duly came on as the earth moved round, she bare one neither like
          the gods nor mortal men, fell, cruel Typhaon, to be a plague to men. Straightway
          large-eyed queenly Hera took him and bringing one evil thing to another such, gave him to
          the dragoness; and she received him. </l>
            <l n="355">And this Typhaon used to work great mischief among the famous tribes of men.
          Whosoever met the dragoness, the day of doom would sweep him away, until the lord Apollo,
          who deals death from afar, shot a strong arrow at her. Then she, rent with bitter pangs,
          lay drawing great gasps for breath and rolling about that place. </l>
            <l n="360">An awful noise swelled up unspeakable as she writhed continually this way and
          that amid the wood: and so she left her life, breathing it forth in blood. Then Phoebus
          Apollo boasted over her: <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Now rot here upon the soil that feeds man' You at least shall
          live no more to be a fell bane to men </l>
            <l n="365">who eat the fruit of the all-nourishing earth, and who will bring hither perfect
          hecatombs. Against cruel death neither Typhoeus shall avail you nor ill-famed Chimera, but
          here shall the Earth and shining Hyperion make you rot.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> </l>
            <l n="370"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Thus said Phoebus, exulting over her: and darkness covered her eyes. And the holy
          strength of Helios made her rot away there; wherefore the place is now called <placeName key="tgn,7010770">Pytho</placeName>, and men call the lord Apollo by another name,
          Pythian; because on that spot the power of piercing Helios made the monster rot away. </l>
            <l n="375"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Then Phoebus Apollo saw that the sweet-flowing spring had beguiled him, and he
          started out in anger against Telphusa; and soon coming to her, he stood close by and spoke
          to her: <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Telphusa, you were not, after all, to keep to yourself this lovely place by
          deceiving my mind, </l>
            <l n="380">and pour forth your clear flowing water: here my renown shall also be and not
              yours alone?”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Thus spoke the lord, far-working Apollo, and pushed over upon her a crag
          with a shower of rocks, hiding her streams: and he made himself an altar in a wooded grove </l>
            <l n="385">very near the clear-flowing stream. In that place all men pray to the great one
              by the name Telphusian, because he humbled the stream of holy Telphusa. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Then Phoebus
          Apollo pondered in his heart what men he should bring in</l>
            <l n="390">to be his ministers in sacrifice and to serve him in rocky <placeName key="tgn,7010770">Pytho</placeName>. And while he considered this, he became aware of a
          swift ship upon the wine-like sea in which were many men and goodly, Cretans from
            <placeName key="tgn,7010870">Cnossos</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Inscriptions show that there was a temple of Apollo Delphinius (cp. ll. 495-6) at
              <placeName key="tgn,7010870">Cnossus</placeName> and a Cretan month bearing the same
            name.</note> the city of Minos, they who do sacrifice to the prince and announce his
          decrees, </l>
            <l n="395">whatsoever Phoebus Apollo, bearer of the golden blade, speaks in answer from his
          laurel tree below the dells of <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>.<milestone n="397" unit="card"/> These men were sailing in their
          black ship for traffic and for profit to sandy <placeName key="perseus,Pylos">Pylos</placeName> and to the men of <placeName key="perseus,Pylos">Pylos</placeName>.
          But Phoebus Apollo met them: </l>
            <l n="400">in the open sea he sprang upon their swift ship, like a dolphin in shape, and lay
          there, a great and awesome monster, and none of them gave heed so as to understand<note anchored="true" resp="ed">
                  <hi rend="ital">sc.</hi> that the dolphin was really
            Apollo.</note>; </l>
            <l n="402a">but they sought to cast the dolphin overboard. But he kept shaking the black
          ship every way and making the timbers quiver. So they sat silent in their craft for fear, </l>
            <l n="405">and did not loose the sheets throughout the black, hollow ship, nor lowered the
          sail of their dark-prowed vessel, but as they had set it first of all with oxhide ropes,
          so they kept sailing on; for a rushing south wind hurried on the swift ship from behind.
          First they passed by Malea, </l>
            <l n="410">and then along the Laconian coast they came to Taenarum, sea-garlanded town and
          country of Helios who gladdens men, where the thick-fleeced sheep of the lord Helios feed
          continually and occupy a gladsome country. There they wished to put their ship to shore,
          and land </l>
            <l n="415">and comprehend the great marvel and see with their eyes whether the monster would
          remain upon the deck of the hollow ship, or spring back into the briny deep where fishes
          shoal. But the well-built ship would not obey the helm, but went on its way all along
            <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>: </l>
            <l n="420">and the lord, far-working Apollo, guided it easily with the breath of the breeze.
          So the ship ran on its course and came to Arena and lovely Argyphea and Thryon, the ford
          of Alpheus, and well-placed Aepy and sandy <placeName key="perseus,Pylos">Pylos</placeName> and the men of <placeName key="perseus,Pylos">Pylos</placeName>; </l>
            <l n="425">past Cruni it went and <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName> and
          past <placeName key="perseus,Dyme">Dyme</placeName> and fair <placeName key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName>, where the Epei rule. And at the time when she was making for Pherae,
          exulting in the breeze from Zeus, there appeared to them below the clouds the steep
          mountain of <placeName key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName>, and Dulichium and Same and
          wooded <placeName key="tgn,7011374">Zacynthus</placeName>. </l>
            <l n="430">But when they were passed by all the coast of <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>, then, towards <placeName key="tgn,7018211">Crisa</placeName>,
          that vast gulf began to heave in sight which through all its length cuts off the rich isle
          of Pelops. There came on them a strong, clear west-wind by ordinance of Zeus and blew from
          heaven vehemently, that with all speed </l>
            <l n="435">the ship might finish coursing over the briny water of the sea. So they began
          again to voyage back towards the dawn and the sun: and the lord Apollo, son of Zeus, led
          them on until they reached far-seen <placeName key="tgn,7018211">Crisa</placeName>, land
          of vines, and into haven: there the sea-coursing ship grounded on the sands. </l>
            <l n="440"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Then, like a star at noonday, the lord, far-working Apollo, leaped from the ship:
          flashes of fire flew from him thick and their brightness reached to heaven. He entered
          into his shrine between priceless tripods, <milestone n="444" unit="card"/>and there made
          a flame to flare up bright, showing forth the splendor of his shafts, so that their
          radiance </l>
            <l n="445">filled all <placeName key="tgn,7018211">Crisa</placeName>, and the wives and
          well-girded daughters of the Crisaeans raised a cry at that outburst of Phoebus; for he
          cast great fear upon them all. From his shrine he sprang forth again, swift as a thought,
          to speed again to the ship, bearing the form of a man, brisk and sturdy, </l>
            <l n="450">in the prime of his youth, while his broad shoulders were covered with his hair:
              and he spoke to the Cretans, uttering winged words: <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Strangers, who are you? Whence come
          you sailing along the paths of the sea? Are you for traffic, or do you wander at random
          over the sea as pirates do who put </l>
            <l n="455">their own lives to hazard and bring mischief to men of foreign parts as they
          roam? Why rest you so and are afraid, and do not go ashore nor stow the gear of your black
          ship? For that is the custom of men who live by bread, whenever they come to land in their
          dark ships from the main, </l>
  <l n="460">spent with toil: at once desire for sweet food catches them about the heart.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>So
          speaking, he put courage in their hearts, and the master of the Cretans answered him and
          said: <!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Stranger —though you are nothing like mortal men </l>
            <l n="465">in shape or stature, but are as the deathless gods —hail and all happiness to
          you, and may the gods give you good. Now tell me truly that I may surely know it: what
          country is this, and what land, and what men live herein? As for us, with thoughts set
          otherwards, we were sailing over the great sea </l>
            <l n="470">to <placeName key="perseus,Pylos">Pylos</placeName> from <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> (for from there we declare that we are sprung), but
          now are come on shipboard to this place by no means willingly —another way and other paths
          —and gladly would we return. But one of the deathless gods brought us here against our
          will.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Then far-working Apollo answered them and said: </l>
  <l n="475"><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Strangers who once dwelt about wooded <placeName key="tgn,7010870">Cnossos</placeName> but now shall return no more each to his loved city and fair house
          and dear wife; here shall you keep my rich temple that is honored by many men. </l>
            <l n="480">I am the son of Zeus; Apollo is my name: but you I brought here over the wide
          gulf of the sea, meaning you no hurt; nay, here you shall keep my rich temple that is
          greatly honored among men, and you shall know the plans of the deathless gods, and by
          their will </l>
            <l n="485">you shall be honored continually for all time. And now come, make haste and do as
          I say. First loose the sheets and lower the sail, and then draw the swift ship up upon the
          land. Take out your goods and the gear of the straight ship, </l>
            <l n="490">and make an altar upon the beach of the sea: light fire upon it and make an
          offering of white meal. Next, stand side by side around the altar and pray:<milestone n="493" unit="card"/> and in as much as at the first on the hazy sea I sprang upon the
          swift ship in the form of a dolphin, </l>
            <l n="495">pray to me as Apollo Delphinius; also the altar itself shall be called Delphinius
          and overlooking<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The epithets are transferred from the god
            to his altar “Overlooking” is especially an epithet of Zeus, as in Apollonius Rhodius
            ii. <date>1124</date>.</note> for ever. Afterwards, sup beside your dark ship and pour
          an offering to the blessed gods who dwell on <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>. But when you have put away craving for sweet food, </l>
            <l n="500">come with me singing the hymn Ie Paean (Hail, Healer!), until you come to the
              place where you shall keep my rich temple.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>So said Apollo. And they readily harkened to
          him and obeyed him. First they unfastened the sheets and let down the sail and lowered the
          mast by the forestays upon the mast-rest. </l>
            <l n="505">Then, landing upon the beach of the sea, they hauled up the ship from the water
          to dry land and fixed long stays under it. Also they made an altar upon the beach of the
          sea, and when they had lit a fire, made an offering of white meal, </l>
            <l n="510">and prayed standing around the altar as Apollo had bidden them. Then they took
          their meal by the swift, black ship, and poured an offering to the blessed gods who dwell
          on <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>. And when they had put away craving
          for drink and food, they started out with the lord Apollo, the son of Zeus, to lead them, </l>
            <l n="515">holding a lyre in his hands, and playing sweetly as he stepped high and featly.
          So the Cretans followed him to <placeName key="tgn,7010770">Pytho</placeName>, marching in
          time as they chanted the Ie Paean after the manner of the Cretan paean-singers and of
          those in whose hearts the heavenly Muse has put sweet-voiced song. </l>
            <l n="520">With tireless feet they approached the ridge and straightway came to <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName> and the lovely place where they were to dwell
          honored by many men. There Apollo brought them and showed them his most holy sanctuary and
          rich temple. <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>But their spirit was stirred in their dear breasts, </l>
  <l n="525">and the master of the Cretans asked him, saying: <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/><!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Lord, since you have brought us
          here far from our dear ones and our fatherland, —for so it seemed good to your heart,—tell
          us now how we shall live. That we would know of you. This land is not to be desired either
          for vineyards or for pastures </l>
  <l n="530">so that we can live well thereon and also minister to men.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --><milestone n="531" unit="card"/> <milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>Then Apollo, the son of Zeus, smiled upon them and said: <!-- <milestone type="startquote"> -->“Foolish mortals
          and poor drudges are you, that you seek cares and hard toils and straits! Easily will I
          tell you a word and set it in your hearts. </l>
            <l n="535">Though each one of you with knife in hand should slaughter sheep continually, yet
          would you always have abundant store, even all that the glorious tribes of men bring here
          for me. But guard you my temple and receive the tribes of men that gather to this place, </l>
            <l n="539a">and especially show mortal men my will, and do you keep righteousness in your
          heart. </l>
            <l n="539b">But if any shall be disobedient and pay no heed to my warning, </l>
            <l n="540">or if there shall be any idle word or deed and outrage as is common among mortal
          men, then other men shall be your masters and with a strong hand shall make you subject
          for ever. All has been told you: do you keep it in your heart.”<!-- <milestone type="endquote"> --> </l>
            <l n="545"><milestone unit="Para" ed="P"/>And so, farewell, son of Zeus and Leto; but I will remember you and another hymn
          also. </l></div>
        </div>
      </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
