<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Meidias</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>The brutality and insolence with which Meidias treats everyone alike are, I
                    suppose, as well known to you, gentlemen of the jury, as to all other citizens.
                    For myself, I have simply taken the course which anyone of you would have
                    adopted, had he been the victim of a similar outrage. I lodged a plaint in the
                    Assembly against him as an offender in connection with the festival, not only
                    for his assault on my person at the Dionysia, but for many other acts of
                    violence during the whole period when I served as chorus-master. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>But when the whole people, acting honorably and rightly, evinced such anger, such
                    exasperation, such deep concern at the wrongs which they knew I had suffered,
                    that, in spite of the frantic efforts of the defendant and a few supporters,
                    they were deaf to their arguments, shut their eyes to their wealth and their
                    promises, and condemned him by an unanimous show of hands, thereupon, gentlemen
                    of the jury, many citizens, including some of you who are here in court, came to
                    me and demanded and even implored that I should take the further step of
                    bringing Meidias under your jurisdiction; and they did so, I think, for two
                    reasons, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, because, so
                    help me heaven! they thought that my own wrongs were serious, and they also
                    wished to punish Meidias for conduct which they had witnessed on other
                    occasions, as a scoundrel and a ruffian who could no longer be tolerated. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>This being so, I have in your interests taken all due precautions, and now that
                    the case is before the court, I am here, as you see, to accuse him, having
                    refused large sums of money, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, which I might have accepted on condition of dropping
                    the prosecution, and having had to steel myself against many appeals and
                    favorable offers-yes, and even menaces.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>What yet remains to do is in your hands; but my hope is that the more the
                    defendant has pestered you with his solicitations—I observed just now what he
                    was up to in front of the courthouse-more likely I am to obtain justice. For I
                    would not insult any of you by imagining that you will be indifferent to the
                    cause in which you so heartily supported me before, or that, in order to grant
                    Meidias immunity for future outrages, any juryman remembering his oath will give
                    other than what he considers a righteous verdict. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>Now if, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I were going
                    to accuse Meidias of unconstitutional proposals or of misconduct on an embassy
                    or of any offence of that sort, I should not feel justified in appealing for
                    your sympathy, for I consider that in such cases the plaintiff ought to confine
                    himself to proving his case, though the defendant may have recourse to prayers.
                    But since Meidias bribed the umpires and so robbed my tribe unfairly of the
                    prize, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>since I in person was struck by him and insulted as perhaps no chorus-master was
                    ever insulted before, and since I am here to follow up the verdict which the
                    Assembly pronounced in indignation and anger at such conduct, for these reasons
                    I shall not shrink even from an appeal to you. For, if I may say so, it is now I
                    who am in the position of a defendant, if indeed to obtain no redress for an
                    insult is the real calamity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>Therefore, gentlemen of the jury, I appeal to you all, and implore you first to
                    grant me a favorable hearing, and secondly, if I prove that the insults of
                    Meidias touch, not me only, but you and the laws and the whole body of citizens,
                    to come at once to any rescue and to your own. For the case stands thus,
                    Athenians. I was the victim and it was my person that was then outraged; but now
                    the question to be fought out and decided is whether Meidias is to be allowed to
                    repeat his performances and insult anyone and everyone of you with impunity.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>Therefore if perhaps anyone of you hitherto assumed that this action was brought
                    from private motives, when he now reflects that this is a matter of general
                    concern, and that public interest demands that no one shall be allowed to act in
                    this way, let him grant me an attentive hearing, and then let him give what
                    seems to him the fairest verdict.But first the clerk shall read you the law
                    which provides for the lodging of plaints in the Assembly; after that I will try
                    to enlighten you on other points. Recite the law.<quote type="Law"
                            ><title>Law</title>[;The Prytanes shall call a meeting of the Assembly
                        in the temple of Dionysus on the day next after the Pandia. At this meeting
                        they shall first deal with religious matters; next they shall lay before it
                        the plaints lodged concerning the procession or the contests at the
                        Dionysia, namely such as have not been satisfied.];</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>This is the law, Athenians, which provides for the lodging of a plaint. It
                    directs, as you have heard, that a meeting of the Assembly shall be held in the
                    temple of Dionysus after the Pandia, and that at this meeting, when the chairmen
                    for the day have dealt with the official acts of the chief Archon, they shall
                    also deal with any offences or illegal acts in connection with the festival—a
                    sound and expedient law, Athenians, as the facts of the present case attest. For
                    when it appears that certain persons, with this threat overhanging them, can be
                    as insolent as ever, how should we expect that such men would behave, if there
                    were no risk and no trial to be faced? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>Now I want to read to you the next law as well, because it will illustrate to all
                    of you the self-restraint of the citizens in general and the hardihood of the
                    defendant. Read the law.<quote type="Law"><title>Law</title><milestone ed="P"
                            unit="para"/>[;Evegorus proposed that, on the occasion of the procession
                        in honor of Dionysus in Peiraeus with the comedies and tragedies, the
                        procession at the Lenaeum with the comedies and tragedies, the procession at
                        the City Dionysia with the boys’ contests and the revel and the comedies and
                        tragedies. and also at the procession and contest of the Thargelia, it shall
                        not be lawful on those days to distrain or to seize any debtors’ property,
                        even if they are defaulters. If anyone transgresses any of these
                        regulations, he shall be liable to prosecution by the aggrieved party, and
                        public plaints against him as an offender may be lodged at the meeting of
                        the Assembly in the temple of Dionysus, as is provided by statute in the
                        case of other offenders.];</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>You will observe, gentlemen of the jury, that whereas in the first law the public
                    plaint may be lodged against those who violate the laws of the festival, in the
                    latter law you have sanctioned plaints against those who exact money from
                    defaulting debtors or seize any property or use violence to that end. So far
                    from thinking it right that any man’s person should be outraged on those days,
                    or that any equipment should be damaged which a citizen provides out of his
                    private means for a public service, you have even conceded that what by law and
                    by verdict belongs to the winner of a suit should remain the property of the
                    loser and original owner, at any rate during the festival. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>You therefore, Athenians, have all risen to such a height of benevolence and
                    piety that during those days you have even suspended the exaction of penalties
                    due for past offences; but Meidias, as I shall prove, chose those very same days
                    to commit offences that call for the severest punishment. I intend to describe
                    in order each outrage of which I have been the victim, before I speak of the
                    blows in which his attacks culminated, for there is not a single one of those
                    attacks for which he will not be shown to have deserved death. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>Two years ago the tribe of Pandionis had failed to appoint a chorus-master, and
                    when the Assembly met at which the law directs the Archons to assign the
                    flute-players by lot to the choruses, there was a heated discussion and mutual
                    recrimination between the Archon and the overseers of the tribe.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Elected, one from each tribe, to help the Archon
                        in directing the procession at the Dionysia.</note> Thereupon I came forward
                    and volunteered to act as chorus-master, and at the drawing of the lots I was
                    fortunate enough to get first choice of a flute-player. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>You, Athenians, all of you, welcomed with the utmost cordiality both these
                    incidents—my voluntary offer and my stroke of luck; and your cheers and applause
                    expressed your approval of my conduct and your sympathy with my good fortune.
                    But there seems to have been one solitary exception, Meidias, who in his chagrin
                    kept up a constant fire of insults, trifling or serious, during the whole period
                    of my service. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Now the trouble that he caused by opposing the exemption of our chorus from
                    military service, or by putting himself forward as overseer at the Dionysia and
                    demanding election, these and other similar annoyances I will pass over in
                    silence; for I am not unaware that although to myself, the victim of his
                    persecution and insolence, each of these acts caused as much irritation as any
                    really serious offence, yet to the rest of you, who were not directly concerned,
                    these things in themselves would hardly seem to call for litigation. I shall
                    therefore confine myself to what will excite indignation in all of you alike.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>His subsequent conduct, which I am now going to describe, passes all limits; and
                    indeed I should never have ventured to arraign him today, had I not previously
                    secured his immediate conviction in the Assembly. The sacred apparel—for all
                    apparel provided for use at a festival I regard as being sacred until after it
                    has been used—and the golden crowns,which I ordered for the decoration of the
                    chorus, he plotted to destroy,men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, by a nocturnal raid on the premises of my goldsmith.
                    And he did destroy them, though not completely, for that was beyond his power.
                    And no one can say that he ever yet heard of anyone daring or perpetrating such
                    an outrage in this city. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>But not content with this, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, he actually corrupted the trainer of my chorus; and if
                    Telephanes, the flute-player, had not proved the staunchest friend to me, if he
                    had not seen through the fellow’s game and sent him about his business, if he
                    had not felt it his duty to train the chorus and weld them into shape himself,
                    we could not have taken part in the competition, Athenians; the chorus would
                    have come in untrained and we should have been covered with ignominy. Nor did
                    his insolence stop even there. It was so unrestrained that he bribed the crowned
                    Archon himself; he banded the choristers against me; he bawled and threatened,
                    standing beside the umpires as they took the oath he blocked the gangways from
                    the wings,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Rooms projecting R. and L. from the
                        back-scene, and giving access to the orchestra for the dithyrambic chorus.
                        Meidias apparently compelled them to enter by the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >pa/rodoi</foreign>, like a tragic chorus. See <bibl>Haigh’s
                                <title>Attic Theatre</title>, p. 117.</bibl></note> nailing up those
                    public thoroughfares without public authority; he never ceased to cause me
                    untold damage and annoyance. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>Of those outrages which were committed in public or before the umpires in the
                    theater, you are yourselves my witnesses, all of you, gentlemen of the jury. And
                    surely the statements on which most reliance should be placed are those of which
                    the jury can themselves attest the truth. So after he had already corrupted the
                    umpires in the men’s contest, he put the cap, as it were, on all his previous
                    acts of wantonness by two outrages: he assaulted my person, and he was chiefly
                    responsible for preventing my tribe, which was winning, from gaining the prize.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>These were the crimes and brutalities which Meidias committed in connection with
                    the festival against my fellow-tribesmen and myself. It was for these, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that I lodged my public
                    plaint; and there are many besides, of which I will describe to you immediately
                    as many as I can. But I have to tell of many other acts of unmitigated rascality
                    and insolence, directed against many of yourselves, and many daring crimes of
                    this blackguard. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>Some of his victims, gentlemen of the jury, suffered in silence, because they
                    were cowed by him and his self-confidence, or by his gang of bullies, his wealth
                    and all his other resources; others tried to obtain redress and failed; others
                    again made terms with him, perhaps because they thought that the best policy.
                    Those, then, who were induced to do so have obtained the satisfaction due to
                    themselves; but of the satisfaction due to the laws, by breaking which Meidias
                    wronged them and is wronging me now and every other citizen—of that satisfaction
                    you are the dispensers. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Therefore include all the offences in one sweeping penalty, whatever you consider
                    just.I will first, then, adduce proofs of the outrages against myself, next of
                    those against you. After that, Athenians, I will examine all the rest of his
                    life and will show that he deserves not one death, but a thousand. First please
                    take and read the deposition of the goldsmith. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p><quote type="Deposition"><title>Deposition</title>[;I, Pammenes, son of Pammenes,
                        of Erchia, have a goldsmith’s shop in the Agora, where I reside and carry on
                        my business. When Demosthenes, for whom I am a witness, commissioned me to
                        fashion a golden crown,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If this document
                            were worth emending, we should have to read <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >stefa/nous xrusou=s</foreign> here and <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >tou\s stefa/nous</foreign> below, to tally with <bibl
                                n="Dem. 21.16">Dem. 21.16</bibl>.</note> and to make a
                        gold-embroidered robe, that he might wear them at the procession in honor of
                        Dionysus; and when I had completed them and had them ready by me, Meidias,
                        who is being prosecuted by Demosthenes, broke into my premises by night,
                        having also others with him, and tried to destroy the crown and the robe,
                        and a part of them he injured, but was not able to destroy them completely,
                        because I appeared and prevented him.];</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>Now I have much to say also, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, about the wrongs which he inflicted on others, as I
                    told you at the beginning of my speech, and I have made a collection of his
                    outrageous and insulting acts, which you shall hear in a moment. The collection
                    was indeed an easy matter, for the victims themselves applied to me.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There is obviously some dislocation here. The
                        evidence of the goldsmith, which concerns the outrages specified in the
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">probolh/</foreign>, should have come, with the
                        other depositions, after <bibl n="Dem. 21.18">Dem. 21.18</bibl>. <bibl
                            n="Dem. 21.23">Dem. 21.23</bibl>, in its present place, with its
                        reference to the beginning of the speech, is nonsense. It is a repetition of
                            <bibl n="Dem. 21.19">Dem. 21.19</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 21.20">Dem.
                            21.20</bibl>, being an introduction to a description of outrages
                        committed against others. This part of his argument Demosthenes commences at
                            <bibl n="Dem. 21.128">Dem. 21.128</bibl>. Goodwin, who thinks that
                        Demosthenes intended to revise his arrangement of topics, but did not carry
                        it out when the case was dropped, brackets <bibl n="Dem. 21.23">Dem.
                            21.23</bibl> here and inserts it before <bibl n="Dem. 21.128">Dem.
                            21.128</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>But before I come to that, I want to speak about the tricks by which I am told he
                    will try to deceive you; for I think it very necessary for me to put my remarks
                    on that subject before you, and very important for you to hear them. Why so?
                    Because the same argument that prevents your deception will help you to cast
                    your votes in accordance with justice and your oath. You must pay attention to
                    this argument above all others and bear it in mind, so as to meet each separate
                    point in his speech. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>And first, it is pretty evident from his private conversation as reported to me
                    that he will say that, if I had really suffered from him as I assert, I ought to
                    have brought various personal suits against him, one for willful damage, arising
                    out of the destruction of the robes and golden crowns, and another for assault,
                    arising out of his alleged attack on my person; but that I ought most
                    emphatically not to have brought him to a public trial and proposed a penalty or
                    a fine which he must pay. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>But of one thing I am perfectly certain, and you should be equally so-that if I
                    had not lodged the public plaint but had brought a civil action, the opposite
                    argument would have been used against me, that if there was any truth in my
                    statements, I ought to have lodged a public plaint and claimed redress at the
                    time when the offences were committed; for the chorus was a state-chorus, the
                    apparel was being prepared entirely for a public festival, and I, the aggrieved
                    party, was official chorus-master. Who then would dream of any other form of
                    redress than that which the law provides against those who profane a festival?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>I am sure that he would have said all that in those circumstances. For it is, I
                    believe, the cue for the defendant, the man who has done a wrong, to try and
                    shuffle out of the method actually adopted to bring him to punishment and to say
                    that a different method should have been employed; but it is the duty of
                    sensible jurymen to ignore such evasions and to chastise anyone whom they
                    convict of an outrage. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>Do not allow him to say that the law affords me a choice of personal suits or an
                    indictment for assault. That is true; but he has to prove that he has not done
                    what I have charged him with, or that in doing it he has not profaned the
                    festival, for that is the ground on which I based my public plaint against him,
                    and that is the question on which you must presently cast your votes. But if I,
                    waiving the profit which a private suit would bring, entrust his punishment to
                    the State, and if I have chosen this particular form of action from which I can
                    receive no benefit myself, then surely it ought to win me your favour and not
                    prejudice my case. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>Now I know that he will also make great use of this argument: <q type="">Do not deliver me
                    into Demosthenes’ hands; do not ruin me to oblige Demosthenes. Because I am at
                    war with him, will you ruin me?</q> That is the sort of language that he will, I am
                    sure, use again and again, with the object of exciting prejudice against me.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>But the truth is quite otherwise. You never <q type="">deliver</q> a malefactor to his
                    accuser; for when someone has been wronged, you do not exact the penalty in such
                    a form as the injured party urges upon you in each case. On the contrary, laws
                    were laid down by you before the particular offences were committed, when the
                    future wrongdoer and his victim were equally unknown. What is the effect of
                    these laws? They ensure for every citizen the opportunity of obtaining redress
                    if he is wronged. Therefore when you punish a man who breaks the laws, you are
                    not delivering him over to his accusers; you are strengthening the arm of the
                    law in your own interests. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>But surely when he says, <q type="">Demosthenes was insulted,</q> he is met by an argument
                    that is just and impartial and in the interests of all. It was not against the
                    individual named Demosthenes that his brutality was directed on that occasion,
                    but also against your chorus-master; and what that implies you may realize from
                    the following considerations. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>You know of course that of the judges who sit in this court none has the name of
                    Judge, but each has some name of his own. Therefore if a man is guilty of
                    assault or slander against anyone of them in his private capacity, he will stand
                    his trial on an indictment for assault or in a suit for slander; but if he
                    assails him as judge, he will incur total disfranchisement. Why so? Because at
                    once by the mere act he is outraging your laws, your public crown of office, and
                    the name that belongs to the State, for Judge is not a private name but a
                    state-title. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>In the same way again, if you strike or abuse the Archon when wearing his crown,
                    you are disfranchised; but if you assault him as a private citizen, you are
                    liable to a private suit. Moreover, this is true not only of these officials,
                    but of everyone to whom the State grants the inviolability of a crowned office
                    or of any other honor. Therefore in my case also, if on any other day in the
                    year Meidias had wronged me as a private citizen, he would have had to give me
                    private satisfaction; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>but if all his outrages are shown to have been aimed at your chorus-master during
                    the holy days of the festival, it is right that he should face public resentment
                    and pay a public penalty. For the chorus master was insulted as well as
                    Demosthenes, and that is a concern of the State, as well as the fact that this
                    occurred on the very days on which the laws expressly forbid it. When you are
                    framing your laws, you must scrutinize their purport; but when you have passed
                    them, you must uphold them and put them in force, for that is required by your
                    oath and by justice as well. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>You had the law—an ancient one—of damage; you had the law of battery and the law
                    of assault. Now if it had been sufficient that those guilty at the Dionysia of
                    any of these offences should be punished according to these laws, there would
                    have been no need for this further law. But it was not sufficient, and the proof
                    of this is that you made a law to protect the sanctity of the god during the
                    Holy Month. If, then, anyone is liable both under those pre-existing laws and
                    under this subsequent one as well as all the rest of the laws, is he for that
                    reason to escape punishment, or should he in fairness suffer a heavier one? I
                    think that it should be the heavier punishment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>I have been told that Meidias goes about inquiring and collecting examples of
                    people who have at any time been assaulted, and that these people are going to
                    give evidence and describe their experiences to you; for instance, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, the Chairman for the day
                    who is said to have been struck by Polyzelus in your court, the judge who was
                    lately struck when trying to rescue the flute-girl, and similar cases. He
                    imagines that if he can point to many other victims of serious assault, you will
                    be less indignant at the assault committed upon me! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>But it seems to me, Athenians, that it would be reasonable for you to do just the
                    reverse, since your duty is to be solicitous for the common good of all. For who
                    of you is unaware that the reason for the frequency of these assaults is the
                    failure to punish the offenders, and that the only way to prevent such assaults
                    in the future is adequately to punish every offender who is caught? Therefore,
                    if it is to your interest to deter others, those cases are an additional reason
                    for punishing Meidias, and punishing him the more severely in proportion to
                    their number and their seriousness; but if you want to encourage him and
                    everybody, you must let him off. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>[;Then again we shall find that he has not the same claim to consideration as
                    these others. For in the first case the man who struck the judge had three
                    excuses: he was drunk, he was in love, and he did not know what he was doing in
                    the darkness and the night. Polyzelus again explained that owing to his
                    ungovernable temper he had lost his head when he committed the offence; there
                    was no hostility behind the act and no intention to insult. But Meidias cannot
                    plead any of these excuses, for he was my enemy, and he assaulted me willfully
                    by daylight, and not only on that, but on every occasion he has shown a
                    deliberate intention to insult me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>And indeed I can see no comparison between my own conduct and that of those
                    others. In the first case it will be proved that the judge took no thought or
                    concern for you or for the laws, but was privately induced by a sum of money—I
                    cannot say how much—to drop his action. In the same way the man who was struck
                    by Polyzelus was privately squared, laughed in his sleeve at you and your laws,
                    and never even prosecuted his assailant. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>Such statements, then, are quite in point if one wishes to accuse those men
                    today, but as a defence of Meidias against my indictments they are the very last
                    pleas that should be urged. For my conduct was clean contrary to theirs. It will
                    be proved that I never got, or tried to get, any advantage for myself, but
                    religiously observed, and have now restored to your keeping, the task of
                    avenging the laws, the god, and your interests.]; Do not then allow him to make
                    these statements, or if he persists, do not give him credence as if his plea
                    were just. If he finds that this is your fixed determination, he will have
                    nothing to say, not a word. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>For what sort of pretext, what decent and moderate excuse, can he show for his
                    conduct? Anger? Possibly that will be his plea. But whereas in cases where a
                    sudden loss of self-control has impelled a man even to inflict a wanton insult,
                    it is open to him to say that he has acted in anger; if, on the other hand, he
                    is detected in a continuous course of law-breaking, spread over many days,
                    surely this is far from a mere fit of anger and he stands convicted of a
                    deliberate policy of insult. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>Very well; since he has clearly done what I accuse him of, and has done it by way
                    of insult, we must now consider the laws, gentlemen of the jury, for it is in
                    accordance with the laws that you have sworn to give your verdict. Observe,
                    moreover, that the laws treat the willful and insolent transgressors as
                    deserving more resentment and a heavier punishment than other classes of
                    offenders. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>First then, all the laws of damage—to take these first—order the offender to pay
                    the amount twice over if the damage is willful, but only once if it is
                    involuntary. This is reasonable, because, while the injured party is in any case
                    entitled to relief, the law does not ordain that the resentment against the
                    aggressor should be the same, whether his act is voluntary or involuntary.
                    Again, the laws of homicide punish willful murder with death, perpetual exile,
                    and confiscation of goods, but accidental homicide they treat with much
                    consideration and charity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>It is not only in these, but in all cases, that the laws may be seen to be severe
                    against premeditated outrages. For how is it that if a man who has lost his case
                    fails to pay, the law thereupon is not content with a private suit for
                    ejectment, but directs the imposition of a further fine to the treasury? Or
                    again, how is it that if a man takes from another by mutual consent a sum of
                    one, two, or ten talents, and then fraudulently withholds it, the State has no
                    concern with him; but if a man, taking something that would merit only a
                    trifling fine, keeps it back by force, then the laws direct the jury to impose
                    an additional fine for the treasury equal to that paid to the private owner?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>The answer is that the legislator regarded every deed of violence as a public
                    offence, committed against those also who are not directly concerned. For force
                    belongs to the few, but the laws to all alike; and the man who agreed to the
                    transaction can right himself privately, but the victim of violence needs relief
                    at the hands of the State. On this principle, for the actual assault the law
                    grants everyone the right to prosecute, but makes over the whole of the fine to
                    the State. The legislator considered that the State, as well as the injured
                    party, was wronged by the author of the outrage, and that his punishment was
                    sufficient compensation for the victim, who ought not to make money for himself
                    out of such wrongs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>Indeed he went to such extreme lengths that even if a slave was assaulted, he
                    granted him the same right of bringing a public action. He thought that he ought
                    to look, not at the rank of the sufferer, but at the nature of the act, and when
                    he found the act unjustifiable, he would not give it his sanction either in
                    regard to a slave or in any other case. For nothing, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, nothing in the world is more
                    intolerable than a personal outrage, nor is there anything that more deserves
                    your resentment. Read me the actual law with regard to it. There is nothing like
                    hearing the law’s own words. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p><quote type="Law"><title>Law</title>If anyone assaults any child or woman or man,
                        whether free or slave, or commits any unlawful act against anyone of these,
                        any Athenian citizen who desires so to do, being qualified, may indict him
                        before the Judges; and the Judges shall bring the case before the Heliastic
                        Court within thirty days from the date of the indictment, unless some public
                        business prevents, in which case it shall be brought on the earliest
                        possible date. Whomsoever the Court shall condemn, it shall at once assess
                        the punishment or the fine which he is considered to deserve. In all cases
                        where an indictment is entered, as the law directs, if anyone fails to
                        prosecute, or after prosecution fails to obtain one fifth of the votes of
                        the jury, he shall pay a thousand drachmas to the Treasury. If he is fined
                        for the assault, he shall be imprisoned until the fine is paid, provided
                        that the offence was committed against a freeman.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>Athenians, you hear the humanity of the law, which does not permit even slaves to
                    be assaulted. In heaven’s name, think what this means. Suppose someone carried
                    this law to the barbarous nations from whom we import our slaves; suppose he
                    praised you and described your city to them in these words: </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p><q type="">There are in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> men so mild and
                    humane in disposition that though they have often been wronged by you, and
                    though they have inherited a natural hostility towards you, yet they permit no
                    insult to be offered even to the men whom they have bought for a price and keep
                    as their slaves. Nay, they have publicly established this law forbidding such
                    insult, and they have already punished many of the transgressors with death.</q>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>If the barbarians heard these words and understood their import, do you not think
                    that they would unanimously appoint you their protectors?<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="grc">pro/cenos</foreign>, here loosely
                        used, is technically a man chosen by a foreign state as its representative
                        in his own native city (nearly a <q type="">consul</q> in the modern sense).</note> As
                    regards this law then, which is so well esteemed among the Greeks and would be
                    well esteemed among the barbarians also, consider what penalty he who
                    transgresses it will have to pay before he has paid his deserts. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>Now if I had not been chorus-master, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, when I was thus maltreated by Meidias, it is only the
                    personal insult that one would have condemned; but under the circumstances I
                    think one would be justified in condemning also the impiety of the act. You
                    surely realize that all your choruses and hymns to the god are sanctioned, not
                    only by the regulations of the Dionysia, but also by the oracles, in all of
                    which, whether given at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> or at
                        <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName>, you will find a solemn
                    injunction to the State to set up dances after the ancestral custom, to fill the
                    streets with the savour of sacrifice, and to wear garlands. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>Please take and read the actual oracles.<cit>
                        <quote type="oracle">
                            <title>Oracles</title>
                            <l met="dactylic">You I address, Pandion’s townsmen and sons of
                                Erechtheus,</l>
                            <l>who appoint your feasts by the ancient rites of your fathers.</l>
                            <l>See you forget not Bacchus, and joining all in the dances</l>
                            <l>Down your broad-spaced streets, in thanks<note resp="Loeb"
                                    anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="grc">i(sta/nai
                                        xa/rin</foreign>, if the Greek is sound, seems to be a
                                    <q type="">portmanteau</q> phrase to set up a dance in gratitude. The oracle
                                    quoted may perfectly well be genuine.</note> for the gifts of
                                the season,</l>
                            <l>Crown each head with a wreath, while incense reeks on the altars.</l>
                            <l>For health sacrifice and pray to Zeus Most High, to Heracles, and to
                                Apollo the Protector; for good fortune to Apollo, god of the
                                streets, to Leto, and to Artemis; and along the streets set
                                wine-bowls and dances, and wear garlands after the manner of your
                                fathers in honor of all gods and all goddesses of <placeName
                                    key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>, raising right hands and
                                left in supplication,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Translating
                                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">lita/s</foreign>, <placeName
                                        key="tgn,1131671">Weil</placeName>’s suggestion.</note> and
                                remember your gifts.</l>
                        </quote>
                        <bibl>unknown</bibl>
                    </cit>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <cit>
                    <quote type="oracle"><title>Oracles from <placeName key="perseus,Dodona"
                                >Dodona</placeName></title>To the people of the Athenians the
                        prophet of Zeus announces. Whereas ye have let pass the seasons of the
                        sacrifice and of the sacred embassy, he bids you send nine chosen envoys,
                        and that right soon. To Zeus of the Ship<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >There was a temple at <placeName key="perseus,Dodona"
                                >Dodona</placeName> dedicated to Zeus under this title to
                            commemorate a rescue from shipwreck.</note> sacrifice three oxen and
                        with each ox three sheep; to Dione one ox and a brazen table for the
                        offering which the people of the Athenians have offered.<p>The prophet of
                            Zeus in <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> announces. To
                            Dionysus pay public sacrifices and mix a bowl of wine and set up dances;
                            to Apollo the Averter sacrifice an ox and wear garlands, both free men
                            and slaves, and observe one day of rest; to Zeus, the giver of wealth, a
                            white bull.</p></quote>
                    <bibl>unknown</bibl>
                </cit>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>Besides these oracles, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    there are many others addressed to our city, and excellent oracles they are. Now
                    what conclusion ought you to draw from them? That while they prescribe the
                    sacrifices to the gods indicated in each oracle, to every oracle that is
                    published they add the injunction to set up dances and to wear garlands after
                    the manner of our ancestors. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>Therefore in the case of all the choruses that are constituted, together with
                    their chorus-masters, during the days on which we meet in competition, these
                    oracles make it clear that we wear our crowns as your representatives, the
                    winner as well as the one destined to be last of all; it is not until the day of
                    the prize-giving that the victor receives his own special crown. If, then, a man
                    commits a malicious assault on any member or master of these choruses,
                    especially during the actual contest in the sacred precinct of the god, can we
                    deny that he is guilty of impiety? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>Moreover, you are aware that, although anxious to exclude aliens from the
                    contest, you do not grant unlimited right to any chorus-master to summon for
                    scrutiny any member of a chorus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If a
                        chorus-master suspected that a member of a rival chorus was an alien, he
                        must not forcibly eject him nor summon him before the Archon to prove his
                        nationality.</note>; if he summons him, he is fined fifty drachmas, and a
                    thousand drachmas if he orders him to sit among the spectators. What is the
                    object? To protect the crowned official, who is doing public service to the god,
                    from being maliciously summoned or annoyed or insulted on that day. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>So even the man who in due course of law summons a member of a chorus will not
                    escape a fine. And shall not he be punished who in contempt of all the laws thus
                    publicly strikes the master of a chorus? Surely it is useless for your laws to
                    be thus well and humanely framed for the protection of the humbler citizen, if
                    those who disobey and flout them are not to incur the resentment of you who are,
                    for the time being, entrusted with their administration. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>And now I solemnly call your attention to another point. I shall beg you not to
                    be offended if I mention by name some persons who have fallen into misfortune;
                    for I swear to you that in doing so I have no intention of casting reproach upon
                    any man; I only want to show you how carefully all the rest of you avoid
                    anything like violent or insulting behavior. There is, for instance, Sannio, the
                    trainer of the tragic choruses, who was convicted of shirking military service
                    and so found himself in trouble. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>After that misfortune he was hired by a chorus-master—Theozotides, if I am not
                    mistaken—who was keen to win a victory in the tragedies. Well, at first the
                    rival masters were indignant and threatened to debar him, but when they saw that
                    the theater was full and the crowd assembled for the contest, they hesitated,
                    they gave way, and no one laid a finger on him. One can see that the forbearance
                    which piety inspires in every one of you is such that Sannio has been training
                    choruses ever since, not hindered even by his private enemies, much less by any
                    of the chorus-masters. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>Then again there is Aristeides of the tribe of Oeneis, who has had a similar
                    misfortune. He is now an old man and perhaps less useful in a chorus, but he was
                    once chorus-leader for his tribe. You know, of course, that if the leader is
                    withdrawn, the rest of the chorus is done for. But in spite of the keen rivalry
                    of many of the chorus-masters, not one of them looked at the possible advantage
                    or ventured to remove him or prevent him from performing. Since this involved
                    laying hands on him, and since he could not be cited before the Archon as if he
                    were an alien whom it was desired to eject, every man shrank from being seen as
                    the personal author of such an outrage. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
                <p>Then is not this, gentlemen of the jury, a shocking and intolerable position? On
                    the one hand, chorus-masters, who think that such a course might bring them
                    victory and who have in many cases spent all their substance on their public
                    services, have never dared to lay hands even on one whom the law permits them to
                    touch, but show such caution, such piety, such moderation that, in spite of
                    their expenditure and their eager competition, they restrain themselves and
                    respect your wishes and your zeal for the festival. Meidias, on the other hand,
                    a private individual who has been put to no expense, just because he has fallen
                    foul of a man whom he hates—a man, remember, who is spending his money as
                    chorus-master and who has full rights of citizenship—insults him and strikes him
                    and cares nothing for the festival, for the laws, for your opinion, or for the
                    god’s honor. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
                <p>Now although men have quarrelled often enough, whether on private or on public
                    grounds, no one has ever been so lost to shame as to venture on such conduct as
                    this. Yet it is said that the famous Iphicrates once had a serious quarrel with
                    Diocles of the Pitthean deme, and, to make matters worse, Iphicrates’ brother
                    Teisias happened to be a chorus-master in competition with Diocles. Iphicrates
                    was a wealthy man with many friends and had a high opinion of himself, as a man
                    would naturally have who had earned so many honors and distinctions at your
                    hands; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
                <p>but Iphicrates never went under cover of night to the goldsmiths’ shops, he never
                    ripped up the costumes intended for the festival, he never bribed the instructor
                    and hindered the training of the chorus, he never played any of the tricks that
                    Meidias repeatedly practised. No, he submitted to the laws and to the wishes of
                    his fellow-citizens, and patiently witnessed the victory and the crowning of his
                    enemy. And he was right; for he felt that such submission was due to the
                    constitution under which he himself had enjoyed such prosperity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="section">
                <p>Take another instance. We all know that Philostratus of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Colonus">Colonus</placeName> was one of the accusers when
                        Chabrias<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Chabrias, with Callistratus, was
                        tried for treachery in connection with the surrender of Oropus in 366. The
                        defence of Callistratus is said to have roused the admiration of
                        Demosthenes, then a youth.</note> was tried for his life on charges relating
                    to Oropus, and that he showed himself the bitterest of them all, and that
                    afterwards he won the prize at the Dionysia with a chorus of boys. Yet Chabrias
                    neither struck him nor snatched the crown off his head nor in any way intruded
                    where he had no right. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
                <p>I could mention many others who on various grounds have quarrelled with their
                    neighbors, but I have never seen or heard of anyone who carried his insolence so
                    far as to behave like this. And I am quite sure that no one here can recall any
                    case where a man, involved in a public or private dispute, has taken his stand
                    beside the umpires while they were being named, or dictated the oath when they
                    were being sworn, or paraded his hostility on any such occasion. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="section">
                <p>These and all similar acts, Athenians, are partly excusable in a chorus-master
                    who is carried away by emulation; but to harass a man with one’s hostility,
                    deliberately and on every occasion, and to boast one’s own power as superior to
                    the laws, that, by Heaven! is cruel and unjust and contrary to your interests.
                    For if each man when he becomes chorus-master could foresee this result: <q type="">If
                    So-and-so is my enemy—Meidias for example or anyone else equally rich and
                    unscrupulous—first I shall be robbed of my victory, even if I make a better show
                    than any of my competitors next I shall be worsted at every point and exposed to
                    repeated insults:</q> who is so irrational or such a poor creature that he would
                    voluntarily consent to spend a single drachma? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="section">
                <p>I suppose what tends to make everyone public-spirited and liberal with his money
                    is the reflection that under a democracy each man has his share of just and
                    equal rights. Now I, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    was deprived of those rights through this man’s acts, and, quite apart from the
                    insults I endured, I was robbed of my victory. Yet I shall prove to all of you
                    beyond a doubt that Meidias, without committing any outrageous offence, without
                    insulting or striking me, had it in his power both to cause me trouble and to
                    display his public spirit to you in a legitimate way, so that I should not be
                    able to open my lips against him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="section">
                <p>This is what he ought to have done, Athenians. When I offered myself to the
                    Assembly as chorus-master for the tribe of Pandionis, he should have got up and
                    offered himself as a rival master for his own tribe of Erechtheis he should have
                    put himself on equal terms with me and spent his money as I was spending mine
                    and tried in that way to wrest the victory from me; but not even as my rival
                    should he have thus insulted and struck me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="section">
                <p>As it was, he did not adopt this course, by which he might have done honor to the
                    people, nor did he work off his high spirits in this way. No; I was his target,
                    I who in my madness, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                    >Athens</placeName>,—for it may be madness to engage in something beyond one’s
                    power perhaps in my ambition, volunteered for chorus-master. He harassed me with
                    a persecution so undisguised and so brutal that neither the sacred costumes nor
                    the chorus nor at last even my own person was safe from his hands. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="section">
                <p>Now if there is anyone of you, Athenians, whose anger against Meidias falls short
                    of a demand for his death, he is wrong. For it is neither just nor proper that
                    the forbearance of the victim should contribute to the acquittal of a man who
                    has put no check on his insolence. The latter you should punish as if the
                    results of his conduct had been utterly irremediable; to the former you should
                    show your goodwill by favouring his cause.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        argument is here condensed. Demosthenes imagines a juryman as saying to
                        himself, <q type="">Demosthenes did not retaliate; therefore the insult was not really
                        intolerable.</q> He replies, <q type="">That only shows my forebearance. You ought to
                        punish Meidias as severely as you would if I had shown that the insult was
                        intolerable by hitting him back.</q></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="section">
                <p>You cannot retort that such acts have never had any serious consequences, but
                    that I am now exaggerating the incident and representing it as formidable. That
                    is wide of the mark. But all, or at least many, know what Euthynus, the once
                    famous wrestler, a youngster, did to Sophilus the prize-fighter. He was a dark,
                    brawny fellow. I am sure some of you know the man I mean. He met him in
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName> at a gathering—just a private
                    pleasure-party-and because he imagined he was insulting him, took such summary
                    vengeance that he actually killed him.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        language is strangely colloquial, not to say slip-shod. Many editors think
                        that we have here a passage which Demosthenes has not finally worked up. Yet
                        the sudden drop in style might be effective, if only the meaning were more
                        clear. Did the wrestler kill the prize-fighter or vice versa? The reader
                        must take his choice. If <foreign xml:lang="grc">o( tu/ptwn</foreign> is
                        retained, it will mean because the striker [;E. or S.?]; intended to insult
                        him [;S. or E.?];. The <foreign xml:lang="grc">kai/</foreign> only makes
                        confusion worse confounded.</note>It is a matter of common knowledge that
                    Euaeon, the brother of Leodamas, killed Boeotus at a public banquet and
                    entertainment in revenge for a single blow. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="section">
                <p>For it was not the blow but the indignity that roused the anger. To be struck is
                    not the serious thing for a free man, serious though it is, but to be struck in
                    wanton insolence. Many things, Athenians, some of which the victim would find it
                    difficult to put into words, may be done by the striker—by gesture, by look, by
                    tone; when he strikes in wantonness or out of enmity; with the fist or on the
                    cheek. These are the things that provoke men and make them beside themselves, if
                    they are unused to insult. No description, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, can bring the outrage as vividly
                    before the hearers as it appears in truth and reality to the victim and to the
                    spectators. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="section">
                <p>In the name of all the gods, Athenians, I ask you to reflect and calculate in
                    your own minds how much more reason I had to be angry when I suffered so at the
                    hands of Meidias, than Euaeon when he killed Boeotus. Euaeon was struck by an
                    acquaintance, who was drunk at the time, in the presence of six or seven
                    witnesses, who were also acquaintances and might be depended upon to denounce
                    the one for his offence and commend the other if he had patiently restrained his
                    feelings after such an affront, especially as Euaeon had gone to sup at a house
                    which he need never have entered at all. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="section">
                <p>But I was assaulted by a personal enemy early in the day, when he was sober,
                    prompted by insolence, not by wine, in the presence of many foreigners as well
                    as citizens, and above all in a temple which I was strictly obliged to enter by
                    virtue of my office. And, Athenians, I consider that I was prudent, or rather
                    happily inspired, when I submitted at the time and was not impelled to any
                    irremediable action; though I fully sympathize with Euaeon and anyone else who,
                    when provoked, takes the law into his own hands. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="section">
                <p>My views were, I think, shared at that trial by many of the jury; for I am told
                    that he was only condemned by a single vote, and yet he had no recourse to tears
                    or supplications and made no effort, small or great, to win the favour of his
                    judges. Let us assume, then, that the judges who condemned him did so, not
                    because he retaliated, but because he did it in such a way as to kill the
                    aggressor, while the judges who acquitted him allowed even this licence of
                    revenge to a man who had suffered an outrage on his person. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="section">
                <p>What follows? I who was so careful not to cause any irremediable mischief that I
                    never retaliated—from whom am I to seek redress for my sufferings? I think it
                    should be from you and from the laws. I think that you should set up a precedent
                    for all to follow, that no one who wantonly assaults and outrages another should
                    be punished by the victim himself in hot blood, but must be brought into your
                    court, because it is you who confirm and uphold the protection granted by the
                    laws to those who are injured. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="section">
                <p>Now I expect, gentlemen of the jury, that some of you are anxious to hear about
                    the quarrel between Meidias and myself; for you must suppose that no human being
                    could treat a fellow-countryman with such violence and brutality, unless he had
                    a long account to settle with him. Well, I am quite willing to give you a
                    detailed account of this quarrel from its inception, so that you may understand
                    that on this score too, as I shall prove, he owes me reparation. The narrative
                    shall be brief, though I may seem to go a long way back for the start. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="section">
                <p>When I brought my action against my guardians for the recovery of my patrimony,
                    being a mere lad, neither acquainted with Meidias nor even aware of his
                    existence—would that I were not acquainted with him now!—when my suit was due to
                    come on in three or four days, Meidias and his brother suddenly burst into my
                    house and challenged me to take over their trierarchy.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Before the system of <q type="">symmories</q> was introduced, the
                        liturgies fell on individuals. A citizen to whom one was assigned could
                        challenge another citizen, whom he thought better able to bear the expense,
                        to undertake the liturgy or exchange properties. Such exchange was called
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)nti/dosis</foreign>.</note> It was the
                    brother, Thrasylochus, who submitted his name and made the challenge; but the
                    real author of all these proceedings was Meidias. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="section">
                <p>And first they forced the doors of the apartments, assuming that these became
                    their property by the terms of the challenge; next in the presence of my sister,
                    who was a young girl still living at home, they used foul language such as only
                    men of their stamp would use—nothing would induce me to repeat to you some of
                    their expressions—and they uttered unrestrained abuse of my mother and myself
                    and all my family. But, what was more shocking still, from words they proceeded
                    to deeds, and they were going to drop the lawsuits, claiming them as their own,
                    to oblige my guardians. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="section">
                <p>All this is ancient history, though I expect some of you remember it, for all
                        <placeName key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName> heard of the challenge and
                    of the plot they then hatched and of their brutal behavior. As for me, being
                    quite alone in the world and a mere lad, I did not want to lose the property
                    that was still in the hands of my guardians, and I expected to obtain, not the
                    trifle that I was actually able to recover, but all that I knew I had been
                    robbed of; so I gave them twenty minas, the sum which they had paid for the
                    performance of their trierarchy by deputy. Such was the scandalous treatment
                    that I received at their hands. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="section">
                <p>Next I brought an action against Meidias for slander and gained the verdict by
                    default, for he did not appear. He had put himself into my power by failing to
                    pay the fine, but I did not lay hands on his property. Instead I obtained leave
                    to bring an action for ejectment, but to this day I have never been able to
                    commence it, such shifts and quibbles does he find to thwart me. While I think
                    it my duty to proceed thus with caution, legally and constitutionally, Meidias,
                    as you learn, thought fit to treat with brutal insolence not only me and mine,
                    but also my fellow-tribesmen through me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="section">
                <p>To prove the truth of this, please call my witnesses, so that you may know that,
                    before obtaining legal redress for my former injuries, I have again been
                    insulted in the way that you have heard.<quote type="Deposition"
                            ><title>Deposition</title>[;We, Callisthenes of Sphettus, Diognetus of
                        Thoricus, Mnesitheus of Alopece, know that Demosthenes, for whom we appear,
                        has brought an action for ejectment against Meidias, who is now also being
                        publicly prosecuted by him, and that eight years have now passed since that
                        action, and that Meidias has been the cause of all the delay by repeated
                        excuses and procrastinations.];</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="section">
                <p>Hear now what he has done, men of <placeName key="tgn,7001393"
                    >Athens</placeName>, in the matter of the legal action and observe his insolent
                    and overbearing conduct on each occasion. In that action—I mean the one in which
                    I obtained a verdict against him—the arbitrator assigned to me was
                            <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> of Phalerum, a man of
                    small means and no experience, but in other respects quite a good fellow; but
                    his appointment proved the unhappy man’s ruin—a ruin undeserved, unjust, and in
                    every way scandalous. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="section">
                <p>This <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>, acting as arbitrator, when
                    the appointed day arrived and all the legal delays had been
                    exhausted—counter-pleas, demurrers, and the rest of them—and there was not a
                    trick left, at first begged me to abandon the arbitration, and then to postpone
                    it till the next day, and at the last, as I continued to refuse and Meidias did
                    not appear in court, and it was getting late, he gave his decision against him.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="section">
                <p>It was now evening and growing dark. Up comes this fellow Meidias to the office
                    of the Archons, and finds them just leaving and
                            <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> already making his way
                    home after having handed to them his judgement of guilty by default. This I
                    learned from one of the bystanders. Well, at first he had the impudence to try
                    and persuade <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> to report a
                    judgement for the defendant instead of one for the plaintiff, and he wanted the
                    Archons to alter the record and offered them fifty drachmas. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="section">
                <p>But finding that they resented the offer and that he could persuade neither
                    Archons nor arbitrator, he threatened them and blackguarded them and went off
                    and—what do you think he did? Just observe his malignity. [;He appealed against
                    the arbitration but omitted the oath, thus allowing the verdict against him to
                    be made absolute, and he was recorded as unsworn. Then, wishing to conceal his
                    real object,]; he waited for the last day<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">It
                        seems safest to follow the scholiast in this difficult passage. He explains
                        that the arbitrators underwent their audit in the eleventh month of the
                        year, i.e. Thargelion, though he makes the odd mistake of calling it
                        Scirophorion. The last day of the month, called <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >e)/nh kai\ ne/a</foreign>, belonged partly to the passing month and
                        partly to the new. Strato, being off his guard, imagined that the month was
                        over and that it was too late for complaints to be brought against
                        him.</note> for appeal against the arbitrators, which falls in Thargelion or
                    Scirophorion, a day on which some of the arbitrators turned up but others did
                    not; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="section">
                <p>he induced the presiding arbitrator to put it to the vote contrary to all the
                    laws, because Meidias had not appended the name of a single witness to the
                    summons; he denounces Strato in his absence and in the absence of witnesses, and
                    gets him struck off the roll of arbitrators and disfranchised. And so a citizen
                    of <placeName key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>, because Meidias lost his
                    suit by default, has been deprived of all his civic rights, and has been
                    irrevocably disfranchised; and it is unsafe for him to bring an action against
                    Meidias when wronged, or to act as arbitrator for him, or even, it seems, to
                    walk the same street with him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="section">
                <p>[;Now you must consider the transaction from this point of view. Estimate what
                    loss Meidias must have suffered before he could plan such a dire revenge against
                    a fellow-citizen; and if it was something really terrible and overwhelming, he
                    may be forgiven, but if it was nothing of the sort, mark the insolent brutality
                    with which he treats all whom he comes across. Well, what loss has he suffered?
                    He was cast, you reply, in a big lawsuit, so big that he has lost all his
                    property. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="section">
                <p>But the lawsuit only involved a thousand drachmas. True, you will say; but the
                    galling thing is to be made to pay unfairly, and it was the unfairness of it
                    that caused him to let the day of payment pass unnoticed.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This, as the scholiast remarks, seems to be obscure. The
                        rankling injustice would be more likely to keep his memory active.</note>
                    But he noticed his mistake the same day, which is the strongest possible proof
                    that <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> had done him no wrong; and
                    he has not yet paid a single drachma. But of that later. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="section">
                <p>But of course he could have moved for a fresh trial on the ground of nullity, and
                    so made me the object of his litigation as at the first. But no; that was not
                    his game. To save him from defending a suit in which the penalty was fixed by
                    law at ten minas—the suit in which he neglected to apppear—to save him from
                    paying the penalty if guilty or if innocent, a citizen of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName> must needs be disfranchised, and must
                    obtain neither pardon nor right of defence nor any sort of equitable treatment,
                    privileges extended even to those whose guilt is established. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="section">
                <p>But now that he has disfranchised the man he wanted to, and you have indulged him
                    in this; now that he has sated that shameless temper that prompted him to this
                    course, has he finished the business? Has he paid the fine, to escape which he
                    ruined the poor fellow? Not a brass farthing of it to this day! He submits
                    rather to be the defendant in an action for ejectment. So the one man is
                    disfranchised and ruined on a side issue; the other is unscathed and is playing
                    havoc with the laws, the arbitrators, and everything else that he pleases. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="section">
                <p>Moreover, he has secured the validity of the award against the arbitrator, which
                    he maneuvered to get without serving a summons, while the suit which he lost to
                    me, wittingly and after due summons, this he renders invalid.]; Yet if such is
                    the vengeance that he claims from arbitrators who have given judgement against
                    him by default, what vengeance ought you to wreak on a man who openly and
                    wantonly transgresses your laws? [;For if disfranchisement and loss of all legal
                    and civil rights is a fitting punishment for that other offence, death seems an
                    inadequate one for this reckless outrage.]; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="section">
                <p>However, to prove the truth of my statements, please call the witnesses, and also
                    read the law concerning arbitrators.<quote type="Witnesses"
                            ><title>Witnesses</title>[;We, Nicostratus of Myrrhinus and Phanias of
                        Aphidna, know that Demosthenes, for whom we appear, and Meidias, who is
                        being prosecuted by Demosthenes, when Demosthenes brought his action against
                        him for slander, chose <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> as
                        arbitrator; and when the statutory day arrived, Meidias did not appear in
                        court but abandoned the case. Judgement having gone by default against
                        Meidias, we know that Meidias tried to induce
                                <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>, the arbitrator, and
                        us, who were at that time Archons, to reverse the judgement against him, and
                        he offered us fifty drachmas, and, when we resented his offer, he threatened
                        us and so departed. Also we know that on this account
                                <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName> was victimized by
                        Meidias and was disfranchised contrary to all justice.];</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="section">
                <p>Read also the law concerning arbitrators.<quote type="Law"
                            ><title>Law</title><p>[;If any parties are in dispute concerning private
                            contracts and wish to choose any arbitrator, it shall be lawful for them
                            to choose whomsoever they wish. But when they have chosen by mutual
                            agreement, they shall abide by his decisions and shall not transfer the
                            same charges from him to another court, but the judgements of the
                            arbitrator shall be final.];</p></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="section">
                <p>Call also <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>, the victim of this
                    persecution, for no doubt he will be allowed to stand up in court.</p>
                <p>This man, Athenians, is a poor man perhaps, but certainly not a bad man. He was
                    once a citizen and served at the proper age in all the campaigns; he has done
                    nothing reprehensible, yet now there he stands silent, stripped not only of all
                    our common privileges, but also of the right to speak or complain; he is not
                    even allowed to tell you whether he has suffered justly or unjustly. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="section">
                <p>All this he has endured at the hands of Meidias, and from the wealth and pride of
                    Meidias, because he himself is poor and friendless and just one of the
                    multitude. If in violation of the laws he had accepted the fifty drachmas and
                    changed his verdict from a condemnation to an acquittal, he would now be a full
                    citizen, untouched by harm and sharing with the rest of us in our common rights;
                    but because he disregarded Meidias in comparison with justice and feared the
                    laws more than his threats, therefore he has met with this great and terrible
                    misfortune through the act of this man. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="section">
                <p>And then this same man, so cruel, so heartless, who has taken such dire vengeance
                    for his wrongs—you have only his word for them, for he really suffered none—will
                    you acquit him when you have detected him in a wanton outrage on one of the
                    citizens? [;If he regards neither festivals nor temples nor law nor anything
                    else, will you not condemn him? Will you not make an example of him?]; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="section">
                <p>If not, what have you to say, gentlemen of the jury? What fair and honorable
                    excuse, in heaven’s name, can you find for him? Is it because he is a ruffian
                    and a blackguard? That is true enough, but surely, men of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>, your duty is to hate such creatures,
                    not to screen them. Is it because he is wealthy? But you will find that his
                    wealth was the main cause of his insolence, so that your duty is to cut off the
                    resources from which his insolence springs, rather than spare him for the sake
                    of those resources; for to allow such a reckless and abominable creature to have
                    such wealth at his command is to supply him with resources to use against
                    yourselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="section">
                <p>What plea, then, is left? Pity, forsooth! He will group his children round him
                    and weep and beg you to pardon him for their sakes. That is his last move. [;But
                    I need not remind you that pity is the due of those who unjustly suffer more
                    than they can endure, not of those who are paying the penalty for the misdeeds
                    they have committed.]; And who could justly pity his children, when he sees that
                    Meidias had no pity for <persName><surname>Strato</surname></persName>’s
                    children, whose distress is enhanced by the reflection that for their father’s
                    calamity no relief is possible? For it is not a question of paying a fixed fine
                    and regaining his civil rights; he has been disfranchised absolutely, at one
                    stroke, by the wanton resentment of Meidias. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="section">
                <p>[;Whose insolence then will be checked, and who will be deprived of the wealth
                    that makes such outrages possible, if you are prepared to pity Meidias as though
                    he were an innocent victim, while, if a poor man, who has done no wrong, has
                    through him become unjustly involved in utmost ruin, you fail even to share in
                    his indignation? It must not be. No one deserves pity who shows no pity; no one
                    deserves pardon who grants no pardon. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="section">
                <p>For I think that all men, in all that they do, feel bound to make a contribution
                    out of their own pockets for the benefit of their own life. Here am I, let us
                    suppose; moderate and merciful towards all, and a benefactor of many. To such a
                    man all men ought to make an equivalent return, if occasion offers or need
                    demands. Here again is a very different man; violent, showing no pity to his
                    neighbor, nor even treating him as a fellow-man. Such a man deserves to be paid
                    in his own coin. And such, Meidias, was the contribution that you paid for your
                    own benefit; such is the return that you deserve.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This metaphor of the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >e)/ranos</foreign>, which means (1) a picnic, (2) a benefit club, to
                        which each member paid a subscription, and from which he could claim help in
                        time of need, is repeated more fully and clearly in <bibl n="Dem. 21.184"
                            >Dem. 21.184</bibl>. Revision of the speech would probably have
                        cancelled this passage; <bibl n="Dem. 21.100">Dem. 21.100</bibl>, <bibl
                            n="Dem. 21.101">Dem. 21.101</bibl> are obelized in S and two other
                        Mss.</note>]; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="section">
                <p>Therefore, men of <placeName key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>, I think that
                    even if I had no other charge to bring against Meidias, and even if what I shall
                    allege hereafter were not more serious than what I have already said, you would
                    be justified, in view of my statements, in condemning him and imposing the
                    utmost penalty of the law. Yet the tale is not complete, and I think I shall not
                    be at a loss what to say next, so lavishly has he furnished me with matter for
                    indictment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="section">
                <p>How he trumped up a charge of desertion against me and bribed another to bring
                    the action—a scoundrel ready for any dirty job, the filthy Euctemon—that I shall
                    pass over; for that blackmailer never moved for a trial, nor had Meidias hired
                    him for any other purpose than to have this notice posted up before the Tribal
                    Heroes for all men to read, <q type="">Euctemon of the Lusian deme has indicted
                    Demosthenes of the Paeanian deme for desertion of his post.</q> Indeed I think he
                    would have been delighted, if it had been in order, to add that Meidias had
                    hired him to indict me. But I pass that over, because Euctemon, having
                    disfranchised himself by failing to follow up the charge, has given me all the
                    satisfaction that I require. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="section">
                <p>But I will now relate a serious act of cruelty committed by him, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, which I at least regard
                    as not merely a personal wrong but a public sacrilege. For when a grave criminal
                    charge was hanging over that unlucky wretch, Aristarchus, the son of Moschus, at
                    first, Athenians, Meidias went round the Market-place and ventured to spread
                    impious and atrocious statements about me to the effect that I was the author of
                    the deed; next, when this device failed, he went to the relations of the dead
                    man, who were bringing the charge of murder against Aristarchus, and offered
                    them money if they would accuse me of the crime. He let neither religion nor
                    piety nor any other consideration stand in the way of this wild proposal: he
                    shrank from nothing. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="section">
                <p>Nay, he was not ashamed to look even that audience in the face and bring such a
                    terrible calamity upon an innocent man; but having set one goal before him, to
                    ruin me by every means in his power, he thought himself bound to leave no stone
                    unturned, as if it were only right that when any man, having been insulted by
                    him, claimed redress and refused to keep silence, he should be removed by
                    banishment without a chance of escape, should even find himself convicted of
                    desertion, should defend himself on a capital charge, and should be in imminent
                    danger of crucifixion. Yet when Meidias is proved guilty of all this, as well as
                    of his insults when I was chorus-master, what leniency, what compassion shall he
                    deserve at your hands? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="106" type="section">
                <p>My own opinion, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is
                    that these acts constitute him my murderer; that while at the Dionysia his
                    outrages were confined to my equipment, my person, and my expenditure, his
                    subsequent course of action shows that they were aimed at everything else that
                    is mine, my citizenship, my family, my privileges, my hopes. Had a single one of
                    his machinations succeeded, I should have been robbed of all that I had, even of
                    the right to be buried in the homeland. What does this mean, gentlemen of the
                    jury? It means that if treatment such as I have suffered is to be the fate of
                    any man who tries to right himself when outraged by Meidias in defiance of all
                    the laws, then it will be best for us, as is the way among barbarians, to grovel
                    at the oppressor’s feet and make no attempt at self-defence. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="107" type="section">
                <p>However, to prove that my statements are true and that these things have actually
                    been perpetrated by this shameless ruffian, please call the witnesses.<quote
                        type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title>[;We, Dionysius of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName> and Antiphilus of Paeania,
                        when our kinsman Nicodemus had met with a violent death at the hands of
                        Aristarchus, the son of Moschus, prosecuted Aristarchus for murder. Learning
                        this, Meidias, who is now being brought to trial by Demosthenes, for whom we
                        appear, offered us small sums of money to let Aristarchus go unharmed, and
                        to substitute the name of Demosthenes in the indictment for
                        murder.];</quote>Now let me have the law concerning bribery. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="108" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>While the clerk is finding the statute, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I wish to address a few
                    words to you. I appeal to all of you jurymen, in the name of Zeus and all the
                    gods, that whatever you hear in court, you may listen to it with this in your
                    minds: What would one of you do, if he were the victim of this treatment, and
                    what anger would he feel on his own account against the author of it? Seriously
                    distressed as I was at the insults that I endured in the discharge of my public
                    service, I am far more seriously distressed and indignant at what ensued. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="109" type="section">
                <p>For in truth, what bounds can be set to wickedness, and how can shamelessness,
                    brutality and insolence go farther, if a man who has committed grave-yes, grave
                    and repeated wrongs against another, instead of making amends and repenting of
                    the evil, should afterwards add more serious outrages and should employ his
                    riches, not to further his own interests without prejudice to others, but for
                    the opposite purpose of driving his victim into exile unjustly and covering him
                    with ignominy, while he gloats over his own superabundance of wealth? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="110" type="section">
                <p>All that, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is just what
                    has been done by Meidias. He brought against me a false charge of murder, in
                    which, as the facts proved, I was in no way concerned; he indicted me for
                    desertion, having himself on three occasions deserted his post; and as for the
                    troubles in Euboea—why, I nearly forgot to mention them!-troubles for which his
                    bosom-friend Plutarchus was responsible, he contrived to have the blame laid at
                    my door, before it became plain to everyone that Plutarchus was at the bottom of
                    the whole business. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="111" type="section">
                <p>Lastly, when I was made senator by lot, he denounced me at the scrutiny, and the
                    business proved a very real danger for me; for instead of getting compensation
                    for the injuries I had suffered, I was in danger of being punished for acts with
                    which I had no concern. Having such grievances and being persecuted in the way
                    that I have just described to you, but at the same time being neither quite
                    friendless nor exactly a poor man, I am uncertain, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, what I ought to do. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="112" type="section">
                <p>For, if I may add a word on this subject also, where the rich are concerned,
                    Athenians, the rest of us have no share in our just and equal rights. Indeed we
                    have not. The rich can choose their own time for facing a jury, and their crimes
                    are stale and cold when they are dished up before you, but if any of the rest of
                    us is in trouble, he is brought into court while all is fresh. The rich have
                    witnesses and counsel in readiness, all primed against us; but, as you see, my
                    witnesses are some of them unwilling even to bear testimony to the truth. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="113" type="section">
                <p>One might harp on these grievances till one was weary, I suppose; but now recite
                    in full the law which I began to quote. Read.<quote type="Law"
                            ><title>Law</title>If any Athenian accepts a bribe from another, or
                        himself offers it to another, or corrupts anyone by promises, to the
                        detriment of the people in general, or of any individual citizen, by any
                        means or device whatsoever, he shall be disfranchised together with his
                        children, and his property shall be confiscated.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="114" type="section">
                <p>This man, then, is so impious, so abandoned, so ready to say or do anything,
                    without stopping for a moment to ask whether it is true or false, whether it
                    touches an enemy or a friend, or any such question, that after accusing me of
                    murder and bringing that grave charge against me, he suffered me to conduct
                    initiatory rites and sacrifices for the Council, and to inaugurate the victims
                    on behalf of you and all the State; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="115" type="section">
                <p>he suffered me as head of the Sacred Embassy to lead it in the name of the city
                    to the Nemean shrine of Zeus; he raised no objection when I was chosen with two
                    colleagues to inaugurate the sacrifice to the Dread Goddesses.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The Eumenides (Furies), whose sanctuary was a cave under the
                        Areopagus.</note> Would he have allowed all this, if he had had one jot or
                    tittle of proof for the charges that he was trumping up against me? I cannot
                    believe it. So then this is conclusive proof that he was seeking in mere wanton
                    spite to drive me from my native land. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="116" type="section">
                <p>Then, when for all his desperate shifts he could bring none of these charges home
                    to me, he turned informer against Aristarchus, aiming evidently at me. To pass
                    over other incidents, when the Council was in session and was investigating the
                    murder, Meidias came in and cried, <q type="">Don’t you know the facts of the case,
                    Councillors? Are you wasting time and groping blindly for the murderer, when you
                    have him already in your hands?</q>-meaning Aristarchus. <q type="">Won’t you put him to
                    death? Won’t you go to his house and arrest him?</q> </p>
            </div>
            <div n="117" type="section">
                <p>Such was the language of this shameless and abandoned reptile, though only the
                    day before he had stepped out of Aristarchus’s house, though up till then he had
                    been as intimate with him as anyone could be, and though Aristarchus in the day
                    of his prosperity had often importuned me to settle my suit with Meidias out of
                    court. Now if he said this to the Council, believing that Aristarchus had
                    actually committed the crime which has since proved his ruin, and trusting to
                    the tale told by his accusers, yet even so the speech was unpardonable. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="118" type="section">
                <p>Upon friends, if they seem to have done something serious, one should impose the
                    moderate penalty of withdrawing from their friendship; vengeance and prosecution
                    should be left to their victims or their enemies. Yet in a man like Meidias this
                    may be condoned. But if it shall appear that he chatted familiarly under the
                    same roof with Aristarchus, as if he were perfectly innocent, and then uttered
                    those damning charges against him in order to involve me in a false accusation,
                    does he not deserve to be put to death ten times—no! ten thousand times over?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="119" type="section">
                <p>I am going to call the witnesses now present in court to prove that my version of
                    the facts is correct; that on the day before he told that tale to the Council,
                    he had entered Aristarchus’s house and had a conversation with him; that on the
                    next day-and this, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    this for vileness is impossible to beat—he went into his house and sat as close
                    to him as this, and put his hand in his, in the presence of many witnesses,
                    after that speech in the Council in which he had called Aristarchus a murderer
                    and said the most terrible things of him; that he invoked utter destruction on
                    himself if he had said a word in his disparagement; that he never thought twice
                    about his perjury, though there were people present who knew the truth, and he
                    actually begged him to use his influence to bring about a reconciliation with
                    me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="120" type="section">
                <p>And yet, Athenians, must we not call it a crime, or rather an impiety, to say
                    that a man is a murderer and then swear that one has never said this to reproach
                    a man with murder and then sit in the same room with him? And if I let him off
                    now and so stultify your vote of condemnation, I am an innocent man apparently;
                    but if I proceed with my case, I am a deserter, I am accessory to a murder, I
                    deserve extermination. I am quite of the contrary opinion, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. If I had let Meidias off, then I
                    should have been a deserter from the cause of justice, and I might reasonably
                    have charged myself with murder, for life would have been impossible for me, had
                    I acted thus. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="121" type="section">
                <p>And now please call the witnesses to attest the truth of these statements
                        also.<quote type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title><p>[;We, Lysimachus of
                            Alopece, Demeas of Sunium, Chares of Thoricus, Philemon of Sphetta,
                            Moschus of Paeania, know that at the date when the indictment was
                            presented to the Council charging Aristarchus, the son of Moschus, with
                            the murder of Nicodemus, Meidias, who is now being tried at the suit of
                            Demosthenes, for whom we appear, came before the Council and stated that
                            Aristarchus, and no one else, was the murderer of Nicodemus, and he
                            advised the Council to go to the house of Aristarchus and arrest him.
                            This he said to the Council, having dined on the previous day with
                            Aristarchus in our company. We also know that Meidias, when he came from
                            the Council after making this statement, again entered the house of
                            Aristarchus and shook hands with him and, invoking destruction on his
                            own head, swore that he had said nothing in his disparagement before the
                            Council, and he asked Aristarchus to reconcile Demosthenes to
                        him.];</p></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="122" type="section">
                <p>Can anything go beyond that? Has there ever been, or could there ever be,
                    baseness to compare with this of Meidias? He felt justified in informing against
                    that unfortunate man, who had done him no wrong—I waive the fact that he was his
                    friend—and at the same time he was begging him to bring about a reconciliation
                    between himself and me; and not content with this, he spent money on an
                    iniquitous attempt to procure my banishment as well as that of Aristarchus. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="123" type="section">
                <p>Yet this habit of his, Athenians, this scheme of involving in yet greater
                    calamities all who stand up against him in just defence, is not something that
                    might well rouse indignation and resentment in me, but that the rest of you
                    should overlook. Far from it. All citizens alike should be stirred to anger,
                    when they reflect and observe that it is exactly the poorest and weakest of you
                    that run the greatest risk of being thus wantonly wronged, while it is the rich
                    blackguards that find it easiest to oppress others and escape punishment, and
                    even to hire agents to put obstacles in the path of justice. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="124" type="section">
                <p>Such conduct must not be overlooked. It must not be supposed that the man who by
                    intimidation tries to debar any citizen from obtaining reparation for his wrongs
                    is doing less than robbing us of our liberties and of our right of free speech.
                    Perhaps I and one or two others may have managed to repel a false and calamitous
                    charge and so have escaped destruction; but what will the vast majority of you
                    do, if you do not by a public example make it a dangerous game for anyone to
                    abuse his wealth for such a purpose? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="125" type="section">
                <p>When the accused man has rendered an account of his actions and has stood his
                    trial on the charges brought against him, then he may retaliate upon unjust
                    assailants; but even then he must not try to spirit away some witness of his ill
                    deeds, nor to escape a trial by bringing false charges; he must not count it a
                    grievance to submit to justice, but must avoid all outrageous conduct from the
                    first. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="126" type="section">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you have now heard how
                    many outrages I endured, both in my own person and in the performance of my
                    public service, and how many escapes I have had from plots and ill-treatment of
                    every kind. Yet I have omitted much, for it was not easy perhaps to mention
                    everything. But the case is this. By none of his acts was I alone wronged, but
                    in the wrongs inflicted on the chorus my whole tribe, the tenth part of the
                    citizens, shared; by his plots and attacks against me he wronged the laws, to
                    which each of you looks for protection;lastly by all these acts he wronged the
                    god to whose service I had been dedicated and that divine and awful power beyond
                    our ken—the power of Holiness. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="127" type="section">
                <p>Those who would exact from him an adequate punishment for his misdeeds must not
                    let their indignation be checked by the reflection that I alone am concerned,
                    but must base the penalty on the ground that all alike are victims of the same
                    wrong—the laws, the gods, the city of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>; and they must look upon those who support him and are
                    marshalled in his defence as something more than mere advocates, as men who set
                    the seal of their approval to his acts. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="128" type="section">
                <p>Now if, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, Meidias had in
                    other respects behaved with decency and moderation, if he had never injured any
                    other citizen, but had confined his brutality and violence to me, I might, in
                    the first place, consider this a piece of my own bad luck, and, in the second
                    place, I should be afraid lest, by pointing to the moderation and humanity of
                    the rest of his life, he might so evade punishment for his outrage on me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="129" type="section">
                <p>But as it is, the wrongs that he has done to many of you are so many and so great
                    that I am relieved of this apprehension; my fear is now, on the contrary, that
                    when you hear of the terrible wrongs that others have suffered at his hands,
                    some such argument as this may occur to you. <q type="">What have you to complain of? Have
                    you suffered more than each of his other victims?</q> Now all that he has done, I
                    could not relate to you, nor would you have the patience to listen, even if I
                    were allowed for the rest of my speech all the time assigned to both of us: all
                    my time and all his in addition would not suffice. I will confine myself to the
                    most important and clearest examples. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="130" type="section">
                <p>Or rather, this is what I propose to do. I will read you all my memoranda, just
                    as I wrote them out for my own use. I will take first whatever incident you
                    would like to hear first; next your second choice, and so on, as long as you
                    care to listen. There is no lack of variety; plenty of examples of assault, of
                    kinsmen swindled, and of sacrilege. There is not a single passage where you will
                    not find that he has committed many crimes worthy of death.<quote
                        n="Memoranda of the Crimes of Meidias">
                        <title>Memoranda of the Crimes of Meidias</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="131" type="section">
                <p>That, gentlemen of the jury, is how he has treated everyone that comes across his
                    path. I have omitted other instances, for no one could compress into a single
                    narrative the violent acts that he has spent a lifetime in committing. But it is
                    worth while noticing to what a height of audacity he has advanced in consequence
                    of his never having been punished for any of these acts. He seems to have
                    thought that no act that one man can commit against an individual was brilliant
                    or dashing enough or worth risking his life for, and unless he could affront a
                    whole tribe or the Council or some class of citizens and harass vast multitudes
                    of you at once, he felt that life was really not worth living.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true"><q type="">He that kills me some six or seven dozen of Scots at a
                        breakfast, washes his hands, and says to his wife ’Fie upon this quiet life!
                        I want work.’</q> (<bibl>Shakespeare,<title>Hen. 4</title>. Pt. 1. 2. 4.
                            115</bibl>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="132" type="section">
                <p>And as to other instances, innumerable as they are, I say nothing, but as regards
                    the cavalry which was dispatched to Argura, and of which he was one, you all
                    know of course how he harangued you on his return from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>, blaming the troop and saying that
                    its dispatch was a scandal to the city. In connection with that, you remember
                    too the abuse that he heaped on Cratinus, who is, I understand, going to support
                    him in the present case. Now if he provoked such serious but groundless quarrels
                    with so many citizens at once, what degree of wickedness and recklessness may we
                    expect from him now? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="133" type="section">
                <p>[;But I should like to ask you, Meidias, which was the greater scandal to the
                    city—the men who crossed to <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>
                    in due order, and with the equipment proper to those who were to take the field
                    against the enemy and to join forces with our allies, or you, who, when lots
                    were drawn for the expedition, prayed that you might draw a blank, who never
                    donned your cuirass, who rode on a saddle with silver trappings, imported from
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, taking with you your shawls
                    and goblets and wine-jars, which were confiscated by the customs? We of the
                    infantry learned this by report, for we had not crossed at the same point as the
                    cavalry. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="134" type="section">
                <p>And then, because Archetion or someone chaffed you on the subject, must you annoy
                    them all?]; If you did what your fellow-troopers say you did, Meidias, and what
                    you complain of them for saying, then you deserved their reproaches, because you
                    were bringing harm and disgrace both on them and on these jurymen here and on
                    all the city. But if you did not do it and it was all a fabrication, and if the
                    rest of the soldiers, instead of reproving the slanderers, chuckled over you, it
                    only shows that from your general manner of life they thought that such a story
                    exactly fitted you. It was yourself, then, that you ought to have kept more
                    under control, instead of accusing the others. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="135" type="section">
                <p>But you threaten all, you bully all. You insist that everyone else shall consult
                    your wishes; you do not your self consult how to avoid annoying others. Yes, and
                    what seems to me the most damning proof of your audacity is this: you come
                    forward, you shameless ruffian, and include all these men in one sweeping
                    accusation. Anyone else would have shuddered at the thought of doing such a
                    thing. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="136" type="section">
                <p>I observe, gentlemen, that in all other trials the defendants are charged with
                    one or two offences only, but they can rely on any number of appeals, such as
                    these: <q type="">Does anyone in court know me to be capable of this? Who among you has
                    ever seen me commit these offences? No one. The plaintiffs are libelling me out
                    of spite. I am the victim of false testimony,</q> and so on. But with Meidias the
                    case is just the reverse; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="137" type="section">
                <p>for I suppose you all know his way of life, his arrogance and his
                    superciliousness, and I even suspect that some have long marvelled at things
                    which they know themselves, but have not heard from my lips today. But I note
                    that many of his victims are reluctant to disclose in evidence all that they
                    have suffered, because they realize his violence and his persistence and the
                    extent of those resources which make him so powerful and so dreaded, despicable
                    though he is. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="138" type="section">
                <p>For a man whose wickedness and violence are supported by power and wealth is
                    fortified against any sudden attack. So this fellow, if he were deprived of his
                    property, would perhaps discontinue his outrages, or if not, he will be of less
                    account in your courts than the most insignificant criminal; for then he will
                    rail and bluster to deaf ears, and for any act of gross violence he will pay the
                    penalty like the rest of us. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="139" type="section">
                <p>But now, I believe, his champions are Polyeuctus and Timocrates and the
                    ragamuffin Euctemon. Such are the mercenaries that he keeps about him; and there
                    are others besides, an organized gang of witnesses, who do not openly force
                    themselves upon you, but readily give a silent nod of assent to his lies. [;I do
                    not of course imagine that they make anything out of him, but there are some
                    people, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, who are
                    strangely prone to abase themselves towards the wealthy, to attend upon them,
                    and to give witness in their favour.]; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="140" type="section">
                <p>All this, I expect, is alarming for the rest of you as individuals, depending
                    each upon his own resources; and that is why you band yourselves together, so
                    that when you find yourselves individually inferior to others, whether in wealth
                    or in friends or in any other respect, you may together prove stronger than any
                    one of your enemies and so check his insolence. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="141" type="section">
                <p>Now, some such ready plea as this will be submitted to you: <q type="">Why did not
                    So-and-so, who suffered this or that at my hands, try to obtain redress from me?
                    Or why did not So-and-so?</q>—naming perhaps another of his victims. But I expect
                    you all know the stock excuses for shirking the duty of self-defence—want of
                    leisure, a distaste for affairs, inability to speak, lack of means, and a
                    thousand such reasons. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="142" type="section">
                <p>I do not, however, think that Meidias has any right to use such language now; his
                    duty is to prove that he has not done what I have accused him of doing, and if
                    he cannot, then he deserves death all the more. For if he is so powerful that he
                    can act like this and yet prevent you individually from obtaining satisfaction
                    from him, you ought all of you, in common and on behalf of all, now that he is
                    in your grasp, to punish him as the common enemy of the State. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="143" type="section">
                <p>History tells us that Alcibiades lived at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> in the good old days of her prosperity, and I want you
                    to consider what great public services stand to his credit and how your
                    ancestors dealt with him when he thought fit to behave like a ruffian and a
                    bully. And assuredly it is not from any desire to compare Meidias with
                    Alcibiades that I mention this story. I am not so foolish or infatuated. My
                    object, men of Athens, is that you may know and feel that there is not, and
                    never will be, anything—not birth, not wealth, not power—that you, the great
                    mass of citizens, ought to tolerate, if it is coupled with insolence. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="144" type="section">
                <p>For Alcibiades, Athenians, was on his father’s side one of the Alcmaeonidae, who
                    are said to have been banished by the tyrants because they belonged to the
                    democratic faction, and who, with money borrowed from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, liberated our city, expelling the
                    sons of Peisistratus, and on his mother’s side he claimed descent from
                    Hipponicus and that famous house to which the people are indebted for many
                    eminent services. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="145" type="section">
                <p>But these were not his only claims, for he had also taken arms in the cause of
                    democracy, twice in <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName> and a third
                    time in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> itself, displaying
                    his patriotism, not by gifts of money or by speeches, but by personal service.
                    He had also to his credit for the Olympian chariot-race and victories there, and
                    we are told that he was regarded as the best general and the ablest speaker of
                    the day. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="146" type="section">
                <p>But yet your ancestors, for all these services, would not allow him to insult
                    them. They made him a fugitive and an outlaw, and in the day of Lacedaemonian
                    power they endured the fortification of Decelea, the capture of their fleet, and
                    every kind of loss, because they deemed any involuntary suffering more honorable
                    than a voluntary submission to the tyranny of insolence. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="147" type="section">
                <p>Yet what was his insolence compared with what has been proved of Meidias today?
                    He boxed the ears of Taureas, when the latter was chorus-master. Granted; but it
                    was as chorus-master to chorus-master that he did it, and he did not transgress
                    the present law, for it had not yet been made. Another story is that he
                    imprisoned the painter Agatharchus. Yes, but he had caught him in an act of
                    trespass, or so we are told; so that it is unfair to blame him for that. He was
                    one of the mutilators of the Hermae. All acts of sacrilege, I suppose, ought to
                    excite the same indignation, but is not complete destruction of sacred things
                    just as sacrilegious as their mutilation? Well, that is what Meidias has been
                    convicted of. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="148" type="section">
                <p>To contrast the two men, let us ask who Meidias is and to whom he displayed his
                    qualities. Do not then imagine that for you, gentlemen, being the descendants of
                    such ancestors, it would be in accordance with justice or piety, to say nothing
                    of honor, if, when you have caught a rascally, violent bully, a mere nobody and
                    son of nobody, you should pronounce him deserving of pardon or pity or favour of
                    any kind. For why should you? Because of his services as general? But not even
                    as a private soldier, much less as a leader of others, is he worth anything at
                    all. For his speeches then? In his public speeches he never yet said a good word
                    of anyone, and he speaks ill of everyone in private. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="149" type="section">
                <p>For the sake of his family perhaps? And who of you does not know the mysterious
                    story of his birth—quite like a melodrama? He was the sport of two opposing
                    circumstances. The real mother who bore him was the most sensible of mortals;
                    his reputed mother who adopted him was the silliest woman in the world. Do you
                    ask why? The one sold him as soon as he was born; the other purchased him, when
                    she might have got a better bargain at the same figure. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="150" type="section">
                <p>And yet, though he has thus become the possessor of privileges to which he has no
                    claim, and has found a fatherland which is reputed to be of all states the most
                    firmly based upon its laws, he seems utterly unable to submit to those laws or
                    abide by them. His true, native barbarism and hatred of religion drive him on by
                    force and betray the fact that he treats his present rights as if they were not
                    his own—as indeed they are not. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="151" type="section">
                <p>Such, then, being the events that make up the life of this shameless blackguard,
                    some of his associates came to me, gentlemen of the jury, urging me to retire
                    and drop this action; but finding me unmoved, they did not venture to assert
                    that he was innocent of all these crimes and would not deserve the severest
                    penalty for his deeds. They took this line of argument. <q type="">He has already been
                    convicted and condemned; what fine do you expect the court to impose on him? Do
                    you not see that he is a rich man and will talk about the equipment of
                    war-galleys and other public services? Then take care that he does not beg
                    himself off by such pleas, and make you his laughingstock, when he pays the
                    State a far less sum than he now offers you.</q> </p>
            </div>
            <div n="152" type="section">
                <p>For myself, in the first place, I do not charge you with anything dishonorable,
                    nor do I suppose that you will lay on him a lighter punishment than will
                    effectually check his insolence; and that means, for choice, death, or failing
                    that, at least the confiscation of all his property. In the next place, my own
                    opinion about his trierarchies and public services and pleas of that sort is
                    this. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="153" type="section">
                <p>If, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, public service
                    consists in saying to you at all the meetings of the Assembly and on every
                    possible occasion, <q type="">We are the men who perform the public services; we are those
                    who advance your tax-money; we are the capitalists</q>—if that is all it means,
                    then I confess that Meidias has shown himself the most distinguished citizen of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; for he bores us at every
                    Assembly by these tasteless and tactless boasts. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="154" type="section">
                <p>But if you want to find out how he really performs his services, I will tell you;
                    and please mark with what fairness I shall test him, for I will compare him with
                    myself. This man, Athenians, who is about fifty years old or only a trifle less,
                    has not performed more public services than I, who am only two and thirty.
                    Moreover I, as soon as I had reached man’s estate, undertook the trierarchy in
                    the days when only two shared the duty, and when we paid all the expenses from
                    our own purses and provided the crews ourselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="155" type="section">
                <p>Meidias, when he was of my present age, had not yet begun to perform services; he
                    has only put his hand to the task since you made twelve hundred citizens joint
                    contributors, from whom such men as Meidias exact a talent and then contract for
                    the equipment of the war-galley at the same price. After this the State provides
                    the crews and furnishes the tackle; so that some of them succeed in really
                    spending nothing at all and by pretending to have performed one public service
                    enjoy exemption from the rest. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="156" type="section">
                <p>Well, is there anything else? He has once equipped a tragic chorus; I have
                    furnished a band of male flute-players; and everyone knows that the latter
                    involves much greater expense than the former. Moreover my service is voluntary;
                    his was only undertaken after a challenge to exchange property. Therefore no one
                    could justly allow him any credit for it. What else? I have feasted my tribe and
                    equipped a chorus for the Panathenaea; he has done neither. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="157" type="section">
                <p>I was chairman of one of the tax-syndicates<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See
                        note on <bibl n="Dem. 2.29">Dem. 2.29</bibl>.</note> for ten years,
                    contributing the same share as Phormio, Lysitheides, Callaeschrus, and the
                    richest citizens, not from my actual property, of which my guardians had robbed
                    me, but from the estimated wealth which my father had left and which I was
                    entitled to inherit when I had passed the scrutiny for citizenship. That is how
                    I have borne myself towards you; but how has Meidias? To this day he has never
                    been chairman of a syndicate, though no one has ever robbed him of any part of
                    his inheritance and he has received from his father a large property. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="158" type="section">
                <p>In what, then, consist his splendor, his public services and his lordly
                    expenditure? I cannot for the life of me see, unless one fixes one’s attention
                    on these facts. He has built at <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis"
                        >Eleusis</placeName> a mansion huge enough to overshadow his neighbors; he
                    drives his wife to the Mysteries, or anywhere else that he wishes, with a pair
                    of greys from <placeName key="tgn,7011104">Sicyon</placeName>; he swaggers about
                    the market-place with three or four henchmen in attendance, describing beakers
                    and drinking-horns and cups loud enough for the passers-by to hear. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="159" type="section">
                <p>I do not see how the mass of Athenians are benefited by all the wealth that
                    Meidias retains for private luxury and superfluous display; I do see that his
                    insolence, fostered by his wealth, affects many of us ordinary folk. You ought
                    not to show respect and admiration for such things on every occasion, nor judge
                    a man’s public spirit by such tests as these—whether he builds himself a
                    splendid house or keeps many maid-servants or handsome furniture, but whether
                    his splendor and public spirit are displayed in those things in which the
                    majority of you can share. There you will find Meidias absolutely wanting. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="160" type="section">
                <p>But, mark you, he gave us a war-galley! I am sure he will brag about that vessel.
                    <q type="">I,</q> he will say, <q type="">presented you with a trireme.</q> Now this is how you must deal
                    with him. If, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, he gave
                    it from patriotic motives, be duly grateful and pay him the thanks that such a
                    gift deserves. But do not give him a chance to air his insolence; that must not
                    be conceded as the price of any act or deed. If, on the other hand, it is proved
                    that his motive was cowardice and malingering, do not be led astray. How then
                    will you know? This too I will explain. I will tell you the story from the
                    start: it is not a long one. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="161" type="section">
                <p>Voluntary gifts were first introduced at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> for the expedition to <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                        >Euboea</placeName>. Meidias was not one of those volunteers, but I was, and
                    my colleague was Philinus, the son of Nicostratus. There was a second call
                    subsequently for <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>. Meidias
                    was not one of those volunteers either. Yet surely the public-spirited man ought
                    to be found at his post on every occasion. We have now these voluntary gifts for
                    the third time, and this time he did make an offer. But how? Though present in
                    the Council when the gifts were being received, he made no offer then. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="162" type="section">
                <p>But when it was announced that the troops at <placeName key="perseus,Tamynae"
                        >Tamynae</placeName> were blockaded, and when the Council carried a
                    preliminary decree to dispatch the rest of the cavalry, to which he belonged,
                    then, alarmed at the prospect of this campaign, he came forward with a voluntary
                    gift at the next meeting of the Assembly, even before the Committee could take
                    their seats. What makes it clear, beyond all possibility of doubt, that his
                    motive was not public spirit but the desire to shirk the campaign? His
                    subsequent proceedings. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="163" type="section">
                <p>For in the first place, when it appeared, as the meeting proceeded and speeches
                    were made, that the services of the cavalry were not now required, but that the
                    proposed expedition had fallen through, he never set foot on the ship he had
                    presented, but dispatched a resident alien, the Egyptian Pamphilus, while he
                    himself stayed at home and behaved at the Dionysia in the way that is the matter
                    of the present trial. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="164" type="section">
                <p>Next, when the general, Phocion, summoned the cavalry from Argura to take their
                    turn of service, and the trickery of Meidias was exposed, then this damnable
                    coward quitted that post and hurried to his ship and never went out with the
                    cavalry whom he claimed to command here at home. But if there had been any risk
                    at sea, he would certainly have hastened to land. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="165" type="section">
                <p>Not so behaved Niceratus, the beloved son of Nicias, though he was himself
                    physically an utter weakling. Not so behaved Euctemon, the son of Aesion, nor
                    Euthydemus, the son of Stratocles. Each of these men had made the gift of a
                    war-galley, yet did not run away from the campaign in this way. Each, as an act
                    of grace and a free gift, supplied the State with a ship ready for sea, and
                    where the law of the State assigned them their posts, there each insisted on
                    giving his personal service. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="166" type="section">
                <p>But not so our cavalry-officer Meidias. He deserted the post assigned him by the
                    laws, and this, which is a punishable offence against the State, he is prepared
                    to count as a meritorious service. Yet, good heavens! what name best befits such
                    a trierarchy as his? Shall we call it patriotism, or tax-jobbing,
                    two-per-cent-collecting, desertion, malingering, and everything of that sort?
                    Unable in any other way to get himself exempt from service with the cavalry,
                    Meidias has invented this new-fangled cavalry-collectorship.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Using nominal service with the cavalry to secure the profits
                        of a collector.</note> Another point. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="167" type="section">
                <p>All the other donors of war-galleys convoyed you when you sailed back from
                        <placeName key="perseus,Styra">Styra</placeName>; Meidias alone took no part
                    in the convoy, but, without a thought for you, he was bringing fences and cattle
                    and door-posts for his own house and pit-props for his silver-mines, and so his
                    command has proved, not a public service, but a lucrative job for this
                    detestable creature. However, to prove to you the truth of my statements, though
                    most of the facts are known to you, I will nevertheless call witnesses. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="168" type="section">
                <p><quote type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title>[;We, Cleon of Sunium, Aristocles
                        of Paeania, Pamphilus, Niceratus of Acherdus, and Euctemon of Sphetta, on
                        the occasion when we sailed home from <placeName key="perseus,Styra"
                            >Styra</placeName> with the entire force, were commanders of triremes
                        along with Meidias, who is now being prosecuted by Demosthenes, for whom we
                        appear as witnesses. When the whole fleet was sailing in formation and the
                        commanders had instructions not to separate until we landed at <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, Meidias lagged behind the fleet
                        and loaded his ship with timber and fencing and cattle and other things, and
                        sailed alone into Peiraeus two days later, and did not join with the other
                        commanders in bringing the force to land.];</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="169" type="section">
                <p>Now if, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, his public
                    services and his conduct were really what he will presently in court allege and
                    boast them to have been and not what I thus prove them to have been, even so
                    surely he has no right, under cover of his services, to escape the punishment
                    due to his insolent acts. For I know that there are many men who have done you
                    great and useful service—though not after the style of Meidias! Some have won
                    naval victories, others have captured cities, others have set up many glorious
                    trophies to the credit of the State. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="170" type="section">
                <p>But yet to not one of these men have you ever yet granted, nor are you likely to
                    grant, this reward—licence for each one of them to oppress his private enemies
                    whenever he likes and in whatever way he can. For not even Harmodius and
                    Aristogeiton were so privileged, though indeed they received from you the
                    highest rewards for the noblest services. You would never have tolerated it if
                    any one had added this to the inscription on their monument, <q type="">And they shall be
                    licensed to oppress whomsoever they will.</q> No, they received their other rewards
                    for this very service, that they had restrained those who acted insolently. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="171" type="section">
                <p>I now propose to show you, Athenians, that he has received from you a recompense
                    adequate not only to the public services he has actually performed—for in that
                    case it would be small indeed!—but even to the most distinguished services; so
                    that you may not imagine that you are still in debt to this contemptible fellow.
                    For it was you, men of Athens, who elected him—he being what he is—steward of
                    the Paralus, and also commander of the cavalry, though he could not sit a horse
                    in the processions through the market-place, and superintendent of the
                    Mysteries, and sacrificer on one occasion, and buyer of the victims and all the
                    rest of it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="172" type="section">
                <p>And then, that a man’s innate baseness and cowardice and wickedness should be
                    redeemed by offices and honors and appointments from you—do you, in heaven’s
                    name, regard that as a trivial gift and favour? Take away, indeed, his right to
                    say, <q type="">I have been commander of the cavalry; I have been made steward of the
                    Paralus,</q> and what else is he good for? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="173" type="section">
                <p>But at any rate you know this, that when he had been made steward of the Paralus,
                    he plundered the people of <placeName key="perseus,Cyzicus">Cyzicus</placeName>
                    of more than five talents, and to avoid punishment he worried and harassed the
                    wretches in every possible way, and by making chaos of the treaties he has
                    alienated their state from ours, while he keeps the money himself. Since he was
                    appointed its commander, he has ruined your cavalry force, getting laws passed
                    which he afterwards disowned. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="174" type="section">
                <p>When he was steward of the Paralus at the time of your expedition to <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> against the Thebans, though he was
                    authorized to expend twelve talents of public money and was instructed by you to
                    sail and convoy the troops, he rendered them no assistance and did not arrive
                    until Diocles had already concluded his truce with the Thebans; moreover he was
                    outstripped by one of the privately owned galleys. That shows you how well he
                    had equipped your sacred galley. Then as cavalry-commander-I do not know what
                    you think of his other performances, but this wealthy fine gentleman did not
                    venture to buy a horse—not even a horse! He led the processions on one borrowed
                    from Philomelus of Paeania, and every cavalryman knows it. Please call the
                    witnesses to prove the truth of these statements also.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="175" type="section">
                <p>Now I propose, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to name
                    those who have been condemned by you, after an adverse vote of the Assembly, for
                    violating the festival, and to explain what some of them had done to incur your
                    anger, so that you may compare their guilt with that of Meidias. First of all
                    then, to begin with the most recent condemnation, the Assembly gave its verdict
                    against Euandrus of <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName> for
                    profanation of the Mysteries on the charge of Menippus, a fellow from <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>. The law concerning the Mysteries is
                    identical with that concerning the Dionysia, and it was enacted later. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="176" type="section">
                <p>Well, Athenians, what had Euandrus done to deserve your condemnation? He had won
                    a commercial suit against Menippus, but being, as he alleged, unable to catch
                    him sooner, he had arrested him while he was staying here for the Mysteries. You
                    condemned him for that alone, and there were no aggravating circumstances. When
                    he came before the court, you were inclined to punish him with death, and when
                    his accuser was induced to relent, you compelled Euandrus to refund the damages,
                    amounting to two talents, which he had won in the former action, and you also
                    made him compensate the fellow for the loss that he had sustained, on his own
                    calculation, by staying here in deference to your preliminary verdict. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="177" type="section">
                <p>There you have one case of a man, in a merely private matter, with no added
                    circumstances of insolence, paying so heavy a penalty for a breach of the law.
                    With good reason; because that is what you are here to guard—the laws and your
                    oath. That is what you who serve on any jury hold as a trust from the rest of
                    the citizens, a trust which must be maintained inviolate in the interests of all
                    who appeal to you with justice on their side. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="178" type="section">
                <p>There was another man who in your opinion had profaned the Dionysia, and although
                    he was actually sitting as assessor to his son, who was Archon, you condemned
                    him, because in ejecting from the theater a man who was taking a wrong seat, he
                    laid a hand on him. That man was the father of the highly respected
                    Charicleides, at that time archon. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="179" type="section">
                <p>Yes, and you thought that his accuser had a strong case when he said, <q type="">If I was
                    taking a wrong seat, fellow, if as you assert I was disregarding the notices,
                    what authority do the laws confer on you or even on the archon himself? The
                    authority to bid the attendants remove me, but not to strike me yourself. If I
                    still refuse to go, you may impose a fine; anything rather than touch me with
                    your own hand; for the laws have taken every precaution to save a citizen from
                    being insulted in his own person.</q> That was his argument. You gave your votes,
                    but the accuser died before he could bring the case before a jury. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="180" type="section">
                <p>Then another man, Ctesicles, was unanimously condemned by the Assembly for
                    profaning the festival, and when he came before you, you sentenced him to death,
                    because he carried a leathern lash in the procession and, being drunk, struck
                    with it a personal enemy of his. It was thought that insolence, not drink,
                    prompted the stroke, and that he seized the excuse of the procession and his own
                    drunkenness to commit the offence of treating freemen like slaves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="181" type="section">
                <p>Now I am certain, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that
                    everyone would admit that the offences of Meidias were much more serious than
                    those of any of these men, of whom one, as I have shown, forfeited the damages
                    he had already received, while the other was actually punished with death. For
                    Meidias, not being in a procession, not having won a suit, not acting as
                    assessor, having in fact no other motive than insolence, behaved worse than any
                    of them. About them I will say no more; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="182" type="section">
                <p>but Pyrrhus, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, one of
                    the Eteobutadae, who was indicted for serving on a jury when he was in debt to
                    the Treasury, was thought by some of you to deserve capital punishment, and he
                    was convicted in your court and put to death. And yet it was from poverty, not
                    from insolence, that he tried to get the juryman’s fee. And I could mention many
                    others who were put to death or disfranchised for far slighter offences than
                    those of Meidias. You yourselves, Athenians, fined Smicrus ten talents and
                    Sciton a similar sum, because he was adjudged to be proposing unconstitutional
                    measures; you had no pity for their children or friends and relations, or for
                    any of those who supported them in court. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="183" type="section">
                <p>Do not, then, display such anger when people make unconstitutional proposals, and
                    such indulgence when not their proposals, but their acts are unconstitutional.
                    For no mere words and terms can be so galling to the great mass of you as the
                    conduct of a man who persistently insults any citizen who crosses his path.
                    Beware, Athenians, of bearing this testimony against yourselves, that if you
                    detect a man of the middle class or a friend of the people committing an
                    offence, you will neither pity nor reprieve him, but will punish him with death
                    or disfranchisement, while you are ready to pardon the insolence of a rich man.
                    Spare us that injustice, and show your indignation impartially against all
                    offenders. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="184" type="section">
                <p>There are some other points that I consider no less necessary to mention than
                    those which I have already put before you. I will mention them and discuss them
                    briefly before I sit down. The leniency of your disposition, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is a great asset and advantage to
                    all wrongdoers. Give me, then, your attention while I show that you have no
                    right to admit Meidias to the least share in that advantage. My view is that all
                    men during their lives pay contributions to their own fortunes,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">See note on <bibl n="Dem. 21.101">Dem. 21.101</bibl>.</note>
                    not only those which are actually collected and paid in, but others also. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="185" type="section">
                <p>For instance, one of us is moderate, kindly disposed and merciful: he deserves to
                    receive an equivalent return from all, if he ever falls into want or distress.
                    Yonder is another, who is shameless and insulting, treating others as if they
                    were beggars, the scum of the earth, mere nobodies: he deserves to be paid with
                    the same measure that he has meted to others. If you will consent to look at it
                    in a true light, you will find that this, and not the former, is the kind of
                    contribution that Meidias has made. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="186" type="section">
                <p>Now I know that he will set up a wail, with his children grouped about him, and
                    will make a long and humble appeal, weeping and making himself as pitiable a
                    figure as he can. But the more he humiliates himself, Athenians, the more he
                    deserves your hatred. Why so? If in his past life he was so brutal and violent
                    because it was impossible for him to be humble, it would be right to abate some
                    of your anger as a concession to his natural temper and to the destiny that made
                    him the man he is; but if he knows how to behave discreetly when he likes, but
                    has deliberately chosen the opposite line of conduct, it is surely obvious that,
                    if he slips through your fingers now, he will once more prove himself the man
                    you know so well. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="187" type="section">
                <p>Pay no attention to him; do not let the present crisis in his affairs, expressly
                    invented by him, carry more weight and influence with you than the whole course
                    of his life, of which you have direct knowledge. I have no children to pose
                    before you, while I weep and wail over them for the insults I have received. For
                    that reason shall I, the victim, be of less account in your court than the
                    perpetrator of the wrong? It must not be. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="188" type="section">
                <p>When Meidias, with his children round him, calls you to cast your votes for them,
                    then you must imagine that I am standing here with the laws by my side and the
                    oath that you have sworn, demanding and imploring each of you to vote for them.
                    It is in every way more just that you should side with the laws than with this
                    man. The laws, Athenians, you have sworn to obey; through the laws you enjoy
                    your equal rights; to the laws you owe every blessing that is yours—not to
                    Meidias nor to the children of Meidias. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="189" type="section">
                <p>Perhaps he will say of me, <q type="">This man is an orator.</q> If an orator is one who
                    offers you such counsel as he thinks expedient for you, yet stops short of
                    pestering or bullying you, then for my part I would neither shun nor disclaim
                    that title. But if by orator he means one of those speakers such as you and I so
                    often see, men who have shamelessly enriched themselves at your expense, I
                    cannot be one, for I have never received a penny from you and I have spent upon
                    you all but a trifle of my fortune. Yet even if I were the most unscrupulous of
                    that gang, I ought rather to be punished according to the laws than insulted in
                    the performance of a public service. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="190" type="section">
                <p>Then again, none of these orators supports me in this trial; nor do I blame them,
                    for I have never said a word in public in support of one of them. I make it a
                    fixed rule to take my own line, speaking and acting in whatever way I believe to
                    be for your advantage. But you will see very soon that Meidias has all the
                    orators in turn ranged on his side. Yet is it fair in him to brand me with the
                    reproach of that title and then to depend on these very men to rescue him? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="191" type="section">
                <p>Perhaps too he will say something of this sort; that my present speech is all
                    carefully thought out and prepared. I admit, Athenians, that I have thought it
                    out, and I should not dream of denying it; yes, and I have spent all possible
                    care on it. I should be a poor creature if all my wrongs, past and present, left
                    me careless of what I was going to say to you about them. Yet the real composer
                    of my speech is Meidias. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="192" type="section">
                <p>The man who has furnished the facts with which the speeches deal ought in strict
                    justice to bear that responsibility, and not the man who has devoted thought and
                    care to lay an honest case before you today. That is what I am doing, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; to that I plead guilty.
                    As for Meidias, he has probably never in his life troubled himself about
                    honesty, for if it had entered his head even for a moment to consider such a
                    thing, he would not have missed it so completely in practice. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="193" type="section">
                <p>Again, I expect that he will not shrink from vilifying the people and the
                    Assembly, but will repeat what he had the effrontery to say when the plaint was
                    first brought in: that the meeting was composed of men who had stayed at home
                    when they ought to have gone to the front and who had left their posts
                    unguarded, and that he was condemned by the votes of chorus-men and aliens and
                    the like. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="194" type="section">
                <p>As those of you who were present know, gentlemen, he had risen on that occasion
                    to such a height of bravado and impudence that, by abusing and threatening and
                    turning his glance to any quarter of the Assembly that was inclined to be
                    obstreperous, he thought he could browbeat the whole body of citizens. That, I
                    think, must surely make his tears today seem ridiculous. Execrable wretch, what
                    have you to say? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="195" type="section">
                <p>Will you claim pity for your children and yourself or a kindly interest in your
                    fortunes from these men whom you have already insulted publicly? Are you alone
                    of living men privileged to be in your daily life so notoriously possessed of
                    the demon of arrogance that even those who have no dealings with you are
                    exasperated by your assurance, your tones and gestures, your parasites, your
                    wealth and your insolence; and then, the instant you are put on your trial are
                    you to be pitied? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="196" type="section">
                <p>It would be indeed a great method that you have devised, or, rather, a great
                    trick, if you could in so short a time make yourself the object of two
                    contradictory sentiments, rousing resentment by your way of life and compassion
                    by your mummeries. You have no conceivable claim to compassion; no, not for an
                    instant. On the contrary, hatred, resentment and wrath—those are what your
                    conduct calls for. But let me come back to my point, that he intends to arraign
                    the people and the Assembly. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="197" type="section">
                <p>Now when he does so, just reflect, gentlemen of the jury, that this same man
                    brought accusations against the cavalry who had served with him, coming into the
                    Assembly after they had sailed for <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                        >Olynthus</placeName>; and now once more, having stayed at home, he will
                    address his denunciation of the people to the men who were then away on service.
                    Are you, then, prepared to admit that you, whether at home or on service, are
                    what Meidias proclaims you to be, or on the contrary that he is, and always has
                    been, an unhallowed ruffian? That is my own opinion of him; [;for how else are
                    we to describe a creature whom his own troopers, his brother-officers and his
                    friends cannot stomach? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="198" type="section">
                <p>I swear solemnly by Zeus, by Apollo, and by Athena—for I will speak out, whatever
                    the result may be—for when this man was going about, trumping up the story that
                    I had abandoned the prosecution, I observed signs of disgust even among his
                    ardent supporters. And by heaven! they had some excuse, for there is no putting
                    up with the fellow; he claims to be the only rich man and the only man who knows
                    how to speak; all others are in his opinion outcasts, beggars, below the rank of
                    men. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="199" type="section">
                <p>Since he stands on such an eminence of pride, what do you think he will do, if he
                    escapes now? I will tell you how you may know it; you have only to observe the
                    signs that followed the adverse vote.]; For who is there that, if an adverse
                    vote had been recorded, and that on a charge of profaning the feast, even if
                    there had been no further suit pending and no danger ahead,—who is there, I say,
                    that would not have made that a reason for effacing himself and behaving
                    decently, at any rate until the time of the trial, if not for ever after? Anyone
                    else would have acted so. But not Meidias. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="200" type="section">
                <p>From that day onwards he has been talking, railing, and bellowing. Is there an
                    election on? Meidias of Anagyrus is a candidate. He is the accredited agent of
                    Plutarchus; he knows all the secrets; the city cannot hold him. His object in
                    all this is obvious;he wants to proclaim that <q type="">I am not a pin the worse for the
                    vote of the people: I have no fears or misgivings about the pending action.</q>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="201" type="section">
                <p>Now a man who thinks it degrading to show any fear of you, Athenians, and a
                    dashing thing to snap his fingers at you, does not such a man deserve death ten
                    times over? [;He really believes that you will have no hold over him. Rich,
                    arrogant, haughty, loud-voiced, violent, shameless, where will you catch him if
                    he gives you the slip now?]; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="202" type="section">
                <p>But in my opinion, if for nothing else, yet for those harangues that he delivers
                    at every opportunity and for the occasions that he chooses for them, he would
                    deserve the severest penalty. For of course you know that if any welcome news is
                    brought to the city, such as we all rejoice to hear, Meidias has never on any of
                    those occasions been found in the ranks of those who share in the public
                    satisfaction or the public rejoicings; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="203" type="section">
                <p>but if it is something untoward, something that no one else would wish to hear,
                    he is the first to jump up at once and harangue the people, making the utmost of
                    his opportunity and enjoying the silence by which you show your distress at what
                    has happened. <q type="">Why, that is the sort of men you Athenians are. You do not serve
                    abroad; you see no need to pay your property-tax. And then do you wonder that
                    your affairs go wrong? Do you think I am going to pay my property-tax and you
                    spend the money? Do you think I am going to fit out war-galleys and you decline
                    to embark in them?</q> </p>
            </div>
            <div n="204" type="section">
                <p>That is how he insults you, seizing the chance to void the rancor and venom that
                    he secretes in his heart against the masses, as he moves about among you. Now is
                    the chance for you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    now when he comes with his humbug and chicanery, with his lamentations, tears
                    and prayers, to throw this answer in his teeth. <q type="">Yes, and that is the sort of
                    man you are, Meidias. You are a bully; you cannot keep your hands to yourself.
                    Then can you wonder if your evil deeds bring you to an evil end? Do you think
                    that we shall submit to you and you shall go on beating us? That we shall acquit
                    you and you shall never desist?</q> </p>
            </div>
            <div n="205" type="section">
                <p>As for the speakers who will support him, their object, I swear, is not so much
                    to oblige him as to insult me, owing to the personal quarrel which that man
                        there<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Demosthenes points at Eubulus. The
                        sentence is clumsy, and even doubtful Greek, and may be corrupt. This and
                        the two following sections are obelized in S and other good Mss.</note> says
                    that I have with himself. He insists that it is so, whether I admit it or not;
                    but he is wrong. Too much success is apt sometimes to make people overbearing.
                    For when I, after all that I have suffered, do not admit that he is my enemy,
                    while he will not accept my disclaimer, but even confronts me in another’s
                    quarrel, and is prepared now to mount the platform and demand that I shall even
                    forfeit my claim to that protection which the laws afford to all, is it not
                    clear that he has grown overbearing and is too powerful to suit the interests of
                    each one of us? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="206" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, Athenians, Eubulus was in his seat in the theater when the people
                    gave their vote against Meidias, and yet, as you know, he never stood up when
                    called upon by name, though Meidias begged and implored him to do so. Yet if he
                    thought that the plaint had been brought against an innocent man, that was the
                    moment to help him by his testimony, if he was really his friend;but if he
                    withheld his support then, because he had pronounced him guilty, but is now
                    going to ask for his acquittal, because he has fallen foul of me, it is not well
                    that you should humor him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="207" type="section">
                <p>In a democracy there must never be a citizen so powerful that his support can
                    ensure that the one party submits to outrages and the other escapes punishment.
                    But if you are anxious to do me an ill turn, Eubulus,though I protest that I
                    know not why you should—you are a man of influence and a statesman; take any
                    legal vengeance you like on me, but do not deprive me of my compensation for
                    illegal outrages. If you find it impossible to harm me in that way, it may be
                    taken as a proof of my innocence that you can readily censure others, but find
                    no ground of censure in me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="208" type="section">
                <p>Now I have learned that Philippides and Mnesarchides and Diotimus of Euonymia and
                    some other rich trierarchs will plead with you for his acquittal, claiming it as
                    a favour due to themselves. I would not utter a word in disparagement of these
                    men; I should indeed be mad to do so: but I will tell you how you ought to
                    reflect and consider, when they make their request. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="209" type="section">
                <p>Suppose, gentlemen of the jury, that these men—never may it so befall, as indeed
                    it never will—made themselves masters of the State, along with Meidias and
                    others like him; and suppose that one of you, who are men of the people and
                    friends to popular government, having offended one of these men,—not so
                    seriously as Meidias offended me, but in some slighter degree—came before a jury
                    packed with men of that class; what pardon, what consideration do you think he
                    would receive? They would be prompt with their favour, would they not? Would
                    they heed the petition of one of the common folk? Would not their first words
                    be, <q type="">The knave! The sorry rascal! To think that he should insult us and still
                    draw breath! He ought to be only too happy if he is permitted to exist</q>? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="210" type="section">
                <p>Do not therefore, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    treat them otherwise than as they would treat you. Keep your respect, not for
                    their wealth or their reputation, but for yourselves. They have many advantages,
                    which no one hinders them from enjoying; then they in their turn must not hinder
                    us from enjoying the security which the laws provide as our common birthright.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="211" type="section">
                <p>Meidias will suffer no distressing hardship if he shall come to possess just as
                    much as the majority of you, whom he now insults and calls beggars, and if he is
                    stripped of the superfluous wealth that incites him to such insolence. Surely
                    such men have no right to ask of you, <q type="">Do not try the case by the laws,
                    gentlemen of the jury; do not help the man who has suffered serious wrongs; do
                    not observe your oaths; grant us your verdict as a favour.</q> If they plead for
                    Meidias, that is what their plea will come to, though these may not be their
                    actual words. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="212" type="section">
                <p>But if they are his friends and think it hard that he should not be rich, well,
                    they are extremely rich themselves; that is their good fortune. Let them spare
                    him some of their own wealth, that you may give your votes honestly, as you
                    swore to do when you came into court, and that they may be generous to him at
                    their own expense, and not at the expense of your honor. But if these men with
                    all their money are not prepared to sacrifice it, how can it be honorable for
                    you to sacrifice your oath? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="213" type="section">
                <p>An imposing muster of wealthy men, whose prosperity has raised them to apparent
                    importance, will come into court to plead with you. Men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, do not sacrifice me to any one of
                    them; but just as each of them will be zealous for his private interests and for
                    the defendant, so be zealous for your own selves and for the laws, as well as
                    for me who have fled to you for refuge, and cleave to the opinion that you
                    already hold. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="214" type="section">
                <p>If, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, at the time of the
                    plaint the people, after hearing the facts, had acquitted Meidias, it would not
                    be so hard to bear: one might console oneself with the fancy that the assault
                    had never been made, or that it was not a profanation of the festival, and so
                    on. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="215" type="section">
                <p>But now this would be the hardest blow for me to bear, if, when the offences were
                    fresh in your memory, you displayed such anger and indignation and bitterness
                    that, when Neoptolemus and Mnesarchides and Philippides and another of these
                    very wealthy men were interceding with you and me, you shouted to me not to let
                    him off, and when Blepaeus the banker came up to me, you raised such an uproar,
                    as if I was going to take a bribe—the old, old story!— </p>
            </div>
            <div n="216" type="section">
                <p>that I was startled by your clamor, Athenians, and let my cloak drop so that I
                    was half-naked in my tunic, trying to get away from his grasp, and when you met
                    me afterwards, <q type="">Mind you prosecute the blackguard,</q> you cried; <q type="">don’t let him
                    go; the Athenians will watch to see what you are going to do</q>; and yet when the
                    act has been condemned by vote as an outrage, and those who gave that verdict
                    were sitting in a sacred building, and when I have stuck to my task and not
                    betrayed either you or myself, if after all this you are going to acquit
                        him.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Editors find this sentence so
                        intolerably clumsy that they see in it a proof that Demosthenes did not
                        revise this part of the speech. It may be urged that the sentence, though
                        involved, is lucid enough and would be very effective as an apparently
                        unpremeditated outburst.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="217" type="section">
                <p>Never! [;Such a result entails all that is most disgraceful. I do not deserve
                    this at your hands, Athenians. How should I, when I am bringing to justice a
                    fellow who is as violent a bully as he is reputed to be, who has offended
                    against decency at a public festival, and who has made not only you, but all the
                    Greeks who were visiting the city, witnesses of his brutality? The people heard
                    what he had done. What was the result? They voted him guilty and passed him on
                    to your court. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="218" type="section">
                <p>So it is impossible that your decision should be concealed or hushed up, or that
                    the question should not be asked, How did you judge the case when it was brought
                    before you? No; if you punish him, you will be thought men of discretion and
                    honor and haters of iniquity; but if you acquit him, you will seem to have
                    capitulated to some other motive.]; For this is not a political issue, nor does
                    it resemble the case of Aristophon, who stopped the plaint against him by
                    restoring the crowns. This case arises from the insolence of Meidias and from
                    the impossibility of his undoing any of his acts. [;Is it then better, in view
                    of the past, to punish him now or the next time he offends? Now is the time, I
                    think, because the trial is a public one, even as the offences for which he is
                    being tried were public.]; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="219" type="section">
                <p> Furthermore, it was not I alone, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, that he then, in his intention, struck and insulted,
                    when he acted as he did, but all who may be supposed less able than I am to
                    obtain satisfaction for themselves. If you were not all beaten, if you were not
                    all insulted while acting as choir-masters, you realize of course that you
                    cannot all be choir-masters at the same time, and that no one could possibly
                    assault all of you at once with a single fist. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="220" type="section">
                <p>But whenever a solitary victim fails to obtain redress, then each one of you must
                    expect to be the next victim himself, and must not be indifferent to such
                    incidents nor wait for them to come his way, but must rather guard against them
                    as long beforehand as possible. I perhaps am hated by Meidias, and each of you
                    by someone else. Would you, then, allow that enemy, whoever he is, to gain the
                    power of doing to each of you what this man has done to me? I should think not
                    indeed. Then neither must you leave me, Athenians, in this man’s power. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="221" type="section">
                <p>Just think. The instant this court rises, each of you will walk home, one
                    quicker, another more leisurely, not anxious, not glancing behind him, not
                    fearing whether he is going to run up against a friend or an enemy, a big man or
                    a little one, a strong man or a weak one, or anything of that sort. And why?
                    Because in his heart he knows, and is confident, and has learned to trust the
                    State, that no one shall seize or insult or strike him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="222" type="section">
                <p>That sense of security, then, with which you walk the streets—will you not
                    guarantee it to me before you set off home? How can I reasonably expect to
                    survive after what I have suffered, if you leave me in the lurch? Perhaps
                    someone will say, <q type="">Take heart! You will not be insulted again.</q> But if I am,
                    will you be angry with him then, after acquitting him now? Do not, gentlemen of
                    the jury, do not betray me or yourselves or the laws. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="223" type="section">
                <p>For if you would only examine and consider the question, what it is that gives
                    you who serve on juries such power and authority in all state-affairs, whether
                    the State empanels two hundred of you or a thousand or any other number, you
                    would find that it is not that you alone of the citizens are drawn up under
                    arms, not that your physical powers are at their best and strongest, not that
                    you are in the earliest prime of manhood; it is due to no cause of that sort but
                    simply to the strength of the laws. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="224" type="section">
                <p>And what is the strength of the laws? If one of you is wronged and cries aloud,
                    will the laws run up and be at his side to assist him? No; they are only written
                    texts and incapable of such action. Wherein then resides their power? In
                    yourselves, if only you support them and make them all-powerful to help him who
                    needs them. So the laws are strong through you and you through the laws. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="225" type="section">
                <p>Therefore you must help them as readily as any man would help himself if wronged;
                    you must consider that you share in the wrongs done to the laws, by whomsoever
                    they are found to be committed; and no excuse—neither public services, nor pity,
                    nor personal influence, nor forensic skill, nor anything else—must be devised
                    whereby anyone who has transgressed the laws shall escape punishment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="226" type="section">
                <p>Those of you who were spectators at the Dionysia hissed and hooted Meidias when
                    he entered the theater; you gave every indication of your abhorrence, though you
                    had not yet heard what I had to say about him. Were you so indignant before the
                    case was investigated, that you urged me to demand vengeance for my wrongs and
                    applauded me when I brought my plaint before the Assembly? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="227" type="section">
                <p>And yet now, when his guilt has been established, when the people, sitting in a
                    sacred building, have anticipated his condemnation, when all the other crimes of
                    this miscreant have been sifted, when it has fallen to your lot to be his judges
                    and it lies in your power to conclude the whole affair by a single vote—now, I
                    say, will you hesitate to succor me, to gratify the people, to give all a lesson
                    in sobriety, and to enjoy perfect safety for the rest of your lives, by making
                    an example of the defendant for the instruction of others?Therefore for all the
                    reasons that I have urged, and above all for the honor of the god whose festival
                    he has been convicted of profaning, punish this man by casting the vote which
                    piety and justice alike demand.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
