<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Carousal, or the Lapiths</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
    <imprint>
        <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
        <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
        <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
    </imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
</monogr>
    <series>                     
        <title>Loeb Classical Library</title>  
    </series>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianha01luciuoft/page/412/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.b000604153?urlappend=%3Bseq=424">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.1.p.413"/>
<head>The Carousal, or the Lapiths<note xml:lang="eng">The sub-title comes from the parallel that Lucian draws
(in section 45) between this affair and the wedding breakfast
of Peirithous, which ended in a hand-to-hand encounter
between the Centaurs and the Lapiths. The piece is thought
to Be modelled on the Symposium of Menippus, the Cynic
satirist.</note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

They say you had all kinds of sport yesterday,
Lycinus, at the house of Aristaenetus, at dinner, and
that several speeches on philosophy were made, out
of which quite a quarrel arose. Unless Charinus was
lying, the affair even ended in wounds and the party
was finally broken up by the shedding of blood.</p>

<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
Now how did Charinus know that, Philo? He did
not dine with us.</p>

<p><label>PHILO</label>
He said that Dionicus, the doctor, told “him.
Dionicus, I suppose, was one of the guests.</p>

<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
Yes, to be sure ; but even he was not there for all
of it, from the very beginning: it was late and the
battle was about half over when he came on the
scene, a little before the wounds. So I am surprised
that he could give a clear account of any of it, as he
did not witness what led up to the quarrel that
ended in bloodshed.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
<label>PHILO</label>
True, Lycinus; and for that very reason Charinus
told us, if we wanted to hear the truth of it and all
the details, to come to you, saying that Dionicus


<pb n="v.1.p.415"/>

himself had said that he was not there for all ot it,
but that you knew exactly what had happened and
could actually recite the speeches, being, as you are,
an attentive and not a careless listener to such
discussions. So do hurry and give us this most
delightful entertainment—-for none, I am sure, could
»be more delightful, at least to me, especially as we
‘shall enjoy a peaceful and bloodless entertainment,
without intemperance and out of range of missiles,
whether it was old men or young who misconducted
themselves at dinner, led on by strong drink to do
and say what they should not.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
<label>LYCINUS</label>
It was rather a silly affair, Philo, and yet you want
me to publish it abroad and tell what happened when
heads were turned with wine, when it all should be
forgotten and the whole business put down'to a god— .
Dionysus, I mean, who scarcely permits anyone to
remain uninitiated in his rites and a stranger to his
revels. Don’t you think it rather bad form to
enquire into such matters minutely? The proper
thing is to leave them behind you in the diningroom when you go away. As you know, there is a
saying from the poets: “I hate to drink with him
that hath a memory.”
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Author unknown : quoted also by Plutarch (Prooemium to
Quaest. Sympos.). See also Index to Corpus Paroemiogr. Gr.</note>
And Dionicus did not do
right, either, to blab it all to Charinus and besprinkle philosophers with the copious dregs of their
stale cups. As for me—get out with you! I shan’t
tell you anything of the kind !</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4">
<p><label>PHILO</label>
That is all put on, Lycinus. But you needn’t have
acted that way with me, for I know very well that



<pb n="v.1.p.417"/>

you are much more eager to talk than I to listen, and
I have an idea that if you had nobody to listen to
you, you would enjoy going up to a pillar or a statue
and pouring it all out in a stream, without a pause.
In fact, if I should wish to go away now, you would
not let me go untold, but would hold me and follow
me and entreat me. And now I am going to take
my turn at putting on. (Turns to‘another friend.) If
you like, let’s go and find out about it from someone
else. (To Lyctnus.) You may keep your story to
yourself!</p>

<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
Don’t get angry! I will tell you, since you
are so anxious, but don’t you tell a lot of people.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5">
<p><label>PHILO</label>
If I have not forgotten all I know of you, Lycinus,
you will do that better than I can, and you will
lose no time in telling everybody, so that I shan’t be
needed.

</p><p>

But first tell me one thing—was it to
celebrate the wedding of his son Zeno that
Aristaenetus entertained you ?</p>

<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
No, he was marrying his daughter Cleanthis to
the son of Eucritus the banker, the lad who is
studying philosophy.</p>

<p><label>PHILO</label>
A very good-looking lad, to be sure; still immature, though, and hardly old enough to be married.</p>

<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
But he could not find anyone who suited him
better, I suppose. As this boy seemed to be
mannerly and had taken an interest in philosophy,


<pb n="v.1.p.419"/>

and also as he was the only son of Eucritus, who is
rich, he preferred him to all the rest as a husband
for his daughter.</p>

<p><label>PHILO</label>
You give a very good reason in saying that Eucritus
is rich. But come, Lycinus, who were the people
at dinner ?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

<label>LYCINUS</label>
Why should I tell you all of them? The philosophers and literary men, whom, I suppose, you
are most eager to hear about, were Zenothemis, the
old man of the Porch,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The Porch: where Zeno the Stoic used to teach.</note> and along with him Diphilus,
whom they call “Labyrinth,” tutor of Aristaenetus’
boy Zeno. From the Walk
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">The Walk (xepfxaros) in the Lyceum, where the Peripatetics had their meeting-place.</note> there was Cleodemus—
you know him, the mouthy, argumentative fellow,
whom his pupils call “Sword” and “Cleaver.”
Hermon the Epicurean was there too, and as he
came in the Stoics at once began to glower at him
and turn their backs on him; it was clear that they
loathed him as they would a parricide or a man
under a curse. These men had been asked to
dinner as Aristaenetus’ own friends and associates, and
also the grammarian Histiaeus and the rhetorician
Dionysodorus.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>

Then, too, on account of Chaereas, the
bridegroom, Ion the Platonic philosopher, who is his
teacher, shared the feast—a grave and reverend
person to look at, with great dignity written on his
features. Indeed, most people call him “Rule,” out
of regard for the straightness of his thinking. When
he came in, they all arose in his honour and received
him like a supernatural being; in short it was a regular
divine visitation, the advent of Ion the marvellous.




<pb n="v.1.p.421"/>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>

By that time we had to take our places, for almost
everyone was there. On the right as you enter, the
women occupied the whole couch, as there were
a good many of them, with the bride among them,
very scrupulously veiled and hedged in by the
women. Toward the back door came the rest of the
company according to the esteem in which each was
held.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

Opposite the women, the first was Eucritus,
and then Aristaenetus. Then a question was raised
whether Zenothemis the Stoic should have _precedence, he being an old man, or Hermon the
Epicurean, because he was a priest of the Twin
Brethren and a member of the leading family in the
city. But Zenothemis solved the problem ; “Aristaenetus,” said he, “if you put me second to
this man here,— an Epicurean, to say nothing worse
of him,—I shall go away and leave you in full
possession of your board.” With that he called his
attendant and made as if to go out. So Hermon
said: “Take the place of honour, Zenothemis; but
you would have done well to yield to me because I
am a priest, if for no other reason, however much
you despise Epicurus.” “You make me laugh,’
said Zenothemis: “an Epicurean priest!’ With
these words he took his place, and Hermon next
him, in spite of what had passed ; then Cleodemus
the Peripatetic ; then Ion, and below him the bridegroom, then myself; beside me Diphilus, and
below him his pupil Zeno; and then the rhetorician
Dionysodorus and the grammarian Histiaeus,


<pb n="v.1.p.423"/>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>

<label>PHILO</label>
Heavens, Lycinus, it’s a learned academy, this dinner
party that you are telling of! Philosophers almost
to a man. Good for Aristaenetus, I say, because
in celebrating the greatest festival day that there is,
he thought fit to entertain the most learned men in
preference to the rest of the world, and culled the
bloom, as it were, of every school, not including some
and leaving out others, but asking all without
discrimination.</p>

<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
Why, my dear fellow, he is not one of the common
run of rich men; he is interested in culture and
spends the better part of his time with these people.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

Well, we dined peacefully at first, and were served
with all sorts of dishes, but I don’t suppose there is
any need of enumerating them—the sauces and
pastries and ragouts. There was everything, and
plenty of it. Meanwhile Cleodemus bent over to
Ion and said : “Do you see the old man ?””—meaning
Zenothemis: I was listening, you know. “How he
stuffs himself with the dainties and has covered his
cloak with soup, and how much food he hands to his
attendant standing behind him! He thinks that the
others do not see him, but he forgets the people at
his back. Point it out to Lycinus, so that he can
testify to it.’ But I had no need of Ion to point it
out, for I had seen it all from my coign of vantage
some time ago.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
Just as Cleodemus said that, Alcidamas the Cynic
romped in uninvited, getting off the commonplace
joke about Menelaus coming of his own accord.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Ihiad 2, 408.</note>
Most of them thought he had done an impudent



<pb n="v.1.p.425"/>

thing, and they slyly retorted. with the first thing
they could think of, one growling under his breath,
<cit>
<quote>
<l>Menelaus, thou’rt a fool!</l></quote> <bibl>Iliad 7, 109.</bibl></cit> another:

<cit>
<quote>
<l>But Agamemnon, Atreus’ son, was sorely vexed,</l></quote> <bibl>Iliad 1, 24.</bibl></cit>

and others
other remarks that, in the circumstances, were to the
point and witty. But nobody dared to speak out,
for they all feared Alcidamas, who was really “good
at the war-cry,”
<note xml:lang="eng" n="3">Like Menelaus: Iliad 2, 408.</note> and the noisiest of all the Cynic
barkers, for which reason he was considered a
superior person and was a great terror to everybody.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13">
<p>
Aristaenetus commended him and bade him take
a chair and sit beside Histiaeus and Dionysodorus.
“Get out with you!” said he. “What you tell me
to do is womanish and weak, to sit on a chair or on
a stool, like yourselves on that soft bed, lying almost
flat on your batks while you feast, with purple cloths
under you. I shall take my dinner on my feet as I
walk about the dining-room, and if I get tired I'll lie
on the floor, leaning on my elbow, with my cloak
under me, like Heracles in the pictures they paint
of him.” “Very well,” said Aristaenetus ; “if you
prefer it that way.” Then Alcidamas began to
circle about for his dinner, shifting 1o richer
pasturage as the Scythians do, and following the
orbits of the waiters. </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14">
<p>But even while he was eating
he was not idle, for he talked of virtue and vice all
the time, and scoffed at the gold and silver plate;
for example, he asked Aristaenetus what was the use
of all those great goblets when earthenware would
do just as well. But he had begun to be a bore by





<pb n="v.1.p.427"/>

this time, so Aristaenetus put a quietus on him for
the moment by directing the waiter to give him a
big bowl and pour him out a stiffer drink. He
thought that he had had a good idea, little realising
what woes that bowl was destined to give rise to.
On taking it, Alcidamas kept quiet for a little while,
throwing himself on the floor and lying there halfnaked as he had threatened, with his elbow squared
under him and the bowl in his right hand, just as
Heracles in the cave of Pholus is represented by
the painters.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>

By this time the cup was going round continually
among the rest of the party, there were toasts and
conversations, and the lights had been brought
in. Meanwhile, noticing that the boy in attendance ~
on Cleodemus, a handsome cup-bearer, was smiling
(I must tell all the incidents of the feast, I suppose,
especially whatever happened that was rather good),
I began to keep special watch to see what he
was smiling about. After a little while he went up
to Cleodemus as if to take the cup from him, and
Cleodemus pressed his finger and gave him two
drachmas, I think, along with the cup. The boy
responded to the pressure of his finger with another
smile, but no doubt did not perceive the money, so
that, through his not taking it, the two drachmas
fell and made a noise,.and they both blushed very
noticeably. Those near by them wondered whose
the coins were ; for the lad said he had not dropped
them, and Cleodemus, beside whom the noise was
made, pretended that he had not let them fall. So
the matter was disregarded and ignored, since not


<pb n="v.1.p.429"/>

very many saw it except surely Aristaenetus, for he
shifted the boy a little later on, sending him out
of the room unobtrusively, and directed one
of the full-grown, muscular fellows, a muleteer
or stable-boy, to wait on Cleodemus. So the affair
turned out in that way, whereas it would have
caused Cleodemus great shame if it had been
speedily noised about among the whole company
instead of being hushed up on the spot by the
clever manner in which Aristaenetus treated the silly
performance.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>

The Cynic Alcidamas, who was tipsy by this time,
enquired the name of the bride, and then, after
calling for silence in a loud voice and fixing his eyes
on the women, he said: “Cleanthis, I pledge you
Heracles, my patron.” Since everybody laughed at
that, he said: “Did you laugh, you scum of the
earth, that I gave the bride a toast to our god
Heracles? I’d have you to know that if she doesn’t
accept the bowl from me, she will never have a son
like me, invincible in courage, unfettered in intellect
and as strong in body as I am,” and with that
he bared himself still more, in the most shameless
way. Again the guests laughed at all this, and he
got up in anger with a fierce, wild look, clearly
not intending to keep the peace any longer. Perhaps he would have hit someone with his staff if just
in the nick of time a huge cake had not been
brought in; but when he set eyes on that, he
became calmer, put away his wrath, and began
to walk about and stuff himself. </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17">
<p>Most of the


<pb n="v.1.p.431"/>

company were drunk by then, and the room was full
of uproar. Dionysodorus the rhetorician was making
speeches, pleading first on one side and then on the
other, and was getting applauded by the servants
who stood behind him. Histiaeus the grammarian,
who had the place next him, was reciting verse,
combining the lines of Pindar and Hesiod and
Anacreon in such a way as to make out of them a
single poem and a very funny one, especially in the
part where he said, as though foretelling what was
going to happen:

<cit><quote><l>They smote their shields together,</l>
</quote> <bibl>Iliad 4, 447.</bibl></cit>
and

<cit><quote><l>Then lamentations rose, and vaunts of men.</l>
</quote> <bibl>Iliad 4, 450</bibl><note xml:lang="eng" n="2">Ausonius’ Cento Nupiialis, an epithalamium composed of tags from Vergil, illustrates Lucian’s
meaning perfectly.</note></cit>

But Zenothemis was reading aloud from a closely
written book that he had taken from his attendant.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18">
<p>
When, as often happens, the service of the waiters
was interrupted for a while, Aristaenetus planned
to prevent even that period from being unentertaining and empty, and ordered the clown to come
in and do or say something funny, in order to
make his guests still merrier. In came an ugly
fellow with his head shaven except for a few hairs
that stood up straight on his crown. First he
danced, doubling himself up and twisting himself
about to cut a more ridiculous figure; then he beat
time and recited scurrilous verses in an Egyptian
brogue, and finally he began to poke fun at the
guests. </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19">
<p>The rest laughed when they were made
fun of, but when he took a fling at Alcidamas in




<pb n="v.1.p.433"/>

the same way, calling him a Maltese lapdog,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The joke here lies primarily in the play on κύων (Cynic),
but it should also be borne in mind that the Greek name
Melite was given not only to the island of Malta, but to the
deme in Athens in which the worship of Heracles, the patron
of the Cynic sect, was localised.</note> Alcidamas got angry: indeed, for a long time it had
been plain that he was jealous because the other
fellow was making a hit and holding the attention
of the room. So, throwing off his philosopher’s
cloak, he challenged him to fight, or else, he said,
he would lay his staff on him. Then poor Satyrion,
for that was the clown’s name, stood up to him and
fought. It was delicious to see a philosopher squaring
off at a clown, and giving and receiving blows in
turn. Though some. of onlookers were disgusted,
others kept laughing, until finally Alcidamas had
enough of his punishment, well beaten by a tough
little dwarf. So they got roundly laughed at.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>


At that point Dionicus, the doctor, came in, not
long after the fray. He had been detained, he said,
to attend a man who had gone crazy, Polyprepon the
flute-player; and he told a funny story. He said
that he had gone. into the man’s room without
knowing that he was already affected by the trouble,
and that Polyprepon, getting out of bed quickly, had
locked the door, drawn a knife, handed him his flutes
and told him to begin playing; and then, because
he could not play, had beaten him with a strap on
the palms of his hands. At last in the face of so
great a peril, the doctor devised this scheme: he
challenged him to a match, the loser to get a certain
number of blows. First he himself played wretchedly, and then giving up the flutes to Polyprepon, he



<pb n="v.1.p.435"/>

took the strap and the knife and threw them quickly
out of the window into. the open court. Then,
feeling safer, he grappled with him and called the
neighbours, who prised the door open and rescued
him. And he showed the marks of the blows, and
a few scratches on his face.
Dionicus, who had made no less of a hit than the
clown, thanks to his story, squeezed himself in
beside Histiaeus and fell to dining on what was left.
His coming was a special dispensation, for he proved
very useful in what followed.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>

You see, a servant
came into the midst of us, saying that he was from
Hetoemocles the Stoic and carrying a paper which
he said his master had told him to read in public, so
that everybody would hear, and then to go back
again. On getting the consent of Aristaenetus, he
went up to the lamp and began to read.</p>

<p><label>PHILO</label>
I suppose, Lycinus, that it was an address in
praise of the bride, or else a wedding-song? They
often write such pieces.</p>

<p><label>LYCINUS</label>
Of course we ourselves expected something of the
sort, but it was far from that: its contents were :</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22">
<p>"Hetoemocles the philosopher to Aristaenetus.</p>
<p>“How I feel about dining out, my whole past life
can testify; for although every day I am pestered
by many men much richer than you are, nevertheless
I am never. forward about accepting, as I am familiar


<pb n="v.1.p.437"/>

with the disturbances and riotous doings at dinnerparties. But in your case and yours only I think I
have reason to be angry, because you, to whom I
have so long ministered indefatigably, did not think
fit to number me among your friends : no, I alone do
not count with you, and that too though I live next
door. I am indignant, therefore, and more on your
account than on my own, because you have shown
yourself so thankless, For me, happiness is not a
matter of getting a wild boar, a hare or a cake—
things which I enjoy ungrudged at the tables of
other people who know what is right. Indeed, today I might have had dinner with my pupil
Pammenes (and a splendid dinner, too, they say), but
I did not accede to his entreaties, saving myself for
you, fool that I was.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
You, however, have given me
the go-by and are entertaining others. No wonder,
for you are even yet unable to distinguish between
the better and the worse, and you have not the
faculty of direct comprehension, either. But I know
where all this comes from—those wonderful philosophers of yours, Zenothemis and the Labyrinth, whose
mouths I could very soon stop, I know, with a single
syllogism, Heaven forgive me for boasting! Just
let one of them say what philosophy is, or, to go
back to the elements, what is the difference between
attribute and accident.<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">More literally, ἕξις means a permanent state, σέσις a
transient state.</note> I shall not mention an
of the fallacies like ‘ the horns,’ ‘ the heap,’ or ‘ the
mower.’
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">The Stoics devoted a great deal of study to the invention
and solution of fallacies. “The horns” ran thus: “All that
you have not lost, you have; but you have not lost horns,
ergo, you have them.” In "the heap” the philosopher proves that one grain of corn makes a heap; in “the
mower,” that a man who says he will mow a field will not
and cannot mow it. Several other fallacies are illustrated
in "Philosophers for Sale,” 22. </note>


<pb n="v.1.p.439"/>

“Well, much may your philosophers profit you !
Holding as I do that only what is honourable is good,
I shall easily stand the slight. </p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24">
<p>But you need not
think you can afterwards take refuge in the plea
that you forgot me in all the confusion and bother,
for I spoke to you twice to-day, not only in the morning at your house, but later in the day, when you
were sacrificing at the temple of Castor and Pollux,
“I have made this statement to set myself right with
your guests.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>

But if you think that I am angry over
a mere dinner, call to mind the story of Oeneus and
you will see that Artemis herself was angry because
she was the only one whom he had not asked to the
sacrifice when he entertained all the rest-of the
gods. Homer puts it something like this:
Whether he forgot or would not, greatly was his soul
at fault.<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Iliad 9, 537.</note>
Euripides says :
<cit><quote><l>This land is Calydon, lying over seas</l>
<l>From Pelops’ isle ; a land of fertile plains.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>From the lost Meleager of Euripides.</bibl></cit>

<note xml:lang="eng" n="2"> .</note>
And Sophocles:

<cit><quote><l>A boar, a monstrous thing, on Oeneus’ fields</l>
<l>Turned loose Latona’s lass, who kills afar.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>From the lost Meleager of Sophocles.</bibl></cit>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
“I bring to your attention only these few points
out of many, so that you may learn what sort of man
you have left out in favour of Diphilus, whom you
entertain and have put in charge of your son. No





<pb n="v.1.p.441"/>

wonder, for he is nice to the boy and is an indulgent tutor. If it were not beneath me to say such
things, I might have told you something more, and
if you wished you could find out from Zopyrus, the
boy’s attendant, that it is true. But it is wrong to.
make trouble at a wedding and to defame others,
especially with charges sounseemly. Albeit Diphilus
deserves it for having won two pupils away from me,
I shall hold my tongue in deference to Philosophy
herself.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>

“I have directed my servant, in case you offer him
a portion of boar’s flesh or venison or sesame-cake to
bring to me as an excuse for not asking me to dinner,
not to take it, for fear it may seem as though I sent
him with that in view.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>

While all that was being read, my dear fellow, the
sweat poured off me for shame, and to quote the
saying, I prayed that the earth would swallow me
when I saw the guests all laughing at every
sentence, especially as many as knew Hetoemocles,
a man with gray hair who looked to be highminded. It was a marvel to me that such a man
had hoodwinked them, deceiving them with his
beard and the concentration expressed in his
features. It was my notion that Aristaenetus
had not carelessly overlooked him, but that, not
thinking he would accept if invited, he would not
expose himself to any such treatment, and so thought
best not to try him at all.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29">
<p> When at last the slave
stopped reading, the whole party looked at Zeno and
Diphilus, who were frightened and pale, and by the
distress in their faces acknowledged the truth of the


<pb n="v.1.p.443"/>

charges brought by Hetoemocles. Aristaenetus was
perturbed and fall of confusion, but he told us to go
on drinking just the same and tried to smooth the
business over, smiling as he did so; the servant he
sent away with the words: “I will see to it.” After
a little while Zeno withdrew unobservedly, for his
attendant directed him to go, as if at the bidding of
his father.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>

Cleodemus had long been looking for an opportunity, as he wanted to pitch into the Stoics and was
ready to burst because he could not find a satisfactory
opening. But at last the letter gave him his cue,
and he said: “That is what your noble Chrysippus
does, and your wonderful Zeno and Cleanthes!
They are nothing but miserable phrase-makers and
question-mongers, philosophers in dress, but in-all
else just like Hetoemocles, most of them. And the
letter—see how venerable it is! To cap all, Aristaenetus is Oeneus and Hetoemocles is Artemis! Good
Lord! In excellent taste, all of it, and just the
thing for a festive occasion!”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p> “Yes,” said Hermon,
from his place above Cleodemus, “I suppose he had
heard that Aristaenetus had a boar ready for the
dinner, so that he thought it not inopportune to
mention the boar of Calydon. Come, Aristaenetus,
in the name of Hospitality send him a portion with
all speed, for fear you may be too late and the old
man may waste away like Meleager from hunger!
Yet it would be no hardship to him, for Chrysippus
held that all such things are of no import.”


<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The Stoics divided the objects of human endeavour into
three classes—the good, which were to be sought; the
bad, which were to be shunned; and the indifferent, or
unimportant, which were neither to be sought nor shunned.</note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="32"><p>


<pb n="v.1.p.445"/>

“What, do you dare to mention the name of
Chrysippus ?” said Zenothemis, rousing himself and
shouting at the top of his voice."Dare you judge
Cleanthes and Zeno, who were learned men, by a
single individual who is not a regular philosopher, by
Hetoemocles the charlatan? Whoare you two, pray,
to say all that? Hermon, didn’t you cut off the hair
of the Twin Brethren because it was gold?<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Antique statues with golden (or gilded) hair are
mentioned not infrequently. In the  "Timon” (4) Lucian
alludes to the theft of the hair from the head of the famous
statue of Zeus in Olympia.</note>
You'll
suffer for it, too, when the executioner gets you!
And as for you, Cleodemus, you had an affair with
the wife of your pupil Sostratus, and were found out
and grossly mishandled. Have the grace to hold your
tongues, then, with such sins on your consciences !”’
“But I don’t sell the favours of my own wife as you
do,” said Cleodemus, “nor did I take my foreign pupil’s
allowance in trust and then swear by Athena Polias
that I never had it, nor do I lend money at four per
cent. a month, nor throttle my pupils if they fail to
pay their fees in time.” “But you can’t deny,” said
Zenothemis, “that you sold Crito a dose of poison for
his father!”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="33"><p>

And with that, being in the act of
drinking, he flung on the pair all that was left in the
cup, and it was about half full! Ion also got the
benefit of his nearness to them, and he quite deserved
it. Well, Hermon, bending forward, began wiping
the wine from his head and calling the guests to
witness what had been done to him. But Cleodemus,
not having a cup, whirled about and spat on Zenothemis; then, taking him by the beard with his left
hand, he was about to hit him in the face, and would



<pb n="v.1.p.447"/>

have’ killed the old man if Aristaenetus had not
stayed his hand, stepped over Zenothemis and lain
down between them, to separate them and make
them keep the peace with him for a dividing-wall.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="34"><p>
While all this was going -on, Philo, various
thoughts were in my mind; for example, the very
obvious one that it is no good knowing the liberal
arts if one doesn’t improve his way of living, too.
At any rate, the men I have mentioned, though
clever in words, were getting laughed at, I saw, for
their deeds. And then I could not help wondering
whether what everyone says might not after all be
true, that education leads men away from right
thinking, since they persist in having no regard for
anything but books and the thoughts in them. At
any rate, though so many philosophers were present,
there really was not a single one to be seen who was
devoid of fault, but some acted disgracefully and
some talked still more disgracefully ;  and I could not
lay what was going on to the wine, considering what
Hetoemocles had written without having had either
food or drink.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="35"><p>

The tables were turned, then, and
the unlettered folk were manifestly dining i in great
decorum, without either getting maudlin or behaving
disreputably ; they simply laughed and passed judgement, perhaps, on the others, whom they used to
admire, thinking them men of importance because of
the garb they wore. The learned men, on the
contrary, were playing the rake and abusing each
other and gorging themselves and bawling and
coming to blows ; and “marvellous” Alcidamas even
made water right there in the room, without showing


<pb n="v.1.p.449"/>

any respect for the women. It seemed to me that,
to use the best possible simile, the events of the
dinner were very like what the poets tell of Discord.
They say, you know, that, not having been asked to
the wedding of Peleus, she threw the apple into the
company, and that from it arose the great war at
Troy.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The golden apple, for the fairest of the goddesses, was
awarded to Aphrodite by Paris, who was paid for his
decision by being given the love of Helen.</note>
Well, to my thinking ‘Hetoemocles by
throwing his. letter into the midst of us like an
Apple of Discord had brought on woes quite as great
as those of the Iliad.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="36"><p>

The friends of Zenothemis and Cleodemus did not
stop quarrelling when Aristaenetus came between
them. “For the present,’ said Cleodemus, “it is
enough if you Stoics are shown up in your ignorance,
but to-morrow I will pay you back as I ought. Tell
me, then, Zenothemis, or you, Diphilus, you pattern
of propriety, why it is that although you say moneygetting is of no import, you aim at nothing in the
world but getting more, and for this reason always
hang about rich people and lend money and extort
high interest and teach for pay; and again, why is
it that although you hate pleasure and inveigh
against the Epicureans, you yourselves do to others
and suffer others to do to you all that is most
shameful for pleasure’s sake; you get angry if a
man does not ask you to dinner, and when you are
actually asked, you not only eat quantities but hand
over quantities to your servants,’—and with that
he tried to pull away the napkin that Zenothemis’
slave was holding. It was full of meats of all kinds,
and he intended to open it and throw its contents



<pb n="v.1.p.451"/>

on the ground, but the slave clung to it stoutly and
did not let him.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="37"><p>

“Bravo, Cleodemus,” said Hermon;
“let them tell why they inveigh against pleasure
when they themselves want to have more of it than
the rest of mankind.” “No,” said Zenothemis, “but
do you, Cleodemus, say why you hold that wealth is
important.” “No, that is for you to do!” This
went on for a long while, until Ion, bending forward
to make himself more conspicuous, said : “Stop, and
if you wish I will put before you a topic for a
discussion worthy of the present festal day, and you
shall talk and listen without quarrelling, exactly as
in our Plato’s circle, where most of the time was
passed in discussion.” All the guests applauded,
especially Aristaenetus and Eucritus, who hoped at
least to do away with the unpleasantness in that
way. Aristaenetus went back to his own place,
trusting that peace had been made.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="38"><p>

At the same
time we were served with what they call the “Full
Dinner”’—a bird apiece, boar’s flesh and_hare’s,
broiled fish, sesame-cakes and sweetmeats; all of
which you had leave to carry away. They did not
put a separate tray in front of each of us, but
Aristaenetus and Eucritus had theirs together on a
single table, and each was to take what was on his
side. In like manner Zenothemis the Stoic and
Hermon the Epicurean had theirs together, and then
Cleodemus and Ion, who came next, and after them
the bridegroom and myself; Diphilus, however, had
two portions set before him, as Zeno had gone away.
Remember all this, Philo, please, because it is of
importance for my story.
ed


<pb n="v.1.p.453"/>

<label>PHILO</label>
I shall remember, of course.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="39"><p>
<label>LYCINUS</label>
Well, Ion said: “Then I will begin first, if you
like”; and after a little pause: “Perhaps with men of
such distinction here we ought to talk of ‘ideas’ and
incorporeal entities and the immortality of the soul ;
but in order that I may not be contradicted by all
those who are not of the same belief in philosophy,
I shall take the topic of marriage and say what is
fitting. It were best not to need marriage, but to
follow Plato and Socrates and be content with friendship: at all events only such as they can attain perfection in virtue. But if we must marry, we should
have our wives in common, as Plato held, so as to be
devoid of envy.”</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="40">
<p>
These remarks gave rise to laughter, because
they were made out of season. But Dionysodorus
said : “Stop your outlandish jabbering! Where can
the word envy be found in that sense, and in what
author?”<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The rhetorician ζῆλος at Ion for using ¢jAos in the sense
of ζηλοτυπία, ‘ jealousy in love.’</note> “What, do you dare open your mouth,
you scum of the earth?” said Ion, and Dionysodorus
began to give him back his abuse in due form.
But the grammarian Histiaeus (simple soul!) said:
“Stop, and I will read you a wedding-song,””</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="41">
<p> and
began to read. The verses were these, if I remember
right :
<quote>
<l>O what a maiden in the halls</l>
<l>Of Aristaenetus</l>
<l>Her gentle nurture had, our queen</l>
<l>Cleanthis glorious !</l>




<pb n="v.1.p.455"/>

<l>Superior to other maids</l>
<l>As many as there be,</l>
<l>Than Aphrodite prettier</l>
<l>And Helen eke is she.</l>
<l>To you, O groom, a greeting too,</l>
<l>Most handsome of your mates</l>
<l>And handsomer than those of old</l>
<l>Of whom Homer relates.</l>
<l>We unto you the song you hear</l>
<l>Will sing repeatedly</l>
<l>To celebrate your wedding-day :</l>
<l>It’s made for both you see !<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The translator’s version is perhaps better than the
original : it could not, be worse.</note></l>
</quote>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="42"><p>

That caused a laugh, as you can imagine; and
then it was time to take what was set before us.
Aristaenetus and Eucritus each took the portion in
front of him: I took what was mine and Chaereas
what was set before him, and Ion and Cleodemus
did likewise. But Diphilus wanted to carry off not
only his own but all that had been served for Zeno,
who was away; he said that it had been served
to him alone, and fought with the servants. They
caught hold of the bird and tried to pull it away
from each other as if they were tugging at the body
of Patroclus, and at last he was beaten and let go.
He made the company laugh heartily, especially
because he was indignant afterwards, just as if he
had been done the greatest possible wrong.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="43"><p>

Hermon and Zenothemis were lying side by side,
as I have said, Zenothemis above and Hermon below
him. The shares served them were identical in all
but one point, and they began to take them



<pb n="v.1.p.457"/>

peaceably. But the bird in front of Hermon was
the plumper, just by chance, no doubt. In that case
too each should have taken his own, but at this
juncture Zenothemis—follow me closely, Philo, for
we have now reached the crisis of events—Zenothemis, I say, let the bird beside him alone and proceeded to take the one before Hermon, which was
fatter, as I have said. Hermon, however, seized it
also and would not let him be greedy. Thereat
there was a shout: they fell on and actually hit
one another in the face with the birds, and each
caught the other by the beard and called for help,
Hermon to Cleodemus, and Zenothemis to Alcidamus
and Diphilus. The philosophers took sides, some
with one, and some with the other, except Ion alone.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="44"><p>

That man
kept himself neutral, and they pitched in
and fought. Zenothemis picked up a bowl that was
on the table in front of Aristaenetus and threw it at
Hermon,

<cit><quote><l>And him it missed and went another way; </l>
</quote>
<bibl>Cf. Iliad 11, 233</bibl></cit>

but it cracked the crown of the bridegroom,
inflicting a wound that was generous and deep. Consequently there was an outcry from the women, and
most of them sprang to the battle-field, especially
the lad’s mother when she saw the blood; and the
bride also sprang from her place in alarm over him.
Meanwhile Alcidamas distinguished himself on the
side of Zenothemis. Laying about him with his
staff, he broke the head of Cleodemus and the jaw of
Hermon, and he disabled several of the servants
who were trying to rescue them. But the -other



<pb n="v.1.p.459"/>

side did not give way, for Cleodemus with a stifl
finger gouged out the eye of Zenothemis and got him
by the nose and bit it off, while as for Hermon, when
Diphilus was coming to the support of Zenothemis
he threw him head first from the couch.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="45"><p>

Histiaeus
the grammarian was wounded, too, in trying to
separate them—he was kicked .in the teeth, I think,
by Cleodemus, who supposed him to be Diphilus.
At all events the poor fellow was laid low, “vomiting
gore,” as his own Homer says. The whole place,
however, was full of noise and tears, and the women,
gathered about Chaereas, were wailing, while the
rest of the men were trying to quiet things down.
Alcidamas wes the greatest nuisance in the world,
for when he had once routed his opponents he hit
everybody that fell in his way. Many would have
gone down before him, you may be sure, if he had
not broken his staff. As for me, I stood by the
wall and watched the whole performance without
taking part in it, for Histiaeus had taught me how -
tisky it is to try to part such fights. You would
have said they were Lapiths and Centaurs, to see
tables going over, blood flowing and cups flying.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="46"><p>


At last Alcidamas knocked over the lamp-stand
and brought on profound darkness, and as you can
imagine, the situation became far worse, for it was
not easy for them to provide more light, while on
the other hand many dire deeds were done in the
darkness. When some one finally came in with a


<pb n="v.1.p.461"/>

lamp, Alcidamas was caught stripping the flute-girl
and trying to ravish her, while Dionysodorus
was found to have done something else that was
ridiculous, for as he got up a bowl fell out of the
folds of his cloak. Then by way of clearing himself
he said that Ion had picked it up in the confusion
and had given it to him, so that it might not get
lost; and Ion considerately said that he had done
so.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="47"><p>

Thereupon the dinner-party broke up. After the
tears, it had ended in a new burst of laughter over
Alcidamas, Dionysodorus and Ion. The wounded
men were carried away in sorry condition, especially
the old man Zenothemis, who had one hand on his
nose and the other on his eye and was shouting that
he was dying with pain, so that Hermon, in spite of
his own sad plight (for he had had two teeth
knocked out) called attention to it and said: “Just
remember, Zenothemis, that you do consider pain of
some cunsequence, after all!” The bridegroom, after
his wound had been dressed by Dionicus, was taken
home with his head wrapped in bandages, in the
carriage in which he had expected to take away his
bride ; it was a bitter wedding that he celebratcd,
poor fellow! As for the rest, Dionicus did the best
he could for them and they were taken of to bed,
most of them vomiting in the streets. But Alcidamas
stayed right there, for they could not turn the man
out, once he had thrown himself down crosswise on
the couch and gone to sleep.


<pb n="v.1.p.463"/>
</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg015.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="48">
<p>
Well, Philo, that was the end of the dinner-party:
it would be better, though, to say at the close as
they do in the plays of Euripides:

<quote>
<l>In many shapes appear the powers above,</l>
<l>And many things the gods surprise us with,</l>
<l>While those we look for do not come about.<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">These lines occur at the close of the Alcestis, the
Andromache, the Barchae and the Helen, and, with a slight
change, in the Medea.</note></l>
</quote>
For all of it, you know, was quite unexpected. This
much, however, I have at last learned, that it is not
safe for a man of peace to dine with men so
learned.


</p>
</div></div>
</body></text></TEI>

