<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - 1 Timothy</title>
                
                <editor>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor>
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="verse"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and verse</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                
                <cRefPattern n="chapter"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            
            <refsDecl>
                <!--<refState delim=" " unit="book"/>-->
                <refState delim=":" unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <!--<refsDecl>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>-->
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-10-26" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion</change>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2010-06-29" who="student">fixing place tags AD</change>
            <change when="2009-10-08" who="rsingh04">began reorganizing texts module by collection.created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files</change>
            <change when="2009-05-27" who="rsingh04">added/fixed cvs log keyword</change>
            <change when="1999-10-14" who="Anne Mahoney">Initial markup from flat ASCII text</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0031.tlg015.perseus-eng2">
                <head>Paul's First Letter to Timothy</head>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                   
                        Paul, an apostle of Christ Jesus according to the commandment
of God our Savior, and Christ Jesus our hope;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        to Timothy, my true child in faith: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God our Father and Christ Jesus our Lord.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        As I exhorted you to stay at Ephesus when I was going into
Macedonia, that you might charge certain men not to teach a different
doctrine,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        neither to pay attention to myths and endless
genealogies, which cause disputes, rather than God's stewardship, which
is in faith --
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        but the end of the charge is love, out of a pure
heart and a good conscience and unfeigned faith;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        from which
things some, having missed the mark, have turned aside to vain talking;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        desiring to be teachers of the law, though they understand
neither what they say, nor about what they strongly affirm.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        But
we know that the law is good, if a man uses it lawfully,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        as
knowing this, that law is not made for a righteous man, but for the
lawless and insubordinate, for the ungodly and sinners, for the unholy
and profane, for murderers of fathers and murderers of mothers, for
manslayers,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        for the sexually immoral, for homosexuals, for
slave-traders, for liars, for perjurers, and for any other thing
contrary to the sound doctrine;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        according to the gospel of the
glory of the blessed God, which was committed to my trust.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        And I
thank him who enabled me, Christ Jesus our Lord, because he counted me
faithful, appointing me to service;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        although I was before a
blasphemer, a persecutor, and insolent. However, I obtained mercy,
because I did it ignorantly in unbelief.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        The grace of our Lord
abounded exceedingly with faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        The saying is faithful and worthy of all acceptance, that Christ
Jesus came into the world to save sinners; of whom I am chief.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        However, for this cause I obtained mercy, that in me first, Jesus
Christ might display all his patience, for an example of those who were
going to believe in him for eternal life.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        Now to the King
eternal, immortal, invisible, to God who alone is wise, be honor and
glory forever and ever. Amen.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        This charge I commit to you, my child Timothy, according to
the prophecies which led the way to you, that by them you may wage the
good warfare;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        holding faith and a good conscience; which some
having thrust away made a shipwreck concerning the faith;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        of
whom is Hymenaeus and Alexander; whom I delivered to Satan, that they
might be taught not to blaspheme.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
                  

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                  
                        I exhort therefore, first of all, that petitions, prayers,
intercessions, and givings of thanks, be made for all men:
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        for
kings and all who are in high places; that we may lead a tranquil and
quiet life in all godliness and reverence.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        For this is good and
acceptable in the sight of God our Savior;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        who desires all people
to be saved and come to full knowledge of the truth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        For there is
one God, and one mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jesus,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        who gave himself as a ransom for all; the testimony in its own
times;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        to which I was appointed a preacher and an apostle (I am
telling the truth in Christ, not lying), a teacher of the Gentiles in
faith and truth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        I desire therefore that the men in every place pray, lifting
up holy hands without wrath and doubting.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        In the same way, that
women also adorn themselves in decent clothing, with modesty and
propriety; not just with braided hair, gold, pearls, or expensive
clothing;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        but (which becomes women professing godliness) with
good works.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        Let a woman learn in quietness with all subjection.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        But I don't permit a woman to teach, nor to exercise authority
over a man, but to be in quietness.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        For Adam was first formed,
then Eve.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Adam wasn't deceived, but the woman, being deceived,
has fallen into disobedience;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        but she will be saved through her
child-bearing, if they continue in faith, love, and sanctification with
sobriety.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
                  
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        This is a faithful saying: if a man seeks the office of an
overseer, he desires a good work.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        The overseer therefore must be
without reproach, the husband of one wife, temperate, sensible, modest,
hospitable, good at teaching;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        not a drinker, not violent, not
greedy for money, but gentle, not quarrelsome, not covetous;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        one
who rules his own house well, having children in subjection with all
reverence;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        (but if a man doesn't know how to rule his own house,
how will he take care of the assembly of God?)
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        not a new convert,
lest being puffed up he fall into the same condemnation as the devil.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        Moreover he must have good testimony from those who are outside,
to avoid falling into reproach and the snare of the devil.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        Deacons, in the same way, must be reverent, not
double-tongued, not addicted to much wine, not greedy for money;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        holding the mystery of the faith in a pure conscience.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        Let them
also first be tested; then let them serve as deacons, if they are
blameless.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        Their wives in the same way must be reverent, not
slanderers, temperate, faithful in all things.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        Let deacons be
husbands of one wife, ruling their children and their own houses well.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        For those who have served well as deacons gain to themselves a
good standing, and great boldness in the faith which is in Christ Jesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        These things I write to you, hoping to come to you shortly;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        but if I wait long, that you may know how men ought to behave
themselves in the house of God, which is the assembly of the living
God, the pillar and ground of the truth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        Without controversy,
the mystery of godliness is great:
God was revealed in the flesh,
   Justified in the spirit,
   Seen by angels,
   Preached among the nations,
   Believed on in the world,
   And received up in glory.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
                    

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        But the Spirit says expressly that in later times some will
fall away from the faith, paying attention to seducing spirits and
doctrines of demons,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        through the hypocrisy of men who speak lies,
branded in their own conscience as with a hot iron;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        forbidding
marriage and commanding to abstain from foods which God created to be
received with thanksgiving by those who believe and know the truth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        For every creature of God is good, and nothing is to be rejected,
if it is received with thanksgiving.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        For it is sanctified through
the word of God and prayer.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        If you instruct the brothers of these
things, you will be a good servant of Christ Jesus, nourished in the
words of the faith, and of the good doctrine which you have followed.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        But refuse profane and old wives' fables. Exercise yourself
toward godliness.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        For bodily exercise has some value, but
godliness has value for all things, having the promise of the life
which is now, and of that which is to come.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        This saying is
faithful and worthy of all acceptance.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        For to this end we both
labor and suffer reproach, because we have set our trust in the living
God, who is the Savior of all men, especially of those who believe.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        Command and teach these things.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        Let no man despise your youth; but be an example to those who
believe, in word, in your way of life, in love, in spirit, in faith,
and in purity.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        Until I come, pay attention to reading, to
exhortation, and to teaching.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Don't neglect the gift that is in
you, which was given to you by prophecy, with the laying on of the
hands of the elders.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        Be diligent in these things. Give yourself
wholly to them, that your progress may be revealed to all.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        Pay
attention to yourself, and to your teaching. Continue in these things,
for in doing this you will save both yourself and those who hear you.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                  
                        Don't rebuke an older man, but exhort him as a father; the
younger men as brothers;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        the elder women as mothers; the younger
as sisters, in all purity.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        Honor widows who are widows indeed.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        But if any widow has children or grandchildren, let them learn
first to show piety towards their own family, and to repay their
parents, for this is acceptable in the sight of God.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Now she who
is a widow indeed, and desolate, has her hope set on God, and continues
in petitions and prayers night and day.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        But she who gives herself
to pleasure is dead while she lives.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        Also command these things,
that they may be without reproach.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        But if anyone doesn't provide
for his own, and especially his own household, he has denied the faith,
and is worse than an unbeliever.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        Let no one be enrolled as a
widow under sixty years old, having been the wife of one man,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        being approved by good works, if she has brought up children, if she
has been hospitable to strangers, if she has washed the saints' feet,
if she has relieved the afflicted, and if she has diligently followed
every good work.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        But refuse younger widows, for when they have grown wanton
against Christ, they desire to marry;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        having condemnation,
because they have rejected their first pledge.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        Besides, they
also learn to be idle, going about from house to house. Not only idle,
but also gossips and busybodies, saying things which they ought not.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        I desire therefore that the younger widows marry, bear children,
rule the household, and give no occasion to the adversary for reviling.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        For already some have turned aside after Satan.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        If any
man or woman who believes has widows, let them relieve them, and don't
let the assembly be burdened; that it might relieve those who are
widows indeed.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        Let the elders who rule well be counted worthy of double
honor, especially those who labor in the word and in teaching.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        For the Scripture says, "You shall not muzzle the ox when it treads out
the grain." And, "The laborer is worthy of his wages."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        Don't receive an accusation against an elder, except at the
word of two or three witnesses.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        Those who sin, reprove in the
sight of all, that the rest also may be in fear.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        I charge you in
the sight of God, and Christ Jesus, and the elect angels, that you
observe these things without prejudice, doing nothing by partiality.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        Lay hands hastily on no one, neither be a participant in other
men's sins. Keep yourself pure.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        Be no longer a drinker of water
only, but use a little wine for your stomach's sake and your frequent
infirmities.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        Some men's sins are evident, preceding them to judgment, and
some also follow later.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        In the same way also there are good
works that are obvious, and those that are otherwise can't be hidden.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
                 

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                   
                        Let as many as are bondservants under the yoke count their own
masters worthy of all honor, that the name of God and the doctrine not
be blasphemed.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Those who have believing masters, let them not
despise them, because they are brothers, but rather let them serve
them, because those who partake of the benefit are believing and
beloved. Teach and exhort these things.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        If anyone teaches a different doctrine, and doesn't consent to
sound words, the words of our Lord Jesus Christ, and to the doctrine
which is according to godliness,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        he is conceited, knowing
nothing, but obsessed with arguments, disputes, and word battles, from
which come envy, strife, reviling, evil suspicions,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        constant
friction of men of corrupt minds and destitute of the truth, who
suppose that godliness is a means of gain. Withdraw yourself from such.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        But godliness with contentment is great gain.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        For we
brought nothing into the world, and we certainly can't carry anything
out.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        But having food and clothing, we will be content with that.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        But those who are determined to be rich fall into a temptation
and a snare and many foolish and harmful lusts, such as drown men in
ruin and destruction.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        For the love of money is a root of all
kinds of evil. Some have been led astray from the faith in their greed,
and have pierced themselves through with many sorrows.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        But you, man of God, flee these things, and follow after
righteousness, godliness, faith, love, patience, and gentleness.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        Fight the good fight of faith. Lay hold of the eternal life to which
you were called, and you confessed the good confession in the sight of
many witnesses.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        I charge you before God, who gives life to all
things, and before Christ Jesus, who before Pontius Pilate testified
the good confession,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        that you keep the commandment without spot,
blameless, until the appearing of our Lord Jesus Christ;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        which
in its own times he will show, who is the blessed and only Ruler, the
King of kings, and Lord of lords;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        who alone has immortality,
dwelling in unapproachable light; whom no man has seen, nor can see: to
whom be honor and eternal power. Amen.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        Charge those who are rich in this present world that they not
be haughty, nor have their hope set on the uncertainty of riches, but
on the living God, who richly provides us with everything to enjoy;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        that they do good, that they be rich in good works, that they be
ready to distribute, willing to communicate;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        laying up in store
for themselves a good foundation against the time to come, that they
may lay hold of eternal life.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        Timothy, guard that which is committed to you, turning away
from the empty chatter and oppositions of the knowledge which is
falsely so called;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        which some professing have erred concerning
the faith. Grace be with you. Amen.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
