<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Aristogeiton 1 </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>Gentlemen of the jury, as I sat here for a long time and listened with you to the
                    speech of Lycurgus for the prosecution, I thought it in general an excellent
                    speech; but when I observed him unduly exerting himself, I was surprised that he
                    should not realize that the strength of our case does not really depend on the
                    arguments that he has used or that I am going to use, but on the disposition of
                    each juryman either to be indignant at wickedness or to condone it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>For myself, I admit it was our duty to undertake the prosecution and to deliver
                    full speeches in accordance with custom and for your information; but I feel
                    that the case has been already decided by each one of you in his inmost
                    conscience, and that now, if the majority of you are men disposed to admire and
                    protect rascals, all our declamation will be wasted, but if you are disposed to
                    hate them, then this man, please God! shall pay the penalty. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Though much has been said, and all of it well
                    said, I shall not scruple to put my own views before you, because the present
                    suit seems to me quite different from all others. Just consider. To all our
                    courts the juries come to learn from plaintiff and defendant the facts upon
                    which they are to give their votes, and each litigant comes to prove that the
                    legal right is strong on his side. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>But how stands it with the present trial? You who are to give the verdict have
                    come here knowing better than we, the accusers, that this man, since he is a
                    state-debtor and registered as such in the Acropolis, has no right to speak at
                    all; so that each of you is in the position of an accuser, knowing the facts and
                    not needing to be told them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>But the defendant is here with nothing whatever to support his acquittal, with no
                    sound plea based on the facts, with no past record of a decent life, with not a
                    single point in his favour. He imagines that he may be saved by what would have
                    frightened anyone else, though innocent; for he bases the hope of his acquittal
                    on the enormity of his wickedness.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This being so, it seems to me that one would not
                    be wrong in saying that, while Aristogeiton is on his trial, it is your
                    character that is being tested, your reputation that is at stake. For if you
                    make it quite clear that you are angry at such patent and gross offences and are
                    determined to punish them, then it will be seen that you have come here to play
                    your true part as judges and guardians of the law. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>But if some other motive prevails, some motive which none would care to confess,
                    but which your votes will betray, then I am afraid that to some you will appear
                    to be playing the part of trainers of any citizen who has a taste for
                    wickedness. For every bad man is in himself weak; he only becomes strong by your
                    countenance and support. Whoever wins that support finds in it his advantage and
                    his strength; to you who give that support, it is a source of shame. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>But before I speak of the private affairs of the defendant, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I should like you seriously but
                    briefly to calculate how much shame and discredit is brought upon our city by
                    these monsters, of whom the defendant is at once the midmost, the first, and the
                    last. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>To mention only one matter; they mount the platform in the Assembly, where you
                    look to your orators to explain their policy, not to flaunt their wickedness;
                    they come equipped with a hardened front, a raucous voice, false charges,
                    intimidation, shamelessness, and all such gifts as these, than which one could
                    name no qualities more hostile to the spirit of debate nor, I think—so Heaven
                    help me!—more discreditable. By these vile tricks they gain supremacy over all
                    that is respectable in the State, over the laws, the committees, the course of
                    public business, and the maintenance of order. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>Now if that is what you want, if their practice accords with your ideas, we must
                    just let them go their own way; but if you think that even at the eleventh hour
                    you ought to put all this right, and reform what has been allowed to go too far,
                    and has been disgracefully misdirected by these men, you must today avert your
                    eyes from all such practices and give a righteous verdict. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>You must magnify the Goddess of Order who loves what is right and preserves every
                    city and every land; and before you cast your votes, each juryman must reflect
                    that he is being watched by hallowed and inexorable Justice, who, as Orpheus,
                    that prophet of our most sacred mysteries, tells us, sits beside the throne of
                    Zeus and oversees all the works of men. Each must keep watch and ward lest he
                    shame that goddess, from whom everyone that is chosen by lot derives his name of
                    juror, because he has this day received a sacred trust from the laws, from the
                    constitution, from the fatherland,—the duty of guarding all that is fair and
                    right and beneficial in our city. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>For if you do not cherish that temper, if you come here and take seats with your
                    usual easy good nature, I am afraid that the case may be reversed, and that we
                    who seem to accuse Aristogeiton may be found to be accusing you; for the more
                    convincingly we prove his guilt without arousing your interest, the greater will
                    be your shame. But enough of that subject! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I shall certainly tell
                    you the truth with the utmost frankness. When I saw you in the Assembly
                    indicating and proposing me as the accuser of Aristogeiton, I was troubled, and
                    I call Heaven to witness that I did not relish the task. For I was not unaware
                    that he who plays such a part in your courts suffers for it in the end, not
                    perhaps so as to feel it at once, but if he undertakes many such tasks and
                    perseveres in them, his character will soon be recognized. I thought it,
                    however, my duty to accede to your wishes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Now as regards the laying of the injunction and the legal points, I considered
                    that Lycurgus would deal adequately with them; and I also saw that he was
                    producing witnesses to the wickedness of the defendant. But I resolved to devote
                    my speech to those points which ought always to be considered and examined by
                    those who are deliberating in the interests of the State and of the laws; and I
                    will now proceed to deal with those points. But do you, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, in Heaven's name grant me the
                    privilege of addressing you on these topics in the way that suits my natural
                    bent and the scheme of my speech, for indeed I could not speak in any other way.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The whole life of men, Athenians, whether they
                    dwell in a large state or a small one, is governed by nature and by the laws. Of
                    these, nature is something irregular and incalculable, and peculiar to each
                    individual; but the laws are something universal, definite, and the same for
                    all. Now nature, if it be evil, often chooses wrong, and that is why you will
                    find men of an evil nature committing errors. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>But the laws desire what is just and honorable and salutary; they seek for it,
                    and when they find it, they set it forth as a general commandment, equal and
                    identical for all. The law is that which all men ought to obey for many reasons,
                    but above all because every law is an invention and gift of the gods, a tenet of
                    wise men, a corrective of errors voluntary and involuntary, and a general
                    covenant of the whole State, in accordance with which all men in that State
                    ought to regulate their lives. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>But that Aristogeiton has been convicted on all the heads of the information, and
                    that he has not a single counter-argument worth considering, can be easily
                    proved. For there are two objects, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, for which all laws are framed—to deter any man from
                    doing what is wrong, and, by punishing the transgressor, to make the rest better
                    men; and it will be shown that both these objects will be secured by the
                    punishment of the defendant. For by his original transgressions he has incurred
                    the due penalties, and for his refusal to acquiesce in them he is now brought
                    into court to receive your punishment; so that no one has any excuse left for
                    acquitting him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>Nor is it possible to say, “After all, these things do no harm to the State.” I
                    will not dwell on the fact that all the fines due to the State are lost, if you
                    admit his sophistries, or that if we must forgive any of our debtors, it ought
                    to be the most decent and respectable and those who have been fined on the least
                    serious charges, not the greatest villain of all, who has committed most
                    offences and incurred the most deserved fines on the most serious charges. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>For what could be more serious than chicanery and breach of the constitution, for
                    both of which the defendant has been condemned? Nor will I urge that even if you
                    let off all other offenders, it is surely wrong to give way to one who resorts
                    to force, for that is surely an outrage. I waive such considerations as these;
                    but I do think that I can clearly prove to you that the defendant's example
                    confounds and destroys all order in law and in government. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I shall say nothing novel or extravagant or
                    peculiar, but only what you all know to be true as well as I do. For if any of
                    you cares to inquire what is the motive-power that calls together the Council,
                    draws the people into the Assembly, fills the law-courts, makes the old
                    officials resign readily to the new, and enables the whole life of the State to
                    be carried on and preserved, he will find that it is the laws and the obedience
                    that all men yield to the laws; since, if once they were done away with and
                    every man were given licence to do as he liked, not only does the constitution
                    vanish, but our life would not differ from that of the beasts of the field. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>You see what the defendant is, when the laws are in force: what do you think he
                    would do, if the laws were done away with? Since then it is admitted that, next
                    after the gods, the laws preserve the State, it is the duty of all of you to act
                    just as if you were sitting here making up a contribution to your club.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="grc">plhrwtai/</foreign>
                        seems to mean either those who pay the contribution or those who see that it
                        is paid.</note> If a man obeys the laws, respect and commend him for paying
                    his contribution in full to the welfare of his fatherland; if he disobeys them,
                    punish him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>For everything done at the bidding of the laws is a contribution made to the
                    State and the community. Whoever leaves it unpaid, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is depriving you of many great,
                    honorable, and glorious benefits, which he is destroying to the best of his
                    ability. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>One or two of these benefits I will name for the sake of example, choosing the
                    best known.The Council of the Five Hundred, thanks to this barrier,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The wooden lattice-work doorway, giving
                        admission through the bar to the council-chamber or law-court. The
                        corresponding Lat. term is cancelii.</note> frail as it is, is master of its
                    own secrets, and no private citizen can enter it. The Council of the Areopagus,
                    when it sits roped off in the King's Portico, enjoys complete freedom from
                    disturbance, and all men hold aloof. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>All the magistrates who are chosen from you by lot, as soon as the attendant
                    cries “Strangers must withdraw,” control the laws which they were appointed to
                    administer and cannot be disturbed by the most unruly. There are thousands of
                    other benefits. All the noble and reverend qualities that adorn and preserve our
                    city,—sobriety, orderliness, the respect of your younger men for parents and
                    elders—hold their own, backed by the laws, against the base qualities of
                    indecency, audacity, and shamelessness. For vice is vigorous, daring, and
                    grasping; on the other hand probity is peaceful, retiring, inactive, and
                    terribly liable to come off second-best. Therefore those of you who sit upon
                    juries ought to protect and strengthen the laws, for with the help of the laws
                    the good overcome the bad. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>If not, all is dissolved, broken up, confounded, and the city becomes the prey of
                    the most profligate and shameless. For tell me this, in Heaven's name; if
                    everyone in the city copied the audacity and shamelessness of Aristogeiton and
                    argued in the same way as he, that in a democracy a man has an unlimited right
                    to say and do whatever he likes, as long as he does not care what reputation
                    such conduct will bring him, and that no one will put him to death at once for
                    any of his misdoings; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>if, acting on this principle, the citizen rejected at the ballot or at the
                    election should put himself on an equality with the chosen citizen; if, in a
                    word, neither young nor old should do his duty, but each man, banishing all
                    discipline from life, should regard his own wish as law, as authority, as all in
                    all—if, I say, we should act like this, could the government continue to be
                    carried on? What? Would the laws be any longer valid? What violence, insolence
                    and lawlessness there would be throughout the city every day! What scurrility
                    instead of our present decency of language and behavior! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>Why need one repeat that order is everywhere maintained by the laws and by
                    obedience to the laws? You yourselves have the sole right of judging our case,
                    though every Athenian was in the ballot and all, I am sure, wanted to be
                    allotted to this court. Why is this? Because by lot you were chosen and then
                    assigned to this case. Those are the instructions of the law. And then will you,
                    who owe your presence here to the laws, allow a man, who flouts the laws by word
                    and deed, to escape from your grasp? Will none of you show anger or bitterness
                    at this shameless ruffian's defiance of the laws? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>Vilest of all living men! Shut out from your right of speech, not by barriers or
                    doors which any man might break open, but by so many heavy penalties, which are
                    registered in the temple of the Goddess, you are trying to force your way in and
                    to approach those precincts from which the laws exclude you. Debarred by every
                    right that holds good in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, by
                    the decisions of three tribunals, by the registers of the archons and of the
                    collectors of taxes, by the indictment for wrongful entry in which you yourself
                    are the plaintiff, curbed, I might almost say, by chains of steel, you wriggle
                    and force your way through all and imagine that by weaving excuses and trumping
                    up false charges you can overturn all the principles of justice. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>I will, however, by a clear and forcible example show the jury that they ought
                    not to overlook such conduct; no, not in a single particular. Imagine for a
                    moment that someone proposed that speakers in the Assembly should be confined to
                    the youngest citizens, or to the richest, or to those who had performed a public
                    service, or to some similar category. I am sure you would have him put to death
                    for trying to overthrow the democracy. And indeed you would be justified. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>Yet any one of these proposals is less dangerous than if it were proposed that
                    speakers should belong to one of the classes to which the defendant
                    belongs—law-breakers, jail-birds, sons of criminals put to death by the people,
                    citizens disqualified after obtaining office by lot, public debtors, men totally
                    disfranchised, or men who by repute and in fact are utter rascals. All these
                    descriptions fit the defendant and apply to those who resemble him in
                    disposition. I think, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    that he deserves death both for what he is doing now and much more, or at least
                    no less, for what he obviously will do, if he gets the power and opportunity
                    from you; which Heaven forfend! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>It is also strange if anyone of you is ignorant that for nothing that is
                    honorable or useful or worthy of our city is he of any use. May Zeus and all the
                    gods grant that <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> may never be
                    so short of real men that any honorable task should have to be performed by an
                    Aristogeiton! We ought to pray Heaven that the occasion may never arise for
                    which such a monster could be found useful. But should it possibly arise, it
                    would be a greater blessing for the city that those who wish for its fall should
                    lack the instrument of their designs than that this fellow should be released
                    and ready to their hand. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>For what fatal or dangerous act will he shrink from, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,—this polluted wretch, infected with
                    hereditary hatred of democracy? What other man would sooner overthrow the State,
                    if only—which Heaven forbid!—he should gain the power? Do you not see that his
                    character and his policy are not guided by reason or by self-respect, but by
                        recklessness?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">We have no exact equivalent
                        for this Greek word; “moral insanity” has been suggested. Read the
                            <bibl>16th <title>Character</title>of Theophrastus</bibl> with Jebb's
                        commentary.</note> Or rather, his policy is sheer recklessness. Now that is
                    the very worst quality for its possessor, terribly dangerous for everyone else,
                    and for the State intolerable. For the reckless man has lost all control of
                    himself, all hope of rational safety, and can only be saved, if at all, by some
                    unexpected and incalculable accident. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>Who, then, that is wise would bind up his own or his country's interests with
                    this failing? Who would not shun it as far as possible, and keep its possessor
                    at arm's length, that he may not be involved in it even against his will?
                    Patriotic statesmen, Athenians, ought to seek out some adviser who will
                    contribute, not recklessness, but intelligence, sound judgement, and ample
                    forethought; for these qualities conduct all men to happiness; the other leads
                    to that goal for which Aristogeiton is bound. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>In considering this question, look not at my speech, but at the general character
                    of mankind. All our cities contain shrines and temples of all the gods, and
                    among them is one of Athena, Our Lady of Forethought,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The goddess with a temple at the entrance to the precincts
                        of Apollo at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> was <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">*)aqh/nh *pronai/a</foreign>, whom the
                                <persName><surname>Pytho</surname></persName> addresses at the
                        beginning of the <title>Eumenides</title> (<bibl n="Aesch. Eum. 21">Aesch.
                            Eum. 21</bibl> and to whom Croesus offered a golden shield (<bibl
                            n="Hdt. 1.92">Hdt. 1.92</bibl>). Perhaps by popular etymology she became
                        the goddess of Providence, which title she is named also in Aeschines (<bibl
                            n="Aeschin. 3.108">Aeschin. 3.108</bibl>). Pausanias mentions both
                        titles (<bibl n="Paus. 9.10.2">Paus. 9.10.2</bibl> and <bibl
                            n="Paus. 10.8.6">Paus. 10.8.6</bibl>).</note> worshipped as a beneficent
                    and powerful goddess, and close to the temple of Apollo at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, immediately as you enter the
                    precincts, she has a large and beautiful temple. Apollo, a god and prophet both,
                    knows what is best. But there is no temple of Recklessness or of Shamelessness.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>Of Justice too and Order and Modesty all men have shrines, some, the fairest and
                    holiest, in the very heart and soul of each man, and others built for the common
                    worship of all. But none is raised to Shamelessness or Chicanery or Perjury or
                    Ingratitude—all qualities of the defendant. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>Now I know that he will avoid the straight and honest path of defence, and will
                    take a devious course, abusing, slandering, and threatening to prosecute,
                    arrest, imprison, and the like. But he will find all this futile, if you duly
                    attend to the case; for which of these tricks has not been exposed over and over
                    again? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>To pass over other occasions, seven times, Aristogeiton, have you indicted me,
                    when you had taken the pay of Philip's agents, and twice you accused me at my
                    audit. As a mere mortal I pay my respects to Nemesis, and I am deeply grateful
                    both to the gods and to all the citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> for their protection. But as for you, it was never once
                    found that you had spoken the truth; you were always convicted of chicanery. If,
                    then, these gentlemen make the laws invalid by acquitting you today, will you
                    convict me now? On what charge? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>I ask the jury to reflect. For two years he has been asserting his claim to
                    address you, though it is illegal for him to do so; but he speaks all the same.
                    All that time he saw the State injured by the wretched Phocides, by the
                    coppersmith from Peiraeus, by the tanner, and by all the others whom he has
                    accused in your courts; but had he no eyes for me, the orator with whom he was
                    at open war, or for Lycurgus, or for the other orators about whom he will have
                    so much to say presently? Yet either way he deserves death; in the one case, if
                    he had a charge against us that he could prove, but passed it over to assail
                    private citizens, or on the other hand, if he has no charge against us, but
                    wants to deceive and hoodwink you by his statements. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>If there really is in our city a man whose disposition prompts him diligently to
                    search for someone ready to accuse and blackmail others, but who does not
                    trouble himself about the justice or injustice of the charges, he could not find
                    an agent less fitted for his purpose than the defendant. And why? Because one
                    who is prepared to accuse others and bring them all to trial, ought to be
                    himself unimpeachable, so that his victims may not escape through his own
                    wickedness. But no one in the city has a record of more numerous and more
                    serious crimes than the defendant. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>Now what is the defendant? “He is the watch dog of the democracy,” cry his
                    friends. Yes, but what sort of dog? One that never snaps at those whom he
                    accuses of being wolves, but himself devours the sheep he pretends to guard. To
                    which of the orators has he done so much harm as to the private citizens against
                    whom he has been convicted of moving unlawful decrees? What statesman has he
                    brought to trial, since he again took to public speaking? Not a single one-but
                    plenty of private citizens. But they say that dogs who taste mutton ought to be
                    cut to bits; so the sooner he is cut up the better. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, he serves no purpose
                    that he claims to serve, but he has turned his attention to an abominable and
                    disgusting trick. In the Assembly he recklessly abuses and attacks all alike,
                    and for all the misrepresentations that he thus foists upon you collectively, he
                    gets his remuneration from each of you separately, when he descends from the
                    platform, by threatening prosecution and by demanding and extorting money.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Editors confess themselves unable to understand
                        the drift of this sentence.</note> Not from the orators, you may be sure:
                    they know how to throw mud back at him: but from the inexperienced private
                    citizens, as those know who have felt his blows. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But perhaps, while admitting the truth of this,
                    you will say that you consider him a useful servant of the State, so that we
                    must overlook all this and spare him. Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, when you have had practical experience of something,
                    you should never take a merely theoretical view of it. This man had no dealings
                    with you in the five years when he was deprived of the right to address you.
                    Well, who in all that time regretted him? What neglect of the city's interests
                    has anyone observed in consequence of his absence, or what improvement now that
                    he is allowed to speak? On the contrary, it seems to me that as long as he did
                    not come before you, the city had respite from the troubles that he caused to
                    everyone, but since he started his harangues again, <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> is in a state of siege from the
                    factious and unruly speeches that he delivers at every meeting of the Assembly.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>I will now trench upon a dangerous topic and offer some remarks to those who, for
                    these reasons, admire him. How such persons ought to be regarded, you shall
                    judge for yourselves; I will say nothing myself, except that they are not wise
                    in taking his part. Now of you who are here in court, I assume that this does
                    not apply to any: it is only fair, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, and honorable and proper that I should both say and
                    think that of you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>But of the rest of our citizens—to confine the reproach to as few as possible—his
                    pupil, or, if you like, his teacher, Philocrates of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>, is the only one whom I account as
                    such, not as if there were not more (for I would that no one else found
                    satisfaction in Aristogeiton), but I have no right publicly to bring a charge
                    against other citizens which I shrink from bringing against you. Moreover the
                    argument, though it applies to one man alone, will have the same force. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>I will not discuss too minutely what character we must assign to an admirer of
                    Aristogeiton, for fear lest I should be committed to a long tirade of
                    vituperation. But one thing I will say. If Aristogeiton is in plain language a
                    rascally and malicious blackmailer, the sort of man in fact that he professes to
                    be, then you have my hearty consent, Philocrates, to support one who so closely
                    resembles you; because, if every one else does his duty and upholds the law, I
                    do not think that your attitude will produce any effect. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>But if he is a jobber and pedlar and retail-dealer in wickedness, if he has all
                    but sold by scale and balance every action of his whole life, why, you silly
                    fellow, do you egg him on? Surely a cook has no use for a knife that does not
                    cut, and in the same way a man who wants by his own efforts to cause trouble and
                    annoyance to everybody has no use for a blackmailer who is ready to sell such
                    services. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>That, I may tell you, is the sort of man the defendant is, though you now it
                    already. You remember how he sold the impeachment of Hegemon. You know how he
                    threw up his brief against Demades. At the trial of Agathon, the olive-merchant,
                    a day or two ago, he bellowed and ranted and cried “Ha-ha!” and threw the
                    Assembly into confusion, saying it was a case for the rack; and after pocketing
                    some trifle or other, though he was present at his acquittal, he kept his mouth
                    shut. He held the threat of impeachment over Democles' head, and what did he
                    make of it? There are thousands of other cases. I should find it a task to
                    mention them all, but you, who were his jackal, must have notes of them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>Then what man, be he good or bad, wants to spare such a fellow? Why spare one who
                    is the betrayer of those who resemble him, and the foe, by instinct and by
                    inheritance, of good men; unless one thinks that the State should preserve, as a
                    farmer might do, the seed and stock of the blackmailer and rascal? But that
                    would be a disgrace, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>;
                    yes, by Heaven! and I account it an impiety too. I cannot believe that your
                    ancestors built you these law-courts as a hotbed for rogues of this sort, but
                    rather to enable you to check and chastise them, until no man shall admire or
                    covet vice. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Depravity may prove a difficult thing to check.
                    When Aristogeiton, for acknowledged misdeeds, is only now on his trial and has
                    not been put to death long ago, what is one to do or say? His wickedness has
                    reached such a pitch that after information had been laid against him, he did
                    not cease to bluster and blackmail and threaten; and because the generals, to
                    whom you have entrusted the most important interests, refused to give him money,
                    he said that they did not deserve to be appointed inspectors of latrines. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>This affront did not touch the generals—no, for they could have silenced his
                    abuse by paying him a trifling sum, but it was a gross insult to your action as
                    electors and a proof of his own depravity. The officials chosen by lot he
                    worried with his demands, extorting money from them and sparing them no insult.
                    And now his latest exploit is to stir up confusion and dissension among us all
                    by publishing false letters, for he was born to be the bane of all men, and his
                    character is clearly shown by his life. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Just consider. There are something like twenty
                    thousand citizens in all. Every single one of them frequents the market-place on
                    some business (you may be sure), either public or private. Not so the defendant.
                    He cannot point to any decent or honorable business in which he has spent his
                    life; he does not use his talents in the service of the State; he is not engaged
                    in a profession or in agriculture or in any other business; he takes no part in
                    any charitable or social organization: </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>but he makes his way through the market-place like a snake or a scorpion with
                    sting erect, darting hither and thither, on the look-out for someone on whom he
                    can call down disaster or calumny or mischief of some sort, or whom he can
                    terrify till he extorts money from him. He never calls at the barber's or the
                    perfumer's or any other shop in the city. He is implacable, restless,
                    unsociable; he has no charity, no friendliness, none of the feelings of a decent
                    human being; he is attended by those companions whom painters couple with the
                    damned souls in hell—by Malediction, Evil-speaking, Envy, Faction, Dissension.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>This man, then, who is likely to find no mercy from the powers below, but to be
                    thrust out among the impious for the depravity of his life—this man, when you
                    have caught him doing wrong, will you not only decline to punish, but actually
                    dismiss him with greater rewards than you would bestow on your benefactors? For
                    what defaulter to the treasury have you ever allowed to enjoy full rights,
                    unless he paid his debt? Not one! Then do not grant this favour to the defendant
                    now, but punish him and make him a warning to the others. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>The sequel too, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is
                    worth hearing. What you have just heard from Lycurgus is serious, or, rather,
                    impossible to exaggerate, but the rest will be found to rival it and to be of
                    the same character. Not content with abandoning his father in prison when he
                    quitted <placeName key="perseus,Eretria">Eretria</placeName>, as you have heard
                    from Phaedrus, this unnatural ruffian refused to bury him when he died, and
                    would not refund the expenses to those who did bury him, but actually brought a
                    law-suit against them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>Not content with offering violence to his mother, as you have just heard from
                    witnesses, he actually sold his own sister—not indeed a sister by the same
                    father, but his mother's daughter, whatever her parentage (for I pass that
                    by)—yes, sold his sister for export, as is stated in the indictment of the
                    action which was brought against him on these grounds by his good brother here,
                    who in the present action will help to defend him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>All this is bad enough, Heaven knows; but you
                    shall hear another dreadful performance. On the occasion when he broke prison
                    and ran away, he visited a certain woman named
                            <persName><surname>Zobia</surname></persName>, with whom he had probably
                    cohabited at one time. She kept him in safe hiding during the first few days,
                    when the police were searching and advertising for him, and then she gave him
                    eight drachmas journey-money and a tunic and a cloak and packed him off to
                        <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>When this same woman, who had been such a benefactress, complained to him, seeing
                    that he was giving himself airs and making a great show here among you, and when
                    she reminded him of her services and claimed some recompense, on the first
                    occasion he cuffed her and threatened her and turned her out of his house. But
                    when she persisted and, woman-like, went about among her acquaintance with
                    complaints of his conduct, he seized her with his own hands and dragged her off
                    to the auction-room at the aliens' registry, and if her tax had not happened to
                    be duly paid, she would have been put up for sale, thanks to this man who owed
                    his safety to her. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>To prove the truth of this statement, please call the man who buried the
                    defendant's father without payment, and also the arbitrator in the action which
                    the witness here in court brought against him for the sale of his sister, and
                    produce the indictment. But first of all please summon the protector of Zobia,
                    who gave him shelter, and the sale-commissioners before whom he carried her. You
                    yourselves just now expressed your indignation at his accusing the man who had
                    contributed towards his defence. Athenians, he is an unclean beast; his touch is
                    pollution. Read the depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>What penalty is adequate for a man who has committed such offences? What
                    retribution does he deserve? To my thinking death is too light a sentence. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>One more instance, then, of his private crimes, and I will pass over the rest.
                    Before Aristogeiton was released, a man of <placeName key="perseus,Tanagra"
                        >Tanagra</placeName> was thrown into the prison until he could find bail.
                    Aristogeiton accosts him and, while chatting on some topic or other, filches the
                    pocket-book that he had on him; and when the man charged him with the theft and
                    made a to-do about it, saying that no one else could have taken it, he so far
                    forgot all decency that he tried to strike him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
                <p>But the Tanagran, a fresh-caught fish, was getting the better of the defendant,
                    who was thoroughly pickled, having been long in jail. So when it came to this,
                    he swallows the other man's nose. Then the unfortunate victim of this outrage
                    abandoned the search for his pocket-book, which was afterwards found in a chest
                    of which the defendant possessed the key. After that the inmates of the prison
                    passed a resolution not to share fire or light, food or drink with him, not to
                    receive anything from him, not to give him anything. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
                <p>To prove the truth of my statements, please call the man whose nose this monster
                    bit off and swallowed.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>What a fine performance for your popular orator! What a privilege to
                    hear words of wisdom from a man with such a record as this! Now read also the
                    precious resolution that was passed about him.<quote type="Resolution">
                        <title>Resolution</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
                <p>Are you not ashamed then, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, if the men who had been thrown into prison for villainy
                    and vice thought him so much more villainous than them selves that they forbade
                    all intercourse with him, while you are ready to admit him to intercourse with
                    yourselves, though the laws have placed him outside the pale of the
                    constitution? What did you find to commend in his life or conduct? Which of all
                    his actions has failed to move your indignation? Is he not impious,
                    blood-thirsty, unclean, and a black mailer? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="section">
                <p>And yet, in spite of his performances and his character, he misses no opportunity
                    in the Assembly of bellowing, “I, only I, am your sincere well-wisher. All these
                    others are in a cabal. You are betrayed. My patriotism is all you have left.” I
                    should like to examine the source and origin of this great and wonderful
                    patriotism of his, so that, if it is as he says, you may trust it and benefit by
                    it; but if not, that you may be on your guard. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
                <p>Because you condemned his father to death and sold his mother when she was found
                    guilty of defrauding her emancipator, do you suppose that that makes him
                    well-disposed to you? By Zeus and all the gods, that is absurd. For if he is
                    well-disposed towards father and mother, and so observes the great law of
                    nature, which is laid down alike for man and beast, that all should love their
                    parents, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="section">
                <p>then he must clearly be ill-disposed to those who have destroyed them and to
                    their laws and their constitution. But if he has no regard for these things, I
                    should like to know who that sees how he has renounced all affection for his
                    parents, can believe in his pretended zeal for the people; for the man who
                    neglects his parents I regard as unworthy of trust and hateful alike to gods and
                    men. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="section">
                <p>But I shall be told it is because you condemned him on information laid and twice
                    put him and his brother into prison; it is for this reason that he is your
                    well-wisher. But that too is ridiculous. Or because you disqualified him for the
                    office to which he had been allotted? Or because you found him guilty of a
                    breach of the constitution? Or because you fined him ten talents? Or because you
                    habitually point the finger of scorn at him as the vilest of all men in the
                    world? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="section">
                <p>Or because, as long as the present laws and constitution stand, he cannot clear
                    himself of these reproaches? Then why is he well-disposed to you? It is because,
                    in his own words, he is impudent. Why is the impudent man so called save
                    because, being lost to a sense of shame, he dares to state what is not, and
                    never will be, true? And that is precisely what the defendant does. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="section">
                <p>Now there are some facts about the information laid against him which Lycurgus
                    seems to have passed over, but which I had better lay before you; for I think
                    you should examine the defendant and the rights of the present case as carefully
                    as you would scrutinize a private debt. Suppose then that A accused B of owing
                    him money, and B denied it. If the registered terms of the loan were still to be
                    read, or if the pillars which marked the mortgaged property were still standing,
                    you would clearly regard as impudent the man who denied the transaction; but if
                    it was shown that these proofs no longer existed, then you would regard the
                    accuser as impudent. That is natural. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="section">
                <p>Well, of Aristogeiton's debt to the State the terms still exist, namely the laws
                    under which all defaulters are registered; and the pillar is the wooden table of
                    the law deposited in the temple of the Goddess. Now if these have been destroyed
                    and the debt wiped out, we are talking nonsense, or rather telling lies; but if
                    they are still in existence and will remain valid until he pays his debt, then
                    there is no truth in his plea, but he is committing a serious crime in trying to
                    suppress the rights of the State. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="section">
                <p>For the point to be argued and decided is not whether all his debts are unpaid,
                    but whether he is still in debt. Otherwise it would be hard on those who are
                    registered for a debt of one drachma, if their indebtedness is to tell against
                    them, because they have done some trifling wrong or even no wrong at all,
                    whereas if a man has committed serious wrongs, he is to regain his civic rights
                    by paying one or two instalments. Moreover, there are three distinct debts
                    registered and forming the ground of the information. Two Aristogeiton has
                    entered in the register;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The defendant admitted
                        these two debts by mortgaging his land for them.</note> the third he has not
                    registered, but he is prosecuting Aristo of Alopece for malicious entry. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="section">
                <p>“Yes,” says he, “for he has registered my name as a debtor unjustly.” Of course
                    it is evident that you have a right to satisfaction for this; but then you ought
                    first to give satisfaction and abide by the penalty you have brought on
                    yourself. Or again, for what do you expect to obtain satisfaction? If you are at
                    liberty to do everything that other citizens do, how are you wronged? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="section">
                <p>I beg the jury in Heaven's name to consider this point also. If he convicts
                    Aristo of malicious intent, what will it mean? His name, of course, will be
                    erased and Aristo's substituted, because that is the law. Good! Then
                    henceforward will this man, whose name has been erased, be a State-debtor, and
                    will the other man, registered as a debtor, retain his full citizenship? That is
                    what follows from the defendant's claim, for if he is not a debtor when his name
                    has been registered, then, when his name has been erased, he will obviously be a
                    debtor. But that is absolutely untrue. No; when his name is erased, then he will
                    be no longer a debtor. In that case the defendant is a debtor now.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">To the reader who fails to follow the argument
                        of this paragraph it may perhaps occur that the jury were not intended to
                        follow it either.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="section">
                <p>Again; if Aristo is acquitted, to whom is the State to look for compensation for
                    the defendant's illegal acts? And what about the men whose execution and
                    imprisonment he tries to procure, as he bustles to and fro in the court? How
                    will they recover their lives or escape from the sufferings they have already
                    endured? For this man, to whom the laws refuse a share in our common everyday
                    privileges, is the cause of intolerable wrongs to others by methods that are
                    neither correct nor constitutional nor convenient. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="section">
                <p>When I see all this, I wonder what meaning you attach to the phrase “upside
                    down.” Is it for the earth to be up there and the stars down here? That is
                    impossible, and let us hope it always will be. But when those who have no rights
                    enjoy rights at your pleasure, when villainy is honored and virtue spurned, when
                    justice and expediency are sacrificed to personal spite, then we must suppose
                    that the universe has indeed been turned upside down. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="section">
                <p>I have before now seen men on their trial, who were being convicted by the actual
                    facts and were unable to prove their innocence, taking refuge some of them in
                    the respectability and moderation of their lives, others in the achievements or
                    public services of their ancestors, or in similar pleas, by which they succeeded
                    in moving their judges to compassion and goodwill. But I cannot see that any one
                    of these topics offers an easy path for the defendant; there is nothing before
                    him but precipices, ravines, and gulfs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="section">
                <p>What true plea can he find? Something perhaps that his father did? But you
                    yourselves condemned that father to death in these very courts as a detected
                    rascal who deserved his doom. Or perhaps, if there is a difficulty about his
                    father, he will appeal to the sobriety and respectability of his own life. What
                    life? Where has he lived it? For the life that you have all seen him leading is
                    not of that description. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="section">
                <p>“But, my dear sir, he will rely on public services.” When and where performed?
                    His father's? Why, there are none. His own? You will find record of delations,
                    arrests, informations—but no services. Or perhaps, putting these aside, his
                    numerous and highly respectable kinsmen will come forward and beg him off. But
                    there are none and never were. How could there be, when he is not even a
                    free-born citizen? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="section">
                <p>No; I am wrong. He has a brother, who is present here in court and who brought
                    that precious action against him. What need to say anything about him? He is own
                    brother to the defendant, born of the same father and mother, and, to add to his
                    misfortunes, he is his twin. It was this brother—I pass over the other facts—who
                    got possession of the drugs and charms from the servant of Theoris of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>, the filthy sorceress whom you put to
                    death on that account with all her family. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="section">
                <p>She gave information against her mistress, and this rascal has had children by
                    her, and with her help he plays juggling tricks and professes to cure fits,
                    being himself subject to fits of wickedness of every kind. So this is the man
                    who will beg him off! This poisoner, this public pest, whom any man would ban at
                    sight as an evil omen rather than choose to accost him, and who has pronounced
                    himself worthy of death by bringing such an action. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What help, then, remains for him, Athenians? The
                    help, I suppose, that comes to all defendants alike from the natural temper of
                    the jury, the help that no man on his trial provides for himself, but that each
                    of you brings with him from home to the court—I mean pity, pardon, benevolence.
                    But of such help religion and justice alike demand that this unclean wretch
                    should receive no share. Why? Because whatever law each man's nature prompts him
                    to apply to his neighbors, that law it is only fair that they should apply to
                    him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="section">
                <p>What law do you think Aristogeiton applies to all other men, and what are his
                    wishes concerning them? Does he wish to see them enjoying prosperity, happiness
                    and good fame? If so, what becomes of his livelihood? For he thrives on the
                    misfortunes of others. Therefore he likes to see everyone involved in trials,
                    lawsuits and vile charges. That is the crop he sows; that is the trade he plies.
                    Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, what sort of man
                    deserves to be called the complete villain, the thrice-accursed, the common foe,
                    the universal enemy, against whom one prays that the earth may neither yield him
                    fruit nor receive him after death? Is it not such a man as this? That is my
                    opinion. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="section">
                <p>What pardon, what pity did the victims of his blackmail obtain from him, the men
                    whose execution he was always demanding in your courts—yes, even before the
                    first verdict was decided?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The jury voted first
                        on the question of guilty or not guilty, and secondly on the penalty, if
                        guilty.</note> Those against whom this wretch showed such cruelty and
                    bitterness were saved from death by the righteous conduct of those of you who
                    had been allotted to try their case, who acquitted the men he was falsely
                    accusing and withheld from him the necessary fifth part of the votes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="section">
                <p>But his bitterness, cruelty and blood-thirstiness were displayed and proved. The
                    sight of the children of some of the defendants and their aged mothers standing
                    in court did not move him to pity? And do you, Aristogeiton, look for pardon?
                    Whence? From whom? Are your children to be pitied? Far from it. You have
                    yourself thrown away their right to pity; nay, you have destroyed it once for
                    all. Do not then seek anchorage in harbors that you have yourself blocked up and
                    filled with stakes; for that is unfair. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>If you heard the slanderous language that he used
                    against you, as he paraded the market-place, you would hate him even more than
                    you do, and with justice. For he says there are many men in debt to the
                    treasury, and all of them in the same case as himself. I admit that these
                    unfortunate men are “many,” though there are but a couple of them; for every
                    state-debtor is one too many,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Lit. “They are
                        more by everyone than is right.”</note> and no others ought to be in debt to
                    the State. But I solemnly swear that their case is not the same as the
                    defendant's, nor anything like it, but quite the contrary. Look at it in this
                    way. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="section">
                <p>And do not imagine, Athenians, that I am debating the point with you, as if you
                    were debtors to the treasury. That is not so, and I hope it never may be; it is
                    no idea of mine. But if any of you has a friend or acquaintance among the
                    debtors, I propose to show you that for that friend's sake he ought to hate the
                        defendant.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>My first reason is that honest
                    folk, who are hampered by security for others and kind offices and private debts
                    involving no wrong to the State, but who happen to have been unlucky, are placed
                    by him in the same infamous category as himself, contrary to what is right and
                    fitting. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="section">
                <p>When you, Aristogeiton, were convicted of a breach of the constitution for having
                    moved that three citizens should be executed without trial, and you escaped with
                    a fine, though you ought to have suffered the extreme penalty, there is no
                    parallel, not the slightest, between your case and that of a man who has gone
                    bail for a friend and then finds himself unable to pay an unexpected fine. My
                    second reason is that the bond of mutual kindness, which you yourselves
                    naturally preserve towards one another, is broken and destroyed by Aristogeiton,
                    as far as in him lies. You will understand this from what I am going to say. For
                    you, Athenians, observing what I have called the natural bond of mutual
                    kindness, live as a corporate body in this city just as families live in their
                    private homes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="section">
                <p>How then do such families live? Where there is a father and grown-up sons and
                    possibly also grandchildren, there are bound to be many divergent wishes; for
                    youth and age do not talk or act in the same way. Nevertheless whatever the
                    young men do, if they are modest, they do in such a way as to avoid notice; or
                    if this is impossible, at any rate they make it that such was their intention.
                    The elders in their turn, if they see any lack of moderation in spending or
                    drinking or amusement, manage to see it without showing that they have seen it.
                    The result is that everything that their various natures suggest is done, and
                    done satisfactorily. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="section">
                <p>And that is just how you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, live in this community on humane and brotherly
                    principles, one class watching the proceedings of the unfortunate in such a way
                    that, as the saying runs, “seeing, they see not; hearing, do not hear”; while
                    the others by their behavior show that they are both on their guard and alive to
                    a sense of shame. Hence it is that that general harmony, which is the source of
                    all our blessings, is firmly established in our city. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="section">
                <p>Those feelings, so happily implanted in your nature and your habits, Aristogeiton
                    would change and remove and overturn. What every other citizen does with as
                    little noise as possible, he performs, one might almost say, with a peal of
                    bells hung about his neck. Neither the president nor the crier nor the chairman
                    nor the tribe on duty can control him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="section">
                <p>So when any of you, annoyed at his outrageous conduct, cries, “To think that he
                    should act like this, and he a debtor to the treasury!” the reply is, “What! Is
                    not So-and-so a debtor too?”—each man suggesting his personal enemy. Thus his
                    wickedness is the cause of the scandals which are circulated about men who do
                    not resemble him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="section">
                <p>Therefore the one thing left, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, for those who wish to get rid of this man, now that
                    they can charge him with a clear and manifest offence against the laws, is, if
                    possible, to punish him with death, or, if not, to impose such a money fine as
                    he will not be able to pay. For depend upon it, there is no other way to be rid
                    of him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="section">
                <p>Among other men, Athenians, you may see the best and most respectable ready at
                    the prompting of nature to do what is right; those who are worse men, but are
                    not classed as the very bad, are careful of offending, because they are afraid
                    of you and are sensitive to disgrace and reproach; the utterly wicked, the moral
                    lepers, as we call them, are said to be taught wisdom only by suffering. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="section">
                <p>Now here is Aristogeiton, who has so far outstripped all men in wickedness that
                    his punishments have not disciplined him and he is once more detected in the
                    same illegal and rapacious acts. Also he is the more deserving of your anger now
                    than before, inasmuch as previously it was only by moving decrees that he
                    ventured to transgress the laws, but now he transgresses them in every possible
                    way—by accusations, by public speeches, by calumnies, by demanding the death
                    penalty, by impeaching and maligning the fully qualified citizens, when he
                    himself is a state-debtor. For nothing is more abominable than that. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="section">
                <p>Surely, then, to admonish such a fellow is madness. A man who never yielded or
                    shrank before the storm of protest with which the whole Assembly admonishes
                    those who offend it, would readily heed the protest of an individual! His case
                    is incurable, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, quite
                    incurable. Just as physicians, when they detect a cancer or an ulcer or some
                    other incurable growth, cauterize it or cut it away, so you ought all to unite
                    in exterminating this monster. Cast him out of your city; destroy him. Take your
                    precautions in time and do not wait for the evil consequences, which I pray may
                    never fall either on individuals or on the community. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="section">
                <p>Let me put it in this way. Perhaps none of you has ever been bitten by an adder
                    or a tarantula, and I hope he never may be. All the same, whenever you see such
                    creatures, you promptly kill them all. In just the same way, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, whenever you see a false accuser, a
                    man with the venom of a viper in his nature, do not wait for him to bite one of
                    you, but always let the man who comes across him exact punishment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="section">
                <p>Lycurgus did well to call Athena and the Mother of the gods to witness. But I
                    will invoke your ancestors and the virtues of your ancestors, whose memory time
                    has not effaced. It is right that I should do so; for their policy was not to
                    lend themselves to cooperation with the worst of rascals and false accusers, not
                    to foster the mutual jealousy that lurks within doors, but to honor those public
                    and private men who were wise and good, and to loathe and chastise those who
                    were wicked and unscrupulous; and that was how they all became competitors in
                    the rivalry of noble deeds. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="section">
                <p>One more thing I have to say before I sit down. You will soon be leaving this
                    court-house, and you will be watched by the bystanders, both aliens and
                    citizens; they will scan each one as he appears, and detect by their looks those
                    who have voted for acquittal. What will you have to say for yourselves,
                    Athenians, if you emerge after betraying the laws? With what expression, with
                    what look will you return their gaze? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="section">
                <p>How will you make your way to the Sanctuary of the Mother-goddess,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Where copies of all Athenian laws were deposited
                        for reference.</note> if you wish to do so? For surely you will never go
                    individually to consult the laws as if they were still valid, unless you have
                    now collectively confirmed them before you depart. How on the first of each
                    month will you climb the Acropolis and pray for blessings on the State and on
                    yourselves, when the defendant and his worthy father are registered there,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl n="Dem. 25.4">Dem. 25.4</bibl>.</note>
                    and you have given your verdict clean against your oaths and the documents there
                    preserved? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="section">
                <p>Or what will you say, Athenians, what will you say, if someone detects and
                    questions those of you who have voted for acquittal? What will you answer? That
                    you were satisfied with him? But who will dare to say that? Who will choose to
                    inherit this fellow's wickedness, with the execration and infamy that it
                    entails? Will each of you deny that he acquitted him? In that case you will have
                    to invoke a curse on the acquitters, as a guarantee from each of you that he was
                    not himself one of them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="section">
                <p>What need to do this, when you can keep your lips undefiled, and can all of you
                    pray for every blessing upon all, both on yourselves and on all other citizens
                    and, I may add, on all aliens and women and children? For the evil influence of
                    the defendant has.extended, yes, extended to all classes, and all alike are
                    anxious to be rid of his wickedness and to see that he has paid the penalty.</p>
            </div>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
