<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Busiris from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg010.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have learned of your fairmindedness, Polycrates, and of the reversal in your life,
          through information from others; and having myself read certain of the discourses which
          you have written, I should have been greatly pleased to discuss frankly with you and fully
          the education with which you have been obliged to occupy yourself. For I believe that when
          men through no fault of their own are unfortunate and so seek in philosophy a source of
            gain,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, from the teaching of the subject.</note>
          it is the duty of all who have had a wider experience in that occupation, and have become
          more thoroughly versed in it, to make this contribution<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For
            the figure of speech in <foreign xml:lang="greek">E)/RANOS</foreign> see <bibl
              n="Isoc. 10.20">Isoc. 10.20</bibl> and <bibl n="Plat. Sym. 177c">Plat.
            Sym.177c</bibl>.</note> voluntarily for their benefit. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But since we have not yet met one another, we shall be able, if we ever do come together,
          to discuss the other topics at greater length; concerning those suggestions, however, by
          which at the present time I might be of service to you, I have thought I should advise you
          by letter, though concealing my views, to the best of my ability, from everyone else. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I am well aware, however, that it is instinctive with most persons when admonished, not
          to look to the benefits they receive but, on the contrary, to listen to what is said with
          the greater displeasure in proportion to the rigor with which their critic passes their
          faults in review. Nevertheless, those who are well disposed toward any persons must not
          shrink from incurring such resentment, but must try to effect a change in the opinion of
          those who feel this way toward those who offer them counsel. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Having observed, therefore, that you take especial pride in your <title>Defense of
            Busiris</title> and in your <title>Accusation of Socrates</title>, I shall try to make
          it clear to you that in both these discourses you have fallen far short of what the
          subject demands. For although everyone knows that those who wish to praise a person must
          attribute to him a larger number of good qualities than he really possesses, and accusers
          must do the contrary, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>you have so far fallen short of following these principles of rhetoric that, though you
          profess to defend Busiris, you have not only failed to absolve him of the calumny with
          which he is attacked, but have even imputed to him a lawlessness of such enormity that it
          is impossible for one to invent wickedness more atrocious. For the other writers whose aim
          was to malign him went only so far in their abuse as to charge him with sacrificing the
            strangers<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the legend of Busiris see <bibl
              n="Apollod. 2.5.7">Apollod. 2.5.7</bibl> and <bibl n="Hdt. 2.45">Hdt. 2.45</bibl>.
            Busiris, in obedience to an oracle, sacrificed strangers on the altar of Zeus. Herodotus
            doubts the truth of the legend that the Egyptians sacrificed men.</note> who came to his
          country; you, however, accused him of actually devouring his victims. And when your
          purpose was to accuse Socrates, as if you wished to praise him, you gave Alcibiades to him
          as a pupil who, as far as anybody observed, never was taught by Socrates,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Alcibiades, if not a disciple of Socrates, was intimately
            associated with the philosopher; cf. <bibl n="Plat. Sym. 172a">Plat. Sym.</bibl> For
            praise of Alcibiades see <bibl n="Isoc. 16">Isoc. 16</bibl>.</note> but that Alcibiades
          far excelled all his contemporaries all would agree. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Hence, if the dead should acquire the power of judging what has been said of them,
          Socrates would be as grateful to you for your accusation as to any who have been wont to
          eulogize him; while Busiris, even if he had been most tender-hearted toward his guests,
          would be so enraged by your account of him that he would abstain from no vengeance
          whatever! And yet ought not that man to feel shame, rather than pride, who is more loved
          by those whom he has reviled than by those whom he has praised? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And you have been so careless about committing inconsistencies that you say Busiris
          emulated the fame of Aeolus and Orpheus, yet you do not show that any of his pursuits was
          identical with theirs. What, can we compare his deeds with the reported exploits of
          Aeolus? But Aeolus restored to their native lands strangers who were cast on his
            shores,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Hom. Od. 10.17-27">Hom. Od.
              10.17-27</bibl>, where Aeolus furnishes escort for Odysseus.</note> whereas Busiris,
          if we are to give credence to your account, sacrificed and ate them! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Or, are we to liken his deeds to those of Orpheus? But Orpheus led the dead back from
            Hades,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A reference to the myth of Orpheus and
            Eurydice.</note> whereas Busiris brought death to the living before their day of
          destiny. Consequently, I should be glad to know what, in truth, Busiris would have done if
          he had happened to despise Aeolus and Orpheus, seeing that, while admiring their virtues,
          all his own deeds are manifestly the opposite of theirs. But the greatest absurdity is
          this—though you have made a specialty of genealogies, you have dared to say that Busiris
          emulated those whose fathers even at that time had not yet been born!<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 11.37">Isoc. 11.37</bibl> for the same argument.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But that I may not seem to be doing the easiest thing in assailing what others have said
          without exhibiting any specimen of my own,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The same
            sentiment occurs in <bibl n="Isoc. 10.15">Isoc. 10.15</bibl>.</note> I will try briefly
          to expound the same subject — even though it is not serious and does not call for a
          dignified style — and show out of what elements you ought to have composed the eulogy and
          the speech in defense. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Of the noble lineage of Busiris who would not find it easy to speak? His father was
          Poseidon, his mother <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName> the daughter of
            Epaphus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Aesch. PB 850">Aesch. PB 850</bibl>,
            where Epaphus is said to be the son of Zeus and Io.</note> the son of Zeus, and she,
          they say, was the first woman to rule as queen and to give her own name to her country.
          Although fortune had given him such ancestors, these alone did not satisfy his pride, but
          he thought he must also leave behind an everlasting monument to his own valor. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> He was not content with his mother's kingdom, considering it too small for one of his
          endowment; and when he had conquered many peoples and had acquired supreme power he
          established his royal seat in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, because he
          judged that country to be far superior as his place of residence, not only to the lands
          which then were his, but even to all other countries in the world. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For he saw that all other regions are neither seasonably nor conveniently situated in
          relation to the nature of the universe, but some are deluged by rains and others scorched
          by heat; <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
              ><placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> here means the Delta of the <placeName
              key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>; cf. <bibl n="Hdt. 2.14">Hdt. 2.14</bibl>. Praise
            of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> is found in <bibl n="Plat. Tim. 22c"
              >Plat. Tim. 22c</bibl>.</note> however, having the most admirable situation of the
            universe,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., as regards climate and fertility.</note>
          was able to produce the most abundant and most varied products, and was defended by the
          immortal ramparts of the <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>a river which by its nature provides not only protection to the land, but also its means
          of subsistence in abundance, being impregnable and difficult for foes to conquer, yet
          convenient for commerce and in many respects serviceable to dwellers within its bounds.
          For in addition to the advantages I have mentioned, the <placeName key="tgn,1127805"
            >Nile</placeName> has bestowed upon the Egyptians a godlike power in respect to the
          cultivation of the land; for while Zeus is the dispenser<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Cf. <bibl n="Hom. Il. 4.84">Hom. Il. 4.84</bibl>.</note> of rains and droughts to the
          rest of mankind, of both of these each Egyptian has made himself master on his own
          account. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And to so perfect a state of happiness have the Egyptians come that with respect to the
          excellence and fertility of their land and the extent of their plains they reap the fruits
          of a continent, and as regards the disposition of their superfluous products and the
          importation of what they lack, the river's possibilities are such that they inhabit an
            island<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A reference to the Delta, enclosed and watered by
            the branches of the <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>.</note>; for the
            <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>, encircling the land and flowing through
          its whole extent, has given them abundant means for both. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> So Busiris thus began, as wise men should, by occupying the fairest country and also by
          finding sustenance sufficient for his subjects. Afterwards, he divided them into
            classes<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates here praises the caste system. Cf.
            Plato in the <title>Republic</title>.</note>: some he appointed to priestly services,
          others he turned to the arts and crafts, and others he forced to practise the arts of war.
          He judged that, while necessities and superfluous products must be provided by the land
          and the arts, the safest means of protecting these was practice in warfare and reverence
          for the gods. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Including in all classes the right numbers for the best administration of the
          commonwealth, he gave orders that the same individuals should always engage in the same
          pursuits, because he knew that those who continually change their occupations never
          achieve proficiency in even a single one of their tasks, whereas those who apply
          themselves constantly to the same activities perform each thing they do surpassingly well.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Hence we shall find that in the arts the Egyptians surpass those who work at the same
          skilled occupations elsewhere more than artisans in general excel the laymen; also with
          respect to the system which enables them to preserve royalty and their political
          institutions in general, they have been so successful that philosophers<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">It is natural to think that there is a reference here to Plato
            and his <title>Republic</title>, but it is not certain.</note> who undertake to discuss
          such topics and have won the greatest reputation prefer above all others the Egyptian form
          of government, and that the Lacedaemonians, on the other hand, govern their own city in
          admirable fashion because they imitate certain of the Egyptian customs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For instance, the provision that no citizen fit for military service could leave the
          country without official authorization, the meals taken in common, and the training of
          their bodies; furthermore, the fact that lacking none of the necessities of life, they do
          not neglect the edicts of the State, and that none engage in any other crafts, but that
          all devote themselves to arms and warfare, all these practices they have taken from
            <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Hdt. 2.80">Hdt. 2.80</bibl> and <bibl n="Hdt. 6.60">Hdt. 6.60</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the Lacedaemonians have made so much worse use of these institutions that all of
          them, being professional soldiers, claim the right to seize by force the property of
          everybody else, whereas the Egyptians live as people should who neither neglect their own
          possessions, nor plot how they may acquire the property of others. The difference in the
          aims of the two polities may be seen from the following: </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>if we should all imitate the sloth and greed of the Lacedaemonians, we should straightway
          perish through both the lack of the necessities of daily life and civil war; but if we
          should wish to adopt the laws of the Egyptians which prescribe that some must work and
          that the rest must protect the property of the workers, we should all possess our own
          goods and pass our days in happiness. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Furthermore, the cultivation of practical wisdom may also reasonably be attributed to
          Busiris. For example, he saw to it that from the revenues of the sacrifices the priests
          should acquire affluence, but self-control through the purifications prescribed by the
          laws, and leisure by exemption from the hazards of fighting and from all work. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And the priests, because they enjoyed such conditions of life, discovered for the body
          the aid which the medical art affords<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Hdt. 2.84">Hdt. 2.84</bibl> and <bibl n="Hdt. 3.129">Hdt. 3.129</bibl>.</note>, not
          that which uses dangerous drugs, but drugs of such a nature that they are as harmless as
          daily food, yet in their effects are so beneficial that all men agree the Egyptians are
          the healthiest and most long of life among men; and then for the soul they introduced
          philosophy's training, a pursuit which has the power, not only to establish laws, but also
          to investigate the nature of the universe. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The older men Busiris appointed to have charge of the most important matters, but the
          younger he persuaded to forgo all pleasures and devote themselves to the study of the
          stars, to arithmetic, and to geometry; the value of these sciences<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For the views of Isocrates in regard to the sciences see <bibl n="Isoc. 12.26"
              >Isoc. 12.26-27</bibl>.</note> some praise for their utility in certain ways, while
          others attempt to demonstrate that they are conducive in the highest measure to the
          attainment of virtue. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The piety of the Egyptians and their worship of the gods are especially deserving of
          praise and admiration. For all persons who have so bedizened themselves as to create the
          impression that they possess greater wisdom, or some other excellence, than they can
          rightly claim, certainly do harm to their dupes; but those persons who have so championed
          the cause of religion that divine rewards and punishments are made to appear more certain
          than they prove to be, such men, I say, benefit in the greatest measure the lives of men.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For actually those who in the beginning inspired in us our fear of the gods, brought it
          about that we in our relations to one another are not altogether like wild beasts<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In <bibl n="Isoc. 3.6">Isoc. 3.6</bibl>, Isocrates affirms
            that the power of speech and of reason has enables us to escape the life of wild beasts.
            See also <bibl n="Isoc. 4.48">Isoc. 4.48 ff.</bibl></note> So great, moreover, is the
          piety and the solemnity with which the Egyptians deal with these matters that not only are
          the oaths taken in their sanctuaries more binding than is the case elsewhere, but each
          person believes that he will pay the penalty for his misdeeds immediately and that he will
          neither escape detection for the present nor will the punishment be deferred to his
          children's time. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And they have good reason for this belief; for Busiris established for them numerous and
          varied practices of piety and ordered them by law even to worship and to revere certain
          animals which among us are regarded with contempt, not because he misapprehended their
          power, but because he thought that the crowd ought to be habituated to obedience to all
          the commands of those in authority, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and at the same time he wished to test in visible matters how they felt in regard to the
          invisible. For he judged that those who belittled these instructions would perhaps look
          with contempt upon the more important commands also, but that those who gave strict
          obedience equally in everything would have given proof of their steadfast piety. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If one were not determined to make haste, one might cite many admirable instances of the
          piety of the Egyptians, that piety which I am neither the first nor the only one to have
          observed; on the contrary, many contemporaries and predecessors have remarked it, of whom
          Pythagoras of <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName> is one<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The celebrated philosopher; cf. <bibl n="Hdt. 4.95">Hdt. 4.95</bibl>.</note>
          On a visit to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> he became a student of the
          religion of the people, and was first to bring to the Greeks all philosophy, and more
          conspicuously than others he seriously interested himself in sacrifices and in ceremonial
          purity, since he believed that even if he should gain thereby no greater reward from the
          gods, among men, at any rate, his reputation would be greatly enhanced. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And this indeed happened to him. For so greatly did he surpass all others in reputation
          that all the younger men desired to be his pupils, and their elders were more pleased to
          see their sons staying in his company than attending to their private affairs. And these
          reports we cannot disbelieve; for even now persons who profess to be followers of his
          teaching are more admired when silent than are those who have the greatest renown for
          eloquence. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Perhaps, however, you would reply against all I have said, that I am praising the land,
          the laws, and the piety of the Egyptians, and also their philosophy, but that Busiris was
          their author, as I have assumed, I am able to offer no proof whatever. If any other person
          criticized me in that fashion, I should believe that his censure was that of a scholar;
          but you are not the one to reprove me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For, when you wished to praise Busiris, you chose to say that he forced the <placeName
            key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName> to break into branches and surround the land<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Hdt. 2.16">Hdt. 2.16</bibl>, where the same verb
              (<foreign xml:lang="greek">PERIRRH/GNUMI</foreign>) is used in connexion with the
            branches of the <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName> in the Delta.</note>, and
          that he sacrificed and ate strangers who came to his country; but you gave no proof that
          he did these things. And yet is it not ridiculous to demand that others follow a procedure
          which you yourself have not used in the slightest degree? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nay, your account is far less credible than mine, since I attribute to him no impossible
          deed, but only laws and political organization, which are the accomplishments of honorable
          men, whereas you represent him as the author of two astounding acts which no human being
          would commit, one requiring the cruelty of wild beasts, the other the power of the gods.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Further, even if both of us, perchance, are wrong, I, at any rate, have used only such
          arguments as authors of eulogies must use; you, on the contrary, have employed those which
          are appropriate to revilers. Consequently, it is obvious that you have gone astray, not
          only from the truth, but also from the entire pattern which must be employed in eulogy.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Apart from these considerations, if your discourse should be put aside and mine
          carefully examined, no one would justly find fault with it. For if it were manifest that
          another had done the deeds which I assert were done by him, I acknowledge that I am
          exceedingly audacious in trying to change men's views about matters of which all the world
          has knowledge. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But as it is, since the question is open to the judgement of all and one must resort to
          conjecture, who, reasoning from what is probable, would be considered to have a better
          claim to the authorship of the institutions of <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
            >Egypt</placeName> rather than a son of Poseidon, a descendant of Zeus on his mother's
          side, the most powerful personage of his time and the most renowned among all other
          peoples? For surely it is not fitting that any who were in all these respects inferior
          should, in preference to Busiris, have the credit of being the authors of those great
          benefactions. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Furthermore, it could be easily proved on chronological grounds also that the statements
          of the detractors of Busiris are false. For the same writers who accuse Busiris of slaying
          strangers also assert that he died at the hands of Heracles; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but all chroniclers agree that Heracles was later by four generations than Perseus, son
          of Zeus and Danae, and that Busiris lived more than two hundred years earlier than
          Perseus. And yet what can be more absurd than that one who was desirous of clearing
          Busiris of the calumny has failed to mention that evidence, so manifest and so conclusive?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But the fact is that you had no regard for the truth; on the contrary, you followed the
          calumnies of the poets, who declare that the offspring of the immortals have perpetrated
          as well as suffered things more atrocious than any perpetrated or suffered by the
          offspring of the most impious of mortals; aye, the poets have related about the gods
          themselves tales more outrageous than anyone would dare tell concerning their enemies. For
          not only have they imputed to them thefts and adulteries, and vassalage among men, but
          they have fabricated tales of the eating of children, the castrations of fathers, the
          fetterings of mothers, and many other crimes<note anchored="true" resp="ed">e.g., Hermes
            steals Apollo's oxen (<bibl n="HH 4.1">HH Herm.</bibl>); the illicit love of Ares and
            Aphrodite (<bibl n="Hom. Od. 8">Hom. Od. 8</bibl>); Apollo, servant of Admetus (<bibl
              n="Eur. Alc.">Eur. Alc.</bibl>); Cronus devours his children and mutilates his father
            Uranus; and Hephaestus fetters Hera.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For these blasphemies the poets, it is true, did not pay the penalty they deserved, but
          assuredly they did not escape punishment altogether; some became vagabonds begging for
          their daily bread; others became blind; another spent all his life in exile from his
          fatherland and in warring with his kinsmen; and Orpheus, who made a point of rehearsing
          these tales, died by being torn asunder<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For example, Homer
            was represented as a blind wanderer; Stesichorus was smitten with blindness for abuse of
            Helen in his verses; and Orpheus was torn to pieces by the women of <placeName
              key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>. Perhaps Archilochus is the poet in exile.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore if we are wise we shall not imitate their tales, nor while passing laws for the
          punishment of libels against each other, shall we disregard loose-tongued vilification of
          the gods; on the contrary, we shall be on our guard and consider equally guilty of impiety
          those who recite and those who believe such lies<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The poet
            Xenophanes, and later Plato, had strongly protested against the attribution of
            immoralities to the gods.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now I, for my part, think that not only the gods but also their offspring have no share
          in any wickedness but themselves are by nature endowed with all the virtues and have
          become for all mankind guides and teachers of the most honorable conduct. For it is absurd
          that we should attribute to the gods the responsibility for the happy fortunes of our
          children, and yet believe them to be indifferent to those of their own. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nay, if any one of us should obtain the power of regulating human nature, he would not
          allow even his slaves to be vicious; yet we condemn the gods by believing that they
          permitted their own offspring to be so impious and lawless. And you, Polycrates, assume
          that you will make men better even if they are not related to you, provided that they
          become your pupils, yet believe that the gods have no care for the virtue of their own
          children! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet, according to your own reasoning, the gods are not free from the two most
          disgraceful faults: for if they do not want their children to be virtuous, they are
          inferior in character to human beings; but if, on the other hand, they desire it but are
          at a loss how to effect it, they are more impotent than the sophists! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Although the subject admits of many arguments for the amplification of my theme of
          eulogy and defense, I believe it unnecessary to speak at greater length; for my aim in
          this discourse is not to make a display to impress others, but to show for your benefit
          how each of these topics should be treated, since the composition which you wrote may
          justly be considered by anyone to be, not a defense of Busiris, but an admission of all
          the crimes charged against him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For you do not exonerate him from the charges, but only declare that some others have
          done the same things, inventing thus a very easy refuge for all criminals. Why, if it is
          not easy to find a crime which has not yet been committed, and if we should consider that
          those who have been found guilty of one or another of these crimes have done nothing so
          very wrong, whenever others are found to have perpetrated the same offences, should we not
          be providing ready-made pleas in exculpation of all criminals and be granting complete
          licence for those who are bent on villainy? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>You would best perceive the inanity of your defense of Busiris if you should imagine
          yourself in his position. Just suppose this case: if you had been accused of grave and
          terrible crimes and an advocate should defend you in this fashion, what would be your
          state of mind? I know very well that you would detest him more heartily than your
          accusers. And yet is it not disgraceful to compose for others a plea in defense of such
          kind that it would arouse your extreme anger if spoken on your own behalf? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Again, consider this, and meditate upon it. If one of your pupils should be induced to
          do those things which you praise, would he not be the most wretched of men who are now
          alive and, in truth, of all who ever have lived? Is it right, therefore,to compose
          discourses such that they will do the most good if they succeed in convincing no one among
          those who hear them? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But perhaps you will say that you too were not unaware of all this but that you wished
          to bequeath to men of learning an example of how pleas in defense of shameful charges and
          difficult causes ought to be made. But I think it has now been made clear to you, even if
          you were previously in ignorance, that an accused person would sooner gain acquittal by
          not uttering a word than by pleading his cause in this way. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And, furthermore, this too is evident, that philosophy<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By
            “philosophy” Isocrates means <foreign xml:lang="greek">TH\N PERI\ TOU\S LO/GOUS
              PAI/DEUSIN</foreign> of §49, fin.—the training in, and cultivation of, the art of
            discourse.</note>, which is already in mortal jeopardy and is hated, will be detested
          even more because of such discourses. If, then, you will listen to me, you will preferably
          not deal in future with such base subjects, but if that cannot be, you will seek to speak
          of such things as will neither injure your own reputation, nor corrupt your imitators, nor
          bring the teaching of rhetoric into disrepute. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And do not be astonished if I, who am younger than you and unrelated to you, essay so
          lightly to admonish you; for, in my opinion, giving good counsel on such subjects is not
          the function of older men or of the most intimate friends, but of those who know most and
          desire most to render service.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
