<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
         	<title>Whether the Affections of the Soul are Worse Than Those of the Body</title>
            <author>Plutarch</author>
            <editor>William Clark Helmbold</editor>
         	<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
         	<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
         	<respStmt>
         		<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
         		<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
         		<name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
         		<name>Bridget Almas</name>
         	</respStmt>
         	<funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
      	<publicationStmt>
      		<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
      		<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
      		<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      		<date type="release">2010-12-13</date>
      	</publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>W. C. Helmbold</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date type="printing">1939</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            	<ref target="https://archive.org/details/moralia03plut/page/297">The Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      	<p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture</p>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
         	<cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="section" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
         		<p>This pointer pattern extracts sections</p>
         	</cRefPattern>
            <!--<state unit="section"/>-->
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>-->
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
         	<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         	<language ident="deu">German</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
      	<change who="RS" when="2010-05">tagged and parsed</change>
      	<change who="Sophia Elzie" when="2019-07-15">tagged and parsed</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
      	<div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg100.perseus-eng3" type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
      		<head>WHETHER THE AFFECTIONS
      			OF THE SOUL ARE WORSE
      			THAN THOSE OF THE BODY
      			(<foreign xml:lang="lat">ANIMINE AN CORPORIS AFFECTIONES SINT PEIORES</foreign>)</head><lb/>
         <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="intro">
            <pb xml:id="v.6.p.378"/>
            <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
            <p rend="indent">
					This popular oration, or diatribe,
            	<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">So Pohlenz, as I think, correctly: I therefore do not accept Wilamowitz's combination of this and the preceding work as fragments of the same dialogue.</note>
            	was read by
					Plutarch<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Xylander, practically alone, denies the genuineness - on what ground he does not say.
					</note> in some city of Asia Minor: Volkmann
            	<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <title rend="italic">Plutarch</title>, vol. i. 62 f.</note>
					thought Sardis, the capital of the province; Haupt<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Opuscula</title>, iii. 554 (<title rend="italic">Hermes</title>, vi. 258).</note>
					thought Halicarnassus; Wilamowitz<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <title rend="italic">Hermes</title>, xl. 161 ff.</note> Ephesus. The
					occasion is clearly the consul's yearly hearing of lawsuits from the whole province.
				</p>
            <p>
					The proof that afflictions of the soul are worse than
					diseases of the body is treated in a popular and, in
					chapter 4, dramatic manner. The conclusion is lost.
				</p>
            <p>
					The same subject was treated in his commonplace
					fashion by Maximus Tyrius,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <title rend="italic">Orat.</title> 7 ed. Hobein, 13 ed. Dübner.</note> who shows no knowledge of Plutarch's oration, nor any relation to his
					sources; Cicero, however, at the beginning of the
					third book of the <title rend="italic">Tusculan Disputations</title>, exhibits some
					kinship with Plutarch's argument. Siefert<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Comm. Ienenses</title>, 1896, pp. 106-110; <title rend="italic">Plutarchs Schrift</title> 
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">Περὶ εὐθυμίας</foreign>, pp. 26-28.</note> has twice
					elaborated his opinion that some of this work of
					
					<pb xml:id="v.6.p.379"/>
					Plutarch's was drawn from the <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπόμνημα</foreign> (I should
					prefer to say <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπομνήματα</foreign>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">See the introduction to the <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">De Tranquillitate</title>.</note>) which Plutarch used in
					writing <title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">De Tranquillitate</title>.
				</p>
            <p>
					The text is not good. The work is listed as No.
					208 in the Lamprias catalogue.
					
				</p>
         </div>
         <pb xml:id="v.6.p.381"/>
         <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="1">
         	<p rend="indent">Homer,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <title rend="italic">Il.</title>, xvii. 446-447; <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> 496 b, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note> having contemplated the mortal varieties
					of animals and having compared them with each
					other in respect to their lives and habits, cried out
					that nothing is
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>More wretched than man,
						</l>
                  <l>Of all that breathes and creeps upon the earth,</l>
               </quote>
					awarding to man an unfortunate primacy in excess of
					evils. But as for us, as though acknowledging that
					man has won the victory in wretchedness and has
					been proclaimed the most miserable of animals, let
					us compare him with himself, dividing body and soul
					for competition of their individual miseries, a task
					not unprofitable but even quite necessary, to the
					end that we may learn whether it is through Fortune
					or through ourselves that we live more wretchedly.
					For while disease grows in the body through Nature,
					vice and depravity in the soul are first the souls
					own doing, and then its affliction. It will be no
					slight aid toward tranquillity of mind, if the worse
					condition be curable, being both lighter to bear
					and lacking intensity.
					
					<pb xml:id="v.6.p.383"/>
					
				        </p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="2">
         	<p rend="indent">The fox in Aesop,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <title rend="italic">Fable</title> 42 ed. Halm; <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 155 b; Babrius, 
         		<title rend="italic">Fable</title> 180 ed. Crusius; Siefert, <title rend="italic">Plutarchs Schrift</title> 
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">Περὶ εὐθυμίας</foreign>, pp. 27-28.</note> disputing at law with the
					leopard concerning their claims to variety,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <foreign xml:lang="grc">ποικιλία</foreign> when applied to an animal's skin refers to colour and markings, but when it is applied to the mind it means 
						<q type="unspecified">subtlety</q> or <q type="unspecified">cunning.</q>
               </note> when the
					leopard had shown her body with its glossy surface
					bright and spotted, and the fox's tawny skin was
					rough and unpleasant to the eye,
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>
                  <quote>But look at me <emph rend="italic">>within</emph>, sir judge,</quote> said she,
						</l>
                  <l>
                     <quote>And you will find me fuller far than she
							</quote>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <quote>Of fair variety,</quote>
                     <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                        <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> Wilamowitz, <title rend="italic">Hermes</title>, xl. p. 164; Diehl, <title rend="italic">Anthologia Lyrica</title>, i. p. 304: Plutarch's words are apparently adapted from an unknown choliambic poet. See also Knox, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Choliambica</title> (L.C.L.), p. 350.</note>
                  </l>
               </quote>
					making manifest the versatility of her character
					which changes to many forms as necessity arises.
					Shall we, then, say in our own case, <q type="unspecified">Many of your
						diseases and affections, O man, your body naturally
						produces of itself, and it receives also many that
						befall it from without; but if you lay yourself open
						on the inside, you will find a storehouse and treasury,
						as Democritus<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Diels, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="deu">Frag. d. Vorsokratiker</title>
                     <hi rend="superscript">5</hi>, vol. ii. p. 172, Frag. 149.</note> says, of all manner of evils and many
						abnormal states, which do not flow in from outside,
						but have, as it were, subterranean and earth-born
						springs, which Vice, being widely diffused and abundantly supplied with those abnormal states, causes to
						gush forth</q>? And if the diseases in the flesh are
					detected by the pulse and biliousness, and temperatures and sudden pains confirm their presence, but the
					evils in the soul escape the notice of most men, they
					are for this reason worse evils, since they also deprive
					the sufferer of any awareness of themselves. For
					although the reason,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> Cicero, <title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Tusc. Disp.</title>, iii. 1.</note> if sound, perceives the diseases
					
					<pb xml:id="v.6.p.385"/>
					
					which affect the body, yet, being itself afflicted with
					those of the soul, it can form no judgement of its
					own afflictions, for it is affected in the very part by
					which it judges; and, of the souls diseases, one
					must account as first and greatest ignorance, which
					causes Vice beyond hope of cure to abide with most
					men, to cling to them through life, and to die with
					them. For the beginning of the riddance of disease
					is awareness which leads the ailing part to the use
					of what will relieve it; but the man who through
					disbelief in his ailment does not know what he needs,
					refuses the remedy, even if it be at hand. For it is
					true of the diseases of the body also that those are
					worse which are attended by inability to perceive the
					body's condition: lethargies, migraine, epilepsies,
					apoplexies, and those very fevers which, raising inflammation to the pitch of delirium and confounding
					consciousness, as on a musical instrument,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Will touch the heart-strings never touched before.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                     <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> 456 c, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note>
               </quote>
				        </p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="3">
         	<p rend="indent">Therefore professional physicians desire, in the
					first place that a man should not be ill; and next,
					if he is ill, that he should not be unaware that he is
					ill<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 102 d; Cicero, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Tusc. Disp.</title>, iii. 6. 12.</note>
         		- which is the case with all the maladies which
					affect the soul. For when men act foolishly<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> Moralia, 81 f.</note> or
					licentiously or unjustly, they do not think that they
					are doing wrong, but some even think that they are
					doing right. For although no one has ever called a
					fever <q type="unspecified">health,</q> nor consumption <q type="unspecified">excellent condition,</q> nor gout <q type="unspecified">swiftness of foot,</q> nor sallowness
					a <q type="unspecified">fresh complexion,</q> yet many call hot temper<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> 462 f, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note>
					
					          <pb xml:id="v.6.p.387"/>
					
					          <q type="unspecified">manliness,</q> and love <q type="unspecified">friendship,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <q type="unspecified">Si on juge de l'amour par la plupart de ses effets, il ressemble plus a la haine qu'a l'amitie.</q> - De la Rochefoucauld.</note> and envy
					<q type="unspecified">emulation,</q> and cowardice <q type="unspecified">caution.</q> Again,
					while men sick in body send for a doctor, since they
					perceive whom they need to counteract their ailments, yet those that are sick in soul avoid philosophers, for they think that they are doing well in those
					very matters where they are at fault. The fact is that,
					if we follow on this line of reasoning, we maintain
					that defective eyesight is easier to bear than madness
					and gout than inflammation of the brain! For a
					man that is sick in body perceives it and calls loudly
					for a physician, and when he comes, allows him to
					anoint the eyes or open the veins; but you hear the
					maddened Agave say,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Euripides, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Bacchae</title>m 1169-1171; 
						<foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign><title rend="italic">Life of Crassus</title>, 
						xxxiii. (564 f): Agave, bearing the head of her son Pentheus, was a commonplace of philosophical rhetoric; see, for example, Horace, 
						<title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Sermones</title>, ii. 3. 303.</note> not recognizing her dearest
					by reason of her affliction:
					<quote rend="blockquote">
                  <l>From the mountain we bring
						</l>
                  <l>To the palace a fresh-cut tendril,
						</l>
                  <l>A fortunate capture.</l>
               </quote>
				        </p>
            <p>
					It is true that one who is sick in body gives in at
					once and goes to bed and remains quiet while he is
					being cured, and if, perchance j when the fever comes
					upon him, he tosses a bit and tumbles his body about,
					one of those who sit by him will say to him gently,
					<quote rend="blockquote">Lie still, poor wretch, and move not from your bed,
						<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Euripides, <title rend="italic">Orestes</title>, 258; 
							<foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> 475 d, <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra</foreign>.</note>
               </quote>
					and so checks and restrains him; but those who suffer
					from diseases of the soul are then most active, then
					
					<pb xml:id="v.6.p.389"/>
					
					least at rest. For impulses are the beginning of
					action, and the soul's abnormal states are violent
					impulses. That is the reason why they do not allow
					the soul to be at rest, but just at the time when
					man most needs repose and silence and relaxation,
					then his fits of temper, of contentiousness, of love,
					of grief, drag him into the open air and strip him
					bare, and he is forced both to do many lawless
					things and to give tongue to many things unsuited
					to the occasion.
				</p>
         </div>
         <div subtype="section" type="textpart" n="4">
         	<p rend="indent">As, therefore, the storm that prevents a sailor
					from putting into port is more dangerous than that
					which does not allow him to sail, so those storms of
					the soul are more serious which do not allow a man
					to compose or to calm his disturbed reason; but
					pilotless and without ballast, in confusion and aimless
					wandering, rushing headlong in oblique and reeling
					courses, he suffers a terrible shipwreck, as it were,
					and ruins his life. Consequently for this reason also
					it is worse to be sick in soul than in body; for men
					afflicted in body only suffer, but those afflicted in soul
					both suffer and do ill.<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> Cicero, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Tusc. Disp.</title>, iii. 5. 10.</note>
				        </p>
            <p>
					But why need I recount the multitude of the soul's
					maladies? The present occasion of itself brings
					them to mind. Do you see this vast and promiscuous
					crowd which jostles and surges in confusion here
					about the tribunal and the market-place? These
					persons have come together, not to sacrifice to their
					country's gods, not to share in each other's family
					rites, not bringing <q type="unspecified">to Ascraean Zeus
						<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">For the cult of Ascraean Zeus at Halicarnassus 
							<foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> Apollonius, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Historia Mirabilium</title>, 13 (Keller, 
							<title xml:lang="lat" rend="italic">Rerum Naturalium Scriptores Graeci Minores</title>, i. p. 47).</note> the first-fruits
						
						<pb xml:id="v.6.p.391"/>
						
					of Lydian harvests,</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Probably a quotation from a poet: Reiske thought Pindar; Haupt (
               	<title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Opuscula</title>, iii. 554), an anonymous tragic poet (and <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign> 
               	Wilamowitz, <title rend="italic">Hermes</title>, xl. 163, 164, note 1).</note> nor, in honour of
					Dionysus, to celebrate his mystic festival on sacred
					nights with common revellings, but, as it were, a
					mighty pestilence drives them together here with
					yearly visitations stirring up Asia, which must come
					for law-suits and litigation at certain stated times;
					and the overwhelming multitude, like streams flowing together, has inundated this one market-place
					and boils with fury and dashes together in a tumult
					<q type="unspecified">of destroyers and destroyed.</q>
               <note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Homer, <title rend="italic">Il.</title>, iv. 451.</note> What fevers, what
					agues, have brought this about? What stoppages,
					or irruptions of blood,<note resp="ed" place="unspecified" anchored="true">
                  <foreign xml:lang="lat">cf.</foreign><title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>, 129 d.</note> or distemperature of heat,
					or overflow of humours, have caused this? If you
					examine every law-suit, as though it were a person,
					to discover what gave rise to it and whence it came,
					you will find that obstinate anger begat one, frantic
					ambition another, unjust desire a third...
					
				</p>
         </div>
      	</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>