<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Sacred Disease</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 20, 2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							<date>1886</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Aph.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Epid.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="section" n="1">
				<p> It is thus with regard to the disease called Sacred: it appears to me to be
					nowise more divine nor more sacred than other diseases, but has a natural cause
					from the originates like other affections. Men regard its nature and cause as
					divine from ignorance and wonder, because it is not at all like to other
					diseases. And this notion of its divinity is kept up by their inability to
					comprehend it, and the simplicity of the mode by which it is cured, for men are
					freed from it by purifications and incantations. But if it is reckoned divine
					because it is wonderful, instead of one there are many diseases which would be
					sacred; for, as I will show, there are others no less wonderful and prodigious,
					which nobody imagines to be sacred. The quotidian, tertian, and quartan fevers,
					seem to me no less sacred and divine in their origin than this disease, although
					they are not reckoned so wonderful. And I see men become mad and demented from
					no manifest cause, and at the same time doing many things out of place; and I
					have known many persons in sleep groaning and crying out, some in a state of
					suffocation, some jumping up and fleeing out of doors, and deprived of their
					reason until they awaken, and afterward becoming well and rational as before,
					although they be pale and weak; and this will happen not once but frequently.
					And there are many and various things of the like kind, which it would be
					tedious to state particularly. </p>

				<p>They who first referred this malady to the gods appear to me to have been just
					such persons as the conjurors, purificators, mountebanks, and charlatans now
					are, who give themselves out for being excessively religious, and as knowing
					more than other people. Such persons, then, using <pb n="p.356"/>the divinity as
					a pretext and screen of their own inability to afford 
					any assistance, have given out that the disease is sacred, adding suitable
					reasons for this opinion, they have instituted a mode of treatment which is safe
					for themselves, namely, by applying purifications and incantations, and
					enforcing abstinence from baths and many articles of food which are unwholesome
					to men in diseases. Of sea substances, the surmullet, the blacktail, the mullet,
					and the eel; for these are the fishes most to be guarded against. And of
					fleshes, those of the goat, the stag, the sow, and the dog: for these are the
					kinds of flesh which are aptest to disorder the bowels. Of fowls, the cock, the
					turtle, and the bustard, and such others as are reckoned to be particularly
					strong. And of potherbs, mint, garlic, and onions; for what is acrid does not
					agree with a weak person. And they forbid to have a black robe, because black is
					expressive of death; and to sleep on a goat's skin, or to wear it, and to put
					one foot upon another, or one hand upon another; for all these things are held
					to be hindrances to the cure. All these they enjoin with reference to its
					divinity, as if possessed of more knowledge, and announcing beforehand other
					causes so that if the person should recover, theirs would be the honor and
					credit; and if he should die, they would have a certain defense, as if the gods,
					and not they, were to blame, seeing they had administered nothing either to eat
					or drink as medicines, nor had overheated him with baths, so as to prove the
					cause of what had happened. But I am of opinion that (if this were true) none of
					the Libyans, who live in the interior, would be free from this disease, since
					they all sleep on goats' skins, and live upon goats' flesh; neither have they
					couch, robe, nor shoe that is not made of goat's skin, for they have no other
					herds but goats and oxen. But if these things, when administered in food,
					aggravate the disease, and if it be cured by abstinence from them, godhead is
					not the cause at all; nor will purifications be of any avail, but it is the food
					which is beneficial and prejudicial, and the influence of the divinity
					vanishes.</p>

				<p>Thus, they who try to cure these maladies in this way, appear to me neither to
					reckon them sacred nor divine. For when they are removed by such purifications,
					and this method of cure, what is to prevent them<pb n="p.357"/> from being
					brought upon men and induced by other devices similar to these? So that the
					cause is no longer divine, but human. For whoever is able, by purifications
					conjurations, to drive away such an affection, will be able, by other practices,
					to excite it; and, according to this view, its divine nature is entirely done
					away with. By such sayings and doings, they profess to be possessed of superior
					knowledge, and deceive mankind by enjoining lustrations and purifications upon
					them, while their discourse turns upon the divinity and the godhead. And yet it
					would appear to me that their discourse savors not of piety, as they suppose,
					but rather of impiety, and as if there were no gods, and that what they hold to
					be holy and divine, were impious and unholy. This I will now explain.</p>

				<p>For, if they profess to know how to bring down the moon, darken the sun, induce
					storms and fine weather, and rains and droughts, and make the sea and land
					unproductive, and so forth, whether they arrogate this power as being derived
					from mysteries or any other knowledge or consideration, they appear to me to
					practice impiety, and either to fancy that there are no gods, or, if there are,
					that they have no ability to ward off any of the greatest evils. How, then, are
					they not enemies to the gods? For if a man by magical arts and sacrifices will
					bring down the moon, and darken the sun, and induce storms, or fine weather, I
					should not believe that there was anything divine, but human, in these things,
					provided the power of the divine were overpowered by human knowledge and
					subjected to it. But perhaps it will be said, these things are not so, but, not
					withstanding, men being in want of the means of life, invent many and various
					things, and devise many contrivances for all other things, and for this disease,
					in every phase of the disease, assigning the cause to a god. Nor do they
					remember the same things once, but frequently. For, if they imitate a goat, or
					grind their teeth, or if their right side be convulsed, they say that the mother
					of the gods is the cause. But if they speak in a sharper and more intense tone,
					they resemble this state to a horse, and say that Poseidon<hi rend="ital"
						>(Neptune)</hi> is the cause. Or if any excrement be passed, which is often
					the case, owing to the violence of the disease, the appellation of Enodia (<hi
						rend="ital">Hecate?</hi>)is adhibited;<pb n="p.358"/> or, if it be passed in
					smaller and denser masses, like bird's, it is said to be from Apollo Nomius. But
					if foam be emitted by the mouth, and the patient kick with his feet, Ares<hi
						rend="ital">(Mars)</hi> then gets the blame. But terrors which happen during
					the night, and fevers, and delirium, and jumpings out of bed, and frightful
					apparitions, and fleeing away,-all these they hold to be the plots of Hecate,
					and the invasions the and use purifications and incantations, and, as appears to
					me, make the divinity to be most wicked and most impious. For they purify those
					laboring under this disease, with the same sorts of blood and the other means
					that are used in the case of those who are stained with crimes, and of
					malefactors, or who have been enchanted by men, or who have done any wicked act;
					who ought to do the very reverse, namely, sacrifice and pray, and, bringing
					gifts to the temples, supplicate the gods. But now they do none of these things,
					but purify; and some of the purifications they conceal in the earth, and some
					they throw into the sea, and some they carry to the mountains where no one can
					touch or tread upon them. But these they ought to take to the temples and
					present to the god, if a god be the cause of the disease. Neither truly do I
					count it a worthy opinion to hold that the body of man is polluted by god, the
					most impure by the most holy; for were it defiled, or did it suffer from any
					other thing, it would be like to be purified and sanctified rather than polluted
					by god. For it is the divinity which purifies and sanctifies the greatest of
					offenses and the most wicked, and which proves our protection from them. And we
					mark out the boundaries of the temples and the groves of the gods, so that no
					one may pass them unless he be pure, and when we enter them we are sprinkled
					with holy water, not as being polluted, but as laying aside any other pollution
					which we formerly had. And thus it appears to me to hold, with regard to
					purifications.</p>

				<p>But this disease seems to me to be no more divine than others; but it has its
					nature such as other diseases have, and a cause whence it originates, and its
					nature and cause are divine only just as much as all others are, and it is
					curable no less than the others, unless when, the from of time, it is confirmed,
					and has became stronger than the remedies applied. Its origin is hereditary, <pb
						n="p.359"/>like that of other diseases. For if a phlegmatic person be born
					of a phlegmatic, and a bilious of a bilious, and a phthisical of a phthisical,
					and one having spleen disease, of another having disease of the spleen, what is
					to hinder it from happening that where the father and mother were subject to
					this disease, certain of their offspring should be so affected also? As the
					semen comes from all parts of the body, healthy particles will come from healthy
					parts, and unhealthy from unhealthy parts. And another great proof that it is in
					nothing more divine than other diseases is, that it occurs in those who are of a
					phlegmatic constitution, but does not attack the bilious. Yet, if it were more
					divine than the others, this disease ought to befall all alike, and make no
					distinction between the bilious and phlegmatic.</p>

				<p>But in them, the brain is the cause of this affection, as it is of other very
					great diseases, and in what manner and from what cause it is formed, I will now
					plainly declare. The brain of man, as in all other animals, is double, and a
					thin membrane <hi rend="ital">(meninx)</hi>divides it through the middle, and
					therefore the pain is not always in the same part of the head; for sometimes it
					is situated on either side, and sometimes the whole is affected; and veins run
					toward it from all parts of the body, many of which are small, but two are
					thick, the one from the liver, and the other from the spleen. And it is thus
					with regard to the one from the liver: a portion of it runs downward through the
					parts on the side, near the kidneys and the psoas muscles, to the inner part of
					the thigh, and extends to the foot. It is called vena cava. The other runs
					upward by the right veins and the lungs, and divides into branches for the heart
					and the right arm. The remaining part of it rises upward across the clavicle to
					the right side of the neck, and is superficial so as to be seen; near the ear it
					is concealed, and there it divides; its thickest, largest, and most hollow part
					ends in the brain; another small vein goes to the right ear, another to the
					right eye, and another to the nostril. Such are the distributions of the hepatic
					vein. And a vein from the spleen is distributed on the left side, upward and
					downward, like that from the liver, but more slender and feeble.</p>

				<p>By these veins we draw in much spirit<hi rend="ital">(gas?)</hi>, since they are
					the spiracles of our bodies inhaling air to <pb n="p.360"/>themselves and
					distributing it to the rest of the body, and to the smaller veins, and they and
					afterwards exhale it. For the breath <hi rend="ital">(pneuma)</hi>cannot be
					stationary, but it passes upward and downward, for if stopped and intercepted,
					the part where it is stopped becomes powerless. In proof of this, when, in
					sitting or lying, the small veins are compressed, so that the breath<hi
						rend="ital">(pneuma)</hi> from the larger vein does not pass into them, the
					part is immediately seized with numbness; and it is so likewise with regard to
					the other veins.</p>

				<p>This malady, then, affects phlegmatic people, but not bilious. It begins to be
					formed while the foetus is still <hi rend="ital">in utero</hi>. For the brain,
					like the other organs, is depurated and grows before birth. If, then, in this
					purgation it be properly and moderately depurated, and neither more nor less
					than what is proper be secreted from it, the head is thus in the most healthy
					condition. If the secretion (melting) the from the brain be greater than
					natural, the person, when he grows up, will have his head diseased, and full of
					noises, and will neither be able to endure the sun nor cold. Or, if the melting
					take place from any one part, either from the eye or ear, or if a vein has
					become slender, that part will be deranged in proportion to the melting. Or,
					should depuration not take place, but it (<hi rend="ital">the secretion?</hi>)
					accumulate in the brain, it necessarily becomes phlegmatic. And such children as
					have an eruption of ulcers on the head, on the ears, and along the rest of the
					body, with copious discharges of saliva and mucus,-these, in after life, enjoy
					best health; for in this way the phlegm which ought to have been purged off in
					the womb, is discharged and cleared away, and persons so purged, for the most
					part, are not subject to attacks of this disease. But such as have had their
					skin free from eruptions, and have had no discharge of saliva or mucus, nor have
					undergone the proper purgation in the womb, these persons run the risk of being
					seized with this disease.</p>

				<p>But should the defluxion make its way to the heart, the person is seized with
					palpitation and asthma, the chest becomes diseased, and some also have curvature
					of the spine. For when a defluxion of cold phlegm takes place on the lungs and
					heart, the blood is chilled, and the veins, being violently chilled, palpitate
					in the lungs and heart, and the heart palpitates, so that <pb n="p.361"/>from
					this necessity asthma and orthopnoea supervene. For it does not receive the
					spirits (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) as much breath as he needs until the
					defluxion of phlegm be mastered, and being heated is distributed to the veins,
					then it ceases from its palpitation and difficulty of breathing, and this takes
					place as soon as it obtains an abundant supply; and this will be more slowly,
					provided the defluxion be more abundant, or if it be less, more quickly. And if
					the defluxions be more condensed, the epileptic attacks will be more frequent,
					but otherwise if it be rarer. Such are the symptoms when the defluxion is upon
					the lungs and heart; but if it be upon the bowels, the person is attacked with
					diarrhoea.</p>

				<p>And if, being shut out from all these outlets, its defluxion be determined to the
					veins I have formerly mentioned, the patient loses his speech, and chokes, and
					foam issues by the mouth, the teeth are fixed, the hands are contracted, the
					eyes distorted, he becomes insensible, and in some cases the bowels are
					evacuated. And these symptoms occur sometimes on the left side, sometimes on the
					right, and sometimes in both. The cause of everyone of these symptoms I will now
					explain. The man becomes speechless when the phlegm, suddenly descending into
					the veins, shuts out the air, and does not admit it either to the brain or to
					the vena cava, or to the ventricles, but interrupts the inspiration. For when a
					person draws in air by the mouth and nostrils, the breath (<hi rend="ital"
						>pneuma</hi>)goes first to the brain, then the greater part of it to the
					internal cavity, and part to the lungs, and part to the veins, and from them it
					is distributed to the other parts of the body along the veins; and whatever
					passes to the stomach cools, and does nothing more; and so also with regard to
					the lungs. But the air which enters the veins is of use (to the body) by
					entering the brain and its ventricles, and thus it imparts sensibility and
					motion to all the members, so that when the veins are excluded from the air by
					the phlegm and do not receive it, the man loses his speech and intellect, and
					the hands become powerless, and are contracted, the blood stopping and not being
					diffused, as it was wont; and the eyes are distorted owing to the veins being
					excluded from the air; and they palpitate; and froth from the lungs issues by
					the mouth. For when the breath (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) does not find <pb
						n="p.362"/>entrance to him, he foams and sputters like a dying person. And
					the bowels are evacuated in consequence of the violent suffocation; and the
					suffocation is produced when the liver and stomach ascend to the diaphragm, and
					the mouth of the stomach is shut up; this takes place when the breath (<hi
						rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) does not enter by the mouth, as it is wont. The
					patient kicks with his feet when the air is shut up in the lungs and cannot find
					an outlet, owing to the phlegm; and rushing by the blood upward and downward, it
					occasions convulsions and pain, and therefore he kicks with his feet. All these
					symptoms he endures when the cold phlegm passes into the warm blood, for it
					congeals and stops the blood. And if the deflexion be copious and thick, it
					immediately proves fatal to him, for by its cold it prevails over the blood and
					congeals it; or, if it be less, it in the first place obtains the mastery, and
					stops the respiration; and then in the course of time, when it is diffused along
					the veins and mixed with much warm blood, it is thus overpowered, the veins
					receive the air, and the patient recovers his senses.</p>

				<p>Of little children who are seized with this disease, the greater part die,
					provided the defluxion be copious and humid, for the veins being slender cannot
					admit the phlegm, owing to its thickness and abundance; but the blood is cooled
					and congealed, and the child immediately dies. But if the phlegm be in small
					quantity, and make a defluxion into both the veins, or to those on either side,
					the children survive, but exhibit notable marks of the disorder; for either the
					mouth is drawn aside, or an eye, the neck, or a hand, wherever a vein being
					filled with phlegm loses its tone, and is attenuated, and the part of the body
					connected with this vein is necessarily rendered weaker and defective. But for
					the most it affords relief for a longer interval; for the child is no longer
					seized with these attacks, if once it has contracted this impress of the
					disease, in consequence of which the other veins are necessarily affected, and
					to a certain degree attenuated, so as just to admit the air, but no longer to
					permit the influx of phlegm. However, the parts are proportionally enfeebled
					whenever the veins are in an unhealthy state. When in striplings the defluxion
					is small and to the right side, they recover without leaving any marks of the
					disease, but there <pb n="p.363"/>is danger of its becoming habitual, and even
					increasing if not treated by suitable remedies. Thus, or very nearly so, is the
					case when it attacks children.</p>

				<p>To persons of a more advanced age, it neither proves fatal, nor produces
					distortions. For their veins are (<hi rend="ital">large?</hi>) and filled with
					hot blood; and therefore the phlegm can neither prevail nor cool the blood, so
					as to coagulate it, but it is quickly overpowered and mixed with the blood, and
					thus the veins receive the air, and sensibility remains; and, owing to their
					strength, the aforesaid symptoms are less likely to seize them. But when this
					disease attacks very old people, it therefore proves fatal, or induces
					paraplegia, because the veins are empty, and the blood scanty, thin, and watery.
					When, therefore, the defluxion is copious, and the season winter, it proves
					fatal; for it chokes up the exhalents, and coagulates the blood if the defluxion
					be to both sides; but if to either, it merely induces paraplegia. For the blood
					being thin, cold, and scanty, cannot prevail over the but being itself
					overpowered, it is coagulated, so that those parts in which the blood is
					corrupted, lose their strength.</p>

				<p>The flux is to the right rather than to the left because the veins there are more
					capacious and numerous than on the left side, for on the one side they spring
					from the liver, and on the other from the spleen. The defluxion and melting down
					take place most especially in the case of children in whom the head is heated
					either by the sun or by fire, or if the brain suddenly contract a rigor, and
					then the phlegm is excreted. For it is melted down by the heat and diffusion of
					the but it is excreted by the congealing and contracting of it, and thus a
					defluxion takes place. And in some this is the cause of the disease, and in
					others, when the south wind quickly succeeds to northern breezes, it suddenly
					unbinds and relaxes the brain, which is contracted and weak, so that there is an
					inundation of phlegm, and thus the defluxion takes place. The defluxion also
					takes place in consequence of fear, from any hidden cause, if we are the at any
					person's calling aloud, or while crying, when one cannot quickly recover one's
					breath, such as often happens to children. When any of these things occur, the
					body immediately shivers, <pb n="p.364"/>the person becoming speechless cannot
					draw his breath, but the breath (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) stops, the brain
					is contracted, the blood stands still, and thus the excretion and defluxion of
					the phlegm take place. In children, these are the causes of the attack at first.
					But to old persons winter is most inimical. For when the head and brain have
					been heated at a great fire, and then the person is brought into cold and has a
					rigor, or when from cold he comes into warmth, and sits at the fire, he is apt
					to suffer in the same way, and thus he is seized in the manner described above.
					And there is much danger of the same thing occurring, if his head be exposed to
					the sun, but less so in summer, as the changes are not sudden. When a person has
					passed the twentieth year of his life, this disease is not apt to seize him,
					unless it has become habitual from childhood, or at least this is rarely or
					never the case. For the veins are filled with blood, and the brain consistent
					and firm, so that it does not run down into the veins, or if it do, it does not
					master the blood, which is copious and hot.</p>

				<p>But when it has gained strength from one's childhood, and become habitual, such a
					person usually suffers attacks, and is seized with them in changes of the winds,
					especially in south winds, and it is difficult of removal. For the brain becomes
					more humid than natural, and is inundated with phlegm, so that the defluxions
					become more frequent, and the phlegm can no longer be the nor the brain be dried
					up, but it becomes wet and humid. This you may ascertain in particular, from
					beasts of the flock which are seized with this disease, and more especially
					goats, for they are most frequently attacked with it. If you will cut open the
					head, you will find the brain humid, full of sweat, and having a bad smell. And
					in this way truly you may see that it is not a god that injures the body, but
					disease. And so it is with man. For when the disease has prevailed for a length
					of time, it is no longer curable, as the brain is corroded by the phlegm, and
					melted, and what is melted down becomes water, and surrounds the brain
					externally, and overflows it; wherefore they are more frequently and readily
					seized with the disease. And therefore the disease is protracted, because the
					influx is thin, owing to its quantity, and is immediately overpowered by the
					blood and heated all <pb n="p.365"/>through.</p>

				<p>But such persons as are habituated to the disease know beforehand when they are
					about to be seized and flee from men; if their own house be at hand, they run
					home, but if not, to a deserted place, where as few persons as possible will see
					them falling, and they immediately cover themselves up. This they do from shame
					of the affection, and not from fear of the divinity, as many suppose. And little
					children at first fall down wherever they may happen to be, from inexperience.
					But when they have been often seized, and feel its approach beforehand, they
					flee to their mothers, or to any other person they are acquainted with, from
					terror and dread of the affection, for being still infants they do not know yet
					what it is to be ashamed.</p>

				<p>Therefore, they are attacked during changes of the winds, and especially south
					winds, then also with north winds, and afterwards also with the others. These
					are the strongest winds, and the most opposed to one another, both as to
					direction and power. For, the north wind condenses the air, and separates from
					it whatever is muddy and nebulous, and renders it clearer and brighter, and so
					in like manner also, all the winds which arise from the sea and other waters;
					for they extract the humidity and nebulosity from all objects, and from men
					themselves, and therefore it (the north wind) is the most wholesome of the
					winds. But the effects of the south are the very reverse. For in the first place
					it begins by melting and diffusing the condensed air, and therefore it does not
					blow strong at first, but is gentle at the commencement, because it is not able
					at once to overcome the and compacted air, which yet in a while it dissolves. It
					produces the same effects upon the land, the sea, the fountains, the wells, and
					on every production which contains humidity, and this, there is in all things,
					some more, some less. For all these feel the effects of this wind, and from
					clear they become cloudy, from cold, hot; from dry, moist; and whatever ear then
					vessels are placed upon the ground, filled with wine or any other fluid, are
					affected with the south wind, and undergo a change. And the a change. And the
					sun, and the moon, it renders blunter appearance than they naturally are. When,
					then, it possesses such powers over things so great and strong, and the <pb
						n="p.366"/>body is made to feel and undergo changes in the changes of the
					winds, it necessarily follows that the brain should be disolved and overpowered
					with moisture, and that the veins should become more relaxed by the south winds,
					and that by the north the healthiest portion of the brain should become
					contracted, while the most morbid and humid is secreted, and overflows
					externally, and that catarrhs should thus take place in the changes of these
					winds. Thus is this disease formed and prevails from those things which enter
					into and go out of the body, and it is not more difficult to understand or to
					cure than the others, neither is it more divine than other diseases.</p>

				<p>And men ought to know that from nothing else but (<hi rend="ital">from the
						brain</hi>) come joys, delights, laughter and sports, and sorrows, griefs,
					despondency, and lamentations. And by this, in an especial manner, we acquire
					wisdom and knowledge, and see and hear, and know what are foul and what are
					fair, what are bad and what are good, what are sweet, and what unsavory; some we
					discriminate by habit, and some we perceive by their utility. By this we
					distinguish objects of relish and disrelish, according to the seasons; and the
					same things do not always please us. And by the same organ we become mad and
					delirious, and fears and terrors assail us, some by night, and some by day, and
					dreams and untimely wanderings, and cares that are not suitable, and ignorance
					of present circumstances, desuetude, and unskilfulness. All these things we
					endure from the brain, when it is not healthy, but is more hot, more cold, more
					moist, or more dry than natural, or when it suffers any other preternatural and
					unusual affection. And we become mad from humidity (<hi rend="ital">of the
						brain</hi>). For when it is more moist than natural, it is necessarily put
					into motion, and the affection being moved, neither the sight nor hearing can be
					at rest, and the tongue speaks in accordance with the sight and hearing.</p>

				<p>As long as the brain is at rest, the man enjoys his reason, but the depravement
					of the brain arises from phlegm and bile, either of which you may recognize in
					this manner: Those who are mad from phlegm are quiet, and do not cry out nor
					make a noise; but those from bile are vociferous, malignant, and will not be
					quiet, but are always doing something improper. If the <pb n="p.367"/>madness be
					constant, these are the causes thereof. But if terrors and fears assail, they
					are connected with derangement of the brain, and derangement is owing to its
					being heated. And it is heated by bile when it is determined to the brain along
					the bloodvessels running from the trunk; and fear is present until it returns
					again to the veins and trunk, when it ceases. He is grieved and troubled when
					the brain is unseasonably cooled and contracted beyond its wont. This it suffers
					from phlegm, and from the same affection the patient becomes oblivious. He calls
					out and screams at night when the brain is suddenly heated. The bilious endure
					this. But the phlegmatic are not heated, except when much blood goes to the
					brain, and creates an ebullition. Much blood passes along the aforesaid veins.
					But when the man happens to see a frightful dream and is in fear as if awake,
					then his face is in a greater glow, and the eyes are red when the patient is in
					fear. And the understanding meditates doing some mischief, and thus it is
					affected in sleep. But if, when awakened, he returns to himself, and the blood
					is again distributed along the veins, it ceases.</p>

				<p>In these ways I am of the opinion that the brain exercises the greatest power in
					the man. This is the interpreter to us of those things which emanate from the
					air, when it (<hi rend="ital">the brain</hi>) happens to be in a sound state.
					But the air supplies sense to it. And the eyes, the ears, the tongue and the
					feet, administer such things as the brain cogitates. For in as much as it is
					supplied with air, does it impart sense to the body. It is the brain which is
					the messenger to the understanding. For when the man draws the breath (<hi
						rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) into himself, it passes first to the brain, and
					thus the air is distributed to the rest of the body, leaving in the brain its
					acme, and whatever has sense and understanding. For if it passed first to the
					body and last to the brain, then having left in the flesh and veins the
					judgment, when it reached the brain it would be hot, and not at all pure, but
					mixed with the humidity from flesh and blood, so as to be no longer pure.</p>

				<p>Wherefore, I say, that it is the brain which interprets the understanding. But
					the diaphragm has obtained its name (<hi rend="ital">frenes</hi>) from accident
					and usage, and not from reality or nature, for I know no power which it
					possesses, either as to <pb n="p.368"/>sense or understanding, except that when
					the man is affected with unexpected joy or sorrow, it throbs and produces
					palpitations, owing to its thinness, and as having no belly to receive anything
					good or bad that may present themselves to it, but it is thrown into commotion
					by both these, from its natural weakness. It then perceives beforehand none of
					those things which occur in the body, but has received its name vaguely and
					without any proper reason, like the parts about the heart, which are called
					auricles, but which contribute nothing towards hearing. Some say that we think
					with the heart, and that this is the part which is grieved, and experiences
					care. But it is not so; only it contracts like the diaphragm, and still more so
					for the same causes. For veins from all parts of the body run to it, and it has
					valves, so as to as to perceive if any pain or pleasurable emotion befall the
					man. For when grieved the body necessarily shudders, and is contracted, and from
					excessive joy it is affected in like manner. Wherefore the heart and the
					diaphragm are particularly sensitive, they have nothing to do, however, with the
					operations of the understanding, but of all but of all these the brain is the
					cause. Since, then, the brain, as being the primary seat of sense and of the
					spirits, perceives whatever occurs in the body, if any change more powerful than
					usual take place in the air, owing to the seasons, the brain becomes changed by
					the state of the air. For, on this account, the brain first perceives, because,
					I say, all the most acute, most powerful, and most deadly diseases, and those
					which are most difficult to be understood by the inexperienced, fall upon the
					brain.</p>

				<p>And the disease called the Sacred arises from causes as the others, namely, those
					things which enter and quit the body, such as cold, the sun, and the winds,
					which are ever changing and are never at rest. And these things are divine, so
					that there is no necessity for making a distinction, and holding this disease to
					be more divine than the others, but all are divine, and all human. And each has
					its own peculiar nature and power, and none is of an ambiguous nature, or
					irremediable. And the most of them are curable by the same means as those by
					which any other thing is food to one, and injurious to another. Thus, then, the
					physician should under-<pb n="p.369"/>stand and distinguish the season of each,
					so that at one time he may attend to the nourishment and increase, and at
					another to abstraction and diminution. And in this disease as in all others, he
					must strive not to feed the disease, but endeavor to wear it out by
					administering whatever is most opposed to each disease, and not that which
					favors and is allied to it. For by that which is allied to it, it gains vigor
					and increase, but it wears out and disappears under the use of that which is
					opposed to it. But whoever is acquainted with such a change in men, and can
					render a man humid and dry, hot and cold by regimen, could also cure this
					disease, if he recognizes the proper season for administering his remedies,
					without minding purifications, spells, and all other illiberal practices of a
					like kind.<pb n="p.370"/></p>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
