<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Parliament of the Gods</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor>Austin Morris Harmon, 1878-1950</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>OCRd, tagged and added initial corrections to  the text</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg001.1st1K-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:1lg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1936</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202111">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<head>The Parliament of the Gods<note><p>This brief comic dialogue records the proceedings of an
assembly on Olympus in which steps are taken to purge the
celestial roster of aliens and interlopers. It has been called a
sequel to Zeus Rants because in that dialogue (§ 42: II, 154)
the caustic remarks of the infidel Damis about the odd gods
worshipped in various parts of the world force Zeus to admit
that Momus had been right in expecting all this to cause trouble
one day, and to promise that he would try to set everything
straight. It is to be noted, however, that in the Parliament of
the Gods there is not only no allusion, direct or indirect, to
Zeus Rants, but no suggestion that this purgation of the
body politic has any relation to hostile criticism on earth.
The connection, therefore, is not remarkably close. It is too
bad that Lucian has left us no record of the subsequent
proceedings before the committee on credentials. An account
of ae appearance of Mithras would have been particularly
welcome.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

<label>ZEUS</label>
No more murmuring, Gods, or gathering in corners
and whispering in each other’s ears because you take
it hard that many share our table who are not worthy.
Now that a public meeting upon this question has
been authorised, let each declare his opinion openly
and bring his charges. Hermes, make the proclamation required by law.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Hear ye! Silence! Among the gods of full standing, entitled to speak, who desires to do so? The
question concerns resident aliens and foreigners.
</p>
<p><label>MOMUS</label>
I, Momus here, Zeus, if you would let me speak.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
The proclamation itself gives permission, so that
you will have no need of mine,


<pb n="v.5.p.421"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
<label>MOMUS</label>
Well then, I say that some of us behave shockingly ;
it is not enough for them that they themselves have
become gods instead of men, but unless they can
make their very attendants and servants as good as
we are, they do not think they have done anything
important or enterprising. And I beg you, Zeus, to
let me speak frankly, for I could not do otherwise.
Everybody knows how free of speech I am, and
disinclined to hush up anything at all that is ill done.
I criticize everybody and express my views openly,
without either fearing anyone or concealing my
opinion out of respect, so that most people think
me vexatious and meddling by nature; they call
me a regular public prosecutor. However, inasmuch
as it is according to law, and the proclamation has
been made, and you, Zeus, allow me to speak with
complete liberty, I shall do so, without anyreservations.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
Many, I say, not content that they themselves
take part in the same assemblies as we and feast
with us on equal terms, and that too when they are
half mortal, havelugged up into heaven their own
servants and boon-companions and have fraudulently
registered them, so that now they receive largesses
and share in sacrifices on an equal footing without
even having paid us the tax of resident aliens.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Let us have no riddles, Momus ; speak in plain and
explicit language, and supply the name, too. Asit is,
you have flung your statement into the midst of us

<pb n="v.5.p.423"/>

all, so that many are making guesses and applying
your remarks now to one and now to another. Being
an exponent of frankness, you must not stick at saying
anything.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
<label>MOMUS</label>
It is splendid, Zeus, that you actually urge me to
frankness; that is a truly royal, high-souled action.
Therefore I shall give the name. It is this peerless
Dionysus, who is half human; in fact, on his mother’s
side he is not even Greek, but the grandson of a
Syrophoenician trader named Cadmus. Inasmuch
as he has been honoured with immortality, I say
nothing of the man himself—either of his hood or of
his drunkenness or of his gait; for you all, I think,
see that he is womanish and unmanly in his character,
half crazy, with strong drink on his breath from the
beginning of the day. But he has foisted upon us a
whole clan; he presents himself at the head of his
rout, and has made gods out of Pan and Silenus and
the Satyrs, regular farm-hands and goat-herds,
most of them—capering fellows with queer shapes.
One of them has horns and looks like a goat from the
waist down, and wears a long beard, so that he is
not much different from a goat. Another is a baldpated gaffer with a flat nose who usually rides on a
donkey. He is a Lydian. The Satyrs are prickeared, and they too are bald, with horns like those
that bud on new-born kids; they are Phrygians, and
they all have tails. D’ye see what sort of gods he is
making for us, the bounder?

<pb n="v.5.p.425"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
And then we wonder that men despise us when
they see such laughable and portentous deities! I
omit to mention that he has also brought up two
women, one his sweetheart Ariadne, whose very
head-band he has admitted into the starry choir, and
the other the daughter of Icarius the farmer!<note n="v.5.p.425.n.1"><p>Erigone; her dog Maera guided her to the spot where Icarius lay buried. He had been slain by drunken shepherds to whom he had given wine that Dionysus Thad taught him how to make. After her suicide Erigone became Virgo, and Maera, it would seem from Lucian’s xuvidiov, Procyon (Canis Minor). No doubt it is Momus’ indignation about the dog that accounts for his failure to mention Icarius’ introduction into the heavens as Bootes. </p></note> And
what is most ridiculous of all, Gods, even Erigone’s
dog—that too he has brought up, so that the little
maid shall not be distressed if she cannot have in
heaven her pet, darling doggie! Does not all
this look to you like insolence, impudence, and
mockery? But let me tell you about others.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
<label>ZEUS</label>
Say nothing, Momus, about either Asclepius or
Heracles, for I see where you are heading in your
speech. As far as they are concerned, one of them
is a doctor who cures people of their illnesses and is
“as good as a host in himself,”<note n="v.5.p.425.n.2"><p>Iliad, XI, 514, alluding to Machaon. </p></note> whilst Heracles,
though my own son, purchased his immortality at
the cost of many labours; so do not denounce them.
</p>
<p><label>MOMUS</label>
I shall hold my tongue, Zeus, for your sake, although
I have plenty to say. Indeed, if there were nothing
else, they still carry the marks of fire!<note n="v.5.p.425.n.3"><p>Heracles cremated himself, and Asclepius was struck by lightning. Cf. p. 6, n. 1. </p></note> And if it
were permissible to employ free speech about yourself, I should have plenty to say.





<pb n="v.5.p.427"/>

<label>ZEUS</label>
I assure you, about me it is quite permissible.
But you are not prosecuting me as an alien, are you?
</p>
<p><label>MOMUS</label>
Well, in Crete not only that may be heard, but
they tell another story about you and show people
atomb. However, I put no faith either in them or
in the Achaeans of Aegium, who assert that you are a
changeling.<note n="v.5.p.427.n.1"><p>Zeus was not only born in Crete, but buried there, in more than one place. His critics in Lucian several times refer to this fact (Timon, 4; Zeus Rants, 45). Lucian very likely means the place that was pointed out to R. Pashley in 1834 as the tomb of Zeus, on Mt. Juktas; see A. J. Cook’s Zeus, I, 157-163. The Achaean version of the birth of Zeus which made him out a changeling is not mentioned elsewhere, but plenty of places gave him other fathers than Cronus, which amounts to the same thing. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
But I do intend to speak of one thing
that in my opinion ought by all means to be censured.</p>

<p>
It was you, Zeus, who began these illegalities and
caused the corruption of our body politic by cohabiting with mortal women and going down to visit them,
now in one form, now in another. It has gone so far
that we are afraid that someone may make a victim
of you if he catches you when you are a bull, or that
some goldsmith may work you up when you are gold,
and instead of Zeus we may have you turning up as a
necklace or a bracelet or an earring. However that
may be, you have filled heaven with these—demigods! I do not care to put it otherwise. And it is a
very ridiculous state of things when one suddenly
hears that Heracles has been appointed a god, but
Eurystheus, who used to order him about, is dead;
and that the temple of Heracles, who was a slave,
and the tomb of Eurystheus, his master, stand side
by side; and again, that in Thebes Dionysus is a



<pb n="v.5.p.429"/>

god, but his cousins Pentheus, Actaeon, and Learchus
were of all mankind the most ill-fated.<note n="v.5.p.429.n.1"><p>All three were own cousins of Dionysus, being sons of other daughters of Cadmus; Pentheus of Agave, Actaeon of Autonoe, and Learchus of Ino. Learchus was killed by his father Athamas. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
From the moment that you, Zeus, once opened our
doors to such as they and turned your attention to
mortal women, everyone else has copied you, and
not the male sex alone but—what is most unseemly—even the goddesses. Who does not know about
Anchises, Tithonus, Endymion, Iasion, and the rest of
them? So I think I shall omit those incidents, for
it would take too long if I were to pass censure on
them.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Say nothing about Ganymede, Momus, for I
shall be angry if you vex the little lad by disparaging
his birth.
</p>
<p><label>MOMUS</label>
Then am I not to speak of the eagle, either, and
say that he too is in heaven, where he sits upon your
royal sceptre and all but nests on your head, passing
for a god?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

Or must I omit him also, for the sake of
Ganymede?
But Attis at all events, Zeus, and Corybas<note n="v.5.p.429.n.2"><p>In Icaromenippus, 27 (II, 312) a similar list of “alien gods of doubtful status’’ is given, in which, besides Pan, Attis, and Sabazius, we find the Corybantes. For Lucian’s conception of them, see the note on The Dance, 8 (p. 220, n. 2). Here only one Corybas is remarked in the sacred precincts. Does Lucian think of him as that one who was slain by the others (Clem. Alex., Protr., II, 19), and so as the central figure of the cult ? </p></note> and
Sabazius<note n="v.5.p.429.n.3"><p>Sabazius was the centre of a wide-spread and important mystery-religion, which merged with that of Dionysus (Zagreus). He is frequently represented sitting in the palm of a great hand opened in a gesture like that of benediction (thumb and first two dingo extended), see Cook’s Zeus, I, 390, Fig. 296. Multitudes of attributes always surround him, and the bull, the ram, and the snake figured in his cult. On initiation, a snake was through the clothing of the initiate, and “snake through the bosom” is said to have been the pass-word (Clem. Alex., Protr., III, 15, 1). </p></note>—how did they get trundled in upon us?





<pb n="v.5.p.431"/>

Or Mithras yonder, the Mede, with his caftan and
his cap, who does not even speak Greek, so that he
cannot even understand if one drinks his health?
The result is that the Scythians—the Getae among
them—seeing all this have told us to go hang, and
now confer immortality on their own account and
elect as gods whomsoever they will, in the selfsame
way that Zamolxis, a slave, obtained fraudulent
admission to the roster, getting by with it somehow
or other.<note n="v.5.p.431.n.1"><p>Lucian recognises that the Getae were not Scythians but Thracians in Icaromenippus, 16, and that Zamolxis belongs to the Thracians in True Story, II, 17, and Zeus Rants, 44. On the other hand, the god is styled Scythian in The Scythian, 1 and 4, and in the passage before us, though he is ascribed to the Getae, they are represented as Scythian. Perhaps these two pieces are earlier than the others, and earlier than Tozaris, where Zamolxis is not mentioned. Zamolxis obtained his ‘fraudulent registration” by hiding in a cave and not appearing for four years, according to Herodotus (IV, 95). Strabo (VII, 5), who says that he was counsellor to the king, who connived at the fraud, adds that he was followed by a continuous succession of such gods; and to these Lucian must be alluding when he speaks of their electing gods. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
All that, however, is as nothing, Gods.—You
there, you dog-faced, linen-vested Egyptian, who
are you, my fine fellow, and how do you make out
that you are a god, with that bark of yours?<note n="v.5.p.431.n.2"><p>Anubis. </p></note> And
with what idea does this spotted bull of Memphis<note n="v.5.p.431.n.3"><p>Apis. </p></note>
receive homage and give oracles and have prophets?
I take shame to mention ibises and monkeys and
billy-goats and other creatures far more ludicrous
that somehow or other have been smuggled out of
Egypt into heaven. How can you endure it, Gods,
to see them worshipped as much as you, or even
more? And you, Zeus, how can you put up with
it when they grow ram’s horns upon you?<note n="v.5.p.431.n.4"><p>Zeus Ammon. </p></note>






<pb n="v.5.p.433"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
<label>ZEUS</label>
All these points that you mention about the Egyptians are in truth unseemly. Nevertheless, Momus,
most of them are matters of symbolism and one who
is not an adept in the mysteries really must not
laugh at them.
</p>
<p><label>MOMUS</label>
A lot we need mysteries, Zeus, to know that gods
are gods, and dogheads are dogheads!
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Never mind, I say, about the Egyptians. Some
other time we shall discuss their case at leisure.
Go on and name the others.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
<label>MOMUS</label>
Trophonius, Zeus, and (what sticks in my gorge
beyond everything) Amphilochus, who, though the
son of an outcast and matricide,<note n="v.5.p.433.n.1"><p>Alcmaeon, son of Amphiaraus; he slew his mother Eriphyle, fled from Argos in frenzy, and never returned. </p></note> gives prophecies,
the miscreant, in Cilicia, telling lies most of the time
and playing charlatan for the sake of his two obols.
That is why you, Apollo, are no longer in favour;
at present, oracles are delivered by every stone and
every altar that is drenched with oil and has garlands
and can provide itself with a charlatan—of whom
there are plenty. Already the statue of Polydamas
the athlete heals those who have fevers in Olympia,


<pb n="v.5.p.435"/>

and the statue of Theagenes does likewise in Thasos ;<note n="v.5.p.435.n.1"><p>Polydamas, a gigantic pancratiast, was said to have killed lions with his bare hands and stopped chariots at full speed by laying hold of them. Pausanias (VI, 5, 1) mentions his statue at Olympia, made by Lysippus, but does not speak of its healing the sick. But about the Thasian statue of Theagenes, who won 1400 crowns as boxer, cratiast, and runner, and was reputed to be a son of Heracles, we hear not only from Pausanias (VI, 11, 6-9) but from Oenomaus (in Euseb., Praep. Evang., V, 34, 6-9) and Dio Chrysostom in his Rhodiaeus (XXXI, 95-97). After his death, when an enemy whipped the statue at night, it fell on him and killed him; so it was tried for murder, and flung into the sea. Harvests then failed, and after the reason had been elicited from Delphi, the statue, miraculously recovered by fishermen in their net, was set up where it had stood before, and sacrifices were thereafter offered before it “as to a god.” Pausanias adds that he knows that Theagenes had many other statues both in Greece and in “barbarian” parts, and that he healed sicknesses and received honours from the natives of those places. A very similar tale about the statue of another Olympic victor, the Locrian Euthycles, previously known only from Oenomaus (ibid., 10-11), can now be traced to the Iambi of Callimachus (Diegeseis, ed. Vitelli-Norsa, i, 37-ii, 8). And in Lucian’s Lover of Lies, 18-20 (III, 346, ff.) there is an amusing account of activities imputed to the statue of Pellichus, a Corinthian general. </p></note>
they sacrifice to Hector in Troy and to Protesilaus
on the opposite shore, in the Chersonese. So, ever
since we became so numerous, perjury and sacrilege
have been increasing, and in general they have
despised us—quite rightly.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
Let this suffice on the subject of those who are
base-born and fraudulently registered. But there
are many outlandish names that have come to my
ears, of beings not to be found among us and
unable to exist at all as realities; and over these
too, Zeus, I make very merry. Where is that famous
Virtue, and Nature, and Destiny, and Chance? They
are unsubstantial, empty appellations, excogitated by
those dolts, the philosophers. All the same, artificial as they are, they have so imposed upon the
witless that nobody is willing to do as much as
sacrifice to us, knowing that though he offer ten
thousand hecatombs, nevertheless “Chance” will
effect what is “fated” and what has been “spun”
for every man from the beginning. So I should like



<pb n="v.5.p.437"/>

to ask you, Zeus, if you have anywhere seen either
Virtue or Nature or Destiny. I know that you too
are always hearing of them in the discussions of the
philosophers, unless you are deaf, so as not to be able
to hear them screaming.</p>

<p>
I still have plenty to say, but I will bring my speech
to an end, for I notice that many are annoyed with
me for my remarks, and are hissing, particularly
those who have been touched to the quick by my
frankness.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
To conclude, then, with your consent,
Zeus, I shall read a motion on this subject which
has already been committed to writing.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Read it, for not all your criticisms were unreasonable, and we must put a stop to most of this, so that
it may not increase.
Momus (reads)
“With the blessing of Heaven! In a regular
session of the assembly, held on the seventh of the
month, Zeus presiding, Poseidon first vice-president,
Apollo second vice-president, Momus, son of Night,
recorder, the following resolution was proposed by
Sleep :<note n="v.5.p.437.n.1"><p>Obtaining from fourth-century Athens a formula for decrees of the senate and people, Olympus has filled in the blanks as best it could. At Athens, the name of a ph le, or tribe, would go in the first blank of the preamble, as “exercising the prytany’’; but Ob ympus has no tribes, and anyhow Zeus should come first. So his name is set down there. The next two offices might now be crossed off; for as Zeus presides at assemblies, there is no function left for the proedros, or chairman of the board of presidents, and the office of epistatés, or chairman of the prytanies, is already filled, since Zeus can hardly be “exercising the prytany” in any other capacity. However, there are the blanks !—and Poseidon, second in the Olympian hierarchy, will do all the better for proedros if it is a sinecure, while the duties actually performed by Apollo as Zeus’ right-hand man and more or less of a factotum, are not too dissimilar to those of an Athenian epistatés in the fourth century B.o. These problems solved, the remaining blanks were easy to fill. </p></note>



<pb n="v.5.p.439"/>

“WHEREAS many aliens, not only Greeks but barbarians, in nowise worthy of admission to our body
politic, by obtaining fraudulent registration in one
way or another and coming to be accounted gods
have so filled heaven that our festal board is packed
with a noisy rabble of polyglot flotsam; and
WHEREas the ambrosia and the nectar have run low,
so that a cup now costs a mina, on account of the
vast number of drinkers; and wHereas in their
boorishness they have thrust aside the ancient and
genuine gods, have claimed precedence for themselves, contrary to all the institutions of our fathers,
and want to be pre-eminently honoured on earth:
therefore
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
“BE IT RESOLVED by the senate and the commons
that a meeting of the assembly be convoked on
Olympus at the time of the winter solstice; that
seven gods of full standing be chosen as deputies, three
to be from the old senate of the time of Cronus, and
four from the Twelve, including Zeus; that these
deputies before convening take the regular oath,
invoking the Styx; that Hermes by proclamation
assemble all who claim to belong to our body; that
these present themselves with witnesses prepared to
take oath, and with birth-certificates ; that they then
appear individually, and the deputies after investigation of each case either declare them to be gods
or send them down to their sepulchres and the
graves of their ancestors; and that if any one of
those who shall fail of approval and shall have
been expelled once for all by the deputies be
caught setting foot in heaven, he be thrown into
Tartarus ;
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
“AND BE IT FURTHER RESOLVED that each ply

<pb n="v.5.p.441"/>

his own trade; that Athena shall not heal the
sick or Asclepius give oracles or Apollo combine in
himself so many activities; he shall select one and
be either seer or singer or physician;
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
that the
philosophers be warned not to make up empty names
or talk nonsense about matters of which they know
nothing;
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>
that in the case of those who already have
been vouchsafed temples or sacrifices, their images be
pulled down and those of Zeus or Hera or Apollo or
one of the others be substituted; but the city shall
raise a funeral-mound for them and set a gravestone
upon it instead of an altar; that if anyone shall fail
to comply with this proclamation and shall be unwilling to appear before the deputies, judgement by
default shall be rendered against him.”
There you have the resolution.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg050.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
<label>ZEUS</label>
It is most equitable, Momus ; so let everyone who is
in favour of the resolution hold up his hand—but
no! I declare it carried, as those who will not vote
for it will be the majority, I know. Well, you may
go now; but when Hermes makes the proclamation,
present yourselves, and let each of you bring unmistakable means of identification and clear proofs—
his father’s name and his mother’s, why and how he
became a god, and his tribe and clan. For if anyone
shall fail to put all this in evidence, it will make no
difference to the deputies that he has a huge temple
on earth and that men believe him to be a god.


<pb n="v.5.p.445"/>
</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>
