<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>In Defense of Mantitheus from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="Intro" unit="part"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>If I were not conscious, gentlemen of the Council, that my accusers are
        seeking every possible means of injuring me, I should feel most grateful to them for this
        accusation; since I consider that the victims of unjust slander have the greatest service
        rendered to them by anyone who will compel them to undergo an examination of the record of
        their lives. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For I have so strong a confidence in myself
        that, if there is anyone who is inclined to dislike me, I hope that when he has heard me
        speak of my conduct in the past he will change his mind, and will think much better of me in
        the future. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Now, gentlemen, I make no claim to special
        merit, if I merely make plain to you that I am a supporter of the existing constitution and
        have been compelled to take my own share in your dangers: but if I am found to have lived,
        in all other respects, a regular life, quite contrary to the opinion and statements of my
        enemies, I request you to pass me through and to think the worse of these persons. I will
        begin by showing that I did not serve in the cavalry or reside here under the Thirty, and
        that I had no hand in the government of that time.<milestone n="Narr" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Our father, before the
        disaster at the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>,<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">At <placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>, 405 B.C.</note> had
        sent us abroad to live at the court of Satyrus, on the <placeName key="tgn,7016619"
          >Pontus</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">At <placeName key="tgn,7012009"
            >Panticapaeum</placeName> in the east corner of the Tauric Chersonese (<placeName
            key="tgn,1003381">Crimea</placeName>), capital of the Kingdom of Bosphorus, which
          exported corn to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> We were not
        residing in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> either when the walls were
        being demolished or when the constitution was being changed.<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">In the spring of <date value="-404">404</date> B.C.</note> We came here five
        days before the people at <placeName key="perseus,Phyle">Phyle</placeName> returned to the
          Peiraeus.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In May, <date value="-403">403</date>
          B.C.</note>
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Surely it was not to be expected that, having arrived at
        such a moment, we should want to share in dangers that concerned others; while obviously the
        Thirty were in no mind to share the government with men who were residing abroad and were
        guilt of no crime: they were rather disfranchising even the men who had helped them to
        overthrow the democracy. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>Moreover, to refer to the register
        for those who served in the cavalry is puerile: for it does not include many of those who
        admit that they served, while some who were absent abroad are on the list. But the strongest
        proof lies in the fact that, after you had returned, you voted that the tribal officers
        should make out a list of those who had served in the cavalry, so that you might recover the
          allowances<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Granted by the State for the provision of
          equipment. The argument is that this return is more satisfactory evidence for ascertaining
          who served and who did not.</note> from them. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Well,
        nobody will be able to show that I was either put on the list by the tribal officers or
        reported to the Revenue Commission or made to refund an allowance: yet it is within the
        knowledge of all that the tribal officers were under the necessity, if they failed to show
        who had the allowances, of bearing the loss themselves. Hence you would be far more
        justified in relying on these lists than on the register: for anyone who wished could easily
        have his name erased from the latter; but in the former the tribal officers were obliged to
        record those who had served. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Besides, gentlemen if I had
        served, I should not deny it as though I had done something monstrous: I should merely
        claim, after showing that no citizen had suffered injury by my act, to pass the scrutiny.
        And I see that you also take this view, and that many of those who served then in the
        cavalry are on the Council, while many others have been elected generals and brigadiers. You
        must therefore conclude that my only reason for making this defense is that they have dared
        thus openly to attack me with a falsehood. Mount the dais, please and bear witness.<quote
          type="Testimony"><title>Testimony</title></quote><milestone n="Proof" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, as regards the charge
        itself, I do not see what more there is to say. But it seems to me, gentlemen, that although
        in other trials one ought to confine one's defence to the actual points of the accusation,
        in the case of scrutinies one has a right to render an account of one's whole life. I
        request you, therefore, to give me a favorable hearing: I will make my defence as briefly as
        I can. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In the first place,
        although but little property had been bequeathed to me, owing to the disasters that had
        befallen both my father and the city, I bestowed two sisters in marriage with a dowry of
        thirty minae apiece; to my brother I allowed such a portion as made him acknowledge that he
        had got a larger share of our patrimony than I had; and towards everyone else my behavior
        has been such that never to this day has a single person shown any grievance against me.
          <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>So much for the tenor of my private life: with regard to
        public matters, I hold that the strongest proof I can give of my decorous conduct is the
        fact that all the younger set who are found to take their diversion in dice or drink or the
        like dissipations are, as you will observe, at feud with me, and are most prolific in lying
        tales about me. It is obvious, surely, that if we were at one in our desires they would not
        regard me with such feelings. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>And moreover, gentlemen,
        nobody will be able to prove that I have ever been cited in a disgraceful private suit, or
        in public proceedings or in a special impeachment; yet you see others frequently involved in
        such trials. Again, as regards campaigns and dangers in face of the enemy, observe how I
        discharge my duty to the State. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>First of all, when you
        made your alliance with the Boeotians, and we had to go to the relief of Haliartus,<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">See <bibl n="Lys. 14">Lys. 14</bibl>, Introduction, p.
          334.</note> I had been enrolled by Orthobulus for service in the cavalry: I saw that it
        was everyoneÕs opinion that, whereas the cavalry were assured of safety, the infantry would
        have to face danger; so, while others mounted on horseback illegally, without having passed
        the scrutiny, I went up to Orthobulus and told him to strike me off the roll, as I thought
        it shameful, while the majority were to face danger, to take the field with precaution for
        my own security. Come forward, please, Orthobulus.<quote type="Testimony"
            ><title>Testimony</title></quote>
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, when the townsmen had
        assembled together before their setting out, as I knew that some among them, though true and
        ardent patriots, lacked means for expenses of service, I said that the well-to-do ought to
        provide what was necessary for those in needy circumstances. Not only did I recommend this
        to the others, but I myself gave thirty drachmae each to two men; not as being a person of
        great possessions, but to set a good example to the others. Come forward, please.<quote
          type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then after that, gentlemen,
        there was the expedition to <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName><note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><date value="-394">394</date> B.C.</note>; and everyone knew
        beforehand that it must be a dangerous affair. Some were trying to shirk their duty, but I
        contrived to have myself posted in the front rank for our battle with the enemy. Our tribe
        had the worst fortune, and suffered the heaviest losses in the ranks: I retired from the
        field later than the fine fellow of Steiria<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Probably
          Thrasybulus: Steiria was a township on the east coast of <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
            >Attica</placeName>.</note> who has been reproaching everybody with cowardice.
          <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>Not many days after this event some strong posts in
          <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> had been occupied, to prevent the
        passage of the enemy: when Agesilaus had forced his way into <placeName key="tgn,7002683"
          >Boeotia</placeName>, the commanders decided to detach some battalions to the rescue;
        everyone felt afraid (with some reason, gentlemen: for it was a serious thing, when they had
        just previously felt the relief of getting off in safety, to face a fresh danger), but I
        went to the commander and urged him to dispatch our battalion.without drawing lots.
          <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>So if any of you are incensed against those who claim
        the management of the cityÕs affairs and yet evade its dangers, you can have no right to
        regard me with any such feeling; for I not only carried out my orders with zeal, but I was
        also forward to face danger. I acted in this way, not because I did not think it a serious
        thing to do battle with the Lacedaemonians, but in order that, if ever I should be involved
        in an unjust prosecution, the better opinion that you would form of me on this account might
        avail to secure me the full measure of my rights. Now let the witnesses to this come
        forward, please.<quote type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
        <milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In every other campaign or
        outpost I have never once failed in my duty, but have adhered throughout to my rule of
        marching out in the first rank and retreating in the last. Surely it is by such conduct that
        one ought to judge who are the aspiring and orderly subjects of the State, and not to take
        the fact of a manÕs wearing his hair long<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">An aristocratic
          fashion among the class of knights.</note> as a reason for hating him; for such habits as
        this do no harm either to private persons or to the public weal, while it is from those who
        are ready to face danger before the enemy that you all derive advantage. <milestone n="19"
          unit="section"/>Hence it is not fair, gentlemen, to like or dislike any man because of his
        appearance, but rather to judge him by his actions; for many who are modest in speech and
        sober in dress have been the cause of grievous mischief, while others who are careless of
        such things have done you many a valuable service.<milestone n="Concl" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I have had occasion to
        observe, gentlemen, that some people are annoyed with me merely for attempting at too early
        an age to speak before the people. But, in the first place, I was compelled to speak in
        public to protect my own interests; and indeed, in the second, I do feel that my tendency
        has been unduly enterprising: for in reflecting on my ancestors, and how they have
        continually taken part in the administration, I had you also in my view— <milestone n="21"
          unit="section"/>I must tell you the truth—as attaching no value to any but men of that
        stamp. So who, on seeing you so minded, would not be stimulated to work and speak for the
        benefit of the State? Moreover, how could you be annoyed with such people? For it is you,
        and none else, who are judges of their worth.</p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
