<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>De causis et signis acutorum morborum </title>
				<author>Aretaeus</author>
				<editor>Francis Adams LL.D.</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Extant Works of Aretaeus, The Cappadocian.</title>
						<author>Aretaeus</author>
						<editor>Francis Adams LL.D.</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Milford House Inc.</publisher>
							<date>1972 (Republication of the 1856 edition).</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="page"/>
			</refsDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="book" n="1">
				<pb n="243"/>
				<head>BOOK I.</head>
				<div type="chapter" n="5">
					<head>CHAPTER V. ON THE PAROXYSM OF EPILEPTICS</head>
					<p> * * * * sluggishness, vertigo, heaviness of the tendons, plethora and
						distension of the veins in the neck; and much nausea indeed after food, but
						also, not unfrequently, with abstinence, there is a faint nausea; and phlegm
						is often vomited; want of appetite and indigestion after little food: they
						have flatulence and meteorism in the hypochondria. These symptoms, indeed,
						are constant.</p>
					<p> But, if it be near the accession of the paroxysm, there are before the sight
						circular flashes of purple or black colours, or of all mixed together, so as
						to exhibit the appearance of the rainbow expanded in the heavens; noises in
						the ears; a heavy smell; they are passionate, and unreasonably peevish. They
						fall down then, some from any such cause as lowness of spirits, but others
						from gazing intently on a running stream, a rolling</p>
					<pb n="244"/>
					<p> wheel, or a turning top. But sometimes the smell of heavy odours, such as of
						the gagate stone (<hi rend="ital">jet</hi>), makes them fall down. In these
						cases, the ailment is fixed in the head, and from it the disorder springs;
						but, in others, it arises also from the nerves remote from the head, which
						sympathise with the primary organ. Wherefore the great fingers of the hands,
						and the great toes of the feet are contracted; pain, torpor, and trembling
						succeed, and a rush of them to the head takes place. If the mischief spread
						until it reach the head, a crash takes place, in these cases, as if from the
						stroke of a piece of wood, or of stone; and, when they rise up, they tell
						how they have been maliciously struck by some person. This deception occurs
						to those who are attacked with the ailment for the first time. But those to
						whom the affection has become habitual, whenever the disease recurs, and has
						already seized the finger, or is commencing in any part, having from
						experience a foreknowledge of what is about to happen, call, from among
						those who are present, upon their customary assistants, and entreat them to
						bind, pull aside, and stretch the affected members; and they themselves tear
						at their own members, as if pulling out the disease; and such assistance has
						sometimes put off the attack for a day. But, in many cases, there is the
						dread as of a wild beast rushing upon them, or the phantasy of a shadow; and
						thus they have fallen down.</p>
					<p> In the attack, the person lies insensible; the hands are clasped together by
						the spasm; the legs not only plaited together, but also dashed about hither
						and thither by the tendons. The calamity bears a resemblance to slaughtered
						bulls; the neck bent, the head variously distorted, for sometimes it is
						arched, as it were, forwards, so that the chin rests upon the breast; and
						sometimes it is retracted to the back, as if forcibly drawn thither by the
						hair, when it rests on this shoulder or on that. They gape wide, the mouth
						is dry; the tongue protrudes, so as to incur the risk of a great wound,
						or</p>
					<pb n="245"/>
					<p> of a piece of it being cut off, should the teeth come forcibly together with
						the spasm; the eyes rolled inwards, the eyelids for the most part are
						separated, and affected with palpitation; but should they wish to shut the
						lids they cannot bring them together, insomuch that the white of the eyes
						can be seen from below. The eyebrows sometimes relaxed towards the mesal
						space, as in those who are frowning, and sometimes retracted to the temples
						abnormally, so that the skin about the forehead is greatly stretched, and
						the wrinkles in the intersuperciliary space disappear: the cheeks are ruddy
						and quivering; the lips sometimes compressed together to a sharp point, and
						sometimes separated towards the sides, when they are stretched over the
						teeth, like as in persons smiling.</p>
					<p> As the illness increases lividity of countenance also supervenes, distension
						of the vessels in the neck, inability of speech as in suffocation;
						insensibility even if you call loudly. The utterance a moaning and
						lamentation; and the respiration a sense of suffocation, as in a person who
						is throttled; the pulse strong, and quick, and small in the
						beginning,--great, slow, and feeble in the end, and irregular throughout;
						tentigo of the genital organs. Such sufferings do they endure towards the
						end of the attack.</p>
					<p> But when they come to the termination of the illness, there are unconscious
						discharges of the urine, and watery discharges from the bowels, and in some
						cases an evacuation also of the semen, from the constriction and compression
						of the vessels, or from the pruriency of the pain, and titillation of the
						humours; for in these cases the pains are seated in the nerves. The mouth
						watery; phlegm copious, thick, cold, and, if you should draw it forth, you
						might drag out a quantity of it in the form of a thread. But, if with length
						of time and much pain, the matters within the chest ferment, but the
						restrained spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) agitates all things, and
						there is a convulsion and disorder of the same, a flood, as it were, of
						humours swells up to</p>
					<pb n="246"/>
					<p> the organs of respiration, the mouth, and the nose; and if along with the
						humours the spirit be mixed, it appears like the relief of all the former
						feelings of suffocation. They accordingly spit out foam, as the sea ejects
						froth in mighty tempests; and then at length they rise up, the ailment now
						being at an end. At the termination, they are torpid in their members at
						first, experience heaviness of the head, and loss of strength, and are
						languid, pale, spiritless, and dejected, from the suffering and shame of the
						dreadful malady.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="6">
					<head>CHAPTER VI. ON TETANUS</head>
					<p> T<hi rend="smallcaps">ETANUS</hi>, in all its varieties, is a spasm of an
						exceedingly painful nature, very swift to prove fatal, but neither easy to
						be removed. They are affections of the muscles and tendons about the jaws;
						but the illness is communicated to the whole frame, for all parts are
						affected sympathetically with the primary organs. There are three forms of
						the convulsion, namely, in a straight line, backwards, and forwards. Tetanus
						is in a direct line, when the person labouring under the distention is
						stretched out straight and inflexible. The contractions forwards and
						backwards have their appellation from the tension and the place; for that
						backwards we call Opisthotonos; and that variety we call Emprosthotonos in
						which the patient is bent forwards by the anterior nerves. For the Greek
						word <foreign xml:lang="grc">TO/NOS</foreign> is applied both to a nerve,
						and to signify tension.</p>
					<p> The causes of these complaints are many; for some are apt to supervene on
						the wound of a membrane, or of muscles, or of punctured nerves, when, for
						the most part, the patients die; for, "spasm from a wound is fatal." And
						women also suffer from</p>
					<pb n="247"/>
					<p> this spasm after abortion; and, in this case, they seldom recover. Others
						are attacked with the spasm owing to a severe blow in the neck. Severe cold
						also sometimes proves a cause; for this reason, winter of all the seasons
						most especially engenders these affections; next to it, spring and autumn,
						but least of all summer, unless when preceded by a wound, or when any
						strange diseases prevail epidemically. Women are more disposed to tetanus
						than men, because they are of a cold temperament; but they more readily
						recover, because they are of a humid. With respect to the different ages,
						children are frequently affected, but do not often die, because the
						affection is familiar and akin to them; striplings are less liable to
						suffer, but more readily die; adults least of all, whereas old men are most
						subject to the disease, and most apt to die; the cause of this is the
						frigidity and dryness of old age, and the nature of the death. But if the
						cold be along with humidity, these spasmodic diseases are more innocent, and
						attended with less danger.</p>
					<p> In all these varieties, then, to speak generally, there is a pain and
						tension of the tendons and spine, and of the muscles connected with the jaws
						and cheek; for they fasten the lower jaw to the upper, so that it could not
						easily be separated even with levers or a wedge. But if one, by forcibly
						separating the teeth, pour in some liquid, the patients do not drink it but
						squirt it out, or retain it in the mouth, or it regurgitates by the
						nostrils; for the isthmus faucium is strongly compressed, and the tonsils
						being hard and tense, do not coalesce so as to propel that which is
						swallowed. The face is ruddy, and of mixed colours, the eyes almost
						immoveable, or are rolled about with difficulty; strong feeling of
						suffocation; respiration bad, distension of the arms and legs; subsultus of
						the muscles; the countenance variously distorted; the cheeks and lips
						tremulous; the jaw quivering, and the teeth rattling, and in certain rare
						cases even the ears are thus affected. I myself have beheld</p>
					<pb n="248"/>
					<p> this and wondered! The urine is retained, so as to induce strong dysuria, or
						passes spontaneously from contraction of the bladder. These symptoms occur
						in each variety of the spasms.</p>
					<p> But there are peculiarities in each; in Tetanus there is tension in a
						straight line of the whole body, which is unbent and inflexible; the legs
						and arms are straight.</p>
					<p> Opisthotonos bends the patient backward, like a bow, so that the reflected
						head is lodged between the shoulder-blades; the throat protrudes; the jaw
						sometimes gapes, but in some rare cases it is fixed in the upper one;
						respiration stertorous; the belly and chest prominent, and in these there is
						usually incontinence of urine; the abdomen stretched, and resonant if
						tapped; the arms strongly bent back in a state of extension; the legs and
						thighs are bent together, for the legs are bent in the opposite direction to
						the hams.</p>
					<p> But if they are bent forwards, they are protuberant at the back, the loins
						being extruded in a line with the back, the whole of the spine being
						straight; the vertex prone, the head inclining towards the chest; the lower
						jaw fixed upon the breast bone; the hands clasped together, the lower
						extremities extended; pains intense; the voice altogether dolorous; they
						groan, making deep moaning. Should the mischief then seize the chest and the
						respiratory organs, it readily frees the patient from life; a blessing this,
						to himself, as being a deliverance from pains, distortion, and deformity;
						and a contingency less than usual to be lamented by the spectators, were he
						a son or a father. But should the powers of life still stand out, the
						respiration, although bad, being still prolonged, the patient is not only
						bent up into an arch but rolled together like a ball, so that the head rests
						upon the knees, while the legs and back are bent forwards, so as to convey
						the impression of the articulation of the knee being dislocated
						backwards.</p>
					<pb n="249"/>
					<p> An inhuman calamity! an unseemly sight! a spectacle painful even to the
						beholder! an incurable malady! owing to the distortion, not to be recognised
						by the dearest friends; and hence the prayer of the spectators, which
						formerly would have been reckoned not pious, now becomes good, that the
						patient may depart from life, as being a deliverance from the pains and
						unseemly evils attendant on it. But neither can the physician, though
						present and looking on, furnish any assistance, as regards life, relief from
						pain or from deformity. For if he should wish to straighten the limbs, he
						can only do so by cutting and breaking those of a living man. With them,
						then, who are overpowered by the disease, he can merely sympathise. This is
						the great misfortune of the physician.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="7">
					<head>CHAPTER VII. ON ANGINA, OR QUINSEY</head>
					<p> A<hi rend="smallcaps">NGINA</hi> is indeed a very acute affection, for it is
						a compression of the respiration. But there are two species of it; for it is
						either an inflammation of the organs of respiration, or an affection of the
						spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) alone, which contains the cause of the
						disease in itself.</p>
					<p> The organs affected are, the tonsils, epiglottis, pharynx, uvula, top of the
						trachea; and, if the inflammation spread, the tongue also, and internal part
						of the fauces, when they protrude the tongue outside the teeth, owing to its
						abnormal size; for it fills the whole of the mouth, and the protuberance
						thereof extends beyond the teeth. This species is called Cynanche, either
						from its being a common affection of those animals, or from its being a
						customary practice for dogs to protrude the tongue even in health.</p>
					<pb n="250"/>
					<p> The opposite symptoms attend the other species; namely, collapse of the
						organs, and diminution of the natural size, with intense feeling of
						suffocation, insomuch that it appears to themselves as if the inflammation
						had disappeared to the internal parts of the thorax, and had seized upon the
						heart and lungs. This we call Synanche, as if from the disease inclining
						inwardly and producing suffocation. It appears to me that this is an illness
						of the spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) itself, which has under-gone a
						morbid conversion to a hotter and drier state, without any inflammation of
						the organ itself. Nor is this any great wonder. For in the Charonæan caves
						the most sudden suffocations occur from no affection of any organ,<note
							n="1">The Charonæan ditches or pits here mentioned, were in Phrygia. See
							Strabo, xii. 8. They are mentioned by Galen, de usu partium, vii.;
							Epid.i.t.xvii. p. 10, ed. K”n; and Pliny, H.N. vii. 93. Their
							pestilential exhalations are often noticed by ancient authors.</note>
						but the persons die from one inspiration, before the body can sustain any
						injury. But likewise a man will be seized with <hi rend="ital">rabies</hi>,
						from respiring the effluvia of the tongue of a dog, without having been
						bitten. It is not impossible then, that such a change of the respiration
						should occur within, since many other phenomena which occur in a man bear a
						resemblance to external causes, such as juices which become spoiled both
						within and without. And diseases resemble deleterious substances, and men
						have similar vomitings from medicines and from fevers. Hence, also, it was
						not a wonderful thing, that in the plague of Athens, certain persons fancied
						that poisonous substances had been thrown into the wells in the Piræus by
						the Peloponnesians; for these persons did not perceive the affinity between
						a pestilential disease and deleterious substances.</p>
					<p> Cases of Cynanche are attended with inflammation of the tonsils, of the
						fauces, and of the whole mouth; the tongue protrudes beyond the teeth and
						lips; they have salivation, the</p>
					<pb n="251"/>
					<p> phlegm running out very thick and cold; they have their faces ruddy and
						swollen; their eyes protuberant, wide open, and red; the drink regurgitates
						by the nostrils. The pains violent, but obscured by the urgency of the
						suffocation; the chest and heart are in a state of inflammation; there is a
						longing for cold air, yet they inspire but little, until they are suffocated
						from the obstruction of the passage to the chest. In certain cases, there is
						a ready transference of the disease to the chest, and these die from the
						metastasis; the fevers feeble, slight, bringing no relief. But if, in any
						case, there is a turn to the better, abscesses form on either side, near the
						ears externally, or internally about the tonsils; and if these occur with
						torpor, and are not very protracted, the patients recover, indeed, but with
						pain and danger. But, if a particularly large swelling should occur, in such
						cases as are converted to an abscess, and the abscess is raised to a point,
						they are quickly suffocated. Such are the peculiar symptoms of cynanche.</p>
					<p> Those of Synanche are, collapse, tenuity, and paleness; the eyes hollow,
						sunk inwardly; the fauces and uvula retracted upwards, the tonsils
						approaching one another still more; loss of speech: the feeling of
						suffocation is much stronger in this species than in the former, the
						mischief being seated in the chest whence the source of respiration. In the
						most acute cases, the patients die the same day, in some instances, even
						before calling in the physician; and in others, although called in, he could
						afford them no relief, for they died before the physician could apply the
						resources of his art. In those in which the disease takes a favourable turn,
						all the parts become inflamed, the inflammation being determined outwardly,
						so that the disease becomes cynanche in place of synanche. It is also a good
						thing when a strong swelling, or erysipelas, appears externally on the
						chest. And the skilful physician diverts the mischief to the chest by means
						of the cupping-instrument, or</p>
					<pb n="252"/>
					<p> by applying mustard to the breast and the parts near the jaws he determines
						outwardly and discusses the disease. In certain cases, indeed, the evil by
						these means has been for a time driven outwards, but when so driven out it
						speedily reverts, and produces suffocation.</p>
					<p> The causes are infinite, more especially exposure to cold, and, less
						frequently, to heat; blows; fish-bones fixed in the tonsils, cold draughts,
						intoxication, repletion, and the ills from respiration.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="8">
					<head>CHAPTER VIII. ON THE AFFECTIONS ABOUT THE UVULA</head>
					<p> T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> solid body suspended from the roof of the
						mouth between the two tonsils is called columella and gurgulio. Uva is the
						name of the affection. The columella (<hi rend="ital">uvula</hi>) is of a
						nervous nature, but humid, for it is situated in a humid region. Wherefore
						this body, the columella, suffers from various affections, for it becomes
						thickened from inflammation, being elongated and of equal thickness from the
						base to the extremity, and is attended with redness. Columna is the
						appellation of this affection. If it be rounded towards the extremity alone,
						and with its enlargement become livid and darkish, the name of the affection
						is Uva; for it altogether resembles a grape in figure, colour, and size. A
						third affection is that of the membranes when they have the appearance of
						broad sails, or the wings of bats, on this side and on that. This is called
						Lorum, for the lengthened folds of the membranes resemble thongs. But if the
						columella terminates in a slender and elongated membrane, having at its
						extremity a resemblance to the butt-end of a spear, it gets the name of</p>
					<pb n="253"/>
					<p> Fimbria. This affection arises spontaneously from a defluxion, like the
						others, but also from an oblique incision when the surgeon leaves the
						membrane at one side.<note n="1">Our author alludes here to the surgical
							operation, excision of the tonsils, described by Paulus Ægineta, vi.
							30.</note> But if the organ (uvula) become bifid with two membranes
						hanging on this side and on that, it has no distinct appellation, but it is
						an easy matter for any one who sees it to recognise the nature of the
						disease.</p>
					<p> A sense of suffocation accompanies all these affections, and they can by no
						means swallow with freedom. There is cough in all the varieties, but
						especially in those named lorum and fimbria. For a titillation of the
						trachea is produced by the membrane, and in some cases it secretly instils
						some liquid into the windpipe, whence they cough. But in uva and columella
						there is still more dyspnœa and very difficult deglutition; for, in these
						cases, the fluid is squeezed up to the nostrils, from sympathy of the
						tonsils. The columella is common in old persons, the uva in the young and in
						adults; for they abound in blood, and are of a more inflammatory nature. The
						affections of the membranes are common in puberty and infancy. It is safe to
						apply the knife in all these varieties; but in the uva, while still red,
						hemorrhage, pains, and increase of inflammation supervene.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="9">
					<head>CHAPTER IX. ON ULCERATIONS ABOUT THE TONSILS</head>
					<p> U<hi rend="smallcaps">LCERS</hi> occur on the tonsils; some, indeed, of an
						ordinary nature, mild and innocuous; but others of an unusual kind,
						pestilential, and fatal. Such as are clean, small, superficial, without
						inflammation and without pain, are mild; but such as</p>
					<pb n="254"/>
					<p> are broad, hollow, foul, and covered with a white, livid, or black
						concretion, are pestilential. Aphtha is the name given to these ulcers. But
						if the concretion has depth, it is an Eschar and is so called: but around
						the eschar there is formed a great redness, inflammation, and pain of the
						veins, as in carbuncle; and small pustules form, at first few in number, but
						others coming out, they coalesce, and a broad ulcer is produced. And if the
						disease spread outwardly to the mouth, and reach the columella (<hi
							rend="ital">uvula</hi>) and divide it asunder, and if it extend to the
						tongue, the gums, and the alveoli, the teeth also become loosened and black;
						and the inflammation seizes the neck; and these die within a few days from
						the inflammation, fever, fœtid smell, and want of food. But, if it spread to
						the thorax by the windpipe, it occasions death by suffocation within the
						space of a day. For the lungs and heart can neither endure such smells, nor
						ulcerations, nor ichorous discharges, but coughs and dyspnœa supervene.</p>
					<p> The cause of the mischief in the tonsils is the swallowing of cold, rough,
						hot, acid, and astringent substances; for these parts minister to the chest
						as to the purposes of voice and respiration; and to the belly for the
						conveyance of food; and to the stomach for deglutition. But if any affection
						occur in the internal parts, namely, the belly, the stomach, or the chest,
						an ascent of the mischief by the eructations takes place to the isthmus
						faucium, the tonsils, and the parts there; wherefore children, until
						puberty, especially suffer, for children in particular have large and cold
						respiration; for there is most heat in them; moreover, they are intemperate
						in regard to food, have a longing for varied food and cold drink; and they
						bawl loud both in anger and in sport; and these diseases are familiar to
						girls until they have their menstrual purgation. The land of Egypt
						especially engenders it, the air thereof being dry for respiration, and the
						food diversified, consisting of roots, herbs of many kinds, acrid seeds, and
						thick drink;</p>
					<pb n="255"/>
					<p> namely, the water of the Nile, and the sort of ale prepared from barley.
						Syria also, and more especially Cœlosyria, engenders these diseases, and
						hence they have been named Egyptian and Syrian ulcers.</p>
					<p> The manner of death is most piteous; pain sharp and hot as from
							carbuncle;<note n="1">The term in the original, <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>A)/NQRAC</foreign>, may either signify "a live coal," or the
							disease "Carbuncle." See Paulus Ægineta, iv. 25. It is somewhat doubtful
							to which of these significations our author applies it here; indeed, the
							former would be the more emphatic.</note> respiration bad, for their
						breath smells strongly of putrefaction, as they constantly inhale the same
						again into their chest; they are in so loathsome a state that they cannot
						endure the smell of themselves; countenance pale or livid; fever acute,
						thirst is if from fire, and yet they do not desire drink for fear of the
						pains it would occasion; for they become sick if it compress the tonsils, or
						if it return by the nostrils; and if they lie down they rise up again as not
						being able to endure the recumbent position, and, if they rise up, they are
						forced in their distress to lie down again; they mostly walk about erect,
						for in their inability to obtain relief they flee from rest, as if wishing
						to dispel one pain by another. Inspiration large, as desiring cold air for
						the purpose of refrigeration, but expiration small, for the ulceration, as
						if produced by burning, is inflamed by the heat of the respiration.
						Hoarseness, loss of speech supervene; and these symptoms hurry on from bad
						to worse, until suddenly falling to the ground they expire.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="10">
					<head>CHAPTER X. ON PLEURISY</head>
					<p> U<hi rend="smallcaps">NDER</hi> the ribs, the spine, and the internal part
						of the thorax as far as the clavicles, there is stretched a thin strong
						membrane,</p>
					<pb n="256"/>
					<p> adhering to the bones, which is named <hi rend="ital">succingens.</hi> When
						inflammation occurs in it, and there is heat with cough and parti-coloured
						sputa, the affection is named Pleurisy. But all these symptoms must
						harmonise and conspire together as all springing from one cause; for such of
						them as occur separately from different causes, even if they all occur
						together, are not called pleurisy. It is accompanied by acute pain of the
						clavicles; heat acrid; <hi rend="ital">decubitus</hi> on the inflamed side
						easy, for thus the membrane (<hi rend="ital">pleura</hi>) remains in its
						proper seat, but on the opposite side painful; for by its weight, the
						inflammation and suspension of the membrane, the pain stretches to all its
						adhesions at the shoulders and clavicles; and in certain cases even to the
						back and shoulder blade; the ancients called this affection Dorsal pleurisy.
						It is attended with dyspnœa, insomnolency, anorexia, florid redness of the
						cheeks, dry cough, difficult expectoration of phlegm, or bilious, or deeply
						tinged with blood, or yellowish; and these symptoms observe no order, but
						come and go irregularly; but, worst of all, if the bloody sputa cease, and
						the patients become delirious; and sometimes they become comatose, and in
						their somnolency the mind wavers.</p>
					<p> But if the disease take a bad turn, all the symptoms getting worse, they die
						within the seventh day by falling into syncope; or, if the commencement of
						the expectoration, and the more intense symptoms occurred with the second
						hebdomad, they die on the fourteenth day. It sometimes happens that in the
						intermediate period there is a transference of all the symptoms to the
						lungs; for the lung attracts to itself, being both porous and hot, and being
						moved for the attraction of the substances around, when the patient is
						suddenly suffocated by metastasis of the affection. But if the patient pass
						this period, and do not die within the twentieth day, he becomes affected
						with empyema. These, then, are the symptoms if the disease get into a bad
						state.</p>
					<pb n="257"/>
					<p> But if it take a favourable turn, there is a profuse hemorrhage by the
						nostrils, when the disease is suddenly resolved; then follow sleep and
						expectoration of phlegm, and afterwards of thin, bilious matters; then of
						still thinner, and again of bloody, thick, and flesh-like; and if, with the
						bloody, the bile return, and with it the phlegm, the patient's convalescence
						is secure; and these symptoms, if they should commence on the third day,
						with an easy expectoration of smooth, consistent, liquid, and (not) rounded
						sputa, the resolution takes place on the seventh day, when, after bilious
						discharges from the bowels, there is freedom of respiration, the mind
						settled, fever diminishing, and return of appetite. But if these symptoms
						commence with the second week, the resolution occurs on the fourteenth
						day.</p>
					<p> But if not so, it is converted into Empyema, as indicated by rigors, pungent
						pains, the desire of sitting erect, and the respiration becoming worse. It
						is then to be dreaded, lest, the lungs suddenly attracting the pus, the
						patient should be thereby suffocated, after having escaped the first and
						greater evils. But if the abscess creep in between the ribs and separate
						them, and point outwardly; or, if it burst into an intestine, for the most
						part the patient recovers.</p>
					<p> Among the seasons of the year winter most especially engenders the disease;
						next, autumn; spring, less frequently; but summer most rarely. With regard
						to age, old men are most apt to suffer, and most readily escape from an
						attack; for neither is there apt to be a great inflammation in an arid
						frame; nor is there a metastasis to the lungs, for old age is more frigid
						than any other age, and the respiration small, and the attraction of all
						things deficient. Young men and adults are not, indeed, very apt to suffer
						attacks; but neither, also, do they readily recover, for from a slight cause
						they would not experience even a slight attack of inflammation, and from
						great attacks there is greater danger. Children are least of all</p>
					<pb n="258"/>
					<p> liable to pleurisy, and in their case it is less frequently fatal; for their
						bodies are rare, secretions copious, perspiration and exhalation abundant;
						hence neither is a great inflammation formed. This is the felicity of their
						period of life in the present affection.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="book" n="2">
				<pb n="261"/>
				<head>BOOK II.</head>
				<div type="chapter" n="1">
					<head>CHAPTER I. ON PNEUMONIA</head>
					<p> A<hi rend="smallcaps">NIMALS</hi> live by two principal things, food and
						breath (<hi rend="ital">spirit, pneuma</hi>); of these by far the most
						important is the respiration, for if it be stopped, the man will not endure
						long, but immediately dies. The organs of it are many, the commencement
						being the nostrils; the passage, the trachea; the containing vessel, the
						lungs; the protection and receptacle of the lungs, the thorax. But the other
						parts, indeed, minister only as instruments to the animal; but the lungs
						also contain the cause of attraction, for in the midst of them is seated a
						hot organ, the heart, which is the origin of life and respiration. It
						imparts to the lungs the desire of drawing in cold air, for it raises a heat
						in them; but it is the heart which attracts. If, therefore, the heart suffer
						primarily, death is not far off.</p>
					<p> But if the lungs be affected, from a slight cause there is difficulty of
						breathing; the patient lives miserably, and death is the issue, unless some
						one effects a cure. But in a great affection, such as inflammation, there is
						a sense of suffocation,</p>
					<pb n="262"/>
					<p> loss of speech and of breathing, and a speedy death. This is what we call
						Peripneumonia, being an inflammation of the lungs, with acute fever, when
						they are attended with heaviness of the chest, freedom from pain, provided
						the lungs alone are inflamed; for they are naturally insensible, being of
						loose texture, like wool. But branches of the aspera arteria are spread
						through them, of a cartilaginous nature, and these, also, are insensible;
						muscles there are nowhere, and the nerves are small, slender, and minister
						to motion. This is the cause of the insensibility to pain. But if any of the
						membranes, by which it is connected with the chest, be inflamed, pain also
						is present; respiration bad, and hot; they wish to get up into an erect
						posture, as being the easiest of all postures for the respiration. Ruddy in
						countenance, but especially the cheeks; the white of the eyes very bright
						and fatty; the point of the nose flat; the veins in the temples and neck
						distended; loss of appetite; pulse, at first, large, empty, very frequent,
						as if forcibly accelerated; heat indeed, externally, feeble, and more humid
						than natural, but, internally, dry, and very hot, by means of which the
						breath is hot; there is thirst, dryness of the tongue, desire of cold air,
						aberration of mind; cough mostly dry, but if anything be brought up it is a
						frothy phlegm, or slightly tinged with bile, or with a very florid tinge of
						blood. The blood-stained is of all others the worst.</p>
					<p> But if the disease tend to a fatal termination, there is insomnolency; sleep
						brief, heavy, of a comatose nature; vain fancies; they are in a doting state
						of mind, but not violently delirious; they have no knowledge of their
						present sufferings. If you interrogate them respecting the disease, they
						will not acknowledge any formidable symptom; the extremities cold; the nails
						livid, and curved; the pulse small, very frequent, and failing, in which
						case death is near at hand, for they die mostly on the seventh day.</p>
					<p> But if the disease abate and take a favourable turn, there is</p>
					<pb n="263"/>
					<p> a copious hemorrhage from the nose, a discharge from the bowels of much
						bilious and frothy matters, such as might seem to be expelled from the lungs
						to the lower belly, provided it readily brings off much in a liquid state.
						Sometimes there is a determination to the urine. But they recover the most
						speedily in whose cases all these occur together.</p>
					<p> In certain cases much pus is formed in the lungs, or there is a metastasis
						from the side, if a greater symptom of convalescence be at hand. But if,
						indeed, the matter be translated from the side to the intestine or bladder,
						the patients immediately recover from the peripneumony; but they have a
						chronic abscess in the side, which, however, gets better. But if the matter
						burst upon the lungs, some have thereby been suffocated, from the copious
						effusion and inability to bring it up. But such as escape suffocation from
						the bursting of the abscess, have a large ulceration in the lungs, and pass
						into phthisis; and from the abscess and phthisis old persons do not readily
						recover; but from the peripneumony, youths and adults.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="2">
					<head>CHAPTER II. ON THE BRINGING UP OF BLOOD</head>
					<p> T<hi rend="smallcaps">HERE</hi> are two species of the discharge of blood by
						the mouth. The one that by the mouth from the head and the vessels there;
						the passage is by the palate and fauces, where are situated the commencement
						of the œsophagus and trachea; and with hawking, and small and more urgent
						cough, they eructate the blood into the mouth; whereas, in that from the
						mouth, neither does hawking accompany, and it is called <hi rend="ital"
							>Emptysis</hi> [<hi rend="ital">or</hi> spitting of blood]. But when the
						discharge is more scanty, and by drops, or when it comes more copiously from
						the head,</p>
					<pb n="264"/>
					<p> or from the mouth, it is no longer called a bringing up, but either the
						same, or a spitting, or a hemorrhage. But if it ascend from the chest, and
						the viscera there, the lungs, aspera arteria, the parts about the spine, the
						discharge from these is not called a spitting, but a bringing up (in Greek,
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">A)NAGWGH/</foreign>, the name being expressive
						of its coming upwards).<note n="1">Cælius Aurelianus, under the head of
							"Sanguinis fluor," thus explains the term:--"Improprium est enim fluorem
							vocare id quod ascensu quodam non lapsu fertur. Sed hæc Græci versa vice
							posuerunt, derivationem nominis intuentes. Hi enim anagogen vocant quod
							magis ex inferioribus ad superiora fluorem significat.'--<hi rend="ital"
								>Tard. pass.</hi> iii. 9. We are at a loss for a proper vocable in
							English to express this term. It is usually translated <hi rend="ital"
								>rejectio</hi> in Latin, which, however, is not sufficiently
							expressive. The most suitable in English, which I can think of, is "a
							bringing up."</note></p>
					<p> The symptoms of both are partly common, small and few in number, such as the
						seat of them, in which there is a coincidence between the bringing up and
						the spitting. But the peculiarities of each are great, many, and of vital
						importance, by which it is easy to distinguish either of them from the
						other. If, therefore, it came from the head, with a large discharge of
						blood, greater and more numerous symptoms will arise, but scanty from a
						slight and small spitting; in these cases, there is heaviness of the head,
						pain, noises of the ears, redness of countenance, distension of the veins,
						vertigo; and these are preceded by some obvious cause, such as a blow,
						exposure to cold, or heat, or intoxication; for drinking of wine speedily
						fills the head, and speedily empties it, by the bursting of a vessel; but
						from a slight intoxication there may be spitting, proceeding from
						rarefaction. Occasionally an habitual hemorrhage from the nostrils is
						stopped, and being diverted to the palate, produces the semblance of a
						bringing up of blood. If, therefore, it be from the head, there is
						titillation of the palate, frequent hawking, and with it a copious spitting
						takes place; a desire supervenes, and they readily cough. But if it flow
						into the aspera</p>
					<pb n="265"/>
					<p> arteria from the palate, they then bring it up by coughing, and this it is
						which deceives them into the supposition that it comes from the viscera
						below. It runs, also, from the head into the stomach, when it is vomited up
						with nausea, and thus proves a source of deception, as appearing to come
						from the stomach. The blood brought up by spitting is not very thick, but
						dark in colour, smooth, consistent, unmixed with other substances; for,
						being hawked up, it comes immediately upon the tongue in a round shape,
						being readily separated; and if you examine the roof of the palate, you will
						find it thickened and ulcerated, and, for the most part, bloody; and a
						slight and simple plan of treatment will suffice, namely, astringents
						applied to the palate in a cold state; for by hot, relaxing, and dilating
						applications the flow is increased, and this is an indication that the
						spitting is from the head, in which case evacuations are to be made from the
						head by the veins, the nostrils, or by any other channel of discharge. And
						these things must be done speedily; for if the blood is discharged a
						considerable time, the flow will become permanent, and the parts there will
						contract the habit of receiving the blood. The trachea, also, becomes
						ulcerated, and the patients cough instead of hawking; and this proves the
						commencement of a consumption.</p>
					<p> The flow of blood from the chest and viscera below is called a bringing up
						(in Greek, <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)NAGWGH/</foreign>). It is truly of a
						fatal nature, if it proceed from any of the vital parts which are
						ruptured--either the <hi rend="ital">vena cava</hi> in the heart, which
						conveys the blood from the liver, or from the large vein which lies along
						the spine. For from hemorrhage, as from slaughtering or impeded respiration,
						death is very speedy. But in those cases in which the blood comes from the
						lungs, the side, or the trachea, they do not die so speedily; but,
						nevertheless, they become affected with Empyema and Phthisis. Of these the
						least formidable is that from the trachea. But if the vomiting come from the
						stomach or bowels, the cases are not of a very</p>
					<pb n="266"/>
					<p> fatal nature, even though the hemorrhage be large; neither is the recovery
						slow and changeable. But if it proceed from the liver and spleen, it is
						neither readily nor constantly discharged upwards, but the defluxion is more
						easy into the stomach and intestines. Yet neither is the discharge upwards
						by the lungs impossible or incredible, for in fevers there occur hemorrhages
						of blood from the liver and spleen by the nostrils, the blood flowing from
						the nostril on the same side as the viscus from which it comes. These, then,
						are the places from which the blood comes in the bringing up, and such the
						differences as to danger or mortality.</p>
					<p> But the modes are three; for it is brought up either from rupture of a
						vessel, or from erosion, or from rarefaction. Rupture, then, takes place
						suddenly, either from a blow, straining at a load, or lifting a weight
						upward, or a leap from a height, or from bawling aloud, from violent
						passion, or some other similar cause, when blood is instantly poured forth
						from the vessel in great quantity.</p>
					<p> But if it proceed from erosion, the patient is to be interrogated if he ever
						had a cough before, or was affected with dyspnœa, and whether nausea or
						vomiting ever afflicted him previously. For from such chronic affections the
						vessels are corroded by a continued, copious, and acrid defluxion. When,
						therefore, the containing vessels, having been long wasted and attenuated,
						at length give way, they pour forth blood.</p>
					<p> But the mode by rarefaction is, indeed, unattended by rupture, and on that
						account the discharge is neither copious nor sudden, nor does it consist of
						thick blood; for by the rarefaction of the vessels, the thin portion is
						excreted. But if much collect in a cavity, and be again brought up, it
						becomes thicker than natural, but yet not very thick, neither black, like a
						clot; but it is quickly brought up in greater quantity, as being from a
						collection. This mode of bringing up blood is common with women who have not
						their monthly purgation,</p>
					<pb n="267"/>
					<p> and appears at the periods of the purgation, and stops during the intervals
						between them; and if the woman is not cured, the discharge upwards of blood
						will revert for many periods, and also, in certain cases, the vessels burst
						from fulness.</p>
					<p> And there is a difference of the discharge, whether it be brought up from an
						artery or a vein. For it is black, thick, and readily coagulates, if from a
						vein; it is less dangerous, and is more speedily stopped; but if from an
						artery, it is of a bright yellow colour and thin, does not readily
						coagulate, the danger is more imminent, and to stop it is not so easy; for
						the pulsations of the artery provoke the hemorrhage, and the lips of the
						wound do not coalesce from the frequent movements of the vessel.</p>
					<p> Recovery, if from erosion, is protracted, difficult, and doubtful; for,
						owing to loss of substance, the parts of the ulcer do not come together, for
						it is an ulcer, and not a wound; and adhesion takes place more readily in
						ruptures, for the lips of the wound touch one another. This, then, is
						another difference as to danger. The mode attended with least danger is that
						from rarefaction; and in it the styptic and refrigerant method of treatment
						is sufficient.</p>
					<p> The places are to be indicated from which the blood is brought up; for many
						of the symptoms are common, deception is easy, and the cure different.
						Blood, then, from erosion is not readily brought up from the stomach, for
						the coldness and stypticity of the articles of food and drink bring the
						parts to a state of condensation. Neither, also, are cases from erosion
						common, although more so than the former; for acrid defluxions do not adhere
						for any length of time, but are either brought up or are passed downwards.
						Rupture is more common in the stomach. If, then, any rupture take place, the
						hemorrhage is not very great, such as that from the thorax; for the veins
						there are slender, and the arteries also are small.</p>
					<pb n="268"/>
					<p> But in appearance the blood is not very black, not intensely yellowish,
						smooth, or mixed with saliva, being brought up with nausea and vomiting,
						slight cough, sometimes with some discharge, and sometimes alone, without
						any expectoration; for the trachea sympathises with the gullet, being
						extended along and connected with it. There is pinching or constriction of
						the ulcer from the things swallowed, more especially if they are very cold,
						hot, or austere; and in certain cases pain is produced in the stomach,
						extending as far as the back; vomitings of phlegm, and sometimes, when the
						disease is long protracted, and there has been long abstinence from food,
						they bring up a great quantity of them; fevers, not of a continual type, but
						of an irregular kind.</p>
					<p> But, from the stomach, what is brought up may be black and coagulated, even
						if it proceed from an artery; but if it proceed from a vein, it is much
						blacker and much more compact; much nausea and vomiting of pituitous and
						bilious matter; blood mixed up with the food, provided the man had eaten
						previously, for both the food and the blood are collected together in the
						same place; eructations frequent and fœtid, and, if much collect together,
						there is anxiety of mind and vertigo; but if these be vomited they are
						relieved. They are prostrate in strength, generally affected with a burning
						heat, and constant pain of the stomach.</p>
					<p> But from the aspera arteria they bring up scanty and very fluid blood, with
						a cough; or, if they do not bring it up, they cough incessantly. There is a
						painful feeling in the throat, either a little below or above; voice hoarse
						and indistinct.</p>
					<p> But if it be from the lungs, the discharge is copious, especially if from
						erosion, with much cough, of an intense yellow colour, frothy, rounded; so
						that what is brought up from one part may be distinguished from what is
						brought up from another. But the defluxion, though contained in a common
						vessel, from the chest, is diversified after mixture, and you</p>
					<pb n="269"/>
					<p> may distinguish parts of them as being portions of the thorax, and parts
						which have a fleshy appearance as being portions of the lungs. There is
						heaviness of the chest, freedom from pain, and much redness of the face,
						particularly in these cases.</p>
					<p> But if brought up from the thorax, pain stretching to the anterior part of
						the breast is indicative of the ruptured part; cough intense, expectoration
						difficult, the blood not very fluid, moderately thick, without froth. But
						if, in passing, the lung be affected by consent, a certain amount of froth
						is imparted to it, for the passage from the chest to the trachea is by the
						lungs.</p>
					<p> But if, indeed, from the side there be discharged with cough blood which is
						black, smooth, fœtid, stinking, as from putrefaction, with acute pain of the
						side, many die after the manner of pleuritics with fever.</p>
					<p> A season that is humid and hot engenders these affections. Spring is thus
						humid and hot. Next the summer; autumn less, but winter least of all. They
						die in summer mostly from hemorrhage, for great inflammations do not readily
						occur then; secondly, in spring, from inflammation and ardent fevers; but in
						autumn, attacks of <hi rend="ital">phthisis</hi> readily occur.</p>
					<p> In a word, every discharge of blood upwards, even if small, and although the
						ruptured vessels may have already united, is attended with lowness of
						spirits, dejection, and despair of life. For who is so firm in mind as to
						see himself enduring a state resembling that of a slaughtered animal, and
						yet have no fear of death? For the largest and most powerful animals, such
						as bulls, die very quickly from loss of blood. That, however, is no great
						wonder. But this is a mighty wonder: in the discharge from the lungs alone,
						which is particularly dangerous, the patients do not despair of themselves,
						even although near the last. The insensibility of the lungs to pain appears
						to me to be the cause of this; for pain, even although slight, makes one to
						fear death, and yet, in most cases, it is more dreadful than pernicious;</p>
					<pb n="270"/>
					<p> whereas the absence of pain, even in the great illnesses, is attended with
						absence of the fear of death, and is more dangerous than dreadful.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="3">
					<head>CHAPTER III. ON SYNCOPE</head>
					<p> W<hi rend="smallcaps">ELL</hi> by all means has the physician, and well have
						the common people succeeded in the appellation of this affection! It is,
						indeed, the name of a very acute malady; for what is there greater or more
						acute than the power of <hi rend="ital">Syncope ?</hi> and what other name
						more appropriate for the designation of this matter? what other organ more
						important than the heart for life or for death? Neither is it to be doubted
						that syncope is a disease of the heart, or that it is an injury of the vital
						powers thereof--such is the rapidity and such the mode of the destruction.
						For the affection is the solution of the bonds of the vital power, being
						antagonistic to the constitution of the man; for having seized fast thereon,
						it does not let go its hold, but brings him to dissolution. Nor is it any
						great wonder; for other diseases are peculiar to, and prove fatal to,
						certain organs, in which they are engendered, and to which they attach
						themselves. Thus pestilential and very malignant buboes derive their origin
						from the liver, but from no other part; tetanus, in like manner, from the
						nerves, and epilepsy from the head. Thus, therefore, syncope is a disease of
						the heart and of life. But such persons as regard it to be an affection of
						the stomach, because by means of food and wine, and in certain cases by cold
						substances, the powers have been restored and the mischief expelled--these,
						it would seem to me, ought to hold phrenitis to be a disease of the hair and
						skin of the</p>
					<pb n="271"/>
					<p> head, since the phrenitics are relieved by the shaving and wetting thereof.
						But to the heart the vicinity of the stomach is most important, for from it
						the heart draws both what is suitable and what is unsuitable to itself. And
						by the lungs the heart draws spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) for
						respiration, but yet the lungs do not hold a primary place in respiration;
						for the powers are not in the organs, but there where is the original of
						life and strength: But the stomach is neither the original nor seat of life;
						and yet one would be injured by atony thereof: for food which proves
						injurious to the heart does not hurt the stomach itself, but by it the
						heart; since those dying in such cases have symptoms of heart-affections,
						namely, pulse small and feeble, <hi rend="ital">bruit</hi> of the heart,
						with violent palpitation, vertigo, fainting, torpor, loss of tone in their
						limbs, sweating copious and unrestrainable, coldness of the whole body,
						insensibility, loss of utterance. How should the stomach endure such
						symptoms? For those peculiar to it are nausea, vomiting, loss of appetite,
						hiccup, eructation, acidity; whereas in cardiac affections the patients are
						more acute in their senses, so that they see and hear better than formerly;
						they are also in understanding more sound, and in mind more pure, not only
						regarding present things, but also with regard to futurity they are true
						prophets. These, then, are the powers, not of the stomach, but of the heart,
						where is the soul and the nature thereof, and to it is to be referred this
						affection of its powers.</p>
					<p> But this form of disease is a solution of the natural tone from a cold cause
						and humidity, and therefore they are not affected with heat, either
						internally or externally, neither do they suffer from thirst, and their
						breath is cold even when the disease proceeds from strong and ardent fevers,
						by which syncope is usually kindled up. For when nature is strong, and of
						the proper temperament, it rules all and commands all, whether humour,
						spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>), or solid, and, by their good order and
						symmetry, regulates the man in life; but if the bond</p>
					<pb n="272"/>
					<p> of nature--that is to say, its tone--be dissolved, then this affection is
						produced. The original of it is <hi rend="ital">causus</hi>, which is in
						this form.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="4">
					<head>CHAPTER IV. ON CAUSUS, OR ARDENT FEVER</head>
					<p> H<hi rend="smallcaps">EAT</hi>, indeed, everywhere, both acrid and subtil,
						but especially in the internal parts; respiration hot, as if from fire;
						inhalation of air large; desire of cold; dryness of tongue; parchedness of
						lips and skin; extremities cold; urine intensely tinged with bile;
						insomnolency; pulse frequent, small, and feeble; eyes clear, glancing,
						reddish; healthy colour of the countenance.</p>
					<p> But if the affection increase, all appearances become greater and worse; the
						pulse very small and very frequent; heat very dry and very acrid; intellect
						wavering; ignorance of all things; they are thirsty; a desire to touch
						anything cold, whether a wall, a garment, the floor, or a fluid; hands cold,
						palms thereof very hot, nails livid; breathing thick; perspiration like dew
						about the forehead and clavicles.</p>
					<p> But if nature attain the extremity of dryness and of heat, the hot is
						converted into cold, and the parched into humidity; for extreme intensities
						of things change to the opposite state. When, therefore, the bonds of life
						are dissolved, this is syncope. Then is there an irrestrainable sweat over
						all the body; respiration cold, much vapour about the nostrils; they have no
						thirst, and yet the other parts are parched except the organs of thirst,
						namely, the mouth and stomach; the urine thin and watery; belly for the most
						part dry, yet in certain cases the discharges are scanty and bilious; a
						redundancy of</p>
					<pb n="273"/>
					<p> humours; even the bones, being dissolved, run off; and from all parts, as in
						a river, there is a current outwards.</p>
					<p> As to the state of the soul, every sense is pure, the intellect acute, the
						gnostic powers prophetic; for they prognosticate to themselves, in the first
						place, their own departure from life; then they foretell what will
						afterwards take place to those present, who fancy sometimes that they are
						delirious; but these persons wonder at the result of what has been said.
						Others, also, talk to certain of the dead, perchance they alone perceiving
						them to be present, in virtue of their acute and pure sense, or perchance
						from their soul seeing beforehand, and announcing the men with whom they are
						about to associate. For formerly they were immersed in humours, as if in mud
						and darkness; but when the disease has drained these off, and taken away the
						mist from their eyes, they perceive those things which are in the air, and
						with the naked soul become true prophets. But those who have attained such a
						degree of refinement in their humours and understanding will scarcely
						recover, the vital power having been already evaporated into air.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="5">
					<head>CHAPTER V. ON CHOLERA</head>
					<p> C<hi rend="smallcaps">HOLERA</hi> is a retrograde movement of the <hi
							rend="ital">materiel</hi> in the whole body on the stomach, the belly,
						and the intestines; a most acute illness. Those matters, then, which collect
						in the stomach, rush upwards by vomiting; but those humours in the belly,
						and intestines, by the passages downwards. With regard to appearance, then,
						those things which are first discharged by vomiting, are watery; but those
						by the anus, liquid and</p>
					<pb n="274"/>
					<p> fetid excrement, (for continued indigestion is the cause of this disease);
						but if these are washed out, the discharges are pituitous, and then bilious.
						At first, indeed, they are borne easily, and without pain; but afterwards
						the stomach is affected with retchings, and the belly with tormina.</p>
					<p> But, if the disease become worse, the tormina get greater; there is
						fainting, prostration of strength in the limbs, anxiety, loss of appetite;
						or, if they take anything, with much rumbling and nausea, there is
						discharged by vomiting bile intensely yellow, and the downward discharges
						are of like kind; spasm, contractions of the muscles in the legs and arms;
						the fingers are bent; vertigo, hiccup, livid nails, frigidity, extremities
						cold, and altogether they are affected with rigors.</p>
					<p> But if the disease tend to death, the patient falls into a sweat; black
						bile, upwards and downwards; urine retained in the bladder by the spasm;
						but, in fact, sometimes neither is there any urine collected in the bladder,
						owing to the metastasis of the fluids to the intestine; loss of utterance;
						pulse very small, and very frequent in the cases affected with syncope;
						continual and unavailing strainings to vomit; the bowels troubled with
						tenesmus, dry, and without juices; a painful and most piteous death from
						spasm, suffocation, and empty vomiting.</p>
					<p> The season of summer, then, engenders this affection; next autumn; spring,
						less frequently; winter, least of all. With regard to the ages, then, those
						of young persons and adults; old age least of all; children more frequently
						than these, but their complaints are not of a deadly nature.</p>
					<pb n="275"/>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="6">
					<head>CHAPTER VI. ON ILEUS</head>
					<p> A<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> inflammation takes place in the intestines,
						creating a deadly pain, for many die of intense tormina; but there is also
						formed a cold dull flatus (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>), which cannot
						readily pass either upwards or downwards, but remains, for the most part
						rolled up in the small convolutions of the upper intestines, and hence the
						disease has got the appellation of <hi rend="ital">Ileus</hi> (<hi
							rend="ital">or Volvulus</hi>). But if in addition to the tormina, there
						be compression and softening of the intestines, and the abdomen protrude
						greatly, it is called <hi rend="ital">Chordapsus</hi>, from the Greek word
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">E(/YHSIS</foreign>, which signifies softening,
						and <foreign xml:lang="grc">XORDH\</foreign>, which is a name for the
						intestines; and hence the Mesentery, which contains all the nerves, vessels,
						and membranes that support the intestines, was called <foreign
							xml:lang="grc">E)PIXORDI\S</foreign> by the ancients.<note n="1">Both
							Petit and Ermerins have animadverted on this singular derivation of the
							term <foreign xml:lang="grc">XORDAYO/S</foreign>. As Petit remarks, the
							true derivation is no doubt from <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>A(/PTESQAI</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="grc">XORDH/</foreign>.
							The Greeks, it is well known, were very fanciful etymologists, of which
							we have striking proofs in the Cratylus of Plato.</note></p>
					<p> The cause of Ileus is a continued corruption of much multifarious and
						unaccustomed food, and repeated acts of indigestion, especially of articles
						which are apt to excite Ileus, as the ink of the cuttle-fish. And the same
						effects may be expected from a blow, or cold, or the drinking of cold water
						largely and greedily in a state of sweating; and in those cases, in which
						the gut has descended into the scrotum with fæces, and has not been replaced
						into the belly, or has been restored to its place with violence, in such
						cases it is customary for the</p>
					<pb n="276"/>
					<p> lower intestines to get inflamed.<note n="2">The substance of all the
							information to be found in the works of the ancient authorities on the
							subject of Hernia, may be seen in Paulus Ægineta, b.vi., 65, p. 66, Syd.
							Soc. Edit. I may mention, however, that although there be nothing in the
							works of the medical authorities which would lead us to suppose that the
							ancient surgeons were in the practice of operating to relieve
							incarcerated Hernia, the following passage in one of Martial's Epigrams
							would almost lead us to suppose the contrary, "Mitius implicitas Alcon
							secat enterocelas," <hi rend="ital">Epigr.</hi> xi. 84; which might be
							thus translated, "The surgeon Alcon inflicts less pain in cutting for
							incarcerated intestinal hernia.'</note> This affection is customary with
						children, who are subject to indigestion, and they more readily escape from
						the mischief, owing to their habits and the humidity of their intestines,
						for they are loose. Old persons do not readily suffer from the complaint,
						but rarely recover. The season of summer engenders the disease rather than
						that of spring; autumn, than winter; but the summer more than both.</p>
					<p> Many therefore die speedily of these tormina. But in other cases pus is
						formed; and then again, the intestine having become black and putrified, has
						separated, and thus the patients have died. In these cases, provided the
						Ileus is mild, there is a twisting pain, copious humours in the stomach,
						loss of tone, languor, vacant eructations bringing no relief, borborygmi in
						the bowels, the flatus passing down to the anus, but not making its
						escape.</p>
					<p> But if the attack of Ileus acquire intensity, there is a determination
						upwards of everything, flatus, phlegm, and bile; for they vomit all these;
						they are pale, cold over the whole body; much pain; respiration bad, they
						are affected with thirst.</p>
					<p> If they are about to die, there is cold sweat, dysuria, anus constricted, so
						that you could not pass a slender metal plate by it;<note n="3">Perhaps he
							means "a needle." See Testa, <hi rend="ital">Mal. del Cuore</hi>, t.
							iii.</note> vomiting of fæces; the patients are speechless; pulse, at
						last</p>
					<pb n="277"/>
					<p> rare and small, but before death very small, very dense, and failing. These
						symptoms attend the disease in the small intestines.</p>
					<p> But the same affections occur also in the colon, and the symptoms are
						similar, as also the issue; some of these escape if pus form in the colon,
						the reason of which is the fleshy thickness of this intestine. The pain is
						slender and sharp in the small intestines, but broad and heavy in the colon;
						the pain also sometimes darts up to the ribs, when the disease puts on the
						appearance of pleurisy; and these, moreover, are affected with fever; but
						sometimes it extends to the false ribs, on this side or on that, so that the
						pain appears to be seated in the liver and spleen; again it affects the
						loins, for the colon has many convolutions in all directions; but in other
						cases it fixes on the sacrum, the thighs, and the cremasters of the
						testicles. But in colic affections, they have rather retchings; and what is
						vomited is then bilious and oily. And the danger therefrom is so much the
						less, as the colon is more fleshy, and thicker than the small intestines,
						and consequently more tolerant of injury.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="7">
					<head>CHAPTER VII. ON THE ACUTE AFFECTIONS ABOUT THE LIVER</head>
					<p> I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> the affections of the liver, the patients do
						not die, indeed, more quickly than in those of the heart; but yet they
						suffer more pain; for the liver is, in a great measure, a concretion of
						blood. But if the cause of death happen to be situated in its <hi
							rend="ital">Portæ</hi>, they die no less speedily than from the heart;
						for these parts are tissues formed of membranes, of important and slender
						nerves, and of large veins. Hence certain of the philosophers</p>
					<pb n="278"/>
					<p> have held that the desires of the soul are seated there. In hemorrhage it
						greatly surpasses all the others; "for the liver is made up from the roots
						of veins." Wherefore a great inflammation does form in it, but not very
						frequently, nor in its vital parts, for the patient would die previously.
						But a smaller inflammation often takes place, whence it happens that they
						escape death, indeed, but experience a more protracted state of disease. For
						of its office, as regards sanguification, there is no stop nor
						procrastination, as from it a supply of blood is sent to the heart, and to
						the parts below the diaphragm.</p>
					<p> If from a greater cause--a stroke, or continued indigestion of much and bad
						food, and intoxication, or great cold--an inflammation forms in the portal
						system, a very speedy death is the result. For there is a latent, smothered,
						and acrid heat; pulse languid; the kind of pain varied, and every way
						diversified, sometimes darting to the right side, so as to resemble a sharp
						weapon fixed in the place, and sometimes resembling tormina; again, at other
						times the pain is deep--nay, very deep; and, intermediate between the pain,
						atony and loss of utterance. The diaphragm and succingens (<hi rend="ital"
							>pleura</hi>) are dragged downwards; for from them the liver is
						suspended as a weight. For this reason, a strong pain extends to the
						clavicle on the same side; an ineffectual cough, or only a desire thereof,
						and when it comes to a conclusion, dry; respiration bad, for the diaphragm
						does not co-operate with the lungs, by assisting them in contraction and
						dilatation. They draw in a small breath, but expire a larger; colour, a
						dark-green, leaden; they loathe food, or if they force themselves to take
						any, they become flatulent in the epigastrium; eructations bilious, acid,
						fetid; nausea, retchings, belly mostly loose, discharges bilious, viscid,
						small in quantity. The affections always go on increasing; mind not very
						much deranged, but torpid, unsettled, stupid; much timidity; coldness of the
						extremities, tremblings, rigors,</p>
					<pb n="279"/>
					<p> hiccup of a spasmodic nature, jaundice, bile intense, the whole body tinged
						with bile. But if it appear before the seventh day, it proves fatal in many
						cases.</p>
					<p> But those who have escaped a fatal termination, either by a hemorrhage, or a
						rapid discharge from the bowels of bilious matters, or from frequent
						discharges of intense urine, in these cases, after three weeks, the liver is
						converted into a purulent abscess. But if it pass considerably this period
						without an abscess, it ends inevitably in dropsy; the patients are thirsty,
						drink little, are dried in body, lose fat; there is a desire for acids, and
						an insensibility to taste.</p>
					<p> Autumn engenders this affection, along with the indigestion produced by much
						summer-fruit and multifarious food. Of all ages, the adult is most subject
						to it.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="8">
					<head>CHAPTER VIII. ON THE ACUTE DISEASE OF THE VENA CAVA</head>
					<p> F<hi rend="smallcaps">ROM</hi> the portæ of the liver, there passes a wide
						vein through the space intermediate between its extremities, which, being
						always divided into slender and more numerous branches, is distributed at
						last all over the liver in vessels imperceptible to the sight; and with
						their extremities anastomose the extremities of other veins, which, at
						first, are slender and numerous, grow larger and fewer in number, and, at
						last, they are collected into one large vein; hence, having become two by
						division, these pass through the liver. The upper one, then, having passed
						through the first lobe, appears on its convex side; then, having passed the
						diaphragm, it is inserted into the heart: this is called the <hi rend="ital"
							>vena cava.</hi> The other, having passed through the lower lobe, the
						fifth, to its concave side, makes its</p>
					<pb n="280"/>
					<p> exit near the spine, and is extended along it as far as the ischiatic
						region; and it, also, is called <hi rend="ital">vena cava.</hi> It obtains
						the same name, as being one and the same vein, which derives its origin from
						the liver. For if one choose, one may pass a plate of metal from the vena
						cava connected with the heart to that by the spine, and from the spine
						through the liver to the heart; for it is the same passage leading
						upwards.</p>
					<p> This vein, then, as I think, is all diseased in acute and strong affections;
						for it is altogether one vein. But other physicians fancy that only the part
						along the spine is affected, because there are no manifest symptoms in
						regard to the portion about the heart; for it is extended through the chest,
						having no adhesions, but floating in the chest, until, from the diaphragm,
						it adheres to the heart. If, then, any of the great ailments seize this
						vein, they are concealed by the thorax surrounding it.</p>
					<p> Wherefore <hi rend="ital">kedmata</hi><note n="1">See the note on the
							English translation of Hippocrates, Syd. Soc. Edit., vol. i. p. 216, and
							the authorities there referred to. The aneurismal varix would apply best
							to it in this place. It is not unlikely that aortal aneurisms were
							sometimes confounded with it. On this subject, see further Testa, <hi
								rend="ital">Malattie del Cuore</hi>, t. iii.</note> also form about
						this vein when a hemorrhage, bursting forth quickly proves fatal, the blood
						being discharged by the lungs and the arteria aspera, if it burst in the
						chest; but if, at its origin, the blood is poured into the lower belly, so
						that the bowels float in it, when the patients die before the blood makes
						its appearance, the belly being filled with blood.</p>
					<p> Inflammation likewise forms about the vein, and it, also, proves fatal, if
						it be great; for there is an acrid and pungent heat enclosed in the cavities
						of both, but little surpassing what is natural, so that to the touch the
						heat appears to be slight; but the patient fancies himself burning hot;
						pulse small, very frequent, so as to appear compressed and forcibly
						accelerated;</p>
					<pb n="281"/>
					<p> coldness of the extremities; intense thirst; dryness of the mouth; redness
						of countenance, along with paleness; he is reddish over the whole body;
						hypochondriac region hard, and retracted upwards; pain principally on the
						right side, and palpitation therein, extending to the flanks; and in certain
						cases, also, of the artery along the spine, provided the pulsation displays
						itself in the other hypochondriac region; for lying, as it does, on the left
						side, it sympathises with the other; the exhalation in the general system
						affording no relief, and not even making the skin soft, for it is dry,
						shrivelled, and rough; and more especially in the regions of the body where
						the bones are prominent, such as the back part of the elbow, the knees, or
						the knuckles. Sleep disturbed; the bowels, in certain cases, discharging
						nothing, and in others, the discharges small, acrid, bilious; urine, a
						bright yellow and pungent; not disordered, indeed, in mind, but they are
						torpid and wasted. Hence, those who have seen this constitution of disease
						have called it Causus, for the present symptoms are those of a species of
						Causus; and in autumn there is a tendency to malignity, both in adults and
						the young, in whom the habit of body is slender, from bad diet and hard
						labour. These, for the most part, die on the fourteenth day; but when the
						disease is protracted, they die in double that period. But those who either
						originally have a slight inflammation, or when a great inflammation is
						gradually resolved, escape the disease indeed, but never get rid of the
						mischief; for they labour under causus a long time. But the dangerous
						symptoms cease, namely, the pains, distension of the hypochondria, the bad
						pulse, and torpor of the intellect; but still they have nausea, are ill at
						ease, with distress of mind; and, moreover, these are attended with an
						accession of causus and thirst, dryness of the tongue and mouth; they
						inspire largely, drawing in a long and copious breath, as if wishing to draw
						in the whole atmosphere, for the purpose of refrigeration. And if they drink
						a large draught of cold water, they are</p>
					<pb n="282"/>
					<p> relieved, indeed, for a short time; but then again the thirst is kindled up,
						and again they drink copiously. And this is the successive course of the
						malady. And a good physician would give with impunity a copious cold
						draught, as in other species of causus, and even with less risk, in the case
						of those labouring under causus from disease of the <hi rend="ital">vena
							cava.</hi> And if either the bowels or the bladder carry off the drink,
						there is no necessity for inducing vomiting; but if not, after much cold
						drink much vomiting must be induced. For the patient would burst, if, after
						drinking so much, he should have no discharges by sweating, by urine, or by
						the bowels.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="9">
					<head>CHAPTER IX. ON ACUTE AFFECTIONS OF THE KIDNEYS</head>
					<p> T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> kidneys, as far as regards the peculiar
						structure of the organ, are not productive of any great danger, even if they
						should suffer acutely; for, being of a glandular nature, they are mild and
						do not experience deadly diseases. But their office is important, namely,
						the secretion of the urine from the blood, and its expulsion.</p>
					<p> It is stopped either by a stone, or an inflammation arising there, or a clot
						of blood, or something such; when no mischief arises from sympathy, owing to
						the peculiar nature of the organ affected, but the retention of the urine
						produces all sorts of dreadful symptoms. Heat, which is acrid, and induces
						nausea; a heavy pain along the spine at the loins; distention of the parts,
						especially of those about the hypochondrium; suppression of urine, not
						entirely, but they pass urine in drops, and have a desire to pass more, for
						there is the sensation of an overflow. But if the urine become acrid and
						pungent, coldness, tremblings, spasms, distention and fulness of the
						hypochondria</p>
					<pb n="283"/>
					<p> supervene. This miserable state and the conjoined feeling become similar to
						that of tympanites produced by indigestion, from the taking of too much
						food. Pulse, at first, indeed, slow and languid; but, if the evil press
						harder, small, frequent, tumultuous, and irregular: sleep slight, painful,
						not continued; and suddenly starting up as if from the stroke of a sharp
						instrument, they fall over again into a deep sleep as if from fatigue: they
						are not much deranged in intellect, but talk incoherently; the countenance
						livid. But if the desire of making water return again, the patients pass a
						small quantity in drops, along with spasms and great pains, when, for a
						short time, they are relieved from their sufferings, and again they
						experience a relapse. Of those that die, they sink most quickly who pass no
						urine; but the greater part recover, either from the stone dropping down
						into the bladder along with the urine, or from the inflammation being
						converted into pus, or from being gradually dispelled. For, if the urine
						pass easily even in small quantity, they escape death; but for a length of
						time they waste in constitution; the patients undergo these sufferings while
						still able to keep up, but gradually fall into a state of consumption. The
						same seasons, places, and ages induce these affections as induce those in
						connection with the venæ cavæ.</p>
					<p> Sometimes blood bursts from the kidneys suddenly in large quantity, and
						flows continuously for many days. None, however, die from the hemorrhage
						itself, but from the inflammation accompanying the hemorrhage, if the
						bleeding is stopped; but most frequently they die of strong inflammation
						induced by the stoppage.</p>
				</div>
				<pb n="284"/>
				<div type="chapter" n="10">
					<head>CHAPTER X. ON THE ACUTE AFFECTIONS ABOUT THE BLADDER</head>
					<p> T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> bladder is a dangerous part to suffer in acute
						diseases, even when it merely sympathizes with other parts; but more
						dangerous and fatal if the affection begin with itself; for it is very
						potent to make the other parts sympathise with it, as the nerves and the
						understanding: for the bladder is a cold and white nerve, at a very great
						distance from the innate heat, but very near the external cold: for it is
						situated in the lowest part of the belly, at the greatest distance from the
						chest. But, also, its office is of vital importance, namely, the passage of
						the urine.</p>
					<p> Even, then, when the passage is only stopped by stones, or clots, or from
						any native or foreign mischief, it is of a deadly nature. In women, the
						phlegmonous tumour of the uterus may compress it; and in men, the straight
						intestine at the end bowels, called the Rectum. In many cases, too, owing to
						involuntary restraint from modesty in assemblies and at banquets, being
						filled it becomes distended; and, from the loss of its contractile power, it
						no longer evacuates the urine. When, then, the urine is stopped, there is
						fulness of the parts above, namely, the kidneys; distension of the ureters,
						grievous pain of the loins, spasms, tremblings, rigors, alienation of mind.
						But if it suffer from an ulcer or inflammation, there are, indeed, many bad
						symptoms; but death from the ulcers is by far the most speedy. With regard,
						however, to the ulceration and purulent abscess, and those other affections
						which are not very acute, they will be treated of among the chronic
						diseases; but such as are acute, and prove fatal in fourteen days, or a
						little earlier or later, such as inflammation, thrombus, or a stone falling
						down to the neck of the bladder, of these I will now treat. If, therefore,
						any of these occur, there is retention</p>
					<pb n="285"/>
					<p> of urine; swelling in the hypogastric region; acute pain all over the
						abdomen; distension of the bladder; a sallow sweat on the tenth day;
						vomitings of phlegm, then of bile; coldness of the whole body, but
						especially of the feet: but, if the mischief spread farther, there come on
						fevers attended with hiccup, pulse irregularly frequent and small, redness
						of the countenance, thirst, distress of mind, delirium, spasms. From
						deleterious substances, such as cantharides and buprestis, both the bladder
						is distended with flatus, and the whole belly suffers violence; and all
						things get worse, and death cannot be long delayed.</p>
					<p> The bladder also sometimes suffers from hemorrhage; the blood there is
						bright and thin, but the patients never die from it, although it may not be
						easy to stop. But from the clots and the inflammation there is danger; for
						the coldness, mortification, gangrene, and the other evils consequent upon
						it readily prove fatal.</p>
					<p> Winter and autumn bring on these diseases. As to age, manhood, but still
						more old age. The other seasons and periods of life do not generally produce
						the diseases, and they very rarely prove fatal. Of all others, infants are
						most free from danger.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="11">
					<head>CHAPTER XI. ON HYSTERICAL SUFFOCATION</head>
					<p> I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> the middle of the flanks of women lies the
						womb, a female viscus, closely resembling an animal; for it is moved of
						itself hither and thither in the flanks, also upwards in a direct line to
						below the cartilage of the thorax, and also obliquely to the right or to the
						left, either to the liver or spleen; and it likewise is subject to prolapsus
						downwards, and, in a word, it is</p>
					<pb n="286"/>
					<p> altogether erratic. It delights, also, in fragrant smells, and advances
						towards them; and it has an aversion to fetid smells, and flees from them;
						and, on the whole, the womb is like an animal within an animal.</p>
					<p> When, therefore, it is suddenly carried upwards, and remains above for a
						considerable time, and violently compresses the intestines, the woman
						experiences a choking, after the form of epilepsy, but without convulsions.
						For the liver, diaphragm, lungs and heart, are quickly squeezed within a
						narrow space; and therefore loss of breathing and of speech seems to be
						present. And, moreover, the carotids are compressed from sympathy with the
						heart, and hence there is heaviness of head, loss of sensibility, and deep
						sleep.</p>
					<p> And in women there also arises another affection resembling this form, with
						sense of choking and loss of speech, but not proceeding from the womb; for
						it also happens to men, in the manner of <hi rend="ital">catochus.</hi> But
						those from the uterus are remedied by fetid smells, and the application of
						fragrant things to the female parts; but in the others these things do no
						good; and the limbs are moved about in the affection from the womb, but in
						the other affection not at all. Moreover, voluntary and involuntary
						tremblings . . . . . . . . . . . but from the application of a pessary to
						induce abortion, powerful congelation of the womb, the stoppage of a copious
						hemorrhage, and such like.</p>
					<p> If, therefore, upon the womb's being moved upwards, she begin to suffer,
						there is sluggishness in the performance of her offices, prostration of
						strength, atony, loss of the faculties of her knees, vertigo, and the limbs
						sink under her; headache, heaviness of the head, and the woman is pained in
						the veins on each side of the nose.</p>
					<p> But if they fall down they have heartburn . . . . . in the hypochondriac
						regions; flanks empty, where is the seat of the womb; pulse intermittent,
						irregular, and failing; strong sense</p>
					<pb n="287"/>
					<p> of choking; loss of speech and of sensibility; respiration imperceptible and
						indistinct; a very sudden and incredible death, for they have nothing deadly
						in their appearance; in colour like that of life, and for a considerable
						time after death they are more ruddy than usual; eyes somewhat prominent,
						bright, not entirely fixed, but yet not very much turned aside.</p>
					<p> But if the uterus be removed back to its seat before the affection come to a
						conclusion, they escape the suffocation. When the belly rumbles there is
						moisture about the female parts, respiration thicker and more distinct, a
						very speedy rousing up from the affection, in like manner as death is very
						sudden; for as it readily ascends to the higher regions, so it readily
						recedes. For the uterus is buoyant, but the membranes, its supporters, are
						humid, and the place is humid in which the uterus lies; and, moreover, it
						flees from fetid things, and seeks after sweet: wherefore it readily
						inclines to this side and to that, like a log of wood, and floats upwards
						and downwards. For this reason the affection occurs in young women, but not
						in old. For in those in whom the age, mode of life, and understanding is
						more mobile, the uterus also is of a wandering nature; but in those more
						advanced in life, the age, mode of living, understanding, and the uterus are
						of a steady character. Wherefore this suffocation from the womb accompanies
						females alone.</p>
					<p> But the affections common to men happen also to the uterus, such as
						inflammation and hemorrhage, and they have the common symptoms; namely,
						fever, asphexy, coldness, loss of speech. But in hemorrhage the death is
						even more sudden, being like that of a slaughtered animal.</p>
				</div>
				<pb n="288"/>
				<div type="chapter" n="12">
					<head>CHAPTER XII. ON SATYRIASIS</head>
					<p> T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> Satyrs, sacred to Bacchus, in the paintings
						and statues, have the member erect, as the symbol of the divine performance.
						It is also a form of disease, in which the patient has erection of the
						genital organ, the appellation of Satyriasis being derived from its
						resemblance to the figure of the god.</p>
					<p> It is an unrestrainable impulse to connection; but neither are they at all
						relieved by these embraces, nor is the tentigo soothed by many and repeated
						acts of sexual intercourse. Spasms of all the nerves, and tension of all the
						tendons, groins, and perineum, inflammation and pain of the genital parts,
						redness of countenance, and a dewy moisture. Wrapped up in silent sorrow,
						they are stupid, as if grievously afflicted with their calamity. But if the
						affection overcome the patient's sense of shame, he will lose all restraint
						of tongue as regards obscenity, and likewise all restraint in regard to the
						open performance of the act, being deranged in understanding as to
						indecency; for they cannot restrain themselves, are thirsty, and vomit much
						phlegm. Afterwards, froth settles on their lips, as is the case with goats
						in the season of rutting, and the smell likewise is similar. The urine,
						after long retention, is white, thick, and like semen; bowels constipated;
						spontaneous titillations of the sides and arm-pits; they have convulsions,
						loathe food, or, if presented to them, they snatch it confusedly.</p>
					<p> But if the illness tend to death, they become flatulent, belly protuberant,
						tension of the tendons and of all the muscles, difficulty of movement,
						contraction of the limbs, pulse small, weak, and irregular.</p>
					<p> All these symptoms have been sometimes removed by copious discharges from
						the bowels of phlegm and bile, and by</p>
					<pb n="289"/>
					<p> vomiting in like manner, not without danger. The proper cure is deep and
						very protracted sleep; for much sleep induces coldness, paralysis, and
						torpor of the nerves; and torpidity and refrigeration cure Satyriasis.</p>
					<p> The affection, for the most part, is formed in spring and summer. Of the
						periods of life, it occurs principally in boys and striplings, more
						especially in such as are naturally prone to sexual intercourse. It is a
						most acute, disgusting, and unseemly ailment. For the most part, the
						patients die on the seventh day. It is said, that women also suffer from
						this affection; that they have the same impulse to venery, and the other
						symptoms the same. I believe, indeed, that lust is engendered in women of a
						humid temperament, so as to induce a copious discharge of the superfluous
						humours; but I do not at all believe that they are affected with Satyriasis,
						for their nature, being cold, is not adapted to it. But neither, also, has
						woman the parts necessary for erection, like those of a Satyr, whence the
						affection derives its name; and neither also are men subject to suffocation
						from the womb, because men have not an uterus.</p>
					<pb/>
				</div>
			</div>


		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
