<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE TEI.2 PUBLIC "-//TEI P4//DTD Main DTD Driver File//EN" "http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/DTD/tei2.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % TEI.XML "INCLUDE">
<!ENTITY % PersProse PUBLIC "-//Perseus P4//DTD Perseus Prose//EN" "http://www.perseus.tufts.edu/DTD/1.0/PersProse.dtd" >
%PersProse;
]>
<TEI.2>
	<teiHeader type="text" status="new">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Exordia</title>
				<title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
				<author>Demosthenes</author>
				<editor role="editor">Norman W. DeWitt</editor>
				<editor role="editor">Norman J. DeWitt</editor> &responsibility; &fund.AnnCPB; </titleStmt> &Perseus.publish; <sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
          <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by Norman W. DeWitt, Ph.D., and Norman J.
            DeWitt, Ph.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1949</date>
        </bibl>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state delim="." n="chunk" unit="exordium"/>
				<state unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language id="en">English </language>
				<language id="greek">Greek </language>
				<language id="la">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change>
				<date>1992</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>staff</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>Text was scanned at St. Olaf Spring, 1992.</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>6/26/92</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>EM</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>changed numbering of erotic elegy, exordia and letters to 0. from 61, 61 and 2</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>28-Feb-00</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>AEM</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>convert to P3</item>
			</change>
			<change>
				<date>29-Feb-00</date>
				<respStmt>
					<name>AEM</name>
					<resp>ed.</resp>
				</respStmt>
				<item>
$Log: tlg0014.tlg062.perseus-eng1.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2013-09-13 23:17:35  balmas01
copyrighted CTS texts from sdl and classics in new canonical structure per github repo

Revision 1.3  2010-08-31 18:43:05  rsingh04
cleaned up log keyword
 
Revision 1.1 2009/11/16 22:16:11 rsingh04 
moved more texts around based on copyright status

Revision 1.7 2009/06/19 19:03:44 lcerrato 
fixed bad bibls 
Revision 1.6 2009/06/12 20:57:09 lcerrato 
fixed bad bibls 

Revision 1.5 2009/06/09 21:46:30 student 
fixed bibl errors - zr
          
Revision 1.4 2009/05/19 20:53:30 lcerrato 
fixed bad bibls 

Revision 1.3 2008/11/26 19:32:57 lcerrato 
fixing bad bibls 

Revision 1.2 2006/02/10 21:10:10 packel 
places/dates now
          actually tagged 

Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:32:11 packel 
Converted to XML 

Revision 1.3 2003/07/01 22:15:59 yorkc 
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup
          (esp. character encodings and typos.) 

Revision 1.2 2000/03/04 20:34:19 dasmith 
Added
          separate funder entity to TEI header. 

Revision 1.1 2000/02/29 21:41:26 amahoney 
split the
          exordia and letters into separate files; add cards to the letters so they can chunk
          gracefully 
        </item>
			</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>

	<text lang="en">
		<body>
			<head>Exordia</head>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="1">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The beginning of Philippic 1 &lpar;<bibl n="Dem. 4">Dem. 4</bibl>&rpar; differs but slightly from this.</note> If it had
          been proposed to discuss some new measure, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I should have waited until most of the regular speakers had
          declared their opinions, and if any of their views had pleased me, I should have held my
          peace; otherwise, I should then have attempted to say what I myself think. But since you
          are now considering matters on which these speakers have often spoken before, I feel that,
          even if the first to rise, I may reasonably appear to be speaking after them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Now, if our interests were prospering, there would be no need to
          deliberate; but since, as you all observe, they are in straits, I shall try, on that
          assumption, to advise what I consider best. In the first place, you ought to recognize
          that none of the policies you pursued while engaged in the war are to be used henceforth,
          but quite their opposites.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Similar advice is given in
              <bibl n="Dem. 8.38">Dem. 8.38</bibl>. Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 2.23">Dem. 2.23</bibl>.</note>
          For if those policies have brought your fortunes low, it is very likely that their
          opposites will improve them.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This advice is satirically
            tendered to Dionysus by Euripides in <bibl n="Aristoph. Frogs 1446">Aristoph. Frogs
              1446-1450</bibl>.</note>
          <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Next, you must consider that it is not the speaker who
          places upon you little or no burden who is in the right, for you see that, as a
          consequence of such optimistic speeches, our present condition has reached the limit of
          wretchedness, but rather the speaker who, putting aside the thought of pleasing you, shall
          tell you what ought to be done and by what means we may cease bringing disgrace upon
          ourselves and incurring losses.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The danger of speaking
            to please only is mentioned in <bibl n="Dem. 9.63">Dem. 9.63-64</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 3.3">Dem. 3.3</bibl>.</note> For, to speak truthfully, if all that a man
          passes over in his speech through reluctance to pain you is going to be passed over also
          by the course of events, it is right to harangue you for your pleasure; but if the charm
          of words, when unbecoming the occasion, becomes a penalty in action,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 4.38">Dem. 4.38</bibl>.</note> it is shameful to cheat
          yourselves, and to do only under the utmost necessity what you should have done
          voluntarily long before.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="2">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>The same thoughts do not present themselves to me, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, when I hear you refer by name to our form of government and again
          when I see the manner in which some of you treat those who speak in its defence. As you
          all know, the name you give to our government is democracy, but I see that some of you
          listen with more pleasure to those who advocate the opposite to it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>I wonder just what their motive may be. Or do you imagine they are
          making these speeches gratis? Well, the masters of the oligarchies, whose cause these men
          are pleading, might quietly increase their fees.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This is
            ironical, explaining<foreign lang="greek">pro/fasis</foreign>; virtual reported
            speech.</note> But honestly, have you assumed that their principles are better than the
          other kind? So oligarchy, presumably, looks better to you than democracy! Then do you
          think the men themselves are better? And yet who could reasonably be regarded by you as
          honest when he speaks in public against the interest of the established government?
          Therefore it remains to conclude that you are mistaken when you hold this opinion.
          Consequently, be on your guard against falling into this error, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, so that you shall not some day give those who
          are plotting against you an opening, and only then learn that you have made a mistake,
          when it will no longer be of the least advantage to you. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Now, the fact that everything is not going as we might wish, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, either at home or among our allies, is perhaps
          not astonishing; for in many things the whim of Fortune prevails and there are many
          plausible reasons why everything does not turn out according to plan, men being but men.
          Yet for the common people to have no portion at all and their opponents a superabundance
          is something to astound and alarm intelligent men, as I judge it, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. This, then, is the starting point of my entire
          speech.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="3">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I believe, <note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The beginning of <bibl n="Dem. 1">Dem.
              1</bibl> differs but slightly.</note> men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that in preference to a large sum of money you would choose the
          plan that will pay you in the matters you are now considering. This being so, it is then
          your duty to show yourselves willing hearers of your prospective counsellors; for not only
          in the event of someone having come here with a useful idea thought out, would you, having
          listened, have the benefit of it, but I also assume it to be part of your good fortune
          that many timely suggestions would occur to some men on the spur of the moment, so that
          from the whole number the choice of the advantageous is made easier for you.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="4">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>It is your duty, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to listen to
          every proposal made, since it is your prerogative to adopt whichever of them you choose.
          For it often happens that the same person is wrong on one point and right on another; and
          so by shouting him down when displeased you may perhaps deprive yourselves of many useful
          ideas, whereas by attending with decorum and in silence, you will act on every sound
          proposal, and if you think someone is making a foolish suggestion, you will ignore it. As
          for me, I am not accustomed to make long speeches, and even if previously I had been in
          the habit, I should not have taken this occasion to do so; instead, I shall tell you as
          briefly as I can what I consider to be in your interests.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="5">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I observe, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that there is no
          mistaking what kind of speeches you would like to hear and to what kind you are averse.
          Yet to say what one thinks will find favour I consider to be the badge of those who wish
          to work some deception, whereas to endure, when one is speaking for measures he is
          convinced are advantageous to the State, either your heckling or what else you choose to
          do, I judge to be the part of a loyal and honest citizen. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>And I should like to have you bear patiently with the speeches of both sides to this
          end, if for no other, in order that, if someone shall be found to offer a proposal better
          than those upon which you are intent, you may avail yourselves of it, but, if he falls
          short and is unable to make his point, that he may seem to have suffered this repulse
          through his own fault and not because of your refusing to listen. Furthermore, your
          experience would not be so disagreeable if you should listen to some fool making a long
          speech as it would if you prevented a man from speaking who had something timely to
          propose. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>In all matters, of course, the first step toward
          right judgement is never to imagine you understand before learning, especially knowing as
          you do that many men before now have often changed their minds. If, then, you on your part
          are now convinced of these truths, I think that I on my part shall seem justified in
          speaking briefly in opposition and be found to propose the plans that are best for
          you.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="6">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Although many speeches have been made, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, by all your counsellors, I do not see that you are now any nearer
          to discovering what ought to be done than before you came up to the Assembly. The cause of
          this, in my opinion, is the same as the cause of the wretched plight of our affairs in
          general, that the speakers do not offer advice about the business before you, but accuse
          and revile one another, accustoming you, in my judgement, to hearing, without process of
          law, all the mischief of which they are the cause, in order that if, after all, they do
          come to face the test some day, you, thinking you are hearing nothing new, but only the
          charges over which you have often been angry, may so become more merciful jurors and
          judges of their misdeeds. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Perhaps it would be foolish at
          the moment to inquire into the exact reason why they do this; but because it harms you,
          for this reason I censure them. For my own part, I will accuse no one today nor will I
          sponsor any charge that I shall not make good on the spot, nor, in general, will I do any
          of the things which these men do; but when I have stated as briefly as I can what I think
          best for your interests and most profitable for you who deliberate, I will step down.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="7">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The beginning of <bibl n="Dem. 14">Dem. 14</bibl> is
            identical</note> Those who praise your forefathers, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, in my judgement choose a charming theme upon
          which to speak, and yet I do not think they do a favour to those whom they extol. For
          instance, when they undertake to tell of the deeds of those men, to which no speaker could
          do justice, while winning for themselves a reputation for ability to speak, they cause the
          valor of those men to seem to their hearers less than had been supposed. As for me, I
          consider the greatest commendation of those heroes to be the test of time, for although a
          long interval has gone by, no others have been able to exhibit greater deeds than those
          performed by them, <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>and I shall myself merely try to tell
          you after what manner I think you will be best able to make your preparations. For this is
          the situation; though we should all prove ourselves to be clever speakers, I know well
          that your interests would not be advanced in the slightest, but if just one speaker, no
          matter who, should come forward and be able to demonstrate convincingly what kind of
          preparation, and how great, and provided from what funds, would be to the State's
          advantage, all our present apprehension is as good as dispelled. This I shall try to do,
          if, after all, I am able, having first told you briefly how my opinion stands with respect
          to our relations with the King.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>, known also as &ldquo;the great
            king&rdquo;</note></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="8">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The beginning of <bibl n="Dem. 14">Dem. 14</bibl> is
            identical</note> Both parties seem to me to be in the wrong, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, both those who have supported the Arcadians and
          those who have supported the Spartans. For, just as if they had come here from one or the
          other of the two countries and were not of your own citizen body, to which both embassies
          are appealing, they are denouncing and abusing one another. This, however, was a concern
          of the visiting envoys, while to discuss the questions in the common interest and to
          consider your own interest without self-seeking is the duty of those who see fit to offer
          advice here in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Yet as things now are, if one could cancel the fact of their being known
          and their using the Attic speech, many people, I believe, would think the one group
          Arcadians and the other Spartans!</p>
				<p>I know myself how difficult it is to propose the best procedure, for when you have been
          deceived and some of you want this and others that, if someone undertakes to suggest a
          compromise and then you do not wait to learn the facts, he will please neither party and
          will be put in the wrong with both sides. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Nevertheless, I shall choose to be thought to talk nonsense, if that, after all, is to be
          my fate, rather than to abandon you to certain people to be deceived in violation of what
          I consider best for you. And so, with your permission, I shall go into other details
          later, and proceed to explain what I think is best, starting from the premises upon which
          both sides agree.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="9">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I have taken the floor, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          because I do not hold the same views as some of those who have spoken. Still I shall not
          allege that these men out of villainy have expressed sentiments opposed to your best
          interests, but I say that many, while neglecting to judge events critically, make a
          practice of considering the words they will use, and if they chance to find an ample
          supply of these, of haranguing the people without more ado. In this they are wrong nor do
          they reflect in their own minds that, since it is the experience of all that over a long
          period many plans have worked out happily and some of them, because of the times, quite
          contrary to their promise, if some speaker cites the one kind and passes over the other,
          he will unconsciously be doing the easiest thing in the world, deceiving himself.
            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Now those who thus use the privilege of advising you
          seem to me to look upon the reputation for eloquence accruing to them from their speeches
          as an adequate ambition, but it is my opinion that the man who proposes to advise the
          State on matters of policy should rather consider how the measures adopted shall prove of
          benefit, and not how his remarks of the moment may find favour. For those who win esteem
          by their words ought to add to it the accomplishment of some useful work in order that not
          only now, but for all time, their utterances may have merit.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="10">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>If you have decided, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, what it
          is best to do in the circumstances, it is a mistake to propose debate; for why should you
          be needlessly bored by listening to what you have yourselves judged to be expedient before
          hearing it discussed? But if, assuming that you must reach a judgement on the basis of
          what shall be said, you are exploring and deliberating, it is wrong to stop those who wish
          to speak, since by so doing you are deprived entirely of whatever practical proposal some
          speakers have thought up, and you cause other speakers to abandon their own conclusions in
          favour of what they think you desire to hear. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>While to
          unite in forcing the speaker to express your wishes shows an intention to do wrong, the
          willingness to deliberate is proved when you listen to his views, scan them and, if any Is
          good, adopt it. I say this, not as one about to recommend measures opposed to those you
          are favouring, but as one who knows that, if you refuse to hear the opposition, they will
          say you have been deceived, while, if you do listen and are not persuaded, they will have
          been proved on the spot to be offering the worse proposals.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="11">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I think you all know, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that you
          have not come here today to put any of the wrongdoers on trial but to deliberate about the
          present state of affairs. So it is our duty to defer all accusations and only when we put
          someone on trial<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The Assembly sometimes acted as a
            court, for example, in cases of treason.</note> should this or that man speak before you
          against another who, he has convinced himself, is an offender. But if anyone has something
          practical or profitable to say, now is the time to declare it. For accusation is for those
          who have fault to find with past actions, but in deliberative session the discussion is
          solely about present and future actions. Therefore the present is no occasion for abuse or
          blame but for taking counsel together, it seems to me. For this reason I shall try to
          guard against falling myself into the error which I condemn in these men and to offer the
          advice that I think best in the present state of affairs.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="12">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I think that no man will deny, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          that it is the mark of a disloyal citizen and a low-minded man so to hate or favour anyone
          who enters into public life that he takes no thought for the State's best interests, but
          shapes his public utterances sometimes to vent his malice and sometimes to prove his
          friendship, as a number of those are doing who come forward here to speak. To these I
          would say no more than this: that in my opinion, if they have done something of the kind,
          their greatest offence is not this, but rather that they show themselves unprepared ever
          to stop doing it! <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>As for yourselves, I give you this
          advice: do not be guilty of self-ruin and think it enough if you punish these men when you
          see fit; but, while holding them in check so far as lies in your power, you must
          yourselves, as becomes men deliberating on behalf of the State, put aside your own private
          feuds and aim at what is most to the common good, reflecting that the punishment of no
          individual, nor even of all the politicians in a body, can square the account if once the
          laws should be destroyed on which your very life depends.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Or, less probably, &ldquo;the laws of which you are in
            charge.&rdquo;</note></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="13">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Perhaps it might seem offensive to certain persons, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, if someone, an ordinary citizen and one of the
          common people like yourselves, should come forward after others who are eminent for both
          long political experience and reputation among you have already stated their opinions, and
          say that he thinks the others are not only wrong but not even near to discerning what
          ought to be done. Nevertheless, I feel so confident that I am going to give more
          profitable counsel than theirs that I shall not hesitate to declare all they have said to
          be worthless. I think that you too would be doing well if you kept in view, not the
          speaker, but the advice being offered. For the right thing, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is to extend your goodwill, not to certain
          persons as though by hereditary privilege, but to those who from time to time offer the
          best counsel.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="14">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I should like you to listen attentively to what I am going to say, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; it is not unimportant. I wonder just why it is
          that, before we come up to the Assembly, any one of you whom a person may chance to meet
          is prepared to say readily by what means the present state of affairs may be improved; and
          then again, the minute you leave the Assembly, each man will be just as ready to say what
          we ought to do. But when we are met together and dealing with these problems, you hear
          anything rather than this from certain speakers. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Then has
          each one of you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, the gift of
          deciding what ought to be done, and does each know how to state the duties of the rest,
          while he is reluctant himself to do his own, and then again, does each man as an
          individual, as if to give the impression of being one who would of course promptly do what
          is best, find fault with everyone else, but as a body are you committed to fighting shy of
          voting such measures as will ensure that you will one and all become engaged in performing
          some duty to the State? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Well then, if you really think
          that no crisis will arrive to make a breach in this fence of evasiveness, it would be
          grand to carry on after this fashion. But if you see your troubles drawing nearer, you
          must plan that you shall not have to grapple with them at close range when it is possible
          to forestall them from a distance, and that you shall not have those whom you now
          disregard exulting later on at your discomfiture</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="15">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>As for the problems now confronting the State, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, even though things are not as they should be, I do not consider it
          altogether difficult to discover by what action one may effect an improvement. I judge, on
          the other hand, that the manner in which I must speak to you about them means very grave
          irritation; not because you will fail to understand what a person will say but because you
          seem to me to have become so accustomed to hearing many untruths and anything rather than
          what best meets your needs, that I fear it may be the lot of the man who now makes the
          best proposal to earn for his reward at your hands the hostility which would properly have
          been the due of those who have deceived you. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For I
          observe that often you hate, not those who are to blame for your troubles, but those who
          have most recently made mention of them to you.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf.
              <bibl n="Dem. 1.16">Dem. 1.16</bibl>.</note> Nevertheless, although I am so precisely
          measuring this hazard, I still think that I must put all other subjects aside and confine
          myself to saying what I think is the best advice about the present situation.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="16">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I should have wished, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that you
          treat yourselves with that benevolence which you are accustomed to practise toward all
          other peoples. As it now is, you are better at rectifying the woes of others than you are
          at taking to heart the troubles which befall yourselves. Someone may perhaps say, of
          course, that this is exactly what brings the greatest glory to the State&mdash;to have
          deliberately chosen to assume many risks for the sake of sheer justice with no thought of
          selfish advantage. Now, while I for one believe this reputation which prevails concerning
          the State to be true and desire it to be, yet I assume it also to be an obligation of
          prudent men to exercise as much foresight in their domestic affairs as in those of
          strangers, so that you may show yourselves to be not only men of goodwill but sensible
          also.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="17">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Perhaps it really is the duty, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          of one who wishes to recommend some measure to you to attempt to speak in such a way that
          you will find it possible to hear him to the end; but otherwise his duty is to leave aside
          all other themes and discuss only those matters you are considering, and these as briefly
          as possible. For I do not think it due to any lack of speeches that now once more you
          observe all your affairs to be in a muddle, but the reason is that some are orating and
          playing politics for their own gain, and others, who have so far not given evidence of
          this offence, are more concerned to be thought good speakers than that some concrete good
          may be effected by what they say. As for me, that I may not unwittingly do the opposite of
          what I myself say is right, and say more about other matters than about those of which I
          have risen to speak, I shall disregard all other topics and endeavor to tell you forthwith
          what I recommend.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="18">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I think that you would rightly pay attention, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, if any man should promise to demonstrate that in the matters you
          are considering justice and expediency coincide. Now I believe that I shall do this
          without difficulty if you on your part will comply with a very slight request of mine. Let
          none of you, according as one or another has an opinion about the present situation, be
          positive that he is right in all his conclusions; but, if it turns out that something be
          said against these, let him consider it, listening to all the points patiently, and then,
          if some suggestion seems to have been rightly made, adopt it. For the measure that
          succeeds will belong no less to you who adopted it than to him who proposed it to you.
          Surely the first step toward sound deliberation is not to have reached a decision before
          you have heard the discussions upon which you should base your decision. For the occasion
          and the method of ratifying your resolutions and of deciding in the first instance what
          seems expedient are not the same.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">A measure was often
            debated several times before being ratified. Debate should be leisurely, ratification
            prompt and decisive: <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 21. 3">Dem. Ex. 21. 3</bibl>.</note></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="19">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I have come forward, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to
          consult with you whether I should speak or not, and I shall explain to you for what reason
          I am at a loss how to decide this by myself. It is obligatory, in my opinion, that one who
          seeks to gratify neither himself nor certain people, but wishes to say on your behalf what
          he is convinced is most expedient, should both support good measures proposed by either
          side, and, conversely, oppose all unfair proposals which either side thinks fit to urge.
          Accordingly, if you should submit to hear both these lines of argument briefly, you would
          deliberate much better on the remaining questions; but, if you should desert me before
          learning my views, it would be my lot to be put in the wrong with both sides without being
          guilty of injustice to either. Now, I do not deserve to be in this plight. Therefore, if
          you bid me, I am prepared to speak; otherwise it is well for me to keep silence.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="20">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I consider it both just and profitable, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, for you to lay aside charges and accusations when we are to
          deliberate, and for each one to say what he thinks is best concerning the matters before
          you. For while we all understand that through the fault of certain men our affairs are in
          a bad way, it is the task of your counsellor to suggest by what means they may be
          improved. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Moreover, I for my part regard as stern
          accusers of the wrongdoers, not those who scrutinize their past actions on such occasions
          as this, when they will pay no penalty, but those who prove able to offer such advice as
          may effect some amelioration of our present situation; for with the help of these men it
          would also be possible at your leisure<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Or,
            &ldquo;when you are at peace.&rdquo;</note> to bring those guilty men to
          justice. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Accordingly, I consider all other topics to be
          out of place but shall attempt to tell you what I think would be expedient in the matters
          you are now considering, making this request only: if after all I do make mention of any
          of those things done in the past, do not think that I am speaking by way of accusation,
          but in order that, having shown you wherein you then erred, I may now avert your suffering
          the same misfortune again.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="21">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>If all along, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, we had been as
          peaceful as at this moment, playing into the hands of no politician,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">On subservience to politicians see <bibl n="Dem. 3.30">Dem.
            3.30-32</bibl>, the reference is to Aeschines; the opening lines seem to refer to the
            Amphissian War of <date value="-339">339</date> B.C. and its sequels: <bibl n="Dem. 17.142">Dem. 17.142-153</bibl>.</note> I believe that the events which now
          have happened would never have taken place and that in many other respects we should be in
          better shape. But of late, because of the high-handedness of some men, it is impossible
          either to come forward or speak, or in general to get in a word.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">For organized interruptions in the Assembly see <bibl n="Dem. 13.20">Dem.
              13.20</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 2.29">Dem. 2.29-30</bibl>.</note>
          <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>The consequences of this are numerous and perhaps not to
          our liking. Accordingly, if what you wish is to be all the time getting this kind of news,
          to be considering what you ought to do, and to be in such a plight as at present, you will
          vote the same measures as for years past&mdash;to launch triremes, to embark, to pay a
          special war-tax and all that sort of thing, forthwith. Then in three or five days, if
          rumors of hostile movements cease and our enemies become inactive, you will once more
          assume that there is no longer need to act. This is just what happened when we heard that
          Philip was in the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName> and again when the
          pirate triremes put in at Marathon.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt"><date value="-352">352</date> B.C.; <bibl n="Dem. 3.4">Dem. 3.4-5</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 4.34">Dem.
              4.34</bibl>.</note>
          <milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>For just as a man would properly employ a force in arms, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you are accustomed to handle your
          deliberations, with dispatch. What you ought to do, however, is to deliberate at leisure
          but put your decisions into effect with speed,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Contrast
              <bibl n="Thuc. 1.70">Thuc. 1.70</bibl>.</note> and to make up your minds to this, that
          unless you shall provide an adequate food-supply and place some general of good sense in
          charge of the war, and be willing to abide by the decisions so taken, you will have to
          your credit just a lot of decrees, and while you will have squandered all that you have
          spent, your interests will be not a whit advanced and in angry mood you will put on trial
          whomever it pleases you. For my part, I wish you to be seen repelling your enemies before
          sitting in judgement on your fellow-citizens; for it is a crime for us to make war upon
          one another rather than upon them. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>In order, therefore, that I may not censure only&mdash; the easiest of all
            things<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf.<bibl n="Dem. 1.16">Dem. 1.16</bibl>.</note>
          shall explain how I think you may accomplish this, requesting you not to make an uproar or
          get the idea that I am merely procrastinating and interposing delay. For it is not those
          who say &ldquo;At once&rdquo; and &ldquo;Today&rdquo; who speak most to
          the point, for we could not prevent by the present reinforcement what has already
          happened; but it will be the man who shows what armament, once furnished, will be able to
          hold out until we either get the upper hand of our enemies or by accepting terms bring the
          war to an end. For in this way we should no longer suffer aggression in time to come.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The preceding six lines are found also in <bibl n="Dem. 4.14">Dem. 4.14-15</bibl></note></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="22">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I believe that all of you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          would agree that our city, when deliberating about any of her domestic affairs, should
          have as much concern for advantage as for justice, but when the question has to do with
          our allies or the general interests of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, as
          in the present instance, she ought to be mindful of nothing so scrupulously as of justice.
          Because in the former matters, expediency suffices, but in such as the latter, honor as
          well ought to play a part. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For, of the actions themselves
          they become arbiters to whom the decisions belong; of the opinion formed of them, however,
          no man is so powerful as to be the arbiter; but whatever opinion shall attach to the
          actions, such is that which the multitude spreads abroad concerning the actors. Therefore
          you must look to it diligently that your actions shall be manifestly just. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>By rights, of course, all men should feel toward those who are
          wronged as each would think fit to demand of all others to feel toward himself if
          something should go amiss, which I pray may not happen. Since, however, certain persons,
          contrary to their own judgement, take the opposite stand, I shall first address a few
          words to them and thereupon offer what I assume to be the best advice for you.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="23">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>No small detriment you would esteem it, as I believe, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, if some offensive opinion and discreditable to
          the city should come to prevail abroad. Now then, right as you are in this judgement, your
          actions in general are not consistent with it; but time and again you are misled into
          doing things that not even you yourselves would say are honorable. And while I am aware
          that all men receive with more pleasure those who praise than those who rebuke, yet I do
          not think it right in quest of this goodwill to say anything but what I judge to be in
          your interests.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 1.16">Dem.
            1.16</bibl>.</note>
          <milestone n="2" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>If, then, at the outset your judgement had been sound, there would have been no need to
          assume that as a body you must do what as individuals you condemn, so that this very thing
          should not be happening which is now going on. While every man goes about saying
          &ldquo;How disgraceful, how shocking!&rdquo; and &ldquo;How long will this
          business go on?&rdquo;, every man sitting here with you is himself one of those who do
          such things. As for me, I should certainly have wished that, just as I know it pays you to
          listen to the speaker who makes the best proposals, so I might be sure it would also pay
          the one who made them; for so I should be much happier.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This clause is found also in <bibl n="Dem. 4.51">Dem. 4.51</bibl>.</note> As it now is,
          I have fears; nevertheless, I shall not be deterred from saying what I am confident will
          prove to be best, even if you shall not be convinced.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="24">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Even if the speaker were one who had never spoken on another subject before you, men of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, surely now, discussing the
          groundless charges which the ambassadors<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Chians,
            Byzantines and Rhodians. See. <bibl n="Dem. 15.3">Dem. 15.3</bibl> and the Introduction
            to that oration.</note> bring against the State, he might well, I think, meet with
          indulgence from all.</p>
				<p>For in certain other contests to be worsted by one's adversaries may seem to be not so
          much a reproach as a misfortune, because luck and the officials in charge and many other
          factors play a part in the winning or the losing of a contest; but in the event of men
          having no self-justification to offer worthy of the merits of their case we shall find the
          reproach of those found in this plight to attach to nothing but their intelligence.
            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Surely if it had been some other people before whom
          these speeches about you were being made, I do not think these men would be finding it so
          easy to lie nor would the hearers have tolerated many of their assertions. But as things
          now are, I think that in general all and every take advantage of your simplicity and in
          particular these men have done so on the present occasion; for they have found in you such
          an audience for charges against yourselves as they would have found in no other people, as
          I know for a certainty. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>And well may you, in my view, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          for this turn of events be grateful to the gods and detest these men.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Chians and Byzantines.</note> For the fact that they see the democracy of
            <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, which used to address you much more
          presumptuously than these, now become your suppliant, I consider a piece of good fortune
          for the State; but that these stupid men should neither consider this, though it is so
          plain to see, nor that you have often gone to the rescue of them one after another, and
          that you have been put to more trouble rectifying the errors of their rashness and
          infatuation, whenever they have chosen to make war on their own account, than in managing
          your own affairs, might well have aroused in you the profoundest wrath, it seems to me.
            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Perhaps, however, it is the destiny of these people
          never to be wise when prosperous.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The same charge is
            made in <bibl n="Dem. 15.16">Dem. 15.16</bibl>.</note> Still it is the fitting thing for
          you, because you are who you are and because of the past performance of the State, to make
          a point of demonstrating to all men that, as in former times, so now and always we prefer
          to practise justice, though certain others, wishing to enslave their own fellow-citizens,
          accuse them falsely before us.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="25">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>If you were of the same mind, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          when listening to the speeches of those who counsel you and when judging the outcome of
          measures taken, offering advice would be the safest thing in the world. For if you met
          with good luck and success&mdash;because one must always use words of good
          omen&mdash;the credit for these would be common to yourselves and the sponsor. But, as
          things are, you most enjoy listening to those who say what you wish to hear, yet often you
          charge them with deceiving you if everything does not turn out the way you would like,
            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>not taking this into account, that of the task of
          studying and calculating the best measures, within human limitations, and of explaining
          them to you, each man is himself the arbiter, but of their execution and profitableness
          the control, for the most part, lies in the power of Fortune.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demosthenes defends himself by this argument in <bibl n="Dem. 18.192">Dem.
              18.192-193</bibl>: <foreign lang="greek">to\ me\n ga\r pe/ras, w(s a)\n o( dai/mwn
              boulhqh=|, pa/ntwn gi/gnetai: h( de\ proai/resis au)th\ th\n tou= sumbou/lou dia/noian
              dhloi=</foreign></note> As a human being it is enough for a man to stand accountable
          for his own thinking; but to stand accountable also for the play of Fortune is quite
          impossible. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Certainly, if a way had been discovered
          whereby a man might address the people with safety to the State and without hazard to
          himself, it would be madness to ignore it; but since it is a certainty that one who
          declares an opinion on actions about to be taken will share in the benefits therefrom
          accruing and participate in the credit for these benefits, I consider it shameful to speak
          as a loyal citizen, yet not face the test if some danger shall arise therefrom.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">He refers to the anger of the Assembly.</note></p>
				<p>So I pray the gods that such measures as are destined to profit both the State and myself
          may occur to my mind to suggest and to you to adopt. For to seek by any and every means to
          be on the winning side is either one of two things, I should say, a sign of mental
          derangement or of one who is bent on selfish gain.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="26">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>If only it might be, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that,
          when assembling to discuss the present questions or any others, the seemingly best for you
          and the really best might be one and the same! It is your duty, however, when deliberating
          on matters of supreme importance and of general concern, to be willing to listen to all
          your counsellors, as it seems to me, thinking it shameful, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to create an uproar now when a number of
          speakers wish to propose some measure, but later to enjoy hearing these same men
          denouncing what has been done. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>I myself know, and I think
          you do too, that just now those please you most who express the same views that you
          yourselves wish to hear; but if something turns out contrary to what you now
          expect&mdash;and may this not be the case &mdash;that you will believe that these
          men have deceived you, while those whom you cannot now endure you will then think to be
          right. In reality, it is those who have done most to persuade you of the wisdom of the
          proposals which you are now considering who have most to gain by the opposition securing
          an opportunity to speak. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>For if it shall be able to show
          that the proposals which seem best to these men are not the best, when as yet no mistake
          has been made, it will by so doing nullify their risks for them<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">They will be spared the anger of the Assembly: <bibl n="Dem. 14">Dem.
              14</bibl>, conclusion</note>; yet if it fails to persuade, they will later, at any
          rate, have no occasion to find fault, but, having obtained all that it was the duty of men
          to give, a hearing, they will rightly be content if defeated, and along with all the rest
          share in the outcome, whatever that maybe.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="27">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p><note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The beginning of <bibl n="Dem. 15">Dem. 15</bibl> is
            identical.</note> I think it your duty, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, when deliberating about such important matters to allow freedom of
          speech to every one of your counsellors. For my own part, I have never at any time
          considered it difficult to make you understand what proposals are best&mdash;for, to
          put it simply, I think you all have decided that,&mdash;but only difficult to persuade
          you to act on these proposals. For when a measure has been approved and confirmed by a
          vote, it is then as far from being put into effect as before it was approved. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>It certainly is something for which I think you owe gratitude to
          the gods that those who, through their own arrogance, not long ago made war upon you now
          repose the hopes of their own deliverance in you alone, and you have good reason to be
          delighted at the present opportunity. For the effect will be, if you decide about it as
          you ought, to rid ourselves, by the language of deeds, of the slanders circulated by the
          traducers of our city, and also to maintain our good repute.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="28">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>The hopes aroused by what has been previously said, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, are great and glorious; I fancy that most of
          you have been somewhat swayed by them without really thinking. As for myself, I have never
          been minded to tell you for the sake of your momentary gratification anything that I did
          not think would also subsequently prove to be of advantage. Naturally it is a trait common
          to most men to like those who join in applauding them, whatever they do, but to dislike
          those who find fault with them. Nevertheless, the sensible man should always strive to
          make reason the master of his feelings. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>I should have
          been glad, myself, to see you happy at putting into effect the measures going to profit
          you, that I might have been found both meeting your wishes and giving good advice. But
          since I see you about to try the opposite measures, I think I ought to speak against them,
          even if I shall be hated for it by certain persons. So, if you will not endure to hear
          even one word from me, you will be thought to be preferring such a course of action, not
          through an error of judgement, but through your natural propensity to do wrong. However,
          if you do listen, you may perhaps be won over to the other view, which I think would be
          most to your advantage. But if you refuse to listen, some will plead ignorance of what was
          advantageous, while others&mdash;well, what a man likes to say he will say.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="29">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>In the first place, it is nothing strange, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that among you are found some who, when action has to be taken,
          will speak against measures already voted.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The Assembly
            could vote at any time to reopen the debate. See <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 34">Dem. Ex.
              34</bibl>.</note> Now, if they were doing this after you had given them the floor
          while still deliberating, it would be the right thing to denounce them for insisting upon
          speaking a second time to questions on which they had been defeated; as it is, there is
          nothing unreasonable in their desiring to express views which then you did not submit to
          hear, <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>and it is you who may well be criticized, men of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, because, when you deliberate about
          something, you do not allow each to say what he thinks, but, if the one side captures you
          first by their plea, you would hear no one from the other side. From this arises a
          situation embarrassing for you, because the men whose advice, before going wrong, you
          might have followed, you applaud later for denouncing your mistakes. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>This very thing is about to happen to you again, it seems to me, unless
          on the present occasion, giving impartial audience to all, and submitting to this tedious
          duty, you shall choose the best proposals and judge those who find any fault with them to
          be no loyal citizens.</p>
				<p>Now I have thought it fair to tell you first of all my views about the questions you are
          considering, in order that, if these meet with your favour, I may also explain the rest of
          my ideas, but, if you disapprove, that I may neither bore you nor tire myself out.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="30">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>It was your duty, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, before going
          to war to have considered what armament would be available for the coming campaign, but
          if, as a matter of fact, war was not foreseen, it was your duty to have considered also
          the question of armament on that occasion when you were deliberating for the first time
          about war after it had become certain. If you shall say that you have commissioned many
          armies which your commanders<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Possibly Chares and
            Charidemus, who failed to save <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> in
              <date value="-348">348</date> B.C.</note> have ruined, no one will accept this excuse
          of you. For the same people cannot both absolve those in charge of their operations and
          claim that through fault of these men these operations are not succeeding. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Since, however, past events cannot be altered<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This commonplace is found also in <bibl n="Dem. 18.192">Dem.
            18.192</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 3.6">Dem. 3.6</bibl>.</note> and it is necessary to
          safeguard our interests as present facilities permit, I see no fitting occasion for laying
          charges but shall try to offer what I think is the best counsel.</p>
				<p>Now, first of all, you must admit this principle, that it is the duty of every man to
          apply to the task the same superabundance of eagerness and emulation that he displayed of
          indifference in times past; because thus there is a bare hope that we may be able, though
          far behind in the pursuit, to overtake what we have let slip. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>In the next place, there must be no discouragement over what has
          happened, because what is worst in the past is the best hope for the future. What, then,
          do I mean by this, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>? That it is
          because you do nothing that you ought to do that your affairs are in a bad way; since if
          you were doing everything you should and your affairs were in this state, there would be
          not even a hope of improvement.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This is called a paradox
            in <bibl n="Dem. 9.5">Dem. 9.5</bibl>; cf. <bibl n="Dem. 4.2">Dem.
          4.2</bibl>.</note></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="31">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Nothing is more mischievous, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          than that those who address your Assembly should both censure and employ the same
          practices. For there is no man so unintelligent as to deny that to behave factiously among
          themselves and to accuse one another when no one is on trial<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">See <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 11">Dem. Ex. 11</bibl> and note.</note> means damage
          to your interests. I think myself that these men would be better citizens if, when
          addressing the Assembly, they should turn the contentiousness they feel toward one another
          against the enemies of the State; and to you I recommend not to take sides with either of
          these factions or to consider how either one is to gain the mastery, but how you as a body
          are to prevail over your enemies. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>And I pray to the gods
          that those who out of contentiousness or spite or any other motive express any other
          sentiments than those they believe to be advantageous may cease to do so; for to invoke a
          curse when speaking in council is perhaps unseemly. Therefore, while I should myself lay
          the blame for this bad state of affairs, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, upon no one except these men as a class, and although I think you
          ought to exact an accounting of them when you have the leisure, yet for the present I
          think you should consider only how the existing situation may be bettered.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="32">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I should have wished, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that
          some of the speakers had displayed as much eagerness to present the best proposals as they
          did to be thought good speakers, in order that these men might have been regarded as
          honest instead of clever at speaking and that your interests, just as is proper, might
          have been in better shape. As it now is, however, some seem to me to be entirely content
          with the reputation for speaking, but to be taking no thought for what will subsequently
          befall you. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>And certainly I wonder whether speeches of
          this sort are capable of deceiving the speaker as much as those to whom they are
          addressed, or whether these men knowingly express before the Assembly opinions directly
          opposed to what they themselves think best. For if they are unaware that he who is going
          to do what requires to be done must not have audacity based upon words but power based
          upon armament, nor yet self-confidence based upon the assumption that our enemies will be
          weak, but confidence that we shall overmaster them even if they shall be strong, the
          elegance of their speeches has prevented them, as it seems, from apprehending the most
          vital facts. Yet if they should not even deny awareness of these facts, and some ulterior
          motive underlies their predilection for this conduct, how can one help assuming that this
          motive, whatever it may be, is base? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>As for me, I shall not be deterred from saying what I think, although I see that you have
          been bewitched<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This meaning of the verb comes from
            magical practices; see Lexicon under <foreign lang="greek">a)gw/gimon</foreign>.</note>;
          for it would be foolish, because you have wrongly yielded to the spell of oratory, for the
          man who in his turn is going to offer better proposals and much more to your advantage, to
          give in to fear. And I ask of you to listen patiently, bearing in mind that you would not
          have formed your present opinions either unless you had listened to the speeches by which
          you have been persuaded. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>Accordingly, just as you would
          have thought it necessary to test a coin if you were judging what its worth might be, so I
          ask of you to scrutinize in the light of what we have to say against it the speech that
          has been made, and if you find it to your advantage, agree with the speaker, and may good
          fortune attend you; but if, after all, as you examine each detail, it shall seem alien to
          your interests, to change your plans before falling into error and to adopt the counsels
          that are right.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="33">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Most of all I should desire, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          that you be convinced by the words I am about to utter, but if after all it should turn
          out otherwise, I should prefer above all else that by me, at least, they had been
          spoken.</p>
				<p>It is a difficult thing, as it seems, not only to explain to you what ought to be done,
          but even to discover it by solitary reflection. Anyone would observe this if he believed
          you would consider, not his speech, but the business upon which you are engaged, and set
          more value upon being thought an honest man than upon showing himself to be a clever
          speaker. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>I, at any rate,&mdash;so help me
          Heaven&mdash;after it occurred to me to reflect upon our present problems, began to
          hit upon themes, and no end of them, to which you would have listened not without
          pleasure. For instance, on the theme &ldquo;You are the most just of the
          Greeks,&rdquo; I observed and now observe many changes to ring, and again,
          &ldquo;You are born of the noblest ancestors,&rdquo; and many such topics.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">These were stock topics of funeral speeches: see <bibl n="Dem. 60">Dem. 60</bibl> and the Introduction to the same</note> Yet these themes,
          though affording pleasure so long as they are being aired, after that vanish away;
            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>and it is the duty of the speaker to show himself the
          adviser of some course of action through which the gain of some real benefit shall also
          afterwards accrue to you.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 8.73">Dem.
              8.73</bibl>.</note> Such a policy as this I know by now from experience to be rare and
          hard to discover. Neither is it enough merely to get a vision of such policies unless a
          man shall also be able to convince you, who jointly are to assume the responsibility. On
          the contrary, there is an obligation resting upon both alike, upon me to tell you what I
          have convinced myself is advantageous, upon you to listen, to judge and, if it is your
          pleasure, to adopt.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="34">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>It was not hard to see, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, the
          other day when you thought there was no need to hear those who desired to speak in
          opposition to the views of a certain speaker,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">It has
            been suggested that <foreign lang="greek">o( dei=na</foreign> was a blank to be filled
            in as occasion required, the <title>Exordia</title> being composed in advance of
            use.</note> that what is now coming to pass would occur&mdash;that those who were
          then prevented from speaking would do so before a subsequent meeting of the Assembly.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">See <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 29">Dem. Ex. 29</bibl> and
            note.</note> If, therefore, you shall do the same as before, and refuse to listen to
          those who wish to support the decisions then approved, these men in turn will take the
          matter to the next meeting and denounce these decisions. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>In no way, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, could your
          situation be made worse nor could you show yourselves more absurd than if none of your
          decisions should seem to be finally settled and, disregarding the policies that pay, you
          should achieve no forward step, but, like the crowds at shows, side with those who
          captivate you first.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">In both Greek and Latin the word
            &ldquo;theater&rdquo; often denotes the spectators or audience. <bibl n="Sen. Ep. 7.11">Seneca Epist. 7.11</bibl>, wrote: &ldquo;for we are audience
            &lpar;theatrum&rpar; enough for each other.&rdquo;</note> Do not let this
          happen, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, but performing this
          tedious duty and giving impartial audience to both sides, first choose a policy you will
          also carry out and then assume that whoever opposes measures thus once sanctioned is
          unprincipled and disloyal to you. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>For while it is
          pardonable that a man who has not obtained a hearing should feel convinced that he has
          himself better plans thought out than those approved by you, yet to go on acting
          shamelessly after you have given a hearing and decided between alternatives, instead of
          giving in to the judgement of the majority and retiring, would plainly justify suspicion
          of some other motive by no means honorable. As for me, although I should have thought it
          proper to remain silent on this occasion had I observed you abiding by your previous
          decisions&mdash;for I am one of those who are convinced that these are to your
          advantage&mdash;yet, now that certain members seem to have changed their minds because
          of the speeches made by these men, even though you perhaps know that what they say is
          neither true nor for your good, I will nevertheless make this clear in case you are
          unaware of it.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="35">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>It would have been just and proper, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, for each member then to try to convince you of what he believed to
          be best when you were considering these matters for the first time, in order that two
          evils might not be resulting which are above all others damaging to the
          city&mdash;that no decision of yours should be proving final and that you should be
          convicting yourselves of madness by changing your minds. Since, however, certain men who
          then kept silence are now finding fault, I wish to address a few words to them. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>For I am amazed at the political procedure of these men, or rather I consider it vile.
          For if, though free to recommend measures when you are considering questions, they choose
          instead to denounce decisions once made, they play the part of doubledealers,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The meaning of &ldquo;sycophant&rdquo; is made
            clear in <bibl n="Dem. 18.188">Dem. 18.188-189</bibl>.</note> not as they claim, of men
          of goodwill. I should like to ask them&mdash;and what I am about to say is not to
          become the signal for any tirade&mdash;just why, since they praise the Spartans in all
          other respects, they do not imitate the most admirable of all their practices, but rather
          do the very opposite. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>For they say, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that among them each man airs any opinion he
          may have until the question is put, but when the decision has been ratified, they all
          approve it and work together, even those who opposed it. Therefore, though few, they
          prevail over many and by actions well timed they get what they cannot get by war; nor does
          any occasion or means of effecting what is to their own advantage escape them; not, by
          Zeus, as we do who, thanks to these men and their like, in trying to get the better of one
          another instead of the enemy,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 2.25">Dem. 2.25</bibl>.</note> have wasted all our time, <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>and if anyone is for making peace in time of war, we hate him, and if anyone talks war
          in time of peace, we fight him, and if anyone advocates keeping quiet and minding our own
          business, we claim that he is wrong too, and in general we are overfull of recriminations
          and empty hopes.</p>
				<p>&ldquo;What then, Sir,&rdquo; someone may say, &ldquo;what do you recommend,
          since you find fault with this conduct?&rdquo; By Zeus, I will tell you.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="36">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>In the first place, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I am not
          altogether sure that a man would reasonably fear on your account lest your deliberations
          would be the worse for your refusing to listen to your counsellors. For, to begin with,
          Fortune&mdash;to whom be thanks&mdash;arranges much of your business to take care
          of itself, so well that you would pray for nothing better, because little of it would be
          in good shape through such foresight as is exercised by those in authority. Next, you know
          in advance, not only what speeches each man will make, but also with what motives each one
          harangues you, and if it were not spiteful, I should also have said, for what price.
            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>I think you are prudent in reducing to a minimum the
          time for being cheated. If I were intending to speak in the same vein as the rest, I
          should not have thought it necessary to bore you by speaking. As it is, I think I have
          something to say that will be worth your while to hear, and utterly different from what is
          expected by the majority. It will be short. Listen and examine it, and, if it pleases you,
          adopt it.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="37">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I shall make the beginning of my speech both short and reasonable, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, nor shall I deliver the whole of it. For I
          believe that, while it is the way of a man who intends deception to cast about for a plan
          whereby he may conceal from you, his hearers, by means of his words the disagreeable
          aspects of the situation, on the other hand, the first duty of a man who has resolved to
          deal candidly with you is to declare which side he has come forward to endorse, in order
          that, <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>if after hearing this statement you are willing to
          hear the sequel, he may enlighten you and explain what measures seem best to himself, but
          if you shall reject his views, that he may have done with the matter and neither annoy you
          nor tire himself out.</p>
				<p>This, then, will be my first statement: It is my opinion that the democratic party in
            <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> has been wronged and that it is
          your duty to obtain justice for them.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The democracy was
            overthrown in <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> after the Social
            War in <date value="-355">355</date> B.C.: <bibl n="Dem. 13.8">Dem. 13.8</bibl> and
              <bibl n="Dem. 15.19">Dem. 15.19</bibl>.</note> For obtaining this justice I have a
          plan to propose when once I have demonstrated that they have been wronged and that it is
          your duty to go to their aid.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="38">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>First of all, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, it is not
          altogether surprising that those who wish to tender you advice do not readily find the
          words, because, when the conditions that require consideration are bad, it is inevitable
          that the recommendations made concerning them should also be disagreeable. Of course, if
          by your refusing to listen there is hope of this situation becoming better, that is the
          thing to do, but if everything is going to get worse and nothing better by so doing, why
          should you, having allowed things to come to the worst, after a longer interval than has
          now elapsed, and with greater difficulty, try to save the situation, though, starting from
          present conditions, it is still possible even now to set things to rights and effect a
          change for the better? <milestone n="2" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Certainly it is reasonable for you to feel angry after these unhappy experiences; but to
          vent your anger, not upon the parties responsible, but upon everybody in turn, ceases to
          be either reasonable or right: because those who are in no way responsible for past events
          but can tell you how an improvement may be effected for the future would rightly meet with
          gratitude, not hostility, from you. If you treat these men with untimely irritation, you
          will make them hesitate to rise and speak. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>And yet I am
          myself not unaware that often it is the lot, not of those who are guilty, but of persons
          who get in the way of those who are angry, to suffer unpleasant consequences. In spite of
          this I have risen to advise you, for I have confidence myself that I shall not be found to
          be advocating any inferior measure, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, but have really better proposals to offer you than other
          speakers.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="39">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>The events that have occurred, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          are such as you have all heard, but you must not allow yourselves to be at all dismayed,
          reflecting that to be discouraged in the face of the present troubles is neither improving
          the situation nor worthy of yourselves. On the contrary, to consider it incumbent on
          yourselves to set these things to rights would manifestly be in keeping also with your
          reputation. Men such as you would profess to be should prove themselves superior to other
          breeds in times of stress. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>As for me, I should by no
          means have wished these calamities to come upon the city nor yet for you to suffer
          misfortune, but if, after all, this had to happen and was in store as something
          predestined, I consider it to your profit that these events have occurred just as they
          have. For the dispensations of Fortune exhibit sharp reversals and impartial visitations
          to both sides, whereas the events that follow upon the villainy of men make for sure
          defeat. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Now, while I am of the opinion that even those
          who have gained the upper hand are not unaware that, should you form your resolve and be
          stung to action by what has happened, it is not yet quite clear whether what has been done
          is good fortune or the opposite for them, yet if it turns out that the exploit has
          inspired them to become over-confident, this would already be another point in your
          favour. For the more they look down upon you, the sooner will they blunder.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="40">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I do not believe, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that you are
          deliberating upon this occasion concerning only the city you have in mind, but concerning
          all the allied cities. For however you decide concerning the city in question, the other
          cities, looking to this decision, will probably expect to receive the same treatment
          themselves. Consequently you must, for the sake both of doing what is best and of guarding
          your own reputation, strive earnestly that you may be clearly seen to be devising measures
          which are alike expedient and just. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now, the initiative in all such matters is in the hands of the generals. Most of these
          men, though they sail out under your orders, do not consider it their duty to cultivate
          those who are friendly to you, people whom they have taken over from their predecessors as
          men who have shared the same dangers as you throughout all our history, but each and all,
          having established their own private friendships, expect you to regard their personal
          flatterers as your friends also. But the facts are exactly the opposite. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>You could find no more bitter or inevitable enemies than these
          flatterers. For the more gains they make by deception, the greater is the number of
          offences for which they think they are due to be punished. And no one could feel goodwill
          toward those at whose hands he expects to suffer some harm. However, the present is
          perhaps not the time to denounce them. Instead, I shall give you the advice that I
          consider in your interests.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="41">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I no not suppose, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that there
          is one of all your number so disloyal to the city as not to feel distressed and pained by
          these events. If, then, it were possible by nursing indignation to render undone any of
          the things that have been done, this is what I should be urging upon you all. But since
          the facts are unalterable and you must take forethought whereby you may escape the same
          misfortune in the future, the keenness of your indignation, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, over what has now taken place ought to set the
          measure for your determination that the same shall not occur again, nor should you think
          that any of your advisers has such a wonderful plan to propose as will be capable of
          redressing the present evils without any of you shouldering a share of the burden. For no
          speech would be wonderful enough for that, only some divine intervention. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now the origin of this present state of affairs hinges upon this fact, that, for the sake
          of a momentary popularity with you, some of those who speak in this place declared to the
          Assembly: &ldquo;There is no need to pay a special war-tax or to do military service,
          but everything will take care of itself.&rdquo; To be sure, the absurdity of this
          ought to have been exposed by some other speaker&mdash;the sort of exposure that
          profits the State: still, even as things now are, it seems to me that Fortune is somehow
          kinder to you than are those at the head of affairs. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>For
          while the occurrence of one loss after another ought to be counted evidence of the
          villainy of those who are in charge, the fact that all your resources have not been
          destroyed long ago I, at least, judge to be a benefaction of the Fortune that attends you.
          In the interval, therefore, while Fortune allows a respite and is holding your foes in
          check, have a care for what lies in the future. Otherwise take heed lest at one and the
          same time you shall be bringing to justice those who have been appointed to the several
          posts, and your power, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, shall be
          declining; for it is impossible that this shall continue to stand, barring some miracle,
          if not one of you puts his hand to the task.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 3.35">Dem. 3.35-36</bibl>.</note></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="42">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>It is nothing out of the ordinary, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that those public men who are always and unceasingly agitating on
          behalf of the oligarchies should be convicted of doing so upon this occasion also. On the
          contrary, one might much more reasonably be astonished that you, though aware of the
          truth, repeatedly prefer to listen to them rather than to those who speak in your own
          defence. It may very well be that it is difficult to act wisely in all public matters,
          just as it is in private matters, but certainly it is wrong to take a light view of things
          of the very greatest importance. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Assuredly all other
          considerations are of less consequence, and when you listen good-naturedly to speeches on
          behalf of government efficiency<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">There is an ironical
            touch in <foreign lang="greek">politei/as</foreign> as if implying that oligarchy was
            the ideal form of government to those whose phrases he here quotes.</note> and killings
          and the overthrow of democracy, how can one help but consider that you too are out of your
          minds? For all other men profit by the example of their fellows and are themselves
          rendered much more cautious thereby,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">cf. <bibl n="Dem. 15.16">Dem. 15.16</bibl>.</note> but you, even when you hear what is happening
          to the rest of the Greeks are incapable of taking alarm, but the very thing that you
          consider men to be witless for awaiting as individuals you seem to me to be calmly
          awaiting yourselves as a community that is, to learn by bitter experience.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="43">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Perhaps none of you has ever inquired, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, just why men in adversity deliberate more wisely over their affairs
          than do the prosperous. This comes about for no other reason than this, that it is not
          natural for the prosperous to feel any alarm or to believe that such dangers as someone
          may report concern themselves; those, however, who are close in time to the mistakes
          through which they have come to adversity are rendered discreet with reference to future
          actions and inclined to moderation.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt"><bibl n="Aesch. Ag. 176">Aesch. Ag. 176-178</bibl> &ldquo;Zeus who sets mortals in the
            path of wisdom and hath enacted a law of learning by suffering.&rdquo;</note>
          <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>It therefore becomes serious-minded men at the very time
          that they enjoy the presence of Fortune at her best to show the greater eagerness to
          practise discretion. For no danger is so formidable that men who are on their guard cannot
          guard against it,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 4.3">Dem.
            4.3</bibl>.</note> and there is none that men who belittle it may not expect to suffer.
          I say this, not to frighten you needlessly, but in order that, when you hear rumors of
          danger, you may not despise them because of your present prosperity&mdash;they may
          come true unless you take forethought for your interests&mdash; but rather in order
          that, without waiting to learn by experience, you may forestall trouble, just as becomes
          men who at least claim to be second to none in point of discretion.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="44">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I assume, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that the time for
          humoring you and the time for recommending the measures I regard as best are not the same;
          for often, I observe, humoring you contrary to one's own judgement has earned more hatred
          than opposing at the outset. Now, if you all held the same opinions, I should not have
          come forward if you seemed to me to prefer the right course, considering it superfluous to
          speak before people doing the right thing of their own accord, nor again, if the contrary
          were true, for I should have thought that a lone person like myself was more likely to
          misapprehend the best measures than all of you. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>But since
          I see some of you holding the same views as myself and the opposite to those held by
          others, I shall try with the support of these to persuade those who differ. Now, if you
          shall think it right to refuse to listen, you will make a mistake; but if you will listen
          in silence and bear with me in this, one of two benefits will accrue to you: for either
          you will be persuaded if we seem to advocate something advantageous, or you will be more
          firmly convinced of the rightness of your own views; for if the grounds upon which we
          think you are going somewhat astray shall be proved valueless, with the benefit of
          argument you will this time have chosen the plans approved before.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="45">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I could wish, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that a certain
            person,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">See <bibl n="Dem. 61.4">Dem. 61.4</bibl>, note
            c.</note> who has won your approval as a speaker on the measures before you, might have
          deserved equal praise for the feasibility and workableness of his proposal. For I call the
          gods to witness that I bear the man no ill will and wish that his plan had been a good one
          for you. But do not forget, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          that making a good speech and choosing sound policies are miles apart, and that the one is
          the part of an orator and the other of a man of sense. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Now, you, the multitude, and especially the oldest among you, while not obliged to speak
          as well as the cleverest, for this art is for the practised speakers, are yet under
          obligation to have as much sense as they and even more, for it is long experience and
          &ldquo;having seen much&rdquo;<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 1.1-5">Hom. Od. 1.1-5</bibl>.</note> that begets this faculty in us. Do
          not therefore, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, show yourselves
          unaware in this crisis that valorous deeds and bold exploits by word of mouth, unless
          backed by ready armament and physical force, though pleasant to hear, are hazardous in
          action. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>For example, &ldquo;Do not leave a free hand
          to aggressors&rdquo;; you see what a fine slogan that is! Do not fail first to take a
          good look at the actual nature of the task. They must master the foe in battle who are
          really going to capture the majesty of this saying. For all things are easy to say, men of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, but not all are easy to do, for
          &ldquo;not so much toil and sweat come before speech as before action.&rdquo;<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt"><bibl n="Hes. WD 289-290">Hes. WD 289-290</bibl>
            &ldquo;But in front of virtue have the deathless gods set sweat.&rdquo;</note>
          <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>I do not think you are naturally inferior to the
          Thebans&mdash;I should be mad to say that&mdash;only less well prepared. What I do
          say is that now is the time to begin your preparation, since you have been negligent up to
          now, not the decisive struggle. For I am not speaking against the plan as a whole but I am
          opposed to your way of going about it.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="46">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>You have all seen, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, with what
          zest the ambassadors<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Probably the Chians, Byzantines and
            Rhodians: <bibl n="Dem. 15.3">Dem. 15.3</bibl>.</note> have denounced our city. For,
          apart from what I cannot imagine, they have attempted to lay all offences at your doors. I
          admit, if their charges were true, you might reasonably be grateful that they were thus
          denouncing you to your faces instead of to others; <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>but
          since they have used the privilege of speaking here to distort the truth, failing to
          mention some things from which you would justly derive great praise, and making charges
          that are false and inapplicable to you, it is right that you should consider them
          unprincipled, when once they have been proved guilty of such conduct as this. For if they
          prefer to be regarded as accomplished rhetoricians rather than truly fair-minded men, it
          is not likely that even they themselves would claim to be gentlemen. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>It is, of course, difficult to rise up to speak before you in your own
          defence, just as it is easy to speak against you. For, by Athena, I do not think that
          there are any other people in the whole world who would listen so complacently when
          reminded of their real faults as you do when you are reviled for faults that are not
          yours. What is more, I do not believe that even these men would lie to you with such
          effrontery if they were not aware of this, and if it were not clear in advance that of all
          people you are the most addicted to listening to whatever anyone may say against you.
            <milestone n="4" unit="section"/></p>
				<p>Now, if you must be punished for this fatuousness, to listen to undeserved charges
          against the State would be that penalty; but if something must, in all fairness, be said
          on behalf of the truth, it is for this purpose that I have come forward, confident, not
          that I shall unaided be able to speak with eloquence worthy of your past actions, but that
          these actions, <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>however one may speak, will be seen to be
          just. It would be my wish, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that
          you become equally willing listeners when you are being defended, and not, through having
          been beguiled, become all too eager to praise the speeches of these men. For no one would
          go on judging it vice on your part if you have been led astray by some clever speaker, but
          it would be thought vice on the part of those who devoted their energies to deceiving
          you.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="47">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I suppose, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you would all say
          you wish to have put into effect what each one considers best for the city. Quite so, but
          it happens that the same plan has not been judged the best by all of you; otherwise some
          of you would not be bidding the speaker &ldquo;Go on&rdquo; and others
          &ldquo;Sit down.&rdquo; Now, to those who hold the same measures to be expedient
          as does the one who is about to speak there is no need of a single word, for they are
          already convinced; but to those who think that the opposite course is for the best, I wish
          to speak briefly. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Unless you will listen, it is, of
          course, absolutely impossible to learn anything,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This
            commonplace appears also in <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 3">Dem. Ex. 3</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 4">Dem. Ex. 4</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 5">Dem. Ex. 5</bibl>.</note> any more than if
          you keep quiet when no one is speaking. But if you do listen it is impossible to miss one
          or the other of two benefits for either, being all persuaded and of the same mind, you
          will be more unanimous in your decision&mdash;and nothing better than this could
          happen for the present emergency&mdash;or else, if the speaker be unable to make his
          point, you will have more confidence in the decisions already reached. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Apart from these two possibilities, there is a suspicion, and by no
          means to your credit, that, although you have come to the assembly under obligation to
          choose the best plan on the basis of what shall be said, instead, you will be found,
          before reaching a judgement on the basis of the speeches, to have been convinced of
          something in your own minds, and this so strongly that you are not even willing to hear
          anything to the contrary.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="48">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Perhaps some of you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, regard me
          as a nuisance, speaking on the same subjects time after time. But if you scan things
          rightly, it is not I who shall justly bear the blame for this, but rather those who do not
          obey your decrees. For if those men had done at the outset what you enjoined, it would not
          have been necessary for us to speak a second time or, if they had complied on the second
          occasion, a third time. As it is, the more often you have voted what your duty demanded,
          the less those men, it seems to me, have been prepared to act upon it. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Previously, I confess by the gods, I did not know what was the point of
          the saying: &ldquo;Responsibility reveals the man.&rdquo;<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">On this topic Demosthenes quotes <bibl n="Soph. Ant. 175-190">Soph. Ant.
              175-190</bibl> in <bibl n="Dem. 19.247">Dem. 19.247</bibl>.</note> But now I think I
          could even tell another what it means. For the officials, or some of them&mdash; to
          avoid saying all&mdash;feel not even the slightest regard for your decrees but
          consider how they shall make some gain. Certainly, if it had been feasible for me to make
          a payment, I might have been justly rebuked for this very reason, if I chose to annoy you
          through balking at a paltry expenditure. But as things are, it is not feasible, as these
          men themselves have not failed to observe. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>What is more,
          if, in the case of a service<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Public services required of
            wealthy citizens at their own expense were called <foreign lang="greek">lh|tourgi/ai</foreign>; these are to be distinguished from services to which salaries
            were attached, <foreign lang="greek">u(phresi/ai</foreign>: see <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 52">Dem. Ex. 52</bibl> and note.</note> due to you they think I am going to leave it to
          themselves to decide, they are fools. And, perhaps, they both wish and expect it; this I
          will not do, but if they will allow me, I shall launch the ship and do my duty; otherwise,
          I shall reveal to you the names of those responsible.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demosthenes, as a member of a group &lpar;<foreign lang="greek">sunte/leia</foreign>&rpar; responsible for equipping a trireme under the system
            of Navy-Boards, protests against being assessed more than his equitable share.
            Apparently, the expenditures were specified in the decrees of the Assembly but the
            officials were making demands in excess of the specifications. For abuses of the system
            see <bibl n="Dem. 18.104">Dem. 18.104</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 21.155">Dem.
              21.155</bibl>. Demosthenes may have been chairman of a Navy-Board at the time; <bibl n="Dem. 21.157">Dem. 21.157</bibl>.</note></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="49">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>In my opinion, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, no intelligent
          citizen would deny that it is best of all for the city, preferably at the outset not to do
          anything inexpedient, but otherwise, that those should be on hand who will object at once.
          To this must be added, however, that you shall be willing to listen and learn; for nothing
          is gained by having a man who will give the best counsel unless he shall have people who
          will listen to him. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Neither would the following
          suggestion prove unprofitable as the next step, that whatever deceptions anyone shall
          practise upon you through some well-timed maneuver,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demosthenes in <bibl n="Dem. L. 2.14">Dem. L. 2.14</bibl> claimed to have been
            condemned, <foreign lang="greek">kairw=| tini\ lhfqei/s</foreign>, because his name
            appeared first on the list of those accused of complicity in the affair of
            Harpalus.</note> or the late hour of the day or by any other opening, that there should
          be someone who will scrutinize the measures a second time, when you, being arbiters of
          your own conduct, are willing to listen, so that of the measures should prove to be such
          as those assert who then persuaded you, you may put them into effect more wholeheartedly
          as having passed the test: but if, after all, they are found to be otherwise, that you may
          halt before going farther. For it would be a shocking thing that those who had failed to
          choose the best plan should be forced to put the worst into effect, and not have a chance
          to reconsider and choose from among other alternatives the plan that had stood second.
            <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Now while all other men, I observe, stand ready to
          submit to an accounting at any time, whenever they are confident that some measure of
          theirs has been honestly put through,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This principle was
            invoked against Aeschines: <bibl n="Dem. 19.2">Dem. 19.2</bibl>.</note> yet these men,
          on the contrary, resent it if you desire now to reverse your action in matters wherein you
          have made a mistake, thinking their deception ought to prevail rather than spend time on
          an inquiry. So, even if the majority of you are perhaps not unaware of pressure on the
          part of these men, it is still one's duty, once he has been given the floor, to declare
          what action he thinks best under the circumstances.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="50">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>Whatever measure is going to benefit the whole State, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I pray that all speakers will propose and you
          will adopt. I, at any rate, shall say what I have persuaded myself is most to your
          advantage, asking only this of you&mdash;that you neither consider those who urge you
          to take the field to be for this reason brave, nor those who undertake to oppose them to
          be for this reason cowards; for the test of speech and the test of action, men of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, are not the same; rather we must now
          show ourselves to have been wise in counsel and later, if in the end this proposal is
          adopted, display the deeds of courage. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Your enthusiasm, I
          allow, is worthy of all praise and such as a man of goodwill toward the State might pray
          for; but the more intense your enthusiasm the more foresighted you should now be to employ
          it as you ought. For you know that no choice of a course of action justifies itself unless
          the end it achieves be beneficial and honorable. I am sure I once heard here in your
          presence, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, a man who was thought
          to be lacking neither in sense nor in experience of war. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>I refer to Iphicrates,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Iphicrates died in <date value="-353">353</date> B.C. when Demosthenes was about thirty years of age. The
            orator's admiration is revealed in <bibl n="Dem. 21.62">Dem. 21.62-63</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 23.129">Dem. 23.129-131</bibl>.</note> who said, &ldquo;A general must so
          choose to risk a battle, that not this or that may result but just this,&rdquo; for
          such were his exact words. The meaning of this was obvious, for he meant &ldquo;that
          he might come off victorious.&rdquo; So, when you take the field, whoever is leader is
          master of you, but now each one of yourselves is a general. Thus it is your duty to show
          yourselves to have made such decisions as will inevitably be good for the State and that
          you shall not, for the sake of mere hopes of future goods, bring about something not so
          good as the prosperity you at present enjoy.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="51">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>I should have thought, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that no
          one who has a clean conscience about the measures taken would prefer a complaint against
          those who move to bring these matters to an accounting; for the more often one examines
          into them, the more the authors of them are bound to grow in esteem. These men themselves,
          however, seem to me to render it manifest that they have not acted with the State's
          interests in view. At any rate, just as if they were bound to be found guilty if they
          should come again to an accounting, they assume the defensive and say we are acting
          outrageously. And yet when you accuse of outrageous conduct those who wish to investigate,
          what are we citizens to say of those who in that very transaction have perpetrated a fraud
          against our own selves?</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="52">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>It would be the righteous thing, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, for you to feel the same anger toward those who attempt to deceive
          you as toward those who have been able to do so. For what it was in the power of these men
          to do has been done, and they led you along. That these designs have fallen short of
          success, credit is due to Fortune and to the fact that you are now wiser than when you
          were misled by these men. Yet the State, I believe, is so far from being able to exact
          justice of the wrongdoers, that it seems to me you must content yourselves if you shall be
          able to avoid sustaining loss; so formidable are the trickeries and chicaneries and, not
          to particularize, certain salaried public services<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The
            word <foreign lang="greek">u(phresi/ai</foreign> denotes services to which pay was
            attached; in all such the people took an avid interest, leaving unpaid offices to the
            wealthy: see <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 55.3">Dem. Ex. 55.3</bibl> and the <bibl n="Xen. Ath. 3">Xen. Const. Ath. 3</bibl>. These could readily be made channels of financial
            corruption. For <foreign lang="greek">lh|tourgi/ai</foreign>, services for which the
            performer himself paid, see <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 48">Dem. Ex. 48</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. L. 2.12">Dem. L. 2.12</bibl>, and notes.</note> that have been organized
          against you. To denounce the villainy of these men, however, would not at this juncture be
          most opportune: but I do wish to say what I deem advantageous with reference to the
          matters I have risen to discuss.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="53">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>The bickering and disorder, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          that are accustomed to injure the State all the time, have proceeded on this occasion from
          the same men as always. But the thing to do is not so much to blame these
          men&mdash;for perhaps they do it out of spite and quarrelsomeness and, what is the
          chief reason, because it pays them to do so&mdash;as to blame yourselves, men of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, if, after assembling on matters of
          common interest and prime importance, you sit and listen to private bickerings and cannot
          figure out for yourselves that the tirades directed against one another by all the
          speakers, when no one is on trial, cause you to pay the penalties for the offences of
          which they convict one another. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For outside of a few
          perhaps, to avoid saying all, not one of them abuses another that any of your interests
          may be forwarded; very far from it, but in order that he may himself with the greater
          immunity succeed in doing what he says, if so-and-so did it, would be the most outrageous
          conduct imaginable. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Do not take my word for it that this
          is so but consider for a little. Has anyone ever stood up before you and said,
          &ldquo;I have come forward, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
          desiring to get my hands on something of yours, not for your sakes &rdquo;? Certainly
          not a single one. Instead, they say &ldquo;for your sakes&rdquo; and &ldquo;on
          your account&rdquo; and cite these plausible motives.</p>
				<p>Come now, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, consider why in the
          world you, &ldquo;for whose sakes&rdquo; they all speak, are on the whole no
          better off now than before, while these, who all say &ldquo;for your sakes,&rdquo;
          without a single one having ever said &ldquo;for our own sakes,&rdquo; have turned
          from beggars into rich men.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">On the wealth of politicians
            see <bibl n="Dem. 13.20">Dem. 13.20</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 21.158">Dem. 21.158</bibl> and
              <bibl n="Dem. 3.29">Dem. 3.29</bibl>.</note> It Is because, though they say they love
          you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, they love not you but
          themselves. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>The portion they allow you is to have a laugh
          and to raise a hubbub and now and then to have a hope, but they would not want you to get
          or acquire for the State any benefit in the proper sense of the word. Yes, and on the day
          when you are freed of this lamentable weakness you will be unable to endure even the sight
          of them. At present with their drachma and gallon measure and four obols<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The drachma was the fee for attending the Assembly; the
            four obols is the juror's fee, which had long been three obols. The <foreign lang="greek">xou=s</foreign> is the measure for a largess of grain. Its content is
            more accurately known than formerly from a specimen found on the side of the Acropolis
            in <date value="1937">1937</date>, which measures 3.2 liters or 2.816 imperial qts. or
            3.379 U.S. qts. This find was confirmed by the discovery of a clepsydra in the Agora
            marked two <foreign lang="greek">xo/es</foreign> and measuring 6.4 liters. The <foreign lang="greek">xou=s</foreign> was one-twelfth of a medimnus, the portion doled out to
            each citizen according to <bibl n="Dem. 34.37">Dem. 34.37</bibl>. Cf.
              <title>Hesperia</title>, 8.<date value="1939">1939</date>, 278 ff.</note> they
          regulate the populace like a sick man, giving you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, doles very similar to the diets of the physicians. For these diets
          neither put strength into the patient nor allow him to die, and these doles neither allow
          you to cry quits and engage in some different and better business, nor can they alone
            suffice.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">this passage is found with variations in
              <bibl n="Dem. 3.33">Dem. 3.33</bibl>.</note></p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="54">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>It is just and right and important, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that we too should exercise care, as you are accustomed, that our
          relations with the gods shall be piously maintained.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">Demosthenes makes an official report upon the execution of a commission to perform
            certain sacrifices. Meidias was chosen to perform similar functions: <bibl n="Dem. 21">Dem. 21</bibl> cf. Theophrastus, <title>Char.</title> 21. &lpar;7.
            Jebb-Sandys&rpar;. This is not a true exordium but included by some error.</note>
          Therefore our commission has been duly discharged for you, for we have sacrificed to Zeus
          the Saviour and to Athena and to Victory, and these sacrifices have been auspicious and
          salutary for you. We have also sacrificed to Persuasion and to the Mother of the Gods and
          to Apollo, and here also we had favorable omens. And the sacrifices made to the other gods
          portended for you security and stability and prosperity and safety. Do you, therefore,
          accept the blessings which the gods bestow.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="55">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>There was, as it seems, a time in your history, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, when the democracy compelled any man whom it observed to be prudent
          and honest to perform public service and to hold office, not through lack of those who
          wished to do so&mdash;for, while deeming the city to be fortunate in all other
          respects, in this one particular I consider it has never been fortunate, that the supply
          of those who wish to reap a harvest from the public business never fails it&mdash;but
          the democracy used to make out of this a fine showing for itself, creditable and
          profitable to the State, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.
            <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>For on the one hand, these men, the kind who hold
          office year after year, when earnest and upright men from a different class were given
          them as yokemates, used to show themselves more circumspect; and on the other hand, the
          kind of men among you who are honest and upright in office, but not at all of the sort to
          push their way and appeal for support, were not shut out of the posts of trust. But now,
          men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you appoint your magistrates in
          exactly the same manner as you appoint your priests.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">While some priesthoods were subject to choice by lot, <bibl n="Dem. 59.106">Dem.
              59.106</bibl>, the majority of them were perhaps hereditary, <bibl n="Dem. 59.104">Dem. 59.104</bibl>, and the reference is to these. For a similar complaint see <bibl n="Dem. Ex. 13">Dem. Ex. 13</bibl>.</note> Then you are amazed when this one is
          prosperous and that one, to your dismay, is year after year taking a rich spoil, while the
          rest of you go around envying these men their blessings! <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>For you are the worst people for taking away the offices that fall to your class, and
          for enacting laws about them if someone serves twice as commissioner of police<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">These <foreign lang="greek">a)stuno/moi</foreign> were ten
            in number, five each for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and the
            Peiraeus; they were responsible for the streets but not for the markets. Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 50.2">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 50.2</bibl>.</note> or something of the
          sort, but you allow the same men to be generals all the time.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">The last statement is confirmed by <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 62.3">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 62.3</bibl>.</note> There is perhaps some excuse for allowing
          those engaged in the active services to continue, but to allow the others, who, though
          doing nothing, have an endless tenure of office and are themselves endlessly benefited is
            folly.<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">There is a touch of tragedy and the mysteries
            in the diction. Perhaps better: &ldquo;hold an unserviceable post to the service of
            which they have themselves been consecrated.&rdquo; For similar irony cf. <bibl n="Dem. 13.19">Dem. 13.19</bibl>
            <foreign lang="greek">telesqh=nai strathgo/s</foreign>, &ldquo;to be consecrated
            general.&rdquo;</note> Instead, you ought to bring in some of your own number, and
          there are not a few of you. For if you set up a standard, as it were, anyone who is worth
          anything will thereafter come forward of his own accord.</p>
			</div1>
			<div1 type="exordium" n="56">
				<milestone n="1" unit="section"/>
				<p>It seems to me a fine and seemly thing, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, for a man who has convinced himself he has something profitable to
          say to take the floor, but I consider it altogether shameful to force people to listen
          against their will. And I think, if you will but take my advice today, you will be better
          able both to choose the best measures and to shorten the speeches of those who come to the
          platform. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>What, then, do I advise? First of all, men of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to require the man who comes forward
          to confine himself to the matters you are considering. For otherwise someone may embrace
          many other topics in his speech and say many witty things, especially those who are smart
          at it, as some of these are. Well, if you have come here to listen to fine phrases, the
          thing to do is to make them and listen to them, but if you have come to deliberate about a
          choice of measures, I urge you to judge the measures strictly by themselves, eliminating
          all passages of a nature to mislead. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>This, then, is my
          first point. My second, which to some of you will perhaps be inconsistent with cutting the
          speeches shorter, is that you listen in silence. For on the question whether this or that
          is expedient and which choice the State might more rightly prefer, there are few arguments
          to be presented, unless by such persons as wish to prattle aimlessly, nor would anyone
          have occasion to state them a second time. As for the claim that it is only fair to listen
          to the heckling,<note anchored="yes" resp="DeWitt">This seems to refer to genuine heckling
            and not to organized interruption as in <bibl n="Dem. 13.20">Dem. 13.20</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 2.29">Dem. 2.29</bibl>.</note> and to give an answer and to make speech after
          speech, there is no one who could not do that. Thus by heckling you do not get rid of
          speeches; instead you are forced in addition to hear speeches that are totally irrelevant.
          Accordingly my judgement concerning the matter before you now begins.</p>
			</div1>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI.2>
