<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Concerning the Team of Horses from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
      <change when="2016-01-26" who="TDBuck">epidoc and CTS</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg004.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>
          <note anchored="true" resp="ed">It should be noted that we have only the second part of
            the speech, the eulogy of Alcibiades the elder; the first part must have presented the
            statement of facts and the citation of evidence.</note>So then, concerning the team of
            horses<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The “team” consisted of four
          race-horses.</note>—that my father was in possession of them, not by having taken them
          away from Teisias, but by having purchased them from the Argive state—you have heard both
          the Argive ambassadors and the others conversant with the facts testify. But in just this
          same fashion all are accustomed maliciously to accuse me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>For they obtain leave to bring actions against me on private complaints, but make their
          accusations on behalf of the interests of the state, and they spend more time in
          slandering my father than they do in informing you with respect to their sworn charges;
          and so great is their contempt of the law that they claim personal satisfaction from me
          for the wrongs which, as they say, you suffered at my father's hands. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>But it is my opinion that charges involving the public interest have nothing to do with
          private suits; but as Teisias often reproaches me with my father's banishment, and is more
          zealous concerning your affairs than he is regarding his own, I must address my defense to
          these matters. Certainly I should be ashamed, if I were to seem to any of my
          fellow-citizens to have less concern for my father's good name than for my own peril. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> Now so far as the older men are concerned, a brief statement could have sufficed: for
          they all know that the same men were responsible for the destruction of the democracy and
          for my father's exile; but for the benefit of the younger men, who have lived after the
          events and have often heard the slanderers, I will begin my exposition from an earlier
          time. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> Now the persons who first plotted against the democracy and established the Four
            Hundred,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Revolution of the Four Hundred in <date
              when="-0411">411 B.C.</date> conducted the Athenian government for only a few
            months.</note> inasmuch as my father, although he was repeatedly invited to join them
          would not do so, seeing that he was a vigorous opponent of their activities and a loyal
          supporter of the people, judged that they were powerless to upset the established order
          until he was removed out of their way. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>And since they knew that in matters pertaining to the gods the city would be most enraged
          if any man should be shown to be violating the Mysteries,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The Eleusinian Mysteries were celebrated annually at Eleusis in Attica and were
            performed in honor of Demeter and her daughter Persephone.</note> and that in other
          matters if any man should dare to attempt the overthrow of the democracy, they combined
          both these charges and tried to bring an action of impeachment before the senate. They
          asserted that my father was holding meetings of his political club with a view to
          revolution, and that these members of the club, when dining together in the house of
            Pulytion,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Andoc. 1.12">Andoc.
            1.12</bibl>.</note> had given a performance of the Mysteries. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>The city was greatly excited by reason of the gravity of the charges, and a meeting of
          the Assembly was hastily called at which my father so clearly proved that the accusers
          were lying that the people would have been glad to punish them, and furthermore elected
          him general for the Sicilian expedition.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The ill-fated
            Sicilian Expedition, <date from="-0415" to="-0413">415-413 B.C.</date></note>
          Thereupon he sailed away, judging that he had been already cleared of their calumnies; but
          his accusers, having united the Council and having made the public speakers subservient to
          themselves, again revived the matter and suborned informers. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Why need I say more? They did not cease until they had recalled my father from the
          expedition and had put to death some of his friends and had banished others from the city.
          But when he had learned the power of his enemies and the misfortunes of his friends,
          although he was of opinion that he was being grossly wronged because they would not try
          him when he was in Athens but were for condemning him in his absence, not even in these
          circumstances did my father see fit to desert to the enemy; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>on the contrary, even in exile he was so scrupulous to avoid injuring his city that he
          went to Argos and remained quietly there. But his enemies reached such a pitch of
          insolence that they persuaded you to banish him from Greece entirely, to inscribe his name
          on a column as a traitor, and to send envoys to demand his surrender by the Argives. And
          he, being at a loss to know what to do in the misfortunes which encompassed him and
          everywhere hemmed him in, as he saw no other means of safety, was compelled at last to
          take refuge with the Lacedaemonians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> These are the actual facts; but such an excess of insolence have my father's enemies
          that they accuse him, who was exiled in so illegal a manner as if he had committed
          outrageous crimes, and try to ruin his reputation by saying that he caused the
          fortification of Decelea,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Decelea was a fort on Mt. Parnes,
            fourteen miles N.E. from Athens. The Lacedaemonians occupied it in <date when="-0413"
              >413 B.C.</date> Cf. <bibl n="Lys. 14.30">Lys. 14.30</bibl>, and for the facts <bibl
              n="Thuc. 6.91.6">Thuc. 6.91.6</bibl>.</note> and the revolt of the islands, and that
          he became the enemy's counsellor. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>And sometimes they pretend to despise him,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Lys. 14">Lys. 14.35-38</bibl>.</note> saying that in no respect did he excel his
          contemporaries; yet at the present time they blame him for all that has happened and say
          that the Lacedaemonians have learned from him the art of war—they who can teach the rest
          of the world this accomplishment! As for me, if I had sufficient time, I could easily
          prove that some of those things he did justly, but that others are unjustly imputed to
          him. Yet the most shocking thing that could happen would be this—if, while after his exile
          my father was recompensed, I, because he was exiled, should be penalized. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> I think, however, that in justice he should obtain from you a full pardon; for you, when
          banished by the Thirty Tyrants,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">After the capture of Athens
            by the Spartans in <date when="-0404">404 B.C.</date> an oligarchy known as the Thirty
            Tyrants was established. The cruelty of their government caused many of the democratic
            party to go into exile. Led by Thrasybulus these exiles were restored when the Thirty
            were overthrown in <date when="-0403">403 B.C.</date></note> experienced the same
          misfortunes as he. Wherefore you should reflect how each of you was affected, what
          thoughts you each had, and what peril each would not have undergone so as to bring his own
          banishment to an end and to return to his native land, and to be avenged on those who
          banished him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>To what city, or friend, or stranger did you not apply, to entreat them to help you to
          get back to your country? From what effort did you abstain in your endeavors to be
          restored? Did you not seize the Piraeus and destroy the crops in the fields and harry the
          land and set fire to the suburbs and finally assault the walls? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>And so vehemently did you believe that these actions were justifiable that you were more
          indignant with those of your fellow-exiles who were inactive than with those who had been
          the authors of your misfortunes. It is not fair, therefore, to censure those who wanted
          the same things which you desired, nor yet to regard all those men as base who, when they
          were exiles, sought to return, but much more should you condemn those oligarchs who,
          remaining in Athens, did deeds which deserved the penalty of exile; nor is it fair that
          you, in judging what sort of citizen my father was, should begin at the time when he had
          no art in the city's affairs; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>on the contrary, you should look to that earlier time and observe how he served the
          people before his exile, and call to mind that with two hundred heavy-armed soldiers he
          caused the most powerful cities in the Peloponnesus to revolt from the
            Lacedaemonians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><date when="-0419">419 B.C.</date> Cf.
              <bibl n="Thuc. 5.52.2">Thuc. 5.52.2</bibl>.</note> and brought them into alliance with
          you, and in what perils he involved the Lacedaemonians themselves, and how he behaved as
          general in Sicily. For these services he is deserving of your gratitude; but for that
          which happened when he was in misfortune it is those who banished him whom you would
          justly hold responsible. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> Remember, too, I beg you, the many benefits he conferred upon the city after his return
          from exile, and, even before that time, the state of affairs here when you received him
          back: the democracy had been overthrown,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By the Revolution
            of the Four Hundred.</note> the citizens were in a state of civil war, the army was
          disaffected toward the government established here, and both parties had reached such a
          state of madness that neither had any hope of salvation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>For the one party<note anchored="true" resp="ed">the Athenian army and fleet, sympathetic
            the the democracy, were at the island of Samos (<bibl n="Thuc. 8.82">Thuc. 8.82</bibl>
            and <bibl n="Thuc. 8.86">Thuc. 8.86</bibl>).</note> regarded those who were in
          possession of the city as greater enemies than the Lacedaemonians<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The oligarchs in Athens.</note> and the other were making overtures to the
          Spartan forces in Decelea, judging that it was preferable to hand over their country to
          its enemies rather than to give a share in the rights of citizenship to those who were
          fighting for the city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Such was the state of mind of the citizens: the enemy was in control of land and sea;
          your financial resources were exhausted, while the Persian king was supplying them with
          funds; furthermore, ninety ships had come from Phoenicia<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The Persian king depended largely upon Phoenicia for ships of war.</note> to
            Aspendus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Aspendus, a town in Asia Minor, in Pamphylia,
            was situated on the river Eurymedon.</note> and were prepared to aid the Lacedaemonians.
          By so many misfortunes and such perils was the city beset </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>when the army summoned my father, and he did not treat them with disdain in their plight,
          nor did he rebuke them for the past, nor did he deliberate about the future; on the
          contrary, he chose at once to suffer any misfortune with his country rather than to enjoy
          prosperity with the Lacedaemonians, and he made it manifest to all that he was warring on
          those who had banished him and not on you, and that his heart was set on a return to
          Athens and not on her ruin. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Having thrown in his lot with you, he persuaded Tissaphernes<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Persian satrap of western Asia Minor from <date when="-0414">414
            B.C.</date></note> not to furnish the Lacedaemonians with money, checked the defection
          of your allies, distributed pay from his own resources to the soldiers, restored political
          power to the people, reconciled the citizens, and turned back the Phoenician fleet. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>As to his later services, it would be an arduous task to enumerate them one by one—all
          the ships of war that he subsequently captured, or the battles that he won, or the cities
          he took by storm or by persuasion made your friends. But although innumerable dangers
          beset the city at that time, never did the enemy erect a trophy of victory over you while
          my father was your leader. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> I am aware that I am omitting many of my father's exploits as your general; I have not
          recounted them in detail because nearly all of you recall the facts. But my father's
          private life they revile with excessive indecency and audacity, and they are not ashamed,
          now that he is dead, to use a license of speech concerning him which they would have
          feared to employ while he lived. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Nay, they have come to such a pitch of folly that they think they will win repute with
          both you and with the world at large if they indulge in the wildest possible abuse of him;
          as if all did not know that it is in the power of the vilest of men to abuse with
          insulting words, not only the best of men, but even the gods. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Perhaps it is foolish for me to take to heart all that has been said; nevertheless, I
          desire very much to recount to you my father's private pursuits, going back a little to
          make mention of his ancestors, that you may know that from early times our standing and
          services have been the greatest and most honorable among the citizens of Athens. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> My father on the male side belonged to the Eupatrids,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            Eupatrids (sons of noble sires) were the nobles, or patricians, in Athens of the early
            time.</note> whose noble birth is apparent from the very name. On the female side he was
          of the Alcmeonidae,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Descendants of Alcmeon, one of the
            greatest families in early Athens, expelled from the city in <date when="-0595">595
              B.C.</date></note> who left behind a glorious memorial of their wealth; for
            Alcmeon<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Son of Megacles.</note> was the first Athenian to
          win at Olympia with a team of horses, and the goodwill which they had toward the people
          they displayed in the time of the tyrants. For they were kinsmen of Pisistratus<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Pisistratus was a tyrant of Athens in the sixth century
            B.C.</note> and before he came to power were closest to him of all the citizens, but
          they refused to share his tyranny; on the contrary, they preferred exile rather than to
          see their fellow-citizens enslaved. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>And during the forty years<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Roughly speaking the period of
            the rule of Pisistratus and his sons, <date from="-0560" to="-0510">560-510
              B.C.</date></note> of civic discord the Alcmeonidae were hated so much more
          bitterly than all other Athenians by the tyrants that whenever the tyrants had the upper
          hand they not only razed their dwellings, but even dug up their tombs<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Hdt. 5.71">Hdt. 5.71</bibl>.</note>; and so completely were the
          Alcmeonidae trusted by their fellow-exiles that they continued during all that time to be
          leaders of the people. At last, Alcibiades and Cleisthenes<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Cleisthenes was the reformer of the Athenian constitution and founder of the
            democracy.</note>—the former my great-grandfather on my father's side, the latter my
          father's maternal great-grandfather—assuming the leadership of those in exile, restored
          the people to their country, and drove out the tyrants. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>And they established that democratic form of government which so effectively trained the
          citizens in bravery that single-handed they conquered in battle<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Marathon, <date when="-0490">490 B.C.</date></note> the barbarians who had
          attacked all Greece and they won so great renown for justice that the Greeks voluntarily
          put in their hands the dominion of the sea; and they made Athens so great in her power and
          her other resources that those who allege that she is the capital of Greece<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.299">Isoc. 15.299</bibl>.</note> and
          habitually apply to her similar exaggerated expressions appear to be speaking the truth.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> Now this friendship with the people, which was, as I have shown, so ancient, genuine,
          and based upon services of the greatest importance, my father inherited from his
          ancestors. My father himself was left an orphan (for his father<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cleinias.</note> died in battle at Coronea<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A
            town in Boeotia where the Athenians were defeated by the Boeotians in <date when="-0466"
              >466 B.C.</date></note>) and became the ward of Pericles, whom all would acknowledge
          to have been the most moderate, the most just, and the wisest of the citizens. For I count
          this also among his blessings that, being of such origin, he was fostered, reared, and
          educated under the guardianship of a man of such character. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>When he was admitted to citizenship, he showed himself not inferior to those whom I have
          mentioned, nor did he think it fitting that he should lead a life of ease, pluming himself
          upon the brave deeds of his ancestors; on the contrary, from the beginning he was so fired
          with ambition that he thought that even their great deeds should be held in remembrance
          through his own. And first of all, when Phormio<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A famous
            Athenian general.</note> led a thousand of the flower of Athenian soldiers to
            Thrace,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Expedition to recover the city of Potidaea in
              <date when="-0439">439 B.C.</date> Thucydides (<bibl n="Thuc. 1.64.2">Thuc.
              1.64.2</bibl>) speaks of 1600 hoplites. Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Sym. 220">Plat. Sym.
              220</bibl> for the award of valor given to Alcibiades.</note> my father served with
          this expedition, and so distinguished himself in the perilous actions of the campaign that
          he was crowned and received a full suit of armour from his general. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Really what is required of the man who is thought worthy of the highest praise? Should he
          not, when serving with the bravest of the citizens, be thought worthy of the prize of
          valor, and when leading an army against the best of the Greeks in all the battles show his
          superiority to them? My father, then, in his youth did win that prize of valor and in
          later life did achieve the latter. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> After this he married my mother<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Hipparet.</note>; and I
          believe that in her he also won a glorious prize of valor. For her father was
            Hipponicus,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Son of Callias, noted for his wealth.</note>
          first in wealth of all the Greeks and second in birth to none of the citizens, most
          honored and admired of his contemporaries. The richest dowry and fairest reputation went
          with his daughter's hand; and although all coveted union with her, and only the greatest
          thought themselves worthy, it was my father whom Hipponicus chose from among them all and
          desired to make his son-in-law. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> About the same time my father, seeing that the festival assembly at Olympia was beloved
          and admired by the whole world and that in it the Greeks made display of their wealth,
          strength of body, and training, and that not only the athletes were the objects of envy
          but that also the cities of the victors became renowned, and believing moreover that while
          the public services performed in Athens redound to the prestige, in the eyes of his
          fellow-citizens, of the person who renders them, expenditures in the Olympian Festival,
          however, enhance the city's reputation throughout all Greece, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>reflecting upon these things, I say, although in natural gifts and in strength of body he
          was inferior to none, he disdained the gymnastic contests, for he knew that some of the
          athletes were of low birth, inhabitants of petty states, and of mean education, but turned
          to the breeding of race-horses, which is possible only for those most blest by Fortune and
          not to be pursued by one of low estate, and not only did he surpass his rivals, but also
          all who had ever before won the victory. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>For he entered a larger number of teams in competition than even the mightiest cities had
          done, and they were of such excellence that he came out first, second, and third.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Thuc. 6.16.2">Thuc. 6.16.2</bibl> and <bibl
              n="Plut. Alc. 11">Plut. Alc. 11</bibl>, who give the same testimony; Alcibiades
            entered seven teams. Cf. Plutarch, <title>Alcibiades</title>: "His horse-breeding was
            famous, among other things, for the number of his racing-chariots. He was the only man,
            not excluding king, who ever entered at Olympia as many as seven. And his winning not
            only first place but second and fourth according to Thucydides—second and third
            according to Euripides—is the highest and most honorable distinction ever won in this
            field. Euripides' Ode contains the following passage: “‘But I will sing thy praises, son
            of Cleinias. A noble thing is victory, noblest of the noble to do what no Greek had ever
            done, be first and second and third in the chariot-race, and go unwearied yet, wreathed
            in the olive of Zeus, to make the herald cry you.’”—(Edmonds, <title>Lyra Graeca</title>
            ii. p. 241.)</note> Besides this, his generosity in the sacrifices and in the other
          expenses connected with the festival was so lavish and magnificent that the public funds
          of all the others<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >*QEWROI/</foreign>, representing the other states.</note> were clearly less than the
          private means of Alcibiades alone. And when he brought his mission to an end he had caused
          the successes of his predecessors to seem petty in comparison with his own and those who
          in his own day had been victors to be no longer objects of emulation, and to future
          breeders of racing-steeds he left behind no possibility of surpassing him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>With regard to my father's services here in Athens as choregus and gymnasiarch and
            trierarch<note anchored="true" resp="ed">These public services (referred to in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 16.32">Isoc. 16.32</bibl>) were the liturgies , discharged by the wealthier
            citizens, e.g., the choregia (expenses of the public choruses); the gymnasiarchia
            (defraying of expenses of training athletes for the contests); and the trierarchia (the
            cost of equipping a war-ship and keeping it in service for a year).</note> I am ashamed
          to speak; for so greatly did he excel in all the other public duties that, although those
          who have served the state in less splendid fashion sing their own praises therefor, if
          anyone should on my father's behalf ask for a vote of thanks even in recognition of
          services as great as his, he would seem to be talking about petty things. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> As regards his behavior as a citizen—for neither should this be passed over in
          silence—just as he on his part did not neglect his civic duties, but on the contrary, to
          so great a degree had proved himself a more loyal friend of the people than those who had
          gained the highest repute, that while, as you will find, the others stirred up sedition
          for selfish advantage, he was incurring danger on your behalf. For his devotion to the
          democracy was not that of one who was excluded from the oligarchy, but of one who was
          invited to join it: indeed, time and again when it was in his power as one of a small
          group, not only to rule the rest, but even to dominate them, he refused, choosing rather
          to suffer the city's unjust penalties rather than to be traitor to our form of government.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Of the truth of these statements no one would have convinced you as long as you still
          continued to be governed as a democracy; but as it was, the civil conflicts which arose
          clearly showed who were the democrats and who the oligarchs, as well as those who desired
          neither rgime, and those who laid claim to a share in both. In these uprisings your
          enemies twice exiled my father: on the first occasion, no sooner had they got him out of
          the way than they abolished the democracy; on the second, hardly had they reduced you to
          servitude than they condemned him to exile before any other citizen; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>so exactly did my father's misfortunes affect the city and he share in her disasters. And
          yet many of the citizens were ill disposed toward him in the belief that he was plotting a
          tyranny; they held this opinion, not on the basis of his deeds, but in the thought that
          all men aspire to this power and that he would have the best chance of attaining it.
          Wherefore you would justly feel the greater gratitude to him because, while he alone of
          the citizens was powerful enough to have this charge<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e.,
            of plotting to become a tyrant.</note> brought against him, he was of opinion that as
          regards political power he should be on an equality with his fellow-citizens. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> Because of the multitude of things that might be said on my father's behalf I am at a
          loss which of them it is appropriate to mention on the present occasion and which should
          be omitted. For always the plea that has not yet been spoken seems to me of greater
          importance than the arguments which have already been presented to you. And I believe that
          it is obvious to everyone that he must needs be most devoted to the welfare of the city
          who has the greatest share in her evil fortunes as well as in her good. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Well then, when Athens was prosperous, who of the citizens was more prosperous, more
          admired, or more envied than my father? And when she suffered ill-fortune, who was
          deprived of brighter hopes, or of greater wealth, or of fairer repute? Finally, when the
          Thirty Tyrants established their rule, while the others merely suffered exile from Athens,
          was he not banished from all Greece? Did not the Lacedaemonians and Lysander<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Spartan general, victorious over the Athenians at Aegospotami
              (<date when="-0405">405 B.C.</date>)</note> exert themselves as much to cause his
          death as to bring about the downfall of your dominion, in the belief that they could not
          be sure of the city's loyalty if they demolished her walls<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The Long Walls, uniting Athens and its harbor Piraeus, were destroyed in <date
              when="-0404">404 B.C.</date> (Xenophon, Hall. ii. 2. 20) and were rebuilt by Conon in
              <date when="-0394">394 B.C.</date></note> unless they should also destroy the man who
          could rebuild them? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>Thus it is not only from his services to you, but also from what he suffered on your
          account, that you may easily recognize his loyalty. For it is self-evident that it was the
          people he was aiding, that he desired the same form of government as yourselves, that he
          suffered at the hands of the same persons, that he was unfortunate when the state was
          unfortunate, that he considered the same persons as you his enemies and friends, that in
          every way he exposed himself to danger either at your hands, or on your account, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>or on your behalf, or in partnership with you, being as a citizen quite unlike
            Charicles,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Charicles was one of the most cruel of the
            Thirty Tyrants. Cf. <bibl n="Lys. 12.55">Lys. 12.55</bibl>; <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 2.3.2"
              >Xen. Hell. 2.3.2</bibl>.</note> my opponent's brother-in-law, who chose to be a slave
          to the enemy, yet claimed the right to rule his fellow-citizens; who, when in exile, was
          inactive, but on his return was ever injuring the city. And yet how could one prove
          himself to be a baser friend or a viler enemy? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>And then do you, Teisias, his brother-in-law and a member of the Council in the time of
          the Thirty Tyrants, have the hardihood to rake up old grudges against those of the other
          side, and are you not ashamed to be violating the terms of the amnesty which permits you
          to reside in the city, nor do you even reflect that, whenever the decision shall be made
          to exact punishment for past crimes, it is you who are menaced by danger more speedy and
          greater than mine? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>For surely they will not inflict punishment on me for my father's acts and at the same
          time pardon you for the crimes you yourself have committed! No, assuredly it will not be
          found that your pleas in extenuation are anything like his! For you were not banished from
          your native land, but on the contrary you were a member of the government; you did not act
          under compulsion, but you were a willing agent; it was not in self-defense, but on our own
          initiative, that you were wronging your fellow-citizens, so that it is not fitting that
          you should be permitted by them even to enter a plea in your defense. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> But on the subject of the political misdeeds of Teisias, very likely some day at his
          trial I shall have the opportunity of speaking at greater length. But as for you, men of
          the jury, I beg you not to abandon me to my enemies nor entangle me in the net of
          irremediable misfortunes. For even now I have had sufficient experience of evils, since at
          my birth I was left an orphan through my father's exile and my mother's death; and I was
          not yet four years of age when I was brought into peril of my life owing to my father's
          exile; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>and while still a boy I was banished from the city by the Thirty. And when the men of the
            Piraeus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The democratic party, led by Thrasybulus, in
              <date when="-0403">403 B.C.</date> had taken Piraeus and made it their
            headquarters.</note> were restored, and all the rest recovered their possessions, I
          alone by the influence of my personal enemies was deprived of the of the land which the
          people gave us as compensation for the confiscated property.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">After Alcibiades' condemnation as participant in the violation of the
            Eleusinian Mysteries. Large portions of the list of these confiscated goods are
            preserved in inscriptions.</note> And after having already suffered so many misfortunes
          and having twice lost my property,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><date when="-0414">414
              B.C.</date> and <date when="-0404">404 B.C.</date></note> I am now the defendant in an
          action involving five talents.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The talent was not a coin,
            but a sum of money roughly equivalent (although it would purchase much more) to $1000
            (over 200).</note> And although the complaint involves money, the real issue is my right
          to continue to enjoy citizenship. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>For although the same penalties are prescribed for all by our laws, yet the legal risk is
          not the same for all; on the contrary, the wealthy risk a fine, but those who are in
          straitened circumstances, as is the case with me, are in danger of disfranchisement, and
          this is a misfortune greater, in my opinion, than exile; for it is a far more wretched
          fate to live among one's fellow-citizens deprived of civic rights than to dwell an alien
          among foreigners. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>I entreat you, therefore, to aid me and not to suffer me to be despitefully treated by my
          personal enemies, or to be deprived of my fatherland, or to be made notorious by such
          misfortunes. The facts in the case would of themselves justly win for me your pity, even
          if I have not the power by my words to evoke it, since pity truly should be felt for those
          who are unjustly brought to trial, who are fighting for the greatest stakes, whose present
          condition is not in accordance with their own worth or with that of their ancestors,
          seeing that they have been deprived of immense wealth and have experienced life's greatest
          vicissitudes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p> Although I have many reasons for lamenting my fate, I am especially indignant for these
          reasons: first, if I must be punished by this man, who should justly be punished by me;
          second, if I shall lose my civic rights by reason of my father's victory at Olympia, when
          I see other men richly rewarded for such a victory<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the
            rewards of victory at Olympia cf. <bibl n="Plat. Apol. 36d">Plat. Apol.
            36d-e</bibl>.</note>; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart"  >
        <p>and, in addition, if Teisias, a man who never did the city any good, is to remain
          powerful in the democracy just as he was in the oligarchy, whereas I, who injured neither
          party, am to be ill-treated by both; and finally, if, while in all other matters your
          actions are to be the opposite of those of the Thirty, you shall in regard to me show the
          same spirit as they, and if I, who then lost my fatherland in company with you, shall now
          be deprived of it by you.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
