<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>First Philippic </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by J. H. Vince, M.A.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1930</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>6/2/92</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserted quotedtext tag around verse</item>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>If the question before us were a new one, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, I should have waited until most of the regular speakers
                    had delivered their opinions, and if satisfied with any of their proposals, I
                    should have remained silent, but if not satisfied, I should then have tried to
                    express my own views. Since, however, it is our fortune to be still debating a
                    point on which they have often spoken before, I can safely claim your indulgence
                    if I am the first to rise and address you. For if in the past their advice had
                    been sound, there would be no need for deliberation today. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>Now in the first place, Athenians, there is no need to despair of our present
                    position, however hopeless it may seem. For that which is worst in the days that
                    are past and gone is just what affords the best assurance for the future. And
                    what is that? It is that your affairs are in this evil plight just because you,
                    men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, utterly fail to do
                    your duty; since surely, were you so placed in spite of every effort on your
                    part, it would be hopeless to look for improvement. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>In the next place, bear this in mind. Some of you have been told, others know and
                    remember, how formidable the Spartans were, not many years ago, and yet how at
                    the call of honor and duty you played a part not unworthy of your country, and
                    entered the lists against them in defence of your rights.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The reference is probably to the invasion of <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> by Agesilaus in 378.</note> I
                    remind you of this, Athenians, because I want you to know and realize that, as
                    no danger can assail you while you are on your guard, so if you are remiss no
                    success can attend you. Learn a lesson from the former strength of the
                    Lacedaemonians, which you mastered by strict attention to your affairs, and the
                    present arrogance of our enemy, which discomposes us because we ignore every
                    call of duty. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>But if anyone here, Athenians, is inclined to think Philip too formidable, having
                    regard to the extent of his existing resources and to our loss of all our
                    strongholds, he is indeed right, yet he must reflect that we too, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, once held <placeName
                        key="perseus,Pydna">Pydna</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,6004814"
                        >Potidaea</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Methone"
                        >Methone</placeName> and had in our own hands all the surrounding territory,
                    and that many of the native tribes now in his service were then free and
                    independent and were indeed more inclined to side with us than with Philip. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>If, therefore, Philip had then come to the conclusion that it was a difficult
                    task to fight the Athenians while they held such strong outposts in his own
                    territory and he was destitute of allies, in that case he would never have
                    gained his present successes, never acquired his present power. But, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, Philip saw clearly that
                    all these outposts were but the open prizes of war, that by natural right the
                    property of the absent belongs to those who are on the spot, and the property of
                    the careless to those who can face toil and danger. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>It was precisely by acting on this principle that he has mastered and now holds
                    them all. Some he has seized by right of arms, others he has won by alliance and
                    friendship. For indeed alliance and respect are willingly offered by all men to
                    those whom they see ready and prompt to take action. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>And you too, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, if you
                    are willing to adopt this principle, now if never before, if each citizen is
                    ready to throw off his diffidence and serve the state as he ought and as he best
                    may, the rich man paying, the strong man fighting, if, briefly and plainly, you
                    will consent to become your own masters, and if each man will cease to expect
                    that, while he does nothing himself, his neighbor will do everything for him,
                    then, God willing, you will recover your own, you will restore what has been
                    frittered away, and you will turn the tables upon Philip. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>Do not believe that his present power is fixed and unchangeable like that of a
                    god. No, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; he is a mark
                    for the hatred and fear and envy even of those who now seem devoted to him. One
                    must assume that even his adherents are subject to the same passions as any
                    other men. At present, however, all these feelings are repressed and have no
                    outlet, thanks to your indolence and apathy, which I urge you to throw off at
                    once. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>For observe, Athenians, the height to which the fellow's insolence has soared; he
                    leaves you no choice of action or inaction; he blusters and talks big, according
                    to all accounts; he cannot rest content with what he has conquered; he is always
                    taking in more, everywhere casting his net round us, while we sit idle and do
                    nothing. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>When, Athenians, will you take the necessary action? What are you waiting for?
                    Until you are compelled, I presume. But what are we to think of what is
                    happening now? For my own part I think that for a free people there can be no
                    greater compulsion than shame for their position. Or tell me, are you content to
                    run round and ask one another, “Is there any news today?” Could there be any
                    news more startling than that a Macedonian is triumphing over Athenians and
                    settling the destiny of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>“Is Philip dead?” you ask. “No, indeed; but he is ill.” And what is that to you?
                    Even if something happens to him, you will soon raise up a second Philip, if
                    that is the way you attend to your affairs; for even this Philip has not grown
                    great through his own unaided strength so much as through our carelessness. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>Nor is this all. If anything happened to him, or if Fortune, which always cares
                    for us better than we care for ourselves, should bring that result about,
                    remember that you must be on the spot if you want to take advantage of the
                    general confusion and to control the situation at your pleasure; but in your
                    present condition you would be unable, even if the opportunity offered, to take
                    over <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, having neither
                    a force nor a policy ready to hand.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Lit. “being
                        cut off [;from <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>];
                        both in forces and in plans,” a vigorous but untranslatable phrase.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>Well, assuming that you are thoroughly convinced that you must all be ready and
                    willing to make this necessary effort, I say no more on that point. But as to
                    the nature and size of the force which I think adequate to relieve the
                    situation, the means of defraying the cost, and the best and speediest method of
                    providing for its equipment, I shall now endeavor to state my views, making just
                    this appeal to you, Athenians. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>Wait till you have heard everything before you pass judgement. Do not be
                    premature; and even if at the outset I seem to be suggesting a novel kind of
                    expeditionary force, do not imagine that I am trying to postpone our operations.
                    It is not those who cry “at once” or “today” that really speak to the purpose,
                    for no dispatch of forces now could prevent what has already happened; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>but it is the man who can indicate the nature, the size, and the source of the
                    expedition that will be able to keep the field until we either defeat the enemy
                    or consent to a termination of hostilities; for that is how we shall avoid
                    trouble in the future. Now I believe that I can indicate this, without prejudice
                    to anyone else's proposal. That is a bold promise, but it will soon be put to a
                    practical test, and you shall be my judges. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>First then, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I propose
                    to equip fifty war-galleys; next you must make up your minds to embark and sail
                    in them yourselves, if necessary. Further I recommend the provision of
                    transports and other vessels, sufficient for the conveyance of half our cavalry.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>All this is a necessary provision against Philip's sudden raids from <placeName
                        key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> against <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName>, the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017285">Chersonese</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                        >Olynthus</placeName>, or where he will. You must present to his mind the
                    consideration that you may possibly shake off your excessive apathy and strike
                    out as you did at <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, and before
                    that, as we are told, at Haliartus, and quite recently at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The Athenians sent a force to <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                            >Euboea</placeName> in 357 (cf. <bibl n="Dem. 1.8">Dem. 1.8</bibl>).
                        They helped the Thebans to defeat Lysander at Haliartus in <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> in 395. In 352, when Philip tried
                        to march from <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> against
                            <placeName key="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName>, he was checked by the
                        dispatch of an Athenian fleet to <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                            >Thermopylae</placeName>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>That, even if you should not act as I, personally, think you ought, is not an
                    altogether trivial matter; for its purpose is that he may either hold his hand
                    through fear, knowing that you are on the alert—he will know it sure enough, for
                    there are some on our side, yes, too many, who report everything to him—or that
                    he may overlook it and so be taken off his guard, provided there is nothing to
                    hinder you from sailing against his country, if he gives you the chance. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>Such, in my opinion, are the resolutions which you ought to adopt, and the force
                    which must be equipped, at once. But in addition to this, Athenians, I propose
                    that you should get ready a corps to carry on a continuous war of annoyance
                    against Philip. Not an imposing army—on paper—of ten or twenty thousand
                    mercenaries! It shall be a real Athenian contingent, and whether you appoint one
                    general or more, whether it is this man or that or the other, him it shall
                    strictly follow and obey. I also urge you to provide for its maintenance. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>And what will this force be, and how large? How will it be maintained, and how
                    far will it consent to effect its purpose? I will tell you, describing each
                    detail separately. Of mercenaries I propose—and beware of the mistake that has
                    so often thwarted your efforts. Thinking that the utmost is too little for the
                    occasion, you choose the biggest scheme in your resolutions, but when it comes
                    to performance, you fail to realize even the smallest. You should rather act and
                    provide on a small scale, adding more if this proves insufficient. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>So I propose that the whole force should consist of two thousand men, but of
                    these five hundred must be Athenians, chosen from any suitable age and serving
                    in relays for a specified period—not a long one, but just so long as seems
                    advisable; the rest should be mercenaries. Attached to them will be two hundred
                    cavalry, fifty at least of them being Athenians, serving on the same terms as
                    the infantry. There will also be cavalry transports provided. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>So far, so good; and what besides? Ten fast-sailing war-galleys. Since Philip has
                    a fleet, we must have fast vessels if our force is to sail in safety. Now how is
                    this army to be maintained? That also I will explain fully, when I have told you
                    why I think so small a force sufficient, and why I insist that those serving
                    shall be citizens. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>I name a force of this size, Athenians, because it is not in our power now to
                    provide one fit to meet him in pitched battle: we must adopt guerilla tactics to
                    start with. The force must therefore be neither unwieldy—for we cannot afford
                    the pay and maintenance—nor altogether insignificant. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>My reasons for insisting on the presence of citizens in the expedition are these.
                    I am told that on a previous occasion the state maintained a mercenary force at
                        <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">During the so-called “Corinthian War,” 394—387, when
                        Iphicrates with a light-armed force destroyed a mora of Spartan hoplites.
                        Chabrias, his successor, is best known for his defeat of the Lacedaemonian
                        fleet at <placeName key="tgn,7012053">Naxos</placeName> in 376. Of
                        Polystratus, little or nothing is known.</note> commanded by Polystratus,
                    Iphicrates, Chabrias, and others, and that you citizens also served in person;
                    and I know from history that you and these mercenaries, fighting shoulder to
                    shoulder, beat the Lacedaemonians in the field. But ever since exclusively
                    mercenary forces have been fighting for you, it is your friends and allies that
                    they have beaten, while the power of your enemies has increased beyond bounds.
                    They cast a casual glance at the war for which <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> has hired them, and off they sail to join Artabazus or
                    anyone else, and the general naturally follows them, for he cannot command if he
                    does not pay. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>What then do I recommend? Deprive both general and men of all excuse by providing
                    pay and by attaching to them citizen soldiers as overseers, so to speak, of
                    their conduct in the field; for at present our system is a mockery. If anyone
                    asked you, “Are you at peace, Athenians?” you would reply, “Certainly not; we
                    are at war with Philip.” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>But have you not been electing from among yourselves ten brigadiers and ten
                    generals and ten squadron—leaders and a couple of cavalry-commanders? And what,
                    pray, are those officers doing? With the exception of the solitary one whom you
                    dispatch to the seat of war, they are all busy helping the state-sacrificers to
                    marshal your processions. You are like the men who model the clay puppets;<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Just as the terra-cotta figurines were
                        manufactured not for practical use, but for the toy-market, so the generals
                        were elected, not to fight, but to make a brave show in the public
                        processions.</note> you choose your brigadiers and commanders for the
                    market-place, not for the field. What! </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>Ought there not to be brigadiers and a cavalry-commander, all chosen from among
                    yourselves, native Athenian officers, that the force might be a truly national
                    one? Yes, but your own cavalry-commander has to sail to <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">We
                        learn from Aristot. <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 61.6">Ath. Pol. 61.6</bibl>,
                        that a <foreign xml:lang="grc">i(/pparxos</foreign> was regularly sent to
                            <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> to take charge of the
                        cavalry there.</note> leaving Menelaus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Identified by Harpocration with a son of Amyntas II. and so half-brother of
                        Philip; more probably a petty Macedonian chief who helped the Athenians at
                            <placeName key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName> in 364, and who is
                        named in a complimentary inscription which has been preserved (C.I.A.
                        2.55).</note> to command the men who are fighting for our city's
                    possessions. I do not say this in his disparagement, but that commander, whoever
                    he is, ought to be one elected by you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>You think perhaps that this is a sound proposal, but you are chiefly anxious to
                    hear what the cost will be and how it will be raised. I now proceed to deal with
                    that point. As to the cost then: the maintenance, the bare rationing of this
                    force, comes to rather more than ninety talents; for the ten fast galleys forty
                    talents, or twenty minae a ship every month; for two thousand men the same
                    amount, that each may receive ten drachmas a month ration-money; for the two
                    hundred cavalry twelve talents, if each is to receive thirty drachmas a
                        month.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The proposed pay is 2 obols a day
                        for infantry and marines, 1 drachma for cavalry. The crew of a trireme
                        numbered 200. The daily pay would therefore be: Galleys: 2 ob. x 200 x 10 =
                        4000 ob. Infantry: 2 ob. x 2000 = 4000 ob. Cavalry: 6 ob. x 200 = <date
                            when="1200">1200</date> ob. Total, 9200 obols or 15 1/3 minae a day; 460
                        minae or 7 2/3 talents a month; 92 talents a year. The hoplite normally
                        received 2 obols for pay and the same for rations; the cavalry thrice this
                        amount. Demosthenes' proposal amounts to this, that the pay should be halved
                        and the men encouraged to make it up by looting. To appreciate these sums,
                        it should he noted that an unskilled laborer at <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> received 3 or 4 obols a
                        day.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>If anyone imagines that ration-money for the men on active service is only a
                    small provision to start with, he is wrong; for I feel quite sure that if no
                    more than that is forthcoming, the force itself will provide the rest out of the
                    war, so as to make up their pay without injury to any Greek or allied community.
                    I am ready to embark as a volunteer and submit to any punishment, if this is not
                    so. I will now tell you the sources from which the sums may be derived which I
                    recommend you to provide.<quote n="Memorandum of Ways and Means">Memorandum of
                        Ways and Means</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>This is the scheme, Athenians, which my colleagues<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">On some financial board, or perhaps only members of the same
                        political party. The suggestion of Dionysius that a new speech commences
                        here has not found favor with the majority of editors.</note> and I have
                    been able to contrive. When you give your votes, you will pass these proposals,
                    if you approve them, because your object is to fight Philip not only with
                    decrees and dispatches, but with deeds also. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="31">
                <p>But you would, I think, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                    >Athens</placeName>, form a better idea of the war and of the total force
                    required, if you considered the geography of the country you are attacking, and
                    if you reflected that the winds and the seasons enable Philip to gain most of
                    his successes by forestalling us. He waits for the Etesian winds<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Northerly winds which blew steadily down the
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002675">Aegean</placeName> in the autumn.</note> or
                    for the winter, and attacks at a time when we could not possibly reach the seat
                    of war. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="32">
                <p>Bearing this in mind, we must rely not on occasional levies, or we shall be too
                    late for everything, but on a regular standing army. You have the advantage of
                    winter bases for your troops in <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>,
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011078">Thasos</placeName>, Sciathos, and the
                    neighboring islands, where are to be found harbors, provisions, and everything
                    that an army needs; and during that season of the year when it is easy to stand
                    close in to shore and the winds are steady, your force will easily lie off his
                    coast and at the mouth of his seaports. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="33">
                <p>How and when this force is to be employed will be a matter for your duly
                    appointed commander to determine according to circumstances, but what it is your
                    task to provide, that I have put down in my resolution. If, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you first provide the funds which I
                    name and then equip the whole force complete, men, ships and cavalry, binding
                    them legally to serve for the duration of the war, and if you make yourselves
                    the stewards and administrators of the funds, looking to your general for an
                    account of his operations, then you will no longer be for ever debating the same
                    question and never making any progress. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="34">
                <p>More than that, Athenians, you will be depriving Philip of his principal source
                    of revenue. And what is that? For the war against you he makes your allies pay
                    by raiding their sea-borne commerce. Is there any further advantage? Yes, you
                    will be out of reach of injury yourselves. Your past experience will not be
                    repeated, when he threw a force into <placeName key="tgn,7011173"
                        >Lemnos</placeName> and Imbros and carried your citizens away captive, when
                    he seized the shipping at Geraestus and levied untold sums, or, to crown all,
                    when he landed at Marathon and bore away from our land the sacred trireme,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The “Paralus,” conveying the <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">qewri/a</foreign>or state-embassy to <placeName
                            key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> in May, touched at Marathon to
                        offer sacrifice in the <foreign xml:lang="grc">*dh/lion</foreign> or
                        sanctuary of Apollo. Readers of the <title>Phaedo</title> will remember why
                        the execution of Socrates was postponed for thirty days.</note> while you
                    are still powerless to prevent these insults or to send your expeditions at the
                    appointed times. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="35">
                <p>And yet, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, how do you
                    account for the fact that the Panathenaic festival and the Dionysia are always
                    held at the right date, whether experts or laymen are chosen by lot to manage
                    them, that larger sums are lavished upon them than upon any one of your
                    expeditions, that they are celebrated with bigger crowds and greater splendor
                    than anything else of the kind in the world, whereas your expeditions invariably
                    arrive too late, whether at <placeName key="perseus,Methone">Methone</placeName>
                    or at <placeName key="tgn,7012084">Pagasae</placeName> or at <placeName
                        key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName>? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="36">
                <p>The explanation is that at the festivals everything is ordered by statute; every
                    man among you knows long beforehand who of his tribe is to provide the chorus or
                    who to equip the gymnasium,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A more important
                        function of the gymnasiarch was to equip a team for the torch-race (<foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">lampadhfori/a</foreign>).</note> what he is to receive,
                    when and from whom he is to receive it, and what he is to do; nothing here is
                    left to chance, nothing is undetermined: but in what pertains to war and its
                    equipment, everything is ill-arranged, ill-managed, ill-defined. Consequently we
                    wait till we have heard some piece of news, and then we appoint our
                    ship-masters, and arrange suits for exchange of property,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">If a citizen, nominated for a “liturgy,” thought that a
                        richer member of his tribe, otherwise eligible, had been passed over, he
                        could challenge him to undertake the burden or exchange properties. In the
                        case of the trierarchy such a challenge was referred to the Strategi.</note>
                    and go into committee of ways and means, and next we resolve that the fleet
                    shall be manned by resident aliens and freedmen, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="37">
                <p>then again by citizens, then by substitutes, then, while we thus delay, the
                    object of our cruise is already lost. Thus the time for action is wasted in
                    preparation, but the opportunities of fortune wait not for our dilatoriness and
                    reluctance. The forces which we fancied would serve us as a stop-gap prove
                    incapable when the crucial moment arrives. Meanwhile Philip has the effrontery
                    to send such letters as these to the Euboeans.<quote n="Reading of the Letter"
                        >Reading of the Letter</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="38">
                <p>Most of what has been read, Athenians, is unfortunately true—possibly, however,
                    not pleasant to listen to. But if all that a speaker passes over, to avoid
                    giving offence, is passed over by the course of events also, then blandiloquence
                    is justified; but if smooth words out of season prove a curse in practice, then
                    it is our disgrace if we hoodwink ourselves, if we shelve whatever is irksome
                    and so miss the time for action, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="39">
                <p>if we fail to learn the lesson that to manage a war properly you must not follow
                    the trend of events but must forestall them, and that just as an army looks to
                    its general for guidance, so statesmen must guide circumstances, if they are to
                    carry out their policy and not be forced to follow at the heels of chance. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="40">
                <p>But you, Athenians, possessing unsurpassed resources—fleet, infantry, cavalry,
                    revenues—have never to this very day employed them aright, and yet you carry on
                    war with Philip exactly as a barbarian boxes. The barbarian, when struck, always
                    clutches the place; hit him on the other side and there go his hands. He neither
                    knows nor cares how to parry a blow or how to watch his adversary. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="41">
                <p>So you, if you hear of Philip in the <placeName key="tgn,7010345"
                        >Chersonese</placeName>, vote an expedition there; if at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName>, you vote one there; if
                    somewhere else, you still keep pace with him to and fro. You take your marching
                    orders from him; you have never framed any plan of campaign for yourselves,
                    never foreseen any event, until you learn that something has happened or is
                    happening. All this was once perhaps possible; now things have come to a crisis,
                    so that it is no longer in your power. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="42">
                <p>It seems to me, Athenians, as if some god, out of very shame for the conduct of
                    our city, had inspired Philip with this activity. For if he did nothing more,
                    but were willing to rest satisfied with what he has already captured and
                    subdued, I believe some of you would be quite content with what must bring the
                    deepest disgrace upon us and brand us as a nation of cowards. But by always
                    attempting something new, always grasping at more power, he may possibly rouse
                    even you, if you have not utterly abandoned hope. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="43">
                <p>Personally I am surprised that none of you, Athenians, is distressed and angry to
                    find that at the beginning of the war our aim was to punish Philip, but at the
                    end it is to escape injury at his hands. But surely it is obvious that he will
                    not stop, unless someone stops him. And is that what we are to wait for? Do you
                    fancy that all is well, if you dispatch an unmanned fleet and the vague hope of
                    some deliverer? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="44">
                <p>Shall we not man the fleet ourselves? Shall we not take the field with at least a
                    proportion of native troops, even now, if never before? Shall we not sail
                    against his territory? “Where then are we to go and anchor?” someone has asked.
                    The progress of the war, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, will itself discover the weak places in his front, if
                    we make the effort; but if we sit here at home listening to the abuse and mutual
                    recriminations of the orators, there is not the slightest chance of our getting
                    anything done that ought to be done. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="45">
                <p>Wherever, I believe, we send out a force composed partly or wholly of our
                    citizens, there the gods are gracious and fortune fights on our side; but
                    wherever you send out a general with an empty decree and the mere aspirations of
                    this platform, your needs are not served, your enemies laugh you to scorn, your
                    allies stand in mortal fear of such an expeditionary force. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="46">
                <p>It is impossible, utterly impossible for one man ever to do all that you want
                    done; he can only promise<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Editors detect a
                        special allusion here. The “promises of Chares” had become
                        proverbial.</note> and assent and throw the blame on someone else. In
                    consequence our interests are ruined. For when your general leads wretched,
                    ill-paid mercenaries, and finds plenty of men here to lie to you about what he
                    has done, while you pass decrees at random on the strength of these reports,
                    what are you to expect? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="47">
                <p>How then is all this to be stopped? As soon as you, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, definitely appoint the same men as
                    soldiers and as eye-witnesses of the campaign, and, on their return, as jurymen
                    at the audit of your generals. In this way you will not merely learn about your
                    affairs by hearsay, but you will be witnesses on the spot. So scandalous is our
                    present system that every general is tried two or three times for his life in
                    your courts, but not one of them dares to risk death in battle against the
                    enemy; no, not once. They prefer the doom of a kidnapper or a pickpocket to a
                    fitting death; for malefactors are condemned to the gallows, generals should die
                    on the field of honor. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="48">
                <p>Some of us spread the rumor that Philip is negotiating with the Lacedaemonians
                    for the overthrow of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> and the
                    dissolution of the free states, others that he has sent an embassy to the Great
                    King, others that he is besieging towns in <placeName key="tgn,7016683"
                        >Illyria</placeName>; in short, each of us circulates his own piece of
                    fiction. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="49">
                <p>Truly, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I do think that
                    Philip is drunk with the magnitude of his achievements and dreams of further
                    triumphs, when, elated by his success, he finds that there is none to bar his
                    way; but I cannot for a moment believe that he is deliberately acting in such a
                    way that all the fools at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
                    know what he is going to do next. For of all fools the rumor-mongers are the
                    worst. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="50">
                <p>But if, putting rumors aside, we recognize that this man is our enemy, who has
                    for years been robbing and insulting us, that wherever we once hoped to find
                    help we have found hindrance, that the future lies in our own hands, and if we
                    refuse to fight now in <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>, we shall
                    perhaps be forced to fight here at home—if, I say, we recognize these facts,
                    then we shall have done with idle words and shall come to a right decision. Our
                    business is not to speculate on what the future may bring forth, but to be
                    certain that it will bring disaster, unless you face the facts and consent to do
                    your duty. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="51">
                <p>For my own part, I have never yet chosen to court your favor by saying anything
                    that I was not quite convinced would be to your advantage; and today, keeping
                    nothing back, I have given free utterance to my plain sentiments. Yet, certain
                    as I am that it is to your interest to receive the best advice, I could have
                    wished that I were equally certain that to offer such advice is also to the
                    interest of the speaker; for then I should have felt much happier. But, as it
                    is, in the uncertainty of what the result of my proposal may be for myself, yet
                    in the conviction that it will be to your interest to adopt it, I have ventured
                    to address you. Whatever shall be to the advantage of all, may that prevail!</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
