<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On the Chersonese</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <editor role="translator">J. H. Vince</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">1996</date>
            </publicationStmt> 			
            <notesStmt><note>Perseus 2.0</note></notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes. Vol. I. Olynthiacs, Philippics, Minor Public Speeches, Speech Against Leptines, I-XVII, XX. With an English translation by J. H. Vince</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date type="printing">1930</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.12682">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="section"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation marks="none"/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-12-21" who="Lisa Cerrato">converted to EpiDoc and CTS</change>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
            <change when="1992-06-02" who="David Smith">inserted quotedtext tag around verse</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body> <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0014.tlg008.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng"> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">It should be the duty of all speakers, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens" >Athens</placeName>, to give no expression to their hatred or their partiality, but to put forward just what each thinks the best counsel, especially when you are debating a question of urgent public importance. But since there are speakers who are impelled to address you, either as partisans or from some other motive, whatever it may be, you citizens who form the majority ought to dismiss all else from your minds, and vote and act in such a way as you think will best serve our city.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>The really serious problem is the state of the <placeName key="tgn,7017285" >Chersonese</placeName> and Philip's Thracian campaign, now in its eleventh month; yet most of the speeches have been confined to what Diopithes is doing or what he is going to do. For my part, when charges are brought against any of those whom you can legally punish whenever you like, I hold that it is open to you either to deal with their case at once or to postpone it; and it is quite unnecessary for me or anyone else to take a strong line on the subject of such charges.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>But when our national enemy, with a strong force, is trying to forestall us in the neighborhood of the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>, and when, if we are once too late, we shall never again be able to save the situation, then I think it is to our interest to complete our plans and preparations as quickly as we can, and not be diverted from our purpose by clamorous accusations about extraneous matters.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p rend="indent">I often wonder at the sort of speeches that are delivered here, but nothing, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, has surprised me more than what I heard uttered in the Council the other day, that your advisers are bound to put before you the plain alternative of fighting or observing the peace.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>But the fact is, if Philip keeps quiet and does not retain any of our territory contrary to the terms of peace, and does not form a general coalition against us, there is nothing more to be said and we must simply observe the peace, and I perceive a readiness to do so on your part at any rate; but if the oath that we took and the terms on which we made peace are published for all men to read, </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>and if it is proved that from the first, even before Diopithes set sail with colonists, whom they now accuse of having started hostilities, Philip has unfairly taken much that is ours, about which your decrees denouncing him still stand good, and that he is all the time repeatedly seizing the property of the other Greeks and of the barbarians, and so equipping himself for an attack upon us, what do they mean by saying that we must either make war or keep peace?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>For we have no choice in the matter, but there remains the most righteous and most necessary task of all, which these gentlemen deliberately pass over in silence. What then is that task? To defend ourselves against the aggressor. Or perhaps they mean that if Philip keeps his hands off <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> and the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>, he is neither injuring our city nor provoking hostilities.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>But if they ground their plea upon this principle, if this is their interpretation of the peace, it is obvious to all that their argument is assuredly impious and intolerable and dangerous to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; and it follows besides that their own words flatly contradict their indictment of Diopithes. For why on earth are we to give Philip leave to do everything else, provided he keeps clear of <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, while Diopithes is not allowed to help the Thracians, or else we shall have to admit that he is starting a war?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>Yes, you may say, as to that indeed the speakers are proved wrong, but the mercenaries are really acting abominably in ravaging the shores of the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>, and Diopithes is wrong in detaining the merchantmen, and we must not sanction it. Very well; be it so. I have no objection.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p>Only I think that, if their advice is really given in perfect good faith, even as they are trying to break up the force belonging to our city by bringing charges before you against the commander, who provides for its maintenance, so they are bound to show that Philip's force will also be disbanded, if you accept their advice. If not, you must observe that they are merely reducing our city to the same plight that has already caused her to forfeit all her existing advantages.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p>For I need not tell you that Philip owes his successes to nothing in the world more than to his being the first in the field. For the man who always keeps a standing army by him, and who knows beforehand what he wants to do, is ready in an instant for anyone that he chooses to attack, while it is only after we have heard of something happening that we begin to bustle about and make our preparations.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p>Hence, I believe, it results that Philip, quite at his leisure, keeps whatever he assails, while we are too late, and whatever we have spent has been lavished in vain; we have succeeded in showing our enmity and our will to thwart him, but by being too late for action we only incur additional ignominy.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p rend="indent">Do not, therefore, fail to observe, Athenians, that at present all else is mere talk and pretence; the real object of this scheming and contriving is that you should stay at home, with no Athenian force in field, while Philip, without the least trouble, settles everything to suit his wishes. For you must first note what is going on at the present moment.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"><p>He is now established in <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> with a large force, and is sending for considerable reinforcements from <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7001399" >Thessaly</placeName>, according to the statements of those on the spot. Now, if he waits for the Etesian winds to blow and marches to the siege of <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>, do you think that the Byzantines will remain in their present state of infatuation and will not call upon you and demand your help?</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15"><p>I think not. Nay, even if there are others whom they distrust more than us, I think they will rather admit such within their walls than surrender their city to Philip—if indeed he does not forestall them by capturing it. Therefore, if we cannot sail from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and if there is no force ready to help them on the spot, their doom is sealed.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16"><p><q type="spoken">Because,</q> you say, <q type="spoken">the wretched creatures are infatuated and stupid beyond measure.</q> Quite so, but still we are bound to preserve them in the interests of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. And then again we are not certain of another thing, that he will not attack the <placeName key="tgn,7017285">Chersonese</placeName>. Indeed, if we may judge from the letter which he sent you, he means to take vengeance on the settlers there.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17"><p>If, therefore, our present force is still in being, it will be able both to save the <placeName key="tgn,7010345">Chersonese</placeName> and to make raids upon Philip's territory. But if it is once disbanded, what shall we do if he marches against the <placeName key="tgn,7010345">Chersonese</placeName>? <q type="spoken">Bring Diopithes to trial,</q> you say. And how will that help matters? <q type="spoken">Well, then, we will set out from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> ourselves.</q> But suppose the winds will not let us? <q type="spoken">But surely Philip will not attack.</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18"><p>And who will go bail for that? Do you not observe and consider, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, what season<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The season of the Etesian winds; see <bibl n="Dem. 8.14">Dem. 8.14</bibl>.</note> of the year is upon us—the season at which certain people think it their duty to keep the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName> clear of you and hand it over to Philip? What if he quits <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> and never approaches the <placeName key="tgn,7010345">Chersonese</placeName> or Byzantium—for you must take that also into your reckoning—but turns up at <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>, just as he did at Oreus not long ago? Will it be better to make our stand here and let the war spread to <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, or to contrive some employment for him away yonder? I prefer the latter.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19"><p rend="indent">Therefore, knowing and weighing these facts, it is the duty of all of you, not surely to try to disparage and break up the force that Diopithes is doing his best to provide for the state, but to provide an additional force yourselves and to keep him well supplied with funds and in every way to give him your loyal co-operation.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20"><p>For suppose someone should ask Philip, <q type="spoken">Tell me, which would you prefer? That the troops now serving with Diopithes, whatever their character may be</q>—for I am not discussing that—<q type="spoken">should prosper and win credit at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and grow in numbers with the co-operation of the government, or that a few accusers and detractors should cause them to be broken up and destroyed?</q> I think he would choose the latter. And what Philip would pray the gods to vouchsafe him, are some of us here trying to compass? And do you still ask how our interests are sacrificed everywhere? </p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21"><p rend="indent">I want therefore to examine frankly the present state of our affairs, and to find out what we are doing ourselves now and how we are dealing with the situation. We refuse to pay war-taxes or to serve in person; we cannot keep our hands off the public funds; we will not pay Diopithes the allowances agreed upon, nor sanction the sums that he raises for himself; </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22"><p>but we grumble and criticize his methods, and ask what he intends to do, and all that sort of thing; and yet, while maintaining that attitude, we refuse to perform our own tasks; with our lips we praise those whose speeches are worthy of our city, but our actions serve only to encourage their opponents.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23"><p>Now, you have a habit of asking a speaker on every occasion, <q type="spoken">What then must be done?</q>; but I prefer to ask you, <q type="spoken">What then must be said?</q> Because, if you are not going to pay your contributions, nor serve in person, nor keep your hands off the public funds, nor grant Diopithes his allowances, nor sanction the sums that he raises for himself, nor consent to perform your own tasks, I have nothing to say. You who have gone so far in granting license to those whose object is fault-finding and calumny, that even about what they say he is going to do, even on that ground they accuse him in advance and you listen to them—what can anyone say? </p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24"><p rend="indent">Now, some of you ought to be told the possible result of all this. I shall speak freely, for indeed I could not speak otherwise. All the generals that have ever set sail from your land—if I am wrong, I submit myself to any penalty—raise money from the Chians, from the Erythraeans, from whatever people they can, I mean of the Greeks of <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25"><p>Generals with only one or two ships raise less; those with a larger fleet raise more. Also those who pay do not pay the sum, be it large or small, for nothing; they are not such madmen. No, they purchase for the merchants sailing from their own harbors immunity from injury or robbery, or a safe conduct for their own ships, or something of that sort. They say that they are granting <q type="soCalled">benevolences.</q> That is the name for these exactions.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26"><p>And so too in this case, while Diopithes has a force with him, it is perfectly plain that all these people will pay up. For where else do you suppose that he looks for the maintenance of his troops, if he gets nothing from you and has no private fortune to furnish their pay? To the sky? No, indeed; it is from what he can collect or beg or borrow that he keeps things going.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27"><p>So those who denounce him to you are simply warning everybody not to grant him a penny, because he will be punished for what he intends to do, apart from what he has done or what he has acquired for himself. That is what they mean when they cry, <q type="spoken">He intends to besiege the towns! He is betraying the Greeks!</q> Do any of these gentlemen really care about the Asiatic Greeks?—and yet they would, I expect, be better champions of other countries than of their own.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28"><p>That, too, is the meaning of the dispatch of a second general to the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName>. For if Diopithes is acting outrageously in detaining the merchantmen, a note, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, a brief note, could put a stop to all this at once; and there are the laws, which direct us to impeach such offenders, but not, of course, to mount guard over ourselves,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. to keep a jealous watch over our own officers.</note> at such a cost and with so large a fleet; for that would be the height of madness.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29"><p>No, against our enemies, who are not amenable to the laws, it is right and necessary to maintain troops, to send out fleets, and to raise funds; but against ourselves we have these resources, a decree, an impeachment, and a dispatch-boat. Those are what right-minded citizens would employ; malignants, bent on the ruin of the State, would do as these men are doing.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30"><p>And that there are some men of this type among you, though bad enough, is not the real evil; but you who sit here are by now in such a mood that if anyone comes forward and asserts that the cause of all our evil is Diopithes or Chares or Aristophon, or any other citizen that he happens to name, you at once agree and applaud the truth of the remark.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31"><p>But if anyone rises and tells you the real truth and says, <q type="spoken">Nonsense, Athenians! The cause of all these evils and all these troubles is Philip, for if he had kept quiet, our city would have been free from trouble,</q> you cannot gainsay it, but you seem to me to be vexed and to feel that you are, as it were, losing something.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32"><p>But as to the reason for this—and in Heaven's name, when I am pleading for your best interests, allow me to speak freely—some of our politicians have been training you to be threatening and intractable in the meetings of the Assembly, but in preparing for war, careless and contemptible. If, then, the culprit named is someone on whom you know you can lay hands in <placeName key="perseus,Athens" >Athens</placeName>, you agree and assent; but if it is someone whom you cannot chastise unless you overcome him by force of arms, you find yourselves helpless, I suppose, and to be proved so causes you annoyance.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33"><p>For it ought to have been the reverse, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens" >Athens</placeName>; all your politicians should have trained you to be gentle and humane in the Assembly, for there you are dealing with rights that concern yourselves and your allies, but in preparing for war they should have made you threatening and intractable, because there you are pitted against your enemies and rivals.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34"><p>As it is, by persuasive arts and caresses they have brought you to such a frame of mind that in your assemblies you are elated by their flattery and have no ear but for compliments, while in your policy and your practice you are at this moment running the gravest risks. For tell me, in Heaven's name, if the Greeks should call you to account for the opportunities that your carelessness has already thrown away, and should question you thus: </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="35"><p><q type="spoken">Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, do you send us embassies on every occasion to explain how Philip is plotting against us and all the other Greeks, and how we must be on our guard against that man, and all that sort of thing?</q>—(we are bound to admit it and plead guilty, for that is just what we do)—<q type="spoken">And yet, you most futile of mortals, when that man has been out of sight<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">As in <bibl n="Dem. 8.2">Dem. 8.2</bibl>, he alludes to Philip's absence on his Thracian campaign.</note> for ten months, cut off from all chance of returning home by disease, by winter, and by war,</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="36"><p><q type="spoken" rend="merge">have you neither liberated <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> nor regained any of your lost possessions? On the other hand, while you stay at home, at leisure and in health</q>—(if indeed they could say that men who behave thus are in health)—<q type="spoken">Philip has set up two despots in <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, entrenching one right over against <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> and the other as a menace to Sciathus;</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="37"><p><q type="spoken" rend="merge">but you—have you never cleared away these obstacles, even if you had no further ambitions, and have you tamely submitted? Undoubtedly you have stood aside from his path and made it abundantly clear that, were he to die ten times over, you at least will make no further move. Then why do you pester us with your embassies and your complaints?</q> If these are their words, what are we to say, Athenians? How are we to answer? For my part, I cannot tell.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="38"><p rend="indent">Now there are some who think they confute a speaker the moment they ask, <q type="spoken">What then ought we to do?</q> To these I will give the fairest and truest answer: not what you are doing now. I will not, however, shrink from going carefully into details; only they must be as willing to act as they are eager to question.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="39"><p>First, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you must fix this firmly in your minds, that Philip is at war with us and has broken the peace. Yes, let there be no more wrangling over that question. He is ill-disposed and hostile to the whole city and to the very soil on which the city stands, </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="40"><p>and, I will add, to every man in the city, even to those who imagine that they stand highest in his good graces. If they doubt it, let them look at Euthycrates and Lasthenes, the Olynthians, who thought they were such bosom-friends of his, and then, when they had betrayed their city, met the most ignominious fate of all. The chief object, however, of his arms and his diplomacy is our free constitution; on nothing in the world is he more bent than on its destruction.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="41"><p>And it is in a way natural that he should act thus. For he knows for certain that even if he masters all else, his power will be precarious as long as you remain a democracy; but if ever he meets with one of the many mischances to which mankind is liable, all the forces that are now under restraint will be attracted to your side.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="42"><p>For nature has not equipped you to seek aggrandizement and secure empire, but you are clever at thwarting another's designs and wresting from him his gains, and quick to confound the plots of the ambitious and to vindicate the freedom of all mankind. Therefore he does not want to have the Athenian tradition of liberty watching to seize every chance against himself. Far from it! Nor is his reasoning here either faulty or idle.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="43"><p>This, then, is the first thing needful, to recognize in Philip the inveterate enemy of constitutional government and democracy, for unless you are heartily persuaded of this, you will not consent to take your politics seriously. Your second need is to convince yourselves that all his activity and all his organization is preparing the way for an attack on our city, and that where any resistance is offered to him, that resistance is our gain.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="44"><p>For no man is so simple as to believe that though Philip covets these wretched objects in Thrace—for what else can one call Drongilus and <placeName key="tgn,7010710">Cabyle</placeName> and Mastira and the other places that he is now occupying and equipping?—and though he endures toil and winter storms and deadly peril for the privilege of taking them, </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="45"><p>yet he does not covet the Athenian harbors and dockyards and war-galleys and silver mines and the like sources of wealth, but will allow you to retain them, while he winters in that purgatory for the sake of the rye and millet of the Thracian store-pits. It is not so, but it is to win these prizes that he devotes his activities to all those other objects.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="46"><p>What, then, is the task of sound patriots? To know and realize all this, to shake off our outrageous and incurable slothfulness, to contribute funds, to call upon our allies, and to provide and arrange for the permanent upkeep of our existing army, so that just as Philip has a force ready to attack and enslave all the Greek states, so you may have one ready to protect and assist them all.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="47"><p>For if you trust to mere expeditions, you can never gain any of your essential objects. You must first levy a force and provide for its maintenance, and appoint paymasters and clerks, and arrange that there shall be the strictest watch kept over your expenditure, and afterwards you must demand from your paymasters an account of their moneys, and from the general an account of his campaign. If you do this, and if you are really in earnest about it, you will either compel Philip to keep the peace fairly and to abide within his own frontiers—and that would be the greatest blessing of all—or you will fight him on equal terms.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="48"><p rend="indent">But if anyone thinks that all this means great expense and much toil and worry, he is quite correct, but if he reckons up what will hereafter be the result to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> if she refuses to act, he will conclude that it is to our interest to perform our duty willingly.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="49"><p>For if you have the guarantee of some god, since no mere mortal could be a satisfactory surety for such an event that if you remain inactive and abandon everything, Philip will not in the end march against yourselves, by Zeus and all the other gods, it would be disgraceful and unworthy of you and of the resources of your city and the record of your ancestors to abandon all the other Greeks to enslavement for the sake of your own ease, and I for one would rather die than be guilty of proposing such a policy. All the same, if someone else proposes it and wins your assent, so be it: offer no resistance, sacrifice everything.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="50"><p>But if no one approves of this, and if on the contrary we all of us foresee that the more we allow him to extend his power, the stronger and more formidable we shall find him in war, what escape is open to us, or why do we delay? When, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, shall we consent to do our duty? <q type="spoken">Whenever it is necessary,</q> you will say.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="51"><p>But what any free man would call necessity is not merely present now, but is long ago past, and from the necessity that constrains a slave we must surely pray to be delivered. Do you ask the difference? The strongest necessity that a free man feels is shame for his own position, and I know not if we could name a stronger; but for a slave necessity means stripes and bodily outrage, unfit to name here, from which Heaven defend us! </p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="52"><p rend="indent">Therefore, although I would gladly touch on all the other topics and explain the way in which certain politicians are working your ruin, I will confine myself to pointing out that whenever any question arises that concerns Philip, instantly up jumps someone and tells you how good a thing it is to preserve peace, and what a bother it is to keep up a large army, and how certain persons want to plunder your wealth, and all that sort of thing; and by these speeches they put you off and afford leisure for Philip to do whatever he wishes.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="53"><p>But the result of this is for you indeed repose and idleness, for the present—blessings which I am afraid you will one day consider dearly purchased—but for the speakers the popularity and the payment. But in my view it is not to you that they should recommend peace, for you have taken the advice and there you sit: it is to the man who is even now on the war-path.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="54"><p>For if Philip can be won over, your share of the compact is ready to hand. Again, they should reflect that the irksome thing is not the expense of securing our safety, but the doom that will be ours if we shrink from that expense. As for the <q type="soCalled">plunder of your wealth,</q> they ought to prevent that by proposing some way of checking it and not by abandoning your interests.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="55"><p>And yet, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, it is just this that rouses my indignation, that some of you should be distressed at the prospect of the plunder of your wealth, when you are quite competent to protect it and to punish any offender, but that you are not distressed at the sight of Philip thus plundering every Greek state in turn, the more so as he is plundering them to injure you.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="56"><p rend="indent">What then is the reason, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens" >Athens</placeName>, why these speakers never admit that Philip is provoking war, when he is thus openly conducting campaigns, violating rights, and subduing cities, but when others urge you not to give way to Philip nor submit to these losses, they accuse them of trying to provoke war? I will explain.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="57"><p>It is because they want the natural anger that you would feel at any sufferings in the war to be diverted against your wisest counsellors, so that you may bring them to trial instead of punishing Philip, and that they may themselves be the accusers instead of paying the penalty for their present wrong-doings. That is the meaning of their suggestion that there is a party among you that desires war, and that that is the question you now have to decide.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="grc">διαδικασία</foreign> is a lawsuit between rival claimants to an estate, etc. The war-party and the peace-party are here rival claimants for the votes of the Athenians.</note></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="58"><p>But I am absolutely certain that, without waiting for any Athenian to propose a declaration of war, Philip is in possession of much of our territory and has just dispatched a force against Cardia. If, however, we like to pretend that he is not at war with us, he would be the greatest fool alive if he tried to disprove that.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="59"><p>But when our turn comes, what shall we say then? For of course he will deny that he is attacking us, just as he denied that he was attacking the men of Oreus, when his troops were already in their territory, or the Pheraeans before that, when he was actually assaulting their walls, or the Olynthians at the start, until he was inside their frontiers with his army. Or shall we say, even at that hour, that those who bid us repel him are provoking war? If so, there is nothing left but slavery; for there is no alternative between that and being allowed neither to defend ourselves nor to remain at peace.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="60"><p>Moreover, you have not the same interests at stake as the other cities, for it is not our subjection that Philip aims at, but our annihilation. He is well assured that you will not consent to be slaves; or if you consent, will never learn how to be slaves, for you are accustomed to rule others; but that you will be able, if you seize your opportunity, to cause him more trouble than all the rest of the world.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="61"><p rend="indent">Therefore you must needs bear in mind that this is a life-and-death struggle, and the men who have sold themselves to Philip must be abhorred and cudgelled to death, for it is impossible to quell the foes without, until you have punished those within your gates <del>who are Philip's servants; but if you are tripped by these stumbling-blocks, you are sure to be baulked of the others</del>.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="62"><p>What do you imagine is his motive in outraging you now—I think no other term describes his conduct—or why is it that, in deceiving the others, he at least confers benefits upon them, but in your case he is already resorting to threats? For example, the Thessalians were beguiled by his generosity into their present state of servitude; no words can describe how he formerly deceived the miserable Olynthians by his gift of <placeName key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName> and many other places;</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="63"><p>the Thebans he is now misleading, having handed over <placeName key="tgn,7002683" >Boeotia</placeName> to them and relieved them of a long and trying war. So each of these states has reaped some benefit from him; some of them have already paid the penalty, as all men know; the rest will pay it whenever the day of reckoning comes. As for you, I say nothing of your losses <add>in war</add>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Some such words seem necessary to avoid a contradiction. The Greek is probably corrupt, though the same reading is found in <bibl n="Dem. 10.65">Dem. 10.65</bibl>.</note> but in the very act of accepting the peace, how completely you were deceived, how grievously you were robbed!</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="64"><p>Were you not deceived about <placeName key="tgn,4003963">Phocis</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName>, the Thraceward districts, Doriscus, Serrium, Cersobleptes himself? Is not Philip now holding the city of the Cardians, and admitting that he holds it? Why then does he deal thus with the other Greeks, but not with you in the same way? Because ours is the one city in the world where immunity is granted to plead on behalf of our enemies, and where a man who has been bribed can safely address you in person, even when you have been robbed of your own.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="65"><p>It would not have been safe in <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus" >Olynthus</placeName> to plead Philip's cause, unless the Olynthian democracy had shared in the enjoyment of the revenues of <placeName key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName>. It would not have been safe in <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> to plead Philip's cause, if the commoners of <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> had not shared in the advantages that Philip conferred when he expelled their tyrants and restored to them their Amphictyonic privileges. It would not have been safe at <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, until he gave them back <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> and wiped out the Phocians.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="66"><p>But at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, though Philip has not only robbed you of <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName> and the Cardian territory, but is also turning <placeName key="tgn,7002677" >Euboea</placeName> into a fortress to overawe you, and is even now on his way to attack <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>, it is safe to speak on Philip's behalf. Indeed, of these politicians, some who were beggars are suddenly growing rich, some unknown to name and fame are now men of honor and distinction; while you, on the contrary, have passed from honor to dishonor, from affluence to destitution. For a city's wealth I hold to be allies, credit, goodwill, and of all these you are destitute.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="67"><p>Because you are indifferent to these advantages and allow them to be taken from you, Philip is prosperous and powerful and formidable to Greeks and barbarians alike, while you are deserted and humiliated, famous for your well-stocked markets, but in provision for your proper needs, contemptible. Yet I observe that some of our speakers do not urge the same policy for you as for themselves; for you, they say, ought to remain quiet even when you are wronged; they themselves cannot remain quiet among you, though no man does them wrong.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">They want you to remain passive, though they themselves lead an active political life, in Philip's interests. See the expansion of this passage in <bibl n="Dem. 10.70">Dem. 10.70-74</bibl>.</note></p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="68"><p rend="indent">Then some irresponsible person comes forward and says, <q type="spoken">Of course, you decline to make a definite proposal or to run any such risk. You are a coward and a milksop.</q> I am not foolhardy, impudent, and shameless, and I pray that I may never be; nevertheless I think myself more truly brave than many of your neck-or-nothing politicians.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="69"><p>For if anyone, Athenians, disregarding what will benefit the State, traffics in trials, confiscations, bribes, and indictments, he shows in this no true bravery, but, ensuring his own safety by the popularity of his speeches and measures, he is bold without risk. But whoever in your best interests often opposes your wishes, and never speaks to win favor, but always gives you of his best, and makes choice of that policy which is more under the dominion of chance than of calculation, and yet accepts the responsibility of either, he is the brave man.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="70"><p>Yes, and it is he who is the useful citizen, not those who for a moment's popularity have made havoc of the chief resources of the State. These men I am so far from envying or deeming them worthy citizens of our city, that if a man should say to me, <q type="spoken">Speak for yourself, and tell us what good you have ever done the State,</q> though I might speak, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens" >Athens</placeName>, of the equipment of war-galleys and of choruses, of money contributions and of the ransom of captives, and of other instances of liberality, </p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="71"><p>I would say not a word of them, but only reply that my policy has never been the policy of these men; that though I could, perhaps as well as the rest, accuse and bribe and confiscate and act in general as they are acting, I have never applied myself to any of these arts nor obeyed the promptings of greed or ambition, but continue to offer advice which does indeed lower me in your esteem, but which, if you will follow it, would contribute to your greatness. So much perhaps I may say of myself without offence.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="72"><p>Nor indeed does it seem to me the part of an honest citizen to devise political measures by which I shall at once take the highest place among you, but you the lowest among the nations. No, the advancement of the State must always go along with the measures proposed by good citizens, and they must always support the best and not the easiest policy; for towards the latter nature herself will lead the way, but to instruct you by speech and guide you to the former is the duty of the good citizen.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="73"><p rend="indent">Now I have even heard some such remark as this: that I, of course, always speak for the best, but that you get nothing from me except words, while what the city wants is deeds and a practical policy of some sort. I will myself explain how I stand in this matter, and I will be perfectly candid. I do not think that your adviser has any business except to give the best counsel he can, and I think I can easily prove that this is so.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="74"><p>For you know, of course, that the famous Timotheus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">One of the most successful of the Athenian generals, from <date when="-0378">378</date> till his eclipse in <date when="-0354">354</date>, when he was condemned and fined for failure in the Social War. His intimacy with Isocrates had made him also an effective speaker. His biography is included in the collection of Cornelius Nepos. The occasion here referred to is the Euboean expedition of <date when="-0357">357</date>, when Demosthenes served as trierarch.</note> once harangued you to the effect that you ought to send an expedition to save the Euboeans, when the Thebans were trying to enslave them, and his words ran something like this: <q type="spoken">Tell me,</q> he said, <q type="spoken">when you have got the Thebans in the island, are you deliberating how you will deal with them and what you ought to do? Will you not cover the sea with your war-galleys, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>? Will you not rise up at once and march down to the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus" >Piraeus</placeName> and drag them down the slips?</q> </p> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="75"><p>That, then, was what Timotheus said, and that was what you did, and the union of the two brought about the practical result. But if Timotheus had given you the best advice he could (as indeed he did), but you had shirked your duty and paid no heed to him, would the State have reaped any of the effects that then followed? Not a bit of it. So the same applies to whatever I utter now and whatever this man or that utters. For deeds you must look to yourselves, but for advice, the best that skill in speech can command, look to the speaker who rises to address you.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="76"><p rend="indent">Let me sum up before I leave the platform. I say that we must pay our contributions and keep together the force now in the field, rectifying whatever seems to be amiss, but not disbanding the whole for any adverse criticism. We must send ambassadors in every direction to instruct, to exhort, to act. While doing all this, we must also punish those politicians who take bribes, and we must hate them wherever found, in order that those who prove their own virtue and honesty may find that their advice has been beneficial to themselves as well as to the citizens at large.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="77"><p>If you deal thus with public affairs and cease to neglect them entirely, perhaps, yes, perhaps even now there may be a change for the better. If, however, you sit here, confining your zeal to cries of dissent or approval, and drawing back from every call to duty, I see not that any words, divorced from the necessary action on your part, can ever save the State.</p> </div> </div> </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
