<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Leptines</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <editor role="translator">J. H. Vince</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">1996</date>
            </publicationStmt> 			
            <notesStmt><note>Perseus 2.0</note></notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes. Vol. I. Olynthiacs, Philippics, Minor Public Speeches, Speech Against Leptines, I-XVII, XX. With an English translation by J. H. Vince</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date type="printing">1930</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.12682">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
            <change when="1992-06-02" who="David Smith">inserted quotedtext tag around verse</change>
        </revisionDesc>    
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>Gentlemen of the jury, it is chiefly because I consider that the State will
                    benefit by the repeal of this law, but partly also out of sympathy with the
                    young son of Chabrias, that I have consented to support the plaintiffs to the
                    best of my ability. It is clear, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, that Leptines and anyone else who defends the law will
                    have nothing fair to say in its favor, but will urge the unworthiness of certain
                    persons who have used their exemption as a means of shirking the public
                    services, and he will take his stand chiefly on that ground. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>For my own part, I shall forbear to retort that it is unjust to take away this
                    privilege from all because you find fault with some; for that objection has
                    already been partially stated,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">By the previous
                        speaker, Phormio.</note> and you probably realize its force. But I should
                    like to ask Leptines on what grounds, even if not some, but all the recipients
                    had been to the last degree undeserving, he has meted out the same treatment to
                    you as to them; for by the clause "none shall be exempt" he has taken away the
                    privilege from those who now enjoy it, while by the addition "nor shall it be
                    lawful hereafter to grant it" he takes away from you the right to bestow it. For
                    surely he cannot mean that precisely as he thought the holders of this privilege
                    unworthy, so he thought the people unworthy of the right to dispense its own
                    favors to whomsoever it wishes. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>But perhaps he may object here that he framed his law in this way because the
                    people are so easily gulled. But by parity of reasoning why should you not be
                    deprived of all your rights—of the whole constitution in fact? For there is no
                    single—right which has not been abused in this way. You have often been deceived
                    into passing decrees; you have sometimes been induced to choose weak allies
                    rather than strong; and generally, I suppose, in many of your public proceedings
                    the same thing is bound to happen. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>Shall we then make a law that hereafter neither Council nor Assembly shall be
                    permitted to deliberate or to vote on any subject? Not so, in my opinion; for we
                    ought not to be deprived of our rights, where we have been misled; we ought to
                    be instructed how to avoid such mistakes, and we ought to make a law, not to
                    strip us of our own authority, but to punish those who mislead us. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>Now if, putting these considerations aside, you would examine the real problem,
                    whether it is more advantageous that you should possess the power of bestowing
                    this privilege, even though you are sometimes duped into bestowing it on a
                    scoundrel, or that by being wholly dispossessed of it you should be unable to
                    grant honors even where they are deserved, you would find the former course the
                    more advantageous. And why? Because the result of rewarding too many citizens is
                    to encourage many to do you good service, but the result of rewarding no one,
                    even if deserving, is to discourage emulation in all. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>There is also this other reason, that those who reward an undeserving individual
                    may be credited with some degree of artlessness,<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb"><foreign xml:lang="grc">eu)h/qeia</foreign>has many shades of
                        meaning from simplicity to folly. Here the contrast with<foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">kaki/a</foreign>shows that the milder sense predominates;
                        not so in <bibl n="Dem. 20.145">Dem. 20.145</bibl>.</note> but those who
                    never requite their benefactors are charged with baseness. Just so far as it is
                    better to be thought artless than unscrupulous, it is more honorable to repeal
                    this law than to enact it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>Nor again, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, on
                    reflection does it seem to me reasonable, when finding fault with some on the
                    ground of the rewards they already enjoy, to rob useful citizens of their
                    honors. For if, while these immunities exist, some of the recipients are, as our
                    opponents say, worthless and unprofitable, what result are we to expect when
                    there is no chance whatever of reward for the good citizens? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>Then again, you must consider this point, that in accordance with the existing
                    laws of long standing—laws of which Leptines himself cannot deny the
                    soundness—there is an interval of a year between each public service, so that
                    half the time a citizen is immune. And then, when all citizens, even those who
                    have not benefited you in the least, enjoy a half share in that privilege, are
                    we to take away from your real benefactors the addition that we made to it?
                    Surely not; for that would be dishonorable and, in your case, especially
                    unbecoming. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>When we have a law which forbids cheating in the marketplace, where a falsehood
                    entails no public injury, is it not disgraceful that in public affairs the same
                    state should not abide by the law which it enjoins on private individuals, but
                    should cheat its benefactors, and that although it is itself likely to incur no
                    small penalty? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>For we must take account not only of loss of money, but of loss of good fame,
                    which you are more anxious to keep than your money—yes, you and your ancestors
                    also. The proof of this is that when they had accumulated vast sums, they spent
                    all for honor, and when reputation was at stake, they never shrank from danger,
                    but even lavished their private fortunes without stint.<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">He refers to the wealth of the State in the time of Pericles
                        (cf. <bibl n="Dem. 13.26">Dem. 13.26</bibl>), and to the exertions of the
                        Athenians during the Peloponnesian War.</note> As it stands, then, this law
                    reflects on your city not honor but disgrace, unworthy alike of your ancestors
                    and of yourselves; for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> is
                    incurring the three worst reproaches—that men should think us envious,
                    faithless, ungrateful. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>Next, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that it is
                    absolutely contrary to the national character to ratify such a law as this, I
                    will also endeavor to show you briefly by an example of our conduct in the past.
                    The Thirty Tyrants are said to have borrowed money from the Lacedaemonians for
                    use against the patriots in the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus"
                        >Piraeus</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In 403 Thrasybulus
                        and the exiled democrats had occupied the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus"
                            >Piraeus</placeName> and defeated the Thirty, whose government was then
                        changed to that of the Ten. The Spartans were persuaded by Lysander to lend
                        the Ten 100 talents, but shortly afterwards Pausanias, the Spartan king, who
                        was no friend to Lysander, intervened, withdrew the Spartan son from the
                        Acropolis, and reconciled the parties. The story of the loan is narrated by
                        Xenophon and Plutarch; the decree of the Assembly, accepting responsibility
                        for the repayment, is attested also by <bibl n="Isoc. 7.67">Isoc. Areop.
                            67</bibl>.</note> But when unity was restored to the State and those
                    disputes were settled, the Lacedaemonians sent envoys to demand payment. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>When the question was discussed and some were for ordering the city-party, who
                    were the real borrowers, to repay, while others claimed that the first sign of
                    reconciliation should be the joint settlement of the debt, they say that the
                    people chose to pay their contribution and bear their share of the loss, so that
                    there should be no breach of the agreement. On that occasion, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to avoid a breach of faith, you
                    consented to pay money to those who had injured you, but now, when you might
                    without any expense requite your benefactors by repealing this law, will it not
                    be strange if you prefer to break your faith? I for one cannot approve of it.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>The instance I have quoted, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, as well many others, will show what our national
                    character is—truthful, honest, and, where money is concerned, not asking what
                    pays best, but what is the honorable thing to do. But as to the character of the
                    proposer of this law, I have no further knowledge of him, nor do I say or know
                    anything to his prejudice; but if I may judge from his law, I detect a character
                    very far removed from what I have described. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>I say, then, that it would be more honorable for Leptines to be guided by you in
                    repealing the law than for you to be guided by him in ratifying it, and it would
                    be more profitable for you, as well as for him, that <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> should persuade Leptines to assume a
                    likeness to herself than that she should be persuaded by Leptines to be like
                    him; for even if he is a really good man—and he may be, for aught I know—he
                    cannot excel her in character. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>Moreover, gentlemen, I think that you would come to a sounder judgement in this
                    matter if you would observe this further truth, that the present law removes
                    just the one advantage which the rewards of a democracy have over those of other
                    constitutions. For in the material value to the recipients of the rewards
                    bestowed, a tyranny or an oligarchy has an immense advantage in that they can
                    make anyone they choose instantaneously rich; but in honor and in security of
                    possession you will find that the gifts of a democracy are to be preferred. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>For not the receipt of a flatterer's pay with its taint of shame, but to be
                    honored, where speech is free, as one who is deemed worthy—that is true glory;
                    and to enjoy the willing admiration of equals seems better than to accept the
                    richest gift from a tyrant's hand. For in those communities the fear of tomorrow
                    outweighs the favor of today, but in your city a man could keep what he won
                    without fear of loss, at any rate in time past. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>So the law which destroys confidence in the rewards takes away the one thing that
                    gives a higher value to rewards which you bestow. And indeed, if from any one of
                    all known forms of government you take away the right of loyal supporters of the
                    constitution to receive favors, you will find that you have deprived those
                    governments of no unimportant safeguard. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>Now perhaps Leptines will try to divert your attention from these points and
                    assert that at present the public services fall upon the poor, but that under
                    his law they will be performed by the wealthiest class. At first hearing, the
                    plea seems to have some weight; but examine it strictly and the fallacy will be
                    exposed. For there are, as you know, among us some services that fall upon
                    resident aliens and others that fall upon citizens, and the exemption, which
                    Leptines would remove, has been granted in the case of both. For from special
                    contributions for war or for national defence and also from the equipment of
                    war-galleys, rightly and justly in accordance with earlier laws, no one is
                    exempt, not even the descendants of Harmodius and Aristogiton, whom Leptines has
                    specially named. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>Let us then see what additional contributors he provides to perform those public
                    services, and how many will be passed over if we turn a deaf ear to him. Now the
                    richest citizens, when equipping a war-galley, are already exempt from the
                    ordinary services, while those whose wealth is insufficient necessarily enjoy
                    exemption and are out of the reach of this tax; so his law will not provide us
                    with another contributor from either of these classes. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>He may reply that he recruits many aliens for the services. But if he can point
                    to five such, I will eat my words. I will assume, then, that this is not the
                    case, but that if the law stands, both the number of aliens performing public
                    services will be greater, and of the citizens none will be excused because he is
                    equipping a war-galley. Now let us consider what the State will gain if all
                    these perform the services, for it will prove to be no compensation at all for
                    the disgrace it will entail. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>Put it thus. Of aliens there are exempt—I will assume ten. And by Heaven, as I
                    said before, I do not believe there are five. Moreover of the citizens there are
                    not half a dozen. Sixteen of both, then. Let us call it twenty, or thirty, if
                    you like. How many, pray, are there that annually perform the regularly
                    recurring services—chorus-masters, presidents of gymnasia, and public hosts?
                    Perhaps sixty in all, or a trifle more. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>In order, then, that we may have thirty more men for the public services, spread
                    over the whole period,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">As there was a list of
                        300 citizens qualified for the<foreign xml:lang="grc"
                        >proeisfora/</foreign>and of <date when="1200">1200</date> for the
                        trierarchy, we may perhaps assume a list of 600 for the regular services. At
                        the rate of 60 a year, it would take 10 years to work through the list, if
                        the contributors were called upon strictly in rotation by the officials of
                        their respective tribes. Therefore the outside estimate of 30 additional
                        contributors, rendered available by abolishing the immunities, would provide
                        only 3 more each year; i.e. 3 citizens out of 60 would be relieved annually.
                        In case of a real shortage of qualified contributors, Demosthenes would
                        prefer the adoption of the system, first instituted for the trierarchy in
                        357, whereby the <date when="1200">1200</date> were divided into 20
                        companies (<foreign xml:lang="grc">summori/ai</foreign>) of 60 each, further
                        subdivided into syndicates (<foreign xml:lang="grc">sunte/leiai</foreign>),
                        each responsible for one ship. This was the system reformed at a later date
                        by Demosthenes himself.</note> is it worth our while to excite the distrust
                    of all? But surely we must know this, that as long as <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> stands, there will be plenty of
                    citizens, without fail, to perform the services, but not a soul will want to do
                    us a good turn, if he sees our previous benefactors wronged. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>So far, so good. But if there were the most serious shortage of possible
                    contributors, in Heaven's name, which would you prefer—to organize syndicates
                    for those services as for the equipment of war-vessels, or to rob your
                    benefactors of what you have given them? I think I should prefer the syndicates.
                    By the present law, while each of these thirty is performing a public service,
                    Leptines affords a respite for the others, and that is all; after that, each of
                    them will have to spend as much as before; but in the other case, each would pay
                    a small contribution, proportioned to his means, and none would be hardly
                    treated, even if his property were quite small. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>Now some of our opponents, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, are so illogical that they make no attempt to answer
                    these arguments, but take a different line, saying for instance how monstrous it
                    is that on the one hand there is nothing left in the Exchequer, but on the other
                    hand private individuals will grow wealthy because they have secured an
                    immunity. But it is not fair to combine both these statements. For if a man has
                    great wealth without doing you any wrong, there is surely no need to look on him
                    with envy; but if they are prepared to say that he has stolen it or gained it in
                    some other disreputable way, there are laws by which he can be suitably
                    punished. But as long as they do not prosecute him, neither have they any right
                    to make this allegation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>Further, with regard to the alleged poverty of the Exchequer, you must reflect
                    that you will not be a whit the better off if you abolish these exemptions, for
                    the expenditure on these services has nothing to do with the revenues or the
                    surplus of the State. And apart from all this, of two possible advantages—wealth
                    and credit with the rest of the world—our State today enjoys the latter. But if
                    anyone imagines that because we have no money we need not also keep our honor
                    bright, his judgement is at fault. For myself indeed, I pray Heaven that, if so
                    it may be, our wealth also may increase, but if not, then at least that our
                    reputation for good faith and constancy may remain sure. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>Now take the large fortunes which, according to our opponents, some citizens will
                    amass if relieved of the services, but which I will show to be available for
                    your needs. For of course you are aware that no one is exempt from the equipment
                    of war-galleys or from the special contributions for war. So this person,
                    whoever he may be, who owns much, contributes much to those objects; there is no
                    getting out of it. And again, all would agree that the resources which the State
                    can rely on for these objects should be as great as possible. For money spent by
                    the chorus-masters affords those of us who are in the theater gratification for
                    a fraction of a day; but money lavished on equipment for war gives security to
                    the whole city for all time. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>Therefore whatever you remit with one hand, you receive with the other; and you
                    grant as an honor exemptions which even those who receive them cannot enjoy, if
                    they have wealth sufficient for the equipment of a war-vessel. But although I
                    suppose you all know that no one is exempt from the latter service, the clerk
                    shall read to you the actual statute. Take the law about the trierarchy and read
                    this clause only.<quote type="Law"><title>Law</title><p>[;And none shall be
                            exempt from the trierarchy except the nine archons.];</p></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>You see, Athenians, how explicitly the law lays down that none shall be exempt
                    from the equipment of a war-galley except the nine archons. So those whose
                    wealth falls short of the qualification for that service will contribute by
                    groups to the special war-tax, but those who reach that qualification will be
                    available both for the war-galleys and for the war-tax. Then what relief does
                    your law, Leptines, afford to the main body of citizens, if from one or two
                    tribes it provides a single contributor, who, having relieved one other citizen
                    on one occasion, will thereafter be exempt?<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >According to Demosthemes' lowest estimate, there would be 5 or 6 citizens
                        exempt: total 16. This number he is willing to double, making the full total
                        30 and the total of citizens presumably 10 or 12. If spread over the l0
                        tribes, the lower estimate would give, roughly, one contributor for 2
                        tribes; and the higher, one for each tribe.</note> I can see no relief. On
                    the other hand it taints the honor and credit of the whole State. Therefore,
                    when the damage it will inflict is greater than the benefit it confers, ought it
                    not to be repealed by this court? Such would be my verdict. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>My next point is this, gentlemen of the jury. The law of Leptines explicitly
                    states that "none, whether citizen or enfranchised alien or foreigner, shall be
                    exempt," and does not specify from what, whether from the public service or from
                    any other charge, but simply that "none shall be exempt except the descendants
                    of Harmodius and Aristogiton." The word "none" must be taken to include all
                    classes, and foreigner is not further defined as resident at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>It follows that Leptines deprives Leucon,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >Leucon, son and succesor of Satyrus, reigned over the Cimmerian Bosporus
                            (<placeName key="tgn,1003381">Crimea</placeName>) from 393 to 353. In
                        return for his services here describd, the Athenians had made him a citizen,
                        voted him a golden crown, and allowed him exemption not only from public
                        services but also from the payment of customs at the <placeName
                            key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>. His sons were Spartacus and
                        Paerisades, who succeeded him as joint rulers, and Apollonius. An
                        inscription in their honor was voted in the years 347-346. It was discovered
                        at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and published in <date
                            when="1877">1877</date>. See <bibl>Hicks, <title>Manual of Greek
                                Historical Inscriptions</title>, no. 111</bibl>.</note> the ruler of
                    the <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, and his children of the
                    reward which you bestowed on them. For, of course, Leucon is a foreigner by
                    birth, though by adoption an Athenian citizen, but on neither ground can he
                    claim exemption, if this law stands. And yet, while of our other benefactors
                    each has made himself useful to us on one occasion, Leucon will be found on
                    reflection to be a perpetual benefactor, and that in a matter especially vital
                    to our city. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="31">
                <p>For you are aware that we consume more imported corn than any other nation. Now
                    the corn that comes to our ports from the <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Black
                        Sea</placeName> is equal to the whole amount from all other places of
                    export. And this is not surprising; for not only is that district most
                    productive of corn, but also Leucon, who controls the trade, has granted
                    exemption from dues to merchants conveying corn to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and he proclaims that those bound
                    for your port shall have priority of lading. For Leucon, enjoying exemption for
                    himself and his children, has granted exemption to every one of you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="32">
                <p>See what this amounts to. He exacts a toll of one-thirtieth from exporters of
                    corn from his country. Now from the <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                        >Bosporus</placeName> there come to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> about four hundred thousand bushels; the figures can be
                    checked by the books of the grain commissioners. So for each three hundred
                    thousand bushels he makes us a present of ten thousand bushels, and for the
                    remaining hundred thousand a present of roughly three thousand.<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">To help his audience in this piece of mental
                        arithmetic, Demosthenes divides his 400,000 into two parts, of 300,000 (of
                        which the thirtieth is easily calculated) and of 100,000, the thirtieth of
                        which is 3333 1/3 or roughly 3000. It should be remembered that the medimnus
                        is more strictly about a bushel and a half.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="33">
                <p>Now, so little danger is there of his depriving our state of this gift, that he
                    has opened another depot at Theudosia, which our merchants say is not at all
                    inferior to the <placeName key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>,<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Here not the district, but the capital,
                            <placeName key="tgn,7012009">Panticapaeum</placeName>, the modern
                        Kertch. Sixty miles west lies Theudosia (<placeName key="tgn,7016693"
                            >Kaffa</placeName>), an ancient colony of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Miletus">Miletus</placeName>.</note> and there, too, he has
                    granted us the same exemption. I omit much that might be said about the other
                    benefits conferred upon you by this prince and also by his ancestors, but the
                    year before last, when there was a universal shortage of grain, he not only sent
                    enough for your needs, but such a quantity in addition that Callisthenes had a
                    surplus of fifteen talents of silver to dispose of.<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">Callisthenes, as<foreign xml:lang="grc">sitw/nhs</foreign>or
                        Food Controller (an office held by Demosthenes himself,<bibl n="Dem. 18.248"
                            >Dem. 18.248</bibl>), received so much corn from Leucon that, after
                        supplying the needs of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                        he was able to make 16 talents for the treasury by selling the surplus
                        elsewhere.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="34">
                <p>What, then, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, do you
                    expect of this man, who has proved himself such a friend to you, if he learns
                    that you have deprived him by law of his immunity, and have made it illegal to
                    bestow it hereafter, even if you change your minds? Are you not aware that this
                    same law, if ratified, will take away the immunity, not only from Leucon, but
                    from those of you who import corn from his country?<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">Because Leucon will, of course, retaliate by imposing the dues
                        again.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="35">
                <p>For surely no one dreams that he will tolerate the cancelling of your gifts to
                    him, and let his own gifts to you stand good. So to the many disadvantages that
                    this law will obviously entail upon you, may be added the immediate loss of part
                    of your resources. In view of this, are you still considering whether you ought
                    to erase it from the statute-book? Have you not made up your minds long ago?
                    Take and read them the decrees touching Leucon. <quote type="Decrees">
                        <title>Decrees</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="36">
                <p>How reasonable and just was the immunity which Leucon has obtained from you,
                    these decrees have informed you, gentlemen of the jury. Copies of all these
                    decrees on stone were set up by you and by Leucon in the <placeName
                        key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName>, in the <placeName
                        key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>, and at Hierum.<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">On the Asiatic side of the entrance to the
                        Thracian Bosporus from the Euxine.</note> Just reflect to what depths of
                    meanness you are dragged by this law, which makes the nation less trustworthy
                    than an individual. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="37">
                <p>For you must not imagine that the pillars standing there are anything else than
                    the covenants of all that you have received or granted; and it will be made
                    clear that Leucon observes them and is always eager to benefit you, but that you
                    have repudiated them while they still stand; and that is a far worse offence
                    than to pull them down<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Both nouns being
                        feminine plural, Demosthenes is able to fuse completely the literal and
                        metaphorical meanings.</note>; for when men wish to traduce our city, there
                    will stand the pillars to witness to the truth of their words. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="38">
                <p>Now mark! Suppose Leucon sends and asks us on what charge or for what fault we
                    have taken away his immunity; what, in the name of wonder, shall we say, or in
                    what terms will the proposer of your reply draft it? He will say, I suppose,
                    that some of those who obtained immunity did not deserve it! </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="39">
                <p>If, then, Leucon replies to this, “Yes; I dare say some of the Athenians are
                    scoundrels, but I have not made that a reason for robbing the good citizens; on
                    the contrary, because I think the Athenians, as a nation, are good men, I allow
                    them all a share”; will there not be more fairness in his words than in ours? To
                    me, at least, it seems so. For it is the custom of all nations, for the sake of
                    their benefactors, rather to include some bad men in their rewards, than to make
                    the worthless men an excuse for withholding their rewards from those who are
                    acknowledged to merit them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="40">
                <p>Nay more, upon consideration, I cannot even see why anyone should not, if he
                    wishes, challenge Leucon to an exchange of property.<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">By the legal process known as<foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >a)nti/dosis</foreign>, a citizen called upon to perform a public
                        service, if he thought that a richer man had been unfairly passed over,
                        could challenge him either to perform the service in his stead or to
                        exchange properties. Demosthenes is here putting an extreme case, for it is
                        difficult to believe that an honorary citizen like Leucon, resident
                        elsewhere, could be called upon for a service, even though he had wealth
                        deposited at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> For
                    there is always property of his at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, and by this law, if anyone tries to lay hands on it
                    Leucon will either forfeit it or be compelled to perform public service. And it
                    is not the question of expense that will trouble him most, but the reflection
                    that you have robbed him of his reward. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="41">
                <p>Again then, Athenians, it is not merely necessary to consider how Leucon may be
                    spared injustice—a man whose anxiety about his privilege would arise from a
                    sense of honor rather than from his needs—but we must also consider whether
                    another man, who did you service when he was prosperous, may not find that the
                    exemption he received from you then is a matter of necessity to him now. To
                    whom, then, do I refer? To Epicerdes of <placeName key="tgn,7000639"
                        >Cyrene</placeName>, than whom no recipient of this honor ever deserved it
                    better, not because his gifts were great or extraordinary, but because they came
                    at a time when we were hard put to it to find, even among those whom we had
                    benefited, anyone willing to remember our benefactions. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="42">
                <p>For Epicerdes, as this decree then passed in his honor declares, gave a hundred
                    minae to our fellow-countrymen at that time prisoners in <placeName
                        key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> under such distressing
                        circumstances,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">For the horrors endured by
                        the 7000 Athenian captives, scorched by day and frozen by night in the deep
                        stone-quarries of <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>,
                        see <bibl n="Thuc. 7.87">Thuc. 7.87</bibl>.</note> and thus he became the
                    chief instrument in saving them from all perishing of hunger. Afterwards, when
                    you had rewarded him with immunity, seeing that in the war<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">The third period of the Peloponnesian War, called the “Decelean”
                        War (413-404) from the Spartan fortified post at Decelea in <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>.</note> just before the rule of the
                    Thirty the people were straitened for want of funds, he gave them a talent as a
                    freewill offering. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="43">
                <p>In the name of Zeus and all the gods, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, ask yourselves how a man could more clearly show his
                    goodwill towards you, or how he could be less deserving of an ill return than
                    if, being first an eye-witness of that national disaster, he should prefer the
                    beaten side and such favors as they might some day bestow, rather than the
                    victors among whom he found himself in their hour of triumph; or if next, seeing
                    a further need arise, he should be found once more a donor, anxious not to hoard
                    his own private means, but to ensure that no cause of yours should fall short of
                    success, so far as in him lay. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="44">
                <p>Yet this man, who in actual deed on those momentous occasions shared his wealth
                    with the people, but enjoyed only a nominal and honorary immunity, will be
                    robbed by you, not of his immunity, for it is evident that he did not use it
                    when he had it, but of his trust in you; and what could be more discreditable
                    than that? Now you shall hear the very words of the decree then passed in his
                    honor. And observe, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    how many decrees this law annuls, how many individuals it wrongs, and what
                    occasions they chose for making themselves serviceable to you; for you will find
                    that the law wrongs just the men who least deserve it. Read. <quote
                        type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="45">
                <p>Gentlemen of the jury, you have heard from the decrees what were the services for
                    which Epicerdes obtained his immunity. Do not stop to ask whether he gave you a
                    hundred minae and a talent as well—for I expect that even those who received it
                    were not struck by the amount of his gift—but think of his zeal, his spontaneous
                    act, and the occasion that he chose. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="46">
                <p>For recompense is due to all alike who are forward to do us service, but in a
                    special degree to those who are friends in time of need; and such an one clearly
                    was Epicerdes. Are we not then ashamed, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, if it appears that we have retained no memory of these
                    services and have robbed of their reward the sons of such a benefactor, though
                    we can charge them with no fault? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="47">
                <p>For if those who were then saved by him and who bestowed on him this immunity
                    were a different generation from you who now propose to take it away, yet that
                    does not remove the infamy of the act; nay, it is just there that its atrocity
                    lies. For if those who knew and experienced his generosity felt that it merited
                    this return, while we, who have only heard the story told, shall revoke the gift
                    as undeserved, shall we not be guilty of more than ordinary atrocity? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="48">
                <p>Now my plea is the same in this case as for those who overthrew the Four Hundred,
                    and for those who proved helpful to the democrats in exile; for I think they
                    would all be atrociously treated if any portion of the rewards then decreed to
                    them should be revoked. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="49">
                <p>Now if any of you is persuaded that our city is far from needing such a
                    benefactor today, let him pray Heaven it may be so, and I will join in that
                    prayer; but let him also reflect, first, that he is going to give his vote on a
                    law under which, if unrepealed, he will have to live, and secondly, that bad
                    laws can injure even communities which fancy they are dwelling in security. For
                    there would have been no changes for better or for worse in the fortunes of
                    states, had it not been that a nation in peril is guided to safety by good
                    policy, good laws, and good citizens and by the observance of order in all
                    things, but in the case of a nation that seems established in perfect
                    prosperity, all these things, being neglected, slip away from it little by
                    little. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="50">
                <p>For most men achieve prosperity by planning soundly and by despising nothing; but
                    they do not take the trouble to guard it by the same means. Let not this mistake
                    be yours today, and do not think that you ought to ratify a law which will taint
                    the reputation of our city in the time of her prosperity and, if ever a crisis
                    comes, will leave her destitute of those who would be willing to do her service.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="51">
                <p>Again, Athenians, it is not only the men who, in a private capacity, chose to
                    benefit you and to offer their services on those important occasions that have
                    been described a little while ago by Phormio and mentioned by me just now—it is
                    not only these men that you must be careful not to wrong, but many others also,
                    who drew whole states, their own native cities, into alliance with us in the war
                    against the Lacedaemonians,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The so-called
                        Corinthian War, <date from="-0395" to="-0387">395</date>-387 B.C.</note>
                    thus furthering by word and deed the interests of your city; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="52">
                <p>and some of these men through their goodwill to you have no longer a fatherland.
                    The first example that I propose to examine is that of the Corinthian exiles.
                    And here I am obliged to mention facts which I myself have only heard from the
                    lips of the older among you.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Demosthenes was
                        now thirty, and the battle was fought ten tears before his birth.</note>
                    Some occasions, then, on which they made themselves useful to us, I will pass
                    over; but when the great battle against the Lacedaemonians was fought near
                        <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, and when the party in
                    that city determined after the battle not to admit our soldiers within their
                    walls, but to send heralds to greet the Lacedaemonians, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="53">
                <p>these men, though they saw that <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> had lost the day and that our enemies were holding the
                        pass,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Between <placeName
                            key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> and its harbor of Lechaeum on
                        the Corinthian Gulf.</note> refused to betray us or to take steps for their
                    own individual safety, but with the whole armed force of the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> close upon them, they opened their
                    gates to us in defiance of the majority and chose along with you, who had been
                    engaged in the battle, to suffer whatever might betide, rather than without you
                    to enjoy a safety that involved no danger; and so they admitted the troops and
                    succeeded in saving both you and your allies. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="54">
                <p>And afterwards, when peace, the peace of Antalcidas,<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">In 387. Antalcidas was the Spartan diplomatist. The Greeks
                        acknowledged the King of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> as
                        the arbiter of their disputes, and abandoned to him their cities in
                            <placeName key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>. All other Greek states
                        were to be independent, except <placeName key="tgn,7011173"
                            >Lemnos</placeName>, Imbros, and Scyros, which were to be retained by
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>'s main object was to break up
                        the power of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> over the
                        other Boeotian cities.</note> was concluded with the Lacedaemonians, the
                    latter requited their acts with exile. But you, in giving them shelter, acted
                    like good men and true; for you decreed them all that they needed. Yet now are
                    we actually debating whether those decrees should remain valid? No! The bare
                    statement is a disgrace, if it should be reported that Athenians are debating
                    whether they ought to let their benefactors keep what they have given them; for
                    that question ought to have been debated, yes, and decided, long ago.</p>
                <p>Read this decree also to the court.<quote type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="55">
                <p>Such, gentlemen of the jury, is the decree passed by you in favor of the
                    Corinthians who were exiled on your account. But think! If one who knew those
                    critical times—whether as an eye-witness or hearing the story from one who
                    knew—if he should hear this law which revokes the gifts that were then bestowed,
                    how he would denounce the baseness of us who made the law—and who were so
                    generous and obliging when our need was pressing, but when we have satisfied all
                    our hopes, are so thankless and churlish that we have robbed men of the rewards
                    they enjoy, and have made a law that hereafter no, such rewards should be
                    bestowed! </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="56">
                <p>“Oh but,” we shall be told, “some of those who received these rewards did not
                    deserve them”; for that thought will run through all their argument. In that
                    case shall we confess that we do not know that a man's deserts should be
                    examined at the time of the reward, and not an indefinitely long time after? For
                    to give no reward in the first instance is an exercise of judgement; to take it
                    away when given shows a grudging spirit, and you must not seem to have been
                    prompted by that. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="57">
                <p>Furthermore, on the question of merit I shall not shrink from saying this to you:
                    I for one do not think that merit should be examined by the State in the same
                    way as by an individual, because the examination is not concerned with the same
                    questions. For in private life each of us tries to find who is worthy, say, to
                    marry into our family, or something of that sort, and such questions are
                    determined by convention and opinion; but in public affairs the State and the
                    people try to find who is their benefactor and savior, and that question you
                    will find is best decided by reference not to birth or opinion, but to plain
                    fact. So, whenever we want to receive benefits, are we to allow anyone to confer
                    them, but when we have received them, then shall we scrutinize the merits of the
                    benefactor? That will be a topsy-turvy policy. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="58">
                <p>But, it may be said, the only sufferers will be those I have mentioned, and all
                    my remarks apply to them alone. That is quite untrue. But I could not even
                    attempt to examine all the instances of men who have benefited you, but who by
                    this law, if it is not repealed, will be robbed of their rewards; by calling
                    your attention to one or two further decrees, I absolve myself from discussing
                    these cases. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="59">
                <p>In the first place, then, will you not wrong the Thasian supporters of Ecphantus,
                    if you revoke their immunity—I mean the men who handed over <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011078">Thasos</placeName> to you by expelling the armed garrison
                    of the Lacedaemonians and admitting Thrasybulus,<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb"><date from="-0408" to="-0407">408</date>-407 B.C. There is some
                        discrepancy as to the date between our two authorities, Xenophon and
                        Diodorus, neither of whom mentions Ecphantus, presumably a democratic leader
                        in <placeName key="tgn,7011078">Thasos</placeName>.</note> and thus, by
                    bringing their own country on to your side, were the means of winning for you
                    the alliance of the district bordering on <placeName key="tgn,7002756"
                        >Thrace</placeName>? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="60">
                <p>In the second place, will you not wrong Archebius and Heraclides, who by putting
                        <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName> into the hands of
                    Thrasybulus made you masters of the <placeName key="tgn,7002638"
                        >Hellespont</placeName>, so that you farmed out the toll of ten per
                        cent,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Levied by the Byzantines on the value
                        of the cargo of every ship passing through the <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                            >Bosporus</placeName>.</note> and thus being well furnished with money
                    forced the Lacedaemonians to conclude a peace favorable to you?<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The Athenians gained <placeName
                            key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName> and <placeName
                            key="perseus,Chalcedon">Chalcedon</placeName> in <date when="-0390"
                            >390</date> B.C. It is strange to find the notorious peace of Antalcidas
                        mentioned with approval.</note> When subsequently they were banished, you,
                    Athenians, passed what I think was a very proper decree in favor of men exiled
                    through devotion to your interests, conferring on them the title of Friends of
                    the State<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A proxenus was a foreigner who, in
                        his own state, looked after Athenian interests. These men, being exiles
                        resident at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, could not
                        perform this duty. The title was an honorary one, giving them rank and
                        privileges above the ordinary resident aliens.</note> and Benefactors,
                    together with immunity from all taxes. For your sakes they were in exile, from
                    you they received a just recompense; and are we now to let them be robbed of
                    this, though we can charge them with no fault? But that would be scandalous.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="61">
                <p>You will grasp the situation best if you will reason it out for yourselves in
                    this way. Suppose at the present day a party of those in power at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Pydna">Pydna</placeName> or <placeName key="tgn,6004814"
                        >Potidaea</placeName> or any of those other places which are subject to
                    Philip and hostile to you— </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="62">
                <p>just as <placeName key="tgn,7011078">Thasos</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName> then were friendly to the
                    Lacedaemonians and estranged from you—promised to hand them over to you in
                    return for the same rewards that you gave to Ecphantus of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011078">Thasos</placeName> and Archebius of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>; and suppose some of these
                    gentlemen here objected to their proposal on the ground that it would be
                    monstrous if a select few of the resident aliens were to escape the public
                    services; how would you deal with their arguments? Is it not certain that you
                    would refuse to listen to such malignant pettifoggers? If so, then it is
                    disgraceful that you should consider such an objection malignant when you are
                    going to receive a benefit, but should lend an ear to it when it is proposed to
                    revoke your gifts to former benefactors. Now let us pass to another argument.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="63">
                <p>The men who betrayed <placeName key="perseus,Pydna">Pydna</placeName> and the
                    other places to Philip—what prompted them to injure us? Is it not obvious to
                    everyone that it was the reward which they calculated on receiving from Philip
                    for their services? Which, then, ought you to have chosen to do, Leptines? To
                    induce our enemies, if you can, to give up honoring those who become their
                    benefactors on the strength of injuries done to us, or to impose a law on us
                    which takes away some part of the rewards which our own benefactors are
                    enjoying? I fancy the former. But that I may not wander from the present point,
                    take and read the decrees passed in honor of the Thasians and the
                        Byzantines.<quote type="Decrees">
                        <title>Decrees</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="64">
                <p>You have heard the decrees, gentlemen of the jury. Perhaps some of the men named
                    are no longer alive. But their deeds survive, since they were done once for all.
                    It is fitting, therefore, to allow these inscriptions to hold good for all time,
                    that as long as any of the men are alive, they may suffer no wrong at your
                    hands, and when they die, those inscriptions may be a memorial of our national
                    character, and may stand as proofs to all who wish to do us service, declaring
                    how many benefactors our city has benefited in return. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="65">
                <p>Nor indeed would I have you forget this, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, that it is a most disgraceful thing to show and
                    proclaim to all mankind that the misfortunes which these men endured for your
                    sake have been confirmed to them for ever, while the grants which they received
                    from you in recompense have been even now rescinded. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="66">
                <p>For it would have been far more fitting to mitigate their distress by letting
                    them keep your gifts, than, while the distress remains, to rob them of your
                    bounty. In Heaven's name, I ask you, who is there that will choose to do you
                    service with the prospect of instant punishment by your enemies, if he fails,
                    and of a dubious gratitude from you, if he succeeds? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="67">
                <p>Now I should be greatly vexed, gentlemen of the jury, if I thought that the only
                    real charge I was bringing against the law was its depriving many of our alien
                    benefactors of the immunity, but should seem unable to point to any deserving
                    recipient of the honor among our own fellow-countrymen. For my prayer would ever
                    be that <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> may abound in all
                    blessings, but especially that the best men and the most numerous benefactors of
                    this city may be her own citizens. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="68">
                <p>First of all, then, in the case of <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>,
                    ask yourselves whether dissatisfaction with the man or his performances
                    justifies the cancelling of the gifts conferred on him. For, as some of you who
                    are his contemporaries can attest, it was just after the return of the exiled
                    democrats from the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>,<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Under Thrasybulus in 403.</note> when our city
                    was so weak that she had not a single ship, and Conon, who was a general in the
                    Persian service and received no prompting whatever from you, defeated the
                    Lacedaemonians at sea and taught the former dictators of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> to show you deference; he cleared the
                    islands of their military governors, and coming here he restored our Long
                        Walls<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><placeName key="tgn,1123029"
                            >Conon</placeName> obtained the support of <placeName key="tgn,7000231"
                            >Persia</placeName> for <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> against <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
                            >Sparta</placeName> and was appointed joint commander, with the satrap
                        Pharnabazus, of the Persian fleet. In 394 he destroyed the Spartan fleet off
                            <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>, sailed about the
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002675">Aegean</placeName> expelling the Spartan
                        harmosts from many of the islands, and finally reached <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, where he restored the Long
                        Wall, dismantled since the Peloponnesian war.</note>; and he was the first
                    to make the hegemony of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> once
                    more the subject of dispute between <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="69">
                <p>For, indeed, he has the unique distinction of being thus mentioned in his
                    inscription; “Whereas Conon,” it runs, “freed the allies of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.” That inscription, gentlemen of the
                    jury, is his glory in your estimation, but it is yours in the estimation of all
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. For whatever boon any one
                    of us confers on the other states, the credit of it is reaped by the fame of our
                    city. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="70">
                <p>Therefore his contemporaries not only granted him immunity, but also set up his
                    statue in bronze—the first man so honored since Harmodius and Aristogiton. For
                    they felt that he too, in breaking up the empire of the Lacedaemonians, had
                    ended no insignificant tyranny. In order, then, that you may give a closer
                    attention to my words, the clerk shall read the actual decrees which you then
                    passed in favor of <placeName key="tgn,1123029">Conon</placeName>. Read
                        them.<quote type="Decrees">
                        <title>Decrees</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="71">
                <p>It was not, then, only by you, Athenians, that
                        <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> was honored for the services
                    that I have described, but by many others, who rightly felt bound to show
                    gratitude for the benefits they had received. And so it is to your dishonor, men
                    of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that in other states his
                    rewards hold good, but of your rewards alone he is to lose this part. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="72">
                <p>Neither is this creditable—to honor him when living, with all the distinctions
                    that have been recited to you, but when he is dead to take back some part of
                    your former gifts. For many of his achievements, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, deserve praise, and all of them
                    make it improper to revoke the gifts they earned for him, but the noblest deed
                    of all was his restoration of the Long Walls. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="73">
                <p>You will realize this if you compare the way in which Themistocles, the most
                    famous man of his age, accomplished the same result. Now history tells us that
                    Themistocles bade his countrymen get on with the building and detain anyone who
                    came from <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, while he went off
                    himself on an embassy to the Lacedaemonians; and while negotiations went on
                    there and the news kept coming that the Athenians were fortifying, he denied it
                    and told them to send envoys to see for themselves, and when these envoys did
                    not return, he urged them to send more. Indeed, I expect you have all heard the
                    story of how he hoodwinked them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="74">
                <p>Now I assert—and I earnestly appeal to you, Athenians, not to take offence at
                    what is coming, but to consider whether it is true—I assert that in proportion
                    as openness is better than secrecy, and it is more honorable to gain one's end
                    by victory than by trickery, so <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>
                    deserves more credit than Themistocles for building the walls. For the latter
                    achieved it by evading those who would have prevented it, but the former by
                    beating them in battle. Therefore it is not right that so great a man should be
                    wronged by you, or should gain less than those orators who will try to prove
                    that you ought to deduct something from what was bestowed on him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="75">
                <p>Very well. But, they will say, we may let the son of Chabrias be robbed of the
                    immunity which his father justly received from you and bequeathed to him. But I
                    am sure there is not a single right-minded man who would approve of that. Now,
                    perhaps you know, even without any words from me, that Chabrias was a man of
                    high character; yet there is no harm if I too recall briefly his achievements.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="76">
                <p>How skilfully, as your commander, he drew up your ranks at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >When <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> helped <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> to repel the invasion of
                        Agesilaus in 378. Chabrias, on his way to <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
                            >Cyprus</placeName> in 388 to help Evagoras against <placeName
                            key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>, landed on <placeName
                            key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName> and killed the Spartan harmost
                        there. He was operating in <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> in
                        380 and again in 361.</note> to face the whole power of the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>, how he slew Gorgopas in
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, what trophies he set up in
                        <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> and afterwards in <placeName
                        key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, how he visited, I might almost say,
                    every land, yet nowhere disgraced our city's name or his own—of all these
                    exploits it is by no means easy to speak adequately, and it would be a great
                    shame if my words should make them fall below the estimate of him which each one
                    of you has formed in his own mind. But of some, which I think I could never
                    belittle in describing them, I will try to remind you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="77">
                <p>Now, he beat the Lacedaemonians in a sea-fight<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >Off <placeName key="tgn,7012053">Naxos</placeName> in 376.</note> and took
                    forty-nine warships; he captured most of the islands near and handed them over
                    to you, turning their previous enmity into friendship; he brought to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> three thousand captives, and paid
                    into the treasury more than a hundred and ten talents taken from the enemy. And
                    in all these facts some of the oldest among you can bear me out. But in
                    addition, he captured more than twenty warships, one or two at a time, and
                    brought them all into your harbors. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="78">
                <p>To sum up; he alone of all our generals never lost a city, a fort, a ship, or a
                    man, as long as he led you; and none of your enemies can boast a single trophy
                    won from you and him, while you possess many won from many enemies while he was
                    your general. But for fear lest my speech should omit any of his exploits, the
                    clerk shall read to you an inventory of all the ships he took and where he took
                    each, the number of cities and the amount of treasure captured, and the place
                    where he set up each trophy. Read.<quote n="Deeds of Chabrias">
                        <title>Deeds of Chabrias</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="79">
                <p>Does it seem to any of you, gentlemen of the jury, that this man, who captured so
                    many cities and ships from your enemies by his victories on sea, and who was the
                    source of so much honor, but never of disgrace, to your city, deserves to be
                    deprived of the immunity which he obtained at your hands and bequeathed to his
                    son? I cannot believe it, for it is out of all reason. Had he lost a single city
                    or as few as ten ships, Leptines and his supporters would have impeached him for
                    high treason, and if he had been convicted, he would have been a ruined man for
                    ever. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="80">
                <p>But since, on the contrary, he took seventeen cities, and captured seventy ships
                    and three thousand prisoners, and paid into the treasury a hundred and ten
                    talents, and set up so many trophies, in that case shall not his rewards for
                    these services stand good? Moreover, Athenians, it will be seen that Chabrias
                    during his lifetime did everything in your behalf, and that he met death itself
                    in no other service; so that for this, as well as for all that he did in his
                    life, you ought to show yourselves generously disposed to his son. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="81">
                <p>Then this too, Athenians, demands your consideration—that we must not prove less
                    generous than the Chians in our treatment of our benefactors. For if they,
                    against whom Chabrias carried arms as an enemy, have not now revoked any of
                    their former gifts, but have made ancient services outweigh recent offences,
                    while you, in whose cause he marched against them to his death, so far from
                    honoring him the more on that account, are even going to rob him of part of the
                    reward of his past services, how will you escape the ignominy that you deserve?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="82">
                <p>Moreover, should the son be robbed of part of his reward, his treatment would be
                    undeserved in view of the fact that no man's child was ever orphaned through the
                    fault of Chabrias, though he frequently led you in war, but the boy himself has
                    grown up an orphan, just because of his father's devotion to your cause. For to
                    me he seems truly to have been such a staunch patriot, that though reputed to be
                    the most cautious of commanders, as indeed he was, it was for your sake that he
                    displayed that quality whenever he led you, but for his own sake, when he found
                    himself assigned to the post of danger, he forgot all his caution and preferred
                    to lay down his life rather than tarnish the honors that you had bestowed. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="83">
                <p>After that, are we to rob the son of those honors which inspired the father to
                    conquer or to die? And what shall we say, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, when the trophies that he set up as general in your
                    name stand plain for all men to see, but a part of the reward for those trophies
                    is found to have been filched away? Will you not observe, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and reflect that today we are not
                    judging the law, to see whether it is suitable or not? It is you who are under
                    examination, to see whether you are suitable persons to receive benefits in the
                    future or whether you are not. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="84">
                <p>Turn now to the decree passed in honor of Chabrias. Just look and see; it must be
                    somewhere there.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">This aside is intended to give
                        an air of reality to the published speech. Editors well compare a similar
                        trick in <bibl n="Cic. Ver. 2.4.3">Cicero Verr. 2.4.3</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
                <p>There is one thing further that I want to say about Chabrias. You, Athenians, in
                    honoring Iphicrates, honored not only him but also on his account Strabax and
                    Polystratus; and again, when giving your reward to Timotheus, you also for his
                    sake rewarded Clearchus and some others with the citizenship<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Iphicrates was honored for the defeat of the
                        Spartan mora in the Corinthian War (390), Timotheus for his successful
                        expedition to <placeName key="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName> after the
                        battle of <placeName key="tgn,7012053">Naxos</placeName> (376). Strabax was
                        presumably a foreign mercenary; Polystratus is mentioned in <bibl
                            n="Dem. 4.24">Dem. 4.24</bibl>, as a commander of Athenian mercenaries
                        at <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>. These last two were
                        rewarded for services under the command of Iphicrates. Clearchus cannot be
                        identified with certainty.</note>; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="85">
                <p>but in the case of Chabrias your honors were for him alone. Now, if at the time
                    when he was receiving his reward, he had claimed that as you had rewarded others
                    for the sake of Iphicrates and Timotheus, so for his sake you should reward some
                    of those men who have actually received the immunity, but to whom our opponents
                    object so strongly that they want all alike to be deprived of it, would you not
                    have granted him that boon? I cannot doubt it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="86">
                <p>For his sake you would have rewarded them then; yet now, on their account, will
                    you take away the immunity from Chabrias himself? Why, that is absurd! For it is
                    inconsistent to seem so generous, when the benefits are recent, that you honor
                    not the benefactors only but their friends as well, but, when a short time has
                    elapsed, to take away even the rewards that you have given to the
                        benefactors.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The argument seems to be this.
                        Some recipients of immunity obtained similar favors for their friends.
                        Chabrias did not, but he might have done so, and his friends might have been
                        the undeserving persons now enjoying immunity. In this rather hypothetical
                        case, after rewarding the jackals from gratitude to the lion, you now
                        penalize the lion out of contempt for the jackals.</note><quote
                        n="Decrees on the Honors of Chabrias">
                        <title>Decrees on the Honors of Chabrias</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="87">
                <p>So these whose names you have heard, as well as many others, are the men whom you
                    will injure if you do not repeal the law. Just reflect and ponder in your own
                    minds, if any of these men now passed away could somehow come to know of the
                    present proceedings, what just ground they would have for indignation! For if of
                    the deeds that each wrought for your advantage there is to be a judgement based
                    on words, if actions nobly performed by them, unless nobly avowed by us in
                    speech, have been wrought in vain for all their toil, are they not suffering a
                    terrible wrong? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="88">
                <p>Now, to satisfy you, Athenians, that every argument that we submit to you is
                    based on perfectly just grounds, and that not a single argument is intended to
                    mislead and deceive you, the clerk shall read the law drafted and proposed by us
                    to take the place of the present one, which we contend is mischievous. For our
                    law will show you that we take some care to ensure that you shall be saved from
                    the appearance of a dishonorable act; that if anyone objects to one of the
                    recipients, he can deprive him of his gift, if the objection is sound, after
                    trial in your courts; and also that those whose claim to the gifts none could
                    dispute shall keep them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="89">
                <p>And in all this there is nothing new, no innovation of our own; but the old law,
                    transgressed by Leptines, lays down this procedure in legislation, that if a man
                    disapproves of an existing law, he shall bring an indictment against it, but
                    shall himself introduce an alternative, such as he proposes to enact after
                    repeal of the other, and that you, after hearing arguments, shall choose the
                    better law. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="90">
                <p>For Solon, who imposed this method, did not think it right that while the junior
                    archons, who are appointed by lot to administer the laws, undergo two
                        scrutinies<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">To ascertain whether they were
                        duly qualified by birth, by character, and by wealth.</note> before entering
                    on office, one in the Council and a second in the law-courts before you, the
                    laws themselves, which regulate their official acts and all other civic duties,
                    should be passed at haphazard to meet some emergency, and should be at once
                    valid without passing a scrutiny. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="91">
                <p>For in those days, indeed, while they legislated in that way, they kept to the
                    existing laws and were not always proposing new ones; but ever since certain
                    statesmen rose to power and, as I am informed, contrived to get into their own
                    hands the right to initiate legislation at any time and in any way they wished,
                    there are so many contradictory statutes that for a long time you have had to
                    appoint a commission to sort out the contradictory ones; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="92">
                <p>yet in spite of this the business never comes to an end. Our laws are no better
                    than so many decrees; nay, you will find that the laws which have to be observed
                    in drafting the decrees are later<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">new/teroi</foreign> has been misunderstood and variously
                        emended. Laws ought to be general and permanent, decrees particular and
                        occasional; but there has been such a glut of hasty legislation, since the
                        restoration of the democracy in 403, that many decrees still stand
                        unrepealed after the laws on which they were based have been superseded. For
                        the legislative commission see Introduction.</note> than the decrees
                    themselves. Not to be content, then, with a bare assertion, but to show you the
                    actual law to which I refer, please take and read the law constituting the
                    original legislative commission. <quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="93">
                <p>You understand, Athenians, the beauty of Solon's directions for legislating. The
                    first stage is in your courts, before men under oath, where all other
                    ratifications are made; the next is the repeal of the contradictory laws, so
                    that there may be only one law dealing with each subject, and that the plain
                    citizen may not be puzzled by such contradictions and be at a disadvantage
                    compared with those who are acquainted with the whole body of law, but that all
                    may have the same ordinances before them, simple and clear to read and
                    understand. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="94">
                <p>Moreover, before these proceedings, Solon ordered that the laws should be exposed
                    before the statues of the eponymous heroes<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The
                        statues of the heroes who gave their names to the ten tribes stood in the
                        Agora near the council-chamber.</note> and handed in to the town-clerk to
                    recite them at the meetings of the Assembly, so that each of you may hear them
                    more than once and digest them at leisure, and if they are just and expedient,
                    may add them to the statute-book. Now, numerous as those enactments are,
                    Leptines yonder has observed not one of them, for, if he had, I do not think
                    that you would ever have consented to pass his law. We on the other hand,
                    Athenians, have observed them all, and we are submitting a much better and more
                    equitable law than his. You will realize that when you hear it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="95">
                <p>Take and read first of all the clauses of his law which we have indicted, and
                    next the clauses we propose to substitute for them. Read.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                        <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">By this, if correct, must be meant the
                            preamble of the amended law, setting forth the objections to the
                            existing law of Leptines. The second "law" read would be the amendments
                            proposed; and at the end of <bibl n="Dem. 20.97">Dem. 20.97</bibl> the
                            whole law as amended is read.</note>
                    </quote></p>
                <p>These are the parts of the law of Leptines which we arraign as unsatisfactory.
                    Next in order read our proposed amendments. Pray attend, gentlemen of the jury,
                    to these as they are recited. Read.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="96">
                <p>Stop there. The laws now in force contain this provision—a capital one, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and unambiguous—that
                    "all rewards granted by the people shall be valid." Equitable too, by all the
                    powers! So Leptines should not have proposed his own law until he had indicted
                    and repealed this. As it is, neglecting proof of his own violation of the law,
                    he nevertheless proceeded to legislate, in face of the fact that another law
                    proclaims his law indictable for this very offence, namely, for contradicting
                    previous legislation. Here is the very law in question.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="97">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, is not the provision
                    that "all rewards granted by the people shall be valid" contradicted by the
                    clause that "no one shall be immune," no one, that is, of those to whom the
                    people has granted immunity? That is plain enough, at any rate. But it is not so
                    in the alternative law which my friend<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >Apsephion.</note> here proposes, and which confirms what you have granted,
                    and provides a fair ground of action against those who have imposed upon you, or
                    have subsequently injured you, or are generally undeserving; so that you will
                    thus prevent anyone you please from retaining his grant. Read the law.<quote
                        type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="98">
                <p>You hear the law, Athenians, and you understand that it enables the deserving to
                    retain their rewards, and those who are judged otherwise to be deprived of any
                    privilege they have unjustly secured; for the future everything is left in your
                    hands, as is right, to grant or to withhold. Now I do not think that Leptines
                    will deny that this law is sound and just, or, if he does, that he will be able
                    to prove it. But perhaps he will try to lead you astray by repeating what he
                    said before the junior archons.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">At the <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">a)na/krisis</foreign> or preliminary trial.</note> For he
                    alleged that the publication of this amended law was a mere trick, and that
                    should his own law be repealed, this one would never be passed. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="99">
                <p>Now, to avoid dispute, I will not press the point that the old law of Solon, in
                    accordance with which the junior archons have notified these amendments to you,
                    clearly enjoins that if the law of Leptines is repealed by your vote, the
                    alternative law shall be valid.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">We may
                        conjecture that the old law (that if the original statute was condemned, the
                        amendment baecame law ipso facto) had in practice been superseded.</note> I
                    will pass to another point. Leptines, in saying this, obviously admits that our
                    law is better and fairer than his own, but bases his argument on the way in
                    which it is to be passed. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="100">
                <p>Now, in the first place, there are many ways open to him, if he wishes, of
                    compelling the amender to introduce his own law. In the next place, Phormio and
                    myself and anyone else he likes to name are prepared to guarantee that we will
                    introduce it. You know there is a law making death the penalty for anyone who
                    breaks his promise to the Assembly or one of the Councils or law-courts. You
                    have our guarantee, our promise. Let the archons record it, and let the matter
                    rest in their hands. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="101">
                <p>Neither do anything that is unworthy of this court, nor, if a worthless person is
                    found among those who enjoy the grant, let him keep it; only let each case be
                    judged on its merits. But if Leptines shall say that that is all talk and
                    humbug, this at any rate is not mere talk; let him bring in the amended law
                    himself and cease to say that we will not do so. It is surely a greater honor to
                    propose the law, stamped with your approval,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >Demosthenes is a trifle premature here.</note> than this of his own
                    devising. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="102">
                <p>It seems to me, Athenians, that Leptines—and pray, be not angry,<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">He addresses himself directly to
                        Leptines.</note> for I am not going to say anything offensive about
                    you—Leptines has either never read Solon's laws or else does not understand
                    them. For if Solon made a law that every man could grant his property to
                    whomsoever he pleased, in default of legitimate offspring, not with the object
                    of depriving the next of kin of their rights of consanguinity, but that by
                    making the prize open to all he might excite a rivalry in doing good one to
                    another; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="103">
                <p>and if you, on the contrary, have proposed a law that the people shall not be
                    permitted to bestow on any man any part of what is their own, how can you be
                    said to have read or understood the laws of Solon? You make the nation barren of
                    would-be patriots by proclaiming unmistakably that those who benefit us shall
                    gain nothing by it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="104">
                <p>Again, there is another excellent law of Solon, forbidding a man to speak ill of
                    the dead, even if he is himself defamed by the dead man's children. You do not
                    speak ill of our departed benefactors, Leptines; you do ill to them, when you
                    blame one<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e. of their descendants, whose
                        demerits are no justification for cancelling a reward once given. But the
                        Greek is not clear.</note> and assert that another is unworthy, though these
                    charges have nothing to do with the dead men.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >Or possibly, if <foreign xml:lang="grc">w)=n</foreign> is masculine,
                        "though the men thus charged have no connection with the dead."</note> Are
                    you not very far from the intention of Solon? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="105">
                <p>Now I have been quite seriously informed that with regard to the absolute
                    prohibition of all rewards,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Demosthenes here
                        misrepresents the law, which only touched the immunities. "Quite seriously"
                        is taken by some with "prepared to use."</note> whatever a man's services
                    may be, our opponents are prepared to use some such argument as this. The
                    Lacedaemonians, who are a well-organized state, and the Thebans grant no such
                    reward to any of their citizens, and yet possibly there are some good men among
                    them. In my opinion, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    all such arguments are provocative, and intended to persuade you to abolish the
                    immunities, but just they are certainly not. For I am quite aware that the
                    Thebans and the Lacedaemonians and ourselves do not observe the same laws and
                    customs, nor the same form of government. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="106">
                <p>For in the first place, if this is their argument, they are about to do exactly
                    what a man cannot do at Sparta—praise the laws of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> or of any other state; nay, so far
                    from that, he is obliged to praise, as well as do, whatever accords with his
                    native constitution. Then again, though the Lacedaemonians do not hold with
                    these customs, yet there are other honors at <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
                        >Sparta</placeName>, which our citizens to a man would shrink from
                    introducing here. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="107">
                <p>What, then, are those honors? Not to take each singly, I will describe one which
                    comprises all the rest. Whenever a man for his good conduct is elected to the
                    Senate, or Gerusia, as they call it, he is absolute master of the mass of
                    citizens. For at <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> the prize of
                    merit is to share with one's peers the supremacy in the State; but with us the
                    people is supreme, and any other form of supremacy is forbidden by
                        imprecations<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">At the opening of every
                        meeting of the Assembly and of the Council a herald recited a curse on
                        enemies of the State and on evil counsellors; see <bibl n="Dem. 19.70">Dem.
                            19.70</bibl>.</note> and laws and other safeguards, but we have crowns
                    of honor and immunities and free maintenance and similar rewards, which anyone
                    may win, if he is a good citizen. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="108">
                <p>And both these customs are right enough, the one at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and the other here. Why? Because in
                    an oligarchy harmony is attained by the equality of those who control the State,
                    but the freedom of a democracy is guarded by the rivalry with which good
                    citizens compete for the rewards offered by the people. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="109">
                <p>Again, with regard to the absence of honors at <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName>, I think I can express the truth thus. The Thebans, men
                    of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, plume themselves more on
                    brutality and iniquity than you on humanity and love of justice. If a prayer may
                    be allowed, may they never cease to withhold honor and admiration from those who
                    do them service, or to deal with kindred states in the same way (For you
                    remember how they treated <placeName key="tgn,7011034"
                        >Orchomenus</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Wiped out by the
                        Thebans in 364. The men were massacred, and the women and children sold into
                        slavery.</note>) And never may you cease to do the opposite, honoring your
                    benefactors and winning your rights from your fellow-citizens by debate and in
                    harmony with the laws! </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="110">
                <p>And in general, I think that then only ought you to praise the habits and
                    character of other nations and decry your own, when it is possible to prove that
                    they are more prosperous than you. As long as you (thank Heaven!) are more
                    prosperous than they, in public policy, in internal harmony, and in every other
                    way, why should you belittle your national institutions and imitate theirs? Even
                    if theirs could be proved superior in theory, yet the good fortune that you have
                    enjoyed under your own institutions makes it worth your while to retain them.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="111">
                <p>Besides all this, if I must say what I think is right, I would put it in this
                    way. It is not right, Athenians, to cite the laws of the Lacedaemonians or of
                    the Thebans in order to undermine the laws established here; it is not right
                    that you should want to put a man to death for transplanting to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> any of the institutions that have
                    made those nations great, and yet lend a willing ear to those who propose to
                    destroy the institutions under which our democracy has flourished. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="112">
                <p>Then they have another argument ready; that even at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in former generations men who had
                    rendered great services met with no recognition of this sort, but were content
                    with an inscription in the Hermes-Portico.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In
                        the Agora. The inscription (quoted by <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.83">Aeschin.
                            3.83</bibl>) was in honor of Cimon's capture of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Eion">Eion</placeName> on the Strymon in 476.</note>
                    Perhaps indeed the inscription will be read to you. But in my opinion,
                    Athenians, this argument is in many ways prejudicial to the State, besides being
                    unjust. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="113">
                <p>For if anyone says that even these men deserved no honor, let him say who does
                    deserve it, if there is no one either before or after them. If he shall say "no
                    one," I should be very sorry for our city, if no one in the course of its
                    history has proved worthy of reward. Again, if while admitting their merit he
                    points out that they got nothing by it, assuredly he accuses the city of
                    ingratitude. But that is not the truth or anything like it; but whenever a man
                    maliciously gives a wrong twist to his arguments, I think they must appear
                    hateful. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="114">
                <p>I, however, will explain the case to you, as truth and justice demand. There
                    were, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, plenty of
                    zealous citizens in former generations, and our city even then honored its good
                    men; only honors then, like everything else, reflected the temper of the times,
                    just as they now reflect the temper of today. And why do I say this? Because for
                    myself I should be inclined to assert that they did get from the State
                    everything that they wished. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="115">
                <p>What is my evidence? Lysimachus,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Son of
                        Aristides the just, pensioned for his father's merits.</note> only one of
                    the worthies of that day, received a hundred roods of orchard in <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> and a hundred of arable land, besides a
                    hundred minas of silver and a pension of four drachmas a day. And the decree in
                    which these gifts are recorded stands in the name of Alcibiades. For then our
                    city was rich in lands and money, though now—she will be rich some day<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A euphemism for "she is poor."</note>; for I
                    must put it in that way to avoid anything like obloquy. Yet today who, think
                    you, would not prefer a third of that reward to mere immunity? To prove the
                    truth of my words, please take the decree. <quote type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="116">
                <p>Now this decree, Athenians, proves that your ancestors, like yourselves, were
                    accustomed to honor good men; if they used different methods from ours today,
                    that is another matter. So even if we should admit that neither Lysimachus nor
                    anyone else gained anything from our ancestors, does that make it any fairer in
                    us to rob the men whom we have just rewarded? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="117">
                <p>For there is nothing outrageous in withholding what one never dreamed of giving;
                    but it is an outrage to give and afterwards take back one's gift, with no fault
                    alleged. Prove to me that our ancestors ever took back the gifts they had
                    bestowed, and you too have my leave to do the same, though the disgrace remains
                    none the less; but if no one can cite an instance from the whole course of our
                    history, why is such a precedent to be set in our generation? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="118">
                <p>Again, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you must also
                    consider well and carefully the fact that you have come into court today, sworn
                    to give your verdict according to the laws, not of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> or <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName>, nor those of our earliest ancestors, but those under
                    which immunities were granted to the men whom Leptines is now trying to rob by
                    his law; and where there are no statutes to guide you, you are sworn to decide
                    according to the best of your judgement. So far, so good. Then you must apply
                    these principles to the law as a whole. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="119">
                <p>Is it right, Athenians, to honor your benefactors? It is. Well then, is it right
                    to allow a man to keep what has once been given him? It is. Then, to observe
                    your oaths, act on that principle yourselves; resent the imputation that your
                    ancestors acted otherwise; and as for those who cite such instances, alleging
                    that your ancestors rewarded no man for great benefits received, look upon them
                    as both knaves and dullards—knaves, because they falsely charge your ancestors
                    with ingratitude; fools, because they do not see that were the charge proved to
                    the hilt, it would better become them to deny than to repeat it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="120">
                <p>Now I expect that another argument of Leptines will be that his law does not
                    deprive the recipients of their inscriptions and their free maintenance, nor the
                    State of the right to confer honor on those who deserve it, but that it will
                    still be in your power to set up statues and grant maintenance and anything else
                    you wish, except this one privilege. But with respect to the powers that he will
                    pretend to leave to the State, I have just this to say. As soon as you take away
                    one of the privileges you have already granted, you will shake the credit of all
                    the rest. For how can the grant of a statue or of free maintenance be more
                    indefeasible than that of an immunity, which you will seem to have first given
                    and then taken away? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="121">
                <p>Further, even if this difficulty were not likely to arise, I cannot think that it
                    is well to bring the State into this dilemma, that it must either put all
                    citizens on an equality with its greatest benefactors, or to avoid this must
                    treat some with ingratitude. Now as for great benefactions, it is not well that
                    you should have many opportunities of receiving them, nor is it perhaps easy for
                    an individual to confer them; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="122">
                <p>but the humbler duties to which one can rise in time of peace and in the civil
                    sphere—loyalty, justice, zeal and the like—it is, in my opinion, both well and
                    necessary that they should be rewarded. Grants ought, therefore, to be so
                    apportioned that each man may receive from the people the exact reward that he
                    deserves. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="123">
                <p>And then again, with regard to what he will say about leaving their honors to
                    those who have received them, some would have a perfectly plain and
                    straightforward answer, when they claim their right to all their rewards,
                    because they were granted for the same service, but the others will reply that
                    the man who says that he leaves them anything is mocking them.<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">"Some" have received other rewards together with
                        immunity; "the others" immunity alone.</note> For if a man has been thought
                    to deserve immunity and has received that from you as his sole reward, be he
                    foreigner or citizen, what reward has he left, Leptines, if that is taken from
                    him? None whatever! Then you have no right to rob some because you arraign the
                    worthlessness of the others, or to rob one class of their sole reward because
                    you say that you are going to leave the other class something. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="124">
                <p>To put it plainly, the danger is not that of doing a greater or less injustice to
                    one member of the whole body, but that of rendering precarious the honors with
                    which we reward men's services, nor is immunity the main topic of my speech, but
                    the evil precedent which this law will establish, so that there will be no
                    security for the nation's gifts. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="125">
                <p>Again, the most unscrupulous argument that they have framed, as they think, to
                    persuade you to withdraw the immunities, is one which I had better explain for
                    fear you should be their innocent dupes. They are going to claim that all such
                    payments are religious dues, and that of course it is monstrous that anyone
                    should be exempt from the dues of religion. For my part, I see no unfairness in
                    such exemption, if the people have bestowed it; the really monstrous thing is
                    the course which they propose, if that is to be their argument. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="126">
                <p>For if by appealing to the name of the gods they try to justify a robbery which
                    they cannot justify otherwise, will not that be most impious and monstrous
                    conduct? In my opinion, whenever a man appeals solemnly to the gods, his conduct
                    ought to be clearly such as would not appear base even if supported only by
                    human authority. Now that there is a difference between exemption from religious
                    duties and exemption from public services, and that the defendants are trying to
                    deceive you by transferring the name of public services to religious acts, I
                    shall adduce Leptines himself as my witness. For the first clause of the law
                    says </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="127">
                <p>"Leptines proposed that, to the end that the wealthiest citizens may perform the
                    public services, none shall be immune save and except the descendants of
                    Harmodius and Aristogiton." But if immunity from religious duties were the same
                    as immunity from public services, what was the object of that clause? For
                    immunity from religious duties has never been granted even to the persons here
                    named. To prove that this is so, please take and read the copy of the
                    inscription and then the beginning of the law of Leptines.<quote
                        n="Copy of Stela Inscription">
                        <title>Copy of Stela Inscription</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="128">
                <p>You hear the copy of the inscription, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, ordering them to be immune, save from religious duties.
                    Now read the beginning of the law of Leptines.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote></p>
                <p>Good; stop there. After the words "to the end that the wealthiest citizens may
                    perform the public services," he added "no one shall be immune save and except,
                    the descendants of Harmodius and Aristogiton." Why so, if to pay for a religious
                    rite is to perform a public service? For if that is his meaning, his own
                    drafting will be found to contradict the inscription. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="129">
                <p>Now I should like to put a question to Leptines. When you say that the public
                    services come under the head of religious dues, in what, according to you, did
                    the immunity consist, which our ancestors then granted and you now leave
                    untouched? For by the old laws they are not immune from all the special
                    war-taxes or from the equipment of war-galleys; and they enjoy no immunity from
                    the state services, since they are included in the religious duties. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="130">
                <p>And yet the inscription says that they shall be immune. From what? From the tax
                    on resident aliens, since nothing else is left? Of course not. It is from the
                    regularly recurring services, as the inscription shows, as your law further
                    specifies, and as all history witnesses. During all that length of time no tribe
                    has ever ventured to nominate one of these descendants as chorus-master, and no
                    one nominated has ever ventured to challenge them to an exchange of property. If
                    Leptines dares to deny it, you must pay no heed to him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="131">
                <p>Again,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">They assert that many aliens have
                        received immunity; he challenges them to produce the decrees conferring it.
                        He admits that many undeserving aliens have been made proxenoi (in the
                        honorary sense explained in note on <bibl n="Dem. 20.60">Dem. 20.60</bibl>),
                        but this distinction does not confer immunity.</note> perhaps they will say
                    in their haphazard<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Literally, trailing the
                        robe; hence slovenly, slipshod.</note> style that some citizens, by claiming
                    to be Megarians and Messenians,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">There is no
                        record of any general exemption granted to these two peoples. If <placeName
                            key="tgn,1131671">Weil</placeName>'s conjecture is right, translate
                        "certain M. and M., by claiming to be Friends of the State."</note> at once
                    gain immunity, whole crowds at a time, to say nothing of slaves and jailbirds
                    like Lycidas and Dionysius; such are the examples they select. When they hold
                    such language, deal with them thus. Tell them, if they are speaking the truth,
                    to produce the decrees which contain these men's immunity; for no one in your
                    city enjoys immunity unless granted by some decree or law. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="132">
                <p>Many such men, however, have been proclaimed Friends of the State here at the
                    instance of your politicians Lycidas, for example. But it is one thing to be a
                    Friend of the State and another to enjoy immunity. Be not misled by them.
                    Because slaves, like Lycidas and Dionysius and perhaps one other, were made
                    Friends of the State by men who are readily bribed to propose such decrees, they
                    must not try to take away the gifts that you have justly bestowed on men of a
                    different class—mentorious, freeborn, munificent benefactors. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="133">
                <p>On this principle, what a gross insult it would be to Chabrias, if politicians of
                    that stamp, not content with making his slave, Lycidas, a Friend of your State,
                    should make the slave an excuse for taking back rewards conferred on the master,
                    and that on a false plea! For neither Lycidas nor anyone else enjoys immunity as
                    a Friend of the State, unless such immurity has been expressly conferred by the
                    people. The men in question have not received it; I defy the defendants to prove
                    it. If they have the effrontery to assert it, they will be acting dishonorably.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="134">
                <p>I now come to speak of a matter about which I feel bound, Athenians, to warn you
                    most seriously. For even if one could admit the truth of all that Leptines will
                    say in praise of his law, it would be impossible under any circumstances to wipe
                    out one disgrace which his law, if ratified, will bring upon our city. To what
                    do I refer? To the reputation of having cheated our benefactors. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="135">
                <p>Now I think you would all agree that this is a distinct disgrace; how much worse
                    in you than in others, hear me explain. You have an ancient law, one held in
                    great respect, that if anyone deceives the people by false promises, he shall be
                    brought to trial, and if convicted shall be punished with death. And are you not
                    then ashamed, Athenians, to find yourselves doing the very thing for which you
                    punish other men with death? Nay, but in everything it is right to take heed
                    against doing whatever seems or is dishonorable, but especially in cases where a
                    man is seen to be indignant with others. For there is no room left even for
                    hesitation in avoiding acts which a man's own judgement has already condemned.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="136">
                <p>Then there is another precaution that you must take—to do nothing as a community
                    which you would shun as individuals. Not a man among you would take away from
                    another his own personal gifts, nor even dream of doing so. Then do not so in
                    your public capacity, but tell the official defenders<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">The advocates named in <bibl n="Dem. 20.146">Dem.
                        20.146</bibl>.</note> of this law that </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="137">
                <p>if they say that any of the recipients of these rewards is undeserving, or holds
                    them under false pretences, or is open to any other charge, they should indict
                    him under the amended law which we are now proposing, either when we have
                    carried it through, as we guarantee and assert that we will, or when they have
                    themselves carried it, that is, as soon as the legislative commission has been
                        appointed.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">At the beginning of the next
                        year (July).</note> But each defender of this law, it seems, has a personal
                    enemy, whether Diophantus or Eubulus or someone else.<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">The official defenders have their personal enemies, who have
                        received immunity and whom it would be natural for them to indict. This they
                        do not venture to do, but try, by this sweeping law, to deprive all, good
                        and bad alike, of their privileges.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="138">
                <p>If they hang back and refuse to take this step, then consider, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, whether it is to your credit that
                    you should be known to have taken away from your benefactors what not one of
                    these men ventures to take from his personal enemy, and that you should pass a
                    law to rob collectively of their rewards men who have served you well and whom
                    no one dreams of indicting, when the handful of unworthy recipients, if there
                    are any, could be dealt with just as effectively, if these men would impeach
                    them and bring them to trial one by one. For it passes my comprehension how the
                    present arrangement can consort with your honor and your dignity. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="139">
                <p>Again, we must not deviate from this principle, that it was fair to investigate
                    their merits at the time of conferring the reward, when none of these men
                    opposed the vote, but after that to let the reward stand, unless you have
                    received any subsequent wrong at their hands. If they allege that (for they
                    cannot prove it), it must be shown that the men were punished at the time of the
                    alleged wrongs. But if you ratify this law, though no such wrong was committed,
                    it will seem that you have taken away their reward because you were envious, not
                    because you found them rascals. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="140">
                <p>Every reproach, I might almost say, should be avoided, but this above all, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Why? Because in every
                    way envy is the mark of a vicious nature, and the man who is subject to it has
                    no claim whatever to consideration. Moreover there is no reproach more alien to
                    our city than the appearance of envy, averse as she is from all that is
                    disgraceful. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="141">
                <p>See what strong evidence we have of this. In the first place, you alone of all
                    mankind publicly pronounce over your dead funeral orations, in which you extol
                    the deeds of the brave. Such, however, is the practice of men who admire
                    bravery, not of men who envy the honors that bravery wins. Next, you have from
                    time immemorial given the richest rewards to those who win crowns in the
                    athletic games; nor, because such honors are necessarily confined to a few, have
                    you grudged or stinted the honors of the victors on that account. Beside these
                    notable instances, no one, I think, has ever surpassed our State in generosity;
                    such a superabundance of rewards has she heaped on those who serve her well.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="142">
                <p>All these, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, are proofs
                    of justice, of virtue, of magnanimity. Then do not now destroy the very
                    qualities on which throughout its history our city's reputation is founded; do
                    not, in order that Leptines may vent his spite on men whom he dislikes, rob both
                    yourselves and your city of the fair fame that has been yours in every age; do
                    not suppose that anything else is at stake in this trial save the honor of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, whether it is to stand
                    unimpaired as of old, or to pass into neglect and degradation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="143">
                <p>But of all the astonishing features of Leptines' law, what astonishes me most is
                    his ignorance of the fact that just as a man who assigns heavy penalties for
                    offences would be unlikely to have contemplated an offence himself, so one who
                    abolishes the rewards for benefactions will not himself be likely to have
                    contemplated a good deed. Now if, as is just possible, he did not know this, he
                    will at once confess it by allowing you to repeal the law which embodies his own
                    error, but if he shows himself obstinate and eager to ratify the law, I for one
                    cannot praise him, though I refrain from censure. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="144">
                <p>Then be not stubborn, Leptines; do not insist on a course which will not add to
                    your own reputation or that of your supporters, especially as this trial no
                    longer endangers you. For owing to the death of the father of Apsephion here,
                    Bathippus, who indicted Leptines when he was still liable, the legal period has
                    elapsed, and now our whole concern is with the law, and its proposer runs no
                        risk.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">See Introduction p. 489.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="145">
                <p>I am told, however, that you assert that three distinct persons indicted you
                    before Apsephion, but dropped the action. Well, if your complaint against them
                    is that they did not endanger you, you must be fonder of danger than other
                    people, but if you bring it forward as a proof of the justice of your proposals,
                    you are doing a very silly thing. For how is your law improved by the fact that
                    one of those who indicted you died before he could come into court, or was
                    induced by you to drop the charge, or even was simply suborned by you? But I am
                    ashamed even to suggest such things. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="146">
                <p>There are advocates appointed to defend the law, and very able speakers they are;
                    Leodamas of Acharnae, Aristophon of Hazenia, Cephisodotus of Ceramicus, and
                    Dinias of Herchia.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">These were the four
                        advocates nominated by the people, with Leptines as a fifth, to defend the
                        law. Aristophon, the best known, was the leading Athenian statesman before
                        the rise of Eubulus. He was now nearly eighty years old, and could boast
                        that he had been 75 times defendant in a <foreign xml:lang="grc">grafh\
                            parano/mwn</foreign> and had always acquitted.</note> Let me tell you,
                    then, how you may reasonably retort upon them, and do you consider whether the
                    retort is fair.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Demosthenes suggests that the
                        personal record of the advocates should lead the jury to reject their
                        arguments.</note> Take Leodamas first. It was he who impeached the grant to
                        Chabrias,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">See <bibl n="Dem. 20.77">Dem.
                            20.77</bibl>.</note> which included among other things the gift of
                    immunity, and when his case came before you, he lost it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="147">
                <p>Now the laws forbid the same man to be tried twice on the same issue, be it a
                    civil action, a scrutiny, a contested claim, or anything else of the sort. But
                    quite apart from all this, it would be a most absurd result if on the first
                    occasion the services of Chabrias outweighed the arguments of Leodamas, but when
                    to his services were added those of all the other benefactors, then the combined
                    effect should be weaker than the arguments. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="148">
                <p>To Aristophon I think I could raise many sound objections. He obtained his grant,
                    which included immunity, by your votes. I find no fault with that, for it is
                    right that you should have it in your power to bestow what is yours on anyone
                    you please. But I do suggest that it is unfair that he should raise no objection
                    when he was going to receive it himself, but when it has been given to others,
                    he should take offence and urge you to withdraw it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="149">
                <p>Moreover it was Aristophon who proposed to pay Gelarchus five talents for sums
                    advanced to the democrats in the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus"
                        >Piraeus</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">See <bibl
                            n="Dem. 20.11">Dem. 20.11</bibl>. Gelarchus is not otherwise known.
                        There were, apparently, no witnesses to his gift.</note>; and he was right.
                    Then, my friend, if you recommended the repayment of unattested sums on the
                    ground of service done to the people, you must not advise the revocation of
                    grants for services which the people themselves attested by inscriptions in the
                    temples, and which are indeed known to all men. You must not exhibit yourself as
                    at the same time proposing that debts ought to be paid, and urging that a man
                    should be deprived of what he has won at the hands of the people. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="150">
                <p>Next, I have this much to say to Cephisodotus. As an orator, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, he is inferior to none. Then it
                    would be far more honorable to use his talents for the chastisement of
                    evil-doers than for the injury of those who deserve well. If he must make
                    enemies, I suggest that they should be those who injure the people, not those
                    who benefit them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="151">
                <p>Then as to Dinias. Perhaps he will tell you of the war-galleys he has equipped
                    and of his other public services. For my part, though Dinias has proved himself
                    a valuable servant of the public, as I sincerely believe, I would urge him
                    rather to claim from you some reward for himself than to tell you to take back
                    rewards previously given to others; for a man gives a surer proof of excellence
                    by claiming a reward for his own services than by grudging others the rewards
                    they have received for theirs. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="152">
                <p>But the most effective retort is one which applies to all the commissioners
                    alike. Each one of them has often before served as commissioner for some
                    business or other. Now you have a very sound law—not, of course, directed
                    against these men, but framed to prevent any commissioner from using his
                    opportunity for profit or blackmail—that no one, elected by the people, be
                    permitted to serve as commissioner more than once. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="153">
                <p>Surely those who are going to advocate a law and urge its necessity ought to show
                    themselves ready to obey existing laws; otherwise it is absurd for them to
                    defend one law as commissioners and violate another themselves. Take and read
                    the law which I cite.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote></p>
                <p>That, Athenians, is both an old and a sound law,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >But it seems to have become obsolete, for sound reasons.</note> which the
                    commissioners will be careful not to violate, if they are wise. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="154">
                <p>I have still a few things to say to you before I sit down. For you ought, in my
                    opinion, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to be
                    anxious for the utmost possible efficiency of our laws, but especially of those
                    on which depends the strength or weakness of our State. And which are they? They
                    are those which assign rewards to those who do good and punishments to those who
                    do evil. For in truth, if from fear of legal penalties all men shunned
                    wrongdoing, and if from ambition for the rewards of good service all chose the
                    path of duty, what prevents our city from being great and all our citizens
                    honest, with not a rogue among them? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="155">
                <p>Now the law of Leptines, Athenians, does harm not only by abolishing the rewards
                    of good service and so rendering fruitless the good intentions of those who are
                    ambitious for honor, but also by leaving our city under the serious reproach of
                    imbecility. For you are of course aware that for each grave offence a single
                    penalty is provided by the law, which says explicitly that “at any trial there
                    shall be not more than one assessment of penalty, whichever the court imposes,
                    whether a personal punishment or a fine, but not both.” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="156">
                <p>But Leptines has used a different measure and says that if anyone claims a return
                    from you, “he shall be disfranchised, and his property shall be confiscated.”
                    There you have two penalties. “The process shall be by laying information or by
                    summary arrest; and if he be convicted, he shall be liable under the law which
                    provides for the case of a man holding office while in debt to the treasury.”
                    Death is what he means, for such is the punishment in that case. Why, here are
                    three penalties!<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">All this is pure
                            sophistry.<foreign xml:lang="grc">a)timi/a</foreign> involving loss of
                        property was not a double penalty, but merely one degree of <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">a)timi/a</foreign>. Moreover, the law cited refers to
                        penalties assessed by the courts, not to those prescribed by statute.
                        Lastly, the so-called third penalty was imposed for the additional offence
                        of contempt, where one who had incurred <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >a)timi/a</foreign> nevertheless claimed <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >a)te/leia</foreign>.</note> Is it not monstrously hard, Athenians, if
                    it proves more serious in your courts to ask for a return for good service than
                    to be convicted of some heinous crime? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="157">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, this law, so
                    dishonorable, so unsound, so suggestive of envy and spite and—I spare you the
                    rest. Those are the sort of things that the framer of the law seems to favor,
                    but you must not imitate them nor display sentiments unworthy of yourselves. I
                    ask you in Heaven's name, what should we all most earnestly deprecate? What do
                    all our laws most carefully guard against? What but those vengeful murders
                    against which our specially appointed protector is the Council of the Areopagus?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="158">
                <p>Now Draco, in this group of laws, marked the terrible wickedness of homicide by
                    banning the offender from the lustral water, the libations, the loving-cup, the
                    sacrifices and the market-place; he enumerated everything that he thought likely
                    to deter the offender; but he never robbed him of his claim to justice; he
                    defined the circumstances that make homicide justifiable and proclaimed the
                    accused in such case free from taint. If, then, your laws can justify homicide,
                    is this fellow's law to forbid any claim, even a just one, to recompense? Not
                    so, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>! </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="159">
                <p>Do not let it appear that you have been more diligent to prevent any of your
                    benefactors from winning a recompense than to suppress murder in your city.
                    Rather, recalling the occasions on which you have repaid the services rendered
                    you, and remembering the inscription of Demophantus, already referred to by
                    Phormio, on which it stands written and confirmed by oath that whoso shall
                    suffer in defence of the democracy shall receive the same reward as Harmodius
                    and Aristogiton, vote for the repeal of this law; for if you do not, it is
                    impossible for you to observe your oaths. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="160">
                <p>And besides all this, observe a further point. That law cannot be a sound one
                    which deals with the past and the future in the same way. “None,” says this law,
                    “shall be immune save and except the descendants of Harmodius and Aristogiton.”
                    Good! “Nor shall anyone in future be granted immunity.” What! not even if other
                    such benefactors arise, Leptines? If you found fault with the past, can it be
                    that you also foresaw the future? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="161">
                <p>Because, you will say, we are now past such expectation.<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">The day of tyrants is past, and the services of tyrannicides are
                        no longer needed.</note> I pray that we may be, Athenians. But as we are
                    mere mortals, neither our language nor our laws should offend religious
                    sentiment; we may both expect blessings and pray for them, but we must reflect
                    that all things are conditioned by mortality. For the Lacedaemonians never
                    dreamed that they would be brought to their present straits, and perhaps even
                    the Syracusans, once a democracy, who exacted tribute from the Carthaginians and
                    ruled all their neighbors and beat at us at sea, little thought they would fall
                    under the tyranny of a single clerk,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Dionysius
                        I. of <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> started life as
                        a clerk in the public service.</note> if report be true. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="162">
                <p>Nor again could the present Dionysius<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Dionysius
                        II., expelled by <persName><surname>Dion</surname></persName> in 357.</note>
                    ever have exacted that <persName><surname>Dion</surname></persName> would come
                    against him in a cargo-boat with a handful of soldiers and expel the master of
                    so many warships and mercenaries and cities. But, methinks, the future is hidden
                    from all men, and great events hang on small chances. Therefore we must be
                    modest in the day of prosperity, and must show that we are not blind to the
                    future. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="163">
                <p>There are still many arguments that one might develop at length, showing that
                    this law is in every respect unsound and opposed to your interests; but to sum
                    up and bring my speech to a conclusion, I will ask you to do this. Calculate and
                    compare in your own minds what will happen to you if you repeal this law, and
                    what if you do not; and then be careful to remember all the consequences of
                    either step, so that you may make the better choice. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="164">
                <p>Now if, on our advice, you reject it, deserving men will receive their due reward
                    from you, and any undeserving man (assuming that there are such) will not only
                    lose his reward, but will pay whatever penalty you approve, in accordance with
                    our alternative law, while all men will acknowledge the honor, justice and
                    veracity of our city. If, on the other hand, you allow it to pass, as I pray you
                    may not, the good will suffer for the sake of the bad, the undeserving will
                    bring calamity on the rest, but come off scot-free themselves, and the
                    reputation of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> will be the
                    very reverse of what I have described; all men will regard her as faithless,
                    envious and mean. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="165">
                <p>It is unworthy of you, Athenians, to prefer such a foul reproach to advantages so
                    honorable and so appropriate to you. For each of you will share individually in
                    the credit of your joint decision. For it is known to all standing round
                        us,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e. the general public; the jury were
                        seated.</note> as to everyone else, that in this court Leptines is
                    contending with us, but within the conscience of each member of the jury
                    humanity is arrayed against envy, justice against malice, and all that is good
                    against all that is most base. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="166">
                <p>If you yield to the nobler impulse and cast your votes with us, you will win for
                    yourselves the credit, and for the State the benefit, of a righteous verdict,
                    and if ever occasion arises, you will not lack friends willing to encounter risk
                    in your behalf. I ask you, therefore, to take all these considerations seriously
                    to heart and to beware that you are not forced into an error of judgement. For
                    on many occasions, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    the justice of the case has not been brought home to you, but a verdict has been
                    wrested from you by the clamor, the violence and the shamelessness of the
                    pleaders. Let not that be your case today, for that would be unworthy of you;
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="167">
                <p>but hold fast to what you are convinced is just, and bear it in mind until you
                    vote, so that true to your oaths you may cast your votes against the counsels of
                    the wicked. If you punish with death those who debase the coinage, I shall be
                    surprised if you lend an ear to men who render our whole State base and
                    counterfeit. By all the gods, I will not believe it of you.</p>
                <p>I think I need say no more, for I believe you understand all my arguments.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
