<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Funeral Speech</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by Norman W. DeWitt, Ph.D.,
                            and Norman J. DeWitt, Ph.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1949</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>After<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In this genre <foreign xml:lang="grc">w)=
                            a)/ndres *)aqhnai=oi</foreign>is unusable because aliens and women were
                        present; there was no salutation for mixed audiences.</note> the State
                    decreed that those who repose in this tomb, having acquitted themselves as brave
                    men in the war, should have a public funeral, and appointed me to the duty of
                    delivering over them the customary speech, I began straightway to study how they
                    might receive their due tribute of praise; but as I studied and searched my mind
                    the conclusion forced itself upon me that to speak as these dead deserve was one
                    of those things that cannot be done. For, since they scorned the love of life
                    that is inborn in all men and chose rather to die nobly than to live and look
                    upon Greece in misfortune, how can they have failed to leave behind them a
                    record of valor surpassing all power of words to express? Nevertheless I propose
                    to treat the theme in the same vein as those who have previously spoken in this
                    place from time to time. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>That the State seriously concerns itself with those who die in battle it is
                    possible to infer both from these rites in general and, in particular, from this
                    law in accordance with which it chooses the speaker at our public funerals. For
                    knowing that among good men the acquisition of wealth and the enjoyment of the
                    pleasures that go with living are scorned,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A
                        commonplace of funeral speeches: <bibl n="Thuc. 2.42.4">Thuc.
                        2.42.4</bibl>.</note> and that their whole desire is for virtue and words of
                    praise, the citizens were of the opinion that we ought to honor them with such
                    eulogies as would most certainly secure them in death the glory they had won
                    while living. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>Now, if it were my view that, of those qualities that constitute virtue, courage
                    alone was their possession, I might praise this and be done with the speaking,
                    but since it fell to their lot also to have been nobly born and strictly brought
                    up and to have lived with lofty ideals, because of all which they had every
                    reason to be good men, I should be ashamed if I were found to have passed over
                    any of these topics.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass censures the author
                        for not following in the sequel a threefold division of his theme, which is
                        here implied and may be found in <bibl n="Plat. Menex. 237a">Plat. Menex.
                            237 a-b</bibl>: nobility of birth, upbringing and education, and
                        exploits. These topics are treated, but not consecutively. Peculiar to this
                        speech is the passage on the ten tribes, <bibl n="Dem. 60.27">Dem.
                            60.27-32</bibl>.</note> I shall begin from the origin of their
                        race.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass compares Isocrates,
                            <title>Helen</title>16 <foreign xml:lang="grc">th\n me\n ou)=n a)rxh\n
                            tou= lo/gou poih/somai toiau/thn tou= ge/nous au)th=s</foreign>, (<bibl
                            n="Isoc. 10.16">Isoc. 10.16</bibl>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>The nobility of birth of these men has been acknowledged from time immemorial by
                    all mankind. For it is possible for them and for each one of their remote
                    ancestors man by man to trace back their being, not only to a physical father,
                    but also to this land of theirs as a whole, a common possession, of which they
                    are acknowledged to be the indigenous children.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >This topic appears in <bibl n="Plat. Menex. 237b">Plat. Menex. 237
                            b-c</bibl>.</note> For alone of all mankind they settled the very land
                    from which they were born and handed it down to their descendants, so that
                    justly one may assume that those who came as migrants into their cities and are
                    denominated citizens of the same are comparable to adopted children; but these
                    men are citizens of their native land by right of legitimate birth.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This topic appears in <bibl n="Hyp. 6.7">Hyp.
                            Epitaph. 7</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>In my view also the fact that the fruits of the earth by which men live were
                    first manifest among us,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">According to tradition
                        the olive was created by the goddess Athena, while the culture of grain,
                        especially wheat and barley, was established by Demeter, whose mysteries
                        were celebrated at Eleusis close to Athens.</note> even apart from their
                    being a superlative boon to all men, constitutes an acknowledged proof that this
                    land is the mother of our ancestors. For all things that bring forth young
                    produce at the same time nutriment out of the organism itself<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Or, <q type="">by a law of nature herself.</q></note> for those that are
                    born. This very thing has been done by this land.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This topic is treated in more detail in <bibl
                            n="Plat. Menex. 237e">Plat. Menex. 237e-238b</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>Such is the pride of birth that belongs to the ancestors of these men throughout
                    the ages. As for Courage and the other elements of virtue, I shrink from
                    rehearsing the whole story, being on my guard for fear an untimely length shall
                    attach to my speech ,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Another commonplace:
                            <bibl n="Hyp. 4">Hyp. 4</bibl> expresses a similar fear.</note> but such
                    facts as it is worth while even for those who are familiar with them to recall
                    to mind and most profitable for the inexperienced to hear,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true"><bibl n="Thuc. 2.36.4">Thuc. 2.36.4</bibl> may be
                        compared.</note> events of great power to inspire and calling for no tedious
                    length of speech, these I shall endeavor to rehearse in summary fashion.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><bibl n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 </bibl>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pi\ kefalai/ou</foreign>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>For the ancestors of this present generation, both their fathers and those who
                    bore the names of these men in time past, by which they are recognized by those
                    of our race, never at any time wronged any man, whether Greek or barbarian, but
                    it was their pride, in addition to all their other good qualities, to be true
                    gentlemen and supremely just, and in defending themselves they accomplished a
                    long list of noble deeds. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>They so prevailed over the invading host of the Amazons as to expel them beyond
                    the Phasis, and the host of Eumolpus and of many another foeman they drove not
                    only out of their own land but also from the lands of all the other
                    Greeks—invaders whom all those dwelling on our front to the westward neither
                    withstood nor possessed the power to halt.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        female warriors known as Amazons were repelled by Theseus. The Phasis River
                        in Colchis, now the Rion, was the legendary boundary between Europe and
                        Asia. Eumolpus invaded Greece from Thrace but was halted by Erechtheus at
                        Eleusis. The route to all parts of the mainland issued from Athens on the
                        west side.</note> Moreover, they were styled the saviors of the sons of
                    Heracles, who himself was the savior of the rest of mankind, when they arrived
                    in this land as suppliants, fleeing before Eurystheus. In addition to all these
                    and many other noble deeds they refused to suffer the lawful rites of the
                    departed to be treated with despite when Creon forbade the burial of <q type="">the seven
                    against Thebes.</q><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This phrase became proverbial
                        as the title of a drama by Aeschylus. Theseus, king of Athens, gave aid to
                        the suppliant wives of the Argive heroes when Creon, king of Thebes, refused
                        burial to their slain husbands: <bibl n="Eur. Supp. 1">Eur.
                        Supp.</bibl></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>Now, omitting mention of many exploits that are classed as myths, I have recalled
                    to mind the above-mentioned, each of which affords so many charming themes that
                    our writers of poetry, whether recited or sung,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >The distinction is between epic and dramatic poetry, which was recited, and
                        odes such as those of Pindar, and dithyrambs, which were sung to musical
                        accompaniment.</note> and many historians, have made the deeds of those men
                    the subjects of their respective arts; at the present time I shall mention the
                    following deeds, which, though in point of merit they are no whit inferior to
                    the former, still, through being closer in point of time, have not yet found
                    their way into poetry or even been exalted to epic rank. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>Those men single-handed twice repulsed by land and sea the expedition assembled
                    out of the whole of Asia,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">King Darius of Persia
                        was repulsed at Marathon, 490, and Xerxes at Salamis, <date when="-0480"
                            >480</date> B.C. The Persian wars are discussed at length in <bibl
                            n="Plat. Menex. 239d">Plat. Menex. 239d ff.</bibl>
                    </note> and at their individual risks established themselves as the authors of
                    the joint salvation of all the Greeks. And though what I shall say next has been
                    said before by many another, still even at this date those dead must not be
                    deprived of their just and excellent praise. For I say that with good reason
                    those men might be judged so far superior to those who campaigned against Troy,
                    that the latter, the foremost princes out of the whole of Greece, with
                    difficulty captured a single stronghold of Asia after besieging it for ten
                        years,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass notes this sentiment in <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 4.83">Isoc. 4.83</bibl>. It is found also in <bibl
                            n="Hyp. 6.35">Hyp. 35</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>whereas those men single-handed not only repulsed a host assembled from an entire
                    continent, which had already subdued all other lands, but also inflicted
                    punishment for the wrong done the rest of the Greeks. Furthermore, checking all
                    acts of selfish aggrandisement among the Greeks themselves, assigning themselves
                    to each station where justice was arrayed, they went on bearing the brunt of all
                    dangers that chanced to arise until the lapse of time brings us to the
                    generation now living. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>Let no one think I have enumerated this list of achievements because I am at a
                    loss what to say about each of them; for if I were the most helpless of all men
                    in discovering what it becomes me to say, the sheer virtue of those dead reveals
                    what sentiments lie to hand and are easy to rehearse. It is my intention,
                    however, after calling to mind their noble birth and the magnificent things done
                    by their ancestors, with all speed to link my speech with the deeds of these
                    dead, to the end that, just as they were akin in the flesh, so I may make the
                    words of praise spoken over them to apply to both alike. I assume that this
                    would be gratifying not only to the ancestors but, best of all, to both them and
                    these dead, if they should come to share one another’s merit not only by virtue
                    of birth but also by reason of our words of praise. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>In the meantime it is necessary to interrupt my discourse for a moment, before
                    declaring the deeds of these men, to solicit the goodwill of those born outside
                    this race who have accompanied us to the tomb.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >The welcome extended to aliens at the public funerals is mentioned in <bibl
                            n="Thuc. 2.34.4">Thuc. 2.34.4</bibl>. Pericles recognizes their
                        presence, <bibl n="Thuc. 36.4">Thuc. 36.4</bibl>.</note> For if I had been
                    appointed to do honor to this burial through expenditure of money or by
                    providing some different kind of a spectacle consisting of equestrian or
                    gymnastic contests, the greater my zeal and the more lavish my expenditure in
                    preparing such spectacles, the better I should have been thought to have done my
                    duty. Having been chosen, however, to extol these men in a speech, unless I have
                    the sympathy of my hearers, I fear that because of my eagerness I may effect the
                    very opposite of what I ought. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>For wealth and speed of foot and strength of body and all other such things have
                    their rewards self-assured to their possessors, and in those fields they win who
                    have the luck, even if not one of the others wishes their success. On the other
                    hand, the persuasiveness of words depends upon the goodwill of the hearers, and
                    with the help of this, even if the eloquence be moderate, it reaps glory and
                    gains favor, but lacking this help, even if it be surpassingly good, it is
                    thwarted by those who hear.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass compares
                            <bibl n="Dem. 18.277">Dem. 18.277</bibl>, but the parallel is not
                        precise.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Now to resume my theme: though many deeds of these men are at hand because of
                    which they will be justly eulogized, I am at a loss what to mention first when I
                    come face to face with the facts. For thronging into my mind as they do, all at
                    one and the same time, it becomes difficult to make a choice among them. I shall
                    endeavor, however, to maintain the same order of topics in my speech as marked
                    the course of the lives of these men. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>From the beginning these men were outstanding in all the activities that formed
                    their schooling, engaging in the exercises that became each stage of life,
                    causing gratification to all who had claim to it—parents, friends, kinsmen.
                    Therefore, just as if recognizing footprints, the memory of those who were near
                    and dear to them now turns to these men every hour in fond recollection, finding
                    many a reminder of occasions when they knew in their hearts that these were lads
                    of surpassing worth. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>Arrived at manhood they rendered their innate nobility known, not only to their
                    fellow-citizens, but to all men. For of all virtue, I say, and I repeat it, the
                    beginning is understanding and the fulfillment is courage; by the one it is
                    judged what ought to be done and by the other this is carried to success.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Kennedy cites <bibl n="Cic. Sest. 40.86">Cicero
                            Pro Sestio 40.86</bibl> <q type="">hoc sentire prudentiae est, facere
                        fortitudinis.</q></note> In both these qualities these men were distinctly
                    superior; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>for if ever a danger affecting all the Greeks was brewing, these were the first
                    to foresee it, and time and again they challenged the rest to save the
                    situation. This action is a demonstration of sound judgement joined with public
                    spirit. Although, again, there was much folly among the Greeks, not unmixed with
                        slackness,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">By <q type="">slackness</q> is meant the
                        acceptance of Macedonian bribes, mentioned by <bibl n="Hyp. 6.10">Hyp.
                            10</bibl>; Blass compares <bibl n="Dem. 18.20">Dem. 18.20</bibl>, where
                        <q type="">folly</q> is used as a euphemism for <q type="">slackness.</q></note> a folly which failed
                    to foresee some dangers and feigned not to see others at a time when it was
                    possible to avert these misfortunes without sacrificing safety, nevertheless,
                    when they did hearken and evinced willingness to do their duty,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The attitude of the Greek states toward the aggressions of
                        Philip of Macedon may be compared to that of the small democratic states of
                        Europe toward Germany before the war of <date from="1939" to="1945"
                            >1939</date>-1945. By his <title>Olynthiacs</title> (<bibl n="Dem. 1"
                            >Dem. 1-3</bibl>) and <title>Phillippics</title>(<bibl n="Dem. 4">Dem.
                            4</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 6">Dem. 6</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 9">Dem.
                        9</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 10">Dem. 10</bibl>) Demosthenes tried to arouse and
                        unite them but with little success, until the year <date when="-0338"
                            >338</date> B.C., when he achieved his great diplomatic triumph in
                        uniting Thebes with Athens, ancient rivals.</note> these men did not bear a
                    grudge but stepping forward and eagerly offering their all, bodies, money, and
                    allies, they entered upon the ordeal of the contest, in which they were not
                    sparing even of their lives. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>Of necessity it happens, when a battle takes place,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The particular reference is to the battle of Chaeronea,
                            <date when="-0338">338</date> B.C., where the Greeks were defeated by
                        Philip of Macedon.</note> that the one side is beaten and the other
                    victorious; but I should not hesitate to assert that in my judgement the men who
                    die at the post of duty on either side do not share the defeat but are both
                    alike victors. For the mastery among the survivors is decided as the deity
                    disposes, but that which each was in duty bound to contribute to this end, every
                    man who has kept his post in battle has done. But if, as a mortal being, he
                    meets his doom, what he has suffered is an incident caused by chance, but in
                    spirit he remains unconquered by his opponents.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Blass notes this sentiment in <bibl n="Dem. 18.208">Dem. 18.208</bibl>, and
                        in <bibl n="Isoc. 4.92">Isoc. 4.92</bibl>. It is subsidiary to the
                        recognition of the supremacy of the deity, fate or fortune, <bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.192">Dem. 18.192</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 18.207">Dem.
                            18.207</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 18.208">Dem. 18.208</bibl>. To commemorate
                        the valor of the fallen Thebans a monumental seated lion was erected facing
                        in the direction of the enemy. It is still extant.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>It is my judgement, therefore, that we have to thank the valor of these men,
                    along with the folly of our opponents, that our enemies did not set foot upon
                    our land; because, every man of them having had proof of their mettle, those who
                    there engaged them on that occasion had no wish to confront in battle a second
                    time the kinsmen of those men, suspecting that, although they would confront men
                    of the same breed, they were not likely to find the fortune of battle so
                    kind.</p>
                <p>Not the least reason for believing that this was their state of mind is afforded
                    by the peace that was made; for it is impossible to cite a more plausible or
                    more creditable reason than that the master of our opponents, astounded at the
                    valor of these who died, chose rather to be friendly toward their kinsmen than
                    once more to assume the risk of all his fortunes.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Philip exacted no vengeance after his victory; Attica was
                        not invaded. The Greek states retained the right of self-government and
                        became allies, not subjects, of the victor.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>I believe also that if someone were to ask those in the opposite ranks whether
                    they thought they had won by their own deeds of valor or by a startling and
                    cruel turn of fortune and by the skill and daring of their own commander, not
                    one of them would be so shameless or audacious as to claim credit for what
                    happened. Furthermore, in contests of which the deity, the master of all, has
                    disposed the outcome as it chose, it is necessary of course to acquit all
                    others, being but human, of the charge of cowardice, but when it comes to the
                    means by which the leader of our opponents prevailed over those appointed to the
                    command of our army, no one could justly locate the cause in the rank and file
                    of either the enemy or ourselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>But if, after all, there is any human being who might rightly lay a charge
                    concerning the issue of that battle, he would with good reason advance it
                    against those of the Thebans who were appointed to this command,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Philip seems to have deceived the Athenians by a
                        feigned retreat while throwing his strongest troops against the Thebans.
                        This stratagem broke the line and decided the battle. The Theban general
                        Theagenes and his colleagues seem to have been no more to blame than the
                        rest.</note> nor could anyone rightly lay blame upon the rank and file of
                    either the Thebans or ourselves. Those men, receiving command of a military
                    force that would neither brook defeat nor make excuse and had an emulous zest
                    for glory, made the right use of none of these. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>As for the other questions touching this campaign, each individual is at liberty
                    to draw conclusions according to his judgement, but what has become manifest to
                    all living men alike is this—that, in effect, the freedom of the whole Greek
                    world was being preserved in the souls of these men. At any rate, since fate
                    removed them, not one of those remaining has made a stand against the foe. While
                    I desire that my words may be free from offence, it seems to me that if one
                    should declare that the valor of these men was the very life of Greece he would
                    speak the truth; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>for at one and the same time their spirits were separated from their dear bodies
                    and the self-esteem of Greece was taken from her. We shall therefore seem guilty
                    perhaps of a bold exaggeration, but still it must be uttered: for just as, if
                    the light of day were removed out of this universe of ours,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Kennedy quotes <bibl n="Cic. Amic. 13.47 ">Cicero De Amic.
                            13.47</bibl> <q type="">solem enim e mundo tollere videntur qui amicitiam e vita
                        tollunt.</q> According to <bibl n="Aristot. Rh. 1.7">Aristot. Rh. 1.7</bibl>
                        and <bibl n="Aristot. Rh. 3.10">Aristot. 3.10</bibl>, Pericles had once said
                        in a funeral speech it was <q type="">as if the spring had been taken out of the
                        year.</q></note> all the remnant of life would be harsh and irksome, so, now
                    that these men have been taken from us, all the old-time ambition of the Greeks
                    is sunk in gloom and profound obscurity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>While it stands to reason that many influences helped to make them what they
                    were, not least was their virtue ascribable to our form of government.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This topic is treated in <bibl
                            n="Plat. Menex. 238b">Plat. Menex. 238b-239d</bibl>. Blass compares
                            <bibl n="Dem. 20.108">Dem. 20.108</bibl>, but the similarity is not
                        impressive.</note> For though absolute governments dominated by a few create
                    fear in their citizens, they fail to awaken the sense of shame. Consequently,
                    when the test of war comes, everyone lightheartedly proceeds to save himself,
                    knowing full well that if only he succeeds in appeasing his masters by presents
                    or any other civility whatsoever, even though he becomes guilty of the most
                    revolting conduct, only slight reproach will attach to him thereafter. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>Democracies, however, possess many other just and noble features, to which
                    right-minded men should hold fast, and in particular it is impossible to deter
                    freedom of speech, which depends upon speaking the truth, from exposing the
                    truth. For neither is it possible for those who commit a shameful act to appease
                    all the citizens,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Under an oligarchy, the
                        speaker means, it is possible for the wrongdoer to seal the mouths of the
                        small ruling clique by means of bribes, but under a democracy it is
                        impossible to buy the silence of thousands of citizens. The reference is to
                        oligarchic governments set up by the Spartans in subject states. Pericles
                        praised the Athenian form of government as against the Spartan, <bibl
                            n="Thuc. 2.37">Thuc. 2.37-39</bibl>.</note> so that even the lone
                    individual, uttering the deserved reproach, makes the guilty wince: for even
                    those who would never speak an accusing word themselves are pleased at hearing
                    the same, provided another utters it. Through fear of such condemnation, all
                    these men, as was to be expected, for shame at the thought of subsequent
                        reproaches,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The fear of exposure as a
                        factor in democratic government is mentioned by Pericles, <bibl
                            n="Thuc. 2.37.3">Thuc. 2.37.3</bibl>, and by <bibl n="Hyp. 6.25">Hyp.
                            25</bibl>. Blass compares <bibl n="Dem. 22.31">Dem. 22.31</bibl>.</note>
                    manfully faced the threat arising from our foes and chose a noble death in
                    preference to life and disgrace. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>The considerations that actuated these men one and all to choose to die nobly
                    have now been enumerated,—birth, education, habituation to high standards of
                    conduct, and the underlying principles of our form of government in general. The
                    incentives that challenged them severally to be valiant men, depending upon the
                    tribes to which they belonged, I shall next relate.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The list which here begins is our chief authority for the
                        names and order of precedence of the ten Athenian tribes as established by
                        Cleisthenes in <date when="-0508">508</date> B.C. The particular myths that
                        suit the context, however, are for the most part obscure and of relatively
                        recent origin. For example, the older legends speak of but one daughter of
                        Erechtheus as being sacrificed. The later version is known to <bibl
                            n="Cic. Tusc. 1.48.116">Cicero Tusc. Disp. 1.48.116</bibl>.</note> All
                    the Erechtheidae were well aware that Erechtheus, from whom they have their
                    name, for the salvation of this land gave his own daughters, whom they call
                    Hyacinthides, to certain death, and so extinguished his race. Therefore they
                    regarded it as shameful, after a being born of immortal gods had sacrificed
                    everything for the liberation of his native land, that they themselves should
                    have been found to have placed a higher value upon a mortal body than upon
                    immortal glory.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><bibl n="Hyp. 6.24">Hyp.
                            24</bibl> reads in part <foreign xml:lang="grc">qnhtou= sw/matos
                            a)qa/naton do/can e)kth/santo</foreign>, <q type="">gained immortal glory at the
                        price of a mortal body.</q></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>Neither were the Aegeidae ignorant that Theseus, the son of Aegeus, for the first
                    time established equality in the State.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >According to <bibl n="Plut. Thes. 25">Plut. Thes. 25</bibl>, it was
                        equality between newcomers and natives that Theseus established; the word
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">i)sonomi/a</foreign> usually means equality
                        before the law and is almost a synonym for democracy.</note> They thought
                    it, therefore, a dreadful thing to be false to the principles of that ancestor,
                    and they preferred to be dead rather than through love of life to survive among
                    the Greeks with this equality lost. The Pandionidae had inherited the tradition
                    of Procne and Philomela, the daughters of Pandion, who took vengeance on Tereus
                    for his crime against themselves.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Procne is
                        said to have murdered her own son Itys and to have served his flesh to her
                        husband Tereus in revenge for his treachery to herself and his cruelty to
                        Philomela. It is curious that the speaker seems less shocked by this crime
                        than by the innocent tale of Alope, <bibl n="Dem. 60.31">Dem. 60.31</bibl>,
                        below.</note> Therefore they decided that life was not worth living unless
                    they, akin by race, should have proved themselves to possess equal spirit with
                    those women, when confronted by the outrage they saw being committed against
                    Greece. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>The Leontidae had heard the stories related of the daughters of Leo, how they
                    offered themselves to the citizens as a sacrifice for their country’s sake.
                    When, therefore, such courage was displayed by those women, they looked upon it
                    as a heinous thing if they, being men, should have proved to possess less of
                    manhood. The Acamantidae did not fail to recall the epics in which Homer says
                    that Acamas sailed for Troy for the sake of his mother Aethra.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Aethra is mentioned in <bibl n="Hom. Il. 3.144">Hom. Il.
                            3.144</bibl>, but the rest of the story is not Homeric. This Acamas is
                        unknown to Homer, though he mentions two other individuals of the same name.
                        It was later myths that told of the rescue of Aethra after the fall of Troy
                        by her two grandsons, not sons, Acamas and Demophon.</note> Now, since he
                    braved every danger for the sake of saving his own mother, how were these men
                    not bound to face every danger for the sake of saving their parents one and all
                    at home? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>It did not escape the Oeneidae that Semele was the daughter of Cadmus, and of her
                    was born one whom it would be sacrilegious to name at this tomb,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Dionysus, or Bacchus, god of wine, who, as an
                        Olympian, could not associate with death.</note> and by him Oeneus was
                    begotten, who was called the founder of their race.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Two demes in Attica were named Oenoe, which was sufficient
                        to justify the invention of a hero Oeneus, but he is not to be confused with
                        the Homeric hero of this name who was associated with Calydon in Aetolia and
                        with Argos. The word means <q type="">wineman,</q> from <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >oi)=nos</foreign>. At Athens the anniversary of this hero fell in the
                        month Gamelion, like the Lenaea of Dionysus. It was natural, therefore, to
                        call him the son of the god, but the relationship plays no part in recorded
                        myths.</note> Since the danger in question was common to both States, on
                    behalf of both they thought themselves bound to endure any Anguish to the
                        end.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The suggestion is that the Oeneidae
                        would have felt equally bound to fight on behalf of Thebes, of which the
                        founder was Cadmus, and on behalf of Athens, one of whose heroes was Oeneus,
                        great-grandson of Cadmus. This is the weakest link in this series.</note>
                    The Cecropidae were well aware that their founder was reputed to have been part
                    dragon, part human, for no other reason than this, that in understanding he was
                    like a man, in strength like a dragon. So they assumed that their duty was to
                    perform feats worthy of both. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>The Hippothoontidae bore in mind the marriage of Alope, from which Hippothoon was
                    born, and they knew also who their founder was; about these matters—to avoid
                    impropriety on an occasion like this<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Alope’s
                        son was said to have been twice exposed, and twice rescued and suckled by a
                        mare. The use of mare’s milk as a food prevailed among the Scythians, as the
                        Greeks knew well from their colonists in the region of the Black Sea, if not
                        from <bibl n="Hdt. 4.2">Hdt. 4.2</bibl>; Gylon, grandfather of Demosthenes,
                        had lived in the Crimea and was said to have married a Thracian wife. The
                        orator was sometimes twitted by his opponents about his Thracian blood. He
                        may have been sensitive. Consequently the attitude here revealed might be
                        construed as evidence for the genuineness of the speech.</note> I forbear to
                    speak plainly—they thought it was their duty to be seen performing deeds worthy
                    of these ancestors. It did not escape the Aeantidae that Ajax, robbed of the
                    prize of valor, did not consider his own life worth living.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Ajax, worsted by Odysseus in a contest for possession of the
                        arms of Achilles, was said to have slain himself: <bibl n="Hom. Od. 11.541"
                            >Hom. Od. 11.541-567</bibl>; the story of his madness and of
                        slaughtering flocks and herds as if they were his enemies is not Homeric:
                            <bibl n="Soph. Aj. 1">Soph. Aj.</bibl></note> When, therefore, the god
                    was giving to another the prize of valor, at once they thought they must die
                    trying to repel their foes so as to suffer no disgrace to themselves. The
                    Antiochidae were not unmindful that Antiochus was the son of Heracles.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The mother of Antiochus was Meda, daughter of
                        Phylas, king of the Dryopes, but the story was unimportant and little
                        known.</note> They concluded therefore that they must either live worthily
                    of their heritage or die nobly. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>Now, though the living kinsmen of these dead deserve our sympathy, bereaved of
                    such brave men and divorced from close and affectionate association, and though
                    the life of our native land is desolate and filled with tears and mourning,
                    nevertheless these dead by a just calculation are happy.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Compare <bibl n="Hyp. 6.24">Hyp. 24</bibl> <q type="">Are we not to
                        think them fortunate because their valor was proven rather than unfortunate
                        because their lives were lost?</q></note> First of all, bartering little for
                    much, a brief time for all eternity, they leave behind them an ageless fame<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">With <foreign xml:lang="grc">eu)/kleian
                            a)gh/rw</foreign> compare <bibl n="Thuc. 2.43.2">Thuc. 2.43.2</bibl>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)gh/rwn e)/painon</foreign>and <bibl n="Hyp. 6.42"
                            >Hyp. 42</bibl>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">eu)doci/an a)gh/raton</foreign>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>In which the children of these men shall be reared in honor and the parents of
                    these men shall enjoy distinction<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This topic is
                        touched upon in <bibl n="Hyp. 6.27">Hyp. 27</bibl>.</note> and tender care
                    in their old age, cherishing the fame of these men as an assuagement of their
                        sorrow.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><bibl n="Thuc. 2.44.4">Thuc.
                            2.44.4</bibl> <q type="">and be comforted by the fair fame of these your
                        sons.</q></note> In the second place, immune from disease of body and beyond
                    the reach of anguish of spirit,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In <bibl
                            n="Hyp. 6.43">Hyp. 43</bibl> may be found <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >a)phllagme/noi ei)si\ no/swn kai\ lu/phs</foreign>, as Blass
                        observes.</note> such as the living must suffer because of the misfortunes
                    which have befallen, they today receive high honor and inspire great emulation
                    while they are accorded the customary obsequies.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Annual sacrifices were performed at the public sepulchre in
                        Athens. They were followed by athletic contests.</note> How, then, since the
                    whole country unites in according them a public burial, and they alone receive
                    the words of universal praise, while their kinsmen and fellow-citizens are not
                    alone in mourning them, but every land that has the right to be called Hellas
                    and the greater part of the whole world mourns with them,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true"><bibl n="Thuc. 2.43.3">Thuc. 2.43.3</bibl> <q type="">for the whole
                        world is the sepulchre of famous men.</q></note> how can we do otherwise than
                    consider them blessed of fortune? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>With excellent reason one might declare them to be now seated beside the gods
                    below, possessing the same rank as the brave men who have preceded them in the
                    islands of the blest. For though no man has been there to see or brought back
                    this report concerning them, yet those whom the living have assumed to be worthy
                    of honors in the world above, these we believe, basing our surmise on their
                    fame, receive the same honors also in the world beyond.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">A similar sentiment is found in <bibl n="Hyp. 6.43">Hyp.
                            43</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>While it is perhaps difficult<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass compares
                            <bibl n="Hyp. 6.41">Hyp. 41</bibl>
                        <foreign xml:lang="grc">xalepo\n me\n i)/sws e)sti/</foreign>.</note> to
                    mitigate the present misfortunes by the spoken word, nevertheless it is our duty
                    to endeavor to turn our minds to comforting thoughts, reflecting that it is a
                    beautiful thing for parents who have begotten men like these, and themselves
                    were born of others like unto them, to be seen enduring their affliction more
                    decorously than the rest of mankind, and, no matter what fortune befalls, to be
                    like them; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>for to the departed such conduct would seem most becoming in you and honorable to
                    them, and to the whole State and to the living it would bring the greatest
                        glory.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This topic is treated at greater
                        length in <bibl n="Plat. Menex. 247d">Plato Menex. 247d-248c</bibl>.</note>
                    It is a grievous thing for fathers and mothers to be deprived of their children
                    and in their old age to lack the care of those who are nearest and dearest to
                    them. Yes, but it is a proud privilege to behold them possessors of deathless
                    honors and a memorial of their valor erected by the State, and deemed deserving
                    of sacrifices and games for all future time. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>It is painful for children to be orphaned of a father. Yes, but it is a beautiful
                    thing to be the heir of a father’s fame. And of this pain we shall find the
                    deity to be the cause, to whom mortal creatures must yield, but of the glory and
                    honor the source is found in the choice of those who willed to die nobly.</p>
                <p>As for myself, it has not been my concern how I might make a long speech, but how
                    I might speak the truth. And now do you, having spent your grief and done your
                    part as law and custom require, disperse to your homes.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
