<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>De curatione acutorum morborum </title>
				<author>Aretaeus</author>
				<editor>Francis Adams LL.D.</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Extant Works of Aretaeus, The Cappadocian.</title>
						<author>Aretaeus</author>
						<editor>Francis Adams LL.D.</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Milford House Inc.</publisher>
							<date>1972 (Republication of the 1856 edition).</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="page"/>
			</refsDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc> 
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="book" n="1">
				<pb n="377"/>
				<head>BOOK I.</head>
				<div type="chapter" n="1">
					<head>PREFACE.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> remedies of acute diseases are connected with
						the form of the symptoms, certain of which have been described by me in the
						preceding works. Whatever, therefore, relates to the cure of fevers,
						according to their differences, the form of the diseases, and the varieties
						in them, the greater part of these will be treated of in my discourses on
						fevers. But acute affections which are accompanied with fevers, such as
						Phrenitis, or those without fevers, as Apoplexy, of these alone will I now
						write; and that I may not commit blunders, or become diffuse by treating of
						the same matters in different places, the beginning and end correspond to
						the same in the work on the affections.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="2">
					<pb n="378"/>
					<head>CHAPTER I. THE CURE OF PHRENITICS.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> patient ought to be laid in a house of moderate
						size, and mild temperature--in a warm situation, if winter, and in one that
						is cool and humid, if summer; in spring and autumn, to be regulated
						according to the season. Then the patient himself, and all those in the
						house, are to be ordered to preserve quiet; for persons in phrensy are sharp
						of hearing, are sensitive to noise, and easily become delirious. The walls
						should be smooth, level, without projections, not adorned with frieze<note
							n="1">The Greek word <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)/XNAI</foreign> would
							appear to have been applied like <hi rend="ital">frieze</hi> in English,
							both to the nap on woollen cloth, and in architecture, to ornaments of
							sculpture on a flat face. Our author evidently uses it in the latter
							sense; but I suspect the translators fail to recognise it. For the
							former meaning, see Erotian, and Föes Œc. Hippocr. Modern lexicographers
							do not seem acquainted with this use of the term. See Liddel and
							Scott's; and Dunbar's Lexicons.</note> or paintings; for painting on a
						wall is an excitant. And, moreover, they catch at certain false appearances
						before their eyes, and grope about things which are not projecting, as if
						they were so; and any unreal occasion may be a cause sufficient to make them
						raise their hands. Length and breadth of the couch moderate, so that the
						patient may neither toss about in a broad one, nor fall out of a narrow bed.
						In plain bed clothes, so that there may be no inducement to pick at their
						nap. But on a soft bed, for a hard one is offensive to the nerves; as in
						phrenitics, above all others, the nerves especially suffer, for they are
						subject to convulsions. Access of their dearest friends is to be permitted;
						stories and conversation not of an exciting character; for they ought to be
						gratified in everything, especially in cases where the delirium tends to
						anger. Whether they are to be laid in darkness or in light must be
						determined by the nature of the attack; for if they are exasperated by the
						light, and</p>
					<pb n="379"/>
					<p>see things which exist not, and represent to themselves things not present,
						or confound one thing with another, or if strange images obtrude themselves
						upon them; and, in a word, if they are frightened at the light, and the
						things in the light, darkness must be chosen; but if not, the opposite
						state. It is a good symptom, too, when they become of a sound mind, and
						their delirium abates, on exposure to the light. Abstinence from food should
						not be prolonged; food should be rather liquid, scanty, and frequently
						administered, for food soothes the soul: the proper time for giving it is
						during the remissions, both of the fever and of the delirium. But if they
						have become delirious from want of food, and if the fever do not remit, we
						are to give food that does not do much harm in fever. It is a favourable
						circumstance, when the fever and the delirium agree both as to the paroxysms
						and intermissions.</p>
					<p>If, therefore, the time for the administering of food be come, in the first
						place, it must be enquired whether it be necessary to abstract blood. If,
						then, the delirium have come on with fever at the commencement, in the first
						or second day, it will be proper to open a vein at the elbow, especially the
						middle. But if the delirium supervene on the third or fourth day, we are to
						open a vein up to the first period of critical days. But if it was past the
						proper time for bleeding, on the sixth or seventh day, it will be proper to
						evacuate considerably before the crises in acute diseases, either by giving
						purgative medicines, or by using other stimulants. But when opening a vein
						you must not abstract much, even if you open the vein at the commencement;
						for phrenitis is an ailment easily convertible into syncope. But if the
						patient be plethoric and youthful, and if the ailment be connected with
						fulness in eating and drinking, those indications have nothing to do with
						the phrenitis; for even without the delirium, it would be proper to abstract
						much blood in such circumstances; but much less is to be abstracted, if such
						persons labour under phrenitis.</p>
					<pb n="380"/>
					<p>But we may open a vein the more boldly in these cases, if the disease proceed
						from the præcordia, and not from the head; for there (in the præcordia) is
						the origin of life. But the head is the seat of sensation, and of the origin
						of the nerves; and it attracts more blood from the heart than it imparts to
						the others. If it therefore suffer, it is not proper to open the vein at the
						elbow; for these affections are such that it is no small injury to evacuate
						in them. And if the strength be sufficient to withstand the evacuation, we
						must abstract only once, lest during the interval between the acts of
						evacuation, the proper season for food be lost. The fevers, in cases of
						phrenitis, are of a continual type, neither have they long intermissions,
						but experience short and ill-marked remissions. But if the patient give way
						before a sufficient quantity has been abstracted, it must be put off until
						another remission, unless it occur at a distant period; but, if not, having
						resuscitated the patient by odours, stroking the face, and pricking the
						feet, we are immediately to abstract blood. The measure of sufficiency is
						the strength.</p>
					<p>Liquid food is proper in all febrile diseases, but especially in phrenitic
						cases, for these are more arid than mere fevers. The mulse is to be given,
						unless they are bilious, for it is indigestible in patients who are subject
						to bitter bile. Alica<note n="2">As this term is of frequent occurrence in
							the works of our author, as in those of Hippocrates, it may be proper to
							mention, once for all, that the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>XO/NDROS</foreign> of the Greeks and the <hi rend="ital">alica</hi>
							of the Romans was the species of grain called Spelt (<hi rend="ital"
								>Triticum Spelta</hi>) broken down into rough granules; that is to
							say, it was coarsely ground Spelt.</note> washed with water, or mulse,
						is a good thing; also it is good to give pottages of a plain kind, such as
						decoctions of savory, of parsley, or of dill, for these are beneficial to
						the respiration, and are diuretic, and a free discharge of urine is
						beneficial in phrenetics. All kinds of pot-herbs, especially melons, for
						their gluten is good for lubricating the tongue, the trachea, and for</p>
					<pb n="381"/>
					<p>the alvine evacuations; but the best of all are beet, blite, cress, gourd in
						season, and whatever else is best in its own season. The juice of ptisan in
						a very liquid state, and containing little nourishment, is most proper at
						first, being made always thicker as the disease progresses. But the quantity
						of nourishment is to be diminished at the crises, and a little before them.
						And, if the disease be protracted, the customary food must not be
						abstracted, but we must give nourishing articles from the cereals, in order
						to support the patient; and when there is need, of the flesh of the
						extremities of beasts and fowls, mostly dissolved in the soups: these ought
						to be completely dissolved during the process of boiling. The rock fishes
						are preferable to all others;<note n="3">All the Greek and Arabian
							authorities on dietetics hold, that fishes caught among rocks are
							particularly excellent. See Paulus Ægineta, t. i. p. 159.</note> but on
						the whole we must choose the best in the country, for countries are believed
						to differ as to the kinds of fish which are best in them. Fruit containing
						wine must be given restrictedly, for it is apt to affect the head and
						præcordia; but if required by the state of the strength and of the stomach,
						we must give such articles as apples boiled in mulse or roasted in suet. Of
						other things, each is to be diluted with hot water, if you give it solely
						for the refreshment of the stomach; but if it is wanted also for strength,
						you must not dilute the vinous part much. In a word, the food must be such
						as I have described.</p>
					<p>For the sake of refrigeration, the head is to be damped with the oil of the
						unripe olive pounded; for in phrenitics the head is not fond of being kept
						warm. But if restlessness and false visions be present, we must mix equal
						parts of rose-oil at first; and the rose-oil is to be increased for the
						astringing and cooling of the head. But if they become disordered in
						understanding, and their voice change, the hair (<hi rend="ital">capillary
							leaves</hi>?) of the wild thyme must be boiled in oils, or the juice of
						ivy or</p>
					<pb n="382"/>
					<p>of knot-grass is also to be infused. But if the delirium get more violent,
						hog's-fennel and cow-parsnip are to be boiled in the oils, and some vinegar
						poured in; for these things dissipate the vapours and heat, and are solvents
						of the thick humours which contribute to the delirium. But care must be
						taken that the moist application do not extend to the neck and the tendons,
						for it is prejudicial to tendons and nerves. Every season is suitable for
						the damp application, except the commencement of a paroxysm; it should be
						used more rarely during the increase, but most frequently at the acme; and
						whenever they are delirious, then, in particular, it will be proper to use a
						cold application, made still more cold in the season of summer, but in
						winter tepid. To soothe the delirium it is well to foment the forehead with
						oxycrate, or the decoction of fleabane, by means of a sponge, and then to
						anoint with the oil of wild vine or of saffron, and also to anoint the nose
						and ears with them.</p>
					<p>These things, moreover, also induce sleep. For if they lay awake all night,
						nor sleep during the day, and the eyes stand quite fixed like horns, and the
						patients toss about and start up, we must contrive to procure sleep and rest
						for them; first, by fomentations to the head, with unmixed rose-oil, or oil
						of marjoram with the juice of ivy, or the decoction of wild thyme or of
						melilot. But poppy boiled in oil is particularly soporific when applied to
						the fontenelle of the head, or with a sponge to the forehead. But the
						poppies, if recently plucked and green, may be applied whole under the
						pillows; for they thicken and humectate the spirit (<hi rend="ital"
							>pneuma</hi>), which is dry and attenuated, and diffuse over the senses
						fumes which prove the commencement of sleep. But if greater applications are
						needed, we may rub in the meconium (<hi rend="ital">expressed juice of
							poppy</hi>) itself on the forehead with water, and also anoint the
						nostrils with the same, and pour it into the ears. Gentle rubbing of the
						feet with oil, patting of the head, and particularly stroking of</p>
					<pb n="383"/>
					<p>the temples and ears is an effectual means; for by the stroking of their ears
						and temples wild beasts are overcome, so as to cease from their anger and
							fury.<note n="4"><p>This passage savours much of magnetical
								manipulation. The following verses of Solon have been quoted as
								referring to the same subject :--</p>
							<p><hi rend="center"><foreign xml:lang="grc">*)/ALLOI *PAIW=NOS
										POLUFARMA/KOU E)/RGON E)/XONTES *)IHTROI/· KAI\ TOI=S
										OU)DE\N E)/PESTI TE/LOS· *POLLA/KI D᾿ E)X O)LI/GHS O)DU/NHS
										ME/GA GI/GNETAI A)/LGOS, *KOU)/K A)/N TIS LU/SAIT' H)/PIA
										FA/RMAKA DOU/S· *TO\N DE\ KAKAI=S NOU/SOISI KUKW/MENON
										A)RGALE/AIS TE *AYA/MENOS XEIROI=N AI)=YA TI/QHS'
										U(GIH=</foreign>.</hi></p></note> But whatever is familiar
						to any one is to him a provocative of sleep. Thus, to the sailor, repose in
						a boat, and being carried about on the sea, the sound of the beach, the
						murmur of the waves, the boom of the winds, and the scent of the sea and of
						the ship. But to the musician the accustomed notes of his flute in
						stillness; or playing on the harp or lyre, or the exercise of musical
						children with song. To a teacher, intercourse with the tattle of children.
						Different persons are soothed to sleep by different means.</p>
					<p>To the hypochondria and region of the stomach, if distended by inflammation,
						hardness, and flatulence, embrocations and cataplasms are to be applied,
						with the addition of the oil of the over-ripe olive, for it is thick,
						viscid, and calefacient; it therefore is required in inflammation: let dill
						or flea-bane be boiled in it, and it is a good thing to mix all together;
						but if flatulence be present also, the fruits of cumin and parsley, and
						whatever other things are diuretic and carminative, along with sifted
						natron, are to be sprinkled on the application. But if the liver experience
						suffering and pain, apply unwashed wool just taken from the ewe, oil from
						the unripe olive, or rose-oil; but we must mix also Hellenic or Cretan rob,
						and boil in it melilot, and mixing all these things into one juice, foment
						the liver therewith. To the spleen the oil must be</p>
					<pb n="384"/>
					<p>mixed with vinegar; or if it should appear to be enlarged in bulk, oxycrate,
						and instead of the wool a soft sponge; for the spleen delights in and is
						relieved by such things. But if the hypochondria be collapsed and retracted
						upwards, and the skin be stretched, it will be best instead of the oil, or
						along with it, to use thick butter in equal quantity, and let fleabane and
						rosemary be boiled in the decoction, and dill is not unsuitable.</p>
					<p>But if it be the proper time for cataplasms, we may use the same oils to the
						same places, the ingredients of the cataplasms being linseed, fenugreek, or
						fine barley-meal; beans and vetches, also, are proper if the abdomen be
						swelled. Roasted millet, also, in bags, makes a light and soft fomentation;
						when ground it makes, along with honey, oil, and linseed, an excellent
						cataplasm for the hypochondria. Also let the same flowers, herbs, and seeds
						which I have described among the embrocations be used for the cataplasms.
						Honey, also, is useful along with these things, to give consistency to the
						dry things, and for the mixing of the toasted things, and for the
						preservation of the heat; it is a good thing, likewise, by itself; also a
						cataplasm half-boiled, and an embrocation dissolved in some of the liquids,
						is effectual as an emollient, calefacient, carminative, and diuretic, and to
						moderate the inflammations. These effects are produced also by mulse when
						drunk, and even more and greater effects when conveyed internally to the
						trachea, the lungs, the thorax, and the stomach.</p>
					<p>The bowels, also, are to be frequently stimulated by suppositories or
						liniments (for they are generally constipated), in order to act as
						derivatives from the head, and also for the evaporation of the vapours in
						the chest, and for the evacuation of the matters in the belly; but, if the
						belly be confined for several days, it must be opened by a clyster of mulse,
						oil, and natron.</p>
					<p>But if the distension of the inflammation do not properly</p>
					<pb n="385"/>
					<p>subside, we must apply a cupping-instrument with scarificators where the
						inflammation points and is greatest, on the first or second day, according
						as the inflamed parts may indicate, and the strength direct; and from those
						the amount of the evacuation of the blood must be determined, for excess
						occasions syncope. During the first and second day the fomentation should be
						the same; but, on the third, cerate with some of the oils used in the
						embrocations is to be applied: then, if they be still in a state of
						inflammation, epithemes, consisting of hyssop, fenugreek boiled in mulse,
						the resin of the turpentine plant, and wax; the oils the same for these
						places. If by these means the delirium do not at all abate, it will be
						necessary to have recourse to cropping of the head, provided the hairs be
						very long, to the extent of one half; but, if shorter, down to the skin:
						then, in the meantime having recruited the strength, to apply a
						cupping-instrument to the vertex, and abstract blood. But dry-cupping is
						first to be applied to the back.</p>
					<p>But since in all the acute diseases the chest must be remedied, this part
						generally suffering with the heart and lungs, more especially from the
						difficulty of the respiration, which is sometimes hot, at other times cold;
						and, moreover, from ardent fever, cough, badness of the humours, and
						sympathy of the nerves, and complaint of the stomach, and illness of the
						pleura and of the diaphragm (for the heart, if it suffer from any dreadful
						illness, never recovers),--in cases of phrenitis these parts in particular
						must be soothed. For, indeed, the delirium in certain cases arises from some
						of the parts in the chest; respiration hot and dry; thirst acrid; febrile
						heat not easily endured, as being determined from all parts to the chest;
						and illness from the perversion of its native heat, but greater and more
						intolerable the communication of the same from the other parts to the chest:
						for the extremities are cold--the head, the feet, and the hands; but, above
						these last, the chest. It is to be remedied,</p>
					<pb n="386"/>
					<p>then, by humectation and refrigeration. For bathing, oil boiled with camomile
						or nard; in summer, also, Hellenic rob. But if it be necessary also to apply
						epithemes, dates moistened with austere wine, then levigated and pounded
						into a mass with nard, barley meal, and flower of the wild vine, form a
						soothing cataplasm for the chest: a cooling one is formed of apples bruised
						with mastich and melilot; all these things, however, are to be mixed up with
						wax and nard. But if the stomach be affected with torpor and loathing of
						food, the juice or hair of worm-wood are mixed up with them; and the
						hypochondriac region is to be fomented with this boiled up in oil. The
						infusion or the juice of it may be drunk before food to the amount of two
						cupfuls of the infusion, or one cupful of the bitter juice with two cupfuls
						of water. But if the stomach be affected with heartburn, not from the
						constitution of the disease, but of itself from acrid and saltish humours,
						or from being pinched with bile, or from being parched with thirst, we must
						give in the food milk mixed with water to the amount of half a hemina of
						milk in one cupful of water; the patient should swallow the most of it, but
						he may take a small portion of it with bread.</p>
					<p>But if the patient be also affected with Causus, and there be thirst,
						restlessness, mania, and a desire of cold water, we must give less of it
						than in a case of Causus without phrenitis, for we must take care lest we
						injure the nerves; we are to give them as much as will prove a remedy for
						the stomach, and a little is sufficient, for phrenitics are spare
						drinkers.</p>
					<p>But if converted into syncope, and this also happens (the powers of life
						being loosened, the patient being melted in sweat, and all the humours being
						determined outwardly, the strength and spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>)
						being also dissolved), we must disregard the delirium, and be upon our guard
						lest the patient be resolved into vapours and humidity. Then the only
						support is wine, to nourish quickly by its substance, and to penetrate</p>
					<pb n="387"/>
					<p>everywhere, even to the extremities; to add tone to tone, to rouse the torpid
						spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>), warm that which is cold, brace what is
						relaxed, restrain those portions which are flowing and running outwards,
						wine being sweet to the senses of smell so as to impart pleasure; powerful
						to confirm the strength for life; and most excellent to soothe the mind in
						delirium. Wine, when drunk, accomplishes all these good purposes; for they
						become composed by the soothing of their minds, are spontaneously nourished
						to strength, and are inspired with pleasure.</p>
					<p>But when the fever has become protracted and feeble, and the delirium is
						converted into fatuity, but the hypochondrium is not much injured by
						swelling, flatulence, or hardness, and the head is the part principally
						affected, we must boldly wash the head, and practise copious affusions on
						it; for thus will the habit of body be moistened, the respiration of the
						head and exhalation over the whole body will be restored; and thus will that
						which is dry become diluted, and the sense purified of its mist, while the
						understanding remains sound and firm. These, indeed, are the indications of
						the removal of the disease.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="3">
					<head>CHAPTER II. THE CURE OF LETHARGICS.</head>
					<p>L<hi rend="smallcaps">ETHARGICS</hi> are to be laid in the light, and exposed
						to the rays of the sun (for the disease is gloom); and in a rather warm
						place, for the cause is a congelation of the innate heat. A soft couch,
						paintings on the wall, bed-clothes of various colours, and all things which
						will provoke the sense of sight; conversation, friction along with squeezing
						of the feet, pulling, tickling. If deep sleep prevail, shouting aloud, angry
						reproach,</p>
					<pb n="388"/>
					<p>threats regarding those matters which he is accustomed to dread, announcement
						of those things which he desires and expects. Everything to prevent
						sleep--the reverse of that which is proper for phrenitics.</p>
					<p>With regard to the depletion of lethargics this should be known:--If the
						obliviousness be the sequela of another disease, such as phrenitis, we must
						not open a vein, nor make a great evacuation of blood in any way, but inject
						the belly, not solely for the evacuation of its contents, but in order to
						produce revulsion from above, and to determine from the head: there should
						be a good deal of salts and natron in it, and it answers very well if you
						add a sprinkling of castor to the clyster; for in lethargics the lower
						intestine is cold, and dead, as it were, to evacuation. But, if the lethargy
						is not the consequence of another disease, but is the original affection,
						and if the patient appear to be plethoric, provided it be with blood, we
						must open a vein at the elbow; but, if with a watery phlegm, or other
						humours, we must purge by means of cneoros<note n="1">Daphne Cneorum
							L.</note> with the ptisan, or by black hellebore with honeyed-water, in
						the beginning, if you wish to do so moderately; but if to a greater extent,
						you must give to the patient when fasting of the medicine called Hiera, to
						the extent of two drams with three cupfuls of honeyed-water; and, having
						waited until it purges, then give food, if it be the proper season; but
						otherwise nourishment is to be given the next day. It will be seasonable
						then to give in the evening a dram of the hiera, dissolved either in two
						cupfuls of water or of honeyed-water.</p>
					<p>Total abstinence from food is bad, as is also much food. It is proper, then,
						to administer a little food every day, but not to withdraw food altogether;
						for the stomach to be reminded of its duties and fomented, as it were,
						during the whole day. Also the food must be attenuant and laxative, rather
						in the form of soups than roasted, such as hens or shell-fish; and the</p>
					<pb n="389"/>
					<p>herb mercury is to be boiled with it, and some vinegar added. And we may add
						to the juices, if it be proper to use the juice of ptisan, something to
						promote exhalation and the discharge of urine, such as fennel, parsley--the
						pot-herbs themselves, or their fruits. Horehound, also, by its acrid
						qualities, does good; and likewise colewort with oil, and the brine of fish
							(<hi rend="ital">garum</hi>). The sweet cumin is a most excellent
						medicine for the flatulence and urine; for the stomach and bladder are to be
						stimulated during the whole time of the disease.</p>
					<p>The moist applications to the head the same as in the case of phrenitics; for
						in both the senses are filled with vapours, which must either be expelled by
						refrigerants and astringents, such as the oil of roses or the juice of ivy,
						or dissipated into exhalation by attenuants, such as wild thyme in vinegar,
						with the rose-oil. But if there be pain of the nerves, and coldness of the
						whole body, but more especially of the extremities, we must besmear and
						bathe the head and neck with castor and oil of dill, and anoint the spine
						with the same along with Sicyonian oil, the oil of must, or old oil; at the
						same time, we must rub both the arms from the shoulders and both the legs
						from the groins. With these, moreover, the bladder is to be soothed, which
						suffers, as being of a nervous nature, and is stressed as being the passage
						for the urine; and also is irritated by the acrimony of the humours, for the
						urine is bilious. But if the trembling increase, and there be danger of a
						convulsion, we must necessarily use Sicyonian oil to the head, but use it in
						small quantity. But if there be inflammation of the hypochondria, and
						fulness thereof, flatulence, and tension of the skin, or if there be a
						hollow there from retraction inwards of the hypochondria, we must apply the
						embrocations and cataplasms, described by us under Phrenitics.</p>
					<p>The cupping-instrument is by no means to be used if the disease be the
						consequence of phrenitis, but this may be done more boldly if it be the
						original disease. If the tongue be</p>
					<pb n="390"/>
					<p>black, and a swelling point in the hypochondria, the cupping-instrument must
						necessarily be used. When in the course of time the senses have been
						evacuated, and the patient is otherwise more tolerant of the disease, we may
						apply the cupping-instrument to the top of the head, since we can evacuate
						from it without injury to the strength.</p>
					<p>Flatulence is to be expelled both upwards and downwards; for lethargy
						produces collections of flatus both in the cavities and in the whole frame,
						from inactivity, torpor, and want of spirit, which motion and watchfulness
						dissipate; wherefore, having rubbed up green rue with honey and natron, we
						anoint therewith; it will expel the wind more effectually if one part of the
						resin of turpentine be added to these things. A fomentation also will expel
						flatus, either with hot unwashed wool, or with rough old rags, or a sponge
						with water in which hyssop, marjoram, penny-royal, or rue, have been boiled.
						The potions<note n="2">Propomata, or whets. See Paulus Ægineta, vol. iii. p.
							544. They correspond to the <hi rend="ital">Liqueurs</hi> of the present
							day, but were taken at the beginning of a feast. Comp. Horat. Sat. ii.
							4, ll. 24--27.</note> also which are taken before food expel flatus, and
						these also bring away phlegm and bile in the stomach and bowels; such are
						hyssop, boiled mulse, Cretan dictamny, or marjoram: maiden-hair and
							agrostis<note n="3">Probably the <hi rend="ital">Triticum
							repens.</hi></note> are acrid, but possessed of expulsive qualities, for
						indeed they evacuate flatus and urine.</p>
					<p>If there be trembling of the hands and head, he may take a draught,
						consisting of castor with three cupfuls of honeyed-water, for some days; or
						if he will not drink this, we may melt down the castor in a sufficient
						quantity of oil, wherein rue has been boiled, to the amount of three
						cupfuls; and a double amount of this is to be injected into the lower bowel,
						and is to be repeated for several days; and after the benefit derived from
						it (for it brings off flatus upwards and downwards, and, in certain cases,
						urine and fæces), if it should</p>
					<pb n="391"/>
					<p>be diffused over the whole system in any way, the nerves recover from their
						tremblings and become strong, and it changes the habit of body to the hot
						and dry, and alters the constitutions of diseases. It is also a very
						excellent thing to blow it into the nostrils, for in this way it expels
						flatulence by sneezing; for as the bladder secretes urine, so does the nose
						mucus. It effects these things by its gentle heat, in which respect it is
						superior to the other sternutatories, pepper, hellebore, soap-wort, and
						euphorbium; for these things, both at their first and last impression are
						harsh, and disorder the head and the sense, whereas castor gradually creates
						a gentle heat. To the head it is also otherwise suitable, because the nerves
						everywhere derive their origin from it; and castor is a remedy for the
						diseases of the nerves; but to mix it with some one or more of the medicines
						described will not be disagreeable, for if it be mixed, it will not
						immediately disorder the head, even in a moderate degree, but after a time
						it will stir up the heat.</p>
					<p>The nose is to be moistened by tickling; by odours acrid indeed to the sense,
						but possessed of heating powers, such as the castor itself, or savory, or
						penny-royal, or thyme, either in a green state, or in a dried, moistened
						well with vinegar.</p>
					<p>Anointing with acrid medicines is proper to the feet and knees. The <hi
							rend="ital">materiel</hi> thereof should be heating and pungent by
						degrees; for there is need of both in cases of lethargy to induce warmth and
						watchfulness. In the first place, it is proper to whip the limbs with the
						nettles, for the down thereof sticking to the skin does not endure long, but
						imparts no disagreeable tingling and pain; it also moderately stimulates,
						induces swelling, and provokes heat. But if you desire to have these effects
						produced more powerfully, rub in equal parts of lemnestis<note n="4">An
							efflorescence collecting about reeds in salt lakes. The same as <foreign
								xml:lang="grc">A)DA/RKH</foreign>, for which see the Appendix to
							Dunbar's Greek Lexicon.</note> and euphorbium, with oil of must. It
						is</p>
					<pb n="392"/>
					<p>also a very good thing to rub with raw squill pulverised; but it is necessary
						to rub off the oily matter of the limb (for everything acrid loses its
						stimulant properties with oil) -- unless it be medicinal -- either the oil
						of privet, or that of must, or the Sicyonian. But if after these things a
						deep coma prevail, it will be proper, having pounded the wild cucumber with
						vinegar, and mixed it with an equal quantity of a cake of mustard, to apply
						this as an acrid cataplasm, and one which will speedily occasion redness,
						and will also quickly produce swelling. But if there be danger of blistering
						and of wounds, it will be proper to raise the cataplasm frequently, and see
						that none of these effects be produced. These things, therefore, are to be
						done to relieve the torpor and insensibility of the parts at all seasons,
						except at the commencement of the paroxysms.</p>
					<p>But if the patient have already recovered his sensibility, but there is still
						some heaviness of the head, noise, or ringing thereof, it will be proper to
						evacuate phlegm by the mouth, first by giving mastich to chew, so that he
						may constantly spit, then again stavesacre, the granum cnidium,<note n="5"
							>Probably the fruit of the <hi rend="ital">Daphne cnidium.</hi></note>
						but more especially mustard, because it is a common article, and also
						because it is more of a phlegmagogue than the others. And if the patient
						drink it willingly, it will be sufficient to dissolve the matters in the
						stomach, it will also be able to moisten the stomach and expel flatulence;
						for this once fortunately happened to myself in the case of a man who drank
						it by my directions; for experience is a good teacher, one ought, then, to
						try experiments, for too much caution is ignorance.</p>
					<p>The head, then, after the hair has been clipped to the skin, if much good is
						not thereby accomplished, is to be shaven to procure insensible
						perspiration, and also to allow the anointing with acrid medicines, such as
						that from lemnestis (or <hi rend="ital">adarce</hi>),</p>
					<pb n="393"/>
					<p>or thapsia,<note n="6"><hi rend="ital">Thapsia Garganica L.</hi>, a species
							of deadly carrot.</note> or mustard moistened with water; these things,
						with double the quantity of bread, are to be rubbed on an old piece of skin,
						and applied to the head, taking good care at the expiry of an hour to foment
						the parts with hot sponges.</p>
					<p>It will also not be devoid of utility, when all, or most at least, of the
						fatal symptoms of the disease are gone, but the languor remains, to bathe;
						and then also gestation, friction, and all gentle motion will be
						beneficial.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="4">
					<head>CHAPTER III. THE CURE OF MARASMUS. <note n="1">I agree with the preceding
							editors in thinking that this chapter is merely a portion of the last
							one.</note>
					</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> these cases, indeed, if Marasmus prevail, we
						must remedy it by quickly having recourse to the bath and to exercises. And
						truly milk is a remedy of marasmus by nourishing, warming, moistening the
						stomach, and soothing the bladder. Moreover, the same means are beneficial
						in cases of <hi rend="ital">catochus</hi>, for the form of these diseases is
						alike and the same. Castor, then, is more particularly proper in these
						cases, and most particularly soothing, whether to drink, to anoint with, or
						to inject into the bowel. The affections similar to these which happen to
						women from the uterus, will be treated of among female diseases.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="5">
					<pb n="394"/>
					<head>CHAPTER IV. THE CURE OF APOPLEXY.</head>
					<p>. . . . . should indeed the apoplexy be severe, for by all means the patients
						are, as it were, dead men whenever one is old, to whom this affection is
						congenial, and they cannot survive the greatness of the illness, combined
						with the misery of advanced life. It has been formerly stated by me, how the
						magnitude of the disease is to be estimated. If the patient be young, and
						the attack of apoplexy weak, it is still no easy matter to effect a cure; it
						must, however, be attempted. The equivalent remedy, then, as being the great
						assistance in a a great disease, is venesection, provided there be no
						mistake as to quantity; but the amount is difficult to determine, since if
						you take a little too much, you despatch the patient at once; for to them a
						little blood is most potent, as being that which imparts the vital heat to
						the frame itself, and to the food. But, if the quantity be inferior to the
						cause, you do little good with this the great remedy, for the cause still
						remains. But it is better to err on the side of smallness; for, if it should
						seem to have been deficient, and the appearance of the eyes, as seen from
						below, be favourable, we can open a vein again. We must open the vein at the
						hollow of the elbow, for the blood flows readily from it in the left arm.
						But in smaller attacks of apoplexy, it is necessary to consider whether the
						paralytic seizure be on the left side or the right. In a word, the
						abstraction is to be made from the healthy parts, for there the blood flows
						more freely, and thither the revulsion is made from the parts affected.
						When, therefore, the patient is seized with apoplexy without any obvious
						cause, we should decide thus concerning the abstraction of the blood. But if
						the attack happen from a blow, a fall from a high place,</p>
					<pb n="395"/>
					<p>or compression, there must be no procrastination, for in certain cases this
						alone is sufficient for the cure and to save life.</p>
					<p>But if it is not thought expedient to open a vein, owing to the patient's
						having been seized with much coldness, torpor, and insensibility, an
						injection must be given for the evacuation of the engorgement in the bowels
						(for very generally persons are seized with apoplexy from the immoderate use
						of food and wine), and for the revulsion of the humours seated in the head.
						The clyster should be acrid; and an evacuant of phlegm and bile, consisting
						not only of natron, but also of euphorbium, to the amount of three oboli,
						added to the usual amount of a clyster, also the medullary part of the wild
						cucumber, or the decoction of the hair (<hi rend="ital">leaves</hi>) of
						centaury in oil or water. The following is a very excellent clyster: To the
						usual amount of honey add rue boiled with oil and the resin of the
						turpentine tree, and some salts, instead of natron, and the decoction of
						hyssop.</p>
					<p>And if by these means the patient be somewhat aroused, either from being
						moved by the supervention of fevers, or having recovered from his
						insensibility, or the pulse has become good, or if the general appearance of
						the face has become favourable, one may entertain good hopes, and apply the
						remedies more boldly. Wherefore, when the strength is confirmed, the
						purgative hiera may be given to the patient fasting, and particularly a full
						dose. But, if the strength be an objection, it is to be given, to the amount
						of one-half, with honeyed-water. And we are to move him about, after having
						laid him stretched on a couch; and those who carry him must do so gently, he
						being allowed to rest frequently, to avoid inducing lassitude. And if there
						be a copious evacuation from the bowels, we are to permit it; but if not,
						give water, or honeyed-water, to the amount of two cupfuls, for drink. And
						if nausea supervene upon the purging, we are not to interfere with it; for
						the exertions of the body have some tendency to</p>
					<pb n="396"/>
					<p>resuscitate the patient, and the vomiting of the bile carries off the cause
						of the disease. The medicine hiera is a purger of the senses, of the head,
						and of the nerves. Enough, indeed, has been said respecting evacuation of
						every kind at the commencement.</p>
					<p>But having wrapped the whole of his person in wool, we are to soak it with
						some oil -- the Sicyonian, oil of musk (<hi rend="ital">gleucinum</hi>), or
						old oil, either each of these separately, or all mixed together; but it is
						best to melt into it a little wax, so as to bring it to the thickness of
						ointments; and it is to be rendered more powerful by adding some natron and
						pepper: these are to be reduced to a powder, and strained in a sieve. But
						castor has great efficacy in cases of palsy, both in the form of a liniment
						with some of the fore-mentioned oils, and it is still more potent when taken
						in a draught with honeyed-water, the quantity being to the amount we have
						stated under lethargics; but, at the same time, we must consider the age and
						disposition of the patient, whether he be ready to take the drink for
						several days. Inunctions are more powerful than fomentations, as being more
						easily borne, and also more efficacious; for the ointment does not run down
						so as to stain the bed-clothes (for this is disagreeable to the patient),
						and adheres to the body until, being melted by the heat thereof, it is drunk
						up. Moreover, the persistence of their effects is beneficial, whereas liquid
						applications run off. The ingredients of the ointments are such as have been
						stated by me; but along with them castor, the resin of the turpentine-tree,
						equal parts of euphorbium, of lemnestis, and of pellitory; of pepper, and of
						galbanum one-half, with triple the amount of Egyptian natron; and of wax, so
						as to bring it to a liquid consistence. But a much more complex mode of
						preparing these medicines has been described by me on various occasions, and
						under a particular head. Cataplasms are to be applied to the hardened and
						distended parts; their ingredients are linseed, fenugreek, barley-meal,
						oil</p>
					<pb n="397"/>
					<p>in which rue or dill has been boiled, the root of mallows pounded and boiled
						in honeyed-water, so as to become of the consistence of wax. They should be
						of a soft and agreeable consistence. These things are to be done if the
						patient still remains free of fever, or if the fever be slight, in which
						case no regard need be had to the heat.</p>
					<p>But if the fevers be of an acute nature, and the remaining disease appear to
						be of minor consequence, and if these induce urgent danger, the diet and the
						rest of the treatment must be accommodated to them. Wherefore, the patients
						must use food altogether light and of easy digestion; and now, most
						especially, attention ought to be paid to the proper season for eating, and,
						during the paroxysms, the whole of the remedial means must be reduced; and,
						altogether, we must attend to the fevers.</p>
					<p>But if the disease be protracted, and if the head be at fault, we must apply
						the cupping-instrument to the back of the head, and abstract blood
						unsparingly; for it is more efficacious than phlebotomy, and does not reduce
						the strength. But, dry-cupping is to be first applied between the shoulders,
						in order to produce revulsion of the matters in the occiput.</p>
					<p>Sometimes, also, the parts concerned in deglutition are paralysed, which is
						the sole help and safety of persons in apoplexy, both for the swallowing of
						food and for the transmission of medicines. For not only is there danger of
						want of nourishment and hunger, but also of cough, difficulty of breathing,
						and suffocation; for if one pour any liquid food into the mouth it passes
						into the trachea, neither the tonsils coming together for the protrusion of
						the food, nor the epiglottis occupying its proper seat where it is placed by
						nature, as the cover of the windpipe; we must, therefore, pour honeyed-water
						or the strained ptisan into a piece of bread resembling a long spoon, and
						passing it over the trachea, pour its contents into the stomach; for in this
						way deglutition is</p>
					<pb n="398"/>
					<p>still accomplished. But if the patient be in the extremity of danger, and the
						neck with the respiration is compressed, we must rub the neck and chin with
						heating things and foment. They effect nothing, and are unskilful in the
						art, who apply the cupping-instrument to the throat, in order to dilate the
						gullet; for distension, in order to procure the admission of food, is not
						what is wanted, but contraction of the parts for the purposes of
						deglutition. But the cupping-instrument distends further; and, if the
						patient wish to swallow, it prevents him by its expansion and revulsion,
						whereas it is necessary to pass into a state of collapse, in order to
						accomplish the contraction of deglutition; and in addition to these, it
						stuffs the trachea so as to endanger suffocation. And neither, if you place
						it on either side of the windpipe, does it any good; for muscles and nerves,
						and tendons and veins, are in front of it.</p>
					<p>The bladder and the loose portion of the rectum are sometimes paralysed, in
						regard to their expulsive powers, when the bowels are constantly filled with
						the excrements, and the bladder is swelled to a great size. But sometimes
						they are affected as to their retentive powers, for the discharges run away
						as if from dead parts. In this case one must not boldly use the instrument,
						the catheter, for there is danger of inducing violent pain of the bladder,
						and of occasioning a convulsion in the patient. It is better to inject with
						no great amount of strained ptisan; and if the bowel be evacuated of the
						fæces, it will be proper to inject castor with oil. But the sole hope, both
						of general and partial attacks of paralysis, consists in the <hi rend="ital"
							>sitz</hi> bath of oil. The manner of it will be described under the
						chronic diseases.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="6">
					<pb n="399"/>
					<head>CHAPTER V. CURE OF THE PAROXYSM OF EPILEPTICS.</head>
					<p>E<hi rend="smallcaps">VEN</hi> the first fall in epilepsy is dangerous, if
						the disease attack in an acute form; for it has sometimes proved fatal in
						one day. The periodical paroxysms are also dangerous; and, therefore, on
						these accounts, epilepsy has been described among the acute diseases. But if
						the patient has become habituated to the illness, and the disease has taken
						a firm hold of him, it has become not only chronic, but, in certain cases,
						perpetual; for if it pass the prime of life, it clings to him in old age and
						in death.</p>
					<p>Such remedies, then, as are applicable in the chronic state will be described
						among the chronic diseases; but such things as must be done for a sudden
						attack of the disease, of these the greater number have been described under
						apoplectics, namely, venesection, clysters, anointings, the cupping
						instrument; these means being the most powerful for the purpose of arousing.
						But I will now describe the peculiar remedies for an attack of the falling
						sickness. In children, then, to whom, owing to dyspepsia, or from excessive
						cold, the disease is familiar, vomiting, either of food, or of phlegm, or of
						any other humour, is beneficial. Feathers, then, dipped in the ointment of
						iris, excite vomiting; and the unguentum irinum is not inapplicable for
						smearing the tonsils with. But having first laid the child on his belly
						(this is the easiest position for vomiting), we must press gently on his
						lower belly. But if the lower jaw be convulsed or distorted, or if the hands
						and legs be tossed about, and if the whole face be fixed, the limbs are to
						be soothed by gentle rubbing with oil, and the distortions of the
						countenance rectified; the straight parts are to be gently bound, so that
						they may not become distorted. The</p>
					<pb n="400"/>
					<p>cold parts are to be fomented with unscoured wool, or with old rags. The anus
						is to be rubbed with honey along with the oil of rue, or with natron and
						liquid resin along with these things; and they are to be gently pushed
						within the anus, for they expel flatus, and children pass flatus in this
						disease. But if they can swallow, we may give them of this medicine: Of
						cardamom, one part; of copper, one siliqua. These things are to be drunk
						with honeyed-water; for either it is vomited up along with the matter
						annoying the stomach, or the bowels are opened. This is a very excellent
						linctus: Of cardamom, of mustard, and of the hair of hyssop equal parts; of
						the root of iris, one part, with a double quantity of natron; of pepper, to
						the amount of one-third. Having mixed up all these things together, and
						having separated the jaw, pour into the mouth, and even beyond the tonsils,
						so that the things may be swallowed. These things are proper for infants,
						and for young persons the same are applicable. But the more powerful emetics
						are to be taken: the bulbous root of narcissus; of mustard and of hyssop,
						equal parts; of copper and pepper, one-half the proportion of the former
						things. They are to be mixed with honey and given. These things are proper,
						in order to rouse from the paroxysm; but those calculated to produce the
						resolution of the disease will be described under the chronic diseases.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="7">
					<head>CHAPTER VI. THE CURE OF TETANUS.</head>
					<p>N<hi rend="smallcaps">OW</hi>, indeed, a soft, comfortable, smooth,
						commodious, and warm bed is required; for the nerves become unyielding,
						hard, and distended by the disease; and also the skin, being dry</p>
					<pb n="401"/>
					<p>and rough, is stretched; and the eye-lids, formerly so mobile, can scarcely
						wink; the eyes are fixed and turned inwards; and likewise the joints are
						contracted, not yielding to extension. Let the house also be in a tepid
						condition; but, if in the summer season, not to the extent of inducing
						sweats or faintness; for the disease has a tendency to syncope. We must also
						not hesitate in having recourse to the other great remedies; for it is not a
						time for procrastination. Whether, then, the tetanus has come on from
						refrigeration, without any manifest cause, or whether from a wound, or from
						abortion in a woman, we must open the vein at the elbow, taking especial
						care with respect to the binding of the arm, that it be rather loose; and as
						to the incision, that it be performed in a gentle and expeditious manner, as
						these things provoke spasms; and take away a moderate quantity at first, yet
						not so as to induce fainting and coldness. And the patient must not be kept
						in a state of total abstinence from food, for famine is frigid and arid.
						Wherefore we must administer thick honeyed-water without dilution, and
						strained ptisan with honey. For these things do not press upon the tonsils,
						so as to occasion pain; and, moreover, they are soft to the gullet, and are
						easily swallowed, are laxative of the belly, and very much calculated to
						support the strength. But the whole body is to be wrapped in wool soaked in
						oil of must or of saffron, in which either rosemary, fleabane, or wormwood
						has been boiled. All the articles are to be possessed of heating properties,
						and hot to the touch. We must rub with a liniment composed of lemnestis,
						euphorbium, natron, and pellitory, and to these a good deal of castor is to
						be added. The tendons also are to be well wrapped in wool, and the parts
						about the ears and chin rubbed with liniments; for these parts, in
						particular, suffer dreadfully, and are affected with tension. Warm
						fomentations, also, are to be used for the tendons and bladder, these being
						applied in bags containing toasted millet, or in the bladders of cattle
						half</p>
					<pb n="402"/>
					<p>filled with warm oil, so that they may lay broad on the fomented parts.
						Necessity sometimes compels us to foment the head, a practice not agreeable
						to the senses, but good for the nerves; for, by raising vapours, it fills
						the senses with fume, but relaxes the nervous parts. It is proper, then, to
						use a mode of fomentation the safest possible, and materials not of a very
						heavy smell; and the materials should consist of oil devoid of smell, boiled
						in a double vessel,<note n="1">A double vessel was a smaller vessel, to
							which heat was applied by placing it in a larger. It was called <hi
								rend="ital">balneum mariœ</hi> by the alchemists. It is frequently
							made mention of in the works of the ancient writers on pharmacy. See, in
							particular, Galen, sec. loc. vii. 2; De Sanit. tuend iv. 8; Meth. Med.
							viii. 5; Dioscorid. ii. 95; Oribasius Meth. Med. viii. 6, and the
							learned note of Daremberg.</note> and applied in bladders; or of fine
						salts in a bag: for millet and linseed are pleasant indeed to the touch, but
						gaseous, and of an offensive smell. The patient having been laid on his
						back, the fomentations are to be spread below the tendons, as far as the
						vertex; but we must not advance further to the bregma, for it is the common
						seat of all sensation, and of all remedial and noxious means it is the
						starting-point. But if it be necessary to apply cataplasms to the tendons,
						it must be done below the occiput; for if placed higher, they will fill the
						head with the steam of the linseed and fenugreek. After the cataplasms, it
						is a good thing to apply the cupping-instrument to the occiput on both sides
						of the spine; but one must be sparing in the use of heat, for the pressure
						of the lips of the instrument is thus painful, and excites contractions. It
						is better, then, to suck slowly and softly, rather than suddenly in a short
						time; for thus the part in which you wish to make the incision will be
						swelled up without pain. Your rule in regard to the proper amount of blood
						must be the strength. These are the remedies of tetanus without wounds.</p>
					<p>But if the spasm be connected with a wound, it is dangerous,</p>
					<pb n="403"/>
					<p>and little is to be hoped. We must try to remedy it, however, for some
						persons have been saved even in such cases. In addition to the other
						remedies, we must also treat the wounds with the calefacient things formerly
						described by me, by fomentations, cataplasms, and such other medicines as
						excite gentle heat, and will create much pus: for in tetanus the sores are
						dry. Let the application consist of the manna of frankincense, and of the
						hair of poley, and of the resins of turpentine and pine-trees, and of the
						root of marsh-mallow and of rue, and of the herb fleabane. These things are
						to be mixed up with the cataplasms, melting some of them, sprinkling the
						others upon them, and levigating others beforehand with oil; but the mallow,
						having been pounded, is to be boiled beforehand in honeyed-water. We are to
						sprinkle, also, some castor on the ulcer, for no little warmth is thereby
						communicated to the whole body, because the rigors proceeding from the sores
						are of a bad kind. Rub the nostrils with castor along with oil of saffron;
						but also give it frequently, in the form of a draught, to the amount of
						three oboli. But if the stomach reject this, give intermediately of the root
						of silphium an equal dose to the castor, or of myrrh the half of the
						silphium: all these things are to be drunk with honeyed-water. But if there
						be a good supply of the juice of the silphium from Cyrene,<note n="2">I
							would remind the professional reader, that the Cyrenaic silphium was a
							superior kind of <hi rend="ital">assa-fœtida</hi>, which at one time
							grew copiously in the region of Cyrene. See Paulus Ægineta, Syd. Soc.
							Edit., t. iii. 337.</note> wrap it, to the amount of a tare, in boiled
						honey, and give to swallow. It is best given in this way, as it slips
						unperceived through the palate; for it is acrid, and occasions disagreeable
						eructations, being a substance which has a bad smell. But if it cannot be
						swallowed thus, it must be given dissolved in honeyed-water; for it is the
						most powerful of all the medicines given to be swallowed, which are
						naturally</p>
					<pb n="404"/>
					<p>warming, diluent, and can relax distensions and soothe the nerves. But if
						they can swallow nothing, we must inject it into the anus with the oil of
						castor; and thus the anus is to be anointed with oil or honey. With this,
						also, we must anoint the fundament, along with oil or honey. But if they
						will drink nothing, we must make an injection of some castor with the oil.
						With this, also, we are to anoint the fundament, along with fat or honey;
						and also foment the bladder; and use it as an ointment, having melted it
						with a sufficiency of wax to bring it to the proper consistence. But if it
						be the time for evacuating flatulence and fæces, we are to inject two drams
						of the purgative hiera along with honeyed-water and oil, since, along with
						the expulsion of these, it warms the lower belly; for hiera is both a
						compound and heating medicine.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="8">
					<head>CHAPTER VII. THE CURE OF QUINSEY.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HERE</hi> are two forms of quinsey. The one is attended
						with heat, and great inflammation of the tonsils, and swelling outwardly;
						moreover, the tongue, uvula, and all the parts there, are raised up into a
						swelling. The other is a collapse of these parts, and compression inwardly,
						with greater sense of suffocation, so that the inflammation appears to be
						determined to the heart. In it, then, particularly, we must make haste to
						apply our remedies, for it quickly proves fatal.</p>
					<p>If, then, it proceed from taking too much food and wine, we must inject the
						bowels on the day of the attack, and that with two clysters: the one a
						common clyster, so as to bring off the feculent matters; and the other for
						the purpose of producing revulsion of the humours from the tonsils and
						chest.</p>
					<pb n="405"/>
					<p>It will therefore be, but not undiluted . . . . . . . and the decoctions of
						centaury and hyssop; for these medicines also bring off phlegm. And if the
						patient has been on a restricted diet, we open the vein at the elbow, and
						make a larger incision than usual, that the blood may flow with impetuosity
						and in large quantity; for such a flow is sufficient to mitigate the heat
						most speedily, is able to relieve the strangulation, and reduce all the bad
						symptoms. It is no bad practice, likewise, to bring the patient almost to
						fainting, and yet not so as that he should faint altogether, for some from
						the shock have died of the fainting . . . . . . . . or binding them with
						ligatures above the ankles and knees. It is a very good thing, likewise, to
						apply ligatures to the forearms above the wrists, and above the forearms to
						the arms. And if deglutition be easy, we are to give elaterium with
						honeyed-water, and the whey of milk, as much as will be sufficient to purge
						the patient. In these cases, elaterium is preferable to all other
						cathartics; but cneoros and mustard are also suitable, for both these purge
						the bowels. If the inflammations do not yield to these means, having bent
						the tongue back to the roof of the mouth, we open the veins in it; and if
						the blood flow freely and copiously, it proves more effectual than all other
						means. Liquid applications to the inflamed parts, at first of an astringent
						nature, so as to dispel the morbid matters: unwashed wool, then, with
						hyssop, moistened in wine, and the ointment from the unripe olive. But the
						cataplasms are similar to the liquid applications,--dates soaked in wine,
						and levigated with rose-leaves. But in order that the cataplasm may be
						rendered glutinous and soft, let flour or linseed, and honey and oil be
						added, to produce the admixture of all the ingredients. But if it turn to a
						suppuration, we are to use hot things, such as those used in the other form
						of synanche. Let fenugreek be the powder, and manna and resin the substances
						which are melted; and let the hair of poley be sprinkled on it, and a hot
						fomentation</p>
					<pb n="406"/>
					<p>be made with sponges of the decoction of the fruit of the bay and of hyssop.
						And the powdered dung of pigeons or of dogs, sifted in a sieve, is most
						efficacious in producing suppuration, when sprinkled on the cataplasm. As
						gargles, honeyed-water, with the decoction of dried lentil, or of hyssop, or
						of roses, or of dates, or of all together. We are also to smear the whole
						mouth, as far as the internal fauces, either with Simples, such as the juice
						of mulberries, or the water of pounded pomegranates, or the decoction of
						dates; or with Compound preparations, such as that from mulberries, or that
						from <hi rend="ital">besasa</hi>,<note n="1">The wild rue, or <hi
								rend="ital">Peganum harmala.</hi> See Dioscorides, iii. 46.</note>
						or that from the juice of pomegranates, and that from swallows. But if the
						ulcers proceed from eschars, these gargles, and washes for the mouth, the
						decoction of hyssop in honeyed-water, or of fat figs in water, and along
						with them starch dissolved in honeyed-water, or the juice of ptisan, or of
						tragus (<hi rend="ital">spelt</hi>?).</p>
					<p>But in the species of synanche attended with collapse, we are to make a
						general determination from within outwardly, of the fluids, of the warmth,
						and of all the flesh, so that the whole may swell out. Let the liquid
						applications then be of a hot nature, with rue and dill, natron being
						sprinkled upon them; and along with them the cataplasms formerly mentioned.
						It is a good thing also to apply a cerate with natron and mustard for
						inducing heat; for heat determined outwardly is the cure of such complaints;
						and thus swelling takes place in the neck, and an external swelling rescues
						from peripneumonia; but in cases of synanche, the evil when inwardly is of a
						fatal nature. But those who, in order to guard against suffocation in
						quinsey, make an incision in the trachea for the breathing, do not appear to
						me to have proved the practicability of the thing by actual experiment; for
						the heat of the inflammation is increased by the wound, and thus contributes
						to the suffocation and cough. And, moreover, if by any means they should
						escape the danger, the lips of the</p>
					<pb n="407"/>
					<p>wound do not coalesce; for they are both cartilaginous, and not of a nature
						to unite.<note n="2">On the Ancient History of Laryngotomy, see Paulus
							Ægineta, t. ii., pp. 301--303, Syd. Soc. Edit. I would avail myself of
							the present opportunity of bringing into the notice of my learned
							readers the very accurate and elegant edition of the Sixth Book of
							Paulus Ægineta, lately published in Paris by Dr. RＯ・Brian. As regards
							the text, it is everything that could be desired; and the translation
							which accompanies it is generally correct.</note> * * * * * * * * * * *
						* * * * * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="9">
					<head>CHAPTER VIII. CURE OF THE AFFECTIONS ABOUT THE COLUMELLA (OR
						UVULA).</head>
					<p>O<hi rend="smallcaps">F</hi> the affections which form about the <hi
							rend="ital">columella</hi>, some require to be treated by excision; but
						the surgical treatment of such cases does not come within the design of this
						work. Some are to be treated as acute affections; for some of them readily
						prove fatal by suffocation and dyspnœa. These are the diseases which we call
							<hi rend="ital">uva</hi> and <hi rend="ital">columella</hi>; for both
						are attended with inflammation and increase in thickness and length, so that
						the parts hang down, and come into the <hi rend="ital">arteria aspera.</hi>
						The <hi rend="ital">columna</hi> is of equal thickness from the base to the
						extremity in the palate: the <hi rend="ital">uva</hi> is of unequal
						thickness; for its base at the palate is slender, whereas at its extremity
						it is rounded and thick, with redness and lividity, whence it gets the
						appellation of <hi rend="ital">uva.</hi> These, then, must be speedily
						relieved; for the death from suffocation is very speedy.</p>
					<p>If, then, the patients be young, we must open the vein at the elbow, and
						evacuate copiously by a larger incision than usual;</p>
					<pb n="408"/>
					<p>for such an abstraction frees one from suffocation, as it were, from
						strangulation. It is necessary, also, to inject with a mild clyster, but
						afterwards with an acrid one, again and again, until one has drawn from the
						parts above by revulsion; and let ligatures be applied to the extremities
						above the ankles and knees, and above the wrists and forearms to the arms.
						But if the suffocation be urgent, we must apply a cupping-instrument to the
						occiput and to the thorax, with some scarifications, and also do everything
						described by me under synanche; for the mode of death is the same in both.
						We must also use the same medicines to the mouth, both astringents and
						emollients, with fomentation of the external parts, cataplasms, and
						liniments to the mouth. For the forms named <hi rend="ital">columella</hi>
						and <hi rend="ital">uva</hi>, as an astringent medicine take the juice of
						pomegranate, acacia dissolved in honey or water, hypocistis, Samian,
						Lemnian, or Sinopic earth, and the inspissated juice of sour grapes. But if
						the diseased part be ulcerated, gum and starch moistened in the decoction of
						roses or of dates, and the juice of ptisan or of spelt (<hi rend="ital"
							>tragus</hi>). But in <hi rend="ital">columella</hi> let there be more
						of the stronger medicines, from myrrh, costus,<note n="1"><hi rend="ital"
								>Auklandia Costus L.</hi> See Paulus Ægineta, t. iii. p.190.</note>
						and cyperus;<note n="2"><hi rend="ital">Cyperus rotundus L.</hi> See Paulus
							Ægineta, t. iii. p. 204.</note> for the <hi rend="ital">columella</hi>
						endures these acrid substances. But should the part suppurate, in certain
						cases even the bones of the palate have become diseased, and the patients
						have died, wasted by a protracted consumption. The remedies of these will be
						described elsewhere.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="10">
					<pb n="409"/>
					<head>CHAPTER IX. CURE OF THE PESTILENTIAL AFFECTIONS ABOUT THE PHARYNX.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> some respects, the treatment of these is the
						same as that of the other affections in the tonsils, and in some peculiar.
						In inflammation and suffocation, the remedies are clysters, venesection,
						liquid applications, cataplasms, fomentation, ligatures, cupping; and all
						these are applicable here. But anointing with more potent medicines is
						proper; for the ulcers do not stop, nor do eschars form on the surface. But
						if a sanies from them run inwardly, the parts, even if before in a healthy
						state, very soon become ulcerated, and very soon the ulcers spread inwardly,
						and prove fatal. It might be beneficial to burn the affection with fire, but
						it is unsuitable owing to the isthmus. But we must use medicines resembling
						fire to stop the spreading and also for the falling off of the eschars:
						these are alum, gall, the flowers of the wild pomegranate, either in a dried
						state or with honeyed-water. And the same medicines may be blown in by means
						of a reed, or quill, or a thick and long tube, so that the medicines may
						touch the sores. The best of these medicines is calcined chalcitis,<note
							n="1">Native Sulphate of Copper. See Paulus Ægineta, t. iii. pp. 401,
							402.</note> with cadmia<note n="2">Calamine. See Paulus Ægineta, t. iii.
							p. 150.</note> triturated in vinegar. Let there be a double proportion
						of the cadmia, and of the root of rhubarb, with some fluid. It is necessary,
						however, to guard against their pressure, for the ulcers thus get moist and
						spread farther. We must, therefore, sprinkle them in a dry state with a
						quill. But the liquid medicines, having been much diluted, are to be
						injected upon the columella. But if the eschars be already loosened, and the
						ulcers become red,</p>
					<pb n="410"/>
					<p>there is then most danger of convulsion; for generally the ulcers are dried
						up, and thereby tonic contractions of the nerves are induced. It is
						necessary then to soften and moisten by means of milk, with starch, and the
						juice of ptisan, or of tragus, or linseed, or the seed of fenugreek. In
						certain cases also the uvula has been eaten down to the bone of the palate
						and the tonsils to their base and epiglottis; and in consequence of the
						sore, the patient could neither swallow anything solid nor liquid; but the
						drink regurgitating has cut him off by starvation.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="11">
					<head>CHAPTER X. CURE OF PLEURISY.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> cases of Pleurisy there is no time for
						procrastination, nor for putting off the great remedy. For the fever, being
						very acute, hastens to a fatal termination; the pain also of the <hi
							rend="ital">succingens</hi> hurries on to the worse; and moreover coughs
						which agitate the chest and head exhaust the powers. Wherefore then, on the
						selfsame day we must by all means open a vein. But if it be in connection
						with repletion of food and drink, having kept the patient fasting for one
						day, we are to abstract blood from the vein in the hollow of the elbow, in a
						line with the opposite side, (for it is better to take it from a very great
						distance); but not to the extent of deliquium animi, for there is danger of
						Peripneumonia supervening if the body, being congealed, should leave the
						soul; for the fluids rush inward when deprived of their external heat and
						tension. For the Lungs are of loose texture, hot, and possessed of strong
						powers of attraction; the lungs also are the neighbours of the ribs,</p>
					<pb n="411"/>
					<p>and their associates in suffering; and this succession of disease is not
						readily recovered from; whereas in Pleuritis from Peripneumonia, recovery
						readily takes place, this combination being milder. It is necessary,
						therefore, after a moderate flow of blood, to recruit the patient for a
						time, and afterwards abstract again; if matters go on well, the same day,
						provided the remission be long; but if not, on the day following. But if
						there is no remission of the fever (for generally the fever prevails and
						increases for one day), we are to abstract blood the third day during the
						second remission, when also food is to be given--after having anointed the
						patient freely, having also applied to the side soft oil with the heating
						ointment of rue, or the decoction of dill. A very soothing fomentation is
						also to be applied to the side. In certain cases, the pain and inflammation
						are determined outwardly, so as to make it appear an affection of the parts
						there; but it is merely an exacerbation of the internal symptoms.</p>
					<p>Let us now treat of regimen, in order that, respecting all the system of
						treatment, there may be no mistake. "For in food will consist the medicines,
						but also the medicines in food." In kind, then, it is to be hot and humid,
						smooth and consistent, detergent, solvent, having the power of dissolving
						and attenuating phlegm. Of all kinds of food, therefore, ptisan is to be
						preferred; at the commencement, then, strained to its juice, so that the
						solid part of it may be separated; and made with honey only; and let the
						usual articles added to it for seasoning and variety be absent (for now the
						juice alone is sufficient). It will be calculated to moisten and warm, and
						able to dissolve and clear away phlegm, to evacuate upwards without pain
						such matters as should be brought up, and also readily evacuate the bowels
						downwards. For its lubricity is agreeable and adapted to deglutition.
						Moreover, its glutinous quality soothes heat, purges the membranes, concocts
						coughs, and softens all the parts. These are the virtues of</p>
					<pb n="412"/>
					<p>barley. The next place to it is held by chondrus,<note n="1">Spelt, <hi
								rend="ital">Triticum spelta</hi>, deprived of its husks and broken
							down into granules. See Paul. Ægin. t. i. p.123, Syd. Soc. Edit.</note>
						being possessed of some of the good qualities of ptisan. For in regard to
						its glutinous quality, its lubricity, and its appropriateness for
						deglutition, it is equal to the other, but in other respects inferior. They
						are to be made plain, with honey alone. The tragus also is excellent.<note
							n="2">The <hi rend="ital">tragus</hi> (called <hi rend="ital"
								>tragum</hi> by Pliny, H. N. xviii. 10) was a culinary preparation
							frym Spelt, and would seem to have been much the same as the <hi
								rend="ital">chondrus.</hi> See Galen, Comment. in lib. de ratione
							victus in morb. acut.</note> But rice is worse than these, inasmuch as
						it has the property of drying, roughening, and of stopping the purgation of
						the sides, rather than of making it more fluid. A very excellent thing is
						dry bread, broken into pieces, passed through a sieve, gently warmed, well
						concocted, which with honeyed-water is sufficient nourishment. But if the
						disease have already progressed, and the patient have given up his food, the
						ptisan of barley is to be administered in a soft state, and well boiled.
						Dill and salts are to be the condiments of the ptisan, and oil which is
						thin, without quality, without viscidity, without asperity; it is better,
						however, not to boil much of the oil with the ptisan; for thus the draught
						becomes fatty, and the oil loses its badness, and with much boiling is no
						longer perceptible, being drunk up by the juice. And let leek with its
						capillary leaves, and bitter almonds, be boiled with the juice of ptisan;
						for the draught thus promotes perspiration, and becomes medicinal, and the
						leeks eaten out of the juice are beneficial and very delicious. Now also is
						the season for using wholesome eggs; but if the expectoration be fluid and
						copious, sprinkle on them some native sulphur and natron. But the best thing
						of all is to give new-laid eggs which have never been subjected to the fire;
						for the heat of the hen is more humid than fire, and</p>
					<pb n="413"/>
					<p>more congenial to the patient, as proceeding from one animal to another. But
						if the phlegm be glutinous and viscid, pour oil into the eggs, and sprinkle
						some of the dried resin of pine--so that the sulphur may be more powerful;
						melting also with them some of the resin of turpentine; pepper also and all
						cognate substances are beneficial in eggs, and in all kinds of food; the
						extremities of animals melted down in soups, pigeons, boiled hens; the
						brains of swine roasted with the cawl, but without it they are not savoury.
						If the patient has no <hi rend="ital">râle</hi>, we must give him fish from
						the depth of the sea, or rock fish, the best which the country produces. And
						that the patient may not transgress in regimen, owing to his appetite, nor
						become wasted by a spare diet, he is to be gratified with some fruit; such
						as apples boiled in water, or honeyed-water, or stewed in suet (but we must
						take off the skin and rough parts within along with the seeds,); and in
						season we may give some figs. We must give likewise of any other kind of
						autumn fruit which is not only not hurtful but also beneficial. So much with
						regard to diet.</p>
					<p>Wool fumigated with sulphur and moistened with oil in which dill and rue have
						been boiled, is to be laid on the side. Foment the side constantly with
						these, and, before the administration of food, apply cataplasms, in addition
						to the usual ingredients containing melilot boiled with honeyed-water, and
						mixing therewith some of the fleshy part of the poppy in a boiled state, and
						sprinkling on it the meal of the manna thuris.<note n="3">See Paul. Ægin. t.
							iii. p. 241.</note> But if the expectoration be more fluid and copious,
						we are to mix the flour of darnel, or of hedge mustard, and sprinkle natron
						on it. But if the disease be prolonged, the pain having become fixed, and
						the purging liquid, it is to be apprehended that pus is about to form;
						wherefore mix with the cataplasms mustard and <hi rend="ital"
							>cachrys;</hi><note n="4">Probably the <hi rend="ital">Cachrys
								libanotis.</hi> See Dioscorides, M. M. iii. 78; and appendix to
							Dunbar's Greek Lexicon under <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>LIBANWTI/S</foreign>.</note></p>
					<pb n="414"/>
					<p>and if the patients have a feeling as if the internal parts were cold, some
						vinegar may be poured into it. The heat of the cataplasms should be of a
						strong kind, that it may last the longer; for this is better than having the
						heat kept up by renewal of the cataplasms. Let the fomentations consist of
						salts and millet in bags, or of warm oil in bladders. Every apparatus used
						for fomentation should be light, so that the weight may not add to the pain.
						These things moreover are to be used also after the food, if the pain be
						urgent.</p>
					<p>And, in addition to these means, now also should be the time of cupping; but
						it is best after the seventh day: before this you should not be urgent with
						it, for the diseases are not of a favourable character which require cupping
						before the seventh day. Let the instrument be large, broad every way, and
						sufficient to comprehend the place which is pained; for the pain does not
						penetrate inwardly, but spreads in width. There should be plenty of heat
						below the cupping-instrument, so as not only to attract, but also to warm
						before the extinction of the fire. And after the extinction, having
						scarified, we are to abstract as much blood as the strength will permit;
						much more than if you had to take away blood from the hypochondria for any
						other cause. For the benefit from cupping is most marked in cases of
						Pleurisy. But salts or natron are to be sprinkled on the scarifications, a
						pungent and painful practice indeed, but yet a healthful one. But we must
						estimate the powers and habits of the patient. For if strong in mind and
						robust in body, we must sprinkle some of the salts, not indeed so as to come
						into immediate contact with the wounds themselves, but they are to be
						sprinkled on a piece of linen-cloth damped with oil, and it is to be spread
						over the place; for the brine which runs from the melting of the salts is
						less stimulant than the salts themselves. We must also pour in much of the
						oil, that by its soothing properties it may obtund the pain occasioned by
						the acrimony of the other. On the second day it will be a very</p>
					<pb n="415"/>
					<p>good rule to apply the cupping-instrument again, so as that a thin sanies may
						be abstracted from the wounds. This, indeed, is much more effectual than the
						previous cupping, and much less calculated to impair the strength; for it is
						not blood, the nutriment of the body, but sanies that runs off. This then
						you are to do after having made a previous estimate of the strength. On the
						third day we are to apply cerate with the ointments of privet and of rue.
						But if the sputa still require purging, we are to melt into the cerates some
						resin, or mix some native sulphur therewith, and again the part is to have a
						fomentation. With regard to the form of the cupping-instrument, it should
						either be an earthen vessel, light, and adapted to the side, and capacious;
						or, of bronze, flat at the lips, so as to comprehend the parts affected with
						pain; and we are to place below it much fire along with oil, so that it may
						keep alive for a considerable time. But we must not apply the lips close to
						the skin, but allow access to the air, so that the heat may not be
						extinguished. And we must allow it to burn a long while, for the heat within
						it, indeed, is a very good fomentation, and a good provocative of
						perspirations.</p>
					<p>And we must not overlook purging downwards, in men injecting oil of rue into
						the gut, and, in women, also into the womb. And let something be constantly
						drunk and swallowed; for this purpose, honeyed-water, with rue and juice of
						ptisan, if there is a constant cough, as being a medicine in the food. But
						if it is not the season of administering food, let it be one of the compound
						preparations, such as butter boiled with honey to a proper consistence. Of
						this, round balls the size of a bean are to be given to hold under the
						tongue, moving them about hither and thither, so that they may not be
						swallowed entire, but melted there. The medicine also from poppies with
						honey and melilot is agreeable, being possessed of soothing and hypnotic
						properties. This is to be given before the administration of food, after it,
						and after sleep. To the patient when fasting, the following medicinal
						substances are</p>
					<pb n="416"/>
					<p>to be given: of nettle, of linseed, of starch, and of pine fruit in powder,
						of each, a cupful (<hi rend="ital">cyathus</hi>), and of bitter almonds
						twenty-five in number, and as many seeds of pepper. These things being
						toasted and triturated with honey, are to be mixed up into a linctus; of
						these the dose is one spoonful (<hi rend="ital">cochleare</hi>). But if he
						expectorate thin and unconcocted matters, two drams of myrrh, one of
						saffron, and fifteen grains of pepper to be mixed with one pound of honey.
						This medicine should be given also before the administration of food to the
						amount of half a spoonful. It is good also in chronic cases, when oxymel
						likewise is to be given if the dyspnœa be urgent.</p>
					<p>Such physicians as have given cold water to pleuritics, I cannot comprehend
						upon what principle they did so, nor can I approve the practice from
						experience; for if certain patients have escaped the danger from having
						taken cold water, these would appear to me not to have been pleuritic cases
						at all. But by the older physicians, a sort of congestion was called
						pleuritis, being a secretion of bile with pain of the side, attended with
						either slight fever or no fever at all. This affection, indeed, got the name
						of pleurisy, but it is not so in reality. But sometimes a spirit (or <hi
							rend="ital">wind, pneuma</hi>) collecting in the side, creates thirst
						and a bad sort of pain, and gentle heat; and this ignorant persons have
						called pleurisy. In them, then, cold water might prove a remedy through the
						good luck of the person using it; for the thirst may have been extinguished,
						and the bile and wind expelled downwards, while the pain and heat have been
						dissipated. But in inflammation of the side and swelling of the <hi
							rend="ital">succingeus</hi>, not only cold water but also cold
						respiration is bad.</p>
					<p>If, then, owing to the treatment formerly described persons affected with
						pleurisy survive the attack, but have still a short cough, and now and then
						are seized with heat, we must hasten to dissipate these symptoms; for the
						residue of the disease either produces a relapse, or it is converted into a
						suppuration.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="book" n="2">
				<pb n="419"/>
				<head>BOOK II.</head>
				<div type="chapter" n="1">
					<head>CHAPTER I. THE CURE OF PERIPNEUMONIA.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">NFLAMMATION</hi> and swelling of the lungs, and along
						with them a sense of suffocation, which does not long endure, constitute a
						very acute and fatal ailment. The remedies opposed to it, therefore, ought
						to be of equal power and speedily applied. We are to open instantly the
						veins at the elbow, and both together, on the right and on the left side,
						rather than abstract blood from one larger orifice, so that revulsion of the
						humours may take place from either side of the lungs: but we must not carry
						it to the extent of <hi rend="ital">deliquium animi</hi> for the <hi
							rend="ital">deliquium</hi> cooperates with the suffocation. But when
						even a small respite has been obtained, we must suppress the flow and
						abstraet more afterwards; for, if the exciting causes be from blood, the
						venesection carries them away; and if phlegm, or froth, or any other of the
						humours be the agent, the evacuations of the</p>
					<pb n="420"/>
					<p>veins widen the compass of the lungs for the passage of the breath.</p>
					<p>We must expel the fluids and flatus downwards, by anointing the anus after
						the venesection with natron, honey, rue, and the liquid resin from
						turpentine. Instead of the venesection,--provided there be a greater
						impediment,--we must give a clyster of acrid juice, namely, of salts, in
						addition to the natron, and turpentine resin with the honey; and rue boiled
						in the oil, and hyssop boiled in the water; and the fleshy parts of the wild
						cucumber, boiled with water, are very excellent.</p>
					<p>Dry-cupping applied to the back, the shoulder, and the hypochondria, is
						altogether beneficial. And if the chest be fleshy, so that the
						cupping-instrument may not by its pressure bruise the skin about the bones,
						it is to be also applied there; for if the humours be attracted from all
						parts of the body, and the spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) be
						determined outwardly, in those cases in which the lungs are, as it were,
						choked, there will be respite from the mischief; for peripneumonia is to be
						attacked in every possible way.</p>
					<p>But, likewise, neither are we to neglect any of the medicines which prove
						useful when swallowed by the mouth, for the lungs attract fluids whether
						they be in health or diseased. We must, therefore, give such medicines as
						attenuate the fluids so as to promote their perspiration, and such as will
						lubricate and render them adapted for expectoration. For speedy relief,
						then, natron is to be drunk with the decoction of hyssop, or brine with
						vinegar and honey; or mustard moistened with honeyed-water; and we may
						confidently sprinkle on each some of the root of iris and pepper. But also
						these things, having been sifted, are to be given in a powder along with
						honey. But if the patients get no sleep during the day, and remain sleepless
						also during all the night, it is to be feared lest they become delirious,
						and there will be</p>
					<pb n="421"/>
					<p>need of various soporific medicines unless the disease give way, so that the
						seasonable administration of these medicines may lull the suffering, for
						these things are usually soporific. But if you give a medicine at the acme
						of the suffocation, or when death is at hand, you may be blamed for the
						patient's death by the vulgar.</p>
					<p>The food also must be suitable, acrid, light, solvent of thick matters,
						detergent: of pot-herbs, the leek, or the cress, or the nettle, or the
						cabbage boiled in vinegar; of austere things (<hi rend="ital"
							>frumentacea?</hi>) the juice of ptisan, taking also of marjoram, or of
						hyssop, and of pepper, and more natron instead of the salts. Also spelt in
						grains well boiled with honeyed-water: in the course of the boiling, they
						should all be deprived of their flatulence, for flatulent things are hurtful
						to persons in peripneumonia. If they are free from fever, wine is to be
						given for drink, but not such as is possessed of much astringency, for
						astringency condenses bodies; but in these the parts are rather to be
						relaxed. We must also promote the expulsion of the sputa. On the whole the
						drink should be scanty, for drenching is prejudicial to the lungs, because
						the lungs attract from the stomach and belly.</p>
					<p>Let the chest be covered up in wool, with oil, natron, and salts. The best
						ointment is that prepared of the lemnestis, and dried mustard with liquid
						cerate; and, on the whole, we are to determine outwardly the fluids, the
						heat, and the spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>). And smelling to acrid
						things is beneficial, also anointings, and ligatures of the extremities.
						When these things are done, if the disease do not yield, the patient is in a
						hopeless condition.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="2">
					<pb n="422"/>
					<head>CHAPTER II. CURE OF THE BRINGING UP OF BLOOD.</head>
					<p>A<hi rend="smallcaps">LL</hi> the forms of the bringing up of blood are of an
						unmild character, not only as to mode, whether the flow proceed from
						rupture, erosion, or even rarefaction; and whether it come from the chest,
						the lungs, the stomach, or the liver, which are the most dangerous cases;
						but also from the head, although it occasions less mischief. For the flow is
						of blood; and blood is the food of all parts, the heat of all parts, and the
						colour of all parts. It is dreadful to see it flowing from the mouth in any
						way; but bad indeed if it proceed from an important viscus, and still worse
						if it proceed from rupture and erosion.</p>
					<p>It is necessary, therefore, that the physician should make the more haste in
						bringing assistance to this affection; and, in the first place, the patient
						must get coldish air to breathe, a chamber on the ground, and a couch firmly
						fixed, so that he may not be shaken (for all shaking is stimulant); the bed
						should be solid, not very yielding, nor deep, nor heated; his position
						erect; rest from speaking and hearing; tranquillity of mind, cheerfulness,
						since depression of spirits especially accompanies these cases; for who is
						there that does not dread death when vomiting blood?</p>
					<p>If, therefore, the patient be full of blood, and have large veins, in every
						form of rejection we must open a vein; whether it proceed from rupture, or
						erosion, venesection is very suitable; and even, if from rarefaction, there
						is danger, lest the fulness of blood burst forth.<note n="1">It is to be
							understood that by <hi rend="ital">rarefaction</hi> our author means
							exhalation; that is to say, increased action of the exhalants.</note>
						And we are to open the hollow vein at the elbow (for the blood flows readily
						from it, and it is easily opened, and the orifice can be safely kept
						open</p>
					<pb n="423"/>
					<p>for several days). In a word, then, in all the diseases of all the vital
						organs, this is the outlet of the blood. For the one higher up and this are
						both branches of the humeral, so that the one above can have no more
						remedial power than the mesal. They are ignorant of these divisions who have
						connected the upper vein with the stomach and liver. But if the flow proceed
						from the spleen, they direct us to open the vein of the left hand, which
						runs between the little finger and the one next the middle; for certain
						physicians held it to terminate in the spleen; but it is a branch of the
						vein below those at the elbow. Why, then, should we rather open the vein at
						the fingers than the one at the elbow? for there it is larger, and the blood
						flows readily from it. Altogether, then, we are to stop before coming to <hi
							rend="ital">deliquium animi.</hi> Yet neither, also, is much blood to be
						abstracted; for the hemorrhage itself is calculated to enfeeble the patient;
						but, after abstracting a small quantity, repeat the bleeding the same day,
						the next, and the day following. But if the patient be thin, and scantily
						supplied with blood, we must not open a vein. So much respecting the
						abstraction of blood.</p>
					<p>We are also to assist by means of ligatures to the extremities. Above the
						feet to the ankles and knees, and above the hands to the wrists and arms, a
						broad band is to be used, so that the constriction may be strong, and yet
						not produce pain. To the regions, also, from which the blood flows, we are
						to apply unwashed wool from the sheep; but moisten it with a liquid, such as
						austere wine, and the oils of roses and of myrtles. But if the hemorrhage be
						of an urgent nature, instead of the wool we are to use sponges, and vinegar
						instead of the wine, and let the part be anointed with myrtle oil; and we
						are to dust upon the sponges some of the dry inspissated juices, such as
						that of acacia, or of hypocistis, or else of aloes. The juice of the unripe
						grape, dissolved in vinegar, is also a very excellent thing. But if the
						liquid application be troublesome or</p>
					<pb n="424"/>
					<p>disagreeable, we are to use plasters; for these stretch the skin around, and
						press it, as it were, with the hand, and they are possessed of very strong
						powers as astringents and desiccants. In addition to these, there are very
						many others of tried efficacy; but the best are those which contain vinegar,
						and the expressed juice of ivy leaves, and asphaltos, and verdigris, alum,
						frankincense, myrrh, calcined copper, the squama æris, and such of the
						plasters as resemble these; or unscoured wool, or sponges damped in a small
						quantity of vinegar. But if the patients cannot bear the distension of the
						plasters, we are to make these things into an epitheme: fat dates, damped in
						dark austere wine, are pounded into a cake; then we are to sprinkle on it
						acacia in a soft state, and the rinds of pomegranate; these things having
						been all rubbed upon a rag, are applied to the chest. Barley-meal, moistened
						in wine or vinegar, or the fine flour of the dried lentil, sifted in a
						sieve, and made up with cerate or rose ointment, is to be applied; we are
						also to mix some of the root of the comfrey sifted. Another: Boil the roots
						of the wild prunes in vinegar, and having pounded into a cake, mix a little
						of sumach, and of gum, and of myrtle. These are to be mixed with one another
						differently, according as the strength of the medicines, mildness, or smell
						thereof is wanted. For we must also gratify the sick. These are the external
						remedies.</p>
					<p>But a more important part of the treatment lies in things drunk and
						swallowed, since these remedies come nearest the injured parts. Of these
						there are three distinct kinds: either they are calculated by the
						contraction or compression of the vessels to bind the passages of the flux;
						or to incrassate and coagulate the fluid, so that it may not flow, even if
						the passages were in a state to convey it; or to dry up the outlets, by
						retaining the blood in its pristine state, so that the parts may not thus
						remain emptied by the flux, but may regurgitate where the effusion is. For
						rarefaction of the veins, astringency</p>
					<pb n="425"/>
					<p>is sufficient, for it runs through the pores like a fluid when poured into a
						water-cask newly wetted. And also in the division of vessels stypticity is
						the remedy, by producing contraction of the lips; but for this purpose we
						must use the greater and more powerful medicines. But if the form of
						hemorrhage be that from erosion, and if the lips of the ulcer do not
						coalesce by the action of the astringents, but the wound gapes, and cannot
						be brought together by compression, we must produce congelation of the
						blood, and also of the heat; for the flow is stopped by the immobility and
						coagulation of these. To the rare parts, then, oxycrate is sufficient for
						producing astriction; for the fluid is not pure blood, but the sanies
						thereof from small orifices; and even of this medicine, there is no
						necessity of much being given, or frequently; and in certain cases, the
						external treatment is sufficient. So, likewise, the decoction of dates and
						of edible carobs, when drunk, has by itself proved sufficient. Let the
						vinegar be from wines of an astringent nature, and if not by pharmaceutical
						preparation, at all events let it be such as by time has become acrid and
						astringent. But in dilatations of the wounds, in addition to the oxycrate,
						let there be given the simple medicines at first, such as the juice of
						plantain, of knot-grass, or of endive; of each an equal part with the
						oxycrate. But if the flow increase, sprinkle on it one dram of the dried
						hypocistis, or of acacia, on three cupfuls of the oxycrate. The juice, also,
						of the wild grape is very excellent. But if the ailment prevail over this,
						sprinkle on it triturated gall, and the dried root of the bramble, and the
						sea stone, the coral, triturated and dried. But the root of rhubarb is more
						powerful than these to cool, to dry, to astringe; in short, for every
						purpose. But it is used with the oxycrate alone; or, if more powerful things
						are required, as a remedy. To the juices of endive with plantain we add some
						of the root, namely, three oboli of it to three or four cyathi of the fluid.
						But in crosions, we must produce astringency</p>
					<pb n="426"/>
					<p>even in it, so as to induce coagulation of the blood that flows, and also for
						the sake of the containing vessels, so that the veins which have sustained a
						large wound may shut their mouths. But the medicines which are drunk should
						be strong, and capable of inducing coagulation. Wherefore, give the juice of
						coriander with vinegar, and the rennet of a hare, or of a hind, or of a kid,
						but not in great quantity (for certain of these have proved fatal in a large
						dose); but of the juice of the coriander give not less than half a cyathus
						to three of the oxycrate, and of the rennet three oboli, or at most four.
						For such modes of the flow, the Samian earth is very excellent, and the very
						white Aster, and the Eretrian, and the Sinopic, and the Lemnian seal: of
						these, at least, one dram weight, and at most three, with some of the
						decoctions, as of dates, or of edible carobs, or of the roots of brambles.
						But if there be roughness of the windpipe, and cough along with it, we must
						sprinkle these things on Cretic rob. Starch, dissolved in these, is a most
						excellent thing for lubricating the windpipe; for along with its power of
						lubricating, it also possesses that of agglutinating. If, therefore, the
						flow of blood be not urgent, it must be given once a day, before the
						administration of food; but if it be urgent, also a second and third time in
						the evening. And from the medicines are to be made draughts of the dried
						substances with honey, boiled to the proper consistence; galls pulverised:
						and a very good thing is sumach for the condiments, also grape-stones, and
						the fruit of the sharp dock, either each by itself, or all together. These
						things, moreover, are good to be kept below the tongue during the whole time
						of melting; but likewise common gum with the plant, (?) and the gum
						tragacanth. The compound medicines of tried efficacy are infinite; and
						various are the usages of trochisks--of that from Egyptian thorn, of another
						from amber, and another named from saffron, of which the composition has
						been described separately.</p>
					<pb n="427"/>
					<p>In the absence of fevers, everything is to be attempted in regard to
						medicines, giving them copiously and frequently. But if fever come on--and
						most frequently fever takes place, along with inflammations of the
						wounds--we must not stop the flow suddenly, nor give medicines during the
						paroxysms, for many die sooner of the fevers than of the flow of blood.</p>
					<p>The articles of food are various in kind like the medicines, but also "the
						medicines are in the food;" for neither would it be easy to find all the
						good properties of food in any one article, nor even if a solitary thing
						were sufficient for the cure, should one only be used, as one would thus
						readily produce satiety; but we must grant variety if the disease should
						prove prolonged. Let the food, then, be astringent and refrigerant in
						properties, as also to the touch, for heat encourages bleeding. Washed
						alica; rice added to oxycrate; but if the vinegar excite coughing, the
						decoction of dates; baked bread which has been dried and pounded down to
						meal, and sifted. Of all these things a draught is to be made with oil;
						savory seasoned with salts, and sumach to be sprinkled upon it. And if you
						wish to gratify the patient's palate, let coriander be added, for this
						purpose, whenever it is agreeable, or any of the diuretic and diffusible
						seeds. Lentil, then, with the juice of plantain, if the hemorrhage be
						urgent, but if not, we should spare the juice, for neither is it of easy
						digestion, nor pleasant to the taste; for in these cases we must not give
						indigestible things. But if you apprehend death from the hemorrhage, you
						must also give what is unpalatable and indigestible; nay, let even harsh
						things be given if they will preserve life; wherefore, let galls, dried and
						pulverised, be sprinkled when dry, and cold lentil: eggs thick from boiling,
						with the seeds of pomegranate or galls, for the food necessarily consists in
						the medicines. The drink altogether should be scanty, since liquids are
						incompatible with a dry diet. These are the proper things, provided you wish
						to astringe and cool. But if</p>
					<pb n="428"/>
					<p>you wish also to thicken the blood and spirit (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>),
						milk along with starch and granulated spelt (<hi rend="ital">chondrus</hi>),
						the milk being sometimes given with the starch, and sometimes with the <hi
							rend="ital">chondrus</hi>; they should be boiled to such a consistence
						as that the draught may not be liquid. But if you wish to incrassate and
						astringe still more, let the <hi rend="ital">chondrus</hi> be boiled with
						dates, and for the sake of giving consistence, let there be starch and milk;
						and the Tuscan <hi rend="ital">far</hi> is a very excellent thing, being
						thick, viscid, and glutinous when given along with the milk; the rennet of
						the kid is to be added to the liquid decoctions for the sake of coagulation,
						so that with the milk, it attains the consistency of new cheese: still
						thicker than these is millet boiled with milk like the <hi rend="ital"
							>far</hi>, having gall and pomegranate rind sprinkled on it as a powder.
						But we must look to the proportions of the desiccants and incrassants, for
						all these things provoke coughing, and in certain cases, from excess of
						desiccant powers, they have burst the veins. But if things turn out well,
						and the blood is stopped, we must gradually change to the opposite plan of
						treatment, "and nothing in excess," for these cases are apt to relapse, and
						are of a bad character. We must also strive to put flesh and fat on the
						patient by means of gestation, gentle frictions, exercise on foot,
						recreation, varied and suitable food.</p>
					<p>These are the means to be used if, after the flow of blood, the wound adhere
						and the part heal properly. But if the ulcer remain and become purulent,
						another plan of treatment is needed, for a discharge of different matters
						succeeds. This, however, will be treated of among the chronic diseases.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="3">
					<pb n="429"/>
					<head>CHAPTER III. THE CURE OF CARDIAC AFFECTIONS.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> Syncope, it is necessary that the physician
						should exercise fore-knowledge; for, if you foresee its approach, and if
						things present co-operate strongly with you,<note n="1">Allusion is here
							made to Hippocrates Aph. i. In the Aphorism it is "the attendants and
							externals" (<foreign xml:lang="grc">TOU\S PARE/ONTAS KAI\ TA\
								E)/XWQEN</foreign>), which our author condenses into "things
							present" (<foreign xml:lang="grc">TA\ PARE/ONTA</foreign>); and this is
							no doubt the reason why in this instance the neuter plural is construed
							with a verb plural. See the text.</note> you may avert it before its
						arrival. When it is come on, patients do not readily escape from it, for I
						have said that syncope is the dissolution of nature; and nature when
						dissolved cannot be restored. We must try to prevent it then, when still
						impending, or if not, at the commencement. We must form our prognosis from
						the circumstances stated by us among the acute diseases, where we have
						described the cause and also the symptoms. The fever Causus, then, is the
						commencement of the attack, and with Causus the worst of symptoms, dryness,
						insomnolency, heat of the viscera, as if from fire, but the external parts
						cold; the extremities, that is to say, the hands and feet, very cold;
						breathing slowly drawn; for the patients desiderate cold air, because they
						expire fire: pulse small, very dense, and trembling. Judging from these and
						the other things stated by me among the symptoms, you will immediately give
						assistance at the commencement.</p>
					<p>Unless, then, when everything is against it, the habit, the age, the season,
						the timidity of the patient, we must open a vein, and even if many symptoms
						contra-indicate it, but an especial one require it, such as the tongue
						rough, dry, and black (for it is indicative of all the internal parts). And
						in</p>
					<pb n="430"/>
					<p>all cases we must form an estimate of the strength, whether or not it has
						failed owing to the pains of the disease and the regimen; for the loss of
						strength takes place, not only from deficiency, but also from smothering;
						and if the syncope arise from redundancy, and if inflammation of the
						hypochondria, or of the liver strongly indicate, there is no necessity for
						deferring the bleeding. We are to open the hollow vein at the elbow, and
						abstract the blood by a small orifice, that it may not have a marked effect
						on the strength; for sudden depletion tries the natural strength: and we
						must take away much less than if from any other cause; for in syncope, even
						a slight mistake readily sends a man to the regions below. We must,
						therefore, immediately give food for the restoration of the strength; for
						Nature delights in the removal of the old, and in the supply of new
						things.</p>
					<p>But if the strength reject venesection, and inflammations be present, we must
						apply the cupping-instrument to the seat thereof a considerable time
						previous to the crisis of the disease; for the crisis takes place at the
						critical periods; since at the same periods Nature brings on a favourable
						crisis, and diseases prove fatal. And if the patient should come to such a
						state as to require wine, it is not very safe to take wine in inflammations;
						for, wine to persons labouring under inflammation is an increase of the
						pains, but to those free from inflammation it is an increase of the natural
						strength. A day or two before the cupping there is need of cataplasms, both
						in order to produce relaxation of the parts and to procure a flow of blood;
						and in certain cases, after the cupping, we are to apply a cataplasm on the
						next day. In this, too, let there be moderation; for there is the same
						danger from the abstraction of too much blood by cupping. Use clysters only
						for removing scybala which have long lodged in the bowels; but spare the
						strength.</p>
					<p>Cold lotions to the head, such as have been directed by me</p>
					<pb n="431"/>
					<p>under Phrenitis, but somewhat more liberally. Pure air, rather cooler than
						otherwise, for respiration. The delight of the sight is to be studied as to
						plants, painting, waters, so that everything may be regarded with pleasure.
						The conversation of attendants cheerful; silence and cheerfulness on the
						part of the patient. Smells fragrant, not calculated to prove heavy to the
						senses in the head. And let the articles of food also possess a fragrant
						smell, such as flour moistened with water or vinegar; bread hot, and newly
						baked. The mouth not to be very often rinsed with wine, nor is it to be
						altogether rejected.</p>
					<p>Drink to be given more frequently and more copiously than in other
						complaints. Food every day, light, digestible, mostly from grain, and that
						which is pleasant, even if somewhat less suitable. For, in these cases,
						rather than in any other, the palate is to be gratified, since not unusually
						the disease is generated in the stomach, so as to occasion resolution
						thereof. Abstinence or famine by no means; for the disease is sufficient to
						devour up all. But if the period be already come to a crisis, if there be a
						dew on the clavicle and forehead, the extremities cold; the pulse very small
						and very frequent, as if creeping, and feeble in tone, the patient must take
						a little food, and partake of wine effectually. The head, too, is to be
						strengthened by lotions, as also the bladder. These remedies have been
						described by me under Phrenitis. We are to give wine, not copiously nor to
						satiety, for certain patients by unseasonable repletion have died of
						anorexia, and inability to eat and drink; and to many patients having a good
						appetite, when the natural powers were dissolved, the abundant supply of
						food was of no avail; the food descending, indeed, into the stomach, but not
						ascending from the belly to recruit the strength. Let the food, therefore,
						be diversified, for the most part from grain, so as that it may be supped
						rather than masticated; or if solid, let it be made easy to</p>
					<pb n="432"/>
					<p>swallow. Eggs, not quite consistent nor roasted whole, but deprived of their
						solid portion; two or three pieces of bread soaked in wine, at first hot;
						but, after these, everything cold, unless there be latent inflammations. The
						wine is to be fragrant, and not very astringent; but by no means thick. Of
						the Greek wines, the Chian or Lesbian, and such other of the insular wines
						as are thin; of the Italian, the Surrentine, or Fundan, or Falernian, or
						Signine, unless it be very astringent; but of these we must reject such as
						are very old or very young. It is to be given at first hot, to the amount of
						not less than four cyathi, before the crisis, nor more than a hemina even if
						the patient be accustomed to drink. But after these things, having given
						food, if the symptoms of inflammation be past, we are again to give it cold
						as if for a remedy of the thirst; but this from necessity, and not by
						itself, but along with the food. We must also take care that the wine do not
						affect the brain; and after this, abstain. And if after an interval, he wish
						to sleep, quiet is to be enforced. But if much sweat flow, the pulse come to
						a stop, the voice become sharp, and the breast lose its heat, we are to give
						as much wine as the patient can drink. For those who are cold, wine is the
						only hope of life. Wine, therefore, if the patient be accustomed to it, is
						sometimes to be taken in drink, and sometimes food is to be eaten with the
						wine, after an interval, as a respite from the fatigue induced by the
						disease and the food, for when the strength is small, they are much
						fatigued, even by the act of taking food. Wherefore the patient must be
						stout-hearted and courageous, and the physician must encourage him with
						words to be of good cheer, and assist with diversified food and drink.</p>
					<p>The other treatment is also to be applied energetically for restraining the
						sweats, and for resuscitating the spark of life. Let, therefore, an epitheme
						be applied to the chest on the left mamma,--dates triturated in wine along
						with aloes and</p>
					<pb n="433"/>
					<p>mastich,--and let these things be mixed up with a cerate composed of
							nard.<note n="2">No doubt the Indian nard, namely, <hi rend="ital"
								>Patrinia Jatamansi</hi>, Don.</note> And if this become
						disagreeable, we may apply another epitheme, made by taking the seed, and
						whatever is hard out of the apples, and having bruised them down, mix up
						with some fragrant meal; then we are to mix together some of the hair of
						wormwood, and of myrtle, and of acacia, and of the manna of frankincense,
						all sifted; which being all rubbed up together, are to be added to the
						cerate of wild vine. But if the sweat be not thereby restrained, the juice
						of the wild grape is to be added to the mixture, and acacia, and gum, and
						the edible part of sumach, and alum, and dates, and the scented juice of
						roses. All these things along with nard and oil of wild vine are to be
						applied to the chest; for this at the same time cools and is astringent. Let
						him lie in cool air, and in a house having a northern exposure; and if the
						cool breeze of Boreas breathe upon him, "it will refresh his soul sadly
						gasping for breath." The prospect should be to-wards meadows, fountains, and
						babbling streams, for the sweet exhalations from them, and the delightful
						view, warm the soul and refresh nature. And, moreover, it is also an
						incentive to eat and to drink. But if from want one is not fortunate enough
						to possess these things, we must make an imitation of the cool breeze, by
						fanning with the branches of fragrant boughs, and, if the season of spring,
						by strewing the ground with such leaves and flowers as are at hand. The
						coverlet should be light and old, so as to admit the air, and permit the
						exhalation of the heat of the chest; the best kind is an old linen sheet. We
						are to sprinkle the neck, the region of the clavicle and chest with flour,
						so that it may nourish by its fragrance, and restrain by its dryness; and
						the spongy parts of the body are to be dusted with meal, but the face with
						the Samian earth, which is to be passed through a sieve; and</p>
					<pb n="434"/>
					<p>having been bound into a spongy cloth, it is to be dusted on the part, so
						that the finer particles may pass through the pores to the forehead and
						cheeks. And slaked lime and roasted gypsum, sifted in a small sieve, are to
						be applied to the moist parts. A sponge out of cold water applied to the
						face has sometimes stopped the sweats, by occasioning congelation of the
						running fluids, and by condensation of the pores. The anus is to be
						anointed, so that the flatus arising from the cold and food may be
						discharged. And we are to recall the heat of the extremities by
							gleucinum,<note n="3">A fragrant oil prepared from must. See Paulus
							Ægineta, t.iii. p. 596.</note> or Sicyonian oil, along with pepper,
						castor, natron, and cachry,<note n="4">The fruit of the <hi rend="ital"
								>Cachrys libanotis, L.</hi> See Dioscorides, iii. 79.</note> melting
						into them a little wax, so that the liniment may stick. And we are to
						resuscitate the heat by means of the ointment of lemnestis, and of
						euphorbium, and of the fruit of the bay. The small red onions raw, along
						with pepper, and the powdered lees of vinegar, make an excellent cataplasm
						to the feet; but it is to be constantly raised from the place every hour,
						for there is danger of ulceration and blisters. From these things there is
						hope that the patient may thus escape.</p>
					<p>And if the physician should do everything properly, and if everything turn
						out well, along with the syncope the inflammations that supervene are
						resolved; and sweat, indeed, is nowhere, but a restoration of the heat
						everywhere, even at the extremities of the feet and the nose; but the face
						is of a good colour; pulse enlarged in magnitude, not tremulous, strong;
						voice the same as customary, loud, and in every respect lively. Lassitude
						not out of place, but the patient is also seen sleeping: and, if sleep seize
						him, he digests his food, recovers his senses, and sprouts out into a new
						nature; and if roused from sleep, the breathing is free, he is light</p>
					<pb n="435"/>
					<p>and vigorous; and here calls to his memory the circumstances of the disease
						like a dream.</p>
					<p>But in other cases obscure fevers are left behind, and sometimes slight
						inflammations, and a dry tongue: they are parched, have rigors, are
						enfeebled, and relaxed, in which cases there is a conversion to marasmus;
						when we must not waste time with rest and a slender diet, but have recourse
						to motions, by gestation, and to friction and baths, so that the embers of
						life may be roused and mended. We are to give milk, especially that of a
						woman who has just borne a child, and that a male child; for such persons
						require nursing like new-born children. Or if it cannot be obtained, we must
						give the milk of an ass which has had a foal not long before, for such milk
						is particularly thin;<note n="4">The author appears to refer to the common
							way of trying the specific gravity of milk, by pouring a small quantity
							on the nail. See Paulus Ægineta, i. 3, Syd. Soc. Ed.</note> and by these
						means the patient is to be brought back to convalescence and his accustomed
						habits.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="4">
					<head>CHAPTER IV. CURE OF CHOLERA.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> Cholera, the suppression of the discharges is a
						bad thing, for they are undigested matters. We must, therefore, readily
						permit them to go on, if spontaneous, or if not, promote them by giving some
						tepid water to swallow, frequently indeed, but in small quantity, so that
						there may be no spasmodic retchings excited in the stomach. But if there
						also be tormina and coldness of the feet, we are to rub the abdomen with hot
						oil, boiled with rue and cumin, to dispel the flatulence; and we are to
						apply wool. And, having anointed the feet, they are to</p>
					<pb n="436"/>
					<p>be gently rubbed, stroking them rather than pinching them. And these things
						are to be done up to the knees for the restoration of the heat; and the same
						is to be practised until the fæces pass downwards, and the bilious matters
						ascend upwards.</p>
					<p>But if all the remains of the food have been discharged downwards, and if
						bile be evacuated, and if there still be bilious vomiting, retchings, and
						nausea, uneasiness and loss of strength, we must give two or three cupfuls
							(<hi rend="ital">cyathi</hi>) of cold water, as an astringent of the
						belly, to stop the reflux, and in order to cool the burning stomach; and
						this is to be repeatedly done when what even has been drunk is vomited. The
						cold water, indeed, readily gets warm in the stomach, and then the stomach
						rejects it, annoyed as it is both by hot and cold: but it constantly
						desiderates cold drink.</p>
					<p>But, if the pulse also fall to a low state, and become exceedingly rapid and
						hurried, if there be sweat about the forehead and region of the clavicles,
						if it run in large drops from all parts of the body, and the discharge from
						the bowels is not restrained, and the stomach still vomits, with retchings
						and deliquium animi, we must add to the cold water a small quantity of wine,
						which is fragrant and astringent, that it may refresh the senses by its <hi
							rend="ital">bouquet</hi>, contribute to the strength of the stomach by
						its spirit, and to the restoration of the body by its nutritious powers. For
						wine is swiftly distributed upwards over the system, so as to restrain the
						reflux; and is subtil, so that when poured into the frame it strengthens the
						habit, and it is strong so as to restrain the dissolving powers. We are also
						to sprinkle on the body some fresh and fragrant meal. But if the bad
						symptoms become urgent, with sweating, and strainings, not only of the
						stomach, but also of the nerves, and if there be hiccups; and if the feet
						are contracted, if there be copious discharges from the bowels, and if the
						patient become dark-eoloured, and the pulse is</p>
					<pb n="437"/>
					<p>coming to a stop, we must try to anticipate this condition beforehand; but if
						it be come on, we must give much cold water and wine, not indeed wine
						slightly diluted, for fear of intoxication, and of hurting the nerves, and
						along with food, namely, pieces of bread soaked in it. We are likewise to
						give of other kinds of food, such as have been described by me under
						syncope, autumnal fruit of an astringent nature, services, medlars, quinces,
						or the grape.</p>
					<p>But if everything be vomited, and the stomach can contain nothing, we must
						return again to hot drink and food, for in certain cases the change stops
						the complaint; the hot things, moreover, must be intensely so. But if none
						of these things avail, we are to apply the cupping-instrument between the
						shoulder-blades, and turn it below the umbilicus; but we are to shift the
						cupping-instrument constantly, for it is painful when it remains on a place,
						and exposes to the risk of blistering. The motion of gestation is beneficial
						by its ventilation, so as to recreate the spirit (<hi rend="ital"
							>pneuma</hi>), stay the food in the bowels, and make the patient's
						respiration and pulse natural.</p>
					<p>But if these symptoms increase, we must apply epithemes over the stomach and
						chest; and these are to be similar to those for syncope--dates soaked in
						wine, acacia, hypocistis, mixed up with rose cerate, and spread upon a linen
						cloth, are to be applied over the stomach; and to the chest we are to apply
						mastich, aloe, the pulverised hair of wormwood, with the cerate of nard, or
						of wild vine, as a cataplasm to the whole chest; but if the feet and muscles
						be spasmodically distended, rub into them Sicyonian oil, that of must, or
						old oil with a little wax; and also add in powder some castor. And if the
						feet also be cold, we are to rub them with the ointment containing lemnestis
						and euphorbium, wrap them in wool, and rectify by rubbing with the hands.
						The spine also, the tendons, and muscles of the jaws are to be anointed with
						the same.</p>
					<pb n="438"/>
					<p>If, therefore, by these means the sweat and discharges from the bowels are
						stopped, and the stomach receives the food without vomiting it again, the
						pulse becomes large and strong, and the straining ceases; if the heat
						prevails everywhere, and reaches the extremities, and sleep concocts all
						matters, on the second or third day the patient is to be bathed, and
						remitted to his usual course of living. But if he vomit up everything, if
						the sweat flow incessant, if the patient become cold and livid, if his pulse
						be almost stopped and his strength exhausted, it will be well in these
						circumstances to try to make one's escape with credit.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="5">
					<head>CHAPTER V. CURE OF ILEUS.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> Ileus it is pain that kills, along with
						inflammation of the bowels, or straining and swelling. A most acute and most
						disgusting form of death! For others, when in a hopeless state of illness,
						fear nothing except their impending death; but those in ileus, from excess
						of pain earnestly desire death. The physician, therefore, must neither be
						inferior to the affection, nor more dilatory; but, if he find inflammation
						to be the cause, open a vein at the elbow by a large orifice, so that blood,
						which is the pabulum of the inflammation, may flow copiously; and it may be
						carried the length of deliquium animi, for this is either the commencement
						of an escape from pain, or of a torpor ending in insensibility. For in ileus
						a breathing-time for a short space, even from loss of sensibility, will
						prove an interval from pain; since, also, to persons enduring these pains,
						to die is happiness, but to impart it is not permitted to the respectable
						physician; but at times it is permitted, when</p>
					<pb n="439"/>
					<p>he foresees that present symptoms cannot be escaped from, to lull the patient
						asleep with narcotics and anæsthetics.</p>
					<p>But if the ileus arise without inflammation, from corruption of the food or
						intense cold, we are to abstain from bleeding, but at the same time to do
						all the other things, and procure vomiting frequently by water, and drinking
						plenty of oil; then, again, we are to procure vomiting, and produce the
						expulsion of the flatus downwards, by stimulant medicines. Such a stimulant
						is the juice of sow-bread, and natron, or salts. Cumin and rue are
						carminatives. Wherefore we must rub in together all these things with
						turpentine resin, and foment with sponges; or we must inject with these
						things and oil, honey, hyssop, and the decoction of the fleshy parts of the
						wild cucumber. And if feculent matter be evacuated, we are again to inject
						hot oil with rue; for, if this remain inwardly, it proves a grateful
						fomentation to the bowels: and apply to the suffering parts lotions composed
						of oil which has been strongly boiled with rue and dill. And the fomentation
						is also to be applied, either by means of earthen or brazen vessels, or with
						millet and roasted salts. In addition to the ordinary cataplasms, one may be
						made of the flour of darnel and cumin, and the hair of hyssop and of
						marjoram. Cupping, without the abstraction of blood, indeed, but frequently
						applied, sometimes to one place, and sometimes to another--to the epigastric
						region, and to the loins as far as the groins, and behind to the ischiatic
						region as far as the kidneys and spine; for it is expedient to produce
						revulsion of the pain by all means. They should also get whetters (<hi
							rend="ital">propomata</hi><note n="1">See Bekker's Charicles, p. 248;
							and Paulus Ægineta, t. iii. p. 546.</note>) of the decoction of cumin,
						or of rue, and of sison;<note n="2">The <hi rend="ital">Sison amomum</hi>,
							Stone parsley, or German amomum. See Dioscorid. M. M. iii. 57; Galen. de
							Simpl.vii.; and Paulus Ægineta, t. iii. p. 339.</note> or along with
						these some of the anodyne medicines. Of these there are very</p>
					<pb n="440"/>
					<p>many of tried efficacy. The medicine from vipers is also a good one, when
						drunk to a larger amount than usual. But if neither the pain remit, nor the
						flatulence nor fæces pass, we must necessarily give of the purgative hiera;
						for either the medicine is rejected with phlegm and bile, or it passes
						downwards, bringing off flatus, scybala, phlegm, and bile, which occasion
						the intensity of the evil. Laxative food: soups of hens, of shell-fish; the
						juice of ptisan boiled with much oil poured in at first before the boiling;
						boil along with it cumin, natron, leek with its hair. Or the cure is to be
						made with some laxative soup: snails much boiled, and their gravy, or that
						of limpet. Water is to be taken for drink, if there be fever, boiled with
						asarabacca, or nard, or cachry. For these things dispel flatus, are
						diuretic, and promote free breathing. But if he be free from pain, wine also
						is beneficial for the heat of the intestines, and for the restoration of the
						strength; and likewise the decoction of fennel-root, in a draught, and
						maiden-hair and cinnamon.</p>
					<p>But if the inflammation turn to an abscess, it is better to contribute
						thereto by using the medicine for abscesses. These have been described under
						chronic diseases, where the treatment of cholics is described.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="6">
					<head>CHAPTER VI. CURE OF THE ACUTE AFFECTIONS ABOUT THE LIVER.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> formation of the blood is in the liver, and
						hence the distribution of it over the whole system. And the entire liver is,
						as it were, a concretion of blood. Wherefore the inflammations there are
						most acute; for nutrition is seated in this</p>
					<pb n="441"/>
					<p>place. If, therefore, inflammation form anywhere else, it is not remarkably
						acute; for it is an influx of blood that is inflamed; but in the liver there
						is no necessity for its coming from another quarter. For if any obstruction
						shut the outlets, the liver becomes inflamed by being deprived of its
						efflux, since the entrance of the food to the liver still continues patent;
						for there is no other passage of the food but this from the stomach and
						intestines to the whole body.</p>
					<p>It is necessary, therefore, to make a copious evacuation, by opening the
						veins at the elbow, and taking away blood frequently, but not in large
						quantity at a time. Total abstinence from food at first, but restricted diet
						afterwards, so that the liver may be devoid of its customary ingesta. It is
						necessary, also, by external applications to dispel the matters impacted in
						the liver. Lotions, therefore, with aloe or natron are proper, and unwashed
						wool is to be applied. There is need, then, of cooling means, because the
						liver is inflamed by the blood; for the blood is hot. The cataplasms, also,
						should be of such a nature, consisting of the meal of darnel, or of
						hedge-mustard, or of barley, or of linseed; and of liquid substances, such
						as acid wine, the juice of apples, of the tendrils of the vine, or of the
						leaves of the vine in season, or of the oil prepared with it. Fomentations
						are to be applied on sponges, of the decoction of the fruit of bays, of the
						lentisk, of penny-royal, and of iris.</p>
					<p>When you have soothed by these means, you must apply a cupping-instrument,
						unusually large, so as to comprehend the whole hypochondriac region, and
						make deeper incisions than usual, that you may attract much blood. And, in
						certain cases, leeches are better than scarifications; for the bite of the
						animal sinks deeper, and it makes larger holes, and hence the flow of blood
						from these animals is difficult to stop. And when the animals fall off quite
						full, we may apply the cupping-instrument, which then attracts the matters
						within. And</p>
					<pb n="442"/>
					<p>if there be sufficient evacuation, we are to apply styptics to the wounds;
						but these not of a stimulant nature, such as spiders' webs, the manna of
						frankincense, and aloe, which are to be sprinkled in powder on the part; or
						bread boiled with rue or melilot, and the roots of marsh-mallow; but on the
						third day a cerate, made with nut-ben, or the hairy leaves of wormwood and
						iris. The malagmata should be such as are calculated to attenuate, rarify,
						or prove diuretic. Of these the best is that "from seeds" (<hi rend="ital"
							>diaspermatôn</hi>) well known to all physicians from experience. That
						also is a good one of which marjoram and melilot are ingredients.</p>
					<p>The food should be light, digestible, possessed of diuretic qualities, and
						which will quickly pass through the bowels; such as granulated seeds of
						spelt (<hi rend="ital">alica</hi><note n="1">See, in particular, Dr.
							Daremberg's elaborate dissertation on the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>XO/NDROS</foreign>, ap. Oribasium, t.i. p. 559.</note>) with
						honeyed-water, and a draught of these articles with salts and dill. The
						juice of ptisan, also, is detergent; and if you will add some of the seeds
						of carrot, you will make it more diuretic: for it evacuates by the passages
						which lead from the liver to the kidneys; and this is the most suitable
						outlet for matters passing out from the liver, owing to the wideness of the
						vessels and the straightness of the passage. We must also attract thither by
						cupping, applying the instrument to the region of the kidneys in the loins.
						To these parts, lotions are also to be applied, prepared with rue, the
						juncus, or calamus aromaticus. By these means, it is to be hoped that the
						patient may escape death.</p>
					<p>But when it is turning to a suppuration, we must use the suppurative
						medicines which will be described by me under the head of colics. But if pus
						is formed, how the collection is to be opened, and how treated, will be
						explained by me in another place. The same observations apply to the spleen,
						in the event of an inflammation seizing this part also.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="7">
					<pb n="443"/>
					<head>CHAPTER VII. CURE OF THE ACUTE DISEASE OF THE DORSAL VEIN AND
						ARTERY.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> inflammation of the <hi rend="ital">vena
							cava</hi> and large artery, which extend along the spine, was called a
						species of Causus by those of former times. For in these cases the
						affections are similar: febrile heat acute and acrid, loathing of food,
						thirst, restlessness; a palpitating pulsation in the hypochondriac region
						and in the back, and the other symptoms described by me under this head.
						Moreover, the febrile heat tends to syncope, as in cases of causus. For,
						indeed, the liver is formed by the roots of the veins, and the heart is the
						original of the artery. You may suppose, then, that the upper portions of
						these viscera are subject to fatal ailments; for it is the heart which
						imparts heat to the artery, and the liver which conveys blood to the vein;
						and being both mighty parts, the inflammations, likewise, which spring from
						them are great.</p>
					<p>Wherefore we are to open the veins at the elbow, and abstract a considerable
						amount of blood; not all at once, however, but at two or three times, and on
						a different day, so that the strength may recruit during the interval. Then
						we are to apply a cupping-instrument and cataplasms to the hypochondrium,
						where is the pulsation of the artery; and also between the scapulæ, for
						there, too, there are pulsations. We are to scarify unsparingly, and
						abstract much blood; for from this sort of evacuation the patients are not
						much prone to deliquium. The bowels, also, are apt to be unusually confined,
						and emollient clysters are to be used to lubricate them, but not on any
						account acrid ones; for they suffer an increase of fever from brine and the
						melting of the natron. The juice, therefore, of linseed and of fenugreek,
						and the decoction of the roots of</p>
					<pb n="444"/>
					<p>mallows, are sufficient to rouse and stimulate the bowels. The extremities,
						namely, the feet and hands, are to be warmed with gleucinum,<note n="1">The
							ointment or oil from must. See Paulus Ægineta, t.iii. p.596.</note> or
						Sicyonian oil, or with the liniment from lemnestis; for these parts of them
						become very cold. And before the administration of food, we must give
						draughts to promote the urinary discharge, containing spignel, asarabacca,
						and wormwood, to which some natron in powder is to be added. But of all such
						medicines the strongest are cassia and cinnamon, provided one has plenty of
						it. In such cases, milk is both food and medicine; for they stand in need of
						refrigeration, a sort of fire being wrapped up within; and also of sweet
						food, and of that a copious supply in small bulk. Such virtues milk
						possesses as an article of food. Plenty of the milk of an ass which has just
						had a foal is to be given, and to two cupfuls of the milk one of water is to
						be added. That of the cow is also very good; and, thirdly, that of a goat.
						The articles of food should be of easy digestion; for the most part juices,
						such as that from the juice of the fennel; and let parsley seed be added to
						it, and honey. And the water which is drunk should contain these things.</p>
					<p>But we must also promote sweats, and in every way make the perspiration moist
						and free. Lotions to the head, as in cases of causus. An epitheme to the
						chest and left mamma, such as in syncope. To lie in bed with the head
						elevated, so that everything may be alike as in causus. Gestation to a small
						extent, so as to provoke sweats; a bath, also, if he be burned up within.
						For these affections do not pass off by crises, even though they be forms of
						causus.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="8">
					<pb n="445"/>
					<head>CHAPTER VIII. CURE OF THE ACUTE DISEASE IN THE KIDNEYS.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">NFLAMMATION</hi> in the kidneys is of an acute nature;
						for the veins passing from the liver to the kidneys are inflamed at the same
						time, and with these the liver; for these veins are not very long, but are
						very broad, so as to give the kidneys the appearance of being suspended near
						the liver. But suppression of urine takes place along with the inflammation,
						thereby contributing to the intensity of the inflammation; for the cavity of
						the kidneys is filled by the overflow of the urine which fails to escape.
						The same happens also with stones, provided one larger than the breadth of
						the ureters be formed in the kidneys: it then becomes seated there, and, not
						passing through, it occasions a stoppage of the urine. But we will treat of
						the formation of calculi among the chronic diseases; how they may either be
						prevented from forming, or how they may be broken when formed. With regard
						to heat and obstruction, such of these affections as prove quickly fatal
						will be described by me in this place.</p>
					<p>Whether it be impaction of stones, or whether it be inflammation, we must
						open the vein at the elbow, unless a particular period of life prove an
						obstacle, and blood must be taken in a full stream and in large quantity.
						For not only are inflammations alleviated by evacuation, but also impacted
						stones are slackened by the evacuation of the vessels, and thus the stones
						escape during the passing of the urine. Then the parts are to be relaxed by
						bathing them with oil of must or of privet, and by fomentations and
						cataplasms. The herb southernwood, the schœnus, and calamus aromaticus,
						should form the ingredients of the cataplasms. Then we are to apply the
						cupping-instrument over the kidneys, in the loins, more</p>
					<pb n="446"/>
					<p>especially if the evacuation from this place has been of service. The bowels
						are to be softened by lubricating clysters, rather of a viscid than of an
						acrid nature, such as the juiees either of mallows or of fenugreek.
						Sometimes, also, diuretic medicines are to be given before food, such as are
						described respecting the liver, and also similar food of easy digestion: for
						in such cases indigestion is bad. Milk is a most excellent article,
						especially that of an ass; next, of a mare; even that of an ewe or a goat is
						useful, as being a kind of milk. If, then, they be free of fever, it is
						better also to prescribe the bath; but if not, they are to be placed in a
						sitz-bath formed of the decoction of herbs, filling the vessel up to their
						navel. But if it be turned to suppuration, what cataplasms and other
						medicines we are to use have formerly been laid down by us on many
						occasions.</p>
					<p>But, if the stone stick, we are to use the same fomentations and cataplasms,
						and try to break the stones with medicines taken in the form of drink. The
						simples are the herbs waterparsnip and <hi rend="ital">prionitis</hi>,<note
							n="1">I am at a loss to decide what herb this was. It is not noticed
							either by Theophrastus or Dioscorides. Indeed, I am not aware that it
							occurs elsewhere, except in the work of Trallian, viii.4. Petit, I know
							not on what authority, suggests that it is the <hi rend="ital">asplenium
								ceterach.</hi> Liddel and Scott identify it with the <foreign
								xml:lang="grc">KE/STRON</foreign>, but do not give their grounds for
							holding this opinion.</note> boiled with oil or edible vinegar, and the
						juice of it taken for drink: the compound ones are, that named from
						Vestinus, that from vipers and the reptile the skink, and such as from
						experience appear to be best. Gestation and succussion are calculated to
						promote the movement and protrusion of the calculi; for the passage of
						calculi into the bladder is very painful. But if the stones drop out, the
						patients become free from pain, which they have not been accustomed to be,
						not even in their dreams; and, as if escaped from inevitable evils, they
						feel relieved both in mind and in body.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="9">
					<pb n="447"/>
					<head>CHAPTER IX. CURE OF THE ACUTE AFFECTIONS ABOUT THE BLADDER.</head>
					<p>A<hi rend="smallcaps">CUTE</hi> affections, resembling those of the kidneys,
						form also in the bladder; namely, inflammations, ulcerations, calculi, and
						the obstructions from clots, and, along with these, suppression of urine and
						strangury. But in this part the pain is more acute, and death most speedy;
						for the bladder is a broad nerve, whereas the kidneys are like a concretion
						of blood, of the same species as the liver. But, moreover, the sufferings
						are most dreadful and most lamentable:</p>
					<p>for there, by far,</p>
					<p>On wretched men most cruel pains inflicts the god of war.</p>
					<p>We must, therefore, straightway make an incision in the flanks, and soothe
						the bladder by means of a fomentation of much oil, with rue and dill. But if
						grumous blood be the cause of the pains and stoppage of the urine, we are to
						give oxymel to drink, or a little quantity of lime with honeyedwater for the
						solution of the clots, and also such other things, both herbs and seeds, as
						promote the secretion of urine. But if there be danger from hemorrhage, it
						is to be stopped without delay, more than in the other cases; for the danger
						from it is not small. We must remedy it by the medicines which stop
						bleeding. In this case refrigeration of the bladder is beneficial; bathing
						with rose-oil and wine, and wrapping the parts in cloths made of unwashed
							wool.<note n="1">This process is very circumstantially described by
							Oribasius under the name of <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>KATEI/LHSLS</foreign> Med. Coll.x.18. Dr. Daremberg translates it,
								<hi rend="ital">l'enroulement avec les bandes.</hi></note> An
						epitheme may be formed with dates soaked in wine, with pomegranate or the
						juice of sumach. But if the patient is averse to the weight of</p>
					<pb n="448"/>
					<p>the epithemes and the great cooling, they must both be given up; for we must
						not cool greatly a part naturally thin and cold like the bladder. But we are
						to anoint the parts with oil of must, or acacia, or hypocistis with wine.
						But we must not use sponges, unless the hemorrhage be very urgent. The food
						should be farinaceous, of easy digestion, wholesome, diuretic, such as have
						been described by me under the head of the kidneys; milk, sweet wine, the
						Theræan and Scybelitic. Medicines should be drunk which are diuretic,
						fragrant, and diffusible, and other such things. A very excellent thing for
						the bladder is <hi rend="ital">cicadœ</hi>; roasted, in season, as an
						article of food; and out of season, when dried and triturated with water.
						Let also a little of the root of nard be boiled up with the <hi rend="ital"
							>cicadœ.</hi> The same things may be used for preparing a bath to sit in
						for relaxation of the bladder.</p>
					<p>But, if it be the impaction of calculi which stops the urine, we must push
						away the calculus and draw off the urine, with the instrument, the catheter,
						unless there be inflammations; for, in inflammations, neither do the
						passages well admit the instrument, and in addition they are hurt by the
						catheter. But if this treatment be inadmissible, and the patient is nearly
						killed with the sufferings, we must make an incision in the part under the
							<hi rend="ital">glans penis</hi>, and the neck of the bladder, in order
						to procure an outlet for the stone and the expulsion of the urine. And we
						must particularly endeavour to cure the part by bringing the wound to
						cicatrization. But if not, it is better that the patient should have a flux
						of urine for the remainder of his life, than that he should die most
						miserably of the pain.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="10">
					<pb n="449"/>
					<head>CHAPTER X. CURE OF THE HYSTERICAL CONVULSION.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> uterus in women has membranes extended on both
						sides at the flanks, and also is subject to the affections of an animal in
						smelling; for it follows after fragrant things as if for pleasure, and flees
						from fetid and disagreeable things as if for dislike. If, therefore,
						anything annoy it from above, it protrudes even beyond the genital organs.
						But if any of these things be applied to the os, it retreats backwards and
						upwards. Sometimes it will go to this side or to that,--to the spleen and
						liver, while the membranes yield to the distension and contraction like the
						sails of a ship.</p>
					<p>It suffers in this way also from inflammation; and it protrudes more than
						usual in this affection and in the swelling of its neck; for inflammation of
						the fundus inclines upwards; but if downwards to the feet, it protrudes
						externally, a troublesome, painful and unseemly complaint, rendering it
						difficult to walk, to lie on the side or on the back, unless the woman
						suffer from inflammation of the feet. But if it mount upwards, it very
						speedily suffocates the woman, and stops the respiration as if with a cord,
						before she feels pain, or can scream aloud, or can call upon the spectators,
						for in many cases the respiration is first stopped, and in others the
						speech. It is proper, then, in these cases, to call the physician quickly
						before the patient die. Should you fortunately arrive in time and ascertain
						that it is inflammation, you must open a vein, especially the one at the
						ankle, and pursue the other means which prove remedial in suffocation
						without inflammation: ligatures of the hands and feet so tight as to induce
						torpor; smelling to fetid substances--liquid pitch, hairs and wool burnt,
						the extinguished flame of a lamp, and castor,</p>
					<pb n="450"/>
					<p>since, in addition to its bad smell, it warms the congealed nerves. Old urine
						greatly rouses the sense of one in a death-like state, and drives the uterus
						downwards. Wherefore we must apply fragrant things on pessaries to the
						region of the uterus--any ointment of a mild nature, and not pungent to the
						touch, nard, or Ægyptian bacchar, or the medicine from the leaves of the
						malabathrum, the Indian tree,<note n="1">A species of wild cinnamon or
							cassia-tree. See Edinburgh Greek Lexicon, Appendix, under the
							term.</note> or cinnamon pounded with any of the fragrant oils. These
						articles are to be rubbed into the female parts. And also an injection of
						these things is to be thrown into the uterus. The anus is to be rubbed with
						applications which dispel flatus; and injections of things not acrid, but
						softening, viscid, and lubricant, are to be given for the expulsion of the
						fæces solely, so that the region of the uterus may be emptied,--with the
						juice of marsh-mallow, or of fenugreek, but let melilot or marjoram be
						boiled along with the oil. But, if the uterus stands in need of support
						rather than evacuation, the abdomen is to be compressed by the hands of a
						strong woman, or of an expert man, binding it round also with a roller, when
						you have replaced the part, so that it may not ascend upwards again. Having
						produced sneezing, you must compress the nostrils; for by the sneezing and
						straining, in certain cases, the uterus has returned to its place. We are to
						blow into the nostrils also some of the root of soapwort,<note n="2">The <hi
								rend="ital">Saponaria officinalis.</hi></note> or of pepper, or of
						castor. We are also to apply the instrument for dry-cupping to the thighs,
						loins, the ischiatic regions, and groins, in order to attract the uterus.
						And, moreover, we are to apply it to the spine, and between the scapulæ, in
						order to relieve the sense of suffocation. But if the feeling of suffocation
						be connected with inflammation, we may also scarify the vein leading along
						the pubes, and abstract plenty of blood. Friction of the</p>
					<pb n="451"/>
					<p>countenance, plucking of the hair, with bawling aloud, in order to arouse.
						Should the patient partially recover, she is to be seated in a decoction of
						aromatics, and fumigated from below with fragrant perfumes. Also before a
						meal, she is to drink of castor, and a little quantity of the hiera with the
						castor. And if relieved, she is to bathe, and at the proper season is to
						return to her accustomed habits; and we must look to the woman that her
						menstrual discharges flow freely.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="11">
					<head>CHAPTER XI. CURE OF SATYRIASIS.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">NFLAMMATION</hi> of the nerves in the genital organs
						occasions erection of the member with desire and pain <hi rend="ital">in re
							venerea:</hi> there arise spasmodic strainings which at no time abate,
						since the calamity is not soothed by the coition. They also become maddened
						in understanding, at first as regards shamelessness in the open performance
						of the act; for the inability to refrain renders them impudent; but
						afterwards . . . . . . . . when they have recovered, their understanding
						becomes quite settled.</p>
					<p>For all these causes, we must open the vein at the elbow, and also the one at
						the ankle, and abstract blood in large quantity and frequently, for now it
						is not unseasonable to induce deliquium animi, so as to bring on torpor of
						the understanding and remission of the inflammation, and also mitigation of
						the heat about the member; for it is much blood which strongly enkindles the
						heat and audacity; it is the pabulum of the inflammation, and the fuel of
						the disorder of the understanding, and of the confusion. The whole body is
						to be purged with the medicine, the hiera; for the patients not only require
						purging, but also a gentle medication, both</p>
					<pb n="452"/>
					<p>which objects are accomplished by the hiera. The genital organs, the loins,
						the perineum and the testicles, are to be wrapped in unwashed wool; but the
						wool must be moistened with rose-oil and wine, and the parts bathed, so much
						the more that no heating may be produced by the wool, but that the innate
						heat may be mitigated by the cooling powers of the fluids. Cataplasms of a
						like kind are to be applied; bread with the juice of plantain,
							strychnos,<note n="1">Doubtful whether he means the <hi rend="ital"
								>Solanum nigrum</hi> or <hi rend="ital">Physalis somnifera.</hi> See
							Paulus Ægineta, t. iii. p. 359.</note> endive, the leaves of the poppy,
						and the other narcotics and refrigerants. Also the genital organs, perineum,
						and ischiatic region, are to be rubbed with similar things, such as cicuta
						with water, or wine, or vinegar; mandragora, and acacia; and sponges are to
						be used instead of wool. In the interval we are to open the bowels with a
						decoction of mallows, oil, and honey. But everything acrid . . . . . .
						Cupping-instruments are to be fixed to the ischiatic region, or the abdomen;
						leeches also are very good for attracting blood from the inner parts, and to
						their bites a a cataplasm made of crumbs of bread with marsh-mallows. Then
						the patient is to have a sitz bath medicated with worm-wood, and the
						decoction of sage, and of flea-bane. But when the affection is protracted
						for a considerable time without any corresponding intermission, there is
						danger of a convulsion (for in this affection the patients are liable to
						convulsions), we must change the system of treatment to calefacients, there
						is need of oil of must or of Sicyonian oil instead of oil of roses, along
						with clean wool and warming cataplasms, for such treatment then soothes the
						inflammations of the nerves,--and we must also give castor with
						honeyed-water in a draught. Food containing little nourishment, in a cold
						state, in small quantity, and such as is farinaceous; mostly pot-herbs, the
						mallow, the blite, the lettuce, boiled gourd, boiled cucumber,</p>
					<pb n="453"/>
					<p>ripe pompion. Wine and fleshes to be used sparingly until convalescence have
						made considerable progress; for wine imparts warmth to the nerves, soothes
						the soul, recalls pleasure, engenders semen, and provokes to venery.</p>
					<p>Thus far have I written respecting the cures of acute diseases. One must also
						be fertile in expedients, and not require to apply his mind entirely to the
						writings of others. Acute diseases are thus treated of, so that you may
						avail yourself of what has been written of them, in their order, either
						singly or all together.</p>
				</div>
			</div>


		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
