<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>On The Refusal Of A Pension from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I can almost find it in me
        to be grateful to my accuser, gentlemen of the Council, for having involved me in these
        proceedings. For previously I had no excuse for rendering an account of my life; but now,
        owing to this man, I have got one. So I will try to show you in my speech that this man is
        lying, and that my own life until this day has been deserving of praise rather than envy;
        for it is merely from envy, in my opinion, that he has involved me in this ordeal.
          <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>But I ask you, if a man envies those whom other people
        pity, from what villainy do you think such a person would refrain? Is it possible that he
        hopes to get money by slandering me?<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A poor man like the
          speaker was not the natural prey of a slander-monger, who would hope to be bought off by a
          wealthy defendant.</note> And if he makes me out an enemy on whom he seeks to be avenged,
        he lies; for his villainy has always kept me from having any dealings with him either as a
        friend or as an enemy. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>So now, gentlemen, it is clear that
        he envies me because, although I have to bear this sore misfortune, I am a better citizen
        than he is. For indeed I consider, gentlemen, that one ought to remedy the afflictions of
        the body with the activities of the spirit; for if I am to keep my thoughts and the general
        tenor of my life on the level of my misfortune, how shall I be distinguished from this man?
          <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well, in regard to those
        matters, let these few words of mine suffice: I will now speak as briefly as I can on the
        points with which I am here concerned. My accuser says that I have no right to receive my
        civil pension, because I am able-bodied and not classed as disabled, and because I am
        skilled in a trade which would enable me to live without this grant. <milestone n="5"
          unit="section"/>In proof of my bodily strength, he instances that I mount on horseback; of
        the affluence arising from my trade, that I am able to associate with people who have means
        to spend. Now, as to the affluence from my trade and the nature of my livelihood in general,
        I think you are all acquainted with these: I will, however, make some brief remarks of my
        own. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>My father left me nothing, and I have only ceased
        supporting my mother on her decease two years ago; while as yet I have no children to take
        care of me. I possess a trade that can give me but slight assistance: I already find
        difficulty in carrying it on myself, and as yet I am unable to procure someone to relieve me
        of the work.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">He means a slave who would learn the business
          and carry it on for him.</note> I have no other income besides this dole, and if you
        deprive me of it I might be in danger of finding myself in the most grievous plight.
          <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Do not, therefore, gentlemen, when you can save me
        justly, ruin me unjustly; what you granted me when I was younger and stronger, do not take
        from me when I am growing older and weaker; nor, with your previous reputation for showing
        the utmost compassion even towards those who are in no trouble, be moved now by this man to
        deal harshly with those who are objects of pity even to their enemies; nor, by having the
        heart to wrong me, cause everyone else in my situation to despond. <milestone n="8"
          unit="section"/>And indeed, how extraordinary the case would be, gentlemen! When my
        misfortune was but simple, I am found to have been receiving this pension; but now, when old
        age, diseases, and the ills that attend on them are added to my trouble, I am to be deprived
        of it! <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>The depth of my poverty, I believe, can be revealed
        more clearly by my accuser than by anyone else on earth. For if I were charged with the duty
        of producing tragic drama, and should challenge him to an exchange of property,<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">See note on <bibl n="Lys. 3.20">Lys. 3.20</bibl>. (A wealthy
          citizen, such as the speaker here, had to undertake certain public services, which he
          could only avoid by challenging some other citizen, whom he considered wealthier than
          himself, either to exchange his property with him, or to undertake the service.)</note> he
        would prefer being the producer ten times over to making the exchange once. Surely it is
        monstrous that he should now accuse me of having such great affluence that I can consort on
        equal terms with the wealthiest people, while, in the event of such a thing as I have
        suggested, he should make that choice. Why, what could be more villainous? <milestone n="10"
          unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>As to my horsemanship, which he has dared
        to mention to you, feeling neither awe of fortune nor shame before you, there is not much to
        tell. For I, gentlemen, am of opinion that all who suffer from some affliction make it their
        single aim and constant study to manage the condition that has befallen them with the least
        amount of discomfort. I am such an one, and in the misfortune that has stricken me I have
        devised this facility for myself on the longer journeys that I find necessary. <milestone
          n="11" unit="section"/>But the strongest proof, gentlemen, of the fact that I mount horses
        because of my misfortune, and not from insolence, as this man alleges, is this: if I were a
        man of means, I should ride on a saddled mule, and would not mount other men’s horses. But
        in fact, as I am unable to acquire anything of the sort, I am compelled, now and again, to
        use other men’s horses. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>Well, I ask you, gentlemen, is it
        not extraordinary that, if he saw me riding on a saddled mule, he would hold his peace,—for
        what could he say?<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">It would be natural for a cripple to
          ride about on a cheaply hired mule, if only he could afford it.</note>—and then, because I
        mount borrowed horses, he should try to persuade you that I am able-bodied; and that my
        using two sticks, while others use one, should not be argued by him against me as a sign of
        being able-bodied, but my mounting horses should be advanced by him as a proof to you that I
        am able-bodied? For I use both aids for the same reason. <milestone n="13" unit="section"
          /><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So utterly has he surpassed the whole human race in
        impudence that he tries with his single voice to persuade you all that I am not classed as
        disabled. Yet if he should persuade any of you on this point, gentlemen, what hinders me
        from drawing a lot for election as one of the nine archons,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
          >The archons were appointed by lot from all the citizens, rich or poor, except,
          apparently, those who were formally classed as infirm.</note> and you from depriving me of
        my obol as having sound health, and voting it unanimously to this man as being a cripple?
        For surely, after you have deprived a man of the grant as being able-bodied, the law
        officers are not going to debar this same person, as being disabled, from drawing a lot!
          <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>Nay, indeed, you are not of the same opinion as he is,
        nor is he either, and rightly so. For he has come here to dispute over my misfortune as if
        over an heiress, and he tries to persuade you that I am not the sort of man that you all see
        me to be; but you —as is incumbent on men of good sense —have rather to believe your own
        eyes than this person’s words. <milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>He says that I am insolent, savage, and utterly abandoned in my behavior, as
        though he needed the use of terrifying terms to speak the truth, and could not do it in
        quite gentle language. But I expect you, gentlemen, to distinguish clearly between those
        people who are at liberty to be insolent and those who are debarred from it. <milestone
          n="16" unit="section"/>For insolence is not likely to be shown by poor men laboring in the
        utmost indigence, but by those who possess far more than the necessaries of life; nor by men
        disabled in body, but by those who have most reason to rely on their own strength; nor by
        those already advanced in years, but by those who are still young and have a youthful turn
        of mind. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>For the wealthy purchase with their money escape
        from the risks that they run, whereas the poor are compelled to moderation by the pressure
        of their want. The young are held to merit indulgence from their elders; but if their elders
        are guilty of offence, both ages unite in reproaching them. <milestone n="18" unit="section"
        />The strong are at liberty to insult whomsoever they will with impunity, but the weak are
        unable either to beat off their aggressors when insulted, or to get the better of their
        victims if they choose to insult. Hence it seems to me that my accuser was not serious in
        speaking of my insolence, but was only jesting; his purpose was, not to persuade you that
        such is my nature, but to set me in a comic light, as a fine stroke of fancy. <milestone
          n="19" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He further asserts that my shop is
        the meeting place of a number of rogues who have spent their own money and hatch plots
        against those who wish to preserve theirs. But you must all take note that these statements
        of his are no more accusations against me than against anyone else who has a trade, nor
        against those who visit my shop any more than those who frequent other men of business.
          <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>For each of you is in the habit of paying a call at
        either a perfumer’s or a barber’s or a shoemaker’s shop, or wherever he may chance to go,
        —in most cases, it is to the tradesmen who have set up nearest the marketplace, and in
        fewest, to those who are farthest from it. So if any of you should brand with roguery the
        men who visit my shop, clearly you must do the same to those who pass their time in the
        shops of others; and if to them, to all the Athenians: for you are all in the habit of
        paying a call and passing your time at some shop or other. <milestone n="21" unit="section"
          /><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But really I see no need for me to be so very particular
        in rebutting each one of the statements that he has made, and to weary you any longer. For
        if I have argued the principal points, what need is there to dwell seriously on trifles in
        the same way as he does? But I beg you all, gentlemen of the Council, to hold the same views
        concerning me as you have held till now. <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>Do not be led by
        this man to deprive me of the sole benefit in my country of which fortune has granted me a
        share, nor let this one person prevail on you to withdraw now what you all agreed to grant
        me in the past. For, gentlemen, since Heaven had deprived us<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">The speaker here solemnly appeals for himself as one of an unfortunate
          class.</note> of the chiefest things, the city voted us this pension, regarding the
        chances of evil and of good as the same for all alike. <milestone n="23" unit="section"
        />Surely I should be the most miserable of creatures if, after being deprived by my
        misfortune of the fairest and greatest things, the accuser should cause me the loss of that
        which the city bestowed in her thoughtful care for men in my situation. No, no, gentlemen;
        you must not vote that way. And why should I find you thus inclined? <milestone n="24"
          unit="section"/>Because anyone has ever been brought to trial at my instance and lost his
        fortune? There is nobody who can prove it. Well, is it that I am a busybody, a hot head, a
        seeker of quarrels? <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>That is not the sort of use I happen
        to make of such means of subsistence as I have. That I am grossly insolent and savage? Even
        he would not allege this himself, except he should wish to add one more to the series of his
        lies. Or that I was in power at the time of the Thirty, and oppressed a great number of the
        citizens? But I went into exile with your people to <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis"
          >Chalcis</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
            >Euboea</placeName>, <date value="-404">404</date> B.C.</note> and when I was free to
        live secure as a citizen with those persons<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e., the
          Thirty.</note> I chose to depart and share your perils. <milestone n="26" unit="section"
        />I therefore ask you, gentlemen of the Council, not to treat me, a man who has committed no
        offence, in the same way as those who are guilty of numerous wrongs, but to give the same
        vote as the other Councils<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e., the Councils of previous
          years by which he had been certified as infirm.</note> did on my case, remembering that I
        am neither rendering an account of State moneys placed in my charge, nor undergoing now an
        inquiry into my past proceedings in any office, but that the subject of this speech of mine
        is merely an obol. <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>In this way you will all give the
        decision that is just, while I, in return for that, will feel duly grateful to you; and this
        man will learn in the future not to scheme against those who are weaker than himself, but
        only to overreach his equals.</p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
