<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>In Defence of Lycophron from Speeches (English). Machine readable
                    text</title>
                <author>Hyperides</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Hyperides</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
                <refState unit="fragment"/>
            </refsDecl>

            <refsDecl n="speech=5">
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="fragment"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
<change><date>May 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>June 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>4/30/93</date><respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>add refdecl, changed some of the FRAG attributes that had commentary in them, made notes have a space after them.</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
            <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="fragment" n="1">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . each man in private and in public life,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass, comparing <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.1">Aeschin.
                            3.1</bibl>, conjectured the sense to be: “I come before you now having
                        put my trust both in the gods, on whom you all rely in private and in public
                        life, and also in the law, etc.”</note> and also in the law and in the oath
                    which bids you give an equal hearing to the prosecution and to the defence. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="2">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . to conduct the prosecution,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The sense is no doubt: “Since you allowed my opponents to
                        conduct the prosecution as they wished, allow me also a fair hearing in my
                        defence.”</note> allow me also in the same way to follow out, so far as I am
                    able, the line of defence which I have chosen. I must ask you all, while I am
                    speaking, to refrain from interrupting me with: “Why are you telling us this?”
                    And do not add anything of your own to the prosecution's argument; rather
                    &lt;attend&gt; to the defence . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="3">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . nor is it true that the law, while allowing
                    freedom to join in the prosecution of men on trial, denies the right to share in
                    their defence. I do not intend to waste words before coming to the point, and
                    shall therefore proceed to the actual defence, after praying the gods to help me
                    and bring me safely through the present trial and requesting you, gentlemen of
                    the jury, first . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="3a">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . either the betrayal of dockyards, the
                    burning of public buildings, or the seizure of the Acropolis . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="4">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . Euphemus . . . first . . . when the husband
                    died . . . of <placeName key="tgn,7012055">Phlya</placeName> . . . from him . .
                    . that the woman . . . he had left his wife with child, which did not entail any
                    breach of the law. But if their interpretation of this story tallied with that
                    given by Ariston in the impeachment, they<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        reference seems to be to those relatives due to benefit by the will in the
                        event of the child's death. See Introduction.</note> should not surely have
                    prevented the nearest relatives from ejecting Euphemus. They ought to have let
                    them do so. Whereas now, by behaving as they did, they have by their own action
                    furnished evidence that the charge against me is false. Besides, is it not
                    strange that if anything had happened to the child at birth, or after, they
                    would have adhered firmly to this will, in which . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="4a">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . nor is it possible for him to deny his own
                    handwriting </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="4b">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . to be sluggish. . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>. . . and he had Ariston's slaves in his works. This fact he confirmed for you
                        himself<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The subject is probably
                        Theomnestus.</note> in court when Ariston was bringing an action against
                        Archestratides.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Nothing is known of this
                        man. He may be the Archestratides against whom Hyperides composed a speech.
                        Compare <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 52">Hyp. Fr. 52.</bibl></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>Let me explain the kind of method which this man Ariston employs. He issues a
                    summons against everyone he meets, accusing and prosecuting those who do not
                    give him money, but letting go all who are willing to pay. He gives the money to
                    Theomnestus who takes it and buys slaves, providing Ariston with a livelihood,
                    as is done for pirates, and paying him an obol a day for each slave, to enable
                    him to continue permanently as a false informer. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When considering the matter, gentlemen of the
                    jury, we ought to begin with the charges which my accusers themselves brought
                    against me at the outset in the Assembly. My relatives communicated the
                    impeachment to me by letter, and also the charges which they made against me in
                    the Assembly when they brought the impeachment in. Among these was recorded a
                    statement of Lycurgus, who claimed to have been told by the relatives that
                    during the wedding of Charippus to the woman I followed and tried to persuade
                    her to reserve herself and have nothing to do with Charippus. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>Let me now repeat to you the answer which I gave to the relatives and also to my
                    own relations directly I arrived, namely this. If these accusations are true, I
                    agree to having done all the other things set down in the impeachment. But they
                    are false, as is surely obvious to everyone. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>For who is there in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> so
                    uncritical as to believe these allegations? There must have been attenders,
                    gentlemen of the jury, with the carriage that conveyed the bride: first a
                    muleteer and a guide, and then her escort of boys, and also Dioxippus.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For Dioxippus, the athlete who accompanied
                        Alexander to <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName> (<bibl
                            n="Diod. 17.100">Diod. Sic. 17.100.2</bibl>), see Introduction to the
                        speech.</note> For he was in attendance, too, since she was a widow being
                    given away in marriage. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>Was I then so utterly senseless, do you think, that with all those other people
                    in the procession, as well as Dioxippus and Euphraeus his fellow-wrestler, both
                    acknowledged to be the strongest men in <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName>, I had the impudence to pass such comments on a free
                    woman, in the hearing of everyone, and was not afraid of being strangled on the
                    spot? Would anyone have listened to such remarks about his sister as these men
                    accuse me of having made, without killing the speaker? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>And to crown it all, as I said just now, are we to conclude that Charippus was so
                    completely obtuse that he was still prepared to marry her, although in the first
                    place she said beforehand, according to their story, that she was pledged to me
                    and in the second place he heard me encouraging her to keep the promises she had
                    made? Do you think that the mad Orestes, or Margites,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Margites, the hero of an old comic epic early attributed to
                        Homer, came to be regarded as the typification of a fool.</note> the
                    greatest fool of all time, would act like that? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But then, in my opinion, gentlemen of the jury,
                    the prosecutors in a trial have many advantages over the defendants. For them
                    the case involves no risk,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For the importance
                        of this statement for determining the date of the speech see
                        Introduction.</note> and so they are free to talk and lie to their heart's
                    content, while the men on trial are afraid and so forget to mention a great
                    deal, even of what they have really done. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>Also, accusers, speaking first, do not confine themselves to putting the just
                    arguments which support their case, but trump up baseless slanders about the
                    accused and so deprive them of the means of defence. The latter are thus
                    affected in one of two ways. Either they defend themselves against the
                    extraneous charges and fall short in the relevant parts of their defence, or
                    else they forget the accusations which have just been made, and so leave the
                    jury with the impression that these are true. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>In addition to this the accusers create a prejudice against the advocates for the
                    defence and distort the case of the accused himself; which is what Ariston here
                    attempted to do, when speaking for the prosecution, since he does not even allow
                    me to benefit from those who come forward to help me intending to share in my
                    defence. What reason is there why they should not? Is it not right that men on
                    trial should be supported by their relatives and friends? Or is there any custom
                    in the city more democratic<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Compare <bibl
                            n="Hyp. 4.11">Hyp. 4.11</bibl>.</note> than that which permits citizens
                    capable of public-speaking to assist those who are incapable when they are in
                    trouble? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>But you, Ariston, have not merely discussed my advocates; you even determine my
                    own arguments and tell the jury what they must listen to, what line of defence
                    they must prescribe for me, and what they must not tolerate. Surely it is most
                    unfair that after conducting the prosecution as you wanted you should rob me of
                    my defence, because you know already the honest answers I can offer to your
                    lies. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>And you accuse me in the impeachment of undermining the democracy by breaking the
                    laws; but you override every law yourself, by presenting an impeachment in a
                    case where the laws require a public charge before the Thesmothetae.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A list of offences for which impeachments were
                        appropriate is given in <bibl n="Hyp. 4.8">Hyp. 4.8</bibl>. The Thesmothetae
                        were concerned mainly with crimes directed against the state, but they also
                        dealt with cases of assault and adultery (<foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >u(/bris</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="greek">moixei/a</foreign>).
                        See <bibl n="Hyp. 4.6">Hyp. 4.6</bibl> and <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 59"
                            >Aristot. Ath. Pol. 59</bibl>.</note> Your object was to run no risk in
                    bringing in the action and also to have the opportunity of writing tragic
                        phrases<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For this use of the noun <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">tragw|di/a</foreign> compare <bibl n="Hyp. 4.26">Hyp.
                            4.26</bibl>. The verb <foreign xml:lang="greek">tragw|de/w</foreign> is
                        used with a similar sense by Demosthenes (e.g. <bibl n="Dem. 18.13">Dem. 18.
                            13</bibl>).</note> in the impeachment, such as you have written now,
                    protesting that I am making many women grow old unmarried in their homes and
                    many live illegally with men unsuited for them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>The fact is that you can instance no other woman in the city whom I have wronged
                    in this way, and as for the subject of your present charge, what view did you
                    take of her? Was she right to live with Charippus, an Athenian citizen who was
                    her husband; or was she growing old unmarried in her home,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This passage is not very clearly expressed in the Greek.
                        Lycophron is answering the charge that he causes women (a) to grow old
                        unmarried; (b) to live with the wrong men. Taking these points in the
                        reverse order he retorts by asking whether in the present case the woman is
                        (b) doing wrong by living with her legal husband or (a) growing old
                        unmarried. In view of the words <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >ou)prosh/kei</foreign> in § l2 above, a negative before <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">prodh/kein</foreign> would make the sense of what
                        follows much clearer. Kirchhoff's suggested emendation is therefore rather
                        tempting.</note> she who was married at once, as soon as Euphemus supplied a
                    talent of silver as a dowry, obviously with no ulterior motive but simply out of
                        kindness?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Probably Ariston had alleged that
                        Euphemus was acting in collusion with Lycophron, but we have no
                        details.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>So Ariston may say whatever he pleases, gentlemen
                    of the jury, and invent lies against me, but surely your verdict upon me must be
                    based, not on the slanders of the prosecutor, but on a review of the whole of my
                    life. No one in the city, whether good or bad, can deceive the community in
                    which you live. Indeed the most reliable testimonial of character which a man
                    can have is his past career, especially in refuting charges like the present.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>Where the crime is one which can be committed at any time during a man's life it
                    should be considered in the light of the particular accusation made. But
                    adultery is a practice which no man can begin after fifty. Either he has been a
                    loose-liver for a long lime—and let these men prove that that is true of me—or
                    else the charge may be presumed false. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>Now I, gentlemen of the jury, have lived with you in <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> all my life. I have never been
                    subjected to any discreditable charge, nor have I brought an accusation against
                    another citizen. I have not been defendant or prosecutor in any lawsuit, but
                    have always been a keen horsebreeder, consistently overtaxing my strength and my
                        resources.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Horsebreeding, which was carried
                        on either for war or racing, was sometimes frowned on as a mark of wealth
                        and ostentation. (Compare <bibl n="Lyc. 1.139">Lyc. 1.139</bibl>. ). But
                        here, though he admits extravagance, Lycophron is simply claiming to be
                        doing his duty as a knight.</note> I have been crowned for bravery by the
                    order of knights and by my colleagues in office. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>For you appointed me, gentlemen of the jury, first as Phylarch and later as
                    Cavalry Leader at <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The ten phylarchs, one from each tribe,
                        commanded the cavalry of their own tribe under the hipparchs. Of these there
                        were two elected from the whole people. One of them was appointed to command
                        a body of Athenian cavalry in <placeName key="tgn,7011173"
                            >Lemnos</placeName>, after the Athenians gained control of the island by
                        the Peace of Antalcidas in <date>387</date> B.C. Compare <bibl
                            n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 61.6">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 6l. 6</bibl>; <bibl
                            n="Dem. 4.27">Dem. 4. 27</bibl>;<title>CIA</title>2. 14 and 593.</note>
                    I held the command there for two years, the only cavalry leader who has ever
                    done so, and prolonged my stay for a third, as I did not wish, in exacting the
                    pay for the horsemen rashly, to burden citizens in financial straits. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>During that time no one there brought an action against me, either private or
                    public. In fact I was crowned three times by the inhabitants of Hephaestia and
                    as many times more by those of Myrine. These facts should satisfy you, in the
                    present trial, that the charges against me are false. No man can be good in
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> if he is bad in <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and you had no poor opinion of me
                    when you dispatched me there and made me responsible for two of your own cities.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Well, gentlemen of the jury, you have heard
                    virtually all that I had to say in my own defence. The prosecutor, who is an
                    experienced speaker and used to frequent litigation, summoned advocates<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The chief of these advocates was the orator
                        Lycurgus. See Introduction to the speech.</note> to help him in unjustly
                    ruining a citizen. So I too am asking you, most earnestly, for your authority to
                    summon my advocates in this important case, and I beg you to give a sympathetic
                    hearing to any of my relatives or friends who can help me. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>I am a fellow-citizen of yours, an amateur unused to speaking, on trial now with
                    the risk not only of losing my life—a minor consideration to men with a proper
                    sense of values—but also of being cast out after death, without even the
                    prospect of a grave in my own country. So if you will give the word, gentlemen
                    of the jury, I will call an advocate. Will you please come up, Theophilus, and
                    say what you can in my defence? The jury ask you to do so.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
