<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On the Estate of Philoctemon from Speeches (ENGLISH). Machine readable
                    text</title>
                <author>Isaeus</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Isaeus</author>
                        <title>Isaeus with an English translation by Edward Seymour Forster,
                            M.A.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
                <language ident="latin">Latin </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
<change><date>March 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>September 1992</date><respStmt><name>D. Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed notes and regularized citations</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
            <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="hypothesis" type="section">
                <p>Philoctemon, a son of Euctemon, adopted Chaerestratus, the son of one of his two
                    sisters and of Phanostratus, in a will which was deposited with Chaereas, the
                    husband of the other sister, and died during his father's lifetime. When the
                    latter also died, Chaerestratus claimed possession in accordance with the law.
                    When Androcles lodged a protestation that the estate was not adjudicable because
                    Euctemon had a legitimate son, namely, Antidorus,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This is a mistake. Antidorus was the name of one of the
                        guardians (<bibl n="Isaeus 6.39">Isaeus 6.39</bibl>, <bibl n="Isaeus 6.47"
                            >Isaeus 6.47</bibl>). The names of the two alleged sons are not stated
                        anywhere in the speech.</note> Chaerestratus and his supporters impugned the
                    protestation, declaring that both Antidorus and his sister<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Another mistake. No sister is mentioned in the
                        speech.</note> were illegitimate and that the law ordains that an
                    illegitimate son or daughter cannot inherit as next-of-kin. The discussion turns
                    on questions of fact; for it is uncertain whether Philoctemon adopted
                    Chaerestratus as his son, and further, whether Antidorus and the other child are
                    legitimate. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>That I am on terms of very close friendship with
                    Phanostratus and with Chaerestratus here, I think most of you, gentlemen, are
                    aware, but to those who are not aware of it I will give a convincing proof. When
                        Chaerestratus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If the reading here is
                        correct, Chaerestratus, who is still a young man at the date of this speech
                            (<bibl n="Isaeus 6.60">Isaeus 6.60</bibl>) and therefore cannot have
                        taken part in the famous Sicilian expedition of <dateRange from="-415"
                            to="-413">415</dateRange>-413 B.C., must have sailed to <placeName
                            key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> on some occasion of which we have
                        no historical record. The emendation <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >*fano/stratos</foreign> adopted by most editors, is precluded by the
                            words<foreign xml:lang="greek">deome/nwn tou/twn</foreign>, which can
                        only refer to Phanostratus and Chaerestratus; although Phanostratus might
                        have taken part in the Sicilian Expedition, Chaerestratus could not have
                        been then alive and therefore would not have requested the speaker to
                        accompany his father to <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
                        >Sicily</placeName>.</note> set sail for <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
                        >Sicily</placeName> in command of a trireme, although, having sailed thither
                    myself before, I knew well all the dangers which I should encounter, yet, at the
                    request of these friends of mine, I sailed with him and shared his misfortune,
                    and we were both made prisoners of war. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>It would be strange if I endured all this in the face of evident danger because
                    of my friendship and affection for them, and yet were not now to attempt so to
                    plead their cause that you shall pass a sentence in accordance with your oath
                    and that justice shall be done to my clients. I entreat you, therefore, to grant
                    me indulgence and to listen to me with goodwill; for the suit is of no slight
                    importance to them, but their most vital interests are at stake. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Philoctemon of Cephisia was a friend of
                    Chaerestratus here, and died, having bequeathed to him his property and having
                    adopted him as his son. Chaerestratus in accordance with the law<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Being adopted posthumously he had to obtain a
                        legal adjudication before he could take possession. This formality was not
                        necessary for a son adopted in the lifetime of the testator.</note> claimed
                    the estate. But, since it is lawful for any Athenian who wishes to do so to
                    dispute an inheritance by bringing a direct action before you, and if he can
                    establish a better claim, to obtain possession of the estate, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>Androcles here put in a protestation declaring that the succession was not
                    adjudicable, thus depriving my client of his right to claim the estate and you
                    of your right to decide who ought to be declared heir to Philoctemon's property.
                    He thus thinks by a single verdict and by a single suit to establish as brothers
                    of the deceased men who have no sort of connection with him, to place himself in
                    possession of the estate without further legal procedure, to, become legal
                    representative of the sister of the deceased, and to annul the will. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>Androcles has made a number of extraordinary allegations in his protestation; I
                    will take one point first and prove that Philoctemon made a will and adopted
                    Chaerestratus here as his son. Seeing that Philoctemon had no issue by the woman
                    to whom he was married, and since, as it was war-time, he was running
                    considerable risks, serving in the cavalry and often sailing as trierarch, he
                    resolved to dispose of his property by will, so that he might not leave his
                    house desolate if anything happened to him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>He had had two brothers, both of whom died without issue: of his two sisters one,
                    who was the wife of Chaereas, had no son and had never had one, though she had
                    been married for many years; the other, who was wife of Phanostratus here, had
                    two sons. It was the elder of these, Chaerestratus here, whom Philoctemon
                    adopted as his son. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>Under the terms of his will, if he had no child by his wife, Chaerestratus
                    inherited his estate. He deposited his will with Chaereas, his brother-in-law,
                    the husband of his other sister. This will shall now be read to you, and those
                    who were present at its execution shall give evidence. Please read it.<quote
                        type="Will. Witnesses"><title>Will. Witnesses</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You have now heard that Philoctemon made a will,
                    and on what conditions he adopted Chaerestratus as his son. To prove that he had
                    a right to do so, I will produce the text of the law which is in my opinion the
                    best source of information in such matters. Please read it.<quote type="Law"
                            ><title>Law</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>This law, gentlemen, holds good for all men alike,
                    permitting anyone to dispose of his property in default of male issue, providing
                    that, at the time of doing so, he is not insane or mentally incapacitated by old
                    age or any other of the causes mentioned in the law. That Philoctemon did not
                    fall under any of these exceptions, I will prove to you in a few words. For how
                    could anyone dare to say that a man was not in full possession of his faculties,
                    who all his life showed himself so good a citizen, that, owing to your esteem
                    for him, he was considered worthy to hold command, and who died fighting against
                    the enemy? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>That he made a will and adopted a son when he was
                    in full possession of his faculties, as he was entitled to do, has been proved
                    to you; it follows from this that Androcles has been proved to have committed
                    perjury. But since he has further stated in his protestation that my opponent is
                    a legitimate son of Euctemon, I will prove this also to be false. The real sons
                    of Euctemon, the father of Philoctemon, namely, Philoctemon himself, Ergamenes,
                    and Hegemon, and his two daughters and their mother, Euctemon's wife, the
                    daughter of Meixiades of Cephisia, are well known to all their relatives and to
                    the members of the ward and to most of the demesmen, and they shall testify to
                    you; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>but no one is aware or ever heard a word during Euctemon's lifetime of his having
                    married any other wife who became mother by him of our opponents. Yet it is only
                    natural that these should be most trustworthy witnesses; for relatives ought to
                    know about such matters. Please call them first and read the depositions.<quote
                        type="Depositions"><title>Depositions</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Further, I will prove that our adversaries have
                    actually given evidence in support of these facts. When the interrogations took
                    place before the archon, and my opponents paid money into court in support of
                    their claim that these young men were the legitimate sons of Euctemon, on being
                    asked by us who, and whose daughter, their mother was, they could not supply the
                    information, although we protested and the archon ordered them to reply in
                    accordance with the law. It was surely a strange proceeding, gentlemen, to make
                    a claim on their behalf as legitimate and to lodge a protestation, and yet not
                    be able to state who was their mother or name any of their relatives. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>At the time they alleged that she was a Lemnian and so secured a delay;
                    subsequently, when they appeared at the interrogation, without giving time for
                    anyone to ask a question, they immediately declared that the mother was Callippe
                    and that she was the daughter of Pistoxenus, as though it was enough for them
                    merely to produce the name of Pistoxenus. When we asked who he was and whether
                    he was alive or not, they said that he had died on military service in
                        <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, leaving a daughter, this
                    Callippe, in the house of Euctemon, and that these two sons were born to her
                    while she was under his guardianship, thus inventing a story surpassing the
                    limits of impudence and quite untrue, as I will prove to you first of all from
                    the answers which they themselves gave. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Fifty-two years have passed since the Sicilian expedition, reckoning from the
                    date of its departure in the archonship of Arimnestus;<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The Sicilian expedition set out in the summer of
                            <date>415</date> B.C. (<bibl n="Thuc. 6.30">Thuc. 6.30</bibl>). The date
                        of this speech must therefore be <date>364</date> B.C.</note> yet the elder
                    of these two alleged sons of Callippe and Euctemon has not yet passed his
                    twentieth year. If these years are deducted, more than thirty years still remain
                    since the Sicilian expedition; so that Callippe, if she were thirty years of
                        age,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The speaker rather arbitrarily
                        calculates the date of her marriage by the birth of her elder son.</note>
                    ought to have been no longer under a guardian, nor unmarried and childless, but
                    long ago married, given in marriage either by her guardian, according to the
                    law, or else by an adjudication of the court. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, she must necessarily have been known to the relatives and to the
                    slaves of Euctemon if she had really been married to him and lived so long in
                    the house. It is not enough merely to produce such statements at the
                    interrogations, but it must be proved that the alleged events really took place
                    and they must be supported by the testimony of the relatives. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>When we insisted that they should indicate one of Euctemon's family who knew of
                    anyone of the name of Callippe as having been either married to him or under his
                    guardianship, and that they should make an inquiry from our slaves, or hand over
                    to us for examination any of their slaves who said they had knowledge of these
                    facts, they refused to take any of our slaves for examination or to hand over
                    any of their own to us. Now please read their answer to the interrogation and
                    our depositions and challenges.<quote
                        type="Answer to Interrogation. Depositions. Challenges"><title>Answer to
                            Interrogation. Depositions. Challenges</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>My opponents, then, avoided a mode of proof so
                    vital to their case; but I will show you the origin and position of these men
                    whom my opponents testified to be legitimate and are seeking to establish as
                    heirs of Euctemon's property. It is perhaps painful, gentlemen, to Phanostratus
                    to bring to light the misfortunes of Euctemon; but it is essential that a few
                    facts should be given, so that, knowing the truth, you may more easily give your
                    verdict aright. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>Euctemon lived for ninety-six years, and for most of this period had the
                    reputation of being a fortunate man; he possessed considerable property and had
                    children and a wife, and in all other respects enjoyed a reasonable degree of
                    prosperity. In his old age, however, a serious misfortune befell him, which
                    brought ruin to his house, caused him great financial loss, and set him at
                    variance with his nearest relatives. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>The cause and manner of it I will set forth in the fewest possible words. He had
                    a freed-woman, gentlemen, who managed a tenement-house of his at the Peiraeus
                    and kept prostitutes. As one of these she acquired a woman of the name of Alce,
                    whom I think many of you know. This Alce, after her purchase, lived the life of
                    a prostitute<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="greek">kaqh/sto
                            e)n oi)kh/mati</foreign> = <foreign xml:lang="latin">in cella meretricia
                            sedebat</foreign>, a technical term that refers to the activities of a
                        working prostitute (see Wyse ad loc. in <title>The Speeches of
                            Isaeus</title>, <placeName key="tgn,7011980">Cambridge</placeName>,
                        1904).</note> for many years but gave it up when she became too old. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>While she was still living in the tenement-house, she had relations with a
                    freedman whose name was <placeName key="perseus,Dion">Dion</placeName>, whom she
                    declared to be the father of these young men; and <placeName key="perseus,Dion"
                        >Dion</placeName> did, in fact, bring them up as his own children. Some time
                    later Dion, having committed a misdemeanor and being afraid of the consequences,
                    withdrew to <placeName key="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>. The woman Alce was
                    then installed by Euctemon to look after his tenement-house in the
                        Cerameicus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The “Potters' Quarter” at
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, partly inside and
                        partly outside the walls near the Dipylon Gate (see Frazer's note on <bibl
                            n="Paus. 1.2.4">Paus. 1.2.4</bibl>).</note> near the postern gate, where
                    wine is sold. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Her establishment there, gentlemen, had many evil consequences. Euctemon, going
                    there constantly to collect the rent, used to spend most of his time in the
                    tenement-house, and sometimes took his meals with the woman, leaving his wife
                    and children and his own home. In spite of the protests of his wife and sons,
                    not only did he not cease to go there but eventually lived there entirely, and
                    was reduced to such a condition by drugs or disease or some other cause, that he
                    was persuaded by the woman to introduce the elder of the two boys to the members
                    of his ward under his name. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>When, however, his son Philoctemon refused to agree to this, and the members of
                    the ward would not admit the boy, and the victim for the sacrifice of admission
                    was removed from the altar,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Apparently the
                        effect of this action would be to defer the question of admission till a
                        later meeting of the wardsmen.</note> Euctemon, being enraged against his
                    son and wishing to pay him out, announced his intention of marrying a sister of
                    Democrates of <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName> and
                    recognizing any children who should be born to her and bringing them into the
                    family, unless he consented to allow Alce's son to be introduced. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>His relatives, knowing that no more children would be born to him at his time of
                    life but that they would be forthcoming in some other manner, and that, as a
                    result, still more serious quarrels would arise, advised Philoctemon, gentlemen,
                    to allow him to introduce this child on the conditions which he demanded, giving
                    him a single farm. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>And Philoctemon, ashamed at his fathers folly but at a loss how to deal with the
                    embarrassment of the moment, made no objection. An agreement having been thus
                    concluded, and the child having been introduced on these terms, Euctemon gave up
                    his project of marriage, proving thereby that the object of his threatened
                    marriage was not to procure children but to obtain the introduction of this
                    child into the ward. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>For what need had he to marry, Androcles, if these children had been born to him
                    from a marriage with an Athenian citizen, as you have affirmed them to have been
                    in your evidence? If they were legitimate, who could prevent him from
                    introducing them? And why did he introduce them on special terms, when the law
                    ordains that all the legitimate sons have an equal right to share in their
                    father's property? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>And why did he introduce the elder child on special terms, but said not a word
                    about the younger child during the lifetime of Philoctemon either to Philoctemon
                    or to his other relatives? Yet you have explicitly borne witness that they are
                    legitimate and heirs to the property of Euctemon. In proof of the truth of these
                    assertions, read the depositions.<quote type="Depositions"
                            ><title>Depositions</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It was after this, then, that Philoctemon died by
                    the enemy's hands while commanding a trireme off <placeName key="tgn,7002670"
                        >Chios</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Probably about
                            <date>376</date> B.C.</note> Some time later Euctemon informed his
                    sons-in-law that he wished to make a written record of his arrangement with his
                    son and place it in safe place. Phanostratus was on the point of setting out
                    with Timotheus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This expedition under Timotheus
                        probably took place in 375 or <date>373</date> B.C.</note> in command of a
                    trireme, and his ship lying at anchor at Munychia,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">A small harbor on the east of the Peiraic peninsula in which
                        part of the Athenian navy was docked.</note> and his brother-in-law Chaereas
                    was there bidding him farewell. Euctemon, taking certain persons with him, came
                    to where the ship was anchored, and having drawn up a document detailing the
                    conditions under which he introduced the child, deposited it in the presence of
                    those men with his relative Pythodorus of Cephisia. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>The very fact that he acted thus is sufficient proof, gentlemen, that Euctemon
                    was not dealing with them as legitimate children, as Androcles has declared in
                    his evidence; for no one ever makes a gift by will of anything to the sons of
                    his own body, because the law of itself gives his father's estate to the son and
                    does not even allow anyone who has legitimate children to dispose of his
                    property. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When the document had remained deposited for
                    almost two years and Chaereas had died, my opponents, having come under the
                    influence of Alce and seeing that the property was going to ruin and that the
                    old age and imbecility of Euctemon gave them an excellent opportunity, made a
                    combined plan of attack. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>They first urged Euctemon to cancel the will on the ground that it was not to the
                    boys advantage; for no one would have any claim to the real estate on Euctemon's
                    death except the daughters and their issue; whereas, if he sold part of the
                    property and left it in cash, they would get secure possession of it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>Euctemon listened to them and immediately demanded the document back from
                    Pythodorus and served upon him a summons to produce it. When Pythodorus appeared
                    before the archon, Euctemon stated that he wished to annul the will. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>Pythodorus was prepared to agree with Euctemon and Phanostratus, who was present,
                    that the document should be destroyed; but, as Chaereas, who had been a party to
                    its deposition, had left an only daughter, he suggested that it should be
                    destroyed only in the presence of her legal representative, and the archon
                    decided in favor of this course. Euctemon, after agreeing to this in the
                    presence of the archon and his assessors, called many persons to witness that
                    the will deposited by him no longer existed and then went his way. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>In a very short time—and this was the object of their advice to Euctemon to annul
                    the will—he sold a farm at Athmonon<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The site of
                        this place was near the modern Marusi, about seven miles north-east of
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> (See Frazer on <bibl
                            n="Paus. 1.31.4">Paus. 1.31.4</bibl>).</note> to Antiphanes for
                    seventy-five minas and the bath-house at Serangion<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The site of these baths has been discovered below the
                        eastern end of the hill on Munychia on the Peiraic peninsula. They consisted
                        of a subterranean chamber with openings in different directions through the
                        cliff (see Frazer's Pausanius 5. p. 477).</note> to Aristolochus for 3000
                    drachmas; and he realized a mortgage of forty-five minas on a house in
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> from the hierophant.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The official who displayed the sacred emblems at
                        the Eleusinian mysteries; he was a member of the house of the
                        Eumolpidae.</note> Further, he sold some goats with their goat-herd for
                    thirteen minas and two pairs of mules, one for eight minas and the other for
                    five hundred and fifty drachmas, and all the slaves he had that were craftsmen.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>In all, the value of the property which he hurriedly sold after Philoctemon's
                    death, was more than three talents. And to prove that I am speaking the truth, I
                    will first call witnesses in support of each of my statements.<quote
                        type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>So much for these transactions. They then
                    immediately began scheming to obtain the rest of the property and planned the
                    most outrageous plot of all, which merits your careful attention. Seeing that
                    Euctemon was completely incapacitated by old age and could not even leave his
                    bed, they began to look about for a means whereby all his property should be
                    under their control after his death. And what did they do? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>They inscribed these two boys before the archon as adopted children of the sons
                    of Euctemon who had died,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Philoctemon and
                        Ergamenes (cf. <bibl n="Isaeus 6.44">Isaeus 6.44</bibl>).</note> inscribing
                    themselves as guardians, and requested the archon to grant a lease of the
                    house-property as being the property of orphans, in order that part of the
                    property might be leased and part might be used as a security, and mortgage
                    notices adfixed to it in the children's names during the lifetime of Euctemon,
                    and they themselves might become lessees and receive the income. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>On the first day that the courts met, the archon put the lease up for auction and
                    they offered to lease the property. Certain persons, however, who were present,
                    denounced the plot to the relatives, and they came and informed the judges of
                    the real state of affairs. The result was that the judges voted against allowing
                    the houses to be leased. If the plot had not been detected, the whole property
                    would have been lost. Please call as witnesses those who were present.<quote
                        type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Before my opponents had made the woman's
                    acquaintance and plotted with her against Euctemon, he and his son Philoctemon
                    possessed so large a fortune that both of them were able to undertake the most
                    costly public offices without realizing any of their capital, and at the same
                    time to save out of their income, so that they continually grew richer. After
                    the death of Philoctemon, on the other hand, the property was reduced to such a
                    condition that less than half the capital remains and all the revenues have
                    disappeared. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>And they were not even content, gentlemen, with this misappropriation; but, when
                    Euctemon died, they had the impudence, while he was lying dead in the house, to
                    shut up the slaves, so that none of them might take the news to his two
                    daughters or to his wife or to any of his relatives. Meanwhile, with the aid of
                    the woman they conveyed the furniture from within to the adjoining house, which
                    was leased and occupied by one of their gang, the infamous Antidorus. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>When Euctemon's daughters and wife arrived, having learnt the news from others,
                    even then they refused them admittance and shut the door in their faces,
                    declaring that it was not their business to bury Euctemon. They only obtained
                    admittance with difficulty about sunset. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>When they entered, they found that he had been dead in the house for two days, as
                    the slaves declared, and that everything in the house had been carried off by
                    these people. While the women, as was right, were attending to the deceased, my
                    clients here immediately called the attention of those who had accompanied them
                    to the state of affairs in the house, and began by asking the slaves in their
                    presence to what place the furniture had been removed. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>When they replied that our opponents had conveyed it away to the next house, and
                    my clients immediately claimed the right to search the house in the proper legal
                    manner, and requested that the slaves who had removed it should be produced, our
                    opponents refused to accede to any of their just demands. And to prove that I am
                    speaking the truth, take and read these documents.<quote type="Depositions"
                            ><title>Depositions</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Having removed all this furniture from the house,
                    and sold so much property and kept the proceeds, and having further made away
                    with the revenue which accrued during that period, they yet expect to obtain
                    possession of what remains; and their impudence is such that, not daring to
                    bring a direct action, they lodged a protestation—as though it were a question
                    of legitimate children—which is at once false and in contradiction to their own
                    previous action. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>For, whereas they had inscribed the children before the archon, one as the son of
                    Philoctemon and the other as the son of Ergamenes, they have now stated in their
                    protestation that they are the sons of Euctemon. Yet if they were Euctemon's
                    legitimate sons and had afterwards been adopted,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">i.e., by Philoctemon and Ergamenes.</note> as our opponent
                    states, even so they cannot be described as the sons of Euctemon: for the law
                    does not allow the return of an adopted son to his original family, unless he
                    leaves a legitimate son in the family which he quits. So that in the light of
                    their own acts their evidence is necessarily untrue. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>If our opponents had then so contrived that the houses were leased, my clients
                    would no longer have been able to claim them; but, as it is, since the judges
                    decided against them as having no right, they have not dared to put in a claim,
                    but, to put the finishing touch to their impudence, they have submitted
                    additional evidence to the effect that these young men, whom you excluded by
                    your verdict, are heirs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Further, mark the effrontery and impudence of the
                    witness himself, who has claimed for himself Euctemon's daughter<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Namely, the widow of Chaeres, cf. <bibl
                            n="Isaeus 6.51">Isaeus 6.51</bibl>.</note> as being an heiress and a
                    fifth part<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The words <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >pe/mptou me/rous</foreign> are certainly corrupt: there is no reason in
                        law why a fifth part should have been claimed. No satisfactory emendation
                        has been proposed.</note> of Euctemon's estate as being adjudicable, while
                    he has given evidence that Euctemon has a legitimate son. In doing so does he
                    not clearly convict himself of having given false evidence? For obviously, if
                    Euctemon had a legitimate son, his daughter could not be heiress or the estate
                    adjudicable. To prove, then, that he made these claims, the clerk shall read you
                    the depositions.<quote type="Depositions"><title>Depositions</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Thus the contrary has been done of that which the
                    law has prescribed; for according to the law no male or female bastard has any
                    right, based on kinship, to participate in the cults or property of a family
                    since the archonship of Eucleides<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><dateRange
                            from="-403" to="-402">403</dateRange>-402 B.C.</note>; yet Androcles and
                    Antidorus consider themselves entitled to rob the legitimate daughters of
                    Euctemon and their issue, and to possess the property both of Euctemon and of
                    Philoctemon. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>And the woman who destroyed Euctemon's reason and laid hold of so much property
                    is so insolent, that relying on the help of our opponents, she shows her
                    contempt not only for the members of Euctemon's family but for the whole city.
                    When you have heard a single instance, you will easily realize the lawlessness
                    of her conduct. Please take and read this law.<quote type="Law"
                            ><title>Law</title></quote><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The law
                        here cited must have been that which excluded slaves and women of immoral
                        life from participating in the festival of the Thesmophoria celebrated in
                        honor of Demeter and Persephone (see <bibl n="Isaeus 3.80">Isaeus
                            3.80</bibl> and note.).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Such are the solemn and pious terms in which you
                    gave legal expression to the importance which you attach to piety towards these
                    goddesses and all the other deities. Yet the mother of these young men, being
                    admittedly a slave, and having always lived a scandalous life, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>who ought never to have entered the temple and seen any of the rites performed
                    there, had the effrontery to join in the procession when a sacrifice was being
                    made in honor of these goddesses and to enter the temple and see what she had no
                    right to see. That I am speaking the truth you will learn from the decrees which
                    the Council passed concerning her. Take this decree.<quote type="Decree"
                            ><title>Decree</title></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You have, therefore, gentlemen, to consider
                    whether this woman's son ought to he heir to Philoctemon's property and go to
                    the family tombs to offer libations and sacrifices, or my client, Philoctemon's
                    sister's son, whom he himself adopted; and whether Philoctemon's sister,
                    formerly the wife of Chaereas and now a widow, ought to pass into the power of
                    our opponents and be married to anyone they choose or else be allowed to grow
                    old in widowhood, or whether, as a legitimate daughter, she ought to be subject
                    to your decision as to whom she ought to marry. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>These are the points which you have now to decide by your verdict; for the
                    purpose of their protestation is to throw all the risk upon my clients, and that
                    our opponents, even if they lose their case on this occasion and the estate is
                    held to be adjudicable, may, by bringing forward a competing claim, fight a
                    second action about the same property. Yet if Philoctemon disposed of his
                    property by will when he was not entitled to do so, the point against which they
                    ought to have protested is that he was not legally capable of adopting my client
                    as his son; but if is lawful to make a will, and our opponent claims on the
                    ground that Philoctemon made no donation or will, he ought not to have hindered
                    proceedings by a protestation, but to have proceeded by means of a direct
                    action. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>As it is, what clearer method is there of convicting him of perjury than by
                    putting the following question to him: “How do you know, Androcles, that
                    Philoctemon neither made a will nor adopted Chaerestratus as his son?” For when
                    a man has been present, gentlemen, it is just that he should give evidence of
                    what he has seen, and when he has not been present but has heard someone else
                    describe what happened, he can give evidence by hearsay; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>but you, though you were not present, have given explicit evidence that
                    Philoctemon made no will and died childless. How, gentlemen, can he possibly
                    know this? It is as though he were to say, not having been present, that he
                    knows about all the acts of you all. Impudent as he is, he will scarcely assert
                    that he was present at and is acquainted with all the acts of Philoctemon's
                    life; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>for Philoctemon regarded him as his bitterest enemy, both because of his general
                    bad character, and because he was the only one of his kinsmen who, in league
                    with the infamous Alce, plotted with this friend of his<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">i.e., Antidorus.</note> and his other accomplices against
                    the property of Euctemon, and committed the acts which I have described to you.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But what calls for the greatest indignation is the
                    wicked use which our opponents make of the name of Euctemon, my client's
                    grandfather. For if, as they assert, Philoctemon had no right to make a will,
                    and the estate was Euctemon's, who have a better right to inherit Euctemon's
                    property? His daughters, who are admittedly legitimate, and we<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The speaker here associates himself with his clients.</note>
                    who are their sons? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>Or men who bear no relation to him, and whose claims are refuted not only by you
                    but also by the acts which they have themselves committed as guardians? For I
                    beg and earnestly beseech you, gentlemen, to remember the point which I put
                    before you a short while ago, that Androcles here declares that he is guardian
                    of my clients as being the legitimate sons of Euctemon, and has also himself
                    claimed for himself the estate of Euctemon and his daughter as heiress; and
                    evidence of this has been placed before you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>By the gods of <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>, is it not
                    extraordinary, gentlemen, that, if the children are legitimate, their guardian
                    should claim for himself the estate of Euctemon and his daughter as an heiress,
                    and, if they are not legitimate, that he should have given evidence now in
                    support of their legitimacy? For these acts are the very contrary of one
                    another; so that he is convicted of perjury not only by us but by his own acts.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>No one is putting in a protestation that the estate is not adjudicable, and
                    Androcles was at liberty to proceed by means of a direct action; now he is
                    depriving everyone else of their right to claim. Having explicitly stated in his
                    evidence that the children are legitimate, he thinks that you will be satisfied
                    with rhetorical digressions, and that if he does not attempt to prove his point
                    or dwells only very lightly upon it, but rails against us in a loud voice and
                    says that my clients are rich, while he is poor—all this will make it appear
                    that the children are legitimate. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>Now the family fortune, gentlemen, is being spent rather upon the city than upon
                    the members of the family themselves. Phanostratus has already been trierarch
                    seven times, and he has performed all the public services and has generally been
                    victorious. Chaerestratus here, young as he is, has been trierarch; he has been
                    choregus in the tragic competitions; he has been gymnasiarch at the torch-races.
                    Both of them have paid all the special war-taxes, being numbered among the three
                        hundred.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., the richest class.</note>
                    Formerly only these two members of the family contributed, but now the younger
                    son here is choregus in the tragic competitions and has been enrolled among the
                    three hundred and pays the war-tax. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
                <p>No grudge ought, therefore, to be felt against them, but rather, by Zeus and
                    Apollo, against our opponents, if they obtain what does not belong to them. If
                    the estate of Philoctemon is adjudicated to my client, he will hold it in trust
                    for you, performing all the public services which you lay upon him, as he has
                    done hitherto, and with even greater generosity. If, on the other hand, our
                    opponents receive it, they will squander it and then seek other victims. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I beseech you, therefore, gentlemen, in order that
                    you may not be misled, to give your careful attention to the protestation about
                    which you are going to give your verdict. Instruct him to make that the subject
                    of his defence, just as it has been the subject of our accusation. The text of
                    the protestation has stated that Philoctemon made no gift of property or will;
                    this has been proved to be false, for those who were present are witnesses that
                    he did so. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
                <p>What further do they say? That Philoctemon died childless. How could he be
                    childless, when he adopted and was survived by his own nephew, to whom the law
                    gives the right of inheritance just as much as to children of his own body?
                    Indeed, it is expressly stated in the law that, if children are born
                    subsequently to one who has adopted a son, each child takes his share of the
                    estate and both classes of children alike inherit. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="section">
                <p>Let Androcles, therefore, prove that the children are legitimate, as any one of
                    you would have to do in similar circumstances. His mere mention of a mother's
                    name does not suffice to make them legitimate, but he must prove that he is
                    speaking the truth by producing the relatives who know that she was married to
                    Euctemon, and the members of the deme and of the ward, if they have ever heard
                    or have any knowledge that Euctemon performed any public services on her behalf.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
                <p>We must know where she is buried and in what sort of tomb, and who has ever seen
                    Euctemon performing the customary rights over her, and whither her sons still go
                    to offer sacrifices and libations, and who of the citizens or of the slaves of
                    Euctemon has ever seen these rites being performed. It is all these details, and
                    not mere invective, which constitute a proof. If you bid him prove the actual
                    contention which is the subject of his protestation, youwill give a verdict
                    which accords with your oath and with the laws, and justice will be done to my
                    clients.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
