<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Philippides from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Hyperides</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>

            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Hyperides</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
                <refState unit="fragment"/>
            </refsDecl>

            <refsDecl n="speech=5">
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="fragment"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
<change><date>May 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>June 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>4/30/93</date><respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>add refdecl, changed some of the FRAG attributes that had commentary in them, made notes have a space after them.</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
            <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div type="fragment" n="1">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . in a free city furthering the interests of
                    tyrants . . . towards slavery . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="6">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . was responsible for actions which did credit
                    to the city and to <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The subject is perhaps <placeName
                            key="tgn,1123029">Conon</placeName>, an Athenian commander who was often
                        praised in this way. Compare <bibl n="Din. 1.14">Din. 1. 14</bibl> and
                        note.</note> Therefore both here and everywhere else he was paid the highest
                    honors . . . rightly . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="8">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . we must thank Alexander on account of those
                    who died . . . but I think. . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="10">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Moreover these men trample on the people in their
                    misfortune, and for this reason they deserve your hatred far more. For just as
                    human bodies need most care when they are sick, so it is with cities, which need
                    most attention in times of misfortune. To these men ?) only . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="11">
                <p>. . . [Very fragmentary.] </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="15a">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . each of them gives, one in <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, another in <placeName
                        key="perseus,Tanagra">Tanagra</placeName> . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="15b">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Or that they do not pray for the overthrow of all
                    that is left in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, when they are
                    deriving profits from the cities that are being destroyed? Or that, while they
                    wish you to spend your lives in fear and danger . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="fragment" n="21">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Unimpressive in person on account of his thinness.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>. . . make accusations. And they make it clear
                    that even when they were friends of the Lacedaemonians<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Hyperides may be alluding to the period from 378 to
                            <date>371</date> B.C., when <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> were at war with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
                            >Sparta</placeName>.</note> their speeches were prompted not by love for
                    them but by hatred of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and a
                    willingness to flatter those whose power at any time threatened you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>And when the power recently shifted from them to Philip they then chose to
                    flatter him and Democrates of <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna"
                        >Aphidna</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Democrates of
                            <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName> was a politician
                        whom Aeschines mentions (<bibl n="Aeschin. 2.17">Aeschin. 2. 17</bibl>;cf.
                            <bibl n="Isaeus 6.22">Isaeus 6. 22</bibl>). He had quite a reputation
                        for wit and some of his sayings are preserved. As a descendant of one of the
                        tyrant-slayers, probably of Aristogiton, who appears to have been a member
                        of the tribe <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName>, he
                        enjoyed free meals in the Prytaneum, a privilege to which apparently only
                        the eldest of each line was entitled (<title>CIA</title>1.8; 2. 240).</note>
                    who never leaves their sides . . . makes jokes on the city's misfortunes,
                    abusing you in the market place by day and then coming at evening to dine at
                    your table. And yet you, Democrates, are the one person who has no right to say
                    a single hard word against the state, for two reasons: </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>first because you needed no one but yourself to show you that the city is
                    grateful to her benefactors, you who now enjoy the honors for services which
                    other men once rendered; and secondly because the people drew up a law
                    forbidding anyone to speak ill of Harmodius and Aristogeiton or sing disparaging
                    songs about them.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Harmodius and Aristogiton are
                        mentioned again in <bibl n="Hyp. 6. 39">Hyp. 6. 39</bibl>. This particular
                        privilege is not elsewhere recorded.</note> It is therefore scandalous that,
                    though the people saw fit to prevent even a drunken man from abusing your
                    ancestors, you should be speaking ill of the state even when you are sober. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I have a few more points to make, gentlemen of the
                    jury, and after summing up my argument will leave the platform. The case in
                    which you are going to vote is an indictment for the proposing of illegal
                    measures and the decree under consideration is one congratulating
                        presidents.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In the 4th century B.C. the
                        chairman of the <foreign xml:lang="greek">pruta/neis</foreign> appointed
                        these presidents by lot, one from each tribe except that to which he himself
                        belonged, for each meeting of the Council or Assembly. After their
                        appointment he drew lots among them for their chairman (<foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">e)pista/ths</foreign>). (See <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.104"
                            >Aeschin. 1. 104</bibl>, <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.39">Aeschin. 3. 39</bibl>,
                        and <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 44.2">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 44.
                        2</bibl>.)</note> Presidents should observe the law during their period of
                    office. These men have broken it. As evidence for both these facts you heard the
                    actual laws read. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>The sequel now rests with you. For you will make it plain whether you are going
                    to punish the proposers of illegal measures or whether you intend to grant those
                    honors, which till now have been paid to your benefactors, to presidents whose
                    conduct is not lawful; and that too when you have sworn to observe the laws in
                    giving your vote. There is, however, one argument open to them, namely that the
                    people were compelled to pass the votes of honor.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">i. e., the votes of honor for certain Macedonians. Hyperides
                        agrees that it may have been impossible to avoid passing the votes of honor,
                        but that there was no need to congratulate the presidents for having done
                        so.</note> Even this cannot possibly mislead you; for it cannot be said that
                    we were under any compulsion to crown the presidents. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>Moreover the defendant has himself made your decision easy, since he stated in
                    writing his reasons for crowning them. They had, he said, been just towards the
                    Athenian people and observed the laws during their office. That is a statement
                    for which you must now summon him to answer. And you, Philippides, show us that
                    what you assumed about the presidents in your decree is true and you will be
                    acquitted. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>But if you think that your usual vulgarity and joking will secure your pardon in
                    court or win from these men any indulgence or sympathy to which you are not
                    entitled, you are a fool and very far from the mark. You see, you laid up
                    popularity for yourself, not in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, but elsewhere. You thought fit to cringe before those
                    whom the people feared rather than before the men who now have power to save
                    you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>You have concluded that one person will be immortal,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This passage is important for determining the date of the
                        speech. It has been held, e. g., by <placeName key="tgn,1029705"
                            >Kenyon</placeName>, that the remark is a gibe, in which there would be
                        no point unless Philip were already dead. But the use of the perfect tense
                            (<foreign xml:lang="greek">u(pei/lhfas</foreign>) seems to imply that he
                        was still living when Hyperides spoke, or had only just been killed.</note>
                    yet you sentenced to death a city as old as ours, never realizing the simple
                    fact that no tyrant has yet risen from the dead, while many cities, though
                    utterly destroyed, have come again to power. You and your party took no account
                    of the history of the Thirty or of the city's triumph over her assailants from
                    without and those within her walls who joined in the attack upon her.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The reference is to the return of the democrats
                        to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in <date>403</date>
                        B.C., under Thrasybulus, who had to contend both with the Spartans under
                        Lysander and with the Thirty.</note> It was well known that you were all
                    watching the city's fortunes, waiting for the chance to say or do something
                    against the people. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>Will you dare then presently to mention opportunities, when the opportunities you
                    sought were for the city's ruin? Have you brought your children with you into
                    court, Philippides?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For the bringing of
                        children into court compare <bibl n="Hyp. 4.41">Hyp. 4.41</bibl>.</note> Are
                    you going to bring them soon on to the platform and so claim pity from the jury?
                    You have no right to pity. When others felt compassion for the city's
                    misfortunes, you and your like were exulting over her.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">At the time of <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                            >Chaeronea</placeName> (<date>338</date> B.C.).</note> They had resolved
                    to save <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> in a spirit which ill
                    deserved the fate they met. But you, who are unjustly bringing <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> into the depths of shame, deserve
                    the punishment you are now about.to suffer. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>Why should you spare this man, gentlemen? Because he is a democrat? Why, you are
                    well aware that he has chosen to be the slave of tyrants and is ready on the
                    other hand to give the people orders. Would it be because he is a good man? No;
                    for you twice condemned him as a criminal. True, you may say, but he is useful.
                    Granted; but if you use a man whom you are known to have condemned as wicked, it
                    will appear either that your judgements are wrong or that you welcome wicked
                    men. It is not therefore right to take upon yourselves this man's misdeeds. On
                    the contrary: the transgressor must be punished. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>And if anyone comes forward with the plea that he has twice before been convicted
                    for illegal proposals and that therefore you should acquit him,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The penalties for illegal proposals and for giving false
                        witness seem to have been the same, although the exact rules governing them
                        in the 4th century B.C. are not quite clear. In the 5th century a man three
                        times convicted of false witness was automatically disfranchised (See <bibl
                            n="Andoc. 1.74">Andoc. 1.74</bibl>), and the present passage suggests
                        that in the 4th century too a third conviction led to partial <foreign
                            xml:lang="greek">a)timi/a</foreign>. (Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 51.12">Dem.
                            51.12</bibl> and <bibl n="Plat. Laws 937">Plat. Laws. 937 c</bibl>,
                        evidently inspired by current Athenian practice.) The actual penalty seems
                        to have been a fine; but if this was not paid the prosecutor had the right
                        to enforce the judgement by a suit of ejection(<foreign xml:lang="greek"
                            >di/kh e)cou/lhs</foreign>) and thus partially disfranchise the culprit.
                        (See <bibl n="Isoc. 16.47">Isoc. 16. 47</bibl>.) When orators speak as if
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)timi/a</foreign> were inevitable after any
                        conviction they are probably exaggerating.</note> please do just the
                    opposite, and that for two reasons. In the first place it is a piece of good
                    fortune, when a man is known to have proposed illegal measures, that you should
                    catch him coming up for trial a third time. He is not a good man and need not be
                    spared as such. Indeed you should rid yourselves of him as quickly as you can,
                    since he has twice already proved his character to you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>And secondly, compare the case of false witness. If people have been twice
                    convicted of this, you have allowed them to refrain from giving evidence a third
                    time, even of events at which they have themselves been present, so that, if
                    anyone is disfranchised, responsibility shall rest, not on the people, but on
                    the man himself, for continuing to bear false witness. Similarly men convicted
                    of illegal proposals need not bring forward proposals in future. If they do they
                    are clearly actuated by some private motive. So that people of this type deserve
                    punishment, not pity. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>I do not wish to speak too long after setting myself as a limit an amphora of
                    water in the clock; so the clerk will read you the indictment again. And now
                    bear in mind the accusations and the laws which you heard read and bring in a
                    verdict that will be just and also expedient for yourselves.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
