<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Aegineticus from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg006.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I was of opinion, citizens of Aegina, that Thrasylochus had arranged his affairs so
          prudently that no one should ever come before a court to bring a suit in opposition to the
          will which he left. But since my adversaries have determined to contest a testament so
          purposefully drawn, I am compelled to try to obtain my rights from you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>My feeling is unlike that of most men. For I see that others are indignant when they are
          unjustly involved in a law-suit, whereas I am almost grateful to my opponents for bringing
          me into this trial.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A commonplace; cf. <bibl n="Lys. 16.1"
              >Lys. 16.1-2</bibl>; <bibl n="Lys. 24.1">Lys. 24.1</bibl>.</note> For if the matter
          had not been brought before a tribunal you would not have known of my devotion to the
          deceased, which led to my being made his heir; but when you learn the facts you will all
          perceive that I might justly have been thought worthy of even a greater reward. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The proper course, however, for the woman who is laying claim to the property would have
          been, not to try to obtain from you the estate left by Thrasylochus, but to show that she
          also was devoted to him and on that ground thought fit to bring suit for it. But the truth
          is, she is so far from repenting of her misconduct towards Thrasylochus in his life-time,
          that now too that he is dead she is trying to annul his will and to leave the home without
          heirs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And I am astonished that those who are acting in her behalf think this action is
          reputable, just because, if they fail to win, they will need to pay no penalty. For my
          part, I think that it will be a severe penalty, if, having been convicted of making a
          wrongful claim, they shall thereafter suffer in your esteem. However, you will know the
          baseness of these men from their very acts when you have heard to the end what they have
          done; and I shall begin the recital of them at the point from which, in my opinion, you
          will be able to learn most quickly the matters at issue. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Thrasyllus, the father of the testator, had inherited nothing from his parents; but
          having become the guest-friend of Polemaenetus, the soothsayer, he became so intimate with
          him that Polemaenetus at his death left to him his books on divination and gave him a
          portion of the property which is now in question. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Thrasyllus, with these books as his capital, practised the art of divination. He became
          an itinerant soothsayer, lived in many cities, and was intimate with several women, some
          of whom had children whom he never even recognized as legitimate, and, in particular,
          during this period he lived with the mother of the complainant. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>When he had acquired a large fortune and yearned for his fatherland, he left this woman
          and the others as well, and debarking at Siphnos married a sister of my father. Thrasyllus
          himself was indeed the leading citizen in wealth, but he knew that our family was likewise
          pre-eminent in lineage and in general standing; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and he cherished so warmly my father's affection for him that at the death of his wife,
          who was without children, he remarried, taking as wife my father's cousin, as he did not
          wish to dissolve the affinity with us. But after he had lived with her for only a short
          time, he suffered the same bereavement as his former wife. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>After this he married a woman of Seriphos, belonging to a family of greater consequence
          than might be expected of a native of their island.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            insignificance of Seriphos was proverbial; cf. <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 329e">Plat. Rep.
              329e</bibl>.</note> Of this marriage were born Sopolis, Thrasylochus, and a daughter,
          who is my wife. These were the only legitimate children left by Thrasyllus and he made
          these his heirs when he died. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Thrasylochus and I, having inherited from our fathers a friendship the intimacy of which
          I have recently mentioned, made the bond still closer. For during our childhood we were
          fonder of each other than of our brothers, and we would perform no sacrifice, make no
          pilgrimage, and celebrate no festival except in one another's company; and when we reached
          manhood we never opposed one another in any action undertaken, for we not only shared our
          private concerns but also held similar sentiments regarding public affairs, and we had the
          same intimates and guest-friends. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And why need I speak further of our intimacy at home?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That
            is, at Siphnos.</note> In truth, not even in exile did we care to be apart. Finally,
          when Thrasylochus was striken with the wasting disease and suffered a long illness—his
          brother Sopolis had previously died<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Sopolis died in Lycia
            (cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 19.40">Isoc. 19.40</bibl>).</note> and his mother and sister had not
            arrived<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At Aegina.</note>—seeing him so completely
          destitute of companionship I nursed him with such unremitting care and devotion that he
          thought he could never repay me with a gratitude adequate to my services; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless he left nothing undone to reward me, and when he was in a grievous condition
          and had given up all hope of life, he summoned witnesses, made me his adoptive son, and
          gave me his sister and his fortune. Please take the will. <quote type="Will"/> Read to
          me also the law of Aegina; for it was necessary that the will be drawn in accordance with
          this law, since we were alien residents of this island. <quote type="Law"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It was in accordance with this law, citizens of Aegina, that Thrasylochus adopted me as
          his son, for I was his fellow-citizen and friend, in birth inferior to no one of the
          Siphnians, and had been reared and educated very much as he himself had been. I therefore
          do not see how he could have acted more consistently with the law, since the law insists
          that persons of the same status may be adopted. Please take also the law of Ceos,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The law of Ceos was valid also in Siphonos.</note> under which
          we were living.<quote type="Law"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If ,therefore, citizens of Aegina, my opponents were refusing to recognize the validity
          of these laws, but were able to produce in support of their case the law of their own
          country, their conduct would have been less astonishing. But the truth is that their own
          law is in agreement with those already read. Please take this document.<quote type="Law"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> What argument is left to them, therefore, since they themselves admit that Thrasylochus
          left the will and that they can cite no law in their favor, whereas all support my
          case—first, the law which is valid among you who are to adjudge the case, next, the law of
          Siphnos, the fatherland of the testator, and finally the law of the country of my
          opponents? And yet from what illegal act do you think these persons would abstain,
          inasmuch as they seek to persuade you that you should declare this will valid, although
          the laws read as you have heard and you have taken oath to cast your votes in conformity
          with them? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> On the issue itself I consider that I have adduced sufficient proof; but that no one may
          think that my possession of the inheritance rests upon feeble grounds, or that this woman
          had been kindly in her behavior toward Thrasylochus and is being defrauded of his fortune,
          I wish also to discuss these matters. For I should be ashamed in behalf of the deceased
          unless you were all convinced that his actions were strictly in accordance, not only with
          the law, but also with justice. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And I believe that proof of this is easy. There was, in truth, this great difference
          between us—that this woman, who bases her contention on the ground of relationship, never
          ceased to be at variance with the testator and evilly-disposed toward him and toward
          Sopolis and their mother, whereas I shall be shown to have been the most deserving of all
          his friends, not only in my relations with Thrasylochus and his brother, but also with
          regard to the estate in controversy. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It would be a long story to tell of the events of long ago; but when Pasinus<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">An unknown person.</note> took Paros, it chanced that my
          friends had the greatest part of their fortune deposited as a pledge with my guest-friends
          there; for we thought that this island was by far the safest. When they were at their
          wits' end and believed that their property was lost, I sailed thither by night and got
          their money out at risk of my life; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for the country was occupied by a garrison, and some of the exiles from our island
          participated in the seizure of the city, and these, in one day and with their own hands,
          had slain my father, my uncle, my brother-in-law and, in addition, three cousins. However,
          I was deterred by none of these risks, but I took ship, thinking I ought to run the risk
          as much for my friends' sake as for my own. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Afterwards when a general flight from the city<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Siphnos.</note> ensued, accompanied by such confusion and fear that some persons were
          indifferent even to the fate of their own relations, I was not content, even in these
          misfortunes, merely to be able to save the members of my own household, but knowing that
          Sopolis was absent and Thrasylochus was in feeble health, I helped him to convey from the
          country his mother, his sister, and all his fortune. And yet who with greater justice
          should possess this fortune than the person who then helped to save it and now has
          received it from its legitimate owners? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have related the adventures in which I incurred danger indeed, yet suffered no harm;
          but I have also to speak of friendly services I rendered him which involved me in the
          greatest misfortunes. For when we had arrived at Melos, and Thrasylochus perceived that we
          were likely to remain there, he begged me to sail with him to Troezen<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">On the southern coast of the Saronic Gulf, in the northeastern part of the
            Peloponnese, near Epidaurus.</note> and by all means not to abandon him, mentioning his
          bodily infirmity and the multitude of his enemies, saying that without me he would not
          know how to manage his own affairs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And although my mother was afraid because she had heard that Troezen was unhealthy and
          our guest-friends advised us to remain where we were, nevertheless we decided that we
          ought to satisfy his wish. No sooner had we arrived at Troezen than we were attacked by
          illnesses of such severity that I barely escaped with my own life, and within thirty days
          I buried my young sister fourteen years of age, and my mother not five days therereafter.
          In what state of mind do you think I was after such a change in my life? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I had previously been inexperienced in misfortune and I had only recently suffered exile
          and living an alien among foreigners, and had lost my fortune; in addition, I saw my
          mother and my sister driven from their native land and ending their lives in a foreign
          land among strangers. No one could justly begrudge it me, therefore, if I have received
          some benefit from the troublesome affairs of Thrasylochus; for it was to gratify him that
          I went to live in Troezen, where I experienced misfortunes so dire that I shall never be
          able to forget them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Furthermore, there is one thing my opponents cannot say of me—that when Thrasylochus was
          prosperous I suffered all these woes, but that I abandoned him in his adversity. For it
          was precisely then that I gave clearer and stronger proof of my devotion to him. When, for
          instance, he settled in Aegina and fell ill of the malady which resulted in his death, I
          nursed him with a care such as no one else I know of has ever bestowed upon another. Most
          of the time he was very ill, yet still able to go about; finally he lay for six months
          bedridden. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And no one of his relations saw fit to share with me the drudgery of caring for him; no
          one even came to see him with the exception of his mother and sister; and they made the
          task more difficult; for they were ill when they came from Troezen, so that they
          themselves were in need of care. But although the others were thus indifferent, I did not
          grow weary nor did I leave the scene, but I nursed him with the help of one slave boy;
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for no one of the domestics could stand it. For being by nature irascible, he became,
          because of his malady, still more difficult to handle. It should not occasion surprise,
          therefore, that these persons would not remain with him, but it is much more a cause for
          wonder that I was able to hold out in caring for a man sick of such a malady; for he was
          filled with pus for a long time, and was unable to leave his bed; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and his suffering was so great that we did not pass a single day without tears,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 14.47">Isoc. 14.47</bibl> for the same
            expression.</note> but kept up our lamentations both for the hardships we both had to
          endure, and for our exile and our isolation. And there was no intermission at any time;
          for it was impossible to leave him or to seem to neglect him—to me this would have seemed
          more dreadful than the woes which afflicted us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I wish I could make clearly apparent to you my conduct with respect to him; for in that
          case I think that you would not endure even a word from my opponents. The truth is, it is
          not easy to describe the duties involved in my care of the invalid, duties that were very
          hard, very difficult to endure, most disagreeably toilsome, and exacting an unremitting
          care. But do you yourselves consider what loss of sleep, what miseries are the inevitable
          accompaniment of a prolonged nursing of a malady like his. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In truth, in my own case, I was reduced to such a condition that all my friends who
          visited me expressed fear that I too would perish with the dying man and they advised me
          to take care, saying that the majority of those who had nursed this disease themselves
          fell victims to it also. My reply to them was this—that I would much prefer to die than to
          see him perish before his fated day for lack of a friend to nurse him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And although my behavior was as I have described, this woman has had the hardihood to
          contest with me his fortune, she who never even saw fit to visit him during his long
          illness, though she had daily information about his condition, and though the journey was
          easy for her. To think that they will now attempt to “brother” him,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed"><foreign xml:lang="greek">A)DELFI/ZEIN</foreign>, a rare word, “to call
            brother.”</note> as if the effect of calling the dead man by a mane of closer kinship
          would not be to make her shortcomings seem worse and more shocking! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Why, when he was at the point of death, and when she saw all our fellow-citizens who were
          in Troezen sailing to Aegina to take part in his funeral, she did not even at that moment
          come, but was so cruel and heartless in conduct that while she did not see fit to come to
          his funeral, yet, less than ten days thereafter she arrived to claim the property he had
          left, as if she were related to his money and not to him! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And if she will admit that her hatred for him was so bitter that this conduct was
          reasonable, then Thrasylochus would be considered not to have been ill-advised in
          preferring to leave his property to his friends rather than to this woman; but if there
          existed no variance between them and yet she was so neglectful of him and so unkind toward
          him, surely with greater justice would she be deprived of her own possessions than become
          heir to his. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Bear in mind that, so far as she was concerned, he had no care during his illness, nor
          when he died was he thought worthy of the customary funeral rites, whereas it was through
          me that he obtained both. Surely you will justly cast your votes in favor, not of those
          who claim blood-relationship yet in their conduct have acted like enemies, but with much
          greater propriety you will side with those who, though having no title of relationship,
          yet showed themselves, when the deceased was in misfortune, more nearly akin than the
          nearest relatives. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> My opponents say that they do not doubt that Thrasylochus left the will, but they assert
          that it is not honorable and proper. And yet, citizens of Aegina, how could anyone have
          given better or greater evidence of interest in the disposal of his own property? He did
          not leave his home without heirs and he has shown due gratitude to his friends and,
          further, he made his mother and his sister possessors, not only of their own property, but
          of mine also by giving the latter to me as wife and by making me, by adoption, the son of
          the former. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Would he have acted more wisely if he had taken the alternative course—if he had failed
          to appoint a protector for his mother, and if he had made no mention of me, but had
          abandoned his sister to chance and permitted the name of his family to perish? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But perhaps I was unworthy of being adopted as a son by Thrasylochus and of receiving
          his sister in marriage. All the Siphnians would bear witness, however, that my ancestors
          were foremost of the citizens there in birth, in wealth, in reputation, and in general
          standing. For who were thought worthy of higher offices, or made greater contributions, or
          served as choregi<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A choregus was a citizen who defrayed the
            expenses of bringing out a chorus. It is of interest to learn that the institution of
            the choregia was in effect on the island of Sophnos, as it was also at Ceos.</note> more
          handsomely, or discharged other special public services with greater magnificence? What
          family in Siphnos has furnished more kings?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">These “kings”
            probably had only religious functions; cf. the Archon Basileus at Athens.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Thrasylochus, therefore, even if I had never spoken to him, would reasonably have wished
          to give his sister to me just for these reasons; and I, even if I had not possessed any of
          these advantages, but had been the lowest of the citizens, would justly have been esteemed
          by him as deserving of the greatest recompenses by reason of the services I had rendered
          him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I believe, moreover, that in making this disposition of his estate he did what was most
          pleasing to his brother Sopolis also. For Sopolis also hated this woman and regarded her
          as ill-disposed toward his interests, whereas he valued me above all his friends. He
          showed this feeling for me in many ways and in particular when our companions in exile
          determined, with the help of their auxiliary troops, to capture the city. For when he was
          designated leader with full powers he both chose me as secretary and appointed me
          treasurer of all funds, and when we were about to engage in battle, he placed me next to
          himself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And consider how greatly he profited thereby; for when our attack on the city met with
          ill success, and the retreat did not succeed as we desired, and when he was wounded,
          unable to walk and in a faint condition, I and my servant carried him off on our shoulders
          to the ship. Consequently he often said to many persons that I was solely responsible for
          his coming through alive. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Yet what greater benefaction than this could a man receive? Moreover, when he had sailed
          to Lycia and died there, this woman, a few days after the news of his death, was
          sacrificing and holding festival, and had no shame before his surviving brother, so little
          regard did she have for the dead man, but I instituted mourning for him in the custom
          prescribed for relatives. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And it was my character and my affection for the two brothers that moved me to do all
          this and not any expectation of this trial; for I did not think that both would come to
          such an unhappy end that by dying without children they were going to oblige us to prove
          how each one of us had felt and acted toward them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> How this woman and myself conducted ourselves toward Thrasylochus and Sopolis you have,
          in the main heard; but perhaps they will have recourse to the one argument which remains
          to them—that Thrasyllus, the father of this woman, will feel that he is being dishonored
          (if the dead have any perception of happenings in this world)<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">A frequent sentiment in Greek literature; cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 14.61">Isoc.
              14.61</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 9.2">Isoc. 9.2</bibl>.</note> when he sees his
          daughter being deprived of her fortune and me becoming the heir of what he had
            acquired.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This passage is interesting as an example of an
            orator's anticipation( anticipatio or <foreign xml:lang="greek">PROKATA/LHYIS</foreign>)
            of an opponent's argument.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But I am of opinion that it is proper for us to speak here, not concerning those who died
          long ago, but of those who recently left their heritage. As to Thrasyllus, he left as
          possessors of his estate the persons of his choice; and it is only just, then, that to
          Thrasylochus also the same privilege should be granted by you, and that not this woman,
          but those whom he designated in his will, should become the successors to the inheritance.
          However, I do not believe that I need evade the judgement of Thrasyllus. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>He would be, I think, the most harsh judge of all for her, if he knows how she has
          treated his children. If you should vote in accordance with the laws, he would be far from
          taking offense, but he would be far more incensed if he should see the testaments of his
          children annulled. If, for instance, Thrasylochus had given property to my family, they
          would have had reason to lay that up against him; as it is, he adopted into his own
          family, so that the plaintiffs have not received less than they gave.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">i.e., all the property has been kept in the family since the continuity of the
            family had been assured by the adoption of the speaker.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Apart from this, it is reasonable to suppose that Thrasyllus, more than anyone else, was
          friendly toward those whose claims are based upon a testamentary gift. For he himself
          learned his art from Polemaenetus the soothsayer, and received his fortune, not through
          family relationship but through merit; surely, therefore, he would not complain if a man
          who had acted honorably toward his children should be regarded as deserving of the same
          reward as himself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>You should call to mind also what I said in the beginning. For I pointed out to you that
          he esteemed relationship with our family so highly that he married the sister and then the
          cousin of my father. And yet to whom would he more willingly have given his own daughter
          in marriage than to that family from which he himself chose his wife? And from what family
          would he have more gladly seen a son adopted according to law than that from which he
          sought to beget children of his own body? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If therefore, you award the inheritance to me, you will stand well with Thrasyllus and
          with all others who have any proper interest in this matter; but if you permit yourselves
          to be deceived by the persuasion of this woman, not only will you do injury to me, but
          also to Thrasylochus, the testator, and to Sopolis, and to their sister, who is now my
          wife, and their mother, who would be the unhappiest of women if it should not be enough
          for her to have lost her children, but also must see this additional sorrow that their
          wishes are nullified, her family without an heir, and this woman, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>as she exults over her misfortunes, making good at law her claim to the property, while I
          am unable to obtain my just rights, although my treatment of her sons has been such that,
          if anyone should compare me—I will not say with this woman, but with any who have ever
          entered their claim to an inheritance on the strength of testamentary gift—I should be
          found to have been inferior to none in my conduct toward my friends. And yet men of my
          kind ought to be honored and esteemed rather than be robbed of the gifts which others have
          bestowed upon them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It is expedient, to, that you should uphold the law which permits us to adopt children
          and to dispose wisely of our property, reflecting that for men who are childless this law
          takes the place of children; for it is owing this law that both kinsmen and those who are
          not related take greater care of each other. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But that I may conclude and occupy no more time in speaking, pray consider how strong
          and how just are the claims with which I have come before you; there is, first, my
          friendship with those who have left the inheritance, a friendship of ancient origin,
          handed down from our fathers, and in all that time never broken; second, my many great
          acts of kindness done for them in their adversity; third, there is a will which my
          opponents themselves acknowledge; and lastly, the law, which supports the will, a law that
          in the opinion of all Greeks is regarded as wisely made. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Of my statement the best proof is this—although the Greek states differ in opinion about
          many other enactments, they are of one accord concerning this one. I beg you, therefore,
          bearing in mind both these considerations and the others I have mentioned, to give a just
          verdict, and prove yourselves to be for me such judges as you would want to have for
          yourselves.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
