<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Leochares</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <p>
                <div type="section" n="1">It is the fault of
                Leochares, the defendant, men of the jury, that he is himself being brought to
                trial, and that I, despite my youth, am addressing you, for he claims the right to
                inherit what does not belong to him, and has made a false affidavit of objections
                before the archon in support of his claim. </div><div type="section" n="2">It was
                incumbent upon us—since the law grants the right of succession to those nearest of
                kin, and we are relatives of Archiades, who originally left the estate—not to suffer
                his house to become extinct, and others, who had no right whatever to it, to inherit
                his property; while the defendant, who was neither a son by blood of the deceased
                nor a son adopted according to your laws, as I shall show, has thus recklessly made
                a false affidavit, and is seeking to rob me of the inheritance. <milestone
                    type="section" n="3">I beg you, men of the jury, to come to the aid of my
                father and myself, if our pleading shall seem just, and not suffer men who are poor
                and without influence to be crushed by the lawless men marshalled against us. For we
                have come before you relying upon the truth, well content if we are permitted to
                obtain our legal rights; while our adversaries have from the first never ceased to
                rely upon intrigue and the spending of money, and very naturally in my opinion; for
                they readily make expenditures from funds which belong to others, and so have
                provided themselves with a host of people who will speak in their behalf and give
                false testimony. </div><div type="section" n="4">My father here ( for the truth
                shall be told you) comes into court with manifest signs that he is, as you are all
                aware, a poor man, and that he knows nothing of pleading in court; for he has long
                been a public crier in Peiraeus, and this is not only a sign of the poverty which is
                common to man, but also of the fact that he has no time to meddle with the law; for
                a man so employed has to spend the whole day in the market-place. If you bear this
                in mind, you will be forced to conclude that, if we did not rely upon the justice of
                our cause, we should never have come before you at all. </div><div type="section"
                    n="5">With reference to matters of this nature
                you will gain clearer information in the course of my address, but I think I must
                now inform you about the affidavit and the case at issue. If, men of the jury,
                Leochares, basing his defence upon the affidavit itself, were going to prove that he
                is the lawfully born son of Archiades, there would be no need of many words, nor any
                need that I should trace our family line back to its origin; <milestone
                    type="section" n="6">but since the matters sworn to in the affidavit are of a
                different nature, and most of the arguments of our adversaries will be devoted to
                proving that they were adopted and should properly inherit the estate by right of
                descent as lawful children, it is necessary for this reason, men of the jury, to go
                back a little way and instruct you regarding the pedigree; for when you understand
                this matter clearly, there will be no danger of your being misled by their
                arguments. </div><div type="section" n="7">Very well then, the case before you is
                one to settle the title to an inheritance. Our claim to the estate is based upon
                descent, theirs upon adoption. We admit here in your presence that all adoptions, if
                rightly made in accordance with the laws, ought to be valid. Bear in mind,
                therefore, the bases upon which our respective claims rest, and if they prove to you
                that the laws grant what they have sworn in their affidavit, adjudge the estate to
                them. </div><div type="section" n="8">And even if they have not the support of the
                laws, but it seems to you that what they say is in accordance with justice and
                generosity, even so we withdraw our claim. However, that you may know that, while we
                are by descent the nearest of kin, we do not rest our case upon this alone, but upon
                all the other grounds as well, I will first instruct you regarding the family itself
                from which the inheritance comes; for I am sure that, if you follow with clear
                understanding this phase of the matter at issue, you will have no difficulty in
                grasping any of the other facts. </div><div type="section" n="9"><milestone ed="P"
                    unit="para">To go back to the beginning, men of the jury, there were born to
                Euthymachus, of Otrynê,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note 1 above.</note>
                three sons, Meidylides and Archippus and Archiades, and a daughter whose name was
                Archidicê. After the death of their father the brothers gave Archidicê in marriage
                to Leostratus of <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName><note
                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>
                    was a deme of the tribe Hippothontis.</note> ; of the three brothers Archippus
                lost his life at <placeName key="perseus,Methymna">Methymna</placeName><note
                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Methymna"
                        >Methymna</placeName> was a town in <placeName key="tgn,7002672"
                        >Lesbos</placeName>.</note> while serving as trierarch, and Meidylides not
                long afterward married Mnesimache, the daughter of Lysippus of Crioa.<note
                    resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Crioa was a deme of the tribe Antiochis.</note>
                </div><div type="section" n="10">To him there was born a daughter, Cleitomachê by
                name, whom he wished to give in marriage to his own brother, who was still
                unmarried; but since Archiades declared that he did not wish to marry, and for this
                reason allowed the property to remain undivided, and lived by himself in <placeName
                    key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, Meidylides at length gave his daughter in
                marriage to Aristoteles of Pallenê,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Pallenê was a
                    deme of the tribe Antiochis.</note> my grandfather. Of them were born three
                sons, Aristodemus here, my father, and Habronichus, my uncle, and Meidylides, who is
                now dead. Our right of inheritance, based on kinship in the family to which the
                estate belongs, is, men of the jury, substantially this. </div><div type="section"
                    n="11">For we are the nearest of kin to Archiades in the male line, and, as we
                deemed it right according to this law that we should inherit his estate, and not
                allow the family to be brought to extinction, we brought suit for the inheritance
                before the archon. Our opponents, who hold the property without right, have now
                filed an affidavit of objections, basing their entire claim upon adoption, but
                alleging also that they are near of kin. </div><div type="section" n="12">Now, with
                regard to this adoption, we will show you plainly later on what its character was;
                but with reference to blood relationship, I must prove to you that they are not
                nearer of kin than we. One thing is admitted, that in the matter of inheritance
                males and those descended from males have the precedence, for the law explicitly
                gives the inheritance as their due to the nearest of kin in the male line, when
                there are no children. Well, it is we who answer this description; for Archiades is
                admitted to have died without issue, and we are the nearest of kin to him in the
                male line. </div><div type="section" n="13">And furthermore, we are also his
                nearest of kin in the female line; for Meidylides was the brother of Archiades, and
                the daughter of Meidylides was the mother of my father, so that Archiades, for whose
                inheritance we are now prosecuting our claim, is uncle ( their fathers having been
                brothers) to the mother of my father, having this relationship in the male line, not
                in the female line. But Leostratus here is in kinship further removed, and is
                related to Archiades on the female side; for the mother of Leocrates, the father of
                the defendant, was niece to the Archiades in question and to Meidylides, as
                descendants of whom we claim the right to win the inheritance. <milestone
                    type="section" n="14">First, men of the jury, to
                prove that our pedigree is as I have stated, the clerk shall read you the
                depositions, and thereafter the law itself which awards inheritances to the families
                and to those nearest of kin in the male line. For, I take it, these are the
                essential points in the case and the matters upon which you cast your vote under
                    oath.Call the witnesses up here, please, and read
                the law.<quote type="Witnesses">
                    <title>Witnesses</title>
                </quote><quote type="Law">
                    <title>Law</title>
                </quote>
                </div><div type="section" n="15">Matters concerning
                their pedigree and concerning ours, men of the jury, stand thus, and so it is right
                that those who have proved on the basis of the affidavits themselves that they are
                nearer of kin, should have the inheritance, and that the madness of the one who made
                the affidavit of objections should not prove stronger than your laws. For if they
                lay stress on the adoption, the nature of which I shall make clear to you, yet
                surely after the death without issue of the adopted son, when the house up to the
                filing of our suit had become extinct, it is right that those who are nearest of kin
                should receive the inheritance, and that you should give your aid, not to those
                citizens who are able to get up the strongest backing, but to those who are
                suffering wrong. </div><div type="section" n="16">If it had been in our power,
                after setting forth matters regarding the pedigree and the affidavit itself, to
                leave the platform, and to have no need of further words, since practically the most
                important arguments would have been advanced, we should not trouble you further. But
                since our opponents will not rely upon the laws, but through having forestalled us
                and got some control of the situation long ago, and through having entered into
                possession of the estate, will use these facts as proofs, and declare that they are
                the heirs, it is perhaps necessary to discuss these matters as well, and to prove
                that of all humankind our opponents are the most arbitrary. <milestone
                    type="section" n="17">To go back to the
                beginning, men of the jury, Meidylides and Archiades gave their sister in marriage
                to Leostratus of Eleusis; and after a time from this sister of theirs, thus given in
                marriage, there was born Leocrates, the Iather of the defendant Leostratus; observe
                how distantly related he is to Archiades, regarding whom they have filed the
                affidavit of objections. When matters were as I have stated, Archiades did not
                marry, but his brother Meidylides, the grandfather of my father here, did marry.
                    </div><div type="section" n="18">They made as yet no division of the property,
                but, both having enough to live on, Meidylides continued to live in the city, and
                Archiades made his home in Salamis. Not long afterward, when Meidylides, my father's
                grandfather, happened to go on a journey out of the country, Archiades fell sick,
                and died during the absence of Meidylides, being still unmarried. What is the proof
                of this? A maiden bearing an urn for water<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">We are
                    told by <bibl n="Poll. 8.66">Pollux Onomasticon 8.66</bibl> that the figure of a
                    maiden bearing a water-pitcher was placed over the tombs of men who died
                    unmarried. Other authorities state that the figure was that of a youth, not of a
                    maiden.</note> stands upon the tomb of Archiades. </div><div type="section"
                    n="19">At this juncture Leocrates, the father of Leostratus here, on the
                pretext of his relationship on the female side, got himself adopted as son to
                Archiades, and so entered into possession of the estate, as though he had been
                adopted by Archiades during his lifetime. When Meidylides returned, he was incensed
                at what had been done, and was in a mood to enter suit against Leocrates; but under
                the persuasion of his relatives and their pleas that he should suffer Leocrates to
                remain in the family as the son by adoption of Archiades, he yielded the point,—not
                through losing his case in court, but absolutely through being deceived by these men
                here and partly also through giving way to the persuasion of his relatives.
                    </div><div type="section" n="20">After this experience Meidylides died, and
                Leocrates continued in possession of the estate of Archiades, and conducted himself
                as heir for many years, as being his adopted son; and we, on our part, inasmuch as
                Meidylides had made this concession, refrained from action. No long time afterwards,
                however,—and now, men of the jury, pay close heed to what I am about to say—
                    </div><div type="section" n="21">Leocrates, who had become son by adoption to
                Archiades, himself returned to the Eleusinians, to whom he originally belonged,
                leaving Leostratus here in the family as a lawfully born son. Even then we did not
                as yet disturb any of the arrangements regarding the estate, but continued as
                before. </div><div type="section" n="22">Well now, Leostratus here, although he was
                an adopted son and had been left in the family of Archiades, himself returned, as
                his father had done, to the Eleusinians, leaving in his place a lawfully born son,
                and, in defiance of the laws, setting up the original adoption as valid through the
                lives of three persons. </div><div type="section" n="23">For how could it be other
                than contrary to the laws, when one, being himself an adopted son, returned to his
                original family leaving adopted sons in his place? That is what Leostratus has done
                up to this day, and by this means they think to rob us of our inheritance, making
                profit from the estate of Archiades, and supporting their children by it, and always
                returning from it to the estate of their fathers, keeping that intact, while
                spending the other. </div><div type="section" n="24"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"
                />Nevertheless, although matters were in this condition, as I have told you, we
                submitted to everything. Until when? Until Leocrates, who had been left by
                Leostratus in the house as a son, died without issue. But since he died without
                issue, we, who are nearest of kin to Archiades, claim to inherit the property; and
                we claim that the defendant cannot, in order to rob us of what is ours, give an
                adopted son to the dead man who was himself adopted. </div><div type="section"
                    n="25">For if Leocrates had himself adopted a son during his lifetime, even
                though the action was contrary to law, we should have made no protest; but since he
                had no son born to him, nor had adopted one during his lifetime, and as the law
                gives inheritances to the nearest of kin, how can it be other than right that we
                should not be robbed of this inheritance, to which we have a double title?
                    </div><div type="section" n="26">For we are nearest of kin to Archiades, to
                whom the property originally belonged, and also to the adopted Leocrates; for his
                father, seeing that he has returned to the Eleusinians,<note resp="Loeb"
                    anchored="true">This does not indicate a mere change of residence. He renounced
                    his membership in the deme Otrynê, and resumed membership in the Eleusinian
                    deme. By so doing, he relinquished the former legal relationship.</note> no
                longer retained his legal relationship, whereas we, to whose family he had come to
                belong, had the closest relationship, being children of that father's first cousin.
                So, if you like, we claim the inheritance as kinsmen of Archiades, or, if you like
                it better, as kinsmen of Leocrates; for since he died without issue, no one is
                nearer of kin than we. </div><div type="section" n="27">So far as you are
                concerned, Leostratus, the family has become extinct; for you sought to maintain a
                relationship with the property, not with those who adopted you. After the death of
                Leocrates, so long as no one laid claim to the estate, you sought to get no one
                adopted as a son to Archiades; but now that we have come forward as kinsmen, then
                you get one adopted, that you may get possession of the property. And you declare
                that Archiades, into whose house you were adopted, had no property, yet you file an
                affidavit of objections against us, seeking to exclude his acknowledged kindred. If
                there is nothing in the estate, wherein do you suffer loss, if we inherit this
                nothing? </div><div type="section" n="28">But the fact is, men of the jury, that
                his impudence and greed are such that he thinks it is legitimate for him to return
                to the Eleusinians and retain the estate of his fathers, and at the same time to be
                master of that into which he was introduced by adoption, there being no son in the
                family. And all this he easily managed, for over us, who are poor men and men
                without influence, he has a great advantage, since he is able to spend what belongs
                to others. I consider, therefore, that it is your duty, men of the jury, to give aid
                to us who are not seeking to gain an advantage over others, but who are content if
                we are allowed to win our legal rights. </div><div type="section" n="29">For what
                are we to do, men of the jury? When the adoption has been continued through three
                persons, and the one last left in the family has died without issue, are we not at
                the last to recover what is our own? Well then, having this just claim, we brought
                suit for the inheritance before the archon. But this fellow Leochares here, having
                lightly sworn a false affidavit, thinks that he has the right to rob us of the
                inheritance in defiance of all the laws. </div><div type="section" n="30"
                    />First, then, to prove that what we have stated
                about the adoptions and the pedigree of these men is true, and that the water-bearer
                does stand upon the tomb of Archiades, we wish to read to you these depositions.
                After that we will instruct you plainly regarding the remaining matters as well, and
                so convict our opponents of having sworn a false affidavit.<milestone ed="P"
                    unit="para">Take, please, the depositions of which I speak.<quote
                    type="Depositions">
                    <title>Depositions</title>
                </quote>
                </div><div type="section" n="31">Such is the real
                meaning of this affair, men of the jury, and such the legal rights of inheritance,
                plainly stated; and you have also heard what amounts to a summary of all that has
                been done from the start. But I consider it necessary to tell you also of what they
                have done since the suit for the inheritance was instituted, and the manner in which
                they have treated us; for in my opinion no other people have ever in an inheritance
                suit been dealt with in a manner so contrary to law as we have been. <milestone
                    type="section" n="32">For when Leocrates died, and his funeral had taken place,
                and we went to take possession of his property, since he had died without issue and
                unmarried, Leostratus here ejected us, declaring that it belonged to him. Now his
                preventing us from performing any of the proper rites for the deceased is perhaps to
                be excused, seeing that he was his father, although the act was contrary to law; for
                it is proper that the care of the funeral should be committed to the natural father,
                but, next after him, also to us the members of the family to whom the deceased was
                related by virtue of the adoption. </div><div type="section" n="33">But after the
                funeral rites were finished, what law will be found to justify him, when the family
                was extinct, in driving us, the nearest of kin, from the estate of the deceased?
                Because, they will say, he was father to the dead man. Yes, but he had returned to
                the family of his fathers, and was no longer master of the estate over which he had
                left his son in charge. Otherwise what is the use of the laws? <milestone
                    type="section" n="34">Well, after our ejectment had taken place ( to omit most
                of the details) we brought suit for the inheritance before the archon, inasmuch as
                the deceased had no son, as I stated, and had not adopted any according to the laws.
                After this, Leostratus here made a deposit for costs, as being the son of the
                aforesaid Archiades, not taking into account that he had returned to the
                Eleusinians, or that adopted children are made such, not by themselves but by those
                who adopt them. </div><div type="section" n="35">But the truth is, I presume his
                one simple idea was that he must by fair means or foul lay claim to the property of
                others. And first he had the audacity to go and enroll himself on the assembly
                    list<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was a list of all those who had the
                    right to vote in the popular assembly (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
                        >e)kklhsi/a</foreign>) .</note> of the Otrynians, although he was an
                Eleusinian, and managed to put this through; then, before his name was entered on
                the adult register<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was the official list of
                    the members of the deme, in which every young man who passed the scrutiny was
                    registered when he reached the age of eighteen. Each deme had its own assembly,
                    presided over by the demarch, or borough-president.</note> of the Otrynians, he
                sought to claim a share in the public benefits in flagrant defiance of law, because
                of his greed for gain. </div><div type="section" n="36">We, seeing what was going
                on, called witnesses and put a stop to it, holding the view that it was necessary
                that the right of inheritance should first be decided in your court before anyone
                should be named as the adopted son of Archiades. He was thwarted then, and convicted
                in the presence of many witnesses of fraudulent action, both in the matter of the
                list, and in the assembly for the election of the deme's officers, yet nevertheless
                he persisted in trying to force his way in, and by his intrigues to prove himself
                stronger than your laws. What is the proof of this? </div><div type="section" n="37"
                />He got together some of the Otrynians with the demarch, and persuaded them at the
                opening of the adult register to inscribe his name. And after that on the occasion
                of the great Panathenaea<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The great Panathenea, the
                    most important of all Athenian festivals, was held every four years in the month
                    of Hecatombaeon ( July) .</note> at the time of the distribution, he came to get
                his admission fee, and when the other demesmen were receiving it, he demanded that
                it be given him also, and that he should be entered on the register under the name
                of Archiades. But when we entered a solemn protest, and all the others declared that
                what he was doing was an outrage, he went away without either having his name
                inscribed or receiving the admission fee. </div><div type="section" n="38"
                    />Now do you not think that a man, who in
                defiance of your decree claimed the right to receive the admission fee before his
                name had been inscribed on the list of the Otrynians, belonging as he did to another
                deme, would lay claim to an inheritance in defiance of the laws? Or when a man,
                before the court has rendered its decision, schemes to get advantages so unjust, can
                you think it reasonable to assume that he relies upon the justice of his case? For
                he, who fraudulently claimed the right to receive the admission fee, has now
                obviously practised the same design regarding the inheritance. <milestone
                    type="section" n="39">Nay more, he even deceived the archon, when he made his
                deposit for costs to thwart us, and in his counter-statement declared that he was an
                Otrynian, when he was in fact a demesman among the Eleusinians. When, however, he
                failed in all these schemes, at the last election of officers the fellow got
                together some of the demesmen, and demanded that he be registered as the adopted son
                of Archiades. </div><div type="section" n="40">Again we protested that the demesmen
                should give their votes only when the inheritance suit should have been decided, and
                not before; and to this they agreed, not on their own responsibility, but out of
                respect for the laws; for it seemed to them an outrageous thing that a man who had
                made a deposit for costs in an inheritance suit, should get himself adopted as a son
                while the matter was still undecided; but the thing which this fellow Leostratus
                contrived after this is the most outrageous of all. </div><div type="section" n="41"
                    />For when he failed to get his own name
                inscribed, he entered his own son Leochares as an adopted son of Archiades, in
                defiance of all the laws, before the scrutiny<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For
                    this scrutiny see note 3 of <bibl n="Dem. 27">Dem. 27</bibl>.</note> of the deme
                had taken place. But Leochares had not yet been introduced to the clansmen of
                Archiades; yet when his name had been entered on the list of the deme, only then did
                Leostratus, by bringing influence to bear upon a certain member of the clan, get the
                name inscribed upon the clan register.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This should
                    have normally have been done shortly after birth, for the enrollment in the clan
                    marked the acceptance of the child as a member of the family, as the enrollment
                    in the deme marked a youth's assumption of the status of citizenship.</note>
                </div><div type="section" n="42">And after that, in his affidavit before the archon
                he inscribed Leochares as being the lawfully born son of the man who had been dead
                many years past—Leochares, who had been registered with the clan only a day or two
                before! So it results that they both lay claim to the inheritance; for Leostratus
                here made the deposit for costs in the inheritance suit as being the lawfully born
                son of Archiades, and Leochares here has filed the affidavit, as being the lawfully
                born son of the same father! </div><div type="section" n="43">And in neither case
                is it to a living man, but to one that is dead, that each of them makes himself an
                adopted son! But in our opinion, men of the jury, you ought, when you shall have
                cast your vote concerning the present case, then, and not till then, to find from
                among us, who are nearest of kin, an adopted son for the deceased, in order that the
                family may not become extinct. </div><div type="section" n="44"><milestone ed="P"
                    unit="para">First, men of the jury, to prove that Leostratus here has returned
                to the Eleusinians from the demesmen of Otrynê, leaving a lawfully born son in the
                family of Archiades; and that his father at an earlier date had done this same
                thing; and that the son so left has died without issue; and that the one who has now
                sworn the affidavit was enrolled among the demesmen before he had been enrolled
                among the members of the clan—to prove these facts the clerk shall read you the
                depositions of the members of the clan and of the deme; and in proof of all the
                other things I have mentioned which these men have done I shall produce testimony
                concerning each several fact.Please call the
                witnesses to come forward.<quote type="Witnesses">
                    <title>Witnesses</title>
                </quote>
                </div><div type="section" n="45">All the facts of
                the case, then, you have heard, men of the jury, all that took place at the first in
                connection with this inheritance, and all that occurred subsequently, as soon as we
                commenced our suit. It remains to speak of the affidavit itself and the laws in
                accordance with which we claim to inherit; and furthermore, if the water holds out
                and we shall not be troubling you too much, to refute the arguments which our
                opponents are going to advance, proving to you that they are neither just nor sound.
                And first let the clerk read the affidavit; and I beg you to give it close
                attention; for it is regarding this that your votes are presently to be cast.<quote
                    type="Affidavit">
                    <title>Affidavit</title>
                </quote>
                </div><div type="section" n="46">Well, then, the
                defendant has sworn, as you have heard, “ that the inheritance of Archiades is not
                open to litigation, since he has children lawfully born and rightfully established
                according to the statute.” Let us, then, inquire if there are any, or if the
                defendant has sworn to what is false. The aforesaid Archiades, whose estate is in
                question, adopted as his son the grandfather of the one who has now sworn this
                affidavit; he, leaving a lawfully born son, Leostratus, the father of the defendant,
                returned to the Eleusinians. </div><div type="section" n="47">After this,
                Leostratus here himself returned to the house of his fathers, leaving a son in the
                adoptive house; and the son whom he left, and who was the last of all the adopted
                children, has died without issue, so that the house thereby becomes extinct and the
                inheritance has reverted again to those originally nearest of kin. <milestone
                    type="section" n="48">How, then, could Archiades still have any sons, as the
                affidavit claims, when it is admitted that his adopted children returned to their
                original family and the last one left has died without issue? It follows, then, of
                necessity that the family is extinct. But when the family is extinct, there cannot
                be lawfully born sons still living. The fellow, then, has sworn that non-existent
                persons exist, and has written in the affidavit “ since he has children,” alleging
                that he himself is one of them. </div><div type="section" n="49">But surely, when
                he says “ lawfully born and rightfully established according to the statute,” he is
                quibbling and defying the laws. For the “ lawfully born” exists, when it is born of
                the body; and the law bears testimony to this, when it says, “ Lawfully born are
                children of a woman whom her father or brother or grandfather has given in
                marriage.” But “ rightfully established” the lawgiver understood of adoptions,
                considering that when a man, being childless and master of his property, adopts a
                son, this action ought to be rightful. Well, our opponent says that Archiades had no
                son of the body, but in the affidavit he has sworn to the words “ since there are
                lawfully born children,” thus making a sworn statement that is contrary to the
                truth. </div><div type="section" n="50">He admits that he is an adopted son, yet it
                is manifest that he was not adopted by the dead man himself; so how can you claim
                that this status is “ rightfilly established according to the statute” ? Because, he
                will say, he was registered as the son of Archiades. Yes, by the arbitrary act of
                these men, and that only the other day, when the suit for the estate had already
                been instituted. Surely it is not right for a man to regard as evidence his own
                illegal act. </div><div type="section" n="51">For is it not an outrageous thing,
                men of tlie jury, that he should state—as he will presently in his speech—that he is
                an adopted son, while in his affidavit he did not dare to write this? Or that, while
                in the affidavit the protest is made as though for a son of the body, the speech
                that will presently be made will be on behalf of an adopted son? If they are going
                to make their defence conflict with the affidavit, surely either what they say, or
                what they swore, is false. It was with good reason that they did not add to the
                affidavit mention of the adoption, for in that case they would have had to add the
                words “ adopted by so-and-so.” But Archiades never did adopt them; they adopted
                themselves, in order to rob us of the inheritance. </div><div type="section" n="52"
                    />Now is not their next proceeding absurd as well
                as outrageous?—that Leostratus here should have made his deposit for costs in the
                inheritance suit before the archon, as being the son of Archiades ( while he was an
                Eleusinian, and Archiades of the deme Otrynê) , but that someone else should have
                sworn the affidavit, as you see for yourselves, alleging that he, too, was a son of
                Archiades? To which of the two should you pay attention, as telling the truth?
                    </div><div type="section" n="53">This very thing is the strongest proof of the
                falsehood of the affidavit—that it is not the same person who makes the claim about
                the same matter. And this is not strange for, I fancy, when Leostratus here made his
                deposit in the inheritance suit against us, the one who has now sworn the affidavit
                had not yet registered himself as a member of the deme. We should therefore be most
                cruelly treated if you should believe an affidavit made after the suit was begun.
                    </div><div type="section" n="54">Nay more,
                Leochares has in the affidavit sworn to facts actually older than himself. For how
                could a person who was not yet a member of the house of Archiades when this suit for
                the inheritance was instituted, know anything about these matters? Moreover, if he
                had sworn it of himself alone, there would have been some sense in his action; he
                would have written what was false, but nevertheless his statement would have
                concerned one of an age to know. But as it is, he has written that the aforesaid
                Archiades had lawfully born sons, meaning, of course, his own father and the one
                made such by the original adoption, not taking cognizance of the fact that they had
                returned to their original family. It follows, then, of necessity that he has sworn
                to events older than himself, and not to things which have happened in his own day.
                Are you, then, to credit one who has dared a thing like that, as though he were
                speaking the truth? </div><div type="section" n="55">Ah, but he will say that he
                has heard from his father the facts to which he has sworn. But the law does not
                admit hearsay evidence, save in the case of deceased persons; whereas this fellow
                has dared to swear to acts done by his father, while that father is still alive.
                Then again, why did Leostratus here inscribe on the affidavit the name, not of
                himself, but of the defendant? For the older facts should have been sworn to by the
                older man. It was, he might say, because I have had this youth adopted as son to
                Archiades. </div><div type="section" n="56">Well then, you who had him adopted and
                concocted the whole affair ought to have rendered an account of it, and made
                yourself responsible for what you have done. You ought absolutely to have done so.
                But you evaded this, and wrote over the affidavit the name of your son here, who
                knew nothing of the matter. You see, then, men of the jury, that the statements in
                the affidavit are false, and they are admitted by these men themselves to be so.
                Why, it would even be right for you to refuse to listen to this man Leostratus, when
                he presently undertakes to make statements to which he did not venture to swear in
                the affidavit. </div><div type="section" n="57"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"
                />Furthermore, that affidavits of objection are of all forms of trial the most
                unjust, and that those having recourse to them are most deserving of your
                resentment, one can see very clearly from the following facts. In the first place,
                they are not necessary as the other forms of procedure are, but they are instituted
                by the will and desire of the one swearing to them.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                    >The affidavit of objection (<foreign xml:lang="grc">diamartu/ria</foreign>) ,
                    like the special plea in bar of action (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
                        >paragrafh/</foreign>) , afforded a means by which the defendant could
                    prevent a case from being tried upon its merits, and so could be regarded as a
                    means of thwarting the course of justice.</note> If in the matter of disputed
                claims there is no other way of getting a judgement than by such an affidavit, it is
                perhaps necessary to make one. </div><div type="section" n="58">But, if it is
                possible without an affidavit of objections to obtain a hearing before all
                tribunals, is not the use of one a mark of recklessness and utter desperation? For
                the lawgiver did not make it obligatory on the contending parties, but granted them
                the privilege of putting in such an affidavit, if they chose, as though he were
                testing the character of each one of us, to see how we stand with reference to a
                reckless procedure.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There is, of course, the
                    implication that those having recourse to this procedure thereby showed
                    themselves either unscrupulous or in despair of their case.</note>
                </div><div type="section" n="59">Further, if it rested with those who file these
                affidavits, there would be neither courts of justice nor trials; for the nature of
                affidavits of objections is to bIock all these things and to prevent all cases from
                being brought into the court-room—at least so far as the will of the one swearing
                the affidavit goes. Therefore I think we should regard such people as the common
                enemies of all men, and that they should never receive any indulgence when they are
                on trial before you; for each one of them comes into court, not under compulsion,
                but having chosen to incur the risk of the oath. </div><div type="section" n="60"
                    />Well then, that the affidavit is false, you
                have learned pretty definitely from the statements contained in it and from the
                arguments which you have heard. But that the laws also give us this inheritance as
                our right, men of the jury, I wish to prove in a few words—not as though this had
                not been made clear to you in what I said at the outset, but that you may the better
                bear in mind the justice of our case, and so meet the false statements of our
                opponents. </div><div type="section" n="61">To sum
                up the matter briefly, we, since we are the nearest of kin in the male line to
                Archiades, to whom this estate belonged, and since of the persons whom he adopted
                some have gone back to the family of their fathers, and the one last left had died
                without issue,—in these circumstances, we, I say, claim to inherit. <milestone
                    type="section" n="62">We are not depriving Leostratus of any property ( for
                these men hold what is their own) , but we claim the estate left by Archiades, which
                is ours according to the laws. For the law, men of the jury, ordains that males and
                the sons of males should have precedence; and such we are. Archiades had no
                children, and we are the ones nearest of kin to him. </div><div type="section"
                    n="63">Further, it is surely not just that an adopted son should bring other
                sons into a family by adoption; he may leave in it children born to him, but in
                default of these he must restore the inheritance to those related by blood. That is
                what the laws ordain.For is it not plain that each
                one of you is excluded from the right of inheritance by direct descent, if this
                licence be granted to children by adoption? For you see that most people who adopt
                children do so through being cajoled by flattery and often in a spirit of
                contentiousness caused by family quarrels. But if an adopted son is to be permitted
                in defiance of the law to adopt whomsoever he pleases, inheritances will never be
                given to blood-relations. </div><div type="section" n="64">It was to guard against
                this that the lawgiver forbade a person who was himself adopted to create a son by
                adoption. In what manner did he declare his view regarding this? When he says “ a
                man may return to his own family, leaving behind him a lawfully born son” he makes
                it plain, I take it, that it is not lawful for him to adopt; for it is impossible
                for a man to leave behind him a lawfully born son, unless he have a son born of his
                body. But you, Leostratus, claim the right to bring an adopted son into the
                inheritance of the dead man, who had himself been adopted into our family, just as
                though you were taking possession of your own property, and not that which the law
                declares shall be given to the nearest of kin. </div><div type="section" n="65"
                    />For ourselves, men of the jury, if the deceased
                had adopted anyone, even though the law does not allow it, we should have submitted;
                or, if he had left a will, we should also have been ready to abide by that; for from
                the beginning this has been our position; we made no objection to their holding the
                property and returning to their original family in whatever manner they pleased.
                    </div><div type="section" n="66">Now, however, that the affair has at length
                been exposed both by these men themselves and by the laws, we hold that it is right
                for us to inherit the estate of Archiades, and that the son to be adopted should
                come from us who have not been adopted before, and not from them. For it was just,
                in my opinion, that the lawgiver, as he laid upon the nearest of kin the duty of
                relieving the misfortunes of their relatives, and of giving in marriage their
                women-folk, so also has given to these same people as their due the right of
                inheriting and of sharing in the good things. </div><div type="section" n="67">But
                that which is the most significant thing, and the thing best known to you, is this:
                the law of Solon does not allow an adopted son even to dispose by will of the
                property in the family into which he comes by adoption. And there is good reason for
                this, in my view; for a person who comes by legal adoption into possession of the
                property of another, ought not to deal with it as if it were his own private estate.
                No, he should act consistently with the laws, and do in each particular what the
                laws prescribe. </div><div type="section" n="68">“All those who had not been
                adopted,” says the lawgiver,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This law is cited more
                    fully in <bibl n="Dem. 46.14">Dem. 46.14</bibl></note>“ at the time when Solon
                entered upon office, may bequeath their property by will, as they see fit,” thus
                indicating that those who were adopted might not so dispose of theirs, but that they
                might return to their families in their lifetime, leaving a lawfully born son in
                their place; otherwise, in case of death, they must give back the property to those
                who from the first were relatives of the adoptive father.</p>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
