<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Nutrimen</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							<date>1923</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>		
		<encodingDesc>
			
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>>
				refState unit="text"/>
				refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl> n="text=Aph.">
				refState unit="text"/>
				refState unit="chapter"/>
				refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl> n="text=intro">
				refState unit="text"/>
				refState unit="chapter"/>
				refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl> n="text=Epid.">
				refState unit="text"/>
				refState unit="book"/>
				refState unit="chapter"/>
				refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			
			<refsDecl>>
				refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader><text xml:lang="en"><body>
				<div type="section" n="1"><head>PART 1<p>I. N<hi rend="sc">UTRIMENT</hi> and form of nutriment, one and
					many. One, inasmuch as its kind is one ; form
					varies with moistness or dryness. These foods too
					have their forms<note>Or "figures."</note> and quantities ; they are for
					certain things, and for a certain number of things.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="2"><head>PART 2<p>II. It increases, strengthens, clothes with flesh,
					makes like, makes unlike, what is in the several
					parts, according to the nature of each part and its
					original power.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="3"><head>PART 3<p>III. It makes into the likeness of a power, when
					the nutriment that comes in has the mastery, and
					when that is mastered which was there to begin
					with.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="4"><head>PART 4<p>IV. It also loses its qualities ; sometimes the
					earlier nutriment, when in time it has been liberated
					or added, sometimes the later, when in time it has
					been liberated or added.</p>
					<pb id="p.345"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="5"><head>PART 5<p>V. Both are weakened in time and after a time by
					the nutriment from without which has continuously
					entered in, and for a long time firmly has interwoven
					itself with all the limbs.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="6"><head>PART 6<p>VI. And it sends forth shoots of its own proper
					form. It changes the old form and descends ; it
					nourishes as it is digested. Sometimes it alters
					the earlier form, and completely obscures the former
					ones.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="7"><head>PART 7<p>VII. Power of nutriment reaches to bone and to
					all the parts of bone, to sinew, to vein, to artery,
					to muscle, to membrane, to flesh, fat, blood, phlegm,
					marrow, brain, spinal marrow, the intestines and all
					their parts ; it reaches also to heat, breath, and
					moisture.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="8"><head>PART 8<p>VIII. Nutriment is that which is nourishing ;
					nutriment is that which is fit to nourish ; nutriment
					is that which is about to nourish.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="9"><head>PART 9<p>IX. The beginning of all things is one and the
					end of all things is one, and the end and beginning
					are the same.</p>
					<pb id="p.347"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="10"><head>PART 10<p>X. And all the particular details in nourishment
					are managed well or ill ; well if as aforesaid, ill if
					ordered in the opposite way to these.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="11"><head>PART 11<p>XI. Juices varied in colours and in powers, to
					harm or to help, or neither to harm nor to help,
					varied in amount, excess or defect, in combination of
					some but not of others.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="12"><head>PART 12<p>XII. And to the warming of all it harms or helps,
					to the cooling it harms or helps, to the power it
					harms or helps.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="13"><head>PART 13<p>XIII. Of power varied natures.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="14"><head>PART 14<p>XIV. Humours corrupting whole, part, from without,
					from within, spontaneous, not spontaneous ;
					spontaneous for us, not spontaneous for the cause.
					Of the cause, part is clear, part is obscure, part is
					within our power and part is not.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="15"><head>PART 15<p>XV. Nature is sufficient in all for all.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="16"><head>PART 16<p>XVI. To deal with nature from without : plaster,
					anointing, salve, uncovering of whole or part,
					covering of whole or part, warming or cooling
					similarly, astriction, ulceration, biting,<note>Apparently, such things
						as a mustard plaster.</note> grease ; from
					within : some of the aforesaid, and in addition an
					obscure cause in part or whole, in some cases but not
					in all.</p>
					<pb id="p.349"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="17"><head>PART 17<p>XVII. Secretions in accordance with nature, by
					the bowels, urine, sweat, sputum, mucus, womb,
					through hemorrhoid, wart, leprosy, tumour, carcinoma,
					from nostrils, lungs, bowels, seat, penis, in
					accordance with nature or contrary to nature. The
					peculiar differences in these things depend on
					differences in the individual, on times and on
					methods. All these things are one nature and not
					one. All these things are many natures and one
					nature.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="18"><head>PART 18<p>XVIII. Purging upward or downward, neither
					upward nor downward.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="19"><head>PART 19<p>XIX. In nutriment purging excellent, in nutriment
					purging bad ; bad or excellent according to
					circumstances.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="20"><head>PART 20<p>XX. Ulceration, burn-scab, blood, pus, lymph,
					leprosy, scurf, dandruff, scurvy, white leprosy,
					freckles, sometimes harm and sometimes help, and
					sometimes neither harm nor help.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="21"><head>PART 21<p>XXI. Nutriment not nutriment if it have not its
					power. Not nutriment nutriment if it can nourish.
					Nutriment in name, not in deed ; nutriment in deed,
					not in name.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="22"><head>PART 22<p>XXII. It travels from within to hair, nails, and to
					the extreme surface ; from without nutriment travels
					from the extreme surface to the innermost parts.</p>
					<pb id="p.351"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="23"><head>PART 23<p>XXIII. Conflux one, conspiration one, all things
					in sympathy ; all the parts as forming a whole, and
					severally the parts in each part, with reference to
					the work.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="24"><head>PART 24<p>XXIV. The great beginning travels to the
					extreme part ; from the extreme part there is
					travelling to the great beginning. One nature to
					be and not to be.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="25"><head>PART 25<p>XXV. Differences of diseases depend on nutriment,
					on breath, on heat, on blood, on phlegm, on
					bile, on humours, on flesh, on fat, on vein, on
					artery, on sinew, muscle, membrane, bone, brain,
					spinal marrow, mouth, tongue, oesophagus, stomach,
					bowels, midriff, peritoneum, liver, spleen, kidneys,
					bladder, womb, skin. All these things both as a
					whole and severally. Their greatness great and not
					great.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="26"><head>PART 26<p>XXVI. Signs : tickling, ache, rupture, mind, sweat,
					sediment in urine, rest, tossing, condition<note>Or, "staring."</note> of
					the eyes,
					imaginations, jaundice, hiccoughs, epilepsy, blood
					entire, sleep, from both these and all other things in
					accordance with nature, and everything else of a
					similar nature that tends to harm or help. Pains of
					the whole or of a part, indications of severity : of the
					one, greater severity, of the other, less, and from
					both come signs of greater severity, and from both
					come signs of less.</p>
					<pb id="p.353"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="27"><head>PART 27<p>XXVII. Sweet, not sweet ; sweet in power, like
					water, sweet to the taste, like honey. Signs of
					either are sores, eyes and tastings, which can also
					distinguish degrees. Sweet to sight, in colours and
					in combinations generally, sweet to a greater or
					less degree.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="28"><head>PART 28<p>XXVIII. Porousness of a body for transpiration
					healthy for those from whom more is taken ; denseness
					of body for transpiration unhealthy for those
					from whom less is taken. Those who transpire
					freely are weaker, healthier, and recover easily ;
					those who transpire hardly are stronger before they
					are sick, but on falling sick they make difficult
					recovery. These for both whole and part.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="29"><head>PART 29<p>XXIX. The lungs draw a nourishment which is
					the opposite of that of the body, all other parts draw
					the same.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="30"><head>PART 30<p>XXX. Beginning of nutriment of breath, nostrils,
					mouth, throat, lungs, and the transpiratory system
					generally. Beginning of nutriment, both wet and
					dry, mouth, oesophagus, stomach. The more ancient
					nutriment, through the epigastrium, where the
					navel is.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="31"><head>PART 31<p>XXXI. Root of veins, liver ; root of arteries, heart.
					Out of these travel to all parts blood and breath, and
					heat passes through them.</p>
					<pb id="p.355"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="32"><head>PART 32<p>XXXII. Power one, and not one, by which all
					these things and those of a different sort are
					managed ; one for the life of whole and part, not
					one for the sensation of whole and part.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="33"><head>PART 33<p>XXXIII. Milk nutriment, for those to whom milk
					is a natural nutriment, but for others it is not. For
					some wine is nutriment, for others not. So with
					meats and the other many forms of nutriment, the
					differences being due to place and habit.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="34"><head>PART 34<p>XXXIV. Nourishment is sometimes into growth
					and being, sometimes into being only, as is the case
					with old men ; sometimes in addition it is into
					strength. The condition of the athlete is not natural.
					A healthy state is superior in all.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="35"><head>PART 35<p>XXXV. It is a great thing successfully to adapt
					quantity to power.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="36"><head>PART 36<p>XXXVI. Milk and blood are what is left over
					from nutriment.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="37"><head>PART 37<p>XXXVII. Periods generally harmonise for the
					embryo and its nutriment ; and again nutriment
					tends upwards to milk and the nourishment of
					the baby.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="38"><head>PART 38<p>XXXVIII. Inanimates get life, animates get life,
					the parts of animates get life.</p>
					<pb id="p.357"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="39"><head>PART 39<p>XXXIX. The natures of all are untaught.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="40"><head>PART 40<p>XL. Blood of another is useful, one's own blood
					is useful ; blood of another is harmful, one's own
					blood is harmful ; one's own humours are harmful,
					humours of another are harmful ; humours of another
					are beneficial, one's own humours are beneficial ; the
					harmonious is unharmonious, the unharmonious is
					harmonious ; another's milk is good, one's own milk
					is bad ; another's milk is harmful, one's own milk is
					useful.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="41"><head>PART 41<p>XLI. Food for the young partly digested, for the
					old completely changed, for adults unchanged.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="42"><head>PART 42<p>XLII. For formation, thirty-five days ; for movement,
					seventy days ; for completion, two hundred
					and ten days. Others, for form, forty-five days ; for
					motion, ninety days ; for delivery, two hundred and
					seventy days. Others, fifty for form ; for the first
					leap, one hundred ; for completion, three hundred
					days. For distinction of limbs, forty ; for shifting,
					eighty ; for detachment, two hundred and forty days.
					It is not and is. There are found therein both more
					and less, in respect of both the whole and the parts,
					but the more is not much more, and the less not
					much less.</p>
					<pb id="p.359"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="43"><head>PART 43<p>XLIII. Nutriment of bones after breaking ; for
					the nostril, twice five ; for jaw, collar-bone and ribs,
					twice this ; for the fore-arm, thrice ; for the leg and
					upper-arm, four times ; for the thigh, five times ;
					there may be, however, in these a little more or less.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="44"><head>PART 44<p>XLIV. Blood is liquid and blood is solid. Liquid
					blood is good, liquid blood is bad. Solid blood is
					good, solid blood is bad. All things are good or bad
					relatively.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="45"><head>PART 45<p>XLV. The way up, down.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="46"><head>PART 46<p>XLVI. Power of nutriment superior to mass ; mass
					of nutriment superior to power ; both in moist things
					and in dry.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="47"><head>PART 47<p>XLVII. It takes away and adds not the same
					thing ; it takes away from one, and adds to another,
					the same thing.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="48"><head>PART 48<p>XLVIII. Pulsations of veins and breathing of the
					lungs according to age, harmonious and unharmonious,
					signs of disease and of health, and
					of health more than of disease, and of disease
					more than of health. For breath too is nutriment.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="49"><head>PART 49<p>XLIX. Liquid nutriment more easily changed
					than solid ; solid nutriment more easily changed
					than liquid. That which is hardly altered is hard of
					digestion, and that which is easily added is easy of
					digestion.</p>
					<pb id="p.361"/>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="50"><head>PART 50<p>L. And for such as need a quick reinforcement, a
					liquid remedy is best for recovery of power ; for such
					as need a quicker, a remedy through smell ; for
					those who need a slower reinforcement, solid
					nutriment.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="51"><head>PART 51<p>LI. Muscles being more solid waste less easily
					than other parts, save bone and sinew. Parts that
					have been exercised resist change, being according
					to their kind stronger than they otherwise would
					have been, and therefore less liable to waste.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="52"><head>PART 52<p>LII. Pus comes from flesh ; pus-like lymph comes
					from blood and moisture generally. Pus is nutriment
					for a sore ; lymph is nutriment for vein and
					artery.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="53"><head>PART 53<p>LIII. Marrow nutriment of bone, and through this
					a callus forms.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="54"><head>PART 54<p>LIV. Power gives to all things increase, nourishment
					and birth.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="section" n="55"><head>PART 55<p>LV. Moisture the vehicle of nutriment.</p>
				</div>
			
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
</body></text></TEI>
