<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Chance</title>
             
                <author>Plutarch</author>
                <editor>Frank Cole Babbitt</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Bridget Almas</name>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">2010-12-13</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <analytic/>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Plutarch</author>
                        <title>Moralia</title>
                        <respStmt>
                            <resp>with an English translation by</resp>
                            <name>Frank Cole Babbitt</name>
                        </respStmt>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                            <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1928</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="http://www.archive.org/stream/moraliainfifteen02plutuoft#page/72/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2018-07-05" who="Charlotte Houghton">Epidoc and CTS conversion, formatting</change>
            <change when="2010-05-01" who="RS">tagged and parsed</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg074.perseus-eng3" xml:lang="eng">
                    <head>CHANCE (DE FORTUNA)</head> 
                <pb xml:id="v.2.p.73"/>
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="intro">
                        <head>INTRODUCTION</head>
                    <p> In default of any information regarding Plutarch's 
                        short essay on Chance, we can only guess that it 
                        may have been delivered as a lecture, although
                        Hartman denies such a possibility. The arguing of 
                        such subjects has always had a certain attraction for 
                        mankind until comparatively recent times, but the 
                        development of a more exact knowledge regarding 
                        psychology has in later years checked such discussions.
                        Yet a knowledge of psychology will not
                        detract from the interest and enjoyment of anyone 
                        who will read this essay.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <pb xml:id="v.2.p.75"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
                    <p>
                        <quote rend="blockquote">Man’s ways are chance and not sagacity.<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">From Chaeremon: Nauck, <title>Trag. Graec. Frag.</title>p. 782. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Cicero, <title>Tusculan Disputations</title>, v. 9 (25).</note>
                        </quote> 
                        Is it true also that man’s ways are not justice 
                        either, or equality, or self-control, or decorum, but was
                        it the result of chance and because of chance that 
                        Aristeides <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch’s <title>Life of Aristides</title>, chap. xxv. (p. 334 B).</note>
                        persevered in his poverty when he could 
                        have made himself master of great wealth, and that
                        Scipio, <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi>Plutarch’s <title>Moralia</title> 200 B.</note> having captured Carthage, neither took nor 
                        saw any of the spoil? Was it the result of chance 
                        and because of chance that Philocrates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Demosthenes, Or. xix. (<title xml:lang="lat">De falsa legatione</title>), 229 (p. 412). The money was the price of treason according to Demosthenes.</note> having
                        received money from Philip, <q>proceeded to spend it on trulls and
                            trout,</q> and was it due to chance that Lasthenes and Euthycrates lost Olynthus, 
                        <q>measuring happiness by their bellies and the most
                            shameless deeds</q>? <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Demosthenes, Or. xviii. (<title xml:lang="lat">De corona</title>), 296 (p. 324). These men also Demosthenes puts in his list of traitors.</note> Was it the result of chance that
                        Alexander,<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plutarch’s <title>Life of Alexander</title>, chap. xxi. (p. 676 B ff.).</note> the son of Philip, forbore to touch the 
                        captive women himself and punished those who 
                        offered them insult, and, on the other hand, was it
                        because the Alexander who was the son of Priam 
                        yielded to the dictates of an evil genius or of chance 
                        that he lay with the wife of his host, and by her
                        abduction filled two of our three continents with 
                        war and woes? For if  these things happen because 
                        <pb xml:id="v.2.p.77"/> 
                        of chance, what is to hinder our saying that cats,
                        goats, and apes because of chance are given over to
                        greediness, lustfulness, and mischievous tricks?</p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
                    <p>If self-control, justice, and bravery exist, how is 
                        it possible to reason  that intelligence does not exist; 
                        and if intelligence exists, must not sagacity exist 
                        also? For self-control is a kind of intelligence, they
                        say, and justice requires the presence of intelligence.<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf. <title>Moralia</title></hi>, 441 A and 1034 C.</note> 
                        Or rather, that particular sagacity and intelligence 
                        which render men virtuous in the midst of pleasures 
                        we call continence and self-control, in perils and 
                        labours we call it perseverance and fortitude, in 
                        private dealings and in public life we call it equity
                        and justice. Wherefore, if we impute the works of 
                        sagacity to chance, let the works of justice and of 
                        self-control be also ascribed to chance, and, by 
                        Heaven, let thieving, stealing purses, and licentious 
                        living all be ascribed to chance, and let us abandon 
                        all our reasoning processes and resign ourselves to 
                        chance, to be driven and carried, as dust or rubbish
                        by a violent wind, hither and thither. If, then, 
                        sagacity does not exist, it is a fair inference that
                        there can be no sagacious planning about what is
                        to be done, and no consideration or searching for
                        what is to the best advantage, but Sophocles <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><title>Oedipus Tyrannus</title>, 110.</note> indulged 
                        in idle talk when he said: 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">Whatever is pursued
                                May be achieved; neglected it escapes;</quote> 
                        and so too in another place where he tries to distinguish 
                        different classes of actions: 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">What can be taught I learn; what can be found
                            I seek; but God I ask to answer prayer.</quote><note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">From an unknown play of Sophocles; Nauck, <title>Trag. Graec. Frag.</title>, Sophocles, No. 759.</note>
                        
                        <pb xml:id="v.2.p.79"/>
                        For what is there which can be found out or learned 
                        by mankind if the issue of all things is determined 
                        by chance? And what deliberative assembly of a 
                        State can there be which is not abolished, or advisory 
                        council of a king which is not dissolved, if all things 
                        are under the dominion of chance, which we reproach 
                        for being blind because we, like blind men, stumble 
                        against it?<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Kock. <title>Com. Att. Frag.</title> iii. p. 121, Menander, No. 417.</note> How can we help doing so when we 
                        pluck out sagacity, as it were our own eyes, and take 
                        as our guide in life a blind leader? </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
                    <p>Yet, suppose someone among us should say that 
                        the act of seeing is chance and not vision nor the 
                        use of <q>light-bringing orbs,</q> as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">In the <title>Timaeus</title>, p. 45 B.</note> calls the
                        eyes, and that the act of hearing is chance and not a 
                        faculty apperceptive of a vibration in the air which 
                        is carried onward through ear and brain.<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Plato, <title>Timaeus</title>, p. 67 B.</note> If such
                        were the case, it were well for us, as it appears, to
                        beware of trusting our senses! But, as a matter of 
                        fact, Nature has conferred upon us sight, hearing, 
                        taste, smell, and our other members and their 
                        faculties to be ministers of sagacity and intelligence, 
                        and 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">Mind has sight and mind has hearing; all the rest is 
                            deaf and blind.
                            <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">From Epicharmus; cited by Plutarch also in <title>Moralia</title>, 33 B and 961 A. <hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <title xml:lang="deu">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</title>, i. p. 123.</note>
                        </quote> Precisely as would be our case if the sun did not exist, 
                        and we, for all the other stars, should be passing our 
                        life in a continual night, as Heracleitus <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Diels, <title xml:lang="deu">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</title>, i, p. 97; Bywater, p. 13. A slightly different version of the saying is given by Plutarch, <title>Moralia</title>, 957 A.</note> affirms, so
                        man, for all his senses, had he not mind and reason,
                        would not differ at all in his life from the brutes. 
                        <pb xml:id="v.2.p.81"/> 
                        But as it is, we excel them and have power over 
                        them, not from chance or accidentally, but the cause 
                        thereof is Prometheus, or, in other words, the power 
                        to think and reason, 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">Which gives the foal of horse and ass, and get 
                            Of bull, to serve us and assume our tasks,</quote>
                        as Aeschylus <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">From the <title>Prometheus Unbound</title> of Aeschylus; Nauck, <title>Trag. Graec. Frag.</title>, Aeschylus, No. 194. The lines are again quoted by Plutarch <title>Moralia</title>, 964 F.</note> puts it. Certainly, in so far as chance 
                        and nature’s endowment at birth are concerned, the 
                        great majority of brute animals are better off than 
                        man. For some are armed with horns, or teeth, or 
                        stings, and Empedocles says, 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">But as for hedgehogs 
                            Growing upon their backs sharp darts of spines stand
                            bristling,<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Diels, <title xml:lang="deu">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker, i. p. 252.</title></note></quote>
                        and still others are shod and clad with scales or hair, 
                        with claws or horny hoofs. Man alone, as Plato <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><title>Protagoras</title>, 321 C.</note> 
                        says, <q>naked, unarmed, with feet unshod, and with 
                            no bed to lie in,</q> has been abandoned by Nature. 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">Yet by one gift all this she mitigates,<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Author unknown, but perhaps Euripides; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi>Nauck, <title>Trag. Graec. Frag.,</title>Adespota, No. 367; cited again by Plutarch, <title>Moralia</title>, 959 D.</note>
                        </quote> 
                        the gift of reasoning, diligence, and forethought. 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">Slight, of a truth, is the strength of man; and yet
                            By his mind’s resourcefulness 
                            Doth he subjugate the monsters 
                            Of the deep, and the purposes 
                            Of the denizens of earth and air.<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">From the <title>Aeolus</title> of Euripides; Nauck, <title>Trag. Graec. Frag.</title>, Euripides, No. 27.</note>
                        </quote> 
                        Horses are the lightest and swiftest of foot, yet 
                        they run for man. The dog is pugnacious and 
                        <pb xml:id="v.2.p.83"/>
                        spirited, yet it watches over man. Fish is most
                        savoury, and the pig very fat, yet for man they are 
                        nourishing and appetizing food. What is bigger than 
                        an elephant or more terrible to behold ? But even 
                        this creature has been made the plaything of man, 
                        and a spectacle at public gatherings, and it learns 
                        to posture and dance and kneel.<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Plutarch has several good stories about elephants in <title>Moralia</title>, 968 ff.</note> Such presentations 
                        are not without their use; indeed, they serve a 
                        purpose in that we may learn to what heights man’s 
                        intelligence raises him, above what it places him, 
                        and how he is master of all things, and in every way
                        superior. 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">No, we are not invincible either in boxing or wrestling, 
                            Nor are we swift in the race.<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Adapted from Homer, <title>Od.</title> viii. 246.</note>
                        </quote> 
                        Indeed, in all these matters we are not so fortunate
                        as the animals; yet we make use of experience, 
                        memory, wisdom, and skill, as Anaxagoras <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> Diels, <title xml:lang="deu">Fragmente der Vorsokratiker</title>, i. p. 409.</note> says, 
                        which are ours, and ours only, and we take their 
                        honey, and milk them, and carry and lead them at 
                        will, taking entire control over them. In all this, 
                        therefore, there is no element of chance at all, but
                        solely and wholly sagacity and forethought. </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
                    <p>Moreover, under the head of <q type="unspecified">man’s ways</q>
                        <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> the first line of chap. i. <foreign xml:lang="lat">supra.</foreign></note> 
                        would fall, no doubt, the activities of carpenters, 
                        copper-smiths, builders, and statuaries, wherein we 
                        see nothing brought to a successful conclusion 
                        accidentally or as it chances. That chance may 
                        sometimes contribute slightly to their success, <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">From Epicurus; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> the quotation in Diogenes Laertius, x. 144.</note> but 
                        <pb xml:id="v.2.p.85"/> 
                        that the arts through themselves bring to perfection 
                        the most and greatest of their works, is plainly suggested 
                        by this poet: 
                        <quote rend="blockquote">Into the highway come, all craftsmen folk, 
                            Who worship Labour, stern-eyed child of Zeus, 
                            With sacred baskets placed about.<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Perhaps from Sophocles; <hi rend="italics">cf.</hi> Nauck, <title>Trag. Graec. Frag.</title>, Sophocles, No. 760. <foreign xml:lang="grc">)Ἐργάνη</foreign> is an epithet applied to Athena as patron of the arts.</note>
                        </quote> For the arts have Labour, that is Athena, and not 
                        Chance as their coadjutor. Of just one artist, <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">Nealces, according to Pliny, <title>Nat. Hist.</title> xxxv. 36 (104). Dio Chrysostom (<title>Or.</title> lxiii. 4) says it was Apelles, and Valerius Maximus (viii. 11. 7) says <q>a famous painter.</q></note> 
                        however, it is related that in painting a horse he had
                        succeeded in nearly every respect in the drawing 
                        and colours, but the frothy appearance of the foam
                        from champing the bit, and the rush of the foamflecked 
                        breath, he had tried again and again to paint, 
                        but without success, and each time had wiped it
                        out, until finally, in a rage, he threw his sponge 
                        just as it was, full of pigments, at the canvas, and 
                        this, as it struck, transferred its contents in some 
                        amazing manner to the canvas, and effected the 
                        desired result. This is the only recorded instance 
                        of a technical achievement due to chance. Rulers,
                        weights, measures, and numbers are everywhere in 
                        use, so that the random and haphazard may find 
                        no place in any production. Indeed, the arts 
                        are said to be minor forms of intelligence, or rather offshoots 
                        of intelligence, and detached fragments of it 
                        interspersed amid life’s common necessities, as it is
                        said in the allegory regarding fire, that it was divided 
                        into portions by Prometheus and scattered some 
                        here and some there. For thus, when intelligence 
                        is finely broken and divided, small portions and fragments
                        of it have gone to their several stations. 
                        <pb xml:id="v.2.p.87"/>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
                    <p>It is therefore amazing how, if the arts have no 
                        need of chance to accomplish their own ends, the
                        greatest and most perfect art of all, the consummation
                        of the high repute and esteem to which man can 
                        attain, can count for nothing! But in the tightening 
                        and loosening of strings there is involved a certain
                        sagacity, which men call music, and also in the preparation
                        of food, to which we give the name of 
                        cookery, and in the cleaning of clothes, which we call
                        fulling; and we teach our children to put on their 
                        shoes and clothes, and to take their meat with the 
                        right hand and hold their bread in the left, on the
                        assumption that even these things do not come by 
                        chance, but require oversight and attention.<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> <title>Moralia</title>, 5 A and 440 A.</note> But 
                        can it be that those things which are most important
                        and most essential for happiness do not call for 
                        intelligence, nor have any part in the processes of 
                        reason and forethought ? But nobody wets clay
                        with water and leaves it, assuming that by chance
                        and accidentally there will be bricks, nor after providing 
                        himself with wool and leather does he sit 
                        down with a prayer to Chance that they turn into 
                        a cloak and shoes for him; and when a man has 
                        amassed much gold and silver and a multitude of
                        slaves, and has surrounded himself with spacious 
                        suites of rooms, and, in addition, has furnished them 
                        with costly couches and tables,<note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><hi rend="italics">Cf.</hi> <title>Moralia</title>, 100 C, <foreign xml:lang="lat">infra.</foreign></note> does he imagine that 
                        these things, without the presence of intelligence 
                        in himself, will be happiness and a blissful life, free 
                        from grief and secure from change? </p>
                    <p> Somebody asked Iphicrates <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">This story also in <title>Moralia</title>, 187 B and 440 B.</note> the general, as though 
                        undertaking to expose him,
                        who he was, since he  was <q>neither a man-at-arms, nor archer, nor targeteer</q>; 
                        and he answered, <q>I am the man who 
                        <pb xml:id="v.2.p.89"/> 
                        commands and makes use of all these.</q>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6" rend="merge">
                    <p>Intelligence 
                        is not gold or silver or repute or wealth or 
                        health or strength or beauty. What then is it? It 
                        is the something which is able to make good use of
                        all these, and something through whose agency each 
                        of these is made pleasant, noteworthy, and profitable. 
                        Without it they are unserviceable, fruitless, 
                        and harmful, and they burden and disgrace their 
                        possessor. It is surely excellent advice that Hesiod’s <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng">In the <title>Works and Days</title>, 86.</note> 
                        Prometheus gives to Epimetheus:
                        <quote rend="blockquote">Never to welcome 
                            Any gifts from Zeus of Olympus, but always return them,</quote>
                        meaning the gifts of chance and external advantages; 
                        as if he were advising him not to play the flute if 
                        ignorant of music, nor to read if illiterate, nor to ride 
                        if unused to horses, thus advising him not to hold 
                        public office if a fool, nor to be rich if miserly, nor to 
                        marry if ruled by a woman. For not only is it true, 
                        as Demosthenes <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" xml:lang="eng"><title>Olynthiac</title>I. 23.</note> has said, that <q>undeserved success
                        becomes a source of misconception for fools,</q>
                        but undeserved good fortune also becomes a source 
                        of misery for the unthinking.
                        
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
