<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Prosecution Of The Stepmother For Poisoning from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Antiphon</author>
        <editor role="translator">K. J. Maidment</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><idno type="OCLC">5331826</idno><idno type="ISBN">0674993403</idno></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=2">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=3">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=4">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.tetralogy">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Tetralogy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd
      </item></change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Checkmark
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/7/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed tetralogy names and div2s again, prior to importing
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>made some corrections to the SGML
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>also fixed quoted text which had no content, just the attribute.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>15 October 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: antiph_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-10-07 21:00:37  rsingh04
began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

Revision 1.6  2009/06/22 19:41:56  student
edited entity tags CEH

Revision 1.5  2008/11/21 21:38:13  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.4  2008/02/13 19:32:23  lcerrato
fixed incorrect bibl tags

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 21:10:04  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 15:48:40  packel
removed stray item tags

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:27:36  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:14:27  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2000/03/04 20:33:52  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.6  2000/01/28 23:23:50  dasmith
Made ID numbers be the tag content.

Revision 1.5  1999/10/15 23:08:23  dasmith
Make sure we get three sections at a time.

Revision 1.4  1999/10/15 21:20:01  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.


</item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="section">
        <p> Not only am I still too young to know anything of courts of law, gentlemen; but I am
          also faced with a terrible dilemma. On the one hand, how can I disregard my father's
          solemn injunction to bring his murderers to justice? On the other hand, if I obey it, I
          shall inevitably find myself ranged against the last persons with whom I should quarrel,
          my half-brothers and their mother. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="section">
        <p>Circumstances for which the defence have only themselves to blame have made it necessary
          that my charge should be directed against them, and them alone. One would have expected
          them to seek vengeance for the dead and support the prosecution; but as it is, the
          opposite is the case; they are themselves my opponents and the murderers, as both I and my
            indictment<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., the charge as formally registered with
            the <foreign xml:lang="greek">basileu/s</foreign> (cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 6.38">Antiph.
              6.38</bibl>, 41 ff.). The action itself was of course a <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >di/kh fo/nou</foreign></note> state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Gentlemen, I have one request. If I prove that my opponents' mother murdered our father
          by malice aforethought, after being caught not merely once, but repeatedly, in the act of
          seeking his life,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A natural rhetorical exaggeration. The
            proof does not in fact occur as promised; but there is no good reason for supposing that
            the speech is therefore incomplete. In the circumstances outlined in the Introduction
            such a proof would have been impossible.</note> then first avenge the outrage against
          your laws, that heritage from the gods and your forefathers which enables you to sentence
          the guilty even as they did; and secondly avenge the dead man, and in so doing give me, a
          lonely orphan, your aid. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="section">
        <p>For you are my kin; those who should have avenged the dead and supported me are his
          murderers and my opponents. So where is help to be sought, where is a refuge to be found,
          save with you and with justice? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>I am at a loss indeed to understand the feelings which have led my brother to range
          himself against me. Does he imagine that his duty as a son consists simply in loyalty to
          his mother? To my mind, it is a far greater sin to neglect the avenging of the dead man;
          and the more so since he met his doom as the involuntary victim of a plot, whereas she
          sent him to it by deliberately forming that plot. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" type="section">
        <p>Further, it is not for my brother to say that he is quite sure his mother did not murder
          our father for when he had the chance of making sure, by torture, he refused it; he showed
          readiness only for those modes of inquiry which could yield no certainty. Yet he ought to
          have been ready to do what I in fact challenged him to do, so that an honest investigation
          of the facts might have been possible; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" type="section">
        <p>because then, if the slaves had admitted nothing, he would have confronted me with a
          vigorous defence based on certainty, and his mother would have been cleared of the present
          charge. But after refusing to inquire into the facts, how can he possibly be certain of
          what he refused to find out? [How, then, is it to be expected, gentlemen of the jury,
          that he should be sure of facts about which he has not learned the truth?<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See critical note.</note>]</p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>What reply does he mean to make to me? He was fully aware that once the slaves were
          examined under torture his mother was doomed; and he thought that her life depended upon
          the avoiding of such an examination, as he and his companions imagined that the truth
          would in that event be lost to sight. How, then, is he going to remain true to his oath as
            defendant,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A curiously loose expression. The oath taken
            by both parties in cases of murder was always a <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >DIWMOSI/A</foreign>, (cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 1.28">Antiph. 1.28</bibl>), never as here,
            an <foreign xml:lang="greek">A)NTWMOSI/A</foreign></note> if he claims to be in full
          possession of the facts after refusing to make certain of them by accepting my offer of a
          perfectly impartial investigation of the matter by torture? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" type="section">
        <p>In the first place, I was ready to torture the defendants' slaves, who knew that this
          woman, my opponents' mother, had planned to poison our father on a previous occasion as
          well, that our father had caught her in the act, and that she had admitted everything—
          save that it was not to kill him, but to restore his love that she alleged herself to be
          giving him the potion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" type="section">
        <p>Owing, then, to the nature of the slaves' evidence, I proposed to have their story tested
          under torture after making a written note of my charges against this woman; and I told the
          defence to conduct the examination themselves in my presence, so that the slaves might not
          give forced answers to questions put by me. I was satisfied to have the written questions
          used; and that in itself should afford a presumption in my favour that my search for my
          father's murderer is honest and impartial. Should the slaves resort to denial or make
          inconsistent statements, my intention was that the torture should force from them the
          charges which the facts demanded: for torture will make even those prepared to lie confine
          their charges to the truth. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>I am quite sure, though, that had the defence approached me with an offer of their slaves
          directly they learned that I intended to proceed against my father's murderer, only to
          meet with a refusal of the offer, they would have produced that refusal as affording the
          strongest presumption of their innocence of the murder. As it is, it was I who in the
          first place volunteered to conduct the examination personally, and in the second told the
          defence to conduct it themselves in my stead. Surely, then, it is only logical that this
          corresponding offer and refusal should afford a presumption in my favour that they are
          guilty of the murder. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" type="section">
        <p>Had I refused an offer of theirs to hand over their slaves for torture, the refusal would
          have afforded a presumption in their favour. The presumption, then, should similarly be in
          my favour, if I was ready to discover the truth of the matter, while they refused to allow
          me to do so. In fact, it is amazing to me that they should try to persuade you not to find
          them guilty, after refusing to decide their case for themselves by handing over their
          slaves for torture. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>In the matter of the slaves, then, it is quite clear that the defence were themselves
          anxious to avoid ascertaining the facts. The knowledge that the crime would prove to lie
          at their own door made them desirous of leaving it wrapped in silence and uninvestigated.
          But you will not do this, gentlemen, as I know full well; you will bring it into the
          light. Enough, though; I will now try to give you a true statement of the facts: and may
          justice guide me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>There was an upper room in our house occupied by Philoneos, a highly respected friend of
          our father's, during his visits to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Now
          Philoneos had a mistress<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Clearly as a slave, as Philoneos has complete control over her, and she was
            later tortured and summarily executed.</note> whom he proposed to place in a brothel. My brother's mother made friends with her;
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" type="section">
        <p>and on hearing of the wrong intended by Philoneos, she sends for her, informing her on
          her arrival that she herself was also being wronged by our father. If the other would do
          as she was told, she said, she herself knew how to restore Philoneos' love for her and our
          father's for herself. She had discovered the means; the other's task was to carry out her
          orders. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" type="section">
        <p>She asked if she was prepared to follow her instructions, and, I imagine, received a
          ready assent.</p>
        <p> Later, Philoneos happened to have a sacrifice to perform to Zeus Ctesius<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Zeus as a god of the household. Hence the sacrifice takes
            place at Philoneus' private residence.</note> in Peiraeus, while my father was on the
          point of leaving for <placeName key="tgn,7012053">Naxos</placeName>. So Philoneos thought
          that it would be an excellent idea to make one journey of it by seeing my father as far as
          Peiraeus, offering the sacrifice, and entertaining his friend. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" type="section">
        <p>Philoneos' mistress accompanied him to attend the sacrifice. On reaching Peiraeus,
          Philoneos of course carried out the ceremony. When the sacrifice was over, the woman
          considered how to administer the draught: should she give it before or after supper? Upon
          reflection, she decided that it would be better to give it afterwards, thereby carrying
          out the suggestion of this Clytemnestra here.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the
            metaphorical use of the name cf. <bibl n="Andoc. 1.129">Andoc. 1.129</bibl>
            <foreign xml:lang="greek">TI/S A)\N EI)/H OU(=TOS; *OI)DI/POUS, H)\
              *AI)/GISQOS;</foreign></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" type="section">
        <p>Now it would take too long for me to furnish or for you to listen to a detailed
          description of the meal so I shall try to give you as brief an account as I can of the
          administration of the poison which followed. </p>
        <p> After supper was over, the two naturally set about pouring libations and sprinkling some
          frankincense to secure the favour of heaven, as the one was offering sacrifice to Zeus
          Ctesius and entertaining the other, and his companion was supping with a friend and on the
          point of putting out to sea. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" type="section">
        <p>But Philoneos' mistress, who poured the wine for the libation, while they offered their
          prayers—prayers never to be answered, gentlemen—poured in the poison with it. Thinking it
          a happy inspiration, she gave Philoneos the larger draught; she imagined perhaps that if
          she gave him more, Philoneos would love her the more: for only when the mischief was done
          did she see that my stepmother had tricked her. She gave our father a smaller draught.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" type="section">
        <p>So they poured their libation, and, grasping their own slayer, drained their last drink
          on earth. Philoneos expired instantly; and my father was seized with an illness which
          resulted in his death twenty days later. In atonement, the subordinate who carried out the
          deed has been punished as she deserved, although the crime in no sense originated from
          her: she was broken on the wheel and handed over to the executioner; and the woman from
          whom it did originate, who was guilty of the design, shall receive her reward also, if you
          and heaven so will.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >AI)TI/A</foreign> must here have the meaning of “ultimately responsible” rather than
            “guilty.” That the <foreign xml:lang="greek">PALLAKH/</foreign> was to some extent
            guilty is implicitly acknowledged in the statement that she deserved her
            punishment.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>Now mark the justice of my request as compared with my brother's. I am bidding you avenge
          once and for all time him who has been wrongfully done to death; but my brother will make
          no plea for the dead man, although he has a right to your pity, your help, and your
          vengeance, after having had his life cut short in so godless and so miserable a fashion by
          those </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" type="section">
        <p>who should have been the last to commit such a deed. No, he will appeal for the
          murderess; he will make an unlawful, a sinful, an impossible request, to which neither
          heaven nor you can listen. He will ask you to refrain from punishing a crime which the
          guilty woman could not bring herself to refrain from committing. But you are not here to
          champion the murderers: you are here to champion the victims willfully murdered, murdered
          moreover by those who should have been the last to commit such a deed. Thus it now rests
          with you to reach a proper verdict; see that you do so. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>My brother will appeal to you in the name of his mother who is alive and who killed
          her husband with out thought and without scruple; he hopes that if he is successful, she
          will escape paying the penalty for her crime. I, on the other hand, am appealing to you in
          the name of my father who is dead, that she may pay it in full; and it is in order that
          judgement may come upon wrongdoers for their misdeeds that you are yourselves constituted
          and called judges. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" type="section">
        <p>I am prosecuting to ensure that she pays for her crime and to avenge our father and your
          laws wherein you should support me one and all, if what I say is true. My brother, on the
          contrary, is defending this woman to enable one who has broken the laws to avoid paying
          for her misdeeds. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" type="section">
        <p>Yet which is the more just: that a willful murderer should be punished, or that he should
          not? Which has a better claim to pity, the murdered man or the murderess? To my mind, the
          murdered man: because in pitying him you would be acting more justly and more righteously
          in the eyes of gods and men. So now I ask that just as this woman put her husband to death
          without pity and without mercy, so she may herself be put to death by you and by justice;
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" type="section">
        <p>for she was the willful murderess who compassed his death: he was the victim who
          involuntarily came to a violent end. I repeat, gentlemen, a violent end; for he was on the
          point of sailing from this country and was dining under a friend's roof, when she, who had
          sent the poison, with orders that a draught be given him, murdered our father. What pity,
          then, what consideration, does a woman who refused to pity her own husband, who killed him
          impiously and shamefully, deserve from you or anyone else? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" type="section">
        <p>Involuntary accidents deserve such pity: not deliberately planned crimes and acts of
          wickedness. Just as this woman put her husband to death without respecting or fearing god,
          hero, or human being, so she would in her turn reap her justest reward were she herself
          put to death by you and by justice, without finding consideration, sympathy, or respect.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" type="section">
        <p/>
        <p>I am astounded at the shameless spirit shown by my brother. To think that he swore in his
          mother's defence that he was sure of her innocence! How could anyone be sure of what he
          did not witness in person? Those who plot the death of their neighbors do not, I believe,
          form their plans and make their preparations in front of witnessess; they act as secretly
          as possible and in such a way that not a soul knows; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" type="section">
        <p>while their victims are aware of nothing until they are already trapped and see the doom
          which has descended upon them. Then, if they are able and have time before they die, they
          summon their friends and relatives, call them to witness, tell them who the murderers are,
          and charge them to take vengeance for the wrong; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" type="section">
        <p>just as my father charged me, young as I was, during his last sad illness. Failing this,
          they make a statement in writing, call their slaves to witness, and reveal their murderers
          to them. My father told me, and laid his charge upon me, gentlemen, not upon his slaves,
          young though I still was. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" type="section">
        <p>I have stated my case; I have championed the dead man and the law. It is upon you that
          the rest depends; it is for you to weigh the matter and give a just decision. The gods of
          the world below are themselves, I think, mindful of those who have been wronged.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., a curse will fall upon the living, unless justice is
            done to the dead. Cf. <title>Tetral.</title> Gen. Introd. pp. 38-39.</note></p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
