<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>In Defence of Euxenippus from Speeches (English). Machine readable
                    text</title>
                <author>Hyperides</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Hyperides</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
                <refState unit="fragment"/>
            </refsDecl>

            <refsDecl n="speech=5">
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="fragment"/>
            </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1'])"><p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p></cRefPattern>
</refsDecl></encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
<change><date>May 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>June 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>4/30/93</date><respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>add refdecl, changed some of the FRAG attributes that had commentary in them, made notes have a space after them.</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
            <change when="2014-10-01" who="#Stella #Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0030.tlg004.perseus-eng1" type="translation" xml:lang="eng"><div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Personally, gentlemen of the jury, as I was just
                    saying to those seated beside me,<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The opening
                        words are the same as those of the speech against Demosthenes.</note> I am
                    surprised that you are not tired by now of this kind of impeachment. At one time
                    the men impeached before you were Timomachus, Leosthenes, Callistratus, Philon
                    of Anaea, Theotimus who lost <placeName key="perseus,Sestos">Sestos</placeName>,
                    and others of the same type.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Timomachus was an
                        Athenian general who failed in his command against Cotys of <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> (c. <date>361</date> B.C.), and on
                        his return to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> was
                        condemned either to death or to a heavy fine. See <bibl n="Dem. 19.180">Dem.
                            19.180</bibl>, and the scholiast on <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.56">Aeschin.
                            1.56</bibl>. Leosthenes, who led an Athenian fleet against Alexander of
                        Pherae (c. <date>361</date> B.C.), lost five triremes, was condemned to
                        death at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and went into
                        exile. See <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.124">Aeschin. 2.124</bibl>, and <bibl n="Diod. 15.95">Diod. Sic. 15.95.2</bibl>. For Callistratus, a prominent
                        orator, exiled at about the same time and later put to death, see <bibl n="Lyc. 1.93">Lyc. 1.93</bibl>. Theotimus, also about the year 361, was
                        impeached for losing <placeName key="perseus,Sestos">Sestos</placeName> to
                        Cotys. Of PhiIon nothing further is known.</note> Some were accused of
                    betraying ships, others of giving up Athenian cities, and another, an orator, of
                    speaking against the people's interests. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
                <p>Though there were five of them, not one waited to be tried; they left the city of
                    their own accord and went into exile. The same is true of many others who were
                    impeached. In fact it was a rare thing to see anyone subjected to impeachment
                    appearing in court. So serious and so notorious were the crimes which at that
                    time led to an impeachment. But the present practice in the city is utterly
                    absurd. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
                <p>Diognides and Antidorus the metic are impeached on a charge of hiring out
                    flute-girls at a higher price than that fixed by law, Agasicles of <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName><note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Agasicles, according to Harpocration and Suidas (sv. <foreign xml:lang="greek">*)agasiklh=s</foreign>), though an alien, bribed the
                        people of Halimus to enroll him in their deme. The former adds that
                        Dinarchus wrote a speech prosecuting him for this. See <bibl n="Din. Fr. 7">Din. Fr. 7</bibl>.</note> because he was registered in Halimus, and
                    Euxenippus because of the dreams which he claims to have had; though surely not
                    one of these charges has anything to do with the impeachment law. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>And yet in public trials, gentlemen of the jury,
                    the jury should refuse to listen to the details of the prosecution until they
                    have first considered the point at issue, and also the written statement of the
                    accused, to see if the pleas are legally valid. It is certainly wrong to
                    maintain, as Polyeuctus did in his speech for the prosecution, that defendants
                    should not insist on the impeachment law; which lays it down that impeachments
                    shall be reserved for the orators themselves, when they speak against the
                    interests of the people, but shall not apply to every Athenian.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
                <p>With me this law would have first claim to notice; and a point, I think, which
                    should be dwelt on as much as any, is how to ensure that the laws in a democracy
                    are binding and that impeachments and other actions brought into court are
                    legally valid. It was with this in view that you made separate laws covering
                    individually all offences committed in the city. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
                <p>Suppose someone commits a religious offence. There is the method of public
                    prosecution before the King-Archon. Or he maltreats his parents. The Archon
                    presides over his case. Someone makes illegal proposals in the city. There is
                    the board of Thesmothetae ready. Perhaps he does something involving summary
                    arrest. You have the authority of the Eleven.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The King-Archon, who supervised all religious ceremonies of state, judged
                        all cases connected with religion, while the Archon himself dealt with
                        family law. (See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57.2">Aristot. Ath. Pol.
                            57.2</bibl> and <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 56.6">Aristot. Ath. Pol.
                            56.6</bibl>.) For the Thesmothetae compare <bibl n="Hyp. 1.12">Hyp.
                            1.12</bibl> and note. Summary arrest could be legally employed against
                        three classes of criminal. Of these, two were tried by the Eleven and one by
                        the Thesmothetae. (See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 52.1">Aristot. Ath. Po1.
                            52.1</bibl>.)</note> Similarly, to deal with every other offence you
                    have established laws, offices, and courts appropriate to each. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
                <p>In what cases then do you think impeachments should be used? Your answer has
                    already been embodied in detail in the law, so as to leave no room for doubt.
                    “If any person,” it says, “seeks to overthrow the democracy of the Athenians.”
                    Naturally, gentlemen of the jury; for a charge like that admits of no excuse
                    from anyone nor of an oath for postponement.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">A
                        man due to be tried could offer the court an excuse (<foreign xml:lang="greek">skh=fis</foreign>) and provide a second party to take
                        an oath (<foreign xml:lang="greek">u(pwmosi/a</foreign>) that this excuse
                        was true. In such cases the jury might grant a postponement.</note> It
                    should come directly into court. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
                <p>“Or if he attends a meeting in any place with intent to undermine the democracy,
                    or forms a political society; or if anyone betrays a city, or ships, or any
                    land, or naval force, or being an orator, makes speeches contrary to the
                    interests of the Athenian people, receiving bribes.” The opening provisions of
                    the law were made applicable by you to the entire citizen body, since those are
                    offences which anyone might commit; but the latter part is directed against the
                    orators themselves, in whose hands the proposing of measures rests. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
                <p>You would have been insane if you had framed the law in any other way; if, when
                    the orators enjoy both the honors and the profits of speaking, you had exposed
                    the ordinary citizen to the risks that go with them. Nevertheless, Polyeuctus is
                    bold enough to assert, though he is bringing in an impeachment, that defendants
                    must not make use of the impeachment law. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
                <p>All other prosecutors who think it necessary, when speaking first, to steal the
                    defendants' arguments from them encourage the jury to refuse to listen to any
                    defendant who does not keep within the scope of the law, to challenge his
                    statements and tell the clerk to read the law. The opposite is true of you: it
                    is recourse to law of which you think you should deprive Euxenippus in his
                    defence. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You also maintain that no one should even help him
                    or be his advocate, and you exhort the jury to refuse a hearing to those who
                    come up to speak. And yet, of the many good institutions of the city, what is
                    better or more democratic<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Compare <bibl n="Hyp. 1.10">Hyp. 1.10</bibl>.</note> than our custom, when some
                    private person is facing the danger of a trial and cannot conduct his own
                    defence, of allowing any citizen who wishes to come forward to help him and give
                    the jury a fair statement of the case? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
                <p>You will claim, no doubt, that you have never worked on such a principle. Yet
                    when you were prosecuted by Alexander of Oeon,<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Nothing further is known of this trial. For other occasions on which
                        Hyperides opposed Polyeuctus compare <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 24">Hyp. Fr.
                            24</bibl> and<bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 25">Hyp. Fr. 25</bibl>.</note> you asked
                    for ten advocates from the tribe Aegeis, and I was one of them, chosen by
                    yourself. You also summoned men from other tribes into the court to help you.
                    But why should I mention other instances? Take your handling of the present
                    trial. Did you not make as many accusations as you wished? Did you not call
                    Lycurgus to join you in the prosecution, a speaker who is the equal of any in
                    the city and who has the reputation among these gentlemen of being sound and
                    honorable? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
                <p>If you then, as a defendant, may summon advocates, or as a prosecutor may bring
                    in co-prosecutors—you who are not merely capable of speaking for yourself but
                    well able to give a whole city trouble—is Euxenippus, because he is not a
                    professional speaker and is now advanced in years, even to be denied the help of
                    friends and relatives, on pain of their being abused by you? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Yes; for in the words of your indictment, his
                    conduct has been scandalous and deserves the death penalty. Gentlemen of the
                    jury, will you please review it and scrutinize it point by point? The people
                    ordered Euxenippus, as one of three, to lie down in the temple; and he tells us
                    that he fell asleep and had a dream which he reported to them. If you assumed,
                    Polyeuctus, that this was true and that he reported to the people what he
                    actually saw in his sleep, why is he to blame for notifying the Athenians of the
                    commands which the god had been giving him? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
                <p>If on the other hand, as you now maintain, you thought that he misrepresented the
                    god and, out of partiality for certain persons, had made a false report to the
                    people, rather than propose a decree disputing the dream you ought to have sent
                    to <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, as the previous speaker
                    said, and inquired the truth from the god. But instead of doing that, you
                    proposed a decree, entirely conceived by yourself,<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">I follow Colin's interpretation of the word <foreign xml:lang="greek">au)totelh/s</foreign> in this passage, although it was
                        often used technically to describe a decree laid before the people without
                        previous consideration by the Council (see <bibl n="Hsch. a.8474.1">Hesychius, sv. <foreign xml:lang="greek">au)totele/s
                            yh/fisma</foreign></bibl>).</note> against two tribes, a measure not
                    only most unjust but self-contradictory also. This was what caused your
                    conviction for illegal proposals. It was not the fault of Euxenippus. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Let us consider it in this way. The tribes, formed
                    into groups of two, shared out the mountains in Oropus awarded to them by the
                    people. This mountain fell to the lot of Acamantis and Hippothoontis. You
                    proposed that these tribes should restore the mountain to Amphiaraus and the
                    price of produce from it which they had sold; your reason being that the fifty
                    boundary officials had selected it beforehand and set it apart for the god, and
                    that the two tribes had no right to be holding it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
                <p>A little later in the same decree you propose that the eight tribes shall provide
                    compensation and pay it to the other two so that they shall not suffer unfairly.
                    But if the mountain really belonged to the two tribes and you tried to take it
                    from them, surely we are entitled to be angry. Alternatively, if they had no
                    right to be occupying it and it belonged to the god, why were you proposing that
                    the other tribes should actually pay them compensation? They should have been
                    well content that when restoring the property of the god they did not also pay a
                    fine in cash. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>These proposals, when examined in court, were
                    considered unsatisfactory, and the jury condemned you. So if you had been
                    acquitted in your trial, Euxenippus would not have misrepresented the god:
                    because you happened to be convicted, must ruin fall on him?<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Apparently it was loss of prestige which caused Polyeuctus
                        to be resentful against Euxenippus, since the actual fine was
                        negligible.</note> And when you, who proposed a decree like that, were fined
                    a mere twenty-five drachmas, is the man who lay down in the temple at the
                    people's request even to be refused a grave in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Yes, you say; for he committed a serious crime in
                    regard to the cup which he allowed Olympias to dedicate to the statue of
                        Health.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Olympias, mother of Alexander the
                        Great, was sent by him about <date>331</date> B.C. to <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName>, where her brother Alexander was
                        king. On the death of the latter she became regent for the young prince
                        Neoptolemus and so controlled Molossia, which had been attached to the
                        kingdom by Philip in <date>343</date> B.C. The statue of Health stood on the
                        Acropolis. (See <bibl n="Paus. 1.23.5">Paus. 1.23.5</bibl>.) It is not known
                        how Euxenippus was connected with this affair.</note> You think that if you
                    bring her name irrelevantly into the case to serve your own ends and accuse
                    Euxenippus of deceitful flattery, you will bring down the jury's hatred and
                    anger upon him. The thing to do, my friend, is not to use the name of Olympias
                    and Alexander in the hope of harming some citizen. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
                <p>Wait till they send the Athenian people some injunctions which are unjust or
                    inappropriate. Then is the time for you to get up and oppose them in the
                    interests of your city, disputing the cause of justice with their envoys and
                    resorting to the Congress of the Greeks<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        Congress, which united all Greek states except <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, was founded by Philip after the
                        battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> in
                            <date>338</date> B.C.</note> as the champion of your country. But you
                    never stood up or spoke about them there; it is only here that you hate Olympias
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
                <p>so that you can ruin Euxenippus by alleging that he flatters her and the
                    Macedonians. If you show us that he has ever been to <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> or entertained any of the people in
                    his own home, that he knows a Macedonian intimately or meets any of them; if you
                    prove that he has said one word about such matters, either in a shop or in the
                    market or anywhere else, instead of quietly and modestly minding his own
                    business as much as any other citizen, the jury may do what they like with him.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
                <p>For if these charges of yours were true, not only you but everyone else in the
                    city would know the facts, as is the case with all the others who speak or act
                    in the interests of <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>. Their
                    conduct is no secret. The rest of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, even the schoolchildren, know the orators who take
                    Macedonian money and the other persons who put up Macedonian visitors, either
                    secretly making them welcome or going into the streets to meet them when they
                    arrive. You will not see Euxenippus classed with a single one of these men
                    anywhere. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
                <p>But you do not prosecute or bring to trial any of the people who are universally
                    known to be doing these things, and yet you accuse Euxenippus of flattery when
                    his manner of life disproves the charge. And yet if you had any sense, you would
                    neither be blaming Euxenippus for the dedication of the cup nor have made any
                    further mention of the affair, since it is impolitic to do so. Why is that? Will
                    you please listen, gentlemen of the jury, to the account which I am going to
                    give? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Olympias has made complaints against you about the
                    incident at <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName>,<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> in
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002705">Epirus</placeName> was, second to
                            <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, the most famous
                        oracle of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. Dione, a consort
                        of Zeus, was often worshipped in his temples.</note> complaints which are
                    unfair, as I have twice already proved in the Assembly before yourselves and the
                    rest of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. I explained to her
                    envoys that the charges she brings against the city are not justified. For Zeus
                    of <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> commanded you through the
                    oracle to embellish the statue of Dione. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
                <p>You made a face as beautiful as you could, together with all the other
                    appropriate parts; and having prepared a great deal of expensive finery for the
                    goddess and dispatched envoys with a sacrifice at great expense, you embellished
                    the statue of Dione in a manner worthy of yourselves and of the goddess. These
                    measures brought you the complaints of Olympias, who said in her letters that
                    the country of Molossia, in which the temple stands, belonged to her, and that
                    therefore we had no right to interfere with anything there at all. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
                <p>Now if you decide that the incidents relating to the cup constitute an offence,
                    we are in a sense condemning ourselves as being wrong in what we did at
                        <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName>. But if we acquiesce in
                    what has been done we shall have taken away her right to these theatrical
                    complaints and accusations. For I presume that when Olympias can furnish
                    ornaments for shrines in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> we
                    may safely do so at <placeName key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName>,
                    particularly when the god demands it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>However, it seems to me, Polyeuctus, that there is
                    nothing which you would not use as grounds for an accusation. But from the time
                    when you decided to play a part in public life, for which I admit you are well
                    fitted, you should not have prosecuted private individuals or made them the
                    victims of your impudence. Wait for an orator to commit a crime and then
                    prosecute him, or for a general to do wrong and then impeach him. These are the
                    men who have power to harm the city, all of them who choose to do so, not
                    Euxenippus or any member of this jury. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="section">
                <p>It is not as if I were prescribing one line of conduct for you having followed
                    another in my own public life. I myself never in my life prosecuted any private
                    citizen, and there are some whom before now I have done my best to help. What
                    men, then, have I prosecuted and brought to trial? Aristophon of Hazenia,<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Of the three orators here mentioned Aristophon
                        was prosecuted by Hyperides in <date>362</date> B.C., Diopithes at an
                        unknown date, and Philocrates in 343. See further, notes on <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 17">Hyp. Fr. 17</bibl>,<bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 15">Hyp. Fr.
                            15</bibl>, and <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 16">Hyp. Fr. 16</bibl>.</note> now a
                    most influential person in public life—he was acquitted in this court by two
                    votes only; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="section">
                <p>Diopithes of Sphettus, thought to be the most formidable man in the city;
                    Philocrates of Hagnus, whose political career has been marked by the utmost
                    daring and wantonness. I prosecuted that man for his services to Philip against
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and secured his
                    conviction in court. The impeachment which I drew up was just and in accordance
                    with the law, referring to him as “an orator giving counsel against the best
                    interests of the people and receiving money and gifts from those working against
                    them.” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="section">
                <p>Even so I was not satisfied to bring in the impeachment before I had added
                    underneath: “These proposals he made against the best interests of the people,
                    because he had taken bribes.” And I wrote his decree underneath. And again I
                    added: “These further proposals he made against the best interests of the
                    people, because he had taken bribes.” And I wrote the decree alongside. Indeed
                    this statement is written down five or six times in my speech; for I thought
                    that I must make the trial and the prosecution just. But you could not include
                    in your impeachment the things which you allege Euxenippus to have said against
                    the best interests of the people. Yet, though he is a private citizen, by your
                    mode of prosecution you class him as an orator. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="section">
                <p>After a scanty reference to the defendant's written statement you are now
                    bringing fresh charges and incriminations against him, mentioning, amongst other
                    similar allegations, that he tried to marry his daughter to Philocles, that he
                    undertook an arbitration for Demotion, and other similar charges.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Nothing is known of Philocles and the reference
                        to Demotion is obscure. He was clearly an unpopular character, perhaps the
                        parasite feeder satirized by comedians (see <bibl n="Ath. 6.243">Athen.
                            6.243</bibl> b). The translation of the phrase <foreign xml:lang="greek">*dhmoti/wnos di/aitan e)/laben</foreign> is doubtful; it might mean:
                        “adopted the method of life of Demotion.”</note> Your intention is that, if
                    the defence neglect the main indictment and deal with the irrelevant
                    allegations, the jury shall interrupt them by calling: “Why do you tell us
                    this?” and if they ignore the additional points entirely their case shall be
                    weakened. For any charge that is not refuted is left to be fastened on by the
                    anger of the jury. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="32" subtype="section">
                <p>The most outrageous feature of your speech was the fact that often during the
                    argument you let fall the remark—you thought that your motive in doing so passed
                    unnoticed, though it was obvious—that Euxenippus was rich, and again, a little
                    later, that he had amassed great wealth dishonestly. It has surely nothing to do
                    with this case whether he is a man of large means or small, and to raise the
                    matter is malicious and implies an unfair assumption regarding the jury, namely
                    that they would base their verdict on other considerations than the point at
                    issue and the question whether the man on trial is offending against you or not.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="33" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You do not realize, Polyeuctus, it seems to me,
                    you and those who share your views, that there is not in the world a single
                    democracy or monarch or race more magnanimous than the Athenian people, and that
                    it does not forsake those citizens who are maligned by others, whether singly or
                    in numbers, but supports them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="34" subtype="section">
                <p>Let me give an instance. When Tisis of Agryle brought in an inventory of the
                    estate of Euthycrates, amounting to more than sixty talents, on the grounds of
                    its being public property, and again later promised to bring in an inventory of
                    the estate of Philip and Nausicles saying that they had made their money from
                    unregistered mines, this jury were so far from approving such a suggestion or
                    coveting the property of others that they immediately disfranchised the man who
                    tried to slander the accused and did not award him a fifth part of the
                        votes.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">No other details are known of the
                        cases mentioned here. An Epicrates of <placeName key="perseus,Pallene">Pallene</placeName> is known to have been trierarch in <date>342</date>
                        B.C. (IG. 2.803 e), and may be the man referred to in connection with the
                        second of the two trials.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="35" subtype="section">
                <p>Or take a recent instance, if you like, the verdict given by the jury last month,
                    surely a most commendable decision. I refer to the case of Lysander, who
                    reported that the mine of Epicrates of <placeName key="perseus,Pallene">Pallene</placeName> had been bored beyond the boundaries. It had already
                    been worked for three years and virtually the richest men in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> had shares in it. Lysander promised
                    to secure three hundred talents for the city, since that, he claimed, was the
                    sum which they had made from the mine. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="36" subtype="section">
                <p>In spite of this the jury were governed, not by the accusers promises, but by the
                    claims of justice. They decided that the mine was within its proper limits, and
                    in one and the same verdict assured the safety of the men's estates and
                    guaranteed their working of the mine for the remainder of the period. That is
                    why the excavation of new mines, neglected previously because men were afraid,
                    is now in progress, and the city's revenues from these are again being
                    increased, revenues which some of our orators impaired by misleading the people
                    and subjecting the mine-workers to tribute. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="37" subtype="section">
                <p>The good citizen, gentlemen of the jury, is not a man to make some small
                    additions to the public funds in ways which cause an ultimate loss, nor one who,
                    by dishonestly producing an immediate profit, cuts off the city's lawful source
                    of revenue. On the contrary, he is the man who is anxious to keep what will be
                    profitable to the city in the future, to preserve agreement among the citizens
                    and safeguard your reputation. There are some who disregard these things. By
                    taking money from contractors they claim that they are providing revenue,
                    although it is the lack of it that they are really causing in the city. For when
                    anxiety is attached to earning and saving, who will want to take the risk? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="38" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now perhaps it is not easy to prevent these men
                    from acting as they do; but you, gentlemen of the jury, have saved many other
                    citizens who were unjustly brought to trial. Then help Euxenippus in the same
                    way, rather than desert him over a trivial matter, and in an impeachment like
                    the present: an impeachment to which he is not liable, which has been framed in
                    defiance of the laws, and which moreover has been partly invalidated by the
                    prosecutor himself. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="39" subtype="section">
                <p>For Polyeuctus has impeached Euxenippus for speaking against the best interests
                    of the people of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, being in
                    receipt of money and gifts from those acting against the people of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Now if he were arguing that there
                    were men outside the city with whom Euxenippus was co-operating on receipt of
                    bribes, he would then be able to say that, since these persons could not be
                    punished, their servants in the city must be brought to justice. But, in fact,
                    he says that it is from Athenians that Euxenippus has had the gifts. For shame,
                    sir; when you have here in the city the men who act against the people, do you
                    let them be and choose instead to harass Euxenippus? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="40" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I will say a few words more about the vote which
                    you are going to give and then leave the platform. When about to go to the
                    ballot, gentlemen of the jury, tell the clerk to read you the impeachment, the
                    impeachment law and the oath sworn by jurymen. Dispense with the arguments of us
                    all let the impeachment and the laws govern your decision and give whatever
                    verdict you consider to be just and in keeping with your oath. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="41" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>And now, Euxenippus, I have done all in my power
                    to help you. It remains for you to ask the jury's permission to summon your
                    friends and bring your children to the bar.</p>
            </div>
        </div></body>
    </text>
</TEI>