<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>

<fileDesc>

<titleStmt>
<title>Minos</title>
<author>Plato</author>
<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
</titleStmt>

	<publicationStmt>
		<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
		<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
		<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
	</publicationStmt>


<notesStmt> <note anchored="true">Text was scanned at St. Olaf Spring, 1992.</note></notesStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
	<monogr>
		<author>Plato</author>
		<title>Plato in Twelve Volumes, translated by W.R.M. Lamb.</title>
		
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">12</biblScope>
			<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
			<date>1927</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>


</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
	<refsDecl n="CTS">
		<cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
			replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">           
			<p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
		</cRefPattern>
	</refsDecl>

<!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="text"/>
<state unit="section"/>
</refsDecl>
<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
<state unit="text"/>
<state unit="page"/>
</refsDecl>-->
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
</langUsage>
	<particDesc>
		<person><persName>Socrates</persName></person>
		<person><persName>Companion</persName></person>
	</particDesc>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change when="2017-09-22" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion.</change>    
<change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
<change when="1992-07-01" who="WPM">Tagged in conformance with Prose.e dtd.</change>
</revisionDesc>

</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="eng">
		<body>
			<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg033.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
				
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="313">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="313"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="313a"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Tell me, what is law?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>To what kind of law does your question refer?</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>What!  Is there any difference between law and law, in this particular point of being law?  For just consider what is the actual question I am putting to you.  It is as though I had asked, what is gold:  if you had asked me in the same manner, to what kind of gold I refer, I think your question would have been incorrect.  For I presume there is no difference between gold and gold, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="313b"/> or between stone and stone, in point of being gold or stone;  and so neither does law differ at all from law, I suppose, but they are all the same thing.  For each of them is law alike, not one more so, and another less.  That is the particular point of my question—what is law as a whole?  So if you are ready, tell me.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Well, what else should law be, Socrates, but things loyally accepted? <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><foreign xml:lang="grc">νομιζόμενα</foreign> in ordinary speech meant <gloss>accepted by custom</gloss>: <q type="mentioned">loyally</q> here attempts to preserve the connection with <foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign> (<gloss>law</gloss> in this context, though sometimes <gloss>custom,</gloss> as below, 315 D).</note></p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And so speech, you think, is the things that are spoken, or sight the things seen, or hearing the things heard?  Or is speech <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="313c"/> something distinct from the things spoken, sight something distinct from the things seen, and hearing something distinct from the things heard;  and so law is something distinct from things loyally accepted?  Is this so, or what is your view?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I find it now to be something distinct.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then law is not things loyally accepted.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I think not.</p></said></div>
				
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="314">
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Now what can law be?  Let us consider it in this way.  Suppose someone had asked us about what was stated just now: <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="314"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="314a"/> Since you say it is by sight that things seen are seen, what is this sight whereby they are seen?  Our answer to him would have been:  That sensation which shows objects by means of the eyes.  And if he had asked us again:  Well then, since it is by hearing that things heard are heard, what is hearing?  Our answer to him would have been:  That sensation which shows us sounds by means of the ears.  In the same way then, suppose he should also ask us:  Since it is by law that loyally accepted things are so accepted, what is this law whereby they are so accepted? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="314b"/> Is it some sensation or showing, as when things learnt are learnt by knowledge showing them, or some discovery, as when things discovered are discovered—for instance, the causes of health and sickness by medicine, or the designs of the gods, as the prophets say, by prophecy;  for art is surely our discovery of things, is it not?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Certainly.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then what thing especially of this sort shall we surmise law to be?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Our resolutions and decrees, I imagine: for how else can one describe law? <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="314c"/> So that apparently the whole thing, law, as you put it in your question, is a city’s resolution.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>State opinion, it seems, is what you call law.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I do.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And perhaps you are right:  but I fancy we shall get a better knowledge in this way.  You call some men wise?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I do.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And the wise are wise by wisdom?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And again, the just are just by justice?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Certainly.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And so the law-abiding are law-abiding by law?</p></said>
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="314d"/>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And the lawless are lawless by lawlessness?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And the law-abiding are just?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And the lawless are unjust?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Unjust.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And justice and law are most noble?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>That is so.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And injustice and lawlessness most base?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And the former preserve cities and everything else, while the latter destroy and overturn them?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Hence we must regard law as something noble, and seek after it as a good.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Undeniably.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And we said that law is a city’s resolution?</p></said>
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="314e"/>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>So we did.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well now, are not some resolutions good, and others evil?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes, to be sure.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And, you know, law was not evil.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>No, indeed.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So it is not right to reply, in that simple fashion, that law is a city’s resolution.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I agree that it is not.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>An evil resolution, you see, cannot properly be a law.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>No, to be sure.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But still, I am quite clear myself that law is some sort of opinion;  and since it is not evil opinion, is it not manifest by this time that it is good opinion, granting that law is opinion?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But what is good opinion?  Is it not true opinion?</p></said></div>
				
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="315">
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="315"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="315a"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And true opinion is discovery of reality?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes, it is.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So law tends to be discovery of reality.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Then how is it, Socrates, if law is discovery of reality, that we do not use always the same laws on the same matters, if we have thus got realities discovered?</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Law tends none the less to be discovery of reality:  but men, who do not use <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="315b"/> always the same laws, as we observe, are not always able to discover what the law is intent on—reality.  For come now, let us see if from this point onward we can get it clear whether we use always the same laws or different ones at different times, and whether we all use the same, or some of us use some, and others others.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Why, that, Socrates, is no difficult matter to determine—that the same men do not use always the same laws, and also that different men use different ones.  With us, for instance, human sacrifice is not legal, but unholy, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="315c"/> whereas the Carthaginians perform it as a thing they account holy and legal, and that too when some of them sacrifice even their own sons to Cronos, as I daresay you yourself have heard.  And not merely is it foreign peoples who use different laws from ours, but our neighbors in Lycaea <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Or Lycoa, a town in the Arcadian district Maenalia.</note> and the descendants of Athamas <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Cf. Herod. vii. 197.  At Alus in Achaea Xerxes was told of human sacrifices offered to purge the guilt of Athamas in plotting the death of his son Phrixus.</note>—you know their sacrifices, Greeks though they be.  And as to ourselves too, you know, of course, from what you have heard yourself, the kind of laws we formerly used in regard to our dead, when we slaughtered sacred victims before <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="315d"/> the funeral procession, and engaged urn-women to collect the bones from the ashes.  Then again, a yet earlier generation used to bury the dead where they were, in the house:  but we do none of these things.  One might give thousands of other instances;  for there is ample means of proving that neither we copy ourselves nor mankind each other always in laws and customs.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And it is no wonder, my excellent friend, if what you say is correct, and I have overlooked it.  But if you continue to express your views after your own fashion in lengthy speeches, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="315e"/> and I speak likewise, we shall never come to any agreement, in my opinion:  but if we study the matter jointly, we may perhaps concur.  Well now, if you like, hold a joint inquiry with me by asking me questions;  or if you prefer, by answering them.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Why, I am willing, Socrates, to answer anything you like.</p></said>
	<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Come then, do you consider <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The word <foreign xml:lang="grc">νομίζειν</foreign> here and in what follows is intended to retain some of the sense of <foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign> as <q type="emph">accepted</q> law and custom which it had in what precedes;  see note, 313 B.</note> just things to be unjust and unjust things just, or just things to be just and unjust things unjust?</p></said></div>
				
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="316">
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I consider just things to be just, and unjust things unjust.</p></said>
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="316"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="316a"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And are they so considered among all men elsewhere as they are here?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And among the Persians also?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Among the Persians also.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Always, I presume?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Always.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Are things that weigh more considered heavier here, and things that weigh less lighter, or the contrary?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>No, those that weigh more are considered heavier, and those that weigh less lighter.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And is it so in <placeName key="perseus,Carthage">Carthage</placeName> also, and in Lycaea?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Noble things, it would seem, are everywhere considered noble,
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="316b"/>and base things base;  not base things noble or noble things base.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>That is so.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And thus, as a universal rule, realities, and not unrealities, are accepted as real, both among us and among all other men.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I agree.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then whoever fails to attain reality, fails to attain accepted law.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>In your present way of putting it, Socrates, the same things appear to be accepted as lawful both by us and by the rest of the world, always: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="316c"/> but when I reflect that we are continually changing our laws in all sorts of ways, I cannot bring myself to assent.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Perhaps it is because you do not reflect that when we change our pieces at draughts they are the same pieces.  But look at it, as I do, in this way.  Have you in your time come across a treatise on healing the sick?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I have.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then do you know to what art such a treatise belongs?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I do:  medicine.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And you give the name of doctors to those who have knowledge of these matters?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="316d"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then do those who have knowledge accept the same views on the same things, or do they accept different views?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>The same, in my opinion.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Do Greeks only accept the same views as Greeks on what they know, or do foreigners also agree on these matters, both among themselves and with Greeks?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>It is quite inevitable, I should say, that those who know should agree in accepting the same views, whether Greeks or foreigners.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well answered.  And do they so always?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes, it is so always.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And do doctors on their part, in their treatises on health, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="316e"/> write what they accept as real?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then these treatises of the doctors are medical, and medical laws.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Medical, to be sure.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And are agricultural treatises likewise agricultural laws?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And whose are the treatises and accepted rules about garden-work?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Gardeners’.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So these are our gardening laws.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Of people who know how to control gardens?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Certainly.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And it is the gardeners who know.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And whose are the treatises and accepted rules about the confection of tasty dishes?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Cooks’.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then there are laws of cookery?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Of cookery.</p></said></div>
				
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="317">
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Of people who know, it would seem, how to control the confection of tasty dishes?</p></said> 
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="317"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="317a"/>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And it is the cooks, they say, who know?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes, it is they who know.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Very well;  and now, whose are the treatises and accepted rules about the government of a state?  Of the people who know how to control states, are they not?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I agree.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And is it anyone else than statesmen and royal persons <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Cf. <title>Euthyd</title>. 291 C, <title>Politicus</title> 266-7, where Plato identifies the statesman’s and the king’s art.</note> who know?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>It is they, to be sure.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then what people call <q type="emph">laws</q> are treatises of state,—<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="317b"/> writings of kings and good men.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>That is true.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And must it not be that those who know will not write differently at different times on the same matters?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>They will not.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Nor will they ever change one set of accepted rules for another in respect of the same matters.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>No, indeed.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So if we see some persons anywhere doing this, shall we say that those who do so have knowledge, or have none?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>That they have no knowledge.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And again, whatever is right, we shall say is lawful for each person, whether in medicine or in cookery or in gardening?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="317c"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And whatever is not right we shall decline to call lawful?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>We shall decline.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then it becomes unlawful.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>It must.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And again, in writings about what is just and unjust, and generally about the government of a state and the proper way of governing it, that which is right is the king’s law, but not so that which is not right, though it seems to be law to those who do not know; for it is unlawful.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
	<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="317d"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then we rightly admitted that law is discovery of reality.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>So it appears.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Now let us observe this further point about it. Who has knowledge of distributing <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The words <foreign xml:lang="grc">διανέμειν</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">νομεύς</foreign> in this passage introduce the primitive meaning of <foreign xml:lang="grc">νόμος</foreign> — <gloss>distribution</gloss> or <gloss>apportionment</gloss> of each person’s status, property, rights, etc.</note> seed over land?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>A farmer.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And does he distribute the suitable seed to each sort of land?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then the farmer is a good apportioner of it, and his laws and distributions are right in this matter?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And who is a good apportioner of notes struck for a tune, skilled in distributing suitable notes, and who is it whose laws are right here?</p></said>
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="317e"/>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>The flute-player and the harp-player.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then he who is the best lawyer in these matters is the best flute-player.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And who is most skilled in distributing food to human bodies?  Is it not he who assigns suitable food?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then his distributions and laws are best, and whoever is the best lawyer in this matter is also the best apportioner.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Certainly.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Who is he?</p></said></div>
				
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="318">
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>A trainer.</p></said> 
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="318"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="318a"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>He is the best man to pasture <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Here <foreign xml:lang="grc" >νόμος</foreign> is connected with a special use of <foreign xml:lang="grc">νέμειν</foreign> — <gloss>find appropriate pasture for</gloss> —derived from its original meaning of <gloss>apportion.</gloss></note> the human herd of the body? <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The awkward imagery of this sentence obviously cannot have come from Plato’s mind or hand.</note></p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And who is the best man to pasture a flock of sheep?  What is his name?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>A shepherd.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then the shepherd’s laws are best for sheep.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And the herdsman’s for oxen.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And whose laws are best for the souls of men? The king’s, are they not? Say if you agree.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I do.</p></said>
		<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="318b"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then you are quite right.  Now can you tell me who, in former times, has proved himself a good lawgiver in regard to the laws of flute-playing?  Perhaps you cannot think of him:  would you like me to remind you?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Do by all means.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then is it Marsyas, by tradition, and his beloved <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>, the Phrygian?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>That is true.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And their flute-tunes also are most divine, and alone stir and make manifest those who are in need of the gods; <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Cf. <title>Sympos</title>. 215 C (from which this allusion to Marsyas is feebly imitated) <foreign xml:lang="grc">δηλοῖ τοὺς τῶν θεῶν τε καὶ τελετῶν δεομένους</foreign>, where <gloss>in need of the gods</gloss> seems to be a mystic phrase for <gloss>ready for divine possession</gloss> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐνθουσιασμός</foreign>).</note> and to this day they only remain, as being divine.</p></said>
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="318c"/>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>That is so.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And who by tradition has shown himself a good lawgiver among the ancient kings, so that to this day his ordinances remain, as being divine?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I cannot think.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Do you not know which of the Greeks use the most ancient laws?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Do you mean the Spartans, and Lycurgus the lawgiver?</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Why, that is a matter, I daresay, of less than three hundred years ago, or but a little more.  But whence is it that <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="318d"/> the best of those ordinances come?  Do you know?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>From <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, so they say.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then the people there use the most ancient laws in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then do you know who were their good kings?  Minos and Rhadamanthus, the sons of Zeus and Europa;  those laws were theirs.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Rhadamanthus, they do say, Socrates, was a just man;  but Minos was a savage sort of person, harsh and unjust.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Your tale, my excellent friend, is a fiction of Attic tragedy.</p></said>
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="318e"/>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>What!  Is not this the tradition about Minos?</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Not in Homer and Hesiod;  and yet they are more to be believed than all the tragedians together, from whom you heard your tale.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Well, and what, pray, is their tale about Minos?</p></said></div>
	
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="319">
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>I will tell you, in order that you may not share the impiety of the multitude: for there cannot conceivably be anything more impious or more to be guarded against than being mistaken in word and deed with regard to the gods, and after them, with regard to divine men; you must take very great precaution, whenever you are about to <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="319"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="319a"/> blame or praise a man, so as not to speak incorrectly. For this reason you must learn to distinguish honest and dishonest men: for God feels resentment when one blames a man who is like himself, or praises a man who is the opposite; and the former is the good man. For you must not suppose that while stocks and stones and birds and snakes are sacred, men are not; nay, the good man is the most sacred of all these things, and the wicked man is the most defiled.
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So if I now proceed to relate how Minos is eulogized by Homer <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="319b"/> and Hesiod, my purpose is to prevent you, a man sprung from a man, from making a mistake in regard to a hero who was the son of Zeus. <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb" >Minos and Rhadamanthus were sons of Zeus and Europa.</note> For Homer, in telling of <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> that there were in it many men and <quote>ninety cities,</quote> says:<quote type="verse"> <l met="dactylic">And amongst them is the mighty city of <placeName key="tgn,7010870">Cnossos</placeName>, where Minos was king, having colloquy <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ὀαριστής</foreign> means <gloss>one who has familiar converse</gloss> (<foreign xml:lang="grc" >ὄαρος</foreign>).</note> with mighty Zeus in the ninth year.</l> </quote><bibl n="Hom. Od. 19.179">Hom. Od. 19.179</bibl> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="319c"/> Now here in Homer we have a eulogy of Minos, briefly expressed, such as the poet never composed for a single one of the heroes. For that Zeus is a sophist, and that sophistry is a highly honorable art, he makes plain in many other places, and particularly here. For he says that Minos consorted and discoursed with Zeus in the ninth year, and went regularly to be educated by Zeus as though he were a sophist. And the fact that Homer assigned this privilege of having been educated by Zeus to no one among the heroes but Minos makes this a marvellous piece of praise. <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="319d"/> And in the Ghost-raising in the <title>Odyssey</title> <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><bibl n="Hom. Od. 11.569">Hom. Od. 11.569</bibl></note> he has described Minos as judging with a golden scepter in his hand, but not Rhadamanthus: Rhadamanthus he has neither described here as judging nor anywhere as consorting with Zeus; wherefore I say that Minos above all persons has been eulogized by Homer. For to have been the son of Zeus, and to have been the only one who was educated by Zeus, is praise unsurpassable.
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>For the meaning of the verse— <quote type="verse"> <l met="dactylic">he was king having colloquy with mighty Zeus in the ninth year” —</l> </quote><bibl n="Hom. Od. 19.179">Hom. Od. 19.179</bibl> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="319e"/> is that Minos was a disciple of Zeus. For colloquies are discourses, and he who has colloquy is a disciple by means of discourse. So every ninth year Minos repaired to the cave of Zeus, to learn some things, and to show his knowledge of others that he had learnt from Zeus in the preceding nine years.</p></said></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="320">
<said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Some there are who suppose that he who has colloquy is a cup-companion and fellow-jester of Zeus: but one may take the following as a proof that <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="320"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="320a"/> they who suppose so are babblers. For of all the many nations of men, both Greek and foreign, the only people who refrain from drinking-bouts and the jesting that occurs where there is wine, are the Cretans, and after them the Spartans, who learnt it from the Cretans. In <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> it is one of their laws which Minos ordained that they are not to drink with each other to intoxication. And yet it is evident that the things he thought honorable were what he ordained as lawful for his people as well. For surely Minos did not, like an inferior person, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="320b"/> think one thing and do another, different from what he thought: no, this intercourse, as I say, was held by means of discussion for education in virtue. Wherefore he ordained for his people these very laws, which have made <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName> happy through the length of time, and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> happy also, since she began to use them; for they are divine.
<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Rhadamanthus was a good man indeed, for he had been educated by Minos; he had, however, been educated, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="320c"/> not in the whole of the kingly art, but in one subsidiary to the kingly, enough for presiding in law courts; so that he was spoken of as a good judge. For Minos used him as guardian of the law in the city, and Talos <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Talos, the brazen man who was given to Minos by Zeus, is described by Apoll. Rhod. iv. 1639ff., and Apollodorus i. 9. 26 (where see J. G. Frazer’s note in this series).</note> as the same for the rest of <placeName key="tgn,7012056" >Crete</placeName>. For Talos thrice a year made a round of the villages, guarding the laws in them, by holding their laws inscribed on brazen tablets, which gave him his name of <q type="emph">brazen.</q> And what Hesiod <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The passage quoted does not occur in our text of Hesiod, nor is it quoted by any other writer. The meter of the first line would be improved if we could read <foreign xml:lang="grc" >βασιλευτότατος</foreign>, from the <foreign xml:lang="grc" >βασιλευτός</foreign> used by Aristotle, <title>Pol.</title>. iii. 17. 1.</note> also has said <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="320d"/> of Minos is akin to this. For after mentioning him by name he remarks—<quote type="verse"> <l met="dactylic">Who was most kingly of mortal kings, and lorded it over more neighboring folk than any, holding the scepter of Zeus: therewith it was that he ruled the cities as king.</l> </quote><bibl n="Hes. Fr. 144">Hes. Fr. 144</bibl>And by the scepter of Zeus he means nothing else than the education that he had of Zeus, whereby he directed <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Then how has it ever come about, Socrates, that this report is spread abroad of Minos, as an uneducated <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="320e"/> and harsh-tempered person?</p></said></div>
	
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="321">
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Because of something that will make both you, if you are wise, my excellent friend, and everybody else who cares to have a good reputation, beware of ever quarreling with any man of a poetic turn. For poets have great influence over opinion, according as they create it in the minds of men by either commending or vilifying. And this was the mistake that Minos made, in waging war on this city of ours, which besides all its various culture has poets of every kind, and especially those who write tragedy. <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="321"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="321a"/> Now tragedy is a thing of ancient standing here; it did not begin, as people suppose, from Thespis or from Phrynicus, but if you will reflect, you will find it is a very ancient invention of our city. Tragedy is the most popularly delightful and soul-enthralling branch of poetry: in it, accordingly, we get Minos on the rack of verse,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">This is the meaning most probably intended, from an imperfect understanding of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐντείνειν</foreign> (<gloss>put some story into verse, or accompany it with music</gloss>) in Plato, <title>Phaedo</title> 60 D;<title>Protag</title>. 326 B. Minos was represented as a harsh despot in Euripides’<title>Cretans</title>, and probably in other lost plays.</note>, and thus avenge ourselves for that tribute which he compelled us to pay <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The legend was that Minos defeated the Athenians in war and compelled them to send a regular tribute of seven youths and seven maidens to be devoured by the Minotaur in the Cretan labyrinth.</note> This, then, was the mistake that Minos made—his quarrel with us—and hence it is that, as you said in your question, he has fallen more and more into evil repute. For that he was a good <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="321b"/> and law-abiding person, as we stated in what went before—a good apportioner—is most convincingly shown by the fact the his laws are unshaken, since they were made by one who discovered aright the truth of reality in regard to the management of a state.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>In my opinion, Socrates, your statement is a probable one.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then if what I say is true, do you consider that the Cretan people of Minos and Rhadamanthus use the most ancient laws?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>I do.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So these have shown themselves the best lawgivers among men of ancient times— <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="321c"/> apportioners and shepherds of men; just as Homer called the good general a <quote>shepherd of the folk.</quote></p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>Quite so, indeed.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Come then, in good friendship’s name: if someone should ask us what it is that the good lawgiver and apportioner for the body distributes to it when he makes it better, we should say, if we were to make a correct and brief answer, that it was food and labor; the former to strengthen, and the latter to exercise and brace it.</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>And we should be right.</p></said>
<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="321d"/>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And if he then proceeded to ask us—And what might that be which the good lawgiver and apportioner distributes to the soul to make it better?—what would be our answer if we would avoid being ashamed of ourselves and our years?</p></said>
<said who="#Companion"><label>Com.</label> <p>This time I am unable to say.</p></said>
<said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But indeed it is shameful for the soul of either of us to be found ignorant of those things within it on which its good and abject states depend, while it has studied those that pertain to the body and rest.</p></said></div>
		</div>
		</body>
	</text>

</TEI>
