<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title type="work" n="Her.">Heracles</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <author n="Eur.">Euripides</author>
                <editor role="translator" n="Coleridge">E. P. Coleridge</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Euripides</author>
                        <title>The Complete Greek Drama, edited by Whitney J. Oates and Eugene
                            O'Neill, Jr. in two volumes. 1. Heracles, translated by E. P.
                            Coleridge</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Random House</publisher>
                            <date>1938</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="card"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change><date>1988</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Judith Nelson</name>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Basic SGML tagging and modernization</item>
            </change>
            <change><date>6/95</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Added missing speaker tags.</item>
            </change>
            <change><date>15-Feb-00</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <resp>Markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item> $Log: tlg0006.tlg009.perseus-eng1.xml,v $ Revision 1.1 2013-09-13 23:17:34
                    balmas01 copyrighted CTS texts from sdl and classics in new canonical structure
                    per github repo Revision 1.1 2013-09-13 11:17:07 balmas01 moving Greg's
                    work-in-progress on CTS-izing greco-roman collection texts to a Work directory
                    Revision 1.2 2013-06-30 12:34:34 gcrane the card divs had had a line range but
                    there was a problem with this, so we just have the start line in the n
                    attribute. Revision 1.1 2009/11/23 18:46:15 rsingh04 moved more xml files around
                    based on copyright status Revision 1.3 2006/02/10 21:10:16 packel places/dates
                    now actually tagged Revision 1.2 2005/08/01 21:15:27 packel removed stray item
                    tags Revision 1.1 2005/07/25 14:33:57 packel Converted to XML Revision 1.8
                    2004/04/21 20:27:27 mimno added card 1s Revision 1.7 2003/07/01 22:16:10 yorkc
                    Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character
                    encodings and typos.) Revision 1.6 2000/03/04 20:34:32 dasmith Added separate
                    funder entity to TEI header. Revision 1.5 2000/02/16 00:07:51 amahoney bring up
                    to p3 </item></change>-->
            <change when="2015-04-15" who="Stella Dee">converted to CTS EpiDoc</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
            <!--
            <castList>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>Amphitryon</role>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>
                        <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>
                    </role>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>Chorus</role>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>Lycus</role>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>Heracles</role>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>Iris</role>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>Madness</role>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>Messenger</role>
                </castItem>
                <castItem type="role">
                    <role>Theseus</role>
                </castItem>
            </castList>-->

            <milestone unit="episode"/>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1">
                <stage>Before the palace of Heracles at <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName>. Nearby stands the altar of Zeus, on the steps of which
                    are now seated Amphitryon, <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>
                    and her sons by Heracles. They are seeking refuge at the altar.</stage>
                <sp n="Amphitryon">
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>What mortal has not heard of the one who shared a wife with Zeus, Amphitryon
                        of Argos, whom once Alcaeus, son of Perseus, begot, Amphitryon the father of
                        Heracles? Who lived here in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName>, where from the sowing <milestone ed="p" n="5"
                            unit="line"/> of the dragon's teeth grew up a crop of earth-born giants;
                        and of these Ares saved a scanty band, and their children's children people
                        the city of Cadmus. Hence sprung Creon, son of Menoeceus, king of this land;
                            <milestone ed="p" n="10" unit="line"/> and Creon became the father of
                        this lady Megara, whom once all Cadmus' race escorted with the glad music of
                        lutes at her wedding, when the famous Heracles led her to my halls.</p>
                    <p>Now he, my son, left <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> where
                        I was settled, left his wife Megara and her kin, <milestone ed="p" n="15"
                            unit="line"/> eager to make his home in <placeName key="tgn,7002739"
                            >Argolis</placeName>, in that walled town which the Cyclopes built, from
                        which I am exiled for the slaying of Electryon; so he, wishing to lighten my
                        affliction and to find a home in his own land, offered Eurystheus a mighty
                        price for my recall: <milestone ed="p" n="20" unit="line"/> to free the
                        world of savage monsters, whether it was that Hera goaded him to submit to
                        this, or that fate was leagued against him. Other toils he has accomplished,
                        and last of all has he passed through the mouth of Taenarus into the halls
                        of Hades to drag to the light <milestone ed="p" n="25" unit="line"/> that
                        hound with three bodies, and from there he has never returned.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="26">
                <sp>
                    <p>Now there is an ancient legend among the race of Cadmus that a certain Lycus
                        in days gone by was husband to Dirce, and he was king of this city with its
                        seven towers, before Amphion and Zethus, sons of Zeus, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="30" unit="line"/> lords of the milk-white steeds, became rulers in
                        the land. His son, called by the same name as his father, although no Theban
                        but a stranger from <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>, slew
                        Creon, and after that seized the government, having fallen on this city when
                        weakened by dissension. <milestone ed="p" n="35" unit="line"/> So this
                        family connection with Creon is likely to prove to us a serious evil; for
                        now that my son is in the bowels of the earth, this new monarch Lycus is
                        bent on extirpating the children of Heracles, <milestone ed="p" n="40"
                            unit="line"/> to quench one bloody feud with another, likewise his wife
                        and me, if useless age like mine is to rank among men, that the boys may
                        never grow up to exact a blood-penalty of their uncle's family. So I, left
                        here by my son, while he is gone into the pitchy darkness of the earth,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="45" unit="line"/> to tend and guard his children in
                        his house, am taking my place with their mother, that the race of Heracles
                        may not perish, here at the altar of Zeus the Savior, which my own gallant
                        child set up <milestone ed="p" n="50" unit="line"/> to commemorate his
                        glorious victory over the Minyae. And here we are careful to keep our
                        station, though in need of everything, of food, drink and clothes, huddled
                        together on the hard bare ground; for we are barred out from our house and
                        sit here for want of any other safety. <milestone ed="p" n="55" unit="line"
                        /> As for friends, some I see are unreliable; while others, who are staunch,
                        have no power to help us further. This is what misfortune means to man; may
                        it never fall to the lot of any who bears the least goodwill to me, to apply
                        this never-failing test of friendship! </p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="60">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="60" unit="line"/> Old warrior, who once razed the
                        citadel of the Taphians leading on the troops of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> to glory, how uncertain are the
                        gods' dealings with man! For I, as far as concerned my father, was never an
                        outcast of fortune, for he was once accounted a man of might by reason of
                        his wealth, <milestone ed="p" n="65" unit="line"/> possessed as he was of
                        royal power, for which long spears are launched at the lives of the
                        fortunate through love of it; children too he had; and he gave me to your
                        son, matching me in glorious marriage with Heracles. And now all that is
                        dead and gone from us; <milestone ed="p" n="70" unit="line"/> and I and you,
                        old friend, are doomed to die, and these children of Heracles, whom I am
                        guarding beneath my wing as a bird keeps her tender chicks under her. And
                        they one after another keep asking me: &#x201C;Mother, tell us, where is our
                        father gone from the land? <milestone ed="p" n="75" unit="line"/> what is he
                        doing? when will he return?&#x201D; Thus they inquire for their father, in
                        childish perplexity; while I put them off with excuses, inventing stories;
                        but still I wonder if it is he whenever a door creaks on its hinges, and up
                        they all start, thinking to embrace their father's knees. <milestone ed="p"
                            n="80" unit="line"/> What hope or way of salvation are you now devising,
                        old friend? for I look to you. We can never steal beyond the boundaries of
                        the land unseen, for there is too strict a watch set on us at every outlet,
                        nor have we any longer hopes of safety <milestone ed="p" n="85" unit="line"
                        /> in our friends. Whatever your scheme is, declare it, lest our death be
                        made ready.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>It is by no means easy, my daughter, to give one's earnest advice on such
                        matters easily, without weary thought; but let us prolong the time, since we
                        are powerless to escape.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="90" unit="line"/> Do you need a further taste of grief,
                        or do you cling so fast to life?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Yes, I love this life, and cling to its hopes.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>So do I; but you should not expect the unexpected, old friend.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>In these delays the only cure for our evils is left.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>It is the biting pain of that interval I feel so.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="95" unit="line"/> Daughter, there may yet be a happy
                        escape from present troubles for me and you; my son, your husband, may yet
                        arrive. So calm yourself, and wipe those tears from your children's eyes,
                        and soothe them with soft words, <milestone ed="p" n="100" unit="line"/>
                        inventing a tale to delude then, piteous though such fraud be. Yes, for even
                        men's misfortunes often flag, and the stormy wind does not always blow so
                        strong, nor are the prosperous ever so; for all things change, making way
                        for each other. <milestone ed="p" n="105" unit="line"/> The bravest man is
                        he who relies ever on his hopes, but despair is the mark of a coward.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="107">

                <milestone unit="choral"/>
                <milestone unit="strophe"/>
                <stage>The Chorus of Old Men of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>
                    enters.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>To the sheltering roof, to the old man's couch, leaning on my staff have I
                        set forth, <milestone ed="p" n="110" unit="line"/> chanting a plaintive
                        dirge like some bird grown grey, I that am only a voice and a fancy bred of
                        the visions of sleep by night, palsied with age, yet meaning kindly. All
                        hail! you orphaned children! <milestone ed="p" n="115" unit="line"/> all
                        hail, old friend! you too, unhappy mother, wailing for your husband in the
                        halls of Hades!</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="119">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Do not faint too soon upon your way, <milestone ed="p" n="120" unit="line"/>
                        or let your limbs grow weary, as a colt beneath the yoke grows weary as he
                        mounts some stony hill, dragging the weight of a wheeled chariot. Take hold
                        of hand or robe, who ever feels his footsteps falter. <milestone ed="p"
                            n="125" unit="line"/> Old friend, escort another like yourself, who once
                        amid his toiling peers in the days of our youth would take his place beside
                        you, no blot upon his country's glorious record.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="130">
                <milestone unit="epode"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="130" unit="line"/> See, how like their father's sternly
                        flash these children's eyes! Misfortune has not failed his children, nor yet
                        has his comeliness been denied them. <milestone ed="p" n="135" unit="line"/>
                        O <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>! if you lose these, of
                        what allies will you rob yourself!</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="138">

                <milestone unit="episode"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p>But I see Lycus, the ruler of this land, drawing near the house.</p>
                </sp>
                <stage>Lycus and his attendants enter.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="140" unit="line"/> One question, if I may, to this
                        father of Heracles and his wife; and certainly as your lord and master I
                        have a right to put what questions I choose. How long do you seek to prolong
                        your lives? What hope, what aid do you see to save you from death?
                            <milestone ed="p" n="145" unit="line"/> Do you trust that these
                        children's father, who lies dead in the halls of Hades, will return? How
                        unworthily you show your sorrow at having to die, you after your idle
                        boasts, scattered broadcast through <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                            >Hellas</placeName>, that Zeus was partner in your marriage-bed and was
                        your partner in children; <milestone ed="p" n="150" unit="line"/> and you,
                        after calling yourself the wife of so peerless a lord.</p>
                    <p>After all, what was the fine exploit your husband achieved, if he did kill a
                        hydra in a marsh or that monster of <placeName key="perseus,Nemea"
                            >Nemea</placeName>? which he caught in a snare, for all he says he
                        strangled it to death in his arms. <milestone ed="p" n="155" unit="line"/>
                        Are these your weapons for the hard struggle? Is it for this then that
                        Heracles' children should be spared? A man who has won a reputation for
                        valor in his contests with beasts, in all else a weakling; <milestone ed="p"
                            n="160" unit="line"/> who never buckled shield to arm nor faced the
                        spear, but with a bow, that coward's weapon, was ever ready to run away.
                        Archery is no test of manly bravery; no! he is a man who keeps his post in
                        the ranks and steadily faces the swift wound the spear may plough.
                            <milestone ed="p" n="165" unit="line"/> My policy, again, old man, shows
                        no reckless cruelty, but caution; for I am well aware I slew Creon, the
                        father of this woman, and am in possession of his throne. So I have no wish
                        that these children should grow up and be left to take vengeance on me in
                        requital for what I have done.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="170">
                <sp n="Amphitryon">
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="170" unit="line"/> Let Zeus defend his his own share in
                        his son; but as for me, Heracles, it is my concern on your behalf to prove
                        by what I say this tyrant's ignorance; for I cannot allow you to be ill
                        spoken of. First then for that which should never have been said&#x2014;for
                        to speak <milestone ed="p" n="175" unit="line"/> of you, Heracles, as a
                        coward is, I think, outside the pale of speech&#x2014;of that must I clear
                        you with heaven to witness. I appeal then to the thunder of Zeus, and the
                        chariot in which he rode, when he pierced the Giants, earth's brood, to the
                        heart with his winged shafts, <milestone ed="p" n="180" unit="line"/> and
                        with gods uplifted the glorious triumph song; or go to Pholoe and ask the
                        insolent tribe of four-legged Centaurs, you craven king, ask them who they
                        would judge the bravest of men; will they not say my son, who according to
                        you is but a pretender? <milestone ed="p" n="185" unit="line"/> Were you to
                        ask Euboean Dirphys, your native place, it would not sing your praise, for
                        you have never done a single gallant deed to which your country can witness.
                        Next you disparage that clever invention, an archer's weapon; <milestone
                            ed="p" n="190" unit="line"/> come, listen to me and learn wisdom. A man
                        who fights in line is a slave to his weapons, and if his fellow-comrades
                        want for courage he is slain himself through the cowardice of his neighbors,
                        or, if he breaks his spear, he cannot defend his body from death, having
                        only one means of defence; <milestone ed="p" n="195" unit="line"/> whereas
                        all who are armed with the trusty bow, though they have but one weapon, yet
                        is it the best; for a man, after discharging countless arrows, still has
                        others with which to defend himself from death, and standing at a distance
                        keeps off the enemy, wounding them for all their watchfulness with invisible
                        shafts, <milestone ed="p" n="200" unit="line"/> and never exposing himself
                        to the foe, but keeping under cover; and this is by far the wisest course in
                        battle, to harm the enemy and keep safe oneself, independent of chance.
                        These arguments are completely opposite to yours <milestone ed="p" n="205"
                            unit="line"/> with regard to the point at issue. Next, why are you
                        desirous of slaying these children? What have they done to you? One piece of
                        wisdom I credit you with, your coward terror of a brave man's descendants.
                        Still it is hard on us, <milestone ed="p" n="210" unit="line"/> if for your
                        cowardice we must die; a fate that ought to have overtaken you at our braver
                        hands, if Zeus had been fairly disposed towards us. But, if you are so
                        anxious to make yourself supreme in the land, let us go into exile;
                            <milestone ed="p" n="215" unit="line"/> abstain from all violence, else
                        you will suffer by it whenever the god causes fortune's breeze to veer
                        round. </p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="217">
                <sp>
                    <p>Ah! you land of Cadmus&#x2014;for to you too will I turn, distributing my
                        words of reproach&#x2014;is this your defense of Heracles and his children?
                            <milestone ed="p" n="220" unit="line"/> the man who faced alone all the
                        Minyans in battle and allowed <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> to see the light with free eyes. I cannot praise
                            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, nor will I ever keep
                        silence, finding her so craven as regards my son; she should have come with
                        fire and sword and warrior's arms <milestone ed="p" n="225" unit="line"/> to
                        help these tender chicks, to requite him for all his labors in purging land
                        and sea. Such help, my children, neither <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                            >Hellas</placeName> nor the city of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> affords you; to me a feeble friend you look, and I
                        am empty sound and nothing more. <milestone ed="p" n="230" unit="line"/> For
                        the vigor which once I had, has gone from me; my limbs are palsied with age,
                        and my strength is decayed. If I were young and still powerful in body, I
                        would have seized my spear and dabbled those flaxen locks of his with blood,
                        so that the coward would now <milestone ed="p" n="235" unit="line"/> be
                        flying from my spear beyond the bounds of Atlas.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p>Have not the brave among mankind a fair occasion for speech, although slow to
                        begin?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p>Say what you will of me in your exalted phrase, but I by deeds will make you
                        rue those words. <milestone ed="p" n="240" unit="line"/>
                        <stage>Calling to his servants</stage> Go, some to Helicon, others to the
                        glens of <placeName key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>, and bid woodmen
                        to cut me logs of oak, and when they are brought to the town, pile up a
                        stack of wood all round the altar on either side, and set fire to it and
                        burn them <milestone ed="p" n="245" unit="line"/> all alive, that they may
                        learn that the dead no longer rules this land, but that for the present I am
                        king. <stage>angrily to the Chorus</stage> As for you, old men, since you
                        thwart my views, not for the children of Heracles alone shall you lament,
                        but likewise for your own <milestone ed="p" n="250" unit="line"/>
                        misfortunes, and you shall never forget you are slaves and I your
                        prince.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="252">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>&#x2014;You sons of Earth, whom Ares once sowed, when from the dragon's
                        ravening jaw he had torn the teeth, up with your staves, on which you lean
                        your hands, <milestone ed="p" n="255" unit="line"/> and dash out this
                        villain's brains! a fellow who, without even being a Theban, but a
                        foreigner, lords it shamefully over the younger men; but my master shall you
                        never be to your joy.</p>
                    <p>&#x2014;Nor shall you reap the harvest of all my toil; <milestone ed="p"
                            n="260" unit="line"/> Go back to where you came from, in your insolence.
                        For never while I live, shall you slay these sons of Heracles; not so deep
                        beneath the earth has their father disappeared from his children's ken.</p>
                    <p>&#x2014;You are in possession of this land which you have ruined, <milestone
                            ed="p" n="265" unit="line"/> while he, its benefactor, has missed his
                        just reward.</p>
                    <p>&#x2014;And yet do I take too much upon myself because I help those I love
                        after their death, when most they need a friend?</p>
                    <p>&#x2014;Ah! right hand, how you desire to wield the spear, but your weakness
                        is a death-blow to your desire. <milestone ed="p" n="270" unit="line"/> For
                        then I would have stopped you calling me slave, and I would have governed
                            <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> with credit. In which
                        you now rejoice; for a city sick with dissension and evil counsels does not
                        think aright; otherwise it would never have accepted you as its master.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="275">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="275" unit="line"/> Old men, I thank you; it is right
                        that friends should feel virtuous indignation on behalf of those they love;
                        but do not on our account vent your anger on the tyrant to your own undoing.
                        Hear my advice, Amphitryon, if there appears to you to be anything in what I
                        say. <milestone ed="p" n="280" unit="line"/> I love my children; strange if
                        I did not love those whom I bore, whom I labored for! Death I count a
                        dreadful fate; but the man who strives against necessity I esteem a fool.
                        Since we must die, let us do so <milestone ed="p" n="285" unit="line"/>
                        without being burnt alive, a source of mockery to our enemies, which to my
                        mind is an evil worse than death; for much good do we owe our family. You
                        have always had a warrior's fair fame, so it is not to be endured that you
                        should die a coward's death; <milestone ed="p" n="290" unit="line"/> and my
                        husband's reputation needs no one to witness that he would never consent to
                        save these children's lives by letting them incur the stain of cowardice;
                        for the noble are afflicted by disgrace on account of their children, nor
                        must I shrink from following my lord's example. <milestone ed="p" n="295"
                            unit="line"/> As to your hopes consider how I weigh them. Do you think
                        your son will return from beneath the earth? And who ever has come back from
                        the dead out of the halls of Hades? But would you soften this man by
                        entreaty? Oh no! better to fly from one's enemy when he is so brutish,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="300" unit="line"/> but yield to men of breeding and
                        wisdom; for you would more easily conclude a friendly truce by accepting
                        regard. True, a thought has already occurred to me that we might by entreaty
                        obtain a sentence of exile for the children; yet this too is misery, to
                        compass their deliverance with dire penury as the result; <milestone ed="p"
                            n="305" unit="line"/> for it is a saying that hosts look sweetly on
                        banished friends for a day and no more. Endure to die with us, for that
                        awaits you after all. By your brave soul I challenge you, old friend; for
                        whoever struggles hard to escape destiny sent by the gods <milestone ed="p"
                            n="310" unit="line"/> shows zeal no doubt, but it is zeal with a taint
                        of folly; for what must be, no one will ever avail to alter.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p>If a man had insulted you, while yet my arms were strong, there would have
                        been an easy way to stop him; but now am I am nothing ; and so you
                        henceforth, Amphitryon, <milestone ed="p" n="315" unit="line"/> must scheme
                        how to avert misfortune.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="316">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>It is not cowardice or any longing for life that hinders my dying, but my
                        wish to save my son's children, though no doubt I am longing for the
                        impossible. See! here is my neck ready for the sword <milestone ed="p"
                            n="320" unit="line"/> to pierce, to hack, to hurl from the rock; only
                        one favor I crave for both of us, king; slay me and this hapless mother
                        before you slay the children, that we may not see the hideous sight, as they
                        gasp out their lives, calling on their mother <milestone ed="p" n="325"
                            unit="line"/> and their father's father; for the rest work your will if
                        so you are inclined; for we have no defense against death.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>I too implore you add a second favor, that by your single act you may put us
                        both under a double obligation; allow me to deck my children in the robes of
                        death, <milestone ed="p" n="330" unit="line"/> first opening the palace
                        gates, for now we are shut out, so that this at least they may obtain from
                        their father's halls.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p>I grant it, and bid my servants undo the bolts. Go in and deck yourselves;
                        robes do not grudge. But as soon as you have clothed yourselves, <milestone
                            ed="p" n="335" unit="line"/> I will return to you to consign you to the
                        nether world.<stage>Lycus and his retinue withdraw.</stage></p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Children, follow the footsteps of your hapless mother to your father's house,
                        where others possess his substance, though his name is still
                            ours.<stage>Megara and her children enter the palace.</stage></p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>O Zeus, in vain, it seems, did I get you to share my bride with me;
                            <milestone ed="p" n="340" unit="line"/> in vain used we to call you
                        partner in my son. After all you are less our friend than you pretended.
                        Great god as you are, I, a mortal, surpass you in true worth. For I did not
                        betray the children of Heracles; but you by stealth found your way to my
                        bed, <milestone ed="p" n="345" unit="line"/> taking another's wife without
                        leave given, while to save your own friends you have no skill. Either you
                        are a god of little sense, or else naturally unjust.<stage>Amphitryon
                            follows Megara into the palace.</stage></p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="348">

                <milestone unit="choral"/>
                <milestone unit="strophe" n="1"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Phoebus is singing a dirge, after his happier strains, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="350" unit="line"/> for Linus dead in his beauty, striking his lyre
                        with key of gold; but I wish to sing a song of praise, a crown to all his
                        toil, on the one who has gone to the gloom beneath the nether world,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="355" unit="line"/> whether I am to call him son of
                        Zeus or of Amphitryon. For the virtue of noble toils is a glory to the
                        dead.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="359">
                <milestone unit="ephymnion" n="1"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>First he cleared the grove of Zeus <milestone ed="p" n="360" unit="line"/> of
                        a lion, and put its skin upon his back, hiding his yellow hair in its
                        fearful tawny gaping jaws.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="364">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe" n="1"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>And then one day with murderous bow he wounded <milestone ed="p" n="365"
                            unit="line"/> the race of wild Centaurs, that range the hills, slaying
                        them with winged shafts. Peneus, the river of fair eddies, knows him well,
                        and those far fields unharvested, <milestone ed="p" n="370" unit="line"/>
                        and the steadings on <placeName key="tgn,4008379">Pelion</placeName> and
                        neighboring caves of Homole, from where the Centaurs rode forth to conquer
                            <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>, arming themselves
                        with pines.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="375">
                <milestone unit="ephymnion" n="1"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="375" unit="line"/> And he slew that dappled deer with
                        horns of gold, that preyed upon the country-folk, glorifying Artemis,
                        huntress queen of Oenoe.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="380">
                <milestone unit="strophe" n="2"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="380" unit="line"/> Next he mounted on a chariot and
                        tamed with the bit the horses of Diomedes, that greedily champed their
                        bloody food at gory mangers with unbridled jaws, devouring with hideous joy
                        the flesh of men; <milestone ed="p" n="385" unit="line"/> then crossing the
                        heights of <placeName key="tgn,7002660">Hebrus</placeName> that flow with
                        silver, he still toiled on for the tyrant of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="389">
                <milestone unit="ephymnion" n="2"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>And at the strand of the Pelian gulf <milestone ed="p" n="390" unit="line"/>
                        by the streams of Anaurus, he slew with his arrows Cycnus, murderer of his
                        guests, the savage wretch who dwelt in Amphanae.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="394">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe" n="2"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>And he came to those minstrel maids, <milestone ed="p" n="395" unit="line"/>
                        to their orchard in the west, to pluck from golden leaves the apple-bearing
                        fruit, when he had slain the tawny dragon, whose terrible coils were twined
                        all round to guard it; <milestone ed="p" n="400" unit="line"/> and he made
                        his way into ocean's lairs, bringing calm to men that use the oar.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="403">
                <milestone unit="ephymnion" n="2"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>And he stretched out his hands to uphold the firmament, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="405" unit="line"/> seeking the home of Atlas, and on his manly
                        shoulders took the starry mansions of the gods.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="408">
                <milestone unit="strophe" n="3"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Then he went through the waves of heaving Euxine against the mounted host of
                        Amazons dwelling round Maeotis, <milestone ed="p" n="410" unit="line"/> the
                        lake that is fed by many a stream, having gathered to his standard all his
                        friends from <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, to fetch the
                        gold-embroidered raiment of the warrior queen, <milestone ed="p" n="415"
                            unit="line"/> a deadly quest for a girdle. <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                            >Hellas</placeName> won those glorious spoils of the barbarian maid, and
                        they are safe in <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="419">
                <milestone unit="ephymnion" n="3"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>He burned to ashes <placeName key="perseus,Lerna">Lerna</placeName>'s
                        murderous hound, <milestone ed="p" n="420" unit="line"/> the many-headed
                        hydra, and smeared its venom on his darts, with which he slew the shepherd
                        of Erytheia, a monster with three bodies.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="425">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe" n="3"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="425" unit="line"/> And many another glorious achievement
                        he brought to a happy issue; to Hades' house of tears has he now sailed, the
                        goal of his labors, where he is ending his career of toil, nor does he come
                        back again. <milestone ed="p" n="430" unit="line"/> Now your house is left
                        without a friend, and Charon's boat awaits your children to bear them on
                        that journey out of life, without return, contrary to the gods' law and
                        man's justice; and it is to your prowess <milestone ed="p" n="435"
                            unit="line"/> that your house is looking although you are not here.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="436">
                <milestone unit="ephymnion" n="3"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Had I been strong and lusty, able to brandish the spear in battle's onset,
                        and my Theban companions too, I would have stood by your children <milestone
                            ed="p" n="440" unit="line"/> to champion them; but now my happy youth is
                        gone and I am left.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="442">

                <milestone unit="episode"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p>But look! I see the children of Heracles who was once so great, wearing the
                        clothes of the dead, <milestone ed="p" n="445" unit="line"/> and his loving
                        wife dragging her babes along at her side, and Heracles' aged father. Ah!
                        woe is me! no longer can I stem the flood of tears <milestone ed="p" n="450"
                            unit="line"/> that spring to my old eyes.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="451">
                <stage>Megara, Amphitryon, and the children enter from the palace.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Come now, who is to sacrifice or butcher these poor children? &#x005B;or rob me
                        of my wretched life?&#x005D; These victims are ready to be led to Hades'
                        halls. O my children! an ill-matched company are we hurried off to die,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="455" unit="line"/> old men and young ones and
                        mothers, all together. Alas! for my sad fate and my children's, whom these
                        eyes now for the last time behold. So I gave you birth and reared you only
                        for our foes to mock, to jeer at, and slay. <milestone ed="p" n="460"
                            unit="line"/> Ah me! how bitterly my hopes have disappointed me in the
                        expectation I once formed from the words of your father. <stage>Addressing
                            each of her sons in turn</stage> To you your dead father was for giving
                            <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>; and you were to dwell
                        in the halls of Eurystheus, lording it over the fair fruitful land of
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName>; <milestone ed="p"
                            n="465" unit="line"/> and over your head would he throw that lion's skin
                        with which he himself was armed. And you were to be king of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, famed for its chariots,
                        receiving as your heritage my broad lands, for so you coaxed your dear
                        father; <milestone ed="p" n="470" unit="line"/> and to your hand he used to
                        resign the carved club, his sure defence, pretending to give it to you. And
                        to you he promised to give <placeName key="perseus,Oechalia"
                            >Oechalia</placeName>, which once his archery had wasted. Thus with
                        three principalities <milestone ed="p" n="475" unit="line"/> would your
                        father exalt you, his three sons, proud of your manliness; while I was
                        choosing the best brides for you, scheming to link you by marriage to
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, and <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, that you might live a happy
                        life with a fast sheet-anchor to hold by. <milestone ed="p" n="480"
                            unit="line"/> And now that is all vanished; fortune's breeze has veered
                        and given to you for brides the maidens of death in their stead, and my
                        tears will be the marriage bath; woe is me for my foolish thoughts! and your
                        grandfather here is celebrating your marriage-feast, the cares of a father,
                        accepting Hades as the father of your brides. <milestone ed="p" n="485"
                            unit="line"/> Ah me! which of you shall I first press to my bosom, which
                        last? on which bestow my kiss, or clasp close to me? Oh! would that like the
                        bee with russet wing, I could collect from every source my sighs in one,
                        and, blending them together, shed them in one copious flood! <milestone
                            ed="p" n="490" unit="line"/> O my dearest Heracles, to you I call, if
                        perhaps mortal voice can make itself heard in Hades' halls; your father and
                        children are dying, and I am doomed, I who once because of you was counted
                        blessed as men count bliss. Come to our rescue; appear, I pray, if only as a
                        phantom, <milestone ed="p" n="495" unit="line"/> since your arrival, even as
                        a dream, would be enough, for they are cowards who are slaying your
                        children.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="497">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Lady, prepare the funeral rites; but I, O Zeus, stretching out my hand to
                        heaven, call on you to help these children, <milestone ed="p" n="500"
                            unit="line"/> if such is your intention; for soon any aid of yours will
                        be unavailing; and yet you have been often invoked; my toil is in vain;
                        death seems inevitable. You aged friends, the joys of life are few; so take
                        heed that you pass through it as gladly as you may, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="505" unit="line"/> without a thought of sorrow from morning until
                        night; for time takes little heed of preserving our hopes; and, when he has
                        busied himself on his own business, away he flies. Look at me, a man who had
                        made a mark among his fellows by deeds of note; yet fortune in a single day
                            <milestone ed="p" n="510" unit="line"/> has robbed me of it as of a
                        feather that floats away toward the sky. I know not any whose plenteous
                        wealth and high reputation is fixed and sure; fare you well, for now you
                        have seen the last of your old friend, my comrades.</p>
                </sp>
                <stage>Megara catches sight of Heracles approaching.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Ah! Old friend, is it my own, my dearest I see? or what am I to say?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="515" unit="line"/> I do not know, my daughter; I too am
                        struck dumb.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Is this he who they told us was beneath the earth?It is, unless some
                        day-dream mocks our sight. What am I saying? What visions do these anxious
                        eyes behold? Old man, this is no one other than your own son. <milestone
                            ed="p" n="520" unit="line"/> Come here, my children, cling to your
                        father's robe, hurry, never loose your hold, for here is one to help you,
                        not at all behind our savior Zeus.</p>
                </sp>
                <stage>Heracles enters.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>All hail! my house and gates of my home, how glad I am to emerge to the light
                        and see you. <milestone ed="p" n="525" unit="line"/> Ah! what is this? I see
                        my children before the house in the robes of death, with chaplets on their
                        heads and my wife amid a throng of men, and my father weeping&#x2014;what
                        misfortune? Let me draw near to them and inquire; <milestone ed="p" n="530"
                            unit="line"/> lady, what strange stroke of fate has fallen on the
                        house?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Dearest of all mankind to me!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>O ray of light appearing to your father!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Are you safe and is your coming just in time to help your dear ones?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>What do you mean? What is this confusion I find on my arrival, father?</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="534">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>We are being ruined; forgive me, old friend, <milestone ed="p" n="535"
                            unit="line"/> if I have anticipated that to which you had a right to
                        tell him; for women's nature is perhaps more prone to grief than men's and
                        they are my children that were being led to death, which was my own lot
                        too.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Apollo! what a prelude to your story!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>My brothers are dead, and my old father.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="540" unit="line"/> How so? what did he do? whose spear
                        did he meet?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Lycus, our new monarch, slew him.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Did he meet him in fair fight, or was the land sick and weak?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Yes, from faction; now he is master of the city of Cadmus with its seven
                        gates.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Why has panic fallen on you and my aged father?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="545" unit="line"/> He meant to kill your father, me, and
                        my children.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>What are you saying? What did he have to fear from my orphan babes?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>He was afraid they might some day avenge Creon's death.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>What is this dress they wear, suited to the dead?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>It is the garb of death we have already put on.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="550" unit="line"/> And were you being forced to die? O
                        woe is me!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Yes, deserted by every friend, and informed that you were dead.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>What put such desperate thoughts into your heads?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>That was what the heralds of Eurystheus kept proclaiming.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Why did you leave my hearth and home?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="555" unit="line"/> He forced us; your father was dragged
                        from his bed.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Had he no shame, to ill-use the old man so?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Shame indeed! that goddess and he dwell far enough apart.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Was I so poor in friends in my absence?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Who are the friends of a man in misfortune?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="560" unit="line"/> Do they make so light of my hard
                        warring with the Minyans?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Megara</speaker>
                    <p>Misfortune, to repeat it to you, has no friends.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="562">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Cast from your heads these chaplets of death, look up to the light, for
                        instead of the darkness below your eyes behold the welcome sun. <milestone
                            ed="p" n="565" unit="line"/> I, meanwhile, since here is work for my
                        hand, will first go raze this upstart tyrant's halls, and when I have
                        beheaded the villain, I will throw him to dogs to tear; and every Theban who
                        I find has played the traitor after my kindness, <milestone ed="p" n="570"
                            unit="line"/> will I destroy with this victorious club; the rest will I
                        tear apart with my feathered shafts and fill Ismenus full of bloody corpses,
                        and Dirce's clear stream shall run red with gore. For whom ought I to help
                        rather than wife <milestone ed="p" n="575" unit="line"/> and children and
                        aged father? Farewell my labors! for it was in vain I accomplished them
                        rather than helping these. And yet I ought to die in their defence, since
                        they for their father were doomed; or what shall we find so noble in having
                        fought a hydra and a lion <milestone ed="p" n="580" unit="line"/> at the
                        commands of Eurystheus, if I make no effort to save my own children from
                        death? No longer then, as before, shall I be called Heracles the victor.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p>It is only right that parents should help their children, their aged fathers,
                        and the partners of their marriage.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="585" unit="line"/> My son, it is like you to show your
                        love for your dear ones and your hate for your enemies; only curb excessive
                        hastiness.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>How, father, am I now showing more than fitting haste?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>The king has a host of allies, needy villains though pretending to be rich,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="590" unit="line"/> who sowed dissension and
                        overthrew the state with a view to plundering their neighbors; for the
                        wealth they had in their houses was all spent, dissipated by their sloth.
                        You were seen entering the city; and, that being so, beware that you do not
                        bring your enemies together and be slain unawares.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="595" unit="line"/> Little I care if the whole city saw
                        me; but chancing to see a bird perched in an ill-omened spot, from it I
                        learned that some trouble had befallen my house; so on purpose I made my
                        entry to the land by stealth.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="599">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Well done; now, on your arrival, go salute your household altar, <milestone
                            ed="p" n="600" unit="line"/> and let your father's halls behold your
                        face. For soon the king will be here in person to drag away your wife and
                        children and murder them, and to add me to the bloody list. But if you
                        remain on the spot all will go well, and you will profit by this security;
                        but do not rouse <milestone ed="p" n="605" unit="line"/> your city before
                        you have these matters well in train, my son.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>I will do so; your advice is good; I will enter my house. After my return at
                        length from the sunless den of Hades and the maiden queen of hell, I will
                        not neglect to greet first of all the gods beneath my roof.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="610" unit="line"/> Did you really go to the house of
                        Hades, my son?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Yes, and brought to the light that three-headed monster.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Did you conquer him in fight, or receive him from the goddess?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>In fight; for I had been lucky enough to witness the rites of the
                        initiated.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Is the monster really lodged in the house of Eurystheus?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="615" unit="line"/> The grove of Demeter and the city of
                            <placeName key="perseus,Hermione">Hermione</placeName> have him now.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Eurystheus does not know that you have returned to the upper world?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>He does not; I came here first to learn your news.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>How is it you were so long beneath the earth?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>I stayed awhile attempting to bring back Theseus from Hades, father.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="620" unit="line"/> Where is he? gone to his native
                        land?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>He set out for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, glad to
                        have escaped from the lower world. Come now, children, attend your father to
                        the house. My entering in is fairer in your eyes, I think, than my going
                        out. Oh, take heart, <milestone ed="p" n="625" unit="line"/> and no more let
                        the tears stream from your eyes; you too, my wife, collect your courage,
                        cease from fear; let go my robe; for I cannot fly away, nor have I any wish
                        to flee from those I love. Ah! they do not loose their hold, but cling to my
                        garments <milestone ed="p" n="630" unit="line"/> all the more; were you on
                        the razor's edge of danger? Well, I must lead them, taking them by the hand
                        to draw them after me, my little boats, like a ship when towing; for I too
                        do not reject the care of my children; here all mankind are equal; all love
                        their children, both those of high estate <milestone ed="p" n="635"
                            unit="line"/> and those who are nothing; it is wealth that makes
                        distinctions among them; some have, others want; but all the human race
                        loves its offspring.<stage>Heracles, Megara, Amphitryon and the children
                            enter the palace.</stage></p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="637">

                <milestone unit="choral"/>
                <milestone unit="strophe" n="1"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Dear to me is youth always, but old age is hanging over my head, a burden
                        heavier <milestone ed="p" n="640" unit="line"/> than <placeName
                            key="tgn,7003867">Aetna</placeName>'s crags, casting its pall of gloom
                        upon my eyes. Oh! never may the wealth of <placeName key="tgn,1000004"
                            >Asia</placeName>'s kings tempt me <milestone ed="p" n="645" unit="line"
                        /> to barter for houses stored with gold my happy youth, which is in wealth
                        and poverty alike most fair! But old age is gloomy and deadly; <milestone
                            ed="p" n="650" unit="line"/> I hate it; let it sink beneath the waves!
                        Would it had never found its way to the homes and towns of mortal men, but
                        were still drifting on for ever down the wind.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="655">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe" n="1"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="655" unit="line"/> Had the gods shown discernment and
                        wisdom, as mortals count these things, men would have won youth twice over,
                        a visible mark of worth <milestone ed="p" n="660" unit="line"/> among
                        whomever found, and after death these would have run a double course once
                        more to the sun-light, while the low born would have had a single portion of
                        life; <milestone ed="p" n="665" unit="line"/> and thus would it have been
                        possible to distinguish the good and the bad, just as sailors know the
                        number of the stars amid the clouds. But, as it is, the gods have set no
                        certain boundary <milestone ed="p" n="670" unit="line"/> between good and
                        bad, but time's onward roll brings increase only to man's wealth.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="673">
                <milestone unit="strophe" n="2"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Never will I cease to link in one the Graces and the Muses, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="675" unit="line"/> sweetest union. Never may I live among uneducated
                        boors, but ever may I find a place among the crowned! <milestone ed="p"
                            n="680" unit="line"/> Yes, still the aged singer lifts up his voice of
                        bygone memories: still is my song of the triumphs of Heracles, whether
                        Bromius the giver of wine is near, or the strains of the seven-stringed lyre
                        and the Libyan pipe are rising; <milestone ed="p" n="685" unit="line"/> not
                        yet will I cease to sing the Muses' praise, my patrons in the dance.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="687">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe" n="2"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>The maids of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> raise their
                        song of joy, circling round the temple gates in honor of Leto's fair son,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="690" unit="line"/> the graceful dancer; so I with
                        my old lips will cry aloud songs of joy at your palace-doors, like the swan,
                        aged singer; for there is a good <milestone ed="p" n="695" unit="line"/>
                        theme for minstrelsy; he is the son of Zeus; yet high above his noble birth
                        tower his deeds of prowess, for his toil secured this life of calm for man,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="700" unit="line"/> having destroyed all fearsome
                        beasts.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="701">

                <milestone unit="episode"/>
                <stage>Amphitryon comes out of the palace as Lycus and his retinue enter.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p>Amphitryon, it is high time you came forth from the palace; you have been too
                        long arraying yourselves in the robes and trappings of the dead. Come, bid
                        the wife and children of Heracles <milestone ed="p" n="705" unit="line"/>
                        show themselves outside the house, to die on the conditions you yourselves
                        offered.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Lord, you persecute me in my misery and heap insult upon me over and above
                        the loss of my son; you should have been more moderate in your zeal, though
                        you are my lord and master. <milestone ed="p" n="710" unit="line"/> But
                        since you impose death's necessity on me, I must acquiesce; what you wish
                        must be done.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p>Now, where is Megara? where are the children of Alcmena's son?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>She, I believe, so far as I can guess from outside&#x2014;</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p>What grounds do you have to base your fancy on?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="715" unit="line"/> Is sitting as a suppliant on the
                        altar's hallowed steps&#x2014;</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p>Imploring them quite uselessly to save her life.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>And calling on her dead husband, in vain.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p>He is nowhere near, and he certainly will never come.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>No, unless perhaps a god should raise him from the dead.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="720" unit="line"/> Go to her and bring her from the
                        palace.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>By doing so I should become an accomplice in her murder.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <p>Since you have this scruple, I, who have left fear behind, will myself bring
                        out the mother and her children. Follow me, servants, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="725" unit="line"/> that we may joyfully put an end to this delay of
                        our work.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Then go your way along the path of fate; for what remains, maybe another will
                        provide. Expect for your evil deeds to find some ill yourself. <stage>Lycus
                            and his servants enter the palace.</stage> Ah! my aged friends, he is
                        marching fairly to his doom; soon will he lie entangled in the snare
                            <milestone ed="p" n="730" unit="line"/> of the sword, thinking to slay
                        his neighbors, the villain! I will go, to see him fall dead; for the sight
                        of a foe being slain and paying the penalty of his misdeeds gives
                            pleasure.<stage>Amphitryon follows Lycus into the palace.</stage></p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="735">

                <milestone unit="choral"/>
                <milestone unit="strophe" n="1"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="735" unit="line"/> Evil has changed sides; he who was
                        once a mighty king is now turning his life backward into the road to Hades.
                        Hail to you! Justice and heavenly retribution.</p>
                    <stage>spoken</stage>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="740" unit="line"/> At last have you reached the goal
                        where your death will pay the penalty, for your insults against your
                        betters.</p>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p>Joy makes my tears burst forth. He has come back&#x2014;<milestone ed="p"
                            n="745" unit="line"/> which I never once thought in my heart would
                        happen&#x2014;the prince of the land.</p>
                    <stage>spoken</stage>
                    <p>Come, old friends, let us look within to see if someone has met the fate I
                        hope.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <stage>within</stage>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="750" unit="line"/> Ah me! ah me!</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="751">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe" n="1"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p>Ha! how sweet to hear that opening note of his within the house; death is not
                        far off him now. The prince cries out, wailing a prelude of death.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Lycus</speaker>
                    <stage>spoken within</stage>
                    <p>O kingdom of Cadmus, I am perishing by treachery!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <stage>spoken</stage>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="755" unit="line"/> You were yourself for making others
                        perish; endure your retribution; it is only the penalty of your own deeds
                        you are paying.</p>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p>Who was he, only a mortal, that aimed his silly saying at the blessed gods of
                        heaven with impious blasphemy, maintaining that they are weaklings after
                        all?</p>
                    <stage>spoken</stage>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="760" unit="line"/> Old friends, our godless foe is now
                        no more.</p>
                    <p>The house is still; let us turn to the dance.</p>
                    <p>Yes, for fortune smiles upon my friends as I desire.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="763">
                <milestone unit="strophe" n="2"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Dances, dances and banquets now prevail throughout the holy town of
                            <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. <milestone ed="p"
                            n="765" unit="line"/> For change from tears, change from sorrow give
                        birth to song. The new king is gone; our former monarch <milestone ed="p"
                            n="770" unit="line"/> rules, having made his way even from the harbor of
                            <placeName key="tgn,1120946">Acheron</placeName>. Hope beyond all
                        expectation is fulfilled.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="772">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe" n="2"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>The gods, the gods take care to heed the right and wrong. It is their gold
                        and their good luck <milestone ed="p" n="775" unit="line"/> that lead men's
                        hearts astray, bringing in their train unjust power. For no man ever had the
                        courage to reflect what reverses Time might bring; but, disregarding law to
                        gratify lawlessness, he shatters <milestone ed="p" n="780" unit="line"/> the
                        black chariot of prosperity.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="781">
                <milestone unit="strophe" n="3"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>O Ismenus, deck yourself with garlands! Break forth into dancing, you paved
                        streets of our seven-gated city! come Dirce, fount of waters fair;
                            <milestone ed="p" n="785" unit="line"/> and joined with her you nymphs
                        of Asopus, come from your father's waves to add your voices to our hymn, the
                        victor's prize that Heracles has won. <milestone ed="p" n="790" unit="line"
                        /> O Pythian rock with forests crowned, and haunts of the Muses on Helicon!
                        you will come to my city and her walls with cries of joy; where the
                        earth-born crop sprang to view, <milestone ed="p" n="795" unit="line"/> a
                        warrior-host with shields of brass, who are handing on their realm to
                        children's children, a divine light to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName>.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="798">
                <milestone unit="antistrophe" n="3"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>All hail the marriage! in which two bridegrooms shared; the one, a mortal;
                            <milestone ed="p" n="800" unit="line"/> the other, Zeus, who came to wed
                        the bride sprung from Perseus; for that marriage of yours, O Zeus, in days
                        gone by has been proved to me a true story beyond all expectation;
                            <milestone ed="p" n="805" unit="line"/> and time has shown the
                        brightness of Heracles' strength; for he emerged from caverns beneath the
                        earth after leaving Pluto's halls below. To me you are a worthier lord
                            <milestone ed="p" n="810" unit="line"/> than that base-born king, who
                        now lets it be plainly seen in this struggle between armed warriors, whether
                        justice still finds favor in heaven.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="815">

                <milestone unit="episode"/>
                <stage>The spectres of Madness and Iris appear from above. The Chorus sees
                    them.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="815" unit="line"/> &#x2014;Ha! see there, my old
                        comrades! is the same wild panic fallen on us all; what phantom is this I
                        see hovering over the house?</p>
                    <p>&#x2014;Fly, fly, bestir your tardy steps! begone! away!</p>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="820" unit="line"/> &#x2014;O savior prince, avert
                        calamity from me!</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="822">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Iris</speaker>
                    <p>Courage, old men! she, whom you see, is Madness, daughter of Night, and I am
                        Iris, the handmaid of the gods. We have not come to do your city any hurt,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="825" unit="line"/> but our warfare is against the
                        house of one man only, against him whom they call the son of Zeus and
                        Alcmena. For until he had finished all his grievous labors, Destiny was
                        preserving him, nor would father Zeus ever suffer me or Hera to harm him.
                            <milestone ed="p" n="830" unit="line"/> But now that he has accomplished
                        the labors of Eurystheus, Hera wishes to brand him with the guilt of
                        shedding kindred blood by slaying his own children, and I wish it also. Come
                        then, unwed maid, child of black Night, harden your heart relentlessly,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="835" unit="line"/> send forth frenzy upon this man,
                        confound his mind even to the slaying of his children, drive him, goad him
                        wildly on his mad career, shake out the sails of death, that when he has
                        conveyed over <placeName key="tgn,1120946">Acheron</placeName>'s ferry that
                        fair group of children by his own murderous hand, <milestone ed="p" n="840"
                            unit="line"/> he may learn to know how fiercely against him the wrath of
                        Hera burns and may also experience mine; otherwise, if he should escape
                        punishment, the gods will become as nothing, while man's power will
                        grow.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Madness</speaker>
                    <p>Of noble parents was I born, the daughter of Night, sprung from the blood of
                        Ouranos; <milestone ed="p" n="845" unit="line"/> and these prerogatives I
                        hold, not to use them in anger against friends, nor do I have any joy in
                        visiting the homes of men; and I wish to counsel Hera, before I see her err,
                        and you too, if you will hearken to my words. This man, against whose house
                        you are sending me, has made himself a name alike in heaven <milestone
                            ed="p" n="850" unit="line"/> and earth; for, after taming pathless wilds
                        and raging sea, he by his single might raised up again the honors of the
                        gods when sinking before man's impiety; . . . wherefore I counsel you, do
                        not wish him dire mishaps.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="855">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Iris</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="855" unit="line"/> Spare us your advice on Hera's and my
                        schemes.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Madness</speaker>
                    <p>I seek to turn your steps into the best path instead of into this one of
                        evil.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Iris</speaker>
                    <p>It was not to practice self-control that the wife of Zeus sent you here.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Madness</speaker>
                    <p>I call the sun-god to witness that here I am acting against my will; but if
                        indeed I must at once serve you and Hera <milestone ed="p" n="860"
                            unit="line"/> and follow you in full cry as hounds follow the huntsman,
                        then I will go; neither ocean with its fiercely groaning waves, nor the
                        earthquake, nor the thunderbolt with blast of agony shall be like the
                        headlong rush I will make into the breast of Heracles; through his roof will
                        I burst my way and swoop upon his house, <milestone ed="p" n="865"
                            unit="line"/> after first slaying his children; nor shall their murderer
                        know that he is killing the children he begot, till he is released from my
                        madness. Behold him! see how even now he is wildly tossing his head at the
                        outset, and rolling his eyes fiercely from side to side without a word; nor
                        can he control his panting breath, like a fearful bull in act to charge; he
                        bellows, <milestone ed="p" n="870" unit="line"/> calling on the goddesses of
                        nether hell. Soon will I rouse you to yet wilder dancing and pipe a note of
                        terror in your ear. Soar away, O Iris, to <placeName key="tgn,7011019"
                            >Olympus</placeName> on your honored course; while I unseen will steal
                        into the halls of Heracles.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="875">

                <milestone unit="choral"/>
                <milestone unit="lyric"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="875" unit="line"/> Alas alas! lament; the son of Zeus,
                        flower of your city, is being cut down. Woe to you, <placeName
                            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>! that will cast from you your
                        benefactor, and destroy him as he dances in the shrill frenzy of
                        Madness.</p>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="880" unit="line"/> She is mounted on her chariot, the
                        queen of sorrow and sighing, and is goading on her steeds, as if for
                        outrage, the Gorgon child of Night, with a hundred hissing serpent-heads,
                        Madness of the flashing eyes.</p>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="885" unit="line"/> Soon has the god changed his good
                        fortune; soon will his children breathe their last, slain by a father's
                        hand.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <stage>within</stage>
                    <p>Ah me! alas!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>O Zeus, unjust Vengeance, mad, relentless, will soon give your childless son
                            <milestone ed="p" n="890" unit="line"/> up to misery.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <stage>within</stage>
                    <p>Alas, O house!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>The dance begins without the cymbals' crash, with no glad waving of the
                        wine-god's staff&#x2014;</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <stage>within</stage>
                    <p>Woe to these halls!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Toward bloodshed, <milestone ed="p" n="895" unit="line"/> and not to pour
                        libations of Dionysus' grape.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <stage>within</stage>
                    <p>O children, make haste to fly!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>That is the chant of death, of death, to the music of pipes.</p>
                    <p>Ah, yes! he is hunting the children down. Never will Madness lead her revel
                        rout in vain.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <stage>within</stage>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="900" unit="line"/> Ah misery!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Ah me! how I lament that aged father, that mother too that bore his children
                        in vain.</p>
                    <p>Look! look! <milestone ed="p" n="905" unit="line"/> A tempest rocks the
                        house; the roof is falling with it.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <stage>within</stage>
                    <p>Oh, oh! what are you doing, Pallas, child of Zeus, to the house? You are
                        sending hell's confusion against the halls, as once you did on
                        Enceladus.</p>
                </sp>

                <milestone unit="episode"/>
                <stage>A messenger enters from the palace.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                    <p>O white-haired old men!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p>Why this loud <milestone ed="p" n="910" unit="line"/> address to me?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                    <p>It is dreadful within!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p>No need for me to call another prophet for that.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                    <p>The children are dead.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p>Alas!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                    <p>Ah weep! for here is cause for weeping.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p>A cruel murder, <milestone ed="p" n="915" unit="line"/> cruel parents'
                        hands!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                    <p>No words can utter more than we have suffered.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <stage>sung</stage>
                    <p>How came the ruin you reveal, the ruin that must be lamented, from a father
                        to his children? Tell me how these heaven-sent woes <milestone ed="p"
                            n="920" unit="line"/> came rushing on the house; say how the children
                        met their sad mischance.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="922">
                <sp n="Messenger">
                    <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                    <p>Victims to purify the house were stationed before the altar of Zeus, for
                        Heracles had slain and cast from his halls the king of the land. <milestone
                            ed="p" n="925" unit="line"/> There stood his group of lovely children,
                        with his father and Megara; and already the basket was being passed round
                        the altar, and we were keeping holy silence. But just as Alcmena's son was
                        bringing the torch in his right hand to dip it in the holy water, <milestone
                            ed="p" n="930" unit="line"/> he stopped without a word. And as their
                        father lingered, his children looked at him; he was no longer himself; his
                        eyes were rolling; he was distraught; his eyeballs were bloodshot, and foam
                        was oozing down his bearded cheek. <milestone ed="p" n="935" unit="line"/>
                        He spoke with a madman's laugh: &#x201C;Father, why should I offer the
                        purifying flame before I have slain Eurystheus, and have the toil twice
                        over? It is the work of my unaided arm to settle these things well; as soon
                        as I have brought the head of Eurystheus here, <milestone ed="p" n="940"
                            unit="line"/> I will cleanse my hands for those already slain. Spill the
                        water, cast the baskets from your hands. Ho! give me now my bow and club! To
                            <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName> will I go; I must
                        take crow-bars and pick-axes, for I will shatter again <milestone ed="p"
                            n="945" unit="line"/> with iron levers those city-walls which the
                        Cyclopes squared with red plumb-line and mason's tools.&#x201D; Then he set
                        out, and though he had no chariot there, he thought he had, and was for
                        mounting to its seat, and using a goad as though his fingers really held
                        one.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="950">
                <sp>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="950" unit="line"/> A twofold feeling filled his
                        servants' breasts, amusement and fear at once; and one looking to his
                        neighbor said: &#x201C;Is our master making sport for us, or is he
                        mad?&#x201D; But he was pacing to and fro in his house; and, rushing into the
                        men's chamber, he said he had reached the city of Nisus; <milestone ed="p"
                            n="955" unit="line"/> and going into the house, he threw himself upon
                        the floor, as he was, and made ready to feast. But after waiting a brief
                        space he began saying he was on his way to the plains amid the valleys of
                        the Isthmus; and then stripping himself of his mantle, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="960" unit="line"/> he fell to competing with no one, and he
                        proclaimed himself victor with his own voice, calling on no one to listen.
                        Next, fancy carrying him to Mycenae, he was uttering fearful threats against
                        Eurystheus. Meantime his father caught him by his stalwart arm, and thus
                        addressed him: <milestone ed="p" n="965" unit="line"/> &#x201C;My son, what
                        do you mean by this? What strange doings are these? Can it be that the blood
                        of your late victims has driven you frantic?&#x201D; But he, supposing it was
                        the father of Eurystheus striving in abject supplication to touch his hand:
                        thrust him aside, and then against his own children aimed his bow <milestone
                            ed="p" n="970" unit="line"/> and made ready his quiver, thinking to slay
                        the sons of Eurystheus. And they in wild fright darted here and there, one
                        to his hapless mother's skirts, another to the shadow of a pillar, while a
                        third cowered beneath the altar like a bird. <milestone ed="p" n="975"
                            unit="line"/> Then cried their mother: &#x201C;O you who begot them, what
                        are you doing? do you mean to slay your children?&#x201D; Likewise his aged
                        father and all the gathered servants cried aloud.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="977">
                <sp>
                    <p>But he, hunting the child round and round the column, in dreadful circles,
                        and coming face to face with him shot him to the heart; and he fell upon his
                        back, <milestone ed="p" n="980" unit="line"/> sprinkling the stone pillars
                        with blood as he gasped out his life. Then Heracles shouted in triumph and
                        boasted loud: &#x201C;Here lies one of Eurystheus' brood dead at my feet,
                        atoning for his father's hatred.&#x201D; Then he aimed his bow against a
                        second, who had crouched <milestone ed="p" n="985" unit="line"/> at the
                        altar's foot thinking to escape unseen. But before he fired, the poor child
                        threw himself at his father's knees, and, flinging his hand to reach his
                        beard or neck, cried: &#x201C;Oh! hear me, dearest father, do not kill me! I
                        am your child, your own; it is no son of Eurystheus you will
                        slay.&#x201D;</p>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="990" unit="line"/> But that other, with savage
                        Gorgon-scowl, as the child now stood in range of his baleful archery, smote
                        him on the head, as a smith strikes his molten iron, bringing down his club
                        upon the fair-haired boy, and crushed the bones. The second caught,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="995" unit="line"/> away he goes to add a third
                        victim to the other two. But before he could, the poor mother caught up her
                        child and carried him within the house and shut the doors. But he, as though
                        he really were at the Cyclopean walls, prized open the doors with levers,
                        and, hurling down their posts, <milestone ed="p" n="1000" unit="line"/> with
                        one shaft laid low his wife and child. Then in wild gallop he starts to slay
                        his aged father; but there came a phantom, as it seemed to us on-lookers, of
                        Pallas, with plumed helm, brandishing a spear; and she hurled a rock against
                        the breast of Heracles, <milestone ed="p" n="1005" unit="line"/> which held
                        him from his frenzied thirst for blood and plunged him into sleep; to the
                        ground he fell, striking his back against a column that had fallen on the
                        floor shattered in two when the roof fell in. <milestone ed="p" n="1010"
                            unit="line"/> Then we rallied from our flight, and with the old man's
                        aid bound him fast with knotted cords to the pillar, so that on his
                        awakening he might do no further evil. So there he sleeps, poor wretch! a
                        sleep that is not blessed, having murdered wife and children; no, for my
                        part <milestone ed="p" n="1015" unit="line"/> I do not know any mortal more
                        miserable than he.<stage>The messenger withdraws.</stage>
                    </p>
                </sp>

            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1016">
                <milestone unit="choral"/>
                <milestone unit="lyric"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>That murder wrought by the daughters of Danaus, which the rock of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> keeps, was once the most famous
                        and notorious in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>; but this
                        has surpassed, <milestone ed="p" n="1020" unit="line"/> has outrun those
                        former horrors . . . for the unhappy son of Zeus.</p>
                    <p>I could tell of the murder done by Procne, mother of an only child, offered
                        to the Muses; but you had three children, wretched parent, and all of them
                        have you in your frenzy slain.</p>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1025" unit="line"/> Alas! What groans or wails, what
                        funeral dirge, or dance of death am I to raise?</p>
                    <p>Ah, ah! see, the bolted doors <milestone ed="p" n="1030" unit="line"/> of the
                        lofty palace are being rolled apart.</p>
                    <p>Ah me! see the wretched children lying before their unhappy father, who is
                        sunk in dreadful slumber after shedding their blood.</p>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1035" unit="line"/> Round him are bonds and cords, made
                        fast with many knots about the body of Heracles, and lashed to the stone
                        columns of his house.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1039">

                <milestone unit="episode"/>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p>But he, the aged father, like mother-bird wailing <milestone ed="p" n="1040"
                            unit="line"/> her unfledged brood, comes hastening here with halting
                        steps on his bitter journey.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1042">
                <stage>The central doors of the palace have opened and have disclosed Heracles lying
                    asleep, bound to a shattered column. Amphtryon steps out. The following lines
                    between Amphitryon and the Chorus are chanted responsively.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Softly, softly! you aged sons of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName>, let him sleep on and forget his sorrows.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1045" unit="line"/> For you, old friend, I weep and
                        mourn, for the children too and that victorious chief.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Stand further off, make no noise nor outcry, do not rouse him from his calm
                            <milestone ed="p" n="1050" unit="line"/> deep slumber.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>O horrible! all this blood&#x2014;</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Hush, hush! you will be my ruin.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>That he has spilled is rising up against him.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Gently raise your dirge of woe, old friends; <milestone ed="p" n="1055"
                            unit="line"/> or he will wake, and, bursting his bonds, destroy the
                        city, rend his father, and dash his house to pieces.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>I cannot, cannot!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Hush! let me note his breathing; <milestone ed="p" n="1060" unit="line"/>
                        come, let me put my ear close.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Is he sleeping?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Yes, he is sleeping, a deadly sleepless sleep, having slain wife and children
                        with the arrows of his twanging bow.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1065" unit="line"/> Ah! mourn&#x2014;</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>I am mourning.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>The children's death&#x2014;</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Ah me!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>And your own son's doom.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Alas!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Old friend&#x2014;</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Hush! hush! he is turning, he is waking! Oh! <milestone ed="p" n="1070"
                            unit="line"/> let me hide myself, concealed beneath the roof.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Courage! darkness still holds your son's eye.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Oh beware! it is not that I shrink from leaving the light after my miseries,
                        poor wretch! but if should he slay me, his father, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="1075" unit="line"/> then he will be devising woe on woe, and to the
                        avenging curse will add a parent's blood.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>Well for you if you had died in that day, when, for your wife, you went forth
                        to exact vengeance for her slain brothers <milestone ed="p" n="1080"
                            unit="line"/> by sacking the Taphians' sea-beat town.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Fly, fly, my aged friends, from before the palace, escape his waking fury. Or
                        soon he will heap up fresh slaughter on the old, <milestone ed="p" n="1085"
                            unit="line"/> ranging wildly once more through the streets of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1086">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p>O Zeus, why have you shown such savage hate against your own son and plunged
                        him in this sea of troubles?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <stage>waking</stage>
                    <p>Aha! I am alive and breathing; and my eyes see what they should, <milestone
                            ed="p" n="1090" unit="line"/> the sky and earth and the sun's darting
                        beam; but how my senses reel! in what strange turmoil am I plunged! my
                        fevered breath in quick spasmodic gasps escapes my lungs. How now? why am I
                        lying here, my brawny chest and arms made fast with cables like a ship,
                            <milestone ed="p" n="1095" unit="line"/> beside a half-shattered piece
                        of masonry, with corpses for my neighbors; while over the floor my bow and
                        arrows are scattered, that once like trusty squires to my arm <milestone
                            ed="p" n="1100" unit="line"/> both kept me safe and were kept safe by
                        me? Surely I have not come a second time to Hades' halls, having just
                        returned from there for Eurystheus? To Hades? From where? No, I do not see
                        Sisyphus with his stone, or Pluto, or his queen, Demeter's child. <milestone
                            ed="p" n="1105" unit="line"/> Surely I am distraught; where am I, so
                        helpless? Ho, there! which of my friends is near or far to cure me in my
                        ignorance? For I have no clear knowledge of things once familiar.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>My aged friends, shall I approach the scene of my sorrow?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1110" unit="line"/> Yes, and let me go with you, not
                        desert you in your trouble.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Father, why do you weep and veil your eyes, standing far from your beloved
                        son?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>My child! mine still, for all your misery.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Why, what is there so sad in my case that you weep?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1115" unit="line"/> That which might make any of the
                        gods weep, if he were to learn it.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>A bold assertion that, but you are not yet explaining what has happened.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Your own eyes see that, if by this time you are restored to your senses.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Fill in your sketch if any change awaits my life.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>I will explain, if you are no longer mad as a fiend of hell.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1120" unit="line"/> Oh! what suspicions these dark hints
                        of yours again excite!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>I am still doubtful whether you are in your sober senses.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>I have no recollection of being mad.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Am I to loose my son, old friends, or what shall I do?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Loose me, yes, and say who bound me; for I feel shame at this.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1125" unit="line"/> Rest content with what you know of
                        your woes; the rest forego.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p> No. for is silence sufficient to learn what I wish?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>O Zeus, do you behold these deeds proceeding from the throne of Hera?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>What! have I suffered something from her enmity?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>A truce to the goddess! attend to your own troubles.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1130" unit="line"/> I am undone; you will tell me some
                        mischance.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1131">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>See here the corpses of your children.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>O horror! what sight is here? ah me!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>My son, against your children you have waged unnatural war.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>War! what do you mean? who killed these?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1135" unit="line"/> You and your bow and some god,
                        whoever is to blame.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>What are you saying? what have I done? Speak, father, you messenger of
                        evil!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>You were insane; it is a sad explanation you are asking.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Was it I that slew my wife also?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Your own unaided arm has done all this.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1140" unit="line"/> Alas! a cloud of mourning wraps me
                        round.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>For this reason I lament your fate.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Did I dash my house to pieces in my frenzy?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>I know nothing but this, that you are utterly undone.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Where did the madness seize me? where did it destroy me?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1145" unit="line"/> When you were purifying yourself
                        with fire at the altar.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Ah me! why do I spare my own life when I have become the murderer of my dear
                        children? Shall I not hasten to leap from some sheer rock, or aim the sword
                        against my heart <milestone ed="p" n="1150" unit="line"/> and avenge my
                        children's blood, or burn my body, which she drove mad, in the fire and so
                        avert from my life the infamy which now awaits me?</p>
                    <p>But here I see Theseus coming to check my deadly counsels, my kinsman and
                        friend. <milestone ed="p" n="1155" unit="line"/> Now shall I stand revealed,
                        and the dearest of my friends will see the pollution I have incurred by my
                        children's murder. Ah, woe is me! what am I to do? Where can I find freedom
                        from my sorrows? shall I take wings or plunge beneath the earth? Come, let
                        me veil my head in darkness; <milestone ed="p" n="1160" unit="line"/> for I
                        am ashamed of the evil I have done, and, since for these I have incurred
                        fresh blood-guiltiness, I do not want to harm the innocent.</p>
                </sp>
                <stage>Theseus and his retinue enter.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>I have come, and others with me, young warriors from the land of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, encamped by the streams of
                        Asopus, <milestone ed="p" n="1165" unit="line"/> to bring an allied army to
                        your son, old friend. For a rumour reached the city of the Erechtheidae,
                        that Lycus had usurped the scepter of this land and had become your enemy
                        even to battle. Wherefore I came making recompense for the former kindness
                        of Heracles <milestone ed="p" n="1170" unit="line"/> in saving me from the
                        world below, if you have any need of such aid as I or my allies can give,
                        old man.</p>
                    <p>Ha! why this heap of dead upon the floor? Surely I have not delayed too long
                        and come too late to check new ills? Who slew these children? <milestone
                            ed="p" n="1175" unit="line"/> whose wife is this I see? Boys do not go
                        to battle; no, it must be some other strange mischance I here discover.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1178">
                <stage>In the following lines, Amphitryon makes sung responses to Theseus' spoken
                    questions.</stage>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>O king, whose home is that olive-clad hill!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Why this piteous prelude in addressing me?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1180" unit="line"/> The gods have afflicted us with
                        grievous suffering.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Whose are these children, over whom you weep?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>My own son's children, woe to him! he was their father and butcher both,
                        hardening his heart to the bloody deed.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Hush! good words only!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1185" unit="line"/> I would I could obey!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>What dreadful words!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Fortune has spread her wings, and we are ruined, ruined.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>What do you mean? what has he done?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Slain them in a wild fit of frenzy <milestone ed="p" n="1190" unit="line"/>
                        with arrows dipped in the venom of the hundred-headed hydra.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>This is Hera's work; but who lies there among the dead, old man?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>My son, my own enduring son, that marched with gods to Phlegra's plain, there
                        to battle with giants and slay them, warrior that he was.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1195" unit="line"/> Ah, ah! whose fortune was ever so
                        cursed as his?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Never will you find another mortal that has suffered more or been driven
                        harder.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Why does he veil his head, poor wretch, in his robe?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>He is ashamed to meet your eye; <milestone ed="p" n="1200" unit="line"/> his
                        kinsman's kind intent and his children's blood make him abashed.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>But I come to sympathize; uncover him.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>My son, remove that mantle <milestone ed="p" n="1205" unit="line"/> from your
                        eyes, throw it from you, show your face to the sun. As a counterweight,
                        fighting along with my tears, I entreat you as a suppliant, as I grasp your
                        beard, your knees, your hands, and let fall <milestone ed="p" n="1210"
                            unit="line"/> the tear from my old eyes. O my child! restrain your
                        savage lion-like temper, for you are rushing forth on an unholy course of
                        bloodshed, eager to join woe to woe, child.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1214">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Enough! To you I call who are huddled there in your misery, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="1215" unit="line"/> show to your friends your face; for no darkness
                        is black enough to hide your sad mischance. Why do you wave your hand at me,
                        signifying murder? is it that I may not be polluted by speaking with you?
                            <milestone ed="p" n="1220" unit="line"/> If I share your misfortune,
                        what is that to me? For once I had good fortune with you. I must refer to
                        the time when you brought me safe from the dead to the light of life. I hate
                        a friend whose gratitude grows old; one who is ready to enjoy his friends'
                        prosperity <milestone ed="p" n="1225" unit="line"/> but unwilling to sail in
                        the same ship with them when they are unfortunate. Arise, unveil your head,
                        poor wretch! and look on me. The gallant soul endures such blows as heaven
                        deals and does not refuse them.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>O Theseus, did you see this struggle with my children?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1230" unit="line"/> I heard of it, and now I see the
                        horrors you mean.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Why then have you unveiled my head to the sun?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Why have I? you, a mortal, can not pollute what is of the gods.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Try to escape, luckless wretch, from my unholy taint.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>The avenging fiend does not go forth from friend to friend.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1235" unit="line"/> For this I thank you; I do not
                        regret the service I did you.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>While I, for kindness then received, now show my pity for you.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Ah yes! I am piteous, a murderer of my sons.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>I weep for you in your changed fortunes.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Did you ever find another more afflicted?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1240" unit="line"/> Your misfortunes reach from earth to
                        heaven.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Therefore I am resolved on death.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Do you suppose the gods attend to your threats?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>The god has been remorseless to me; so I will be the same to the gods.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Hush! lest your presumption add to your sufferings.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1245" unit="line"/> My ship is freighted full with
                        sorrow; there is no room to stow anything further.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>What will you do? Where is your fury drifting you?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>I will die and return to that world below from which I have just come.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Such language is fit for any common fellow.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Ah! yours is the advice of one outside sorrow.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1250" unit="line"/> Are these indeed the words of
                        Heracles, the much-enduring?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Though never so much as this. Endurance must have a limit.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Is this the benefactor and great friend to mortals?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Mortals bring no help to me; no! Hera has her way.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Never would <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> allow you to die
                        through sheer perversity.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1255">
                <sp n="Heracles">
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1255" unit="line"/> Hear me a moment, that I may enter
                        the contest with words in answer to your admonitions; and I will unfold to
                        you why life now as well as formerly has been unbearable to me. First I am
                        the son of a man who incurred the guilt of blood, before he married my
                        mother Alcmena, <milestone ed="p" n="1260" unit="line"/> by slaying her aged
                        father. Now when the foundation is badly laid at birth, it is necessary for
                        the race to be cursed with woe; and Zeus, whoever this Zeus may be, begot me
                        as an enemy to Hera; yet do not be vexed, old man; <milestone ed="p"
                            n="1265" unit="line"/> for you rather than Zeus I regard as my father.
                        Then while I was being suckled, that bedfellow of Zeus foisted into my
                        cradle fearsome snakes to cause my death. After I took on a cloak of
                        youthful flesh, <milestone ed="p" n="1270" unit="line"/> of all the toils I
                        then endured what need to tell? what did I not destroy, whether lions, or
                        triple-bodied Typhons, or giants or the battle against the hosts of
                        four-legged Centaurs? or how when I had killed the hydra, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="1275" unit="line"/> that monster with a ring of heads with power to
                        grow again, I passed through a herd of countless other toils besides and
                        came to the dead to fetch to the light at the bidding of Eurystheus the
                        three-headed hound, hell's porter. Last, ah, woe is me! I have dared this
                        labor, <milestone ed="p" n="1280" unit="line"/> to crown the sorrows of my
                        house with my children's murder. I have come to this point of necessity; no
                        longer may I dwell in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>,
                        the city that I love; for suppose I stay, to what temple or gathering of
                        friends shall I go? For mine is no curse that invites greetings. <milestone
                            ed="p" n="1285" unit="line"/> Shall I go to <placeName
                            key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>? how can I, when I am an exile
                        from my country? Well, is there a single other city I can rush to? Am I then
                        to be looked at askance as a marked man, held by cruel stabbing tongues:
                        &#x201C;Is not this the son of Zeus that once murdered children <milestone
                            ed="p" n="1290" unit="line"/> and wife? Plague take him from the
                        land!&#x201D; Now to one who was once called happy, such changes are a
                        grievous thing; though he who is always unfortunate feels no such pain, for
                        sorrow is his birthright.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1294">
                <sp>
                    <p>This, I think, is the piteous pass I shall one day come to; <milestone ed="p"
                            n="1295" unit="line"/> for earth will cry out forbidding me to touch
                        her, the sea and the river-springs will refuse me a crossing, and I shall
                        become like Ixion who revolves in chains upon that wheel. And so this is
                        best, that I should be seen by no one of the Hellenes, <milestone ed="p"
                            n="1300" unit="line"/> among whom in happier days I lived in bliss. What
                        right have I to live? what profit can I have in the possession of a useless,
                        impious life? So let that noble wife of Zeus dance, beating her foot in its
                        shoe; <milestone ed="p" n="1305" unit="line"/> for now has she worked her
                        heart's desire in utterly confounding the first of <placeName
                            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>' sons. Who would pray to such a
                        goddess? Her jealousy of Zeus for his love of a woman has destroyed
                            <milestone ed="p" n="1310" unit="line"/> the benefactors of <placeName
                            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, guiltless though they were.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus Leader</speaker>
                    <p>This is the work of none other of the gods than the wife of Zeus; you are
                        right in that surmise.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>I cannot counsel you . . . rather than to go on suffering. There is not a man
                        alive that has wholly escaped misfortune's taint, <milestone ed="p" n="1315"
                            unit="line"/> nor any god either, if what poets sing is true. Have they
                        not intermarried in ways that law forbids? Have they not thrown fathers into
                        ignominious chains to gain the sovereign power? Still they inhabit
                            <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> and brave the issue of
                        their crimes. <milestone ed="p" n="1320" unit="line"/> And yet what shall
                        you say in your defence, if you, a child of man, take your fate excessively
                        hard, while they, as gods, do not? No, then, leave <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> in compliance with the law, and
                        come with me to the city of Pallas. There, when I have purified you of your
                        pollution, <milestone ed="p" n="1325" unit="line"/> I will give you homes
                        and the half of all I have. Yes, I will give you all those presents I
                        received from the citizens for saving their fourteen children, when I slew
                        the bull of <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>; for I have plots
                        of land assigned me throughout the country; these shall henceforth
                            <milestone ed="p" n="1330" unit="line"/> be called after you by men,
                        while you live; and at your death, when you have gone to Hades' halls, the
                        whole city of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> shall exalt
                        your honor with sacrifices and a monument of stone. For it is a noble crown
                        of a good reputation <milestone ed="p" n="1335" unit="line"/> for citizens
                        to win from <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, by helping a
                        man of worth. This is the return that I will make you for saving me, for now
                        you are in need of friends. But when the gods honor a man, he has no need of
                        friends; for the god's aid, when he chooses to give it, is enough.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1340">
                <sp n="Heracles">
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1340" unit="line"/> Alas! this is quite beside the
                        question of my troubles. For my part, I do not believe that the gods indulge
                        in unholy unions; and as for putting bonds on hands, I have never thought
                        that worthy of belief, nor will I now be so persuaded, nor again that one
                        god is naturally lord and master of another. <milestone ed="p" n="1345"
                            unit="line"/> For the deity, if he be really such, has no wants; these
                        are miserable tales of the poets. But I, for all my piteous plight,
                        reflected whether I should let myself be branded as a coward for giving up
                        my life. For whoever does not withstand disasters <milestone ed="p" n="1350"
                            unit="line"/> will never be able to withstand even a man's weapon. I
                        will be steadfast in living; I will go to your city, with grateful thanks
                        for all you offer me. <stage>He weeps.</stage> But I have tasted of
                        countless troubles, as is well known; never yet did I faint at any or shed a
                        single tear; no, nor did I ever think <milestone ed="p" n="1355" unit="line"
                        /> that I should come to this, to let the tear-drop fall. But now, it seems,
                        I must be fortune's slave.</p>
                    <p>Well, let it pass; my old father, you see me go forth to exile, and in me you
                        see my own children's murderer. <milestone ed="p" n="1360" unit="line"/>
                        Give them burial, and lay them out in death with the tribute of a tear, for
                        the law forbids my doing so. Rest their heads upon their mother's bosom and
                        fold them in her arms, sad fellowship, which I, alas! unwittingly did slay.
                        And when you have buried these dead, <milestone ed="p" n="1365" unit="line"
                        /> live on here still, in bitterness maybe, but still constrain your soul to
                        share my sorrows. O children! he who begot you, your own father, has been
                        your destroyer, and you have had no profit of my triumphs, all my restless
                        toil to win for you by force <milestone ed="p" n="1370" unit="line"/> a fair
                        name, a glorious advantage from a father. You too, unhappy wife, this hand
                        has slain, a poor return to make you for preserving the honor of my bed so
                        safely, for all the weary watch you long have kept within my house. Alas for
                        you, my wife, my sons! alas for me, <milestone ed="p" n="1375" unit="line"/>
                        how sad my lot, cut off from wife and child! Ah! these kisses, bitter-sweet!
                        these weapons which it is pain to own! I am not sure whether to keep or let
                        them go; dangling at my side they thus will say, <milestone ed="p" n="1380"
                            unit="line"/> &#x201C;With us you destroyed children and wife; we are
                        your children's slayers, and you keep us.&#x201D; Shall I carry them after
                        that? what answer can I make? Yet, am I to strip myself of these weapons,
                        the comrades of my glorious career in <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                            >Hellas</placeName>, and put myself in the power of my foes, to die a
                        death of shame? <milestone ed="p" n="1385" unit="line"/> No! I must not let
                        them go, but keep them, though it grieves me. In one thing, Theseus, help my
                        misery; come to <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> and help me
                        to manage the conveyance of the wretched dog; lest, if I go all alone, my
                        sorrow for my sons may do me some hurt.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1389">
                <sp>
                    <p>O land of Cadmus, and all you people of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName>! <milestone ed="p" n="1390" unit="line"/> cut off
                        your hair, and mourn with me; go to my children's burial, and with one dirge
                        lament us all, the dead and me; for on all of us has Hera inflicted the same
                        cruel blow of destruction.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Rise, unhappy man! you have had your fill of tears.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1395" unit="line"/> I cannot rise; my limbs are rooted
                        here.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Yes, even the strong are overthrown by misfortunes.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Ah! Would I could become a stone upon this spot, oblivious of trouble.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Peace! give your hand to a friend and helper.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>No, let me not wipe off the blood upon your robe.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1400" unit="line"/> Wipe it off and spare not; I will
                        not refuse you.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Bereft of my own sons, I find you as a son to me.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Throw your arm about my neck; I will be your guide.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>A pair of friends indeed, but one a man of sorrows. Ah! aged father, this is
                        the kind of man to make a friend.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1405" unit="line"/> Blessed in her sons, the country
                        that gave him birth!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Theseus, turn me back again to see my children.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>What for? Do you think to find a drug in this to soothe your soul?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>I long to do so, and would embrace my father.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Here am I, my son; your wish is no less dear to me.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1410" unit="line"/> Have you so short a memory for your
                        troubles?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>All that I endured before was easier to bear than this.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>If anyone sees you play the woman, they will scoff.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Have I by living grown so abject in your sight? It was not so once, I
                        think.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Yes, too much so; in your sickness you are not the glorious Heracles.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1415" unit="line"/> What about you? What kind of hero
                        were you when in trouble in the world below?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>I was worse than anyone as far as courage went.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>How then can you say of me, that I am abased by my troubles?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Theseus</speaker>
                    <p>Forward!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Farewell, my aged father!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>Farewell to you, my son!</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>Bury my children as I said.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>But who will bury me, my son?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p><milestone ed="p" n="1420" unit="line"/> I will.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>When wil you come?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>After you have buried my children.</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Amphitryon</speaker>
                    <p>How?</p>
                </sp>
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Heracles</speaker>
                    <p>I will fetch you from <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> to
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. But carry my
                        children within, a grievous burden to the earth. And I, after ruining my
                        house by deeds of shame, will follow as a little boat in the wake of
                        Theseus, totally destroyed. <milestone ed="p" n="1425" unit="line"/> Whoever
                        prefers wealth or might to the possession of good friends, thinks
                            wrongly.<stage>Theseus and his attendants lead Heracles
                        away.</stage></p>
                </sp>
            </div>

            <div type="textpart" subtype="card" n="1427">
                <sp>
                    <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                    <p>With grief and many a bitter tear we go our way, robbed of all we prized most
                        dearly.</p>
                </sp>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
