<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Surgery </title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">Charles Darwin Adams</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 20, 2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">Charles Darwin Adams</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Dover</publisher>
							<date>1868</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Aph.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Epid.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="section" n="1">
				<head>Part 1</head>
				<p>It's the business of the physician to know, in the first place, things similar
					and things dissimilar; those connected with things most important, most easily
					known, and in anywise known;<note>The meaning of the first clause of this
						sentence, according to Galen, is, that the first thing which the medical
						practitioner must do is to make himself well acquainted with semeiology, by
						comparing carefully the condition of disease with that of health. In all
						cases of accident, it was the practice of the ancient surgeons to compare
						carefully the injured part with its fellow or corresponding part on the
						opposite side.</note> which are to be seen, touched, and heard; which are to
					be perceived in the sight, and the touch, and the hearing, and the nose, and the
					tongue, and the understanding; which are to be known by all the means we know
					other things.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="2">
				<head>Part 2</head>
				<p> The things relating to surgery, are- the patient; the operator; the assistants;
					the instruments; the light, where and how; how many things, and how; where the
					body, and the instruments; the time; the manner; the place.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="3">
				<head>Part 3</head>
				<p> The operator is either sitting or standing, conveniently for himself, for the
					person operated upon, for the light. There are two kinds of light, the common
					and the artificial; the common is not at our disposal, the artificial is at our
					disposal. There are two modes of using each, either to the light, or from the
					light (to the side?). There is little use of that which is from (<hi rend="ital"
						>or</hi> oblique to the light), and the degree of it is obvious. As to
					opposite the light, we must turn the part to be operated upon to that which is
					most brilliant of present and convenient lights, unless those parts which should
					be concealed, and which it is a shame to look upon; thus the part that is
					operated upon should be opposite the light, and the operator opposite the part
						operated<pb n="p.162"/> upon, except in so far as he does not stand in his
					own light; for in this case the operator will indeed see, but the thing operated
					upon will not be seen. With regard to himself when sitting, his feet should be
					raised to a direct line with his knees, and nearly in contact with one another;
					the knees a little higher than the groins, and at some distance from one
					another, for the elbows to rest upon them. The robe, in a neat and orderly
					manner, is to be thrown over the elbows and shoulders equally and
					proportionally. With regard to the part operated upon; we have to consider how
					far distant, and how near, above, below, on this side on that side, or in the
					middle. The measure as to distance and proximity is, that the elbows do not
					press the knees before, nor the sides behind; that the hands be not raised
					higher than the breasts, nor lower than so as that when the breast reposes on
					the knees he may have the hands at right angles with the arm: thus it is as
					regards the medium; but as concerns this side or that, the operator must not be
					beyond his seat, but in proportion as he may require turning he must shift the
					body, or part of the body, that is operated upon. When standing, he must make
					his inspection, resting firmly and equally on both feet; but he must operate
					while supporting himself upon either leg, and not the one on the same side with
					the hand which he makes use of; the knee being raised to the height of the
					groins as while sitting; and the other measures in like manner. The person
					operated upon should accommodate the operator with regard to the other parts of
					his body, either standing, sitting, or lying; so as that he may continue to
					preserve his figure, avoid sinking down, shrinking from, turning away; and may
					maintain the figure and position of the part operated upon, during the act of
					presentation, during the operation, and in the subsequent position.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="4">
				<head>Part 4</head>
				<p> The nails should be neither longer nor shorter than the points of the fingers;
					and the surgeon should practice with the extremities of the fingers, the
					index-finger being usually turned to the thumb; when using the entire hand, it
					should be prone; when both hands, they should be opposed to one another. It
					greatly promotes a dexterous use of the fingers when the space between them is
					large, and when the thumb is opposed to the<pb n="p.163"/> index. But it is
					clearly a disease when the thumb is impaired from birth, or when, from a habit
					contracted during the time of nursing, it is impeded in its motions by the
					fingers. One should practice all sorts of work with either of them, and with
					both together (for they are both alike), endeavouring to do them well,
					elegantly, quickly, without trouble, neatly, and promptly.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="5">
				<head>Part 5</head>
				<p>The instruments, and when and how they should be prepared, will be treated of
					afterwards; so that they may not impede the work, and that there may be no
					difficulty in taking hold of them, with the part of the body which operates. But
					if another gives them, he must be ready a little beforehand, and do as you
					direct.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="6">
				<head>Part 6</head>
				<p> Those about the patient must present the part to be operated upon as may seem
					proper, and they must hold the rest of the body steady, in silence, and
					listening to the commands of the operator.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="7">
				<head>Part 7</head>
				<p> There are two views of bandaging: that which regards it while doing, and that
					which regards it when done. It should be done quickly, without pain, with ease,
					and with elegance; quickly, by despatching the work; without pain, by being
					readily done; with ease, by being prepared for everything; and with elegance, so
					that it may be agreeable to the sight. By what mode of training these
					accomplishments are to be acquired has been stated. When done, it should fit
					well and neatly; it is neatly done when with judgment, and when it is equal and
					unequal, according as the parts are equal or unequal. The forms of it (the
					bandage?) are the simple, the slightly winding (called ascia), the sloping
					(sima), the monoculus, the rhombus, and the semi-rhombus. The form of bandage
					should be suitable to the form and the affection of the part to which it is
					applied.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="8">
				<head>Part 8</head>
				<p> There are two useful purposes to be fulfilled by bandaging: (<hi rend="ital"
						>first</hi>,) strength, which is imparted by the compression and the number
					of folds. In one case the bandage effects the cure, and in another it
					contributes to the cure. For these purposes this is the rule- that the force of
					the constriction be such as to prevent the adjoining parts from separating,
					without compressing them much, and so that the parts may be adjusted but not <pb
						n="p.164"/>forced together; and that the constriction be small at the
					extremities, and least of all in the middle. The knot and the thread that is
					passed through should not be in a downward but in an upward direction, regard
					being had to the circumstances under which the case is presented; to position,
					to the bandaging, and to the compression. The commencement of the ligatures is
					not to be placed at the wound, but where the knot is situated. The knot should
					not be placed where it will be exposed to friction, nor where it will be in the
					way, nor where it will be useless. The knot and the thread should be soft, and
					not large.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="9">
				<head>Part 9</head>
				<p> (<hi rend="ital">Second.</hi>) One ought to be well aware that every bandage has
					a tendency to fall off towards the part that declines or becomes smaller; as,
					for example, upwards, in the case of the head, and downwards, in the case of the
					leg. The turns of the bandage should be made from right to left, and from left
					to right, except on the head, where it should be in a straight direction. When
					opposite parts are to be bandaged together, we must use a bandage with two
					heads; or if we make use of a bandage with one head, we must attach it in like
					manner at some fixed point: such, for example, as the middle of the head; and so
					in other cases. Those parts which are much exposed to motion, such as the
					joints, where there is a flexion, should have few and slight bandages applied to
					them, as at the ham; but where there is much extension, the bandage should be
					single and broad, as at the kneepan; and for the maintenance of the bandage in
					its proper place, some turns should be carried to those parts which are not much
					moved, and are lank, such as the parts above and below the knee. In the case of
					the shoulder; a fold should be carried round by the other armpit; in that of the
					groin, by the flanks of the opposite side; and of the leg, to above the calf of
					the leg. When the bandage has a tendency to escape above, it should be secured
					below, and <hi rend="ital">vice versa</hi>; and where there is no means of doing
					this, as in the case of the head, the turns are to be made mostly on the most
					level part of the head, and the folds are to be done with as little obliquity as
					possible, so that the firmest part being last applied may secure the portions
					which are more movable. When we cannot secure the bandaging by means of <pb
						n="p.165"/>folds of the cloth, nor by suspending them from the opposite
					side, we must have recourse to stitching it with ligatures, either passed
					circularly or in the form of a seam.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="10">
				<head>Part 10 </head>
				<p> The bandages should be clean, light, soft, and thin. One should practice rolling
					with both hands together, and with either separately. One should also choose a
					suitable one, according to the breadth and thickness of the parts. The heads of
					the bandages should be hard, smooth, and neatly put on. That sort of bandaging
					is the worst which quickly falls off; but those are bad bandages which neither
					compress nor yet come off.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="11">
				<head>Part 11</head>
				<p> The following are the object which the upper bandage, the under bandage, or both
					aim at: The object of the under bandage is either to bring together parts that
					are separated, or to compress such as are expanded, or to separate what are
					contracted, or to restore to shape what are distorted, or the contrary. It is
					necessary to prepare pieces of linen cloth, which are light, thin, soft, clean,
					having no seams nor protuberances on them, but sound, and able to bear some
					stretching, or even a little more than required; not dry, but wetted with a
					juice suitable to the purpose required. We must deal with parts separated (<hi
						rend="ital">in a sinus?</hi>) in such wise, that the parts which are raised
					may touch the bottom without producing pressure; we must begin on the sound
					part, and terminate at the wound; so that whatever humor is in it may be
					expelled, and that it may be prevented from collecting more. And straight parts
					are to be bandaged in a straight direction, and oblique obliquely, in such a
					position as to create no pain; and so that there may be no constriction nor
					falling off on a change of position, either for the purpose of taking hold of
					anything, or laying the limb; and that muscles, veins, nerves, and bones may be
					properly placed and adjusted to one another. It should be raised or laid in a
					natural position, so as not to occasion pain. In those cases in which an abscess
					is formed, we must act in a contrary way. When our object is to bring together
					parts which have become expanded, in other respects we must proceed on the same
					plain; and we must commence the bringing together from some considerable
					distance; and after their approach, we must apply compression, at first slight,
						<pb n="p.166"/>and afterwards stronger, the limit of it being the actual
					contact of the parts. In order to separate parts which are drawn together, when
					attended with inflammation, we must proceed on the opposite plan; but when
					without inflammation, we must use the same preparations, but bandage in the
					opposite direction. In order to rectify distorted parts, we must proceed
					otherwise on the same principles; but the parts which are separated must be
					brought together by an underbandage, by agglutinants, and by suspending it (<hi
						rend="ital">the limb?</hi>) in its natural position. And when the
					deformities are the contrary, this is to be done on the contrary plan.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="12">
				<head>Part 12</head>
				<p> In fractures we must attend to the length, breadth, thickness, and number of the
					compresses. The length should be that of the bandaging; the breadth, three or
					four fingers; thickness, three or fourfold; number so as to encircle the limb,
					neither more nor less; those applied for the purpose of rectifying a deformity,
					should be of such a length as to encircle it; the breadth and thickness being
					determined by the vacuity, which is not to be filled up at once. The upper
					bandages are two, the first of which is to be carried from the seat of the
					injury upwards, and the second from the seat of the injury downwards, and from
					below upwards; the parts about the seat of the injury being most compressed, the
					extremities least, and the rest in proportion. The upper bandages should take in
					a considerable portion of the sound parts. We must attend to the number, length,
					and breadth of the bandages; the number must be such as not to be inferior to
					what the injury requires, nor occasion compression with the splints, nor prove
					cumbersome, nor occasion any slipping of them, nor render them inefficient. As
					to length and breadth, they should be three, four, five, or six cubits in
					length, and as many fingers broad. The folds of the strings (<hi rend="ital"
						>selvages?</hi>) should be such as not to occasion pressure; they are to be
					soft and not thick; and all these things are to be proportionate to the length,
					breadth, and thickness of the part affected. The splints are to be smooth, even,
					and rounded at the extremities; somewhat less all along than the upper
					bandaging, and thickest at the part to which fracture inclines. Those parts
					where there are tuber-<pb n="p.167"/>osities, and which are devoid of flesh,
					such as the ankles or fingers, we must guard from the splints which are placed
					over them, either by position, or by their shortness. They are to be secured by
					the strings in such a manner as not to occasion pressure at first. A soft,
					consistent, and clean cerate should be rubbed into the folds of the bandage.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="13">
				<head>Part 13</head>
				<p> As to the temperature and quantity of the water used, its heat should be just
					such as the hand can bear, and it ought to be known that a large quantity is
					best for producing relaxation and attenuation, whereas a moderate quantity is
					best for incarnating and softening. The limit to the affusion is, to stop when
					the parts become swelled up, and before the swelling subsides; for the parts
					swell up at first, and fall afterward. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="14">
				<head>Part 14</head>
				<p> The object on which to (<hi rend="ital">the limb?</hi>) is laid should be soft,
					smooth, and sloping upwards toward the protuberant parts of the body, such as
					the heel or hips, so that there may be no projection, nor bending inwards, nor
					turning aside. The canal (<hi rend="ital">spout or gutter?</hi>) should rather
					comprehend the whole limb than the half of it, attention being paid to the
					injury and to whatever else appears to create inconvenience.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="15">
				<head>Part 15</head>
				<p> The presentation of the injured part to the physician, the extension, the
					arrangement, and so forth, are to be regulated according to nature. What is
					nature in these operations is to be determined by the accomplishment of the
					object which we have in view, and for this purpose we must look to the part in
					the state of rest, in its middle state, and to habit; in regard to the state of
					rest and relaxation, as in the arm, that it be in a line with the hand; and with
					regard to the medium between flexion and extension, that the forearm be at right
					angles to the arm; and with regard to habit, it should be considered that some
					limbs bear certain positions preferably, as, for example, the thighs extension;
					for in such attitudes the parts can best bear to be placed for a considerable
					time without a change of posture. And in the change from the state of
					distention, the muscles, veins, nerves, and bones, when properly arranged and
					secured, will preserve their relations to one another while the limb is raised
					or placed.<pb n="p.168"/></p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="16">
				<head>Part 16</head>
				<p> The extension should be most powerful when the largest and thickest bones, or
					when both are broken; next when the under-bone, and least of all, when the
					upper. When immoderate, it is injurious, except in the case of children. The
					limb should be a little elevated. The model by which we judge if the part be
					properly set is the sound part of the same name, or the part which is its
					pair.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="17">
				<head>Part 17</head>
				<p> Friction can relax, brace, incarnate, attenuate: hard braces, soft relaxes, much
					attenuates, and moderate thickens.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="18">
				<head>Part 18</head>
				<p> The following should be the state of matters on the first application of the
					bandage. The person to whom it has been applied should say that he feels the
					compression particularly at the seat of the injury, but very little at the
					extremities; the parts should be adjusted but not pressed together, and that
					rather by the number of the bandages than by the force of the constriction; and
					the tightness should rather be on the increase during the first day and night;
					but on the next it should be less, and on the third the bandages should be
					loose. On the next day a soft swelling should be observed in the extremities;
					and on the third day, when the bandaging is loosed, the swelling should be found
					diminished in size, and this should be the case every time the bandages are
					removed. At the second application of the bandage, it should be ascertained
					whether the dressing has been properly done, and then greater compression should
					be made, and with more bandages; and on the third, still greater, and still
					more. On the seventh day from the first dressing, when the bandages are loosed,
					the limb should be found slender and the bones mobile. We must then have
					recourse to the splints, provided the limb be free of swelling, pruritus, and
					ulceration, and allow them to remain until twenty days after the accident; but
					if any suspicions arise, the bandages must be loosed in the interval. The
					splints should be tightened every third day. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="19">
				<head>Part 19</head>
				<p> The suspending of a fractured limb in a sling, the disposition of it, and the
					bandaging, all have for their object to preserve it in position. The principal
					considerations with regard to the position are the habits and the peculiar
					nature of each<pb n="p.169"/> of the limbs: the varieties are shown in running,
					walking, standing, lying, action, repose. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="20">
				<head>Part 20</head>
				<p>It should be kept in mind that exercise strengthens, and inactivity wastes.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="21">
				<head>Part 21</head>
				<p>Compression should be produced by the number of bandages, rather than by the
					force of the constriction.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="22">
				<head>Part 22</head>
				<p>In cases of ecchymosis, contusions, sprains, or swellings not attended with
					inflammations, blood is to be expelled from the wound, in greatest quantity to
					the upper part, and in smallest to the inferior; neither the arm nor the leg
					should be placed in a declining position: the head of the bandage should be
					placed on the wound, and there the greatest pressure should be made; the least
					at the extremities, and intermediately in the middle; the last fold of the
					bandage should be at the upper part of the body. As to binding and compression,
					these objects are to be attained rather by the number of the bandages than the
					force of the constriction; and moreover, in these cases the bandages should be
					thin, light, soft, clean, broad, sound, so that they may effect their purpose,
					even without splints. And we must use affusions. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="23">
				<head>Part 23</head>
				<p>Dislocations, sprains, diastases of bones, violent separation, abruption of the
					extremities of bones, and distrainings, so as to induce <hi rend="ital"
						>varus</hi> or <hi rend="ital">valgus</hi>, in these cases we must apply the
					bandages so as not to compress the part whence the displacement took place, and
					that we may render them tight at the side to which the displacement was, and
					give the limb an inclination in the opposite direction, and that in an excessive
					degree. We employ bandages, compresses, suspension of the limb in a sling,
					attitude, extension, friction, rectification; and along with these the affusion
					of much water.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="24">
				<head>Part 24</head>
				<p> In treating parts which are atrophied, we must comprehend a considerable part of
					the sound limb with the bandage, so that by the influx thereby produced, the
					wasted part may acquire a supply greater than its loss, and may be thus disposed
					to growth and restoration of its fleshy parts. It is better also to bandage the
					parts above, as the thigh in the case of the leg, <pb n="p.170"/>and also the
					thigh and leg of the opposite side, so that they may be placed in similar
					circumstances, and may both equally be deprived of motion; and that the supply
					of nourishment may be alike curtailed and open to both. The compression should
					be the effect rather of the number of the bandages than of their tightness. We
					relax first the part most requiring it, and have recourse to that kind of
					friction which will promote the growth of flesh, and to affusion. No splints.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="25">
				<head>Part 25</head>
				<p> Those things which are for the purpose of giving support and strength to the
					part, as to the breast, side, head, and so forth, are used in such cases as the
					following: for pulsations, that there may be no motion in the part; and in
					separation at the sutures of the skull, in order to give support; and in order
					to strengthen the chest and head, in coughs, sneezings, and other movements. In
					all these cases the same measure of bandaging is to be observed, for where the
					injury is, there the bandage should compress most, and something soft is to be
					placed below that suits with the complaint; and we must not apply the bandages
					tighter than just to stop the pulsations from creating disturbance, and that the
					separated parts at the sutures may be brought into contact, they must not be
					such as absolutely to stop the coughs and sneezings, but so as to give support,
					and, without occasioning uneasiness, prevent the parts from being shaken.</p>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
