<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>THE OATH </title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 1, 2005</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							              <date>1923</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="">English</language>
				        <language ident="">Greek</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="lat"
              type="edition"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg013.perseus-eng2">
			         <pb n="p.299"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
				           <head>OATH</head>
				           <p>I <hi rend="sc">SWEAR</hi> by Apollo Physician, by Asclepius, by Health, by
					Panacea and by all the gods and goddesses, making them my witnesses, that I will
					carry out, according to my ability and judgment, this oath and this indenture.
					To hold my teacher in this art equal to my own parents ; to make him partner in
					my livelihood ; when he is in need of money to share mine with him ; to consider
					his family as my own brothers, and to teach them this art, if they want to learn
					it, without fee or indenture ; to impart precept,<note>Apparently the written
						rules of the art, examples of which are to be found in several Hippocratie
						treatises. These books were not published in the strict sense of the word,
						but copies would be circulated among the members of the " physicians'
						union."</note> oral instruction, and all other instruction<note>Probably, in
						modern English, " instruction, written, oral and practical."</note> to my
					own sons, the sons of my teacher, and to indentured pupils who have taken the
					physician's oath, but to nobody else. I will use treatment to help the sick
					according to my ability and judgment, but never with a view to injury and
					wrong-doing. Neither will I administer a poison to anybody when asked to do so,
					nor will I suggest such a course. Similarly I will not give to a woman a pessary
					to cause abortion. But I will keep pure and holy both my life and my art. I will
					not use the knife, not even, verily, on sufferers from stone, but I will give
					place to such as are craftsmen</p>
				           <pb n="p.301"/>
				           <p>therein. Into whatsoever houses I enter, I will enter to help the sick, and I
					will abstain from all intentional wrong-doing and harm, especially from abusing
					the bodies of man or woman, bond or free. And whatsoever I shall see or hear in
					the course of my profession, as well as outside my profession in my intercourse
					with men,<note>This remarkable addition is worthy of a passing notice. The
						physician must not gossip, no matter how or where the subject-matter for
						gossip may have been acquired ; whether it be in practice or in private life
						makes no difference.</note> if it be what should not be published abroad, I
					will never divulge, holding such things to be holy secrets. Now if I carry out
					this oath, and break it not, may I gain for ever reputation among all men for my
					life and for my art ; but if I transgress it and forswear myself, may the
					opposite befall me.</p>
			         </div>


			         <pb n="p.305"/>
		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
