<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On Organization </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by C. A. Vince, M. A. and J.
                            H. Vince, M.A.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1926</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>6/2/92</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserted quotedtext tags around verse</item>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>In dealing with the sum of money under discussion and the other matters referred
                    to this Assembly, I see no difficulty, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, in either of two methods: I may attack the officials
                    who assign and distribute the public funds and may thus gain credit with those
                    who regard this system as detrimental to the State, or I may approve and commend
                    the right to receive these doles and so gratify those who are especially in need
                    of them. For neither class has the interest of the State in view, when they
                    approve or complain of the system, but they are prompted respectively by their
                    poverty or their affluence.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>I myself would neither propose such a distribution of the doles, nor oppose the
                    right to receive them; but I do urge you to reflect seriously in your own minds
                    that while the sum of money you are discussing is a trifle, the habit of mind
                    that it fosters is a serious matter. Now if you so organize the receipt of money
                    that it is associated with the performance of duties, so far from injuring, you
                    will actually confer on the State and on yourselves the greatest benefit; but if
                    a festival or any other pretext is good enough to justify a dole, and yet you
                    refuse even to listen to the suggestion that there is any obligation attached to
                    it, beware lest you end by acknowledging that what you now consider a proper
                    practice was a grievous error.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>My idea of our duty—do not drown with your clamor what I am about to say, but
                    hear me before you judge—my idea is that, as we have devoted a meeting of the
                    Assembly to the question of receiving the dole, so we ought also to devote a
                    meeting to organization and to equipment for war; and everyone must show himself
                    not merely ready to hear what is said, but also willing to act, so that you may
                    depend on yourselves, Athenians, for your hopes of success, and not be always
                    asking what service this individual or that is rendering. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>The total revenues of the State, including your own resources, now squandered on
                    unnecessary objects, and the contributions of your allies, must be shared by
                    each citizen equally, as pay by those of military age and as overseers' fees, or
                    whatever you like to call it, by those beyond the age-limit; and you must serve
                    in person and not resign that duty to others, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>but our army must be a national force, equipped from the resources I have named,
                    so that you may be well provided for the performance of your task, and that we
                    may have no repetition of what usually happens now, when you are always bringing
                    your generals to trial and the net result of your exertions is the announcement
                    that “So-and-so, the son of So-and-so, has impeached So-and-so.” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>But what is to be the result for you? In the first place, that your allies may be
                    kept loyal, not by maintaining garrisons among them, but by making their
                    interests identical with yours; next, that our generals may not lead mercenaries
                    to the plunder of our allies without even coming in sight of the enemy, so that
                    the profit is all their own, while the State at large incurs the hatred and the
                    abuse, but that they may have their own citizens at their back, and may so deal
                    with our enemies as they now deal with our friends.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>But apart from this, many operations demand your actual presence, and beside the
                    advantage of using a national force in a national quarrel, this is necessary on
                    every other ground. For if you were content to let things slide and not worry
                    about the state of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, it would be
                    another matter.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>But, as it is, you claim to take the lead and to determine the rights of other
                    states; yet neither in the past nor today have you furnished a sufficient force
                    to superintend and secure this claim. On the contrary, it was when you stood
                    utterly aloof and indifferent that the democracies of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> and of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> were destroyed. “Yes, but <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> was our enemy,” you may say. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>But you should consider, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, that our hostility towards oligarchies, purely on the
                    ground of principle, is stronger than our hostility towards democracies on any
                    grounds whatever. But to return to my point. My view is that you must be brought
                    under a system, and there must be a uniform scheme for receiving public money
                    and for performing necessary services. I have addressed you before on this
                    subject and have described the method of organizing you, whether you serve in
                    the infantry or the cavalry or in other ways, and also how ample provision may
                    be ensured for all alike.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>I will tell you without any concealment what has caused me most disappointment.
                    It is that though the many reforms proposed were all of them important and
                    honorable, no one remembers any of them, but everyone remembers the two
                        obols.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The charge for admission to the
                        theater defrayed by the State.</note> Yet these can never be worth more than
                    two obols, but the other reforms, together with those that I proposed, are worth
                    all the wealth of the Great King—that a city, so well provided with infantry,
                    triremes, cavalry, and revenues, should be duly organized and equipped.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>Why then, you may ask, do I choose the present time for these remarks? Because I
                    think that, as the principle that all citizens should serve for pay is
                    displeasing to some people, and yet the advantage of organization and equipment
                    is approved by all, you ought to begin the business at this point, giving
                    everyone a chance of stating his views on the subject. For the case stands thus:
                    if you are convinced that now is the opportunity for these reforms, all things
                    will be ready when the need of them arrives, but if you pass over the
                    opportunity as unsuitable, then, just when you want to use them, you will be
                    compelled to begin your preparations. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>It has been before now remarked, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, by some speaker—not one of the great body of citizens,
                    but one of those who are likely to have a fit if these reforms are carried
                    out—“What good have we ever got from the speeches of Demosthenes? He comes
                    forward, whenever he thinks well, fills our ears with phrases, denounces our
                    present state, extols our ancestors, and then descends from the platform after
                    raising our hopes and inflating our pride.” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>But if I could only induce you to accept any of my proposals, I think that I
                    should confer such benefits on the State that if I tried to describe them now,
                    many of you would disbelieve them, as being too good to be true. And yet even
                    this too I consider no mean benefit, if I accustom you to listen to the best
                    advice. For he who would benefit the State, Athenians, must first purge your
                    ears, for they have been poisoned; so many lies have you been accustomed to
                    hear—anything, in fact, rather than the best advice. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>Let me give you an instance, and let no one interrupt me till I have finished my
                    story. You know that a day or two ago the treasury of the Parthenon<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The chamber at the back of the cella of the
                        Parthenon was used as a treasury.</note> was broken into. So the speakers in
                    the Assembly, one and all, cried that the democracy was overthrown, that the
                    laws were null and void, and so on. And yet, Athenians, though the culprits—mark
                    whether my words are true—deserved death, it is not through them that the
                    democracy is endangered. Again, a few oars were stolen. “Scourge the thieves
                    torture them,” cried the orators; “the democracy is in danger.” But what is my
                    opinion I say, like the others, that the thief deserves death, but not that the
                    democracy is endangered by such means.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>The real danger to democracy no one is bold enough to name; but I will name it.
                    It is in danger when you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, are wrongly led, when in spite of your numbers you are
                    helpless, unarmed, unorganized and at variance, when no general or anyone else
                    pays any heed to your resolutions, when no one cares to tell you the truth or
                    set you right, when no one makes an effort to remedy this state of things. And
                    that is what always happens now.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>Yes, by heavens, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and
                    there are other phrases, false and injurious to the State, that have passed into
                    your common speech, such as “In the law-courts lies your salvation,” and “It is
                    the ballot-box that must save the State.” I know that these courts are sovereign
                    to uphold the rights of citizen against citizen, but it is by arms that you must
                    conquer the enemy, and upon arms depends the safety of the State. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>For resolutions will not give your men victory in battle, but those who with the
                    help of arms conquer the enemy shall win for you power and security to pass
                    resolutions and to do what you will. For in the field you ought to be terrible,
                    but in the courts sympathetic. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>If my speeches seem to be greater than my own worth, that is itself a virtue in
                    them. For a speech, if it is to be delivered on behalf of this great city and
                    our wide interests, ought always to appear greater than the individual who
                    utters it; it ought to approximate to your reputation, not to the reputation of
                    the speaker. But none of the men whom you delight to honor speaks like that, and
                    I will tell you what their excuse is.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>Men who aim at office and at official rank go to and fro cringing to the favours
                    of the electorate; each one's ambition is to join the sacred ranks of the
                    generals, not to do a man's work. If anyone is really capable of undertaking a
                    job, he thinks that by exploiting the reputation and renown of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, profiting by the absence of
                    opposition, holding out hopes to you and nothing but hopes, he will be sole
                    inheritor of your advantages—and so he is; but if you act as your own agents in
                    every case, he will only have his equal share with the rest, both in the labours
                    and also in their results.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>The politicians, absorbed in their profession, neglect to devise the best policy
                    for you and have joined the ranks of the office-seekers; and you conduct your
                    party-politics as you used to conduct your tax-paying—by syndicates.<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">See <bibl n="Dem. 2.29">Dem. 2.29</bibl>.</note>
                    There is an orator for chairman, with a general under him, and three hundred to
                    do the shouting. The rest of you are attached now to one party and now to
                    another. Hence all that you gain is that So-and-so has a public statue and
                    So-and-so makes his fortune—just one or two men profiting at the expense of the
                    State. The rest of you are idle witnesses of their prosperity, surrendering to
                    them, for the sake of an easy life from day to day, the great and glorious
                    prosperity which is yours by inheritance. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>Yet consider how things were managed in the days of your ancestors, for you need
                    not go abroad for examples to teach you your duty. Take Themistocles, who was
                    your general in the sea-fight at <placeName key="tgn,7002340"
                        >Salamis</placeName>, and Miltiades, who commanded at Marathon, and many
                    more whose good services were far greater than those of our present generals:
                    verily our ancestors put up no bronze statues to them, but rewarded them as men
                    in no way superior to themselves.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>For truly, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, they never
                    robbed themselves of any of their achievements, nor would anyone dream of
                    speaking of Themistocles' fight at <placeName key="tgn,7002340"
                        >Salamis</placeName>, but of the Athenians' fight, nor of Miltiades' battle
                    at Marathon, but of the Athenians' battle. But now we often hear it said that
                    Timotheus took <placeName key="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName>, that Iphicrates
                    cut up the Spartan detachment, or that Chabrias won the sea-fight off <placeName
                        key="tgn,7012053">Naxos</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In
                        376, 390,and 376 respectively.</note> For you seem to waive your own right
                    to these successes by the extravagant honors which you have bestowed on each of
                    these officers. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>Rewards to citizens, rightly thus granted by our ancestors, are wrongly granted
                    by you. But how about foreigners? When Meno of <placeName key="tgn,7010797"
                        >Pharsalus</placeName> gave twelve talents of silver towards the war at
                        <placeName key="perseus,Eion">Eion</placeName> near <placeName
                        key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName><note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">Presumably in 424, but Themistocles does not mention it. The
                        historical examples here are borrowed from <bibl n="Dem. 23">Dem.
                        23</bibl></note> and supported us with two hundred cavalry of his own
                    vassals, our ancestors did not vote him the citizenship, but only gave him
                    immunity from taxes. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>On an earlier occasion, when Perdiccas,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"
                        >According to Herodotus, it was the Thracians, not the Macedonians, who
                        harassed the retreating Persians, and the king of <placeName
                            key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> was Alexander, the father of
                        Perdiccas.</note> who was king of <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
                        >Macedonia</placeName> at the time of the Persian invasions, destroyed the
                    barbarians who were retreating after their defeat at <placeName
                        key="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName> and so completed the discomfiture
                    of the Great King, they did not vote him the citizenship, but only gave him
                    immunity from taxes; because, I presume, they regarded their own country as
                    great, glorious, and venerable, and as something greater than any service
                    rendered. But now, Athenians, you make citizens of the scum of mankind, menial
                    sons of menial fathers, charging a price for it as for any other commodity. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>You have got into the habit of acting thus, not because in ability you are
                    inferior to your ancestors, but because it was second nature with them to have a
                    high opinion of themselves, while you, Athenians, have lost that virtue. You
                    cannot, I suppose, have a proud and chivalrous spirit, if your conduct is mean
                    and paltry, any more than your spirit can be mean and humble, if your conduct is
                    honorable and glorious; for whatever a man's pursuits are, such must be his
                    spirit. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>But reflect on what might be named as the outstanding achievements of your
                    ancestors and of yourselves, if haply the comparison may yet enable you to
                    become your own masters. For five and forty years<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">Between the Persian and Peloponnesian wars.</note> they
                    commanded the willing obedience of the Greeks; more than ten thousand talents
                    did they accumulate in our Acropolis; many honorable trophies for victories on
                    sea and on land did they erect, in which even yet we take a pride. Yet remember
                    that they erected them, not that we might wonder as we gaze at them, but that we
                    might also imitate the virtues of the dedicators.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>Thus did our ancestors; but as for us, who have gained, as you all see, a clear
                    field, consider whether we can match them. Have we not wasted more than fifteen
                    hundred talents on the needy communities of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName>?<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">No one knows to what
                        this refers; but the passage is only a parody of the <title>Third
                            Olynthiac.</title></note> Have we not squandered our private estates,
                    our public funds, and the contributions of our allies? Have not the allies
                    gained in war been lost in the peace?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>But, it may be said, in these respects alone things were better then than now,
                    but in other respects worse. Far from it; but let us examine any instance you
                    please. The buildings which they left behind them to adorn our city—temples,
                    harbors, and their accessories—were so great and so fair that we who come after
                    must despair of ever surpassing them; the Propylaea yonder, the docks, the
                    porticoes and the rest, with which they beautified the city that they have
                    bequeathed to us.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>But the private houses of those who rose to power were so modest and so in
                    accordance with the style of our constitution that the homes of their famous
                    men, of Themistocles and Cimon and Aristides, as any of you can see that knows
                    them, are not a whit more splendid than those of their neighbors.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>But today, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, while our
                    public works are confined to the provision of roads and fountains, whitewash and
                    balderdash (and I blame, not those who introduced these improvements—far from
                    it!—but you, if you imagine that these are all that is required of you), private
                    individuals, who control any of the State-funds, have some of them reared
                    private houses, not merely finer than the majority, but more stately than our
                    public edifices, and others have purchased and cultivated estates more vast than
                    they ever dreamed of before. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="31">
                <p>The cause of all this change is that then the people controlled and dispensed
                    everything, and the rest were well content to accept at their hand honor and
                    authority and reward; but now, on the contrary, the politicians hold the
                    purse-strings and manage everything, while the people are in the position of
                    lackeys and hangers-on, and you are content to accept whatever your masters dole
                    out to you.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="32">
                <p>Such, in consequence, is the state of our public affairs that if anyone read out
                    your resolutions and then went on to describe your performances, not a soul
                    would believe that the same men were responsible for the one and for the other.
                    Take for instance the decrees that you passed against the accursed
                        Megarians,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Neither this nor the following
                        allusion can be determined with certainty.</note> when they appropriated the
                    sacred demesne, that you should march out and prevent it and forbid it; in
                    favour of the Phliasians, when they were exiled the other day, that you should
                    help them and not give them up to their murderers, and should call for
                    volunteers from the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="33">
                <p>That, Athenians, was all very noble and right and worthy of our city; but the
                    resultant action was simply of no account. So your hostility is expressed in
                    your decrees, but action is beyond your control. Your decrees accord with the
                    traditions of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, but your
                    powers bear no relation to your decrees. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="34">
                <p>I, however, would advise you—do not be angry with me—either to humble yourselves
                    and be content to mind your own affairs, or else to get ready a more powerful
                    force. If I felt sure that you were Siphnians or Cythnians<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb"><placeName key="tgn,7011054">Siphnos</placeName> and Cythnos are
                        two of the <placeName key="tgn,7011270">Cyclades</placeName>, S.E. of
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Perhaps the speaker
                        remembered the retort of Themistocles to the man of Seriphos (<bibl
                            n="Plut. Them. 18">Plut. Them. 18</bibl>).</note> or people of that
                    sort, I should counsel you to be less proud, but since you are Athenians, I urge
                    you to get your force ready. For it would be a disgrace, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, a disgrace to desert that post of
                    honor which your ancestors bequeathed to you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="35">
                <p>But besides it is no longer in your power, even if you wished it, to hold aloof
                    from Greek affairs. For you have many exploits to your credit from the earliest
                    times, and it would be disgraceful to abandon the friends you have, while it is
                    impossible to trust your enemies and allow them to grow powerful. In short, you
                    stand in the same position as your statesmen stand to you—they cannot retire
                    when they would; for you are definitely involved in the politics of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="36">
                <p>This, Athenians, is the sum of all that I have said. Your orators never make you
                    either bad men or good, but you make them whichever you choose; for it is not
                    you that aim at what they wish for, but they who aim at whatever they think you
                    desire. You therefore must start with a noble ambition and all will be well, for
                    then no orator will give you base counsel, or else he will gain nothing by it,
                    having no one to take him at his word.</p>
            </div>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
