<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Goddesse of Surrye</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1925</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianhar04luciuoft/page/338/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202129?urlappend=%3Bseq=346">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.4.p.339"/>
<head>The Goddesse of Surrye<note xml:lang="eng"><p>
An account of the worship of "Juno” (Atargatis) at
Hieropolis in Syria, done, not in Lucian’s customary Attic
Greek, but in the Ionic dialect, after the manner of Herodotus, which Lucian counterfeits so cleverly and parodies so
slyly that many have been unwilling to recognize him as the
author.</p>
<p>It would be most unfair to Lucian to turn this tale into
contemporary English. In order to have the same effect
that it had in his own day, and to be really intelligible, it
must seem to come from the lips of an ancient traveller.
The version here offered seeks to secure that effect through
mimicry of Sir John Mandeville. It is true that Herodotus
was better known in Lucian’s time than Mandeville is
known now, and his language seemed less remote. In every
other respect, however—in his limited vocabulary, in his
simple style, and in his point of view—Mandeville provides
a mask uniquely adapted to the part—if only its wearer
does not fall down in it and break it.</p>
<p>In the notes, which are more extensive than usual because
Lucian’s topic here is outside the ordinary classical range,
several books which have been of particular service are cited
by abbreviated titles: E. Schrader, Die Keilinschriften und
das Alte Testament, pt. ii, Religion und Sprache, 3rd ed.,
1903, by H. Zimmern (Schrader-Zimmern) ; Stanley A. Cook,
Religion of Ancient Palestine, etc., London, 1908 (Cook) ; W. W.
Graf Baudissin, Adonis und Esmun, Leipzig, 1911 (Baudissin),
and his Studien zur Semitischen Religionsgeschichte, 1878
(Studien) ; Sir J. G. Frazer, Adonis, Attis, Osiris, in Golden
Bough, pt iv, London, 1919 (Frazer), and his Folklore in the
id Testament, London, 1919 (Folklore); Albert T. Clay,
A Hebrew Deluge Story, etc, New Haven1921 (Clay).
Those who wish to see the piece in modern English may be
referred to the version by fa A. Strong (London, 1913).
This is supplied with an introduction and notes by J. E,
Garstang, whose commentary will be found to supplement
this in many points, especially in the matter of Hittite
parallels.</p></note></head>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

In Surrye, not fer fro the Ryvere Eufrate, is a
Cytee that Holy highte and holy is in sothe, for it
is of Iuno Assurien.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.339.n.1"><p>Hierapolis, or better, in accordance with the coins, Hieropolis. It is N.W. of Aleppo, on the main road into Mesopotamia, 15 Roman miles from the crossing of the Euphrates, and by road about 116 Roman miles from Lucian’s birthplace, Samosata. Its Syrian name was Makog, (properly Manbog, i.e. “spring,” according to Baudissin, Studien, ii, 159), in Greek, Bambyce. 1t was dubbed Hieropolis in the time of Seleucus Nicator (Ael. V.H. 12, 2), but the old name persisted (Manbij; le Strange, Palestine under the Moslems, p 500) and still attaches to the ruins, on which see Hogarth, Annual of the British School at Athens, 1907-8, p. 186 sqq ; Cumont, Beudes Syriennes, p. 22 sqq., p. 35 sgq. Lucian does not identify the city with “ancient Ninus,” as do Philostratus and Ammianus. </p></note> Yit I wene that the cyteene
hadde not this name atte firste, whan that it was
founded, but of olden tyme it was other, and after,”
whan here servys of the Goddesse wex gret, it was their
chaunged to this. Touching this cytee I purpos
me to seyn alle that is in it, and I schalle speke of
the customes that thei folwen in here rytes, and the
feste dayes that thei kepen, and the sacrifises that
thei perfourmen. And I schalle reherce alle the
tales that men tellen of hem that establisschede the
holy place, and how that the temple was bylded.
And I that write am Assurien,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.339.n.2"><p>Confusion between Assyrian and Syrian is not peculiar to this piece nor to Lucian. It goes back to Herodotus, who says that “Syrian” is the Greek equivalent of the barbarian “Assyrian” (7,63 ; see Macan’s note, and cf. 140). </p></note> and of that that I
devyse you, some partie saughe I with mine owne
eyen, and some partie I lerned be informacioun fro _
the prestes, that is to seyn, tho thynges that I
descryve that weren beforn min owne tyme.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
Of alle peples whereof wee knowen, Egyptyens
weren firste, as men seyn, for to taken conceyte of




<pb n="v.4.p.341"/>

Goddes, and to stablisschen holy places and closes,
and to apoynten feste dayes. And thei firste knewen
holy names and maden holy tales. But no long
tyme after, Assuryens herden rumour and speche
of Egyptyens as touching to goddes, and rereden
seyntuaryes and temples, in the whiche thei lette
putten ymages and setten symulacres.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.341.n.1"><p>In Astrology, Lucian similarly credits the Egyptians with priority over the Chaldaeans in the study of the stars. In th cases his view, surprising in a Syrian, was the common one of his time, to be found, for instance, in Diodorus </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
But auncientlye amonges Egyptyens weren temples withouten symulacres. And in Surrye ben temples almost
als olde as tho in Egypte, of the whiche I have seen
the moste, and namely the temple of Hercules in
Tyre, not that Hercules that Grekes preysen in here
songes, but that oon wherof I speke is moche elder,
and is Tyres patroun.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.341.n.2"><p>The god was Melkart. Herodotus was told by the priests there that the cult was established when the city was founded, and was then (ca. 430 B.c.) 2,300 years old (Herod. 2, 44). </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

In Phenicye is another grete temple that men of
Sidon kepen. Thei seyn, it is of Astarte, and
Astarte, I trowe, is Luna the Mone.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.341.n.3"><p>The Emperor Elagabalus, being the Sun, brought — Astarte the Moon from Phoenicia and wedded her (Herodian 5, 6, 3-5). But she was not originally or at any time primarily the moon; and in Babylonia, as Ishtar, she had for her emblem a star, the planet Venus (Baudissin, 19). Clay (p. 47) believes that the name Ashera, Ashirta, Ishtar, is that of a mortal woman, an early queen of Hallab (Aleppo). </p></note> But oon of
the prestes tolde me, it belongeth to Europe, Cadmus
suster. Sche was Agenor the Kinges daughter ;
and after that sche vanisched, Phenicyens yafen
hir that temple for worschipe and maden a storie
of hir, that sithe sche was fair, love coveytede hir,
and transformed his lyknesse in to a bole, and than
ravissched hir awey and bar hir on his bac to Crete.
That same storie I herde of othere Phenicyens also ;





<pb n="v.4.p.343"/>

and the moneye that Sidonyes usen hath Europe
sittynge on the bole that is Iove.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.343.n.1"><p>The coins are described in Head, Historia Nummorum, 2nd ed., pp. 797 sg. The temple itself contained, in later days at least, a painting of the Europa episode (Achilles Tatius 1, 1). The story was also localized at Tyre, where the house of Agenor and the bower of Europa were shown (Arrian, Anab. 2, 24, 2; Nonnus, Dionys. 40, 353 sqq.) and where in the eighth century (Malalas, p. 31) the people still mourned the abduction in a feast called the ak) ayer, The name Europa is considered Greek ; whether this particular myth is Cretan or Phoenician in origin the evidence does not seem sufficient to determine. </p></note> Natheles wille
thei not avowen that the temple is of Europe.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
And Phenicyens han an other maner servys, not
Assuryen but Egyptyen, that cam from Elyople into
Phenicye. I have not seen it, but it also is gret and
auncien.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.343.n.2"><p>This cult was at Heliopolis (Baalbek). The god, who appears to have been originally Hadad but to have undergone syncrisis with the sun-god and with the Syrian ‘ “Apollo,” was worshipped far and wide as Jupiter Heliopolitanus. The cult image, says Macrobius (Saturn. 1, 23, 10) came from Heliopolis in Egypt by way of Assyria. The ambiguity of Lucian’s Greek (for fepdy suggests “holy place”) seems meant to convey the jocose implication that the magnificent new temple, built by Antoninus Pius, had been transported thither without human hands, </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
But I saughe in Byblos a gret temple of Venus of
Byblos, wherin thei perfourmen cerimonyes in mynde
of Adoon; and I lernede tho cerimonyes.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.343.n.3"><p>To natives of Byblos their goddess was just Baalat (Mistress), and to other Semites Baalat Gebal (Mistress of Byblos) ; in Syriac and Greek Baltis or Beltis is used as if it were her name. So too Adonis to them was simply Adon (Lord); an early name, or perhaps epithet, was Kliun (Philo of Byblos; cf. Baudissin, p. 76, Meyer, Gesch., p. 395). It was only late, if at all, that fe was there identified with Tammuz, upon whom, as fourth king of Erech, see Clay, pp. 44 sgg. The temple, which contained a baetylic stone, is represented on coins (Babelon, Perses Achéménides, p. 200, and pl. xxvii, 1] and 12), </p></note> Thei
seyn that the dede that was don to Adoon be the
bore befell in here londe, and for memorie of that
myschaunce everyche yeer thei beten here brestes
and sorwen and perfourmen tho cerimonyes, makynge gret doel thorgh that contree. And whan mournthe betynge and the wepynge is atte ende, first thei
maken offringes to Adoon, as though he were ded;
and than, on the morwe, thei fablen that he is quick,
and fecchen him forth in to the eyr, and lette air





<pb n="v.4.p.345"/>

schaven here hedes as don Egyptyens whan that
Apis is ded.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.345.n.1"><p>Lucian abridges his account of the rites because they were familiar. I see no reason to suppose that they differed essentially from the Alexandrian rites as described by Theocritus (15 end). From him we learn that Adonis comes to life for but a day, during which he is couched with the goddess in the temple. Next morning the women carry him to the sea-shore, and (cf. scholion) commit him to the waves. Lucian’s phrase és tty hépa xéumovet, which has been curiously interpreted, is to my mind equivalent to #£w oloedues in Theocritus, and the usual éxxoulCovar. </p></note> And alle wommen that wole not lette
schaven hem, thei payen this penance, that upon
o day thei profren hem for achat of here beautee ;
but the merkat is open to straungers alle only, and
the huyr becometh an offring to Venus.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.345.n.2"><p>See Frazer i, 36 sqg., and the comment of How and Wells on Herodotus 1, 199. Note also the apocryphal Epistle of Jeremiah, 42; and on the “hire,” Deuteronomy 23, 18. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
Natheles, ther ben somme men of Byblos that
seyn Osiris of Egypte lyeth enterred amonges hem,
and the doel and the cerimonyes ben alle made in
mynde of Osiris in stede of Adoon.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.345.n.3"><p>Byblos was known to the Egyptians from the time of the Old Kingdom, and her goddess impressed them deeply. She was identified with Hathor at least as early as the Middle Kingdom, and her story contributed to the shaping of the Isis-Osiris myth. When the coffin of Osiris was thrown into the Nile by Typhon, it drifted out to sea, and so to Byblos, where Isis sought and found it (Plutarch, Zsis and Osiris, c. 13 sgg.; cf. Frazer, ii. 9 sqg., 12, 127; Baudissin, pp. 193 sqq. ). </p></note> And I schalle
seye you the cause whi this semeth hem trewe.
Eech yeer an heed cometh from Egypte to Byblos, heaa
that passeth the see betwene in seven iorneyes, and the
windes dryven it, be governaunce of the Goddes,
and it torneth not asyde in no wyse but cometh all
only to Byblos. And this is hoolyche merveylle. whoty
It befalleth everyche yere, and befel that tyme that
I was in Byblos, and I saughe the heed, that is of
Byblos.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.345.n.4"><p>The pun signifies that the head was of papyrus, made, no doubt, of a sort of papier m4ché, as in a mummy-case. In the commentary of Cyril on Isaiah 18 (Migne 70, 441) we learn, instead, of an earthen pot that contained a letter from the women of Alexandria to those of Byblos, saying that Aphrodite had found Adonis. There may be something in the tale of its drift, for the Nile current sets over to the Phoenician shore, and it is Nile mud that silts up Phoenician harbours (cf. H. Guthe, Paldstina, p. 27). </p></note>






<pb n="v.4.p.347"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
And in the londe of Byblos is arf other merveylle,
a Ryvere goynge out of the Mount Libanon in to the
See, the which is cleped Adoon. Everyche yeer it
is bebledde and leseth his kyndely hewe, and whan natural
it falleth in to the See, it maketh mochel therof
rede; and so it betokneth the doel to hem of
Byblos.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.347.n.1"><p>The Adonis is the present Nahr Ibrahim, a short distance S. of Byblos, “I have crossed it on Easter day when it was turbid and ruddy with the rich red sandstone soil from Lebanon” (C. R. Conder, Palestine, p. 206; cf. Frazer i, 225). A similar discoloration of certain unnamed rivers and springs is implied in the tale of Philo of Byblos that Uranus was mutilated by Cronus at a certain place in the interior near springs and rivers, that his blood flowed into them, and that the place was still pointed out (Miiller, Fr. Hist. Graec., iii, p. 568). Epiphanius (adv. Haeres. 51, 30) bears personal witness that at the exact day and hour of the miracle of Cana the water of a spring at Cibyra in Caria used to turn into wine, and on the word of his brothers that the same was true of the river of Gerasa in Arabia. He does not tell us who is his warrant in the case of the Nile, but observes that that is why the natives bottle and set away Nile-water on a certain date. See also Pausanias 4, 35, 9, and Frazer’s note. </p></note> For they seyn that in tho dayes Adoon
is ywounded up Libanon, and his blod that cometh
into the water chaungeth the ryvere and yeveth the
streme his name. Thus seyn lewed folk. But I
trowe that a man of Byblos spak sothe that devysed
me an other cause of the chaunge, seyinge: “The
Flom Adoon, o straunger, renneth thorgh Libanon,
and erthe of Libanon is right broun. Therfore whan
roughe windes that arysen in tho dayes beren the
erthe to the ryvere, the erthe, that is ful rody,
maketh him blody. So of this chaunge nys not the
blod, as they seyn, the resoun, but the lond.” He
of Byblos devysed me thus; but and al it so be that
he spak trewely, yit to me it semeth passing
merveyllous that the wind aryseth at the righte
tyme.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
Also, I went up on Libanon fro Byblos, oon
iorneye, be cause I lernede that ther was an old



<pb n="v.4.p.349"/>

seyntuarye of Venus that Cinyras founded; and I
saughe the temple, and it was old.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.349.n.1"><p>At Aphaea, between Byblos and Baalbek, at the head of the Adonis, where Adon was buried and Baalat died of grief. Down to the fifth century a bright light appearing in the sky near the temple summoned the worshippers at set times, and an artificial pond gave omens; offerings were thrown into it, which sank if the goddess was favourable or floated if she was adverse (Zosimus i, 58; cf. Socrates 1, 18). The site is eloquently described by Frazer, i, 28, and pictured in Perrot-Chipiez, Hist. de l’Art iii, fig. 18, opposite p. 56 ; for the rock-sculptures in the neighbourhood, to one of which the description of the goddess in Macrobius (Saturn. 1, 21, 5) refers, see Baudissin, p. 78 and pls. i-iii, and for the ruins of the temple, destroyed under Constantine but possibly rebuilt under Talia Rouvier, Bulletin Archéologique, 1900, 169 sqq. Lucian’s amusing reticence is by way of parody on Herodotus, |’ and derives its point from the fact that his reader, knowing: the reputation of the place (Euseb. Vit. Constant. 3, 55), is’ all agog to hear about it. </p></note>
Thise ben the olde and grete seyntuaryes in
Surrye.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
But of hem alle, as I wene, is non gretter
than tho in the Holy Cytee, ne non other temple
mo blessed, ne non other lond holier. Costevouse costly
werkes ben therinne, and aunciene offringes, and
manye merveylles, and symulacres in lyknesse of
goddes. Also, the goddes ben apertely reveled unto
hem; for here symulacres sweten and meven and
prophecyen, and ofte tymes hath ben schowtynge
in the temple whan the holy place was under lokke,
and many han herde. Certes, in richesse it is first
amonges alle that I knowe; for thider cometh moche
tresor from Arabye and Phenicye and Babiloyne,
and moche fro Cappadocye, and som Cilicyens
bryngen, and som Assuryens. And I saughe what
hath ben prively put up in the temple, many robes
and other thinges that have ben chosen out as
silver outher gold. And of festes and solempnytees
noon other folk in the world hath apoynted so
many.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

Whan I asked how many yeres the seyntuarye
hadde dured, and who thei wenden that here supposed
Goddesse were, manye stories weren tolde, both



<pb n="v.4.p.351"/>

prestes lore and lewede folkes, and verraye fables;
and some weren outlandissche, but othere somme
acordeden to hem of Grece. Alle thise seyinges
schalle reherce, but I beleve hem not in no kynde.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
The more partie seyn, Deucalioun, the Scythe,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.351.n.1"><p>Deucalion in the réle of a Scythian is odd. Hence Buttmann, rightly recognising that the tale is close akin to the Babylonian flood-story, proposed the reading Σισύθεα, considering Sisythes a possible variant of the name that in Berossus is Xisouthros. This is tempting, and has been widely accepted ; but the mistake, if there be one, is quite as likely to be due to Lucian or to his informant as to a scribe. </p></note>
founded the seyntuarye—that Deucalioun in the
tyme thereof the grete Flode befel. Of Deucalioun
Ihave herd a tale amonges Grekes, that thei tellen
in mynde of him; and the storie is of this maner
kynde.</p>

<p>
This generacioun, the men of now a dayes, nas not
the firste, but that firste generacioun al perissched,
and thise ben of the seconde generacioun that cam
of Deucalioun and multiplyed eftsones. Of tho
firste men, thei seyn that thei were right felonouse
and didde wikkede dedis, for thei ne kepten not non
othes, ne herberweden no straungers, ne receyveden harno fugityves; and for that skylle the grete tribu- cause
lacioun cam upon hem. Anon the erthe sent forthe
moche water and grete reynes were made and the
ryveres flowede gretli and the see wex wondur high,
in to tyme that alle thinges weren chaunged to water
and alle men weren dede, outtaken Deucalioun that
was laft unto the seconde generacioun for his gode
conseil and his gode werkes. And his deliveraunce
cam in this wyse. In to a gret arke that he hadde he
putte his children and his wyves, and thanne entrede,
and at entrynge ther camen to him swyn and hors
and lyouns kynd and serpentes and alle bestes that



<pb n="v.4.p.353"/>

lyven on erthe, two and two. And he resceyvede as
hem alle, and thei diden him non harm, but betwene
hem was great charitee fro the goddes, and in oon;
arke thei alle seyleden whyl the water prevayled.
So seyn Grekes of Deucalioun.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.353.n.1"><p>In spite of Lucian’s repeated assurance, the story is more Semitic than Greek. On the West Semitic origin of the flood-story, see Clay, where also a translation of the Babylonian tale according to Berossus may be found (p. 82 sq.). </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
But of that that sewede, men of the Holy Cytee sotiowed
tellen a tale that is worthy of gret merveylle, how
that in here londe opnede a huge hole and resceyvede
alle the water; and whan this happed, Deucalioun
leet maken awteres and leet bylden over the hole a atars
temple halowed to Iuno.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.353.n.2"><p>At Gezer, not far from Jerusalem, “there is a living tradition that the waters of the flood burst forth in the neighbourhood” (Cook, p. 107). Likewise at Athens, within the enclosure of Olympian Zeus, in the precinct of Olympian Earth: ‘here the ground is cloven to a cubit’s width; and they say that after the deluge which happened in Deucalion’s time the water ran away down this cleft. Every year they throw into it wheaten meal kneaded with honey” (Pausanias 1, 18, 7, Frazer’s translation). </p></note> I saughe the hole, that is
benethe the temple, a right lityl oon. If whilom it
was gret and now is become suche as it is, I wot
neer, but that I saughe is smal.</p>

<p>
In tokene of that storie thei don thus. Twyes
eech yeer water cometh fro the See in to the temple.
And not prestes only bryngen it, but al Surrye and
Arabye; and fro beyonden Eufrate gon manye men
to the See and bryngen alle watre, that anon thei
scheden out in the temple, and thanne it goth
adoun in to that hole; and al be it that the hole is
smal, natheles it taketh inne gret plentee of water.
And in doynge thus thei seyn that Deucalioun made
suche ordeynaunce for the seyntuarye in memorie of
that tribulacioun and that benefice.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.353.n.3"><p>Further details of this rite are given in ¢. 48. Frazer's note on Pausanias l.c. compares an Athenian Hydrophoria connected with the memory of the flood; also the annual water-pouring in the Temple at Jerusalem on the Feast of Tabernacles. The performance was not simply commemorative; the offering at Athens of meal and honey was chthonic, and so was the water-pouring there (Cleidemus in Athenaeus 5, p. 410a). At Hieropolis the object was to quell evil spirits, according to Melito. “But touching Nebo, which is in Mabug, why should I write to you; for lo! all the priests which are in Mabug know that it is the image of Orpheus, a Thracian Magus. And Hadran (i.e. Hadaranes, a double of Hadad) is the image of Zaradusht, a Persian Magus, because both of these Magi practised Magism to a well which is in a wood in Mabug, in which was an unclean spirit, and it committed violence and attacked the passage of every one who was passing by in all that place in which now the fortress of Mabug is located; and these same Magi charged Simi, the daughter of Hadad (cf. c. 33), that she should draw water froin the sea, and cast it into the well, in order that the spirits should not come up,” etc. (Cureton, Spicil, Syr. 44 sq.) Early modern travellers have seen seawater poured into a brook (Baudissin, Studien, ii, p. 181), and it is perhaps significant that nowadays the Jans are angry if water is spilled on the hearth (Baldensperger, Jmmovable East, p. 85). Cf. Baudissin, p. 437, 3. </p></note> a





<pb n="v.4.p.355"/>

Now that is the olde aunciene storie amonges
hem touching to the temple.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
But othere men ,
trowen that Semiramys of Babyloyne, of the which
sothely ben manye werkes in Asye, sche made this
foundacioun, and not for Iuno but for hir owne
Moder, that hadde to name Derketoun.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.355.n.1"><p>A legend of Ascalon made Semiramis the daughter of Derceto by a Syrian youth with whom Aphrodite (i.¢. Astarte) made Derceto fall in love. In her grief and shame, Derceto destroyed the youth, exposed the daughter, and herself leaped into a pool and was turned into a fish. Semiramis was miraculously attended by doves until she was discovered and handed over to Simmas, a royal overseer ; eventually she married Ninus (Ctesias, quoted by Diodorus Siculus 2, 4). She was intimately connected with temple traditions at Hieropolis : two statues of her stood near the temple, with one of which the story was connected that she had once tried to usurp the place of the goddess (cc. 39, 40), and some thought that the “token” of c. 33 represented her. </p></note>. And I
beheld the schap of Derketoun in Phenicye, a
straunge merveylle, halfundel womman, but the
tothere half, wel fro thighes to feet, streccheth out
in a fissches tayl.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.355.n.2"><p>Cook, p. 30 sg. speaks of “various rude and almost shapeless objects of bronze which have been interpreted, thanks to a more realistic specimen from the Judaean Tell Zakariya, as models of an amphibious creature with human head and the tail of a fish;”’ and he adds: “a splendid Carthaginian sarcophagus of a priestess (M. Moore, Carthage of the Phoenicians, frontispiece) represents a woman of strange beauty with the lower part of the body so draped as to give it a close resemblance to a fish’s tail.” But in Hellenistic times the goddess was almost always represented in human form. For other stories of her transformation, see W. Robertson Smith, Eng. Hist. Rev., ii (1887), 303 sg. ; Gruppe, Gr. Mythol. p. 1345; for the survival of the belief into modern times, Niéldeke, Zeitschr. der Deutsch. Morgenlind. Gesellsch. 35, 220. </p></note>. But the ymage in the Holy
Cytee is hoolyche woman, and the tokenes of here
seyinge ben not right certeyn. Thei leven fissches
holy thynge, and thei ne touchen fissche never; and




<pb n="v.4.p.357"/>

though of othere foules thei eten alle, the dowve
thei ne eten not, but sche is holy, as thei wenen.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.357.n.1"><p>See cc. 45, 54, with the notes thereon. </p></note>
And thise thinges ben don, thei trowen, be cause of
Derketoun and Semiramys, the oon for that Derketoun hath schap of a fissche, and the tother
because that atte laste Semiramys tornede to a
dowve.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.357.n.2"><p>On the transformation of Semiramis into a dove, see Athenagoras, Legat. pro Christ. 76 (Ctesiae Fragmenta ed. Miiller, p. 17); Diodorus 2, 20, 2. Diodorus (2, 4, 6; cf. Hesychius) says that the name Semiramis is derived from the word for dove in the Syrian dialect. At all events the similarity of the Assyrian word summatu (dove) helps to account for her introduction into these stories (Lehmann- Haupt, Roscher’s Lexikon, s.v. Semiramis, p. 694). </p></note> But to me, that the temple was bylded of
Semiramys peraventure may I graunte; but that it
longeth to Derketoun I ne leve not in no kynde.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.357.n.3"><p>Lucian’s scepticism is unjustified. Pliny (5, 81) and Strabo (16, p. 785) were better informed. Atargatis is the Greek version of ‘Atar-‘ata; Derceto is the Greek version of the abbreviated form Tar-‘ata. See Cumont in Pauly- Wissowa, Realencycl., under Atargatis and Dea Syria. </p></note>
For amonges somme peples of Egypte thei ne eten
not fissche, and that is not-don for no favour to
Derketoun.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.357.n.4"><p>In Astrology, c. 7, Lucian tells why these Egyptians do it; it is because they were especially devoted to the sign Pisces. This may be more than a mere jest ; Cumont says: “Old totems of Semitic tribes or of Egyptian nomes survived in the form of constellations” (Astrology and Religion, p. 116; cf. p. 81). But for the abstaining in Egypt other reasons were given, from Herodotus on (2, 37; cf. Plutarch, Isis and Osiris, cc. 7, 32, 72, and for other references, Frazer, Pausanias iv, p. 154). See also page 398, note 1. </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
Ther is also an other holy storie that I herde from a
wys man, how that the goddesse is Cibella and the
servys founded of Attis. Attis was a Lydien of
kynde, that first leet teche the ceremonyes that
longen to Cibella. And alle rytes that Phrygiens and
Lydiens and Samothracyens perfourmen, tho rytes
lerneden thei of Attis. For whan Cibella gelt him,
he cessed to lede the lyf of a man, but chaunged
to femele schappe, and did on wommenes clothynge,
and goynge to every londe perfourmed ceremonyes
and reherced what betyd him and preysed Cibella
in songes. Ther with alle cam he to Surrye, and for
als moche as the peple beyonden Eufrate resceyvede






<pb n="v.4.p.359"/>

him not, ne his cerimonyes nouther, he founded the
seyntuarye in this place. And for a signe thereof,
the goddesse for the most partie ressembleth Cibella,
for lyouns drawen hir and sche holt a timbre and
bereth tours on hir hede, right as Lydiens formen
Cibella. Also he spak of Galles that ben in the
temple, seyinge that Galles gelden hem and counterfeten Attis not at alle for no worschipe of luno but
for worschipe of Cibella.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.359.n.1"><p>This identification of the Dea Syria with Rhea has been spoken of as a temple-legend. Is it not rather a simple deduction of Lucian’s “wise man,” based upon general resemblance and upon the presence of Galli in both cults? The resemblance, however, was real, and the identification was not unusual ; a striking instance is in Bardesanes, where the Syriac version (Cureton, 31) has Tharatha, the Greek, as quoted by Eusebius, Rhea. It has been revived by modern scholars, notably Meyer, and with good reason ; but whether the “Mother-goddess” is Semitic in origin, as he formerly held, or non-Semitic (Hittite), as he now argues, is still, it seems to me, an open question. See note below on Combabus. </p></note>
</p>

<p>
But after myn avis, al be it that this is wel
semynge, it is not trewe, for I have herde an other
cause whi thei gelden hem that is a gret dele mo to
beleven.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
 Me liketh what men seyn of the seyntuarye
that acorden fulle wel to hem of Grece,that demen the
goddesse Iuno and the seyntuarye mad of Bachus,
Semeles sone. For withouten doubte Bachus cam
to Surrye in that passage in the whiche he wente to
Ethiope. And in the temple ben manye tokenes of
Bachus foundour, as namely foreyne garnements and
precious stones of Ynde and olifauntes hornes, that
Bachus broght from Ethiope. And two yerdes, or
pileres, stont in the entree, passynge highe, on the
whiche is writen this scripture : “I Bachus presentede


<pb n="v.4.p.361"/>

thise yerdes to Iuno my step moder.”<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.361.n.1"><p>Phallic pillars, further described below, cc. 28-29. The inscription is much too pointed to be genuine ; it is a hoax like that in the True Story 1, 7 (vol. i, p. 255). Pillars were an ordinary feature of Semitic “high places,” both of wood (asherim) and of stone (masseboth) ; see Frazer, Folklore, iii, 62 sqq. In the case of the asherim I know of no direct evidence that they were phallic, but the masseboth, many of which still survive, are sometimes clearly of that nature (Cook, 14, 28 ; see also le Strange, Palestine wnder the Moslems, p. 294, for a curious survival of this significance). The pillars at Hieropolis were made of wood, since cleats were nailed to them; they were therefore asherim, and form a further bond between Ashera (Astarte) and Atargatis. Whether originally phallic or not, they were in Lucian’s day themselves used as “high places” ; see below. </p></note> Now to
me this sufficeth, natheles I schalle seye you another
thing that is in the temple, that longeth to ceremonyes of Bachus. Men of Grece formen yerdes
for worschipe of Bachus that beren on hem litylle
men made of wode that han grete membres, the
whiche men thei nempnen Popets.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.361.n.2"><p>See Herodotus 2, 48, on Egyptian puppets (ἀγάλματα νευρόσπαστα). </p></note> And in the
temple ther is this same thing; on the righte syde
sitt a lityl man of brasse that hath a gret membre.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
So seyn thei of the foundours of the holy place.
And now I schalle speke of the temple, wher that it
was sett and who that leet bylden it. Men seyn,
the temple that stont now is not that oon the
whiche was bylded atte firste, but that was beten
doun sithen som tyme, and the temple that stont
now is the werk of Stratonice, wyf to the Kyng
of Assurye.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.361.n.3"><p>Stratonice was daughter of Demetrius Poliorcetes and wife of Seleucus Nicator; she was subsequently surrendered by him to his son Antiochus I, Soter, by a former wife, Apama. The famous tale which follows (in Lucian a pure digression, but quite in the Herodotean manner) is rehearsed at length by Plutarch also (Demetrius 38). Rohde has made it pretty clear that, though possible enough (Galen claimed to have detected hidden love in the same way), as far as Antiochus is concerned it is fiction (Griech. Roman, p. 52.) </p></note></p>

<p>
I trowe, this is thilke Stratonice that hir step
sone lovede, that was betraysed by the phisicyens<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.361.n.4"><p>Erasistratus (Plutarch, l.c.), </p></note>
invencioun, For whan the infortune oppressed him,






<pb n="v.4.p.363"/>

he mighte not susteyne the mysese that semede
him schamful, and so he stille (quietly) felle into syknesse,
and lay withouten ony peyne; and his hewe
chaunged outerly, and his bodye feblede eech
day. But whan the phisicyen saughe that he
was wayk withouten pleyne cause, he iugged that
the syknesse was love. For of derne (secret) love ther
ben manye signes, as waike eyen, voyce, hewe,
teeres. And whan that he perceyved it, he did
thus. With his righte honde he kepte the yonge
mannes herte, and thanne he sent after all tho that
weren in the house. And whan everyche of the
othere entrede, this was in gret ese, but whan his
step moder cam, he chaunged his hewe and swatte
and schoke and his herte stirte (leaped). Thise thinges
scheweden his love to, the phisicyen, that helede
him thus.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>After that he hadde clepede the yonge
mannes fader, that was sor adrad, “This syknesse,”
quod he, “wherof thy child is wayk nis not syknesse
but synne, for verrayly he soffreth of no peyn, but
of love and wodenesse (frenzy). And he coveyteth that
he may not have in no wyse, lovynge my wyf
that I wil not forgon.” So that oon lyde in gyle.
And anon that other besoghte him: “Be thy
conynge and thy phisik, destroie me not my sone ;
for he is not in this cas of his owne wille but hath
the syknesse mawgree himself. Therfore do thou not
thorghe despyt make sorwe in alle the rewme, ne
thou that art phisicyen brynge manslaughtre in to
phisik.” Thus preyde he, al unwar. And_ that
oon answerde: “Thou forthrest wykked dedis,
revynge me from my mariage and destreyninge a
pore leche. What woldestow thiself have don and
he coveytede thy wyf, thou that axest suche bones (boons)

<pb n="v.4.p.365"/>

of me?” Therwith he replyede that he him self
wolde never have ben ialous over his wyf ne grucched (begrudged)
his sone deliveraunce, if so be he hadde coveyted his
step moder; for it was not the lyke infortune to
lese awyfasasone.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.365.n.1"><p>Compare the famous story in Herodotus (3, 119) of the wife of Intaphrenes, who preferred brother to husband and sons. </p></note>_ And whan the phisicien herde
that, “Wherfore than,” quod he, “dostow beseche
me? Parfey, he loveth thy wyf, and alle that I
seyde was fausse!” Than was the fader overcomen, and yold bothe wyf and rewme (realm) to his sone,
and goyinge himself to the contree of Babyloyne leet
make a cytee nyghe Eufrate that was cleped after
his owne name, ther as his dethe befel.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.365.n.2"><p>The known facts are that Seleucus made Antiochus joint-ruler in 293 B.c.; that the marriage of Stratonice to Antiochus may have taken place at that time, but the date is not known; and that in 281, on becoming master of the whole realm of Alexander through the defeat of Lysimachus, he planned to entrust, and perhaps actually did entrust, all Asia to his son, intending himself to assume the throne of Macedonia. But within a few months he was assassinated by Ptolemy Ceraunus near Lysimachia in Thrace. He built many cities named after him; this Seleucia, 15 miles below Baghdad, is generally called “on the Tigris,” but it lay between the two rivers, which at that point are only 25 miles apart, and the canal Naarmalcha, connecting the Euphrates with the Tigris, flowed by it. </p></note> Thus did
the phisicien bothe knowe and hele love.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>

Now, I seye you, why] yit that Stratonice duellede
with her formere housbond, hir mette a dreme how
that Iuno bade hir to bylde the temple for hir in the
Holy Cytee, and if sche sholde not obeye, sche
manaced hir with manye harmes. Atte first, sche
ne took no fors (note) of it ; but after, whan a grete sykness
hent hir, sche told the dreme to hir housbond and
enforced hir to apayen (appease) Iuno, and behight (promised) to bylde
the temple. Anon sche becam hool, and thanne hir
housbond wolde sende hir to the Holy Cytee, and
with hir a gret tresor and a gret hoost, some for to
bylden and other some for here seurtee. Therfore
he sompned oon of his frendes, a right fayr yong man




<pb n="v.4.p.367"/>

that highte Combabe,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.367.n.1"><p>The name Kombabos, which does not occur elsewhere in Greek, has been identified as that of the opponent of Gilgamesh in the Gilgamesh-Epic, Hu(m)-ba-ba (Schrader- Zimmern, p. 570, and note 2), Clay has shown (pp. 49-53) that this name is not Elamite, but Amorite or West Semitic ; he holds that it was borne by a historical personage who lived in a cedar district of the West and humiliated Babylonia at the time of Gilgamesh, about 4000 B.c. However that may be, Kombabos is Humbaba, and in this story, which is the temple-legend, the name of Kombabos is the significant part ; Stratonice has taken the place of an earlier female. I believe her immediate predecessor was Semiramis, from Ammianus Marcellinus, 14, 6, 17, and her general connection with this site; she in her turn probably ousted an earlier Sima or Ata, with whom Kombabos may have been brought into connection through building or rebuilding the temple (cf. Clay, p. 51, note 22). </p></note> and seyde: “For thou art
noble, Daun Combabe, I love thee most of alle mine
frendes, and I preyse thee gretli for thy coninge and
for thy gode wille to me, that thou hast discovered
beforn. And now me  nedeth of grete feyth,
wherfore I wole that thou folwe my wyf, for to
acomplisshe the werke in my name, and to perfourme the sacrifises, and to reule the hoost ; and
whan thou retornest thou schalt gete highe worschipe
fro me.”
Therwith anon Combabe gan preye and beseche
him ful besily that he scholde not send him forth ne
betaken (entrust) him nouther that tresor, that was moche to en:rust
gret for him, ne his wyf, ne the holy werk. For he
was adrad lest that ialousie scholde assayle him
afterwardes as touching to Stratonice, that he moste
lede forthe allone.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>

But sithe the kyng wolde not
herknen in no kynde, he assayde an other requeste,
for to graunte him seven dayes space, and than sende
him forth, whan he hadde don a thing thereof he
hadde most nede. And whan he obteyned this
bone lightely, he wente to his owne house and caste
himself adoun and pleyned right so: ‘Allas wrecche,
what have I to don with this feythe, what have I to
don with this viage, whereof I seighe now the ende ?
I am yong, and schal folwen a fayre womman. This
schalle be gret meschief to me, but if I putte awey



<pb n="v.4.p.369"/>

al cause of evylle ; therfore most I perfourme a gret
dede that schal hele me of alle fere.”
</p>

<p>
Thus he seyde, and thanne he marrede him self ;
and whan he hadde kutte offe his genitours he put
hem into a lityl pot, and bawme with alle, and hony
and othere thinges of swete smelle. Thanne he
selede it with a signet that he bar, and helede his
wounde. And after, whan him wel semede for to
don iorneye, goynge to the kyng, beforn manye men
that ther weren he toke (gave) him the pot, seyinge thus :
“O sire, this grete tresor I was wont for to kepe
prevely, and I lovede it wel ; but now, for als moche
as I schal gon a fer weye, I wole betaken it to you.
Kepeth it sikkerly ; for this to me is bettre than
gold, this to me is als dereworth as my lyf. Whan
I retorne, I schal bere it home ayen saf and sound.”
So the kyng resceyved it and seelede it with an
other signet and bad his stywardes for to kepen it
curyously.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
Than Combabe mad his weye safly ; and whan thei
were comen to the Holy Cytee thei gan bylde the
temple besily, and thei spenten three yeres in the werk,
and in tho yeres that Combabe dredde befel. For
in companyinge with him a gret whyl Stratonice
began for to love him, and thanne sche wex right
wode over him. Men of the Holy Cytee seyn that
Iuno was voluntarie cause thereof, to the entente
that Combabes godeness scholde not lye hidde and
Stratonice scholde ben punissched be cause that
sche ne behight not the temple buxomly (readily).
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
Atte firste sche was mesurable and hyd hir
maladye; but whan as hir miseyse becam to gret
for pees, sche sorwede openly and wepte everyche
day, and cryde on the name of Combabe, and Com-


<pb n="v.4.p.371"/>

babe was alle the worlde to hir. And fynally, for
sche ne mighte not susteyne suche adversitee, sche
soughte a wel semynge peticioun. Now sche was
war for to avowen hir love to ony other, yit sche
hadde scham for to assayen ought hirself. _Therfore
sche bethoghte hir of this devys, that sche scholde
make hirself dronke with wyn and thanne speke
with him ; for what tyme wyn cometh inne, boldness
of speche cometh inne with alle, and disconfiture
nys not over schamful, but all that is don passeth
into foryetynge (forgetfulness).
</p>

<p>
Right as hir thoghte, right so sche didde. For
aftre mete sche wente to the house wherin Combabe
was logged, and besoghte him and embraced his
knees and avowed hir love. But he resceyved hir
wordes rudeliche, and wolde not assente to the dede,
and reprevede hir of dronkenesse. But whan sche
made manace to don hirself som gret harm, thanne
for fere he told hir alle the storie and descryved al
his owne cas and discovered his doynge. And
whan Stratonice saughe that hir ne thoghte never
fulness
to seen, sche stente of (desisted from) hir wodenesse, yit sche forgat desisted
not at alle of hir love, but companyed with him “™
alle weyes and in that gyse solacede the love, therin
sche mighte not speden. That maner love abydeth
yit in the Holy Cytee, and is mad now a dayes;
wommen coveyten Galles and Galles wexen wode
for love of wommen; natheles is no man ialous, but
hem thenketh this thing right holy.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
Now that that had happened in the Holy Cytee
touching Stratonice scaped not the kyng in no
kynde, but manye that retorneden acuseden hem
and reherceden here doynges; wherfore the kyng
was grevously troubled and sompnede Combabe fro


<pb n="v.4.p.373"/>

the werk or it was finissched. Othere men seyn not
sooth, that whan Stratonice fayled of hir purpos,
sche hir self wroot lettres to hir housbond and
acused Combabe, blamynge him of assayinge _hir.
Right as men of Grece seyn of Steneboye and of
Fedre Cnossien, right so seyn Assuriens of Stratonice.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.373.n.1"><p>The story of Joseph and his master’s wife (Genesis39) would be in this instance a parallel more apt. And with both compare the scorning of Ishtar by Gilgamesh in the Epic (Schrader-Zimmern, p. 571 sq.). </p></note> Now to me, I ne beleve not that Steneboye
dide no suche thing, ne Fedre nouther, if Fedre
trewely lovede Ypolite. But lat tho thinges worth (go)
right as thei weren.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.373.n.2"><p>This sentence parodies Herodotus 2, 28: ταῦτα μέν νυν ἔστω ὡς ἔστι τε καὶ ὡς ἀρχὴν ἐγένετο, and similar transitions. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>
Whan the tidinges were come to the Holy Cytee,
and Combabe lernede the acusaccioun, he wente
boldely, for because he had laft his answere-at home.
And at arryvinge, anon the kyng bond him and
kepte him in prisoun; and after, whan his frendes
there weren that there weren beforn, whan Combabe
was sent forth, he ladde him in presence and began
for to blamen him, reprevinge him of avowtrie and
vileinye ; and in sore bitternesse of herte he putte
him in remembraunce of feythe and frendschipe,
seyinge that Combabe didde three fold wrong be cause
he was avowtrer and brak feyth and synned ayeyns
the goddesse in whoos servys that he so wroughte.
And manye stode forth and made witnessing that
thei sanghen hem companye togider openly. And
atte laste alle demeden that Combabe scholde dye
right anon, for his dedis disserveden dethe.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
In this tyme he stondynge seyde noght. But
whan thei wolde leden him to his dethe, he spak,



<pb n="v.4.p.375"/>

and requered that tresor, seyinge, he wolde sleen
him, not for no vileinye ne avowtrie, but coveytinge
tho thinges that in goynge he hadde betoken him.
Thanne the kyng called his styward and bad him ~
brynge what hadde ben goven him for to kepe; and
whan he broght it, Combabe brak the seel and
schewed what was with inne and what he himself
hadde soffred. And he seyde: “O Kyng, for I was
adrad of this whan ye wolde sende me on this weye,
therfore me was loth to gon; and whan ye gretly constreyned me, I wroghte this maner dede, that is gode
for my maistre but not wel for me. Natheles, I that
am such as ye seen am reprevede of a mannes synne.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
At this seyinge that other youled and toke him in
armes and wepynge seyde: “O Combabe, wherfore
hastow wrought gret mescheef? Wherfore hastow
don thiself suche a despyt that never yit no man ne
sayde? I preyse this not at alle. O herde herte,
that wast hardy for to don suche thinges, that I
wolde thou hadde neer soffred ne I neer seen! Me
wantede not this answere. But for als moche
as it was goddes wille, first shaltow han vengeaunce
of oure grace, the dethe of thi false chalengeres
hem self, and after schal comen a gret yifte, moche
gold and gret plentee silver and Assuriene clothes
and rialle destreres (royal chargers). And thou shalt come before
me withouten that ony man presente thee, and
noon schalle lette thee fro sight of me, thoghe I be
abedde with my wyf.”<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.375.n.1"><p>A plain reminiscence of Herodotus3, 84 and118, with the significant change of fv uh yuraki to οὐδ᾽ ἣν γυναικί (Allinson). </p></note> Right as he seyde, right so
he didde. Tho weren ladde to dethe anon, but to
him the yiftes were goven and grettere frendschipe


<pb n="v.4.p.377"/>

was graunted. And it semede that Combabe hadde
not his pere in Assurye for wisdom and for blisse.</p>

<p>
And after, ther as he besoghte to finissche the
remenant of the temple, for he hadde laft it unfinissched, he was sent eftsones and broght it to an
ende, and abood there fro thens fromward. And be
cause of his vertue and wel doynge, the kyng vouchede
saf that his ymage in brasse scholde ben set in the
seyntuarye. And so for gerdon Combabe dwelleth yit
in the close, formed of brasse be crafte of Ermocle
the Rodien, lyk a womman in schappe, but clothed
as a man.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.377.n.1"><p>Hermocles of Rhodes is known only from this passage ; his name must have been preserved by an inscription on the statue, which we may be sure was the restoration of an older statue of the putative originator of the Galli and possibly real founder of the temple, installed in connection with the Seleucid restoration of the temple itself. </p></note></p>

<p>
The storie telleth that his beste frendes, for solas
of his wo, chosen to parte his lot; for thei gelten
hem and ladde that same manere lyf. But othere
men rehercen prestes lore to this matere, how that
Iuno lovynge Combabe putte it in the thoghtes of
manye to gelden hem, in the entente that he
scholde not mourne allone for manhode.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>
But evermore sithen that this custom was first establissched,
it abydeth yit, and everyche yeer manye men
gelden hem in the close and becomen as wommen,
wher it be that thei solacen Combabe or reioysen
Iuno. Algates thei gelden hem. And thise no
lenger clothen hem as men, but weren wommenes
wedes and don wommenes werkes. And as I herde,
the blame of this also is leyde on Combabe; for a
thyng befel him in this wyse. A straunge womman
that cam thider on pilgrimage saughe him whyl
he was fayre and clad yit as a man, and sche was
seysed of gret love. But after, whan sche lernede



<pb n="v.4.p.379"/>

that he was marred, sche slowe hirself. Thanne for
despeyr that Combabe hadde be cause he was
acurst in love, he didde on femele clothinge to the
ende that never non other womman scholde ben
so begyled. That is whi Galles weren femele
aparayl.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.379.n.1"><p>Since Kombabos bears a very ancient name, since the temple-story ascribes the origin of the Galli to him, not to Attis, and since Attis does not figure at all in the worship as described by Lucian, the Galli can hardly be a Seleucid importation from Phrygia (Cumont); in that case Attis would have been imported also. Meyer, who believes the cult ancient here, but Hittite-Anatolian in its origin, finds evidence of Attis-worship in the name Atargatis (Atat-Ata), which he interprets as the Astarte of Attis; 7.¢., the goddess that is characterized by the worship of Attis (Aesch., p. 650). This view not only leaves Kombabos out of account, but does not reckon with the fact that the deity Ata was often, if not always, thought of as feminine (cf. Baudissin, p. 158, 1). The connection, however, between Attis and Ata is indubitable ; and I believe that there is an analogous connection between Kombabos (Assyr. Hum-ba-ba, Baby]. Hu-wa-wa, with characteristic w for b) and KéBnBos (Gallus), KvB48n (the goddess Cybele). It cannot be mere coincidence that in Syria Ku(m)baba serves Ata, while in Bhrygie Cybebe is served by Attis. That the transfer in which man and goddess exchanged names was from Semitic to non-Semitic soil is, it seems to me, likely from the antiquity of the name Ku(m)baba. Other arguments are not wanting. </p></note></p>

<p>
Of Combabe have I seyd ynow, and of Galles I
schalle make mencioun sone in another partie of my
boke,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.379.n.2"><p>C. 50-53. </p></note> how that they ben gelded, and in what
manere that thei ben buryed, and wherfore thei
entren not into the temple. But first it listeth me
to telle of the site of the temple and his gretnesse,
and therfore I schalle don right so.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>

The place therinne the temple sytt isa hille ; and *
it liggeth wel in the myddes of the cytee, and two
walles enviroune it. Oon of tho walles is auncien,
but the tother is not mocheles elder than oure tyme.
The entree of the holy place maketh out toward the
Septemtryon, wel a <num>100</num> fadmes of largenesse; and in
that entree stont tho yerdes that Bachus leet set,
on heighte a <num>300</num> fadmes.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.379.n.3"><p>Some reduce these 300-fathom emblems to 30 by conjecture, but it is in unimportant details like this that Lucian ves rein to his inclination to parody. Mandeville gives the Howe of Babel the modest height of 64 furlongs—eight miles. </p></note> A man goth up the oon





<pb n="v.4.p.381"/>

of thise yerdes twyes in the yeer and woneth at the
cop of the yerde for the space of <num>7</num> dayes. And the
cause of his goynge up, as men seyn, is this. Lewed
folk trowen that he speketh with the goddes on highe
and axeth bones for alle Surrye, and the goddeg
heren his preyeres fro there nyghe.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.381.n.1"><p>This is evidently the true reason, and not either of the two that follow. That the gods can hear better from near at hand is good Semitic psychology ; but the use of a pillar instead of a mountain-top, or a ziggurat, or the roof of a house, appears otherwise unevidenced in early Syria. “It was perhaps the memory of this strange rite (not however peculiar to Syria, but known also in India) which led Simeon the Stylite to ascend his column four centuries later ata site not very far west of the old temple of the Dea Syria” (C. R. Conder, Palestine, p. 206). </p></note> But othere
wenen that this also is don be cause of Deucalioun,
in tokene and mynde of that tribulacioun, whan
men wenten into montaynes and into the gret highe
trees for fere of the flode. Now to me, that is not
to beleven. I suppose wel that thei don this for
worschipe of Bachus, and I conclude it thus. Yerdes
that thei maken for worschipe of Bachus, on tho yerdes
thei setten alle weyes wodene men; but I schalle
not seye whi.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.381.n.2"><p>Compare Herodotus 2, 48, and the iepds Adyos. The explanation that Lucian has in mind is probably the ee story (Clement of Alexandria, Protrept. 2, p. 30 P.). </p></note> Therfore me thenketh, in goynge
up, that oon countrefeteth that other woden man.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>

The manere of his goynge up is this. He putteth
a schort corde abouten himself and the yerde, and
thanne he climbeth on peces of wode ynaylled on
the yerde, bigge ynow for to lette setten (set his toes) on his
toon; and ther as he climbeth he throweth up the
corde with bothe hondes right as he mighte schake
the reynes of a charre. If ony ther be that hath
not seen this thing, but hath seen men that climben
trees of palme in Arabye or in Egypte, or elles
where, he undirstondeth wherof I speke.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.381.n.3"><p>This method of climbing palms is alluded to by Pliny, 13, 29. </p></note>





<pb n="v.4.p.383"/>
</p>

<p>
Whan he is comen to the ende of his weye, he
letteth falle an other corde that he hath, that is
long, and draweth uppe what him list, wode and
clothes and purveyaunce, of the whiche he frameth
a sete lyk as a nest, theron he sytteth and abydeth
for the space of the before seyde dayes, And
manye comynge putten gold or silver or peraunter
brasse, that thei usen for here moneyes, in to a
vesselle that lyeth there neer, seyinge everychon
his name. Thann oon that stondeth there beside
calleth it uppe ; and whan that other resceyveth the
name of eech, he preyeth for him, and in preyinge
schaketh a thyng of brasse that souneth gret and
schrille whan it is stered.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.383.n.1"><p>Very likely the bronze sistrum ; fragments of these have been found in Phoenicia (Cook 45). The object was to scare away evil spirits, which as Lucian says elsewhere (vol. iii, p. 343), take flight if they hear a chink of bronze or iron. </p></note> And he ne slepeth never.
For if that ever he falle on slepe, a scorpioun goynge
up awaketh him and doth him pitous harm; and
that is the peyne that is leyde on him for slepynge.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.383.n.2"><p>There is probably special significance in the scorpion. Not only does it occur frequently on Babylonian seals, and later become the sign of the Zodiac, but in the Gilgamesh Epic (Frazer, Folklore,i, 112), the mountain, where the sun goes down (i.e. Antilian on ; Schrader-Zimmern, p. 573), is guarded by a scorpion man and woman. </p></note>
Now this tale that is told of the scorpioun is a holy
tale and wel semyng, but wher it be trewe or non,
I wot neer. Natheles, me semeth that drede of
fallynge avayleth moch to wakfulnesse.
</p>

<p>Now thanne, of yerde-climberes have I seyd y
now.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>
But as touching the temple, it loketh ayenst
the sonnes rysynge, and the form and makyng
therof is right as thei bylden temples in Ionye. A
gret platte forme ryseth fro the erthe <num>2</num> fadmes of
highte, where on the temple sytt. The weye up to




<pb n="v.4.p.385"/>

it is mad of stone, that is not over long. And
whan thou art aboven, the parvys of the temple
scheweth thee a thing of grete merveylle, for it is
dight with dores of gold. And with inne, the temple
schyneth with mocheles gold, and the ceylours ben
alle goldene. And a hevenlyche savour cometh out
of it, lyk as cometh, men seyn, out of the londe of
Arabye. In goynge up, fro fer it sendeth toward
thee a wondur swete brethe; and ther as thou gost
thy weye, it fayleth never, but thi clothes kepen
that brethe ful longe tyme, and thou schalt evermore ben in remembraunce ther of.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p>
And with inne, the temple is not oon, but in it is
mad an other chambre, to the which is an other weye
up, that is but schort. That chambre is not dight
with dores but liggeth alle open ayens thee. In to
the grete temple comen alle men, but in to the
litylle chambre the prestes only, and not alle the
prestes, but only thei that ben most nyghe to
the Goddes and han in governaunce alle the servys
of the temple. And in that chambre arn throned
the ydoles, that oon Iuno and that other that is
Tove, algates thei clepen him be another name.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.385.n.1"><p>The other name, the right one, is Hadad, or Ramman, god of the lightning and of the waters (rains and floods), known from very early times to the Semites, to the Mitani folk under the name of Teshub, and to the Hittites, upon whose monuments he is conspicuous, with the axe and the thunderbolt for attributes. He underlies not only Jupiter Heliopolitanus but Jupiter Dolichenus. Consequently his identification here also with Jupiter was inevitable, and it is chiefly in virtue of this that his spouse was identified with Juno (cf. Dussaud, Pauly-Wissowa, s.v., and Schrader- Zimmern, p. 447). </p></note>
And both ben of gold, and both sytten, but lyouns
beren Iuno, and that other sytt on boles.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.385.n.2"><p>Lucian’s statement is borne out by the coins; see Head, Hist. Numm., 2nd ed., p. 777. Atargatis is seen sometimes riding on a lion, sometimes enthroned between two of them ; Hadad (not Baal Kevan) is seated between two oxen. ‘On an inscription from North Syria (eighth century) Hadad has horns, and with this agrees the association of the bull with the god . . . we may conjecture that the small heads of bulls unearthed by the excavations are connected with his worship” (Cook, 90; cf. Schrader-Zimmern, p. 778). Compare Tobit, 1, 5. The lion appears also in connection with Ata, with “Kadesh,” who stands upon a lion in an Egyptian representation of her, and with several Babylonian deities, as well as with Cybele. </p></note>




<pb n="v.4.p.387"/>
</p>

<p>
And certeynely the symulacre of Iove ressembleth
Iove in alle pointes, as heed and garnements and
throne; and thou mightest not lyknen him unto
no thing elles, and thou wolde.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="32"><p>
 But whan thou
lokest on Iuno, sche wil schewe thee grete dyversitee of semblauntz; for al be it that the hool, trewely
considered, be luno, natheles it conteyneth some
dele of Minerve and Venus and Luna and Cibella
and Deane and Fortune and Parcas.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.387.n.1"><p>Compare Plutarch, Crassus, 17, 6: “And the first warning sign came to him from this very goddess, whom some call Venus, others Juno, while others (cf. Cornutus 6) still regard her as the natural cause which supplies from moisture the beginnings and seeds of everything, and points out to mankind the source of all blessings. for as they were leaving her temple (where, Plutarch says, he had been taking an inventory of the treasures), first the younger Crassus stumbled and fell at the gate, and then his father fell over him” (Perrin’s translation). The identification with Aphrodite, which occurs on inscriptions from Delos, is due to her Astarte side ; to Lucian in this case it is of course particularly suggested by the famous cestus. What suggested the other goddesses is not clear to me in the case of Athena or of Nemesis; the rays indicate Selene, the distaff Artemis, and the sceptre the Parcae, or Moirai (Fates). cestus </p></note> And in that
oon hond sche holt a troncheon, and in that
other a distaf; and on hir hede sche bereth rayes,
and a tour, and that ceynt that men arayen with
Venus Celestial allone. And abouten hir sche hath
mo gold and precious stones right costlewe, some
whyte and some watry, and manye lyk wyn and
manye lyk fuyr; and therto sardoynes withouten
nombre and berylles and emeraudes. Thise stones
bryngen men of Egypte and Inde and Ethyope and
Medye and Ermonye and Babyloyne. But I schal
devyse you a thyng that is yit mo to speke of.
Sche bereth on hir hede a ston that hight Lampe
and hath his name after that that it doth. That ston
schyneth in the nyght with grete claretee and
serveth all the temple with light, right as it were
of lampes. In the daye his schyninge is feble but



<pb n="v.4.p.389"/>

it hath a right fuyry aspect.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.389.n.1"><p>Compare Herodotus2, 44, on the great emerald pillar in the temple of Melkart at Tyre; also Mandeville, pp. 239, 276, ed. Halliwell, on luminous stones in the possession of the Emperor of Cathay and of Prester John. Diodorus (3, 39, 8) credits the topaz with this power. </p></note> And ther is an
other merveylle in that ydole. Gif thou loke on
hir stondynge ayenst hir, sche loketh on thee, and
if thou remeve thee, hir regard folweth thee; natheles
if an other beholde hir fro the tothere syde, sche
doth right so to him also.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="33"><p>
And betwene hem stont a symulacre of gold, not
lyk the othere symulacres in no kynde, that hath
no propre schap but bereth the qualitees of the
other goddes. And the Assuriens hem selve clepen
it Tokene, for thei han not goven him no propre name ;
in sothe thei mowe not seyn whens it cam ne what
maner thyng it is. But some beleven, it is of Bachus, ~
and othere that it is of Deucalioun, and othere that it
is of Semiramys. And for sothe a dowve of gold
stont on his hede, and so thei devisen that it is
Semiramys Tokene. And it doth iorney twyes
eech yeer to the See, for to fecchen that water
aforseyde.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.389.n.2"><p>It is clear from the passage in Melito quoted above that Lucian’s “token” (semeion) rests upon a misunderstanding of the name of a goddess, Simi, Simia, Semea (Néldeke ; cf. Hoefer, s.v. Semea in Roscher). The name also figures in the Semiramis-Derceto myth, for the royal overseer is called Simmas. Note also that the figure has a dove on its head. A Talmudic gloss cited by Drusius says: ‘“Samaritanus circumcidit in nomine imaginis columbam referentis quam inventam in vertice montis Garizim certo quodam ritu colunt” (Selden, de Dis Syris, p. 275). See Montgomery, Samaritans, p. 320. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="34"><p>
In the temple himself on the left syde in entrynge is
first a thron of Elye the sonne, but noon ymage of him
sytt there on. For of Sonne and Mone only schewen
thei non symulacres, and I lernede wherfore thei
folwen this usaunce. Thei seyn that of othere
goddes it is leful to lete make symulacres, for that




<pb n="v.4.p.391"/>

here schappes ben not seen of alle men. But Sonne
and Mone ben wel visible and alle men beholden
hem. Whi thanne make symulacres of thynges that
aperen in the eyr?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.391.n.1"><p>Compare Meyer, Gesch., p. 192, on the lack of images and temples in the Egyptian worship of Ra. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="35"><p>
And ther nyghe this throne is sett a symulacre ~
of Apollo, not lyk as he is wont to ben formed. For
alle othere Jeven Apollo yong and formen him as a
stripling, but thise allone schewen a symulacre of
Apollo berded. And doynge this thei preisen hem
selve and repreven Grekes and alle othere men that
worschippen Apollo in lyknesse of a child. And the
resoun is, for it semeth hem gret folye to maken
schappes of Goddes inperfyt, and al that is yong
thei demen yit inperfyt. And here Apollo hath
other novelrye; for thei allone arayen him with
clothynges.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.391.n.2"><p>Apollo is Nebo, whose statue, bearded and clothed, erected at Kelach by Adad-Nirari III, son of Semiramis, may be seen at the British Museum (illustrated in Roscher, Lexikon, I, p. 49). The inscription that it bears implores long life for Adad-Nirari, king of Assyria, and for Sammuramat, the Lady of the Palace. Nebo was highly favoured by Semiramis, and also, in later days, by Antiochus Soter, who rebuilt his temple at Borsippa in 268 B.c. At Edessa, near Hieropolis, his worship continued until the coming of Christianity (Cureton, Ancient Syriac Documents, pp. 14, 22, 41). Contemporary testimony to its existence at FReropolie is furnished by Melito; see above, p. 353, note 3. Thestatue at Hieropolis that we find described in Macrobius seems to be a later one; for though it was bearded and clothed, as in Lucian’s day, there was a calathus on the head, a spear topped with a little figure of Victory in the right hand, a flower in the left, a breastplate on his body, and over it a snaky aegis; also, two eagles near by (Saturn, 1, 17, 67-70). </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="36"><p>
Now of the wondres that he doth I can speke
largely, but I wol telle only that that is most
marveyllous; and first I schalle make mencioun
of the oracle. Ther ben manye oracles amonges
Grekes and manye amonges Egyptyens, and some in
Libye, and also manye in Asye. But thise oracles
speken not withouten prestes or prophetes; but




<pb n="v.4.p.393"/>

that oon meveth be himself and be himself acomplischeth his fercastinge, wher of the maner is right
so. Whan heis in wille for to make predicatioun, atte
firste he meveth on his thron, and thanne anon the
prestes beren him up; but if thei ne beren him
not up, he sweteth and meveth ever the more. And
whyls thei carryen him on here scholdres, he dryveth
hem, tornynge hem in alle weyes and lepynge fro
that oon to that other. And atte last the Chefe
Preste meteth him and axeth him of alle manere
thinges; and gif he wole not that a thyng ben don,
he draweth him backwardes; but if he commende a
thyng, he dryveth his bereres forwardes right as he
were dryvinge a charre.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.393.n.1"><p>At Heliopolis, Jupiter Heliopolitanus, who had absorbed “Apollo,” gave oracles in much the same way (Macrobius, Saturn, 1, 28. 13sgq.). So also did Ammon at his great Libyan shrine (Siwa) ; the description of the procedure when Alexander consulted it (Diodorus, 17, 50-51), somewhat blind in itself, is clear in the light of these parallels. The ikon of the Virgin at Phaneromene, Salamis, is credited with similar owers to-day (Capps), and for a parallel in modern Sierra eone, see Frazer, Folklore, iii, p. 323. . </p></note> So assemblen thei the
predicatiounes, and withouten this don thei no
thing, ne solempne ne lewede. And he speketh of
the yeer and the sesouns ther of, ye, whan thei
ne axe not; and he speketh of the Tokene, whan
it schal gon that iorney aforseyde.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="37"><p>
And I schalle
seye you an other wonder that he wroghte in min
owene presence. Whan the prestes wolde beren
him up and carryen him, he lafte hem doun on the
erthe and fleighe in the eyr al be him self.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="38"><p>
There beside Apollo is a symulacre of Atlas, and
there neer, of Mercure and of Lucine.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.393.n.2"><p>This is very likely the same triad of Semitic deities under another set of names, and in slightly different manifestations. For Atlas I would suggest Hadaranes, who according to Melito was worshipped here; a sign of the Zodiac would have sufficed to suggest the supporter of the heavens. Hermes(Mercury) should be Nebo at bottom, because that planet is the planet of Nebo; but the Heliopolitan Mercury who took the place of the Hieropolitan Apollo-Nebo in the triad is thought to have been called Simios (Dussaud). Eileithyia (Lucina), the helper in childbirth, is Mylitta, though here they may not have called her by that name (cf. Schrader-Zimmern, 423, note 7). </p></note>




<pb n="v.4.p.395"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="39"><p>
Now have I devysed you how that the temple
is aparaylled with innen. Withouten is set a gret
awtere of brasse, and there nyghe ben othere symulacres of kynges and prestes withouten nombre ; and
I schalle telle you tho that ben moste worthy of
mencioun. At the lefte syde of the temple stont a
symulacre of Semiramys schewinge the temple with
hir righte hond, the whiche was sett up for this
resoun. Sche made ordeynaunce unto alle that
duelleden in Surrye that thei scholde worschippe hir
as here goddesse, recchynge nought of the othere
goddes and [uno hirself. And thei didde right
so. But after, for als moche as syknesses and tribulaciouns and peynes weren leyde on hir by the
goddes, sche cessed of that folye and knouleched that
sche was mortalle and commaunded alle hir subgettes
to tornen hem ayen un to Iuno. Wherfore sche
stont yit in suche gyse, devysing to alle that comen
that thei schulle worschippe luno, and knoulechynge
that sche is not goddesse no more, but that other.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.395.n.1"><p>There may be some truth in this legend, for Semiramis actually received worship in Carchemish, just north of Hieropolis. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="40"><p>
And in that place saughe I also ymages of Eleyne
and Ecube and Andromacha and Parys and Ector
and Achilles. And I saughe Nireos ymage, that
was sone of Aglaye, and Philomele and Progne, that
weren yit wommen, and Tereus himself, that was a
brid, and an other ymage of Semiramys, and of
Combabe that that I spak of, and a right fayr of
Stratonice, and oon of Alexaundre lyk as it were the
verray man, and there beside him stont Sardanapalle
in other schappe and other aparayl.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.395.n.2"><p>That is, with the figure and clothing of a woman. </p></note>



<pb n="v.4.p.397"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="41"><p>
And in the clos at large pasturen grete boles
and hors and egles and beres and lyouns; and thei
don no manere harm to men but ben everyche of
hem holy and tame.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.397.n.1"><p>Sacred animals were a common feature of temple-closes in Greece (Gardner-Jevons, Manual, p. 188). Plato introduces sacred bulls into his utopian Atlantis, Critias, 119 p. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="42"><p>
Prestes thei apoynten withouten nombre, of the
whiche some sleen the victimes and some beren the
offrynges of licours and some ben cleped Fuyrbereres
and some Awtere Prestes. Whan I was there, mo
than a <num>300</num> weren wont to assemblen hem for sacrifise.
Thei ben clothed in whyte robes alle, and thei han
a poynted cappe on here hedes.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.397.n.2"><p>For the pointed cap, see Cumont in Daremberg-Saglio, Dict. des Ant., s.v. Syria Dea, fig. 6698, and the reference in the next note (Abd-Hadad). </p></note> And everyche
yeer a newe chefe preste is sett over hem, that
allone wereth a robe of purpre and is crouned with a
coronale of gold.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.397.n.3"><p>Coins of Hieropolis, of the fourth century, B.c. (Babelon, Perses achéménides, No. 315), show the high priest Abd-Hadad in the dress here described. Compare Herodian 5, 3, 6 (costume of Elagabalus; cf. Dio Cassius 79, 11); Cureton, Ancient Syriac Documents, p. 41 (Sharbil, priest of Nebo) ; Athenaeus 5, 215 8.c. (priest of Sandan at Tarsus). </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="43"><p>
And therto is other gret multytude of religious men, of floyteres and piperes and
Galles, and also wommen that ben wode and out of
here witte.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="44"><p>
Twyes each day sacrifise is perfourmed, to the
which allecomen. To Iove thei sacrificen withouten
ony noys, ne syngynge not ne floytynge; but whan
thei presenten offrynges to Iuno, thanne thei syngen
and floyten and sounen cymbales. And as to this
thei mighte not telle me no thing certeyn.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="45"><p>
Ther is also a lak, a lityl fro the temple, in the
whiche holy fissches ben norysscht, withouten nombre
and of dyverse kyndes. Some of hem ben ful grete,
and thise han names and comen whan thei ben





<pb n="v.4.p.399"/>

cleped. And whan I was there, amonges hem was
oon that werde gold. On his fynne was festned a
ioyelle of gold; and often tymes I saughe him, and
he hadde that ioyelle.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.399.n.1"><p>"At Hierapolis in Syria, in the lake of Venus, they (the fish) obey the spoken commands of the acditui ; when called, they come with their golden ornaments ; they show affection and let themselves be tickled (adulantes scalpuntur), and they open their mouths for people to put in their hands” (Pliny, Nat. Hist. 32, 17). According to Aelian (Nat. Hist. 12, 2) they swam in regular formation, and had leaders. The pond still exists, but the fish are no more (Cumont, Etudes Syriennes, p. 36 sq.). There were similar ponds at Ascalon, Edessa, and Smyrna: see the interesting inscription from Smyrna in Dittenberger, Sylloge Inscr. Grace.*, No. 584. The custom was transmitted to modern times (Baudissin, Studien, ii, pp. 159 and 165; Hogarth, Jc, p. 189). On the fish tabu in Syria, see Xenophon, Anab. 1, 4, 9; Menander, fragment 544 Kock; Cicero, de Nat. Deor. 3, 39; Diodorus 2, 4, 3; Plutarch, Moral. 170 D, 730D; Ovid, Fasti 2, 461 sqqg.; Athenaeus 4, 157 B; 8, 346 ¢ sqq. ; Clement Alex., Protrept. 2, 39, p. 35 e; Hyginus, Fab. 197;. Astron. 2, 30. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="46"><p>
That lak is passynge depe. I assayde it not, but
men seyn that it hath wel mo than a <num>200</num> fadmes ;
and in the myd place ther of stont an awtere of
stone. Seeynge it on a sodeyne, thou woldest
trowen that it fleyted and rode upon the water, and
manye men wenen thus; but I suppose that a gret
piler pight undernethe bereth up the awtere. And
it is ever more dressed with gerlondes and hath
encens brennynge, and manye swymmen overthwart
to it eech day for a vowe that thei han, and bryngen
gerlondes.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.399.n.2"><p>Gruppe (Gr. Myth. u. Religionsgesch., p. 813) connects this "Floating” island with the holy island of Tyre, the floating island of Chemmis in the swamps of Buto, and with the Greek stories of Delos and Patmos. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="47"><p>
At that place ben wondur grete festes, the which
highte Desceyntes unto the Lak, be cause that in
tho festes alle the ydoles gon doun to the lak.
Amonges hem Iuno cometh first, be cause of the
fissches, to the entente that Iove schalle not seen
hem first; for if so be that this happeth, thei dyen
alle, as men seyn. And for sothe he cometh to




<pb n="v.4.p.401"/>

seen hem, but sche, stondynge beforn him, letteth ; «3
him, and with manye supplicatiouns sendeth him his : **
weye.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.401.n.1"><p>"The rite of descending to the water (xardBaois, Semitic yerid) was common all over Syria. . . . Its purpose was to revive the water-sources and bring rain” (Dussaud, Pauly- Wissowa s.v. Hadad). Why the fish should need protection from Hadad is a mystery to me, unless here too Hadad had begun to be identified with the sun. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="48"><p>
Wondur grete ben also the festes that thei ben
wont to make in goynge to the see. Of tho festes
ne can I not seye no thing certeyn, be cause that
I ne wente not myself ne assayde not that pilgrimage. But what thei don whan thei retornen,
that I saughe and schalle devyse you. Thei beren
everychon a pot fulle of water, and thise pottes ben
seeled with waxe. And of hem self thei ne breke
not the seel for to schede it out; but ther is a holy
Cokke,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.401.n.2"><p>Not, according to Dussaud, a Gallus, but an overseer. </p></note> that woneth (dwells) nyghe to the lak, that whan
he resceyveth the vesseles he loketh to the seel, and
getteth him a fee for to undon the bond and remeve
the waxe; and the Cokke gadereth moche silver
thorghe this werk. And fro thens thei hem self
bryngen it in to the temple, and scheden it out;
and after this thei perfourmen sacrifise, and than
thei wenden hoom ayen.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="49"><p>
But the grettest of alle festes wherof I knowe is
kepte in the firste somer sesoun, and some men
clepen it Fuyr Feste and some Torche Feste. Ther
inne thei don sacrifise in this wyse. Thei kutten
grete trees and setten hem in the clos, and after,
brynginge gotes and schepe and othere bestes, thei
hangen hem fro the trees, alle on lyve, and eke
briddes (birds) and clothes and ioyelles of gold and of silver,
And whan thei han mad everyche thing complet and
perfyt, thei beren the ydoles aboute the trees, and
thanne thei casten inne fuyr and als swythe alle tho




<pb n="v.4.p.403"/>

thinges brennen.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.403.n.1"><p>Baudissin (176, 3) knows no closer parallel than the Continental Mai-feste, and thinks that, if the Syrian custom came down from the North, a community of origin is possible. Somewhat similar is the practice at Tarsos of erecting a pyre, setting on it an image of the god Sandan, and then burning it up. Frazer (i, 126, 146) associates the two customs and ascribes their origin to the immolation of a human victim, the priest-king. For myself, I should like to know what became of the tree in the Attis-cult, that was cut down and brought into the temple, that the image of Attis might be tied to it (Frazer, i, 267). In the Gilgamesh Epic, Humbaba is posted by Bel as watcher of the cedars (Schrader-Zimmern, 570); and sacred trees still have offerings hung on them (Robertson Smith, Jel. of the Senvites, pp. 185-6). </p></note> To this feste comen manye bothe
fro Surrye and from alle the marches there aboute ;
and alle bryngen here owne holy thinges and han
alle here Tokenes made in lyknesse of that on.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="50"><p>
And upon sette dayes the multytude assemblen
hem in the clos, and manye Galles and tho religious
men that I spak of pertourmen here cerimonyes ;
and thei kutten here owne armes and beten that oon
that other upon the bak.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.403.n.2"><p>See 1 Kings, 18, 26-28. </p></note>— And manye that stont
ther neer floyten, and manye beten timbres, and
othere syngen wode songes and holy. This is don
withouten the temple, and thei that don it comen
not in to the temple.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="51"><p>
And in thise dayes Galles ben made. For whan
tho floyten and perfourmen here rytes, that folye
sone entreth into manye, and manye ther ben that
camen for to seen and thanne wroghten in thilke
manere. And I shal descryve what thei don. ‘The
yong man to whom Fortune hath goven this adversitee, he casteth offe his clothinge and cometh in to
the myddes, cryinge in a grete voyce, and taketh
up a swerd that hath stode there thise manye
yeeres, I wene. Thanne he geldeth him right anon
and renneth throghe the Cytee berynge in his
hondes tho parties therof he gelt him. And that
house into the whiche he schalle casten thise, he




<pb n="v.4.p.405"/>

getteth thens femele wedes and wommanlyche
aparayles. Thus don thei whan thei gelden hem.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="52"><p>
And Galles at here dyenge ben not enterred in
lyk manere as other men, but gif a Galle dye, his
felawes liften him up and carryen him in to the
skirtes of the Cytee and sette doun the man himself
and the fertre on the whiche thei broghte him, and
easten stones aboven;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.405.n.1"><p>Compare Joshua8, 29, and for the modern practice, Baldensperger, 16, 1. Perhaps originally the Gallus was stoned to death at the expiration of a certain time. </p></note> and whan this is don, thei
wenden hoom ayen. And thei wayten for the nombre
of <num>7</num> dayes or that thei entren in to the temple; for
if thei entren before, thei misdon.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="53"><p>
And the customes that thei folwen therto ben thise. If so
be that ony of hem seeth a dede man, he cometh
not in to the temple that day; but on the nexte
daye, aftre that he hath pured him, thanne he
entreth. And tho that ben of the dede mannes kyn
wayten for the space of <num>30</num> dayes and lette schaven
here hedes or thei entren; but before that this hath
ben don, it is not leful for to entren.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.405.n.2"><p>On the pollution of death, see Leviticus 21, 1-3; Ezekiel 44,25. Cf. Frazer, ii, 227 sqgq. On shaving the head, Levit. 21,5; Ezekiel 44, 20. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="54"><p>
Thei sacrificen boles and kyn and gotes and schepe.
Swyn only thei ne sacrificen not nouther eten be cause
that thei demen hem unclene.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.405.n.3"><p>Klagabalus, by way of syortula, gave away all manner of animals except pigs; “for he abstained from them by the law of the Phoenicians” (Herodian 5, 6,9; cf. Dio Cassius 79,11). Suidas 8.v. Aouvivos alludes to the custom as Syrian, and Sophronius (Migne 87, 3, p. 3624) in the case of a girl from Damascus ascribes it to the worship of Adonis. See Baudissin, p. 142 sgg. “In Palestine and Syria the animal was used in certain exceptional sacrifices which were recognized as idolatrous (Isaiah 65, 4 ; 66, 17) and it was an open: uestion whether it was really polluted or holy” (Cook, 48). here was similar uncertainty in Egypt; see Herodotus 2,47, and Plutarch, Jsis and Osiris, 8. Lucian is perhaps thinking of the pig as holy in connection with the Eleusinian mysteries, and Demeter worship generally. It was holy also in Crete, and apparently in Babylon (Ninib). </p></note> But othere men
demen hem not unclene but holy. And amonges
briddes the dowve semeth hem wondur holy thing,





<pb n="v.4.p.407"/>

and thei ben not wont so moche as to touchen hem ;
and gif thei touchen hem maugree hem selven, thei
ben unclene that day. Therfore dowves lyven:
amonges hem and entren here houses and gadren
here mete for the moste part atte erthe.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.407.n.1"><p>“In Syria by the sea is a city named Ascalon. ... I saw there an impossible number of doves at the crossways and about every house. When I asked the reason, they said it was not permissible to catch them; for the inhabitants, from a remote period, had been forbidden to enjoy them. So tame is the creature through security that it always lives not only under the same roof with man but at the same table, and abuses its immunity” (Philo Judaeus, quoted by Eusebius, Pracp. Evang. 8, 14, 50). See Hehn, Kulturpflanzen und Haustiere,6 p. 329 sqq. ; Baudissin, Studien, ii, p. 191. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="55"><p>
And I schal telle you what the pilgrimes alle don.
Whan that a man wole faren for the firste sythe (time) to
the Holy Cytee, he schaveth his heed and his browes,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.407.n.2"><p>Shaving the head and brows was probably purificatery in this connection. See Plutarch, Isis and Osiris, 4. </p></note>
and after that, he sacrificeth a schep; and than he
kerveth it and eteth it alle, saf only the flees that
he leyeth on the erthe and kneleth ther on, and
taketh the bestes feet and heed and putteth upon
his owne heed. Ther with alle he preyeth, askynge
that this present sacrifise be resceyved and behotynge (promising) a grettere that nexte sythe.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.407.n.3"><p>By this procedure the worshipper seems clearly to indicate that the sacrificed sheep is a substitute for himself; it is so understood by Frazer, Folklore, i, 414, 425-428. What the worshipper says and does is equivalent to: “Take “ this poor offering in my stead, part for part ; myself I will offer next time,” In Schrader-Zimmern, p. 597, a cuneiform inscription is cited that concerns such a vicarious sacrifice : "The lamb, the substitute for a man, the lamb he gives for the man’s life; the head of the lamb he gives for the head of the man,” etc. For another view, see Robertson Smith, Rel. of the Semites, p. 438. </p></note> And whan alle this is
atte ende, he putteth a gerlond on his owne heed
and on the hedes of his felawes that wolle gon that
ilke pilgrimage. Thanne levynge his owne contree
he doth iorney; and he useth cold watre bothe for
to wasschen with and to drynken, and slepeth
alle weyes on the erthe; for he ne may not liggen
in no maner bedde un to tyme that his pilgrimage
be fulfilled and he be comen ayen to his owne
contree.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.407.n.4"><p>Psalm 132, 3; cf, Robertson Smith, Rel. of the Semites, 481 sqq. </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="56"><p>
And in the Holy Cytee he is reseeyved






<pb n="v.4.p.409"/>

of an hoste that he knoweth not propurly. For
certeyne men in that place ben apoynted unto
everyche cytee as hostes, and dyverse kynredes han
this office of linage. And Assuryens clepen tho
men Maistres be cause thei techen hem everyche
thing.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="57"><p>
And the sacrifises ben not perfourmed in the
temple, but whan he hath presented his victime
beforn the awtere, he schedeth offrynge of wyn
there on, and thanne he ayen ledeth him on lyve
to his logging, and’ whan he is comen there he
sacrificeth and preyeth be him self.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="58"><p>
Ther is also this other maner sacrifise. Theidressen
here victimes with gerlondes and hurlen hem doun
the degrees of the entree on lyve, and in fallynge
doun thei dyen. And some men hurlen here owne
children thens, but not in lyke manere as the bestes.
Thei putten hem in a walet and beren hem doun
in hond, and thei scornen hem with alle, seyinge
that thei ben not children but oxen.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.409.n.1"><p>A relic of child-sacrifice. “Shall I give my first-born for my transgression, the fruit of my body for the sin of my soul?” (Micah 6,7). On traces of infant sacrifice discovered in the excavations in Palestine, see Cook, pp. 36, 38, 43; Frazer, Folklore i, 418 and note. From recent excavations in asanctuary of Tanit at Carthage, it is apparent that firstborn children were offered to that goddess during the whole period of Punic occupation (Am. Journal of Archaevl., 1923, R 107). “Jephthah’s daughter had many successors before adrian tried to stamp out the practice. At Laodicea a virgin was annually sacrificed to ‘ Athena’ until a deer took her place ; Elagubalus was accused of offering children in his sun-temple at Rome; . . . an Arabian tribe annually sacrificed a child, which they buried beneath the altar that served them as an idol. In many parts, too, bodies of slain victims were used for purposes of. divination” (Bouchier, Syria as a Roman Province, p. 247 sq.). </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="59"><p>
And alle Ieten marke hem, some on the wriste
and some on the nekke; and for that skylle alle
Assuryens beren markes.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.409.n.2"><p>Lucian probably means tattooing, although actual brandng was practised on occasion. “Some are afflicted with such an extravagancy of madness that, leaving themselves no room for a change of mind, they embrace slavery to the works of human hands, admitting it in writing, not upon sheets of papyrus as the custom is in the case of human chattels, but by branding it upon their bodies with a heated iron with a view to its indelible permanency ; for even time does not fade these letters” (Philo Judaeus, de Monarchia 1, 8 fin.). The view that this was the “mark of Cain” is forever being advanced anew, only to be anew denied. The practice was forbidden to the Jews (Levit. 19, 28, where the Septuagint reads: kal ypdupara orixta ob worhoere ev éyiv), Among the Moslem population it still survives, but apparently without any religious significance. “A Syrian custom: the workers in tattoo are generally Syrian, and the decoration is seen mainly in Syria and North Palestine” (H. Rix, Tent and Testament, p. 103). In du Soul’s time all Christians who visited the Holy Land came back tattooed, he tells us (Lucian, ed. Hemsterhuys-Reitz, iii, p. 489). </p></note>




<pb n="v.4.p.411"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg041.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="60"><p>
And thei don another thing, in the whiche thei
acorden to men of Trosen allone of Grekes, and I
schalle telle you what tho don. Men of Trosen han
made ordeynaunce as touchinge the maydens and
the bachelers, that thei schulle not maryen or thei
lette scheren here lokkes for worschipe of Ypolite ;
and so thei don. That thing is don also in the
Holy Cytee. The bacheleres offren of here berdes,
and the children from here birthe leten holy crulles
growe, the which thei scheren whan thei ben presented in the temple and putten in boystes outher
of silver or often tymes of gold, that thei naylen
faste in the temple, and than gon here weye; but
first thei wryten there on here names everychon.
Whan I was yong, I fulfilled that ryte; and bothe
my crulle and my name ben yit in the seyntuarye.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.4.p.411.n.1">For the custom at Troezen see Pausanias 2, 32, 1; but he speaks only of girls. Its general prevalence is shown in Frazer’s note on that passage, in which the item of chief interest in connection with Lucian is that in Caria, at the temple of Zeus Panamaros, it was customary for a man to dedicate a lock of hair in a stone receptacle on which was carved his name and that of the priest or priestess in charge the receptacle was preserved in the temple.</note>
</p></div>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>

