<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Evagoras</title>
        
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor>Larue Van Hook</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by Larue Van Hook, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
          <date type="print">1945</date>
          <date type="reprint">1968</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg015.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When I saw you, Nicocles<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For Nicocles see Introd. to this
            discourse.</note>, honoring the tomb of your father, not only with numerous and
          beautiful offerings, but also with dances, music, and athletic contests, and, furthermore,
          with races of horses and triremes, and leaving to others no possibility of surpassing
            you<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A favorite expression of Isocrates; Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.5">Isoc. 4.5</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 16.34">Isoc. 16.34</bibl>.</note> in
          such celebrations, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I judged that Evagoras (if the dead have any perception of that which takes place in this
            world),<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 19.42">Isoc. 19.42</bibl> and
              <bibl n="Isoc. 14.61">Isoc. 14.61</bibl>; also <bibl n="Plat. Apol. 40c">Plat. Apol.
              40c</bibl>.</note> while gladly accepting these offerings and rejoicing in the
          spectacle of your devotion and princely magnificence in honoring him, would feel far
          greater gratitude to anyone who could worthily recount his principles in life and his
          perilous deeds than to all other men; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for we shall find that men of ambition and greatness of soul not only are desirous of
          praise for such things, but prefer a glorious death to life, zealously seeking glory
          rather than existence,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 5.135">Isoc.
              5.135</bibl>.</note> and doing all that lies in their power to leave behind a memory
          of themselves that shall never die. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Expenditure of money can effect nothing of this kind, but is an indication of wealth
          only; and those who devote themselves to music and letters and to the various contests,
          some by exhibiting their strength and others their artistic skill, win for themselves
          greater honor. But the spoken words which should adequately recount the deeds of Evagoras
          would make his virtues never to be forgotten among all mankind. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now other writers should have praised those who in their own time had proved themselves
          good men, to the end that those who have the ability to glorify the deeds of their
          contemporaries, by speaking in the presence of those who knew the facts might have
          employed the truth concerning them, and also that the younger generation might with
          greater emulation have striven for virtue, knowing well that they would be praised more
          highly than those whom they have excelled in merit. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But as it is, who would not be disheartened when he sees those who lived in the time of
          the Trojan war, and even earlier,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">e.g. Heracles, Theseus,
            and the Argonauts.</note> celebrated in song and tragedy, and yet foresees that even if
          he himself surpass their valorous achievements he will never be thought worthy of such
          praise? The cause of this is envy, which has this as its only good—it is the greatest evil
          to those who feel it. For some are so ungenerous by nature that they would listen more
          gladly to the praise of men of whose existence they are uncertain rather than of those who
          may have been their own benefactors. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Men of intelligence, however, should not let themselves be enslaved by men whose minds
          are so perverted; on the contrary, they should ignore such as these and accustom their
          fellows to hear about those whom we are in duty bound to praise, especially since we are
          aware that progress is made, not only in the arts, but in all other activities, not
          through the agency of those that are satisfied with things as they are, but through those
          who correct, and have the courage constantly to change, anything which is not as it should
          be. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I am fully aware that what I propose to do is difficult—to eulogize in prose the virtues
          of a man. The best proof is this: Those who devote themselves to philosophy<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Really oratory and rhetoric: for the meaning of “philosophy”
            in Isocrates see the General Introd., Vol. I, p. xxvi.</note> venture to speak on many
          subjects of every kind, but no one of them has ever attempted to compose a discourse on
          such a theme.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Prose encomia existed before this time, but
            they were mostly exercises on mythical subjects written by Sophists.</note> And I can
          make much allowance for them. For to the poets is granted the use of many embellishments
          of language, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>since they can represent the gods as associating with men, conversing with and aiding in
          battle whomsoever they please, and they can treat of these subjects not only in
          conventional expressions, but in words now exotic, now newly coined, and now in figures of
          speech, neglecting none, but using every kind with which to embroider their poesy.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">With this passage compare <bibl n="Aristot. Poet. 1457b"
              >Aristot. Poet. 1457b</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Orators, on the contrary, are not permitted the use of such devices; they must use with
          precision only words in current use and only such ideas as bear upon the actual facts.
          Besides, the poets compose all their works with meter and rhythm, while the orators do not
          share in any of these advantages; and these lend such charm that even though the poets may
          be deficient in style and thoughts, yet by the very spell of their rhythm and harmony they
          bewitch their listeners.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 601b"
              >Plat. Rep. 601b</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The power of poetry may be understood from this consideration: if one should retain the
          words and ideas of poems which are held in high esteem, but do away with the meter, they
          will appear far inferior to the opinion we now have of them. Nevertheless, although poetry
          has advantages so great, we must not shrink from the task, but must make the effort and
          see if it will be possible in prose to eulogize good men in no worse fashion than their
          encomiasts do who employ song and verse. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In the first place, with respect to the birth and ancestry of Evagoras,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 3.42">Isoc. 3.42</bibl>.</note> even if
          many are already familiar with the facts, I believe it is fitting that I also should
          recount them for the sake of the others, that all may know that he proved himself not
          inferior to the noblest and greatest examples of excellence which were of his inheritance.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it is acknowledged that the noblest of the demigods are the sons of Zeus, and there
          is no one who would not award first place among these to the Aeacidae: for while in the
          other families we shall find some of superior and some of inferior worth, yet all the
          Aeacidae have been most renowned of all their contemporaries. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In the first place Aeacus,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Aeacus, son of Zeus and
              <placeName key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, was renowned for his piety.</note>
          son of Zeus and ancestor of the family of the Teucridae, was so distinguished that when a
          drought visited the Greeks and many persons had perished, and when the magnitude of the
          calamity had passed all bounds, the leaders of the cities came as suppliants to him; for
          they thought that, by reason of his kinship with Zeus and his piety, they would most
          quickly obtain from the gods relief from the woes that afflicted them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Having gained their desire, they were saved and built in <placeName key="tgn,7011087"
            >Aegina</placeName> a temple<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This was the Aiakeion,
            described by Pausanias ii. 29.</note> to be shared by all the Greeks on the very spot
          where he had offered his prayer. During his entire stay among men he ever enjoyed the
          fairest repute, and after his departure from life it is said that he sits by the side of
          Pluto and Kore<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Persephone.</note> in the enjoyment of the
          highest honors.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Aeacus, Minos, and Rhadamanthys were
            reputed to be the judges in the world of the dead.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The sons of Aeacus were Telamon and Peleus; Telamon won the meed of valor in an
          expedition with Heracles against Laomedon,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Laomedon, with
            the help of Poseidon, built <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.</note> and
          Peleus, having distinguished himself in the battle with the Centaurs and having won glory
          in many other hazardous enterprises, wedded Thetis, the daughter of Nereus, he a mortal
          winning an immortal bride. And they say that at his wedding alone, of all the human race
          who have ever lived, the wedding-song was sung by gods. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>To each of these two were born sons—to Telamon Ajax and Teucer, and to Peleus Achilles,
          and these heroes gave proof of their valour in the clearest and most convincing way: for
          not alone in their own cities were they pre-eminent, or in the places where they made
          their homes, but when an expedition was organized by the Greeks against the
            barbarians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., the Trojans.</note> and a great army
          was assembled on either side </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and no warrior of repute was absent, Achilles above all distinguished himself in these
          perils. And Ajax was second to him in valor, and Teucer, who proved himself worthy of
          their kinship and inferior to none of the other heroes, after he had helped in the capture
          of <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, went to <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
            >Cyprus</placeName> and founded <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, giving
          to it the name of his former native land<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The island
              <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName> near Athens.</note>; and he left
          behind him the family that now reigns. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> So distinguished from the beginning was the heritage transmitted to Evagoras by his
          ancestors. After the city had been founded in this manner, the rule at first was held by
          Teucer's descendants: at a later time, however, there came from <placeName
            key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName> a fugitive, who after he had gained the
          confidence of the king who then reigned, and had won great power, showed no proper
          gratitude for the favor shown him; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>on the contrary, he acted basely toward his host, and being skilled at grasping, he
          expelled his benefactor and himself seized the throne. But distrustful of the consequences
          of his measures and wishing to make his position secure, he reduced the city to barbarism,
          and brought the whole island into subservience to the Great King.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The kind of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>,
            Artaxerxes.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Such was the state of affairs in <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, and
          the descendants of the usurper were in possession of the throne when Evagoras was born. I
          prefer to say nothing of the portents, the oracles, the visions appearing in dreams, from
          which the impression might be gained that he was of superhuman birth, not because I
          disbelieve the reports, but that I may make it clear to all that I am so far from
          resorting to invention in speaking of his deeds that even of those matters which are in
          fact true I dismiss such as are known only to the few and of which not all the citizens
          are cognizant. And I shall begin my account of him with the generally acknowledged facts.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When Evagoras was a boy he possessed beauty, bodily strength, and modesty, the very
          qualities that are most becoming to that age. Witnesses could be produced for these
          assertions: for his modesty— fellow-citizens who were educated with him: for his
          beauty—all who beheld him: for his strength—all the contests<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">I.e., the official records of winners in the contests sanctioned by the
            state.</note> in which he vanquished his age-mates. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>When he attained to manhood not only did all these qualities grow up with him, but to
          them were also added manly courage, wisdom, and justice, and that too in no ordinary
          measure, as is the case with some others, but each of these characteristics in
          extraordinary degree. So surpassing was his excellence of both body and mind, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>that when the kings of that time looked upon him they were terrified and feared for their
          throne, thinking that a man of such nature could not possibly pass his life in the status
          of a private citizen, but whenever they observed his character, they felt such confidence
          in him that they believed that even if anyone else should dare to injure them, Evagoras
          would be their champion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And although opinions of him were so at variance, they were mistaken in neither respect:
          for he neither remained in private life, nor did them injury: on the contrary, the Deity
          took such thought for him that he should honorably assume the throne, that all the
          preparations which necessarily involved impiety were made by another, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>while he preserved for Evagoras those means whereby it was possible for him to gain the
          rule in accordance with piety and justice. For one of the princes,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Abdemon: cf. Diodorus xiv. 98.</note> starting a conspiracy, slew the tyrant
          and attempted to arrest Evagoras, believing that he would not be able to retain the rule
          himself unless he should get him out of the way. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But Evagoras escaped this peril, and having saved himself by fleeing to <placeName
            key="perseus,Soli">Soli</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName>
          did not show the same spirit as those who are the victims of like misfortune. For other
          exiles from royal power are humbled in spirit because of their misfortunes,whereas
          Evagoras attained to such greatness of soul that, although until that time he had lived as
          a private citizen, when he was driven into exile he determined to gain the throne. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The wandering life of an exile, the dependence upon the help of others in seeking his
          restoration and the paying of court to his inferiors—all these he scorned: but this he
          took as his guiding principle, which those who would be god-fearing men must take—to act
          only in self-defense and never to be the aggressor: and he chose either by success to
          regain the throne or, failing in that, to die. And so, calling to his side men numbering,
          according to the highest estimates, about fifty, with these he prepared to effect his
          return from exile. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And from this venture especially the character of Evagoras and his reputation among his
          associates may be seen: for although he was on the point of sailing with so few companions
          for the accomplishment of so great a design, and although all the attendant dangers were
          near at hand, neither did he himself lose heart, nor did any of his companions see fit to
          shrink from these dangers: nay, as if a god were their leader, they one and all held fast
          to their promises, and Evagoras, just as if either he had an army superior to that of his
          adversaries or foresaw the outcome, held to his opinion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>This is evident from his acts: for, when he had landed on the island, he did not think it
          necessary to seize a strong position, make sure of his own safety, and then to wait and
          see if some of the citizens would rally to his aid: but immediately, just as he was, on
          that very night he broke through a little gate in the wall, and leading his followers
          through this opening, attacked the palace. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The confusion attendant upon such occasions, the fears of his followers, the exhortations
          of their leader—why need I take the time to describe<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. 4.97">Isoc. 4.97</bibl> for a similar passage in reference to the
            sea-fight at <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>. In <bibl n="Isoc. 5.93"
              >Isoc. 5.93-94</bibl> Isocrates justifies such “autoplagiarism.”</note>? When the
          supporters of the tyrant opposed him and the citizens generally were observers (for they
          held their peace because they feared either the authority of the one party or the valor of
          the other), </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>he did not cease from fighting, whether alone against many or with few opposing all the
          foe, until, having captured the palace, he had taken vengeance upon the enemy and had
          succoured his friends: furthermore, he restored its ancestral honors to his family<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 3.28">Isoc. 3.28</bibl>.</note> and
          established himself as ruler of the city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I think that even if I should mention nothing more, but should discontinue my discourse
          at this point, from what I have said the valor of Evagoras and the greatness of his deeds
          would be readily manifest: nevertheless, I consider that both will be yet more clearly
          revealed from what remains to be said. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For of all the many sovereigns since time began, none will be found to have won this
          honor more gloriously than Evagoras. If we were to compare the deeds of Evagoras with
          those of each one, such an account would perhaps be inappropriate to the occasion, and the
          time would not suffice for the telling. But if we select the most illustrious of these
          rulers and examine their exploits in the light of his, our investigation will lose nothing
          thereby and our discussion will be much more brief. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Who then, would not choose the perilous deeds of Evagoras before the fortunes of those
          who inherited their kingdoms from their fathers? For surely there is no one so mean of
          spirit that he would prefer to receive that power from his ancestors than first to acquire
          it, as he did, and then to bequeath it to his children. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, of the returns to their thrones by princes of ancient times the most
          renowned are those of which the poets tell us: indeed they not only chronicle for us those
          which have been most glorious, but also compose new ones of their own invention.
          Nevertheless no poet has told the story of any legendary prince who has faced hazards so
          formidable and yet regained his throne: on the contrary, most of their heroes have been
          represented as having regained their kingdoms by chance, others as having employed deceit
          and artifice to overcome their foes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nay, of those who lived later, perhaps indeed of all, the one hero who was most admired
          by the greatest number was Cyrus, who deprived the Medes of their kingdom and gained it
          for the Persians. But while Cyrus with a Persian army conquered the Medes, a deed which
          many a Greek or a barbarian could easily do, Evagoras manifestly accomplished the greater
          part of the deeds which have been mentioned through strength of his own mind and body.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Again, while it is not at all certain from the expedition of Cyrus that he would have
          endured the dangers of Evagoras, yet it is obvious to all from the deeds of Evagoras that
          the latter would have readily attempted the exploits of Cyrus. In addition, while piety
          and justice characterized every act of Evagoras, some of the successes of Cyrus were
          gained impiously: for the former destroyed his enemies, but Cyrus slew his mother's
            father.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Astyages, father of Mandane, who married
            Cambyses, father of Cyrus. That Cyrus slew Astyages is not stated by any other
            writer.</note> Consequently if any should wish to judge, not of the greatness of their
          successes, but of the essential merit of each, they would justly award greater praise to
          Evagoras than even to Cyrus. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And if there is need to speak concisely, without reservation or fear of arousing
          ill-feeling, but with the utmost frankness, I would say that no one, whether mortal,
          demigod, or immortal, will be found to have obtained his throne more nobly, more
          splendidly, or more piously. Anyone would in the highest degree be confirmed in this
          belief if, distrusting completely what I have said, he were to set about examining how
          each gained royal power. For it will be manifest that it is through no desire whatever of
          grandiloquence, but because of the truth of the matter, that I have spoken thus boldly
          about Evagoras. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now if he had distinguished himself in unimportant ways only, he would fittingly be
          thought worthy also of praise of like nature: but as it is, all would admit that of all
          blessings whether human or divine supreme power is the greatest, the most august, and the
          object of greatest strife. That man, therefore, who has most gloriously acquired the most
          glorious of possessions, what poet or what artificer of words<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed"><foreign xml:lang="greek">LO/GWN EU(RETH/S</foreign> is found also in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 5.144">Isoc. 5.144</bibl>. It means “prose-writer,” and refers especially to
            composers of “set discourses” or “show-pieces.”</note> could raise in a manner worthy of
          his deeds? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Nor again, though he was a man of surpassing merit in these respects, will Evagoras be
          found deficient in all others, but, in the first place, although gifted by nature with the
          highest intelligence and capable of successful action in very many fields, yet he judged
          that he should not slight any matter or act on the spur of the moment in public affairs:
          nay, he spent most of his time in inquiring, in deliberation, and in taking counsel, for
          he believed that if he should prepare his mind well, all would be well with his kingdom
            also<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.10">Isoc. 2.10</bibl>.</note>;
          and he marvelled at those who, while they cultivate the mind for all other ends, take no
          thought of the mind itself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Again, in public affairs he held to the same opinion: for, seeing that those persons who
          look best after realities are least worried, and that the true freedom from anxiety is to
          be found, not in inactivity, but in success and patient endurance, he left nothing
          unexamined: on the contrary, so thoroughly was he cognizant of public affairs and so
          thorough was his knowledge of each of the citizens, that neither those who conspired
          against him took him unawares, nor did the good citizens remain unknown to him, but all
          got their deserts: for he neither punished nor honored them on the basis of what he heard
          from others, but from his own knowledge he judged them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When he had engaged himself in the care of such matters he made not a single mistake in
          dealing with the unexpected incidents which daily befell, but he governed the city so
          reverently and humanely that visitors to the island<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. §
            51.</note> did not so much envy Evagoras his office as they did the citizens their
          government under him: for throughout his whole life he never acted unjustly toward anyone
          but ever honored the good: and while he ruled all his subjects with strictness, yet he
          punished wrongdoers in accordance with the laws; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and while he was in no need of advisers, yet he sought the counsel of his friends. He
          yielded often to his intimates, but in everything dominated his enemies: he inspired
          respect, not by the frownings of his brow, but by the principles of his life—in no thing
          was he disposed to carelessness or caprice, but observed his agreements in deed as well as
          word; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>he was proud, not of successes that were due to Fortune, but of those that came about
          through his own efforts: his friends he made subject to himself by his benefactions the
          rest by his magnanimity he enslaved: he inspired fear, not by venting his wrath upon many,
          but because in character he far surpassed all others: of his pleasures he was the master
          and not their servant: by little labor he gained much leisure, but would not, to gain a
          little respite, leave great labors undone; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>in general, he fell in no respect short of the qualities which belong to kings, but
          choosing from each kind of government the best characteristic, he was democratic in his
          service to the people, statesmanlike in the administration of the city as a whole, an able
          general in his good counsel in the face of dangers, and princely in his superiority in all
          these qualities. That these attributes were inherent in Evagoras, and even more than
          these, it is easy to learn from his deeds themselves.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In §§
            43-46 the strong influence of Gorgias is obvious in the long series of artificial
            antitheses and in the varied assonance.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> After he had taken over the government of the city, which had been reduced to a state of
          barbarism and, because it was ruled by Phoenicians, was neither hospitable to the Greeks
          nor acquainted with the arts, nor possessed of a trading-port or harbor, Evagoras remedied
          all these defects and, besides, acquired much additional territory, surrounded it all with
          new walls and built triremes, and with other construction so increased the city that it
          was inferior to none of the cities of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. And
          he caused it to become so powerful that many who formerly despised it, now feared it.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.141">Isoc. 4.141</bibl> for the fleet and
            army of Evagoras.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet it is not possible that cities should take on such increase unless there are
          those who govern them by such principles as Evagoras had and as I endeavored to describe a
          little before. In consequence I am not afraid of appearing to exaggerate in speaking of
          the qualities of the man, but rather lest I greatly fall short of doing justice to his
          deeds. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For who could do justice to a man of such natural gifts, a man who not only increased the
          importance of his own city, but advanced the whole region surrounding the island to a
          regime of mildness and moderation? Before Evagoras gained the throne the inhabitants were
          so hostile to strangers and fierce that they considered the best rulers to be those who
          treated the Greeks in the most cruel fashion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>At present, however, they have undergone so great a change that they strive with one
          another to see who shall be regarded as most friendly to the Greeks, and the majority of
          them take their wives from us and from them beget children, and they have greater pleasure
          in owning Greek possessions and observing Greek institutions than in their own, and more
          of those who occupy themselves with the liberal arts and with education in general now
          dwell in these regions than in the communities in which they formerly used to live. And
          for all these changes, no one could deny that Evagoras is responsible. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The most convincing proof of the character and uprightness of Evagoras is this—that many
          of the most reputable Greeks left their own fatherlands and came to Cyrus to dwell,
          because they considered Evagoras's rule less burdensome and more equitable than that of
          their own governments at home.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">E.g., Andocides, the
            Athenian orator, who had an estate in <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>
            (cf. <bibl n="Andoc. 1.4">Andoc. 1.4</bibl>), and other Greeks who were forced into
            exile.</note> To mention all the others by name would be too great a task: </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but who does not know about Conon, first among the Greeks for his very many glorious
          deeds, that when his own city had met with ill-fortune,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            Athenian fleet under Conon was defeated by the Spartans at <placeName key="tgn,6000070"
              >Aegospotami</placeName> in <date when="-0405">405 B.C.</date> After this
            “ill-fortune” Conon, with eight triremes, took refuge with Evagoras, where he remained
            until <date when="-0397">397 B.C.</date></note> he chose out of all the world Evagoras
          and came to him, believing that for himself Evagoras would provide the most secure asylum
          and for his country the most speedy assistance. And indeed Conon, although he had been
          successful in many previous ventures, in no one of them, it is believed, had he planned
          more wisely than in this; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for the result of his visit to <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> was that
          he both conferred and received most benefits. In the first place, no sooner had Evagoras
          and Conon met one another than they esteemed each other more highly than those who before
          had been their intimate friends. Again, they not only were in complete harmony all their
          lives regarding all other matters, but also in matters relating to our own city they held
          to the same opinion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For when they beheld Athens under the domination of the Lacedaemonians and the victim of
          a great reversal of fortune, they were filled with grief and indignation, both acting
          fittingly: for Conon was a native son of Athens, and Evagoras, because of his many
          generous benefactions, had legally been given citizenship by the Athenians.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">This is attested by <bibl n="Dem. 12.10">Dem.
            12.10</bibl>.</note> And while they were deliberating how they might free Athens from
          her misfortunes, the Lacedaemonians themselves soon furnished the opportunity: for, as
          rulers of the Greeks on land and sea, they became so insatiate that they attempted to
          ravage Asia<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Agesilaus, king of <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, was leader.</note> also. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Conon and Evagoras seized this opportunity, and, as the generals of the Persian king were
          at a loss to know how to handle the situation, these two advised them to wage war against
          the Lacedaemonians, not upon land but upon the sea, their opinion being that if the
          Persians should organize an army on land and with this should gain a victory, the mainland
          alone would profit, whereas, if they should be victors on the sea, all <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> would have a share in the victory. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And that in fact is what happened: the generals followed this advice, a fleet was
          assembled, the Lacedaemonians were defeated in a naval battle<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Off <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>, <date when="-0394">394
              B.C.</date></note> and lost their supremacy, while the Greeks regained their freedom
          and our city recovered in some measure its old-time glory and became leader of the allies.
          And although all this was accomplished with Conon as commander, yet Evagoras both made the
          outcome possible and furnished the greater part of the armament. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In gratitude we honored them with the highest honors and set up their statues<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In front of the Zeus Stoa in the Agora: cf. Pausanias i. 3.
            2.</note> where stands the image of Zeus the Savior, near to it and to one another, a
          memorial both of the magnitude of their benefactions and of their mutual friendship. The
          king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>, however, did not have the same
          opinion of them: on the contrary, the greater and more illustrious their deeds the more he
          feared them. Concerning Conon I will give an account elsewhere<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Isocrates gives a brief discussion of Conon's affairs in <bibl n="Isoc. 5.62"
              >Isoc. 5.62-64</bibl>.</note>; but that toward Evagoras he entertained this feeling
          not even the king himself sought to conceal. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For he was manifestly more concerned about the war in <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
            >Cyprus</placeName> than about any other, and regarded Evagoras as a more powerful and
          formidable antagonist than Cyrus, who had disputed the throne with him.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Xen. Anab. 1">Xen. Anab. 1</bibl> for the famous
            expedition of Cyrus the Younger against his brother Artaxerxes II. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.145">Isoc. 4.145</bibl>.</note> The most convincing proof of this statement
          is this: when the king heard of the preparations Cyrus was making he viewed him with such
          contempt that because of his indifference Cyrus almost stood at the doors of his palace
          before he was aware of him.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The battle of <placeName
              key="tgn,6001621">Cunaxa</placeName> (<date when="-0401">401 B.C.</date>) in which
            Cyrus was slain. The distance from <placeName key="tgn,7002626">Babylon</placeName>,
            according to Xenophon, was 360 stades (c. 45 miles).</note> With regard to Evagoras,
          however, the king had stood in terror of him for so long a time that even while he was
          receiving benefits from him he had undertaken to make war upon him—a wrongful act, indeed,
          but his purpose was not altogether unreasonable. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For the king well knew that many men, both Greeks and barbarians, starting from low and
          insignificant beginnings, had overthrown great dynasties, and he was aware too of the
          lofty ambition of Evagoras and that the growth of both his prestige and of his political
          activities was not taking place by slow degrees: also that Evagoras had unsurpassed
          natural ability and that Fortune was fighting with him as an ally. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore it was not in anger for the events of the past, but with forebodings for the
          future, nor yet fearing for <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> alone, but for
          reasons far weightier, that he undertook the war against Evagoras. In any case he threw
          himself into it with such ardor that he expended on this expedition more than fifteen
          thousand talents.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A talent of gold was worth about $1200 or
            300 pounds.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But nevertheless, although Evagoras was inferior in all the resources of war, after he
          had marshalled in opposition to these extraordinarily immense preparations of the king his
          own determination, he proved himself in these circumstances to be far more worthy of
          admiration than in all those I have mentioned before. For when his enemies permitted him
          to be at peace, all he possessed was his own city; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but when he was forced to go to war, he proved so valiant, and had so valiant an ally in
          his son Pnytagoras, that he almost subdued the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
            >Cyprus</placeName>, ravaged <placeName key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>, took
            <placeName key="tgn,7002862">Tyre</placeName> by storm, caused <placeName
            key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName> to revolt from the king, and slew so many of his
          enemies that many of the Persians, when they mourn over their sorrows, recall the valor of
            Evagoras<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.161">Isoc.
            4.161</bibl>.</note>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And finally he so glutted them with war<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A Homeric
            reminiscence.</note> that the Persian kings, who at other times were not accustomed to
          make peace with their rebellious subjects until they had become masters of their persons,
          gladly made peace,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the actual facts see <bibl
              n="Diod. 15.9">Dio. Sic. 15.9</bibl>.</note> abandoning this custom and leaving
          entirely undisturbed the authority of Evagoras. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And although the king within three years<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><date
              from="-0397" to="-0394">397-394 B.C.</date></note> destroyed the dominion of the
            Lacedaemonians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An exaggeration: it was the Spartan
            sea-power only that was destroyed.</note> who were then at the height of their glory and
          power, yet after he had waged war against Evagoras for ten years,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">390-380 (?) B.C.</note> he left him lord of all that he had possessed before
          he entered upon the war. But the most amazing thing of all is this: the city which, held
          by another prince, Evagoras had captured with fifty men, the Great King, with all his vast
          power, was unable to subdue at all. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In truth, how could one reveal the courage, the wisdom, or the virtues generally of
          Evagoras more clearly than by pointing to such deeds and perilous enterprises? For he will
          be shown to have surpassed in his exploits, not only those of other wars, but even those
          of the war of the heroes which is celebrated in the songs of all men. For they, in company
          with all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, captured <placeName
            key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> only,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.83">Isoc. 4.83</bibl>.</note> but Evagoras, although he possessed but one
          city, waged war against all Asia. Consequently, if the number of those who wished to
          praise him had equalled those who lauded the heroes at <placeName key="perseus,Troy"
            >Troy</placeName>, he would have gained far greater renown than they. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For whom shall we find of the men of that age—if we disregard the fabulous tales and look
          at the truth—who has accomplished such feats or has brought about changes so great in
          political affairs? Evagoras, from private estate, made himself a sovereign: his entire
          family, which had been driven from political power, he restored again to their appropriate
          honors: the citizens of barbarian birth he transformed into Hellenes, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>cravens into warriors, and obscure individuals into men of note: and having taken over a
          country wholly inhospitable and utterly reduced to savagery, he made it more civilized and
          gentler: furthermore, when he became hostile to the king, he defended himself so
          gloriously that the Cyprian War has become memorable for ever: and when he was the ally of
          the king, he made himself so much more serviceable than the others that, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>in the opinion of all, the forces he contributed to the naval battle at <placeName
            key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName> were the largest, and as the result of this battle,
          while the king became master of all Asia, the Lacedaemonians instead of ravaging the
          continent were compelled to fight for their own land, and the Greeks, in place of
          servitude, gained independence, and the Athenians increased in power so greatly that those
          who formerly were their rulers<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A reference to the
            Lacedaemonians before the battle of <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>: see
              <bibl n="Isoc. 7.65">Isoc. 7.65</bibl>.</note> came to offer them the hegemony. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="69" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Consequently, if anyone should ask me what I regard as the greatest of the achievements
          of Evagoras, whether the careful military preparations directed against the Lacedaemonians
          which resulted in the aforesaid successes, or the last war, or the recovery of his throne,
          or his general administration of affairs, I should be at a great loss what to say in
          reply: for each achievement to which I happen to direct my attention seems to me the
          greatest and most admirable. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="70" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Therefore, I believe that, if any men of the past have by their merit become immortal,
          Evagoras also has earned this preferment: and my evidence for that belief is this—that the
          life he lived on earth has been more blessed by fortune and more favored by the gods than
          theirs. For of the demigods the greater number and the most renowned were, we shall find,
          afflicted by the most grievous misfortunes, but Evagoras continued from the beginning to
          be not only the most admired, but also the most envied for his blessings. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="71" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For in what respect did he lack utter felicity? Such ancestors Fortune gave to him as to
          no other man, unless it has been one sprung from the same stock, and so greatly in body
          and mind did he excel others that he was worthy to hold sway over not only <placeName
            key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName> but the whole of Asia also: and having acquired
          most gloriously his kingdom he continued in its possession all his life: and though a
          mortal by birth, he left behind a memory of himself that is immortal, and he lived just so
          long that he was neither unacquainted with old age, nor afflicted with the infirmities
          attendant upon that time of life.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Evagoras seized the power
            not later than <date when="-0411">411 B.C.</date>, when the Athenian orator Andocides,
            in exile, found him reigning. He died in <date from="-0374" to="-0373">374-373
              B.C.</date> Isocrates, in his depiction of the happy lot of the king, naturally
            must ignore the fact that Evagoras seems to have been assassinated !</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="72" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In addition to these blessings, that which seems to he the rarest and most difficult
          thing to win—to be blessed with many children who are at the same time good—not even this
          was denied him, but this also fell to his lot. And the greatest blessing was this: of his
          offspring he left not one who was addressed merely by a private title: on the contrary,
          one was called king,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A reference to Nicocles.</note> others
          princes, and others princesses. In view of these facts, if any of the poets have used
          extravagant expressions in characterizing any man of the past, asserting that he was a god
          among men, or a mortal divinity, all praise of that kind would be especially in harmony
          with the noble qualities of Evagoras. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="73" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> No doubt I have omitted much that might be said of Evagoras: for I am past my prime of
            life,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates was perhaps seventy years of age when he
            wrote the <title>Evagoras</title>.</note> in which I should have worked out this eulogy
          with greater finish and diligence. Nevertheless, even at my age, to the best of my ability
          he has not been left without his encomium. For my part, Nicocles, I think that while
          effigies of the body are fine memorials, yet likenesses of deeds and of the character are
          of far greater value,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.36">Isoc.
              2.36</bibl>.</note> and these are to be observed only in discourses composed according
          to the rules of art. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="74" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>These I prefer to statues because I know, in the first place, that honorable men pride
          themselves not so much on bodily beauty as they desire to be honored for their deeds and
          their wisdom: in the second place, because I know that images must of necessity remain
          solely among those in whose cities they were set up, whereas portrayals in words may be
          published throughout <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, and having been
          spread abroad in the gatherings of enlightened men, are welcomed among those whose
          approval is more to be desired than that of all others; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="75" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and finally, while no one can make the bodily nature resemble molded statues and
          portraits in painting, yet for those who do not choose to be slothful, but desire to be
          good men, it is easy to imitate the character of their fellow-men and their thoughts and
          purposes—those, I mean, that are embodied in the spoken word. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="76" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For these reasons especially I have undertaken to write this discourse because I believed
          that for you, for your children, and for all the other descendants of Evagoras, it would
          be by far the best incentive, if someone should assemble his achievements, give them
          verbal adornment, and submit them to you for your contemplation and study. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="77" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For we exhort young men to the study of philosophy<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
            Vol. I, Introd. pp. xxvi and xxvii for the “philosophy” of Isocrates.</note> by praising
          others in order that they, emulating those who are eulogized, may desire to adopt the same
          pursuits, but I appeal to you and yours, using as examples not aliens, but members of your
          own family, and I counsel you to devote your attention to this, that you may not be
          surpassed in either word or deed by any of the Hellenes </p>
      </div>
      <div n="78" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And do not imagine that I am reproaching you for indifference at present, because I
          often admonish you on the same subject.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See Isocrates, Vol.
            I, p. 39, L.C.L., Introd. to the discourse <title>To Nicocles</title>, <bibl n="Isoc. 2"
              >Isoc. 2</bibl>.</note> For it has not escaped the notice of either me or anyone else
          that you, Nicocles, are the first and the only one of those who possess royal power,
          wealth, and luxury who has undertaken to pursue the study of philosophy, nor that you will
          cause many kings, emulating your culture, to desire these studies and to abandon the
          pursuits in which they now take too great pleasure. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="79" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Although I am aware of these things, none the less I am acting, and shall continue to
          act, in the same fashion as spectators at the athletic games: for they do not shout
          encouragement to the runners who have been distanced in the race, but to those who still
          strive for the victory. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="80" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It is my task, therefore, and that of your other friends, to speak and to write in such
          fashion as may be likely to incite you to strive eagerly after those things which even now
          you do in fact desire: and you it behooves not to be negligent, but as at present so in
          the future to pay heed to yourself and to discipline your mind that you may be worthy of
          your father and of all your ancestors. For though it is the duty of all to place a high
          value upon wisdom, yet you kings especially should do so, who have power over very many
          and weighty affairs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="81" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>You must not be content if you chance to be already superior to your contemporaries, but
          you should be chagrined if, endowed as you are by nature, distantly descended from Zeus
          and in our own time from a man of such distinguished excellence, you shall not far
          surpass, not only all others, but also those who possess the same high station as yourself
          It is in your power not to fail in this: for if you persevere in the study of philosophy
          and make as great progress as heretofore, you will soon become the man it is fitting you
          should be.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
