<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Philon from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I did not suppose, gentlemen
        of the Council, that Philon would ever carry audacity to the point of consenting to appear
        before you in order to pass a scrutiny. But since he is audacious, not in one instance only,
        but in many, and I have taken oath before entering the Council-chamber <milestone n="2"
          unit="section"/>that my counsel would be for the best advantage of the State, and as the
        terms of that oath require us to expose any person appointed by lot whom we know to be
        unsuitable for service on the Council, I shall deliver the accusation against this man
        Philon: I am not, however, pursuing any private feud, nor am I prompted by my ability or
        practice in speaking before you, but I merely rely on the multitude of his offences, and
        feel bound to abide by the oaths that I have sworn. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Now you
        will recognize that the contest will be an unequal one: my resources will not be so ample
        for showing up his character as his were for contriving his villainies. Nevertheless, if I
        should not altogether discharge my part in speaking to the accusation, it would not be right
        that he should benefit by that, but rather that he should be rejected on the score of any
        points that I can demonstrate to your satisfaction. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>For my
        speech will be found defective only on account of my imperfect acquaintance with the whole
        of his actions, but adequate on account of the vileness of all his ways. And I also call
        upon those among you who may have more ability in speaking than I to amplify my exposure of
        his offences, and to make use of any points that I omit for accusing Philon, in your turn,
        of offences known to you. For it is not from my sole statement that you ought to form your
        views of his character. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What
        I say is that only those have the right to sit in Council on our concerns who, besides
        holding the citizenship, have their hearts set upon it. For to them it makes a great
        difference whether this city is prosperous or unsuccessful, because they consider themselves
        obliged to bear their share in her calamities as they also share in her advantages.
          <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>But those who, though citizens by birth, adopt the view
        that any country in which they have their business is their fatherland, are evidently men
        who would even abandon the public interest of their city to seek their private gain, because
        they regard their fortune, not the city, as their fatherland. <milestone n="7"
          unit="section"/>Now I will demonstrate that Philon here has set his private safety above
        the public danger of the city, and has held it preferable to pass his life without danger to
        himself rather than save the city by sharing her dangers with the rest of the citizens.
          <milestone n="8" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>For this man, gentlemen of
        the Council, in the midst of the city’s disaster (which I only touch upon so far as I am
        forced to do so), was banned from the town by the Thirty along with the main body of the
        citizens, and for a while he lived in the country: but when the party of Phyle returned to
        the Peiraeus, and the people, not only from the country, but from over the border, assembled
        together, partly in the town and partly in the Peiraeus, and when each to the extent of his
        powers came to the rescue of his fatherland, Philon’s conduct was the opposite of that shown
        by the rest of the citizens. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>For he packed up all his
        belongings and left the city to live beyond the border, at Oropus, where he paid the aliensÕ
        tax and resided under the protection of a patron, since he preferred the life of an alien
        among those people to citizenship with us. And so he would not even do as some citizens did,
        who turned about when they saw the party of Phyle succeeding in their efforts; he did not
        even think fit to take any share in these successes, but chose to come when the business was
        achieved rather than join in the return after achieving something for the advantage of the
        common wealth. For he did not come to the Peiraeus, nor is there any instance of his having
        placed himself at your disposal. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>But I ask you, if on
        seeing us successful he did not shrink from betraying us, what must he have done to us, had
        we failed of our object? Now those who were prevented by private calamities from sharing the
        dangers that then beset the city deserve some indulgence: for misfortune befalls no man of
        his own will. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>But those who acted thus by design merit no
        indulgence, since their conduct was due not to mishap, but to policy. It is a custom
        accepted as just among all mankind that in face of the same crimes we should be most
        incensed with those men who are most able to avoid criminal action, but should be indulgent
        to the poor or disabled because we regard their offences as involuntary. <milestone n="12"
          unit="section"/>This man, therefore, deserves no indulgence; for neither was he disabled
        and thus unfit for hardship, as you see for yourselves, nor did he lack means for the public
        services, as I shall establish. If, then, he was as backward as he was able to help, how
        should he not hated with good reason by you all? <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>Nor
        indeed will you incur the enmity of any of the citizens if you reject him; for it is by no
        means one party, but both, that he has manifestly betrayed, so that he can claim friendship
        neither with those who were in the town (for he did not think fit to stand by them in their
        peril), nor with those who occupied the Peiraeus, since he did not consent to return even
        with them; and that, too, when he was, as he asserts, a townsman!<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">The text here is very doubtful. The meaning seems to be that he claims to be a
          citizen in the fullest sense, yet has not shown any of the feelings of a citizen. He and
          any associates of his are utterly disloyal.</note>
        <milestone n="14" unit="section"/>But if there yet remains a party of the citizens that had
        a share in his proceedings, if ever—may Heaven forfend it!—they get the city into their
        hands, let him claim his seat on the Council with them.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well,
        that he lived at Oropus under the protection of a patron, that he possessed ample means, and
        yet stood to arms neither in the Peiraeus nor in the town, are my first contentions: to make
        sure of their truth, hear the witnesses.<label>Witnesses</label>
        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So now it remains for him
        to state that owing to some infirmity that befell him he was incapacitated from assisting
        the party in the Peiraeus, but that he offered to spend his own resources either in
        contributing to the people’s funds or in arming some of his fellow-townsmen as infantry,
        after the example of many other citizens who were unable to give their loyal services in
        person. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>Now, to preclude him from deceiving you with lies,
        I will give you clear information at once on these points also, since I shall not be at
        liberty afterwards to come forward in this place and expose him. Please call Diotimus of
          Acharnae<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The principal township of <placeName
            key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, 7 miles north of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName>.</note> and those who were appointed with him to arm the townsmen as
        infantry from the funds then contributed. <label>Testimony of Diotimus and
            those Appointed With Him</label>
        
        <milestone n="17" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So this man had no
        intention of aiding the city in such a moment, in such a position of her affairs; his
        purpose was to make a profit out of your disasters. For he set out from Oropus, going
        sometimes alone and sometimes at the head of others who took your misfortunes as so much
        good fortune, and so traversed the countryside: <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>where he
        met with the most elderly citizens who had stayed behind in their townships with scanty
        supplies that barely sufficed them,—men who were attached to the democracy, but unable owing
        to their age to give it their support,—he stripped them of their resources, thinking it more
        important to make his own petty gains than to spare them injury. It is not possible for all
        these to prosecute him today, from the very same cause that disabled them from supporting
        the city: <milestone n="19" unit="section"/>yet this man ought not to benefit twice from
        their disability, and be helped thereby to pass your present scrutiny as he was before to
        rob them of what they had. Nay, if but a single one of those whom he has wronged appears in
        court, make much of it, and utterly detest this man, who could bring himself to strip of
        their resources those on whom other men, out of pity for their straits, freely bestowed
        something from their own. Pray call the witnesses. <label>Witnesses</label>
        <milestone n="20" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well now, I do not see how
        your judgement of him should differ from that of his own people; for the facts are of such a
        nature that, even if he had committed no other offence, they would alone justify his
        rejection. The strange things of which his mother accused him while she was alive I will
        pass over; but on the evidence of the measures that she took at the close of her life you
        can easily judge how he treated her. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>She demurred to
        committing herself to his care after her death, but as she had confidence in Antiphanes, who
        was no connection of hers, she gave him three minae of silver for her burial, ignoring this
        man, who was her own son. Obviously, of course, she was convinced that he would not perform
        the last duties even on the ground of his relationship. <milestone n="22" unit="section"
        />Now I ask you, if a mother,—who is naturally most willing to tolerate even an injury at
        the hands of her own children, and who counts little benefits as great gains because she
        assesses their behavior by affection rather than logic,—believed that this man would seek
        his profit from her even in death, what should be your feeling about him? <milestone n="23"
          unit="section"/>For when a man commits such offences in regard to his own relations, what
        would he do in regard to strangers? To prove that these also are true facts, hear the
        statement of the actual person who received the money and buried her.
        <label>Testimony</label>
        <milestone n="24" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What inducement, then,
        could you have for approving this man? Because he has committed no offence ? But he is
        guilty of the gravest crimes against his country. Or do you think he will reform? Then, I
        say, let him reform first in his bearing towards the city, and claim a seat on the Council
        later, when he has done her a service as signal as the wrong that he did her before. The
        saner course is to recompense everyone for his services after they have been performed; for
        I consider it monstrous that for the offences which he has already committed he is never to
        pay the penalty, but for the benefits which he intends to confer he is to be already
        possessed of honor. <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>Or is it to make the citizens better
        when they see all men honored alike,—is this why he is to be approved? But the danger is
        that good men, when they observe that they and the bad are honored alike, will desist from
        their good behavior, expecting that the same persons who honor the wicked may well be
        forgetful of the virtuous. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>And this further point is
        worthy of your attention,—that whereas anyone who had betrayed a fort or a ship or an army
        which happened to have in it some part of our people, would be visited with the extreme
        penalty, this man, who has betrayed the whole city, is planning not merely to escape
        requital but even to obtain honor! But surely anyone who has betrayed liberty in the
        flagrant manner of this man deserves to be faced with a judgement awarding him, not a seat
        on the Council, but slavery and the heaviest punishment. <milestone n="27" unit="section"
          /><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He argues, so I am told, that, if it was a crime to
        absent himself at that crisis, we should have had a law expressly dealing with it, as in the
        case of all other crimes. He does not expect you to perceive that the gravity of the crime
        was the reason why no law was proposed to deal with it. For what orator would ever have
        conceived, or lawgiver have anticipated, that any of the citizens would be guilty of so
        grave an offence? <milestone n="28" unit="section"/>So, I suppose, if one should desert
        one’s post when the city itself was not in danger, but was rather endangering another
          people,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e., we are to suppose, forsooth, that desertion
          is a crime only when the city is so far from being in danger as to be at war with another
          city.</note> a law would have been made condemning that as a grievous crime; but if one
        deserted the city itself when the city itself was in danger, we should have had no law
        against this! Certainly we should, if there had been a thought that any of the citizens
        would ever commit such a crime. <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>Not a man but would have
        reason to rebuke you, gentlemen, if, after honoring in a manner worthy of the city our
        resident aliens for having supported the democracy beyond the requirements of their duty,
        you are not going to inflict on this man, for having betrayed the city in violation of his
        duty, if not some heavier punishment of another kind, at least the dishonor which you hold
        over him today. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>Recall to your minds what reason you can
        have for honoring those who have proved themselves good servants of the State and for
        dishonoring those who serve her ill. In either case the distinction has been made not so
        much for the sake of those who have come into the world, as of those who are yet to come, in
        order that they may strive to become worthy by studious effort, and in no single direction
        may attempt to be base. <milestone n="31" unit="section"/>Reflect, moreover, on this: what
        kind of oaths do you think he would regard, when by his act he has betrayed his ancestral
        gods? Or how could he give good counsel on our State affairs, when he did not even desire to
        liberate his country? Or what secrets would he keep, when he did not even choose to obey
        public orders? How can it be suitable that this man, who was not even the last to come at
        the call of danger, should be placed in front of those who achieved our success to receive
        this honor today? It would be deplorable if he, who accounted the whole body of our citizens
        as nothing, should not in his single person be disqualified by you. <milestone n="32"
          unit="section"/>I see certain persons who are preparing today to support him and to plead
        with you, since they were not able to seduce me; but in those days of your dangers and
        sorest struggles, when the constitution itself was at stake and you had to contend not
        merely for seats on the Council but for freedom itself, they did not plead with him then to
        support both you and the commonwealth, and to betray neither his country nor the Council, to
        which he now demands admission without any right, since our success was achieved by others.
          <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>He alone, gentlemen of the Council, will have no fair
        cause for complaint if he is not admitted: for it is not you who are debarring him from
        honor today; it is he who deprived himself of it, at the time when he declined to come, with
        a zeal such as brings him now for the drawing of the lots, to take his stand with you then
        as a champion of the Council. <milestone n="34" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>I believe that what I have said is sufficient; and yet there are many things
        that I have omitted. But I am confident that even without these you will make for yourselves
        the decision that is best for the city. To judge of those who are worthy to sit on the
        Council you need no other test than yourselves and the civic character which enabled you to
        pass your own scrutiny. For this man’s conduct sets up a standard that is novel and foreign
        to all democracy.</p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
