<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>De curatione diuturnorum morborum </title>
				<author>Aretaeus</author>
				<editor>Francis Adams LL.D.</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 1, 2005</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Extant Works of Aretaeus, The Cappadocian.</title>
						<author>Aretaeus</author>
						<editor>Francis Adams LL.D.</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>Boston</pubPlace>
							<publisher>Milford House Inc.</publisher>
							<date>1972 (Republication of the 1856 edition).</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="page"/>
			</refsDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="book" n="1">
				<pb n="457"/>
				<head>BOOK I.</head>
				<div type="chapter" n="1">
					<head>CHAPTER I. THE PROŒMIUM.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> chronic diseases, the postponement of medical
						treatment is a bad thing; for, by procrastination, they pass into incurable
						affections, being of such a nature that they do not readily go off if they
						once attack; and if protracted by time, they will become strong, and end
						only in death. Small diseases also are succeeded by greater, so that
						although devoid of danger at first, their progeny proves deadly. Wherefore
						neither should the patient conceal his complaint, from the shame of
						exposure, nor shrink from fear of the treatment; nor should the physician be
						inactive, for thus both would conspire to render the disease incurable. Some
						patients, from ignorance of the present and what will come at last, are
						content to live on with the disease. For since in most cases they do not
						die, so neither do they fear death, nor, for this reason, do they entrust
						themselves to the physician. Cephalæa, of which I am about to treat in the
						first place, is a proof of these statements.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="2">
					<pb n="458"/>
					<head>CHAPTER II. CURE OF CEPHALÆA.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> head, inasmuch as it is necessary towards life,
						so is it also very dangerous in disease. And the onset of diseases about it
						is quite tolerable, being attended with slight pain, noises in the ears, and
						heaviness; but if they acquire increase, they become fatal at last.
						Wherefore even slight pains should not be overlooked, and, in certain cases,
						they have been cured by slight remedies. But if prolonged for a longer
						space, as greater sufferings supervene, we must open the vein at the elbow.
						But, for two days previous, the patient must get wine to drink, and the
						quantity of blood abstracted must be regulated by the strength; and it is
						best not to make the whole evacuation at once, so that the strength may bear
						the amount thereof; and the disease is rather removed by the repetition of
						the means. The same rule applies to all chronic diseases. During an interval
						of three or four days, a fuller diet is to be given, and then the purgative
						hiera is to be taken in a draught; for it, in an especial manner, draws the
						pabulum of the disease from the head. The quantity of the medicine given is
						to be to the amount of four or five drams. And if well purged, we are to
						administer the bath, give wine, and improve the strength. Then again we are
						to open the straight vein (<hi rend="ital">temporal?</hi>) on the forehead,
						for abstraction by it is most efficacious; the amount, about a hemina (<hi
							rend="ital">half-pint?</hi>) or a little more. But we must not evacuate
						further, for we must avoid emptying the vessels. Then, having removed the
						hair with a razor, we are first to apply one cupping-instrument to the
						vertex, and another between the scapulæ, without drawing blood; but along
						with the instrument applied to the vertex,</p>
					<pb n="459"/>
					<p>we are to scarify unsparingly, for the purpose of attracting the redundant
						fluid and of making an incision in the deep-seated parts. For remedial means
						applied even to the bones are beneficial in cephalæa. When the wounds are
						cicatrised, we are to excise a portion of the arteries;<note n="1">See
							Paulus Ægineta, b. vi. 5.</note> (of these there are two, one behind the
						ears, at a little distance from them, being obvious from their pulsations;
						the others in front of the ear, and close to it, for they lie close to the
						antitragus; and these also are discovered by their pulsations); we are to
						incise the larger ones at the bones, for they afford relief. Adjacent to
						them are others, very slender, which there is no benefit from excising. The
						mode of operating has been described under operative surgery. This is the
						great remedy in cephalæa, epilepsy, vertigo, and, in fine, in all the
						diseases of the head.</p>
					<p>In all cases we are to bring off phlegm, first evacuating the bowels, either
						by a purgative draught, or by a clyster; and sometimes from the nostrils by
						sternutatories; and sometimes from the mouth by sialogogues. Among the kinds
						of sternutatories are pepper, the root of soapwort, and the testicle of the
						beaver; these may all be used together; having levigated and sifted them, we
						are to blow the powder in, either with a reed or the thick stalk of a goose
						quill. Euphorbium is more active and stronger than these when mixed with any
						of them. It is also mixed up with the oils, such as <hi rend="ital"
							>gleucinum</hi>, the Sicyonian, or the ointment from storax. It is made
						into a liquid form as an injection, and it is injected by means of a nasal
						pipe; the instrument consists of two pipes united together by one outlet, so
						that we can inject by both at the same time. For to dilate each nostril
						separately is a thing which could not be borne, as the head gets quickly
						filled, and thus contracts a sharp pain. The medicines which evacuate phlegm
						from the mouth are, mustard, the <hi rend="ital">granum cnidium</hi>,</p>
					<pb n="460"/>
					<p>pepper, stavesacre, these either together or separately; and one may
						masticate these substances and spit out constantly; and give them mixed up
						with water or honeyed-water, rinse the mouth, and press them back to the
						tonsils with stretching of the neck, thus wash out along with the breath in
							expiration;<note n="2">This is rather an obscure description of the
							simple process of <hi rend="ital">gargling.</hi> See the note of
							Petit.</note> and when you have evacuated phlegm as much as you think
						proper, you must bathe and foment the head with a very large quantity of hot
						water to promote perspiration, for the obstructions become strong.</p>
					<p>Supper should be spare; but wine also is to be given, to restore the tone of
						the stomach, for it also suffers in this complaint. When, in the meantime,
						you have re-established the strength, you will require to give a common
						clyster having sprinkled upon it much natron, or dissolving it in two drams
						of the resin of the turpentine tree. On the next day we are to abstract
						blood from the inside of the nostrils, and for this purpose push into them
						the long instrument named <hi rend="ital">Katidion</hi>, or the one named
							<hi rend="ital">Toryne</hi>, or, in want of these, we must take the
						thick quill of a goose, and having scooped the nervous part of it into teeth
						like a saw, we are to push it down the nostrils as far as the ethmoid cells,
						then shake it with both hands so that the part may be scarified by its
						teeth. Thus we shall have a ready and copious flow of blood; for slender
						veins terminate there, and the parts are soft and easily cut. The common
						people have many modes of scarification, by rough herbs, and the dried
						leaves of the bay, which they introduce with the fingers and move
							strongly.<note n="3">On this practice, see Paulus Ægineta, tom. i. p.
							326, Syd. Soc. Edit.</note> Having evacuated to a sufficient amount--say
						to the amount of half a hemina--we are to wipe the parts with sponges and
						oxycrate, or blow in some styptic powder, gall, fissil alum, or the flower
						of the wild pomegranate.</p>
					<pb n="461"/>
					<p>Whether the pain remain, or cease after these things, we must go on to the
						conclusion of the system of treatment; for the mischief is apt to return,
						and frequently lurks in the seat of the disease. Wherefore, having removed
						the hair with a razor (and this also is beneficial to the head), we are to
						burn with heated cauteries, superficially, down to the muscles; or if you
						wish to carry the burning to the bone, you must avoid the muscles, for the
						muscles when burnt occasion convulsions. And if you burn superficially you
						must foment the part with plenty of fragrant sweet wine, along with
						rose-oil; a linen cloth wetted with this is to be spread over the eschars
						until the third day. But, if the eschars be deep, having pounded the hairy
						leaves of leeks with salt, and spread upon a linen rag, we are to apply it.
						On the third day, we are to put the cerate from rose-oil upon the
						superficial eschars, and lentil with honey upon the deeper. The medicinal
						applications to be made to the wound will be described in another place.
						Some have made an incision in the skin above the forehead, at the coronal
						suture, down to the bone, and having scraped it, or cut out a portion down
						to the diploe, have afterwards brought the part to incarnation. Some have
						perforated the bone, even to the meningx. These are bold remedies, but are
						to be used, if, after all, the cephalæa continue, and the patient be
						courageous, and the tone of the body good.<note n="4">On this <hi
								rend="ital">heroic</hi> method of treating diseases of the head, see
							Paulus Ægineta, t.ii. pp. 248-250, and 258, Syd. Soc. Edit. Before
							making trial of it, I would recommend the reader to consult the part of
							De Haen's works there referred to.</note></p>
					<p>But, if they progress gradually, they are to take exercises in the erect
						state of the body for the benefit of the chest and shoulders; the <hi
							rend="ital">chironomy</hi>,<note n="5">See Oribasius, vi. 30, and p.663,
							ed. Bussemaker and Daremberg.</note> the throwing of the <hi rend="ital"
							>halteres</hi>; leaping, and the well-regulated contortions of the body
						accompanying</p>
					<pb n="462"/>
					<p>it; friction, first and last of the limbs, of the head in the middle of the
						process.</p>
					<p>The process of pitching<note n="6">See Paulus Ægineta, t.i. p. 82, Syd. Soc.
							Edit.</note> is to be frequently applied to the head; and also
						rubefacients, sometimes rubbing in mustard with double quantity of bread, so
						that the heat may not be intolerable; and sometimes other medicines are to
						be so used, like the compound from lemnestis, euphorbium, and pellitory. The
						juice of thapsia, and the medicines made with it which produce swelling of
						the skin, and an eruption resembling vari, are beneficial both for allaying
						present pain and contributing to eradicate the evil.</p>
					<p>The diet in both kinds of the complaint should be light; little drink, water
						for drink, especially before giving any medicine; complete abstinence from
						acrid things, such as onions, garlic, the juice of silphium, but not
						altogether from mustard, for its acrimony, in addition to its being
						stomachic, is not unpleasant to the head, dissolving phlegm, and exhaling or
						discharging downwards. Of pulse, the worst is the common bean and its
						species, the common peas, and the species called <hi rend="ital"
							>ochrys</hi>,<note n="7">The <hi rend="ital">pisum ochrys.</hi></note>
						and the common kidney-beans; next to them are the lentils, which have indeed
						certain good properties for promoting digestion and secretion, but induce
						fulness of the head and occasion pain; only when boiled with pepper they are
						not to be rejected. Granulated spelt (<hi rend="ital">alica</hi>) when
						washed, is pleasant along with wine and honey, so as to sweeten, and, in
						like manner, their soups, and with plain broths. The seeds of carui,
						coriander, anise, and parsley, in the Lydian sauce<note n="8">See Hesychius,
							under <foreign xml:lang="grc">KHRUKEI/A</foreign> and -- <foreign
								xml:lang="grc">KH</foreign>, Athen. Deip. p. 516, Ed. Casaub.</note>
						are excellent. But, of these articles, the best are the herbs mint and
						penny-royal, with the fragrant things which have some diuretic and
						carminative properties. Of fleshes, all such</p>
					<pb n="463"/>
					<p>as are old are bad; of the recently killed, that of the hen is good; of
						birds, the wood pigeon, the common pigeon, and such others as are not very
						fat; the extremities of the swine; the roasted hare; that of the ox and of
						the sheep is incrassant and fills the head; the kid is not altogether bad.
						Milk and cheese occasion headache. Of fishes, those found among rocks, and
						those things that are best in each particular country. Of potherbs, such as
						promote the urinary and alvine discharges, the mallow, the blite, the beet,
						and asparagus; but the kale is also acrid. Among raw articles, the lettuce
						is the best of all. Roots are bad, even when boiled, such as radishes,
						navews, and parsnips, which are diuretic, but occasion repletion; the garden
						parsnip indeed is flatulent and swells up the stomach. Wine which is white,
						thin, and sweet, is to be admitted, if it have some astringency, so as not
						to bind the bowels. All articles of the dessert occasion headache, except
						dates of every species. In autumn the fig and grape are wholesome, and
						whatever other fruit is very good at any particular season. Repletion of all
						things, even of such as are proper, is bad; and so, also, indigestion is
						bad. Lassitude is less injurious than indigestion, but still it is hurtful.
						The morning walk after evacuation of the bowels, but so as not to affect the
						breathing nor induce weariness; and it is also very good after supper.
						Prolonged gestation, not exposed to wind or sun, is good for the head; but
						the dog-star is bad for it. Sexual intercourse is a self-inflicted evil to
						the head and nerves. A journey from a cold to a warmer climate, or from a
						humid to a drier, is proper; also a sea-voyage, and passing one's life at
						sea; and if one lives by the sea-side it is a good thing to bathe in the
						sea-water, to tumble on the sands, and to reside close by the sea.</p>
					<p>The remedies for <hi rend="ital">heterocrania</hi> are the same; for it is
						well to apply to a portion of the head the same remedies as are proper for
						the whole of it. In all cases in which the disease is not</p>
					<pb n="464"/>
					<p>removed by these means, we are to use hellebore, as being the last and most
						potent of all methods of treatment.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="3">
					<head>CHAPTER III. CURE OF VERTIGO.</head>
					<p>V<hi rend="smallcaps">ERTIGO</hi> arises as the successor of cephalæa; but
						also springs up as a primary affection from certain causes, as the
						suppression of the hemorrhoidal flux; and if blood which used to flow from
						the nose has ceased to flow; or if the body has not perspired properly,
						either by sweating, or labour, when it had been used to labour. If then it
						arise as the consequence of cephalæa, we must do for its cure those things
						which have been described under cephalæa; and I will afterwards state
						certain other more powerful means which must be tried ultimately. But if the
						disease happen from the suppression of any of the humours, we must excite
						the customary secretion; for the recurrence of nature promotes recovery. If
						it be delayed, and the disease increases, in the other suppressions, those
						by the nose or sweats, we are to open the vein at the elbow; but in plethora
						of the liver, spleen, or any of the viscera in the middle of the body,
						cupping affords relief, but as much blood as is taken from a vein, so much
						is to be thus abstracted from them; for it is the nutriment of the exciting
						cause, in like manner as the belly. After this the remedies of the head are
						to be applied, opening the straight vein on the forehead, or those at the
						canthi on either side of the nose; a cupping-instrument is to be fastened to
						the vertex, the (<hi rend="ital">temporal?</hi>) arteries are to be excised,
						the head shaven, rubefacients applied to it, phlegm evacuated from the
						nostrils by sternutatories, or from the mouth as I have stated--all these
						things are to be</p>
					<pb n="465"/>
					<p>done in the order described under cephalæa, except that the juice of
						sow-bread or of pimpernel is to be used as an injection into the nose.</p>
					<p>But when you have exhausted all the remedies for cephalæa, the more violent
						means which are applicable for vertigo are to be used; we must use the
						emetics after supper, and those from radishes, which is also required as a
						preparation for the hellebore; for the stomach is to be trained beforehand
						to the more violent emetics. But the phlegm now becomes thinner, and fit for
						solution in the hellebore. There are several modes of giving the hellebore;
						to the stronger sort of patients it is to be given to the size of a <hi
							rend="ital">sesame</hi>,<note n="1">The <hi rend="ital">sesamum
								orientale</hi>, or oily-grain of the East. See Appendix to the
							Edinburgh Greek Lexicon.</note> or a little larger; or, in slices, with
						washed chondrus or lentil, the dose, about two drams. In the case of feebler
						and more slender persons, the decoction with honey, to the amount of two or
						three spoonfuls, is to be given. The manner of preparing it will be
						described else-where. In the interval between each remedy, the patient is to
						be supported, in order that he may be able to endure what is to be given in
						the intermediate periods.</p>
					<p>The patient is to be assisted during the paroxysms thus:--The legs are to be
						bound above the ankles and knees; and the wrists, and the arms below the
						shoulders at the elbows. The head is to be bathed with rose-oil and vinegar;
						but in the oil we must boil wild-thyme, cow-parsnip, ivy, or something such.
						Friction of the extremities and face. Smelling to vinegar, penny-royal, and
						mint, and these things with vinegar. Separation of the jaws, for sometimes
						the jaws are locked together; the tonsils to be tickled to provoke vomiting;
						for by the discharge of phlegm they are sometimes roused from their gloom.
						These things, then, are to be done, in order to alleviate the paroxysm and
						dispel the gloomy condition.</p>
					<pb n="466"/>
					<p>With regard to the regimen during the whole period of the treatment and
						afterwards, I hold as follows:--Much sleep is bad, and likewise
						insomnolency; for truly much sleep stupefies the senses of the head. From a
						redundance of vapours there is disinclination to every exertion; and these
						are also the cause of the weight in the head, the noises, and the flashes of
						light, which are the marks of the disease. Insomnolency induces dyspepsia,
						atrophy, and wearies out the body; the spirits flag, and the understanding
						is unsettled; and for these reasons such patients readily pass into mania
						and melancholy. Moderate sleep is suitable for the proper digestion of the
						food and refreshment from the labours of the day; care and perseverance in
						these respects; and particular attention is to be paid to the evacuation of
						the bowels, for the belly is the greater source of the bodily perspiration.
						Next, friction of the limbs, by means of rough towels, so as to produce
						rubefaction; then, of the back and sides; last, of the head. Afterwards,
						exercise in walking, gentle at first and in the end; carried to running in
						the middle; rest and tranquillity of the breathing (<hi rend="ital"
							>pneuma</hi>) after the walking. They are to practise vociferation,
						using grave tones, for sharp occasion distension of the head, palpitation of
						the temples, pulsatory movements of the brain, fulness of the eyes, and
						noises in the ears. Sounds of medium intensity are beneficial to the head.
						Then the season of gestation should be regulated so as to promote the
						expulsion of the weight in the head; it should be prolonged, yet not so as
						to induce fatigue; neither should gestation be made in tortuous places, nor
						where there are frequent bendings of the road, for these are provocative of
						vertigo. But let the walks be straight, long, and smooth. If then the
						patients have been in the habit of taking lunch, we must only allow of a
						little bread, so as to be no impediment to the exercises; for digestion
						should take place previously. The head and the hands, and the frictions
						thereof, are to be attended to; in the latter it</p>
					<pb n="467"/>
					<p>is to be gently performed for the restoration of the heat, for plumpness, and
						strength. Then the head is to be rubbed while the patient stands erect below
						a person of higher stature than himself. Gymnastics skilfully performed
						which tend to distension of the neck, and strong exercise of the hands. It
						is proper, also, by raising the head, to exercise the eyes at <hi
							rend="ital">chironomy</hi>, or at throwing the quoit, or contending at
						boxing. The exercise both with the large and the small ball is bad, for the
						rolling of the head and eyes, and the intense fixing of them, occasion
						vertigo. Leaping and running are very excellent; for everything that is keen
						is beneficial to the limbs, and gives tone to the general system.<note n="2"
							>For an account of most of the ancient exercises mentioned by our
							author, see Paulus Ægineta, t. i. p. 22--27, Syd. Soc. Edit.</note> The
						cold bath is better than no bath at all; no bath at all is better than the
						hot bath: the cold bath is very powerful as an astringent, incrassant, and
						desiccant of the head, which is the condition of health; while the warm bath
						is most powerful to humectate, relax, and create mistiness; for these are
						the causes of disease of the head, and such also are south winds, which
						occasion dulness of hearing. There should be rest after exercises, to allay
						the perturbation. Pinching of the head, even to the extent of producing
						excoriation of the skin.</p>
					<p>Whetters made of water, or of wine diluted with water, should be given before
						a meal. Lunch should be slight: laxatives from the capillary leaves of
						pot-herbs,--of mallow, of beet, and of blite. A condiment of a stomachic
						nature, which is pleasant to the mouth, laxative of the bowels, and not
						calculated to induce heaviness of the head, is made of thyme, or of savory,
						or of mustard. Eggs, hot in winter, and cold in summer, stripped of their
						shell, not roasted; olives, dates, pickled meat in season. Granulated spelt
						washed, with some of the sweet things, so as to give it a relish, is to be
						chosen; and, with</p>
					<pb n="468"/>
					<p>these, salts. Solitude, rest as regards hearing and speaking. Promenades in a
						well-ventilated place, rendered agreeable by trees or herbs. But if it be
						come to supper-time, they are again especially to take the cold bath, having
						been slightly anointed with oil; or, otherwise, the limbs only. The supper
						should be of frumentaceous articles, such as pastry, or a soup from chondrus
						(granulated spelt), or a carminative ptisan, rendered easy of digestion by
						boiling. The medicines used for seasoning of the ptisan, pepper,
						penny-royal, mint, a small proportion of onions or of leeks, not so much as
						to float on the stomach; the acrid part of vinegar is suitable; of fleshes,
						the parts of fat animals which are not fat; of swine, the feet and head; all
						winged animals--you must select from the great variety of them what is
						suitable; the hare and the other kinds of venison are proper; the hen is
						easily procured, and suitable. All articles of the dessert create headaches,
						except the date, or figs in the summer season, or the grape if the patient
						be free from flatulence; and of sweetmeats, such as are well seasoned,
						without fat, and light. Walking, exhilaration; in solitude, resignation to
						sleep.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="4">
					<head>CHAPTER IV. CURE OF EPILEPSY.</head>
					<p>O<hi rend="smallcaps">F</hi> remedies, whatever is great and most powerful is
						needed for epilepsy, so as to find an escape not only from a painful
						affection, and one dangerous at each attack, but from the disgust and
						opprobrium of this calamity. For it appears to me, that if the patients who
						endure such sufferings were to look at one another in the paroxysms, they
						would no longer submit to live. But the want of sensibility and of seeing
						conceals from</p>
					<pb n="469"/>
					<p>every one what is dreadful and disgusting in his own case. It is best that
						the method of cure should follow the alleviation of nature, when, with the
						changes of age, she changes greatly the man. For if the diet akin to the
						ailment, and on which the disease subsisted, be changed, the disease no
						longer seizes the man, but takes its departure along with that in which it
							delighted.<note n="1">See Hippocrat. Aph. ii. 45.</note></p>
					<p>If, then, it seize on the head, it settles there; to it, therefore, we are to
						do those things which have been described by me under cephalæa, regarding
						the abstraction of blood (and also the purgings) from the veins at the
						elbow, the straight vein at the forehead, and by cupping; but the
						abstraction is not to be carried the length of deliquium animi; for
						deliquium has a tendency to induce the disease; we are to open all the
						ordinary arteries before and behind the ears, and we are also to practise
						purgings, which are more potent than all these things, by the purgative <hi
							rend="ital">hiera</hi> and those medicines which draw off phlegm from
						the head; but the medicines should be particularly powerful, for the habit
						of such persons renders them tolerant of pains, and their goodness of
						spirits and good hopes render them strong in endurance. It is necessary,
						also, to apply heat to the head, for it is effectual. In the first place, we
						must perforate the bone as far as the diploe, and then use cerates and
						cataplasms until the meninx separate from the bone. The exposed bones are to
						be perforated with the trepan if still any small portion prevent its
						spontaneous removal, when the meninx there is found black and thickened; and
						when, having gone through the process of putrefaction and cleansing under
						the bold treatment of the physician, the wound comes to complete
						cicatrization, the patients escape from the disease. In all cases we are to
						use rubefacient applications to the head; namely, the common ones, as
						described by</p>
					<pb n="470"/>
					<p>me formerly; and a still more powerful one is that from cantharides, but for
						three days before using it the patient must drink milk as a protection of
						the bladder, for cantharides are very injurious to the bladder. These are
						the remedies when the head is the part affected.</p>
					<p>But if the cause be seated in the middle parts, and if these induce the
						disease (this, however, very rarely happens, for, as in a mighty ailment,
						the middle parts of the body rather sympathise with the head, which is the
						origin of the disease), but however it may be, we must open the vein at the
						elbow in these cases also; for the flow by it is from the viscera. But such
						patients, more than the others, are to be purged with the <hi rend="ital"
							>hiera, cneoron</hi>,<note n="2">The rock-rose, or <hi rend="ital"
								>Daphne cneorum</hi>, L.</note> and the <hi rend="ital">granum
							cnidium</hi>,<note n="3">Seed of the <hi rend="ital">Daphne
								cnidium.</hi> See Paulus Ægineta, t. iii. p. 179.</note> for these
						are phlegmagogues. But the most suitable remedy in these cases is cupping.
						Of epithemes and cataplasms the components are well known, and it would be
						superfluous to describe them on all occasions, except in so far as to know
						the powers of them; namely, that by such means we must attenuate, promote
						exhalation, and render the secretions and perspirations healthy. We are also
						to use digestive, heating, desiccant, and diuretic articles, both in food
						and in medicine. But the best of all things is castor, taken frequently
						during the month in honeyed-water, and the compound medicines which possess
						the same powers, as the compound medicine from vipers, and the still more
						complex one of Mithridates, and also that of Vestinus; for these things
						promote digestion, form healthy juices, and are diuretic; for whatever
						simple medicines you could describe are contained in these powerful
						compositions -- cinnamon. cassia, the leaves of melabathrum, pepper, and all
						the varieties of seseli; and which of the most potent medicines will you not
						find in them? It is told, that the brain of a vulture, and the heart of a
						raw cormorant, and the domestic weasel, when</p>
					<pb n="471"/>
					<p>eaten, remove the disease; but I have never tried these things. However, I
						have seen persons holding a cup below the wound of a man recently
						slaughtered, and drinking a draught of the blood! O the present, the mighty
						necessity, which compels one to remedy the evil by such a wicked
						abomination! And whether even they recovered by this means no one could tell
						me for certain. There is another story of the liver of a man having been
						eaten. However, I leave these things to be described by those who would bear
						to try such means.</p>
					<p>It is necessary to regulate the diet, in respect to everything that is to be
						done either by others or by the patient himself. Now nothing must be
						omitted, nor anything unnecessarily done; and more especially we must
						administer everything which will do the slightest good, or even that will do
						no harm; for many unseemly sights, sounds, and tastes, and multitudes of
						smells, are tests of the disease. Everything, therefore, is to be
						particularly attended to. Much sleep induces fatness, torpor, and mistiness
						of the senses, but moderate sleep is good. An evacuation of the bowels,
						especially of flatulence and phlegm, is very good after sleep. Promenades
						long, straight, without tortuosities, in a well ventilated place, under
						trees of myrtle and laurel, or among acrid and fragrant herbs, such as
						calamint, penny-royal, thyme, and mint; so much the better if wild and
						indigenous, but if not, among cultivated; in these places, prolonged
						gestation, which also should be straight. It is a good thing to take
						journeys, but not by a river side, so that he may not gaze upon the stream
						(for the current of a river occasions vertigo), nor where he may see
						anything turned round, such as a rolling-top, for he is too weak to preserve
						the animal spirits (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>) steady, which are,
						therefore, whirled about in a circle, and this circular motion is
						provocative of vertigo and of epilepsy. After the gestation, a gentle walk,
						then rest so as to induce tranquillity of the agitation created by the
						gestation. After these, the exercises</p>
					<pb n="472"/>
					<p>of the arms, their extremities being rubbed with a towel made of raw flax.
						Not much oil to be used in the inunction. The friction to be protracted, and
						harder than usual for condensation, since most of them are bloated and fat:
						the head to be rubbed in the middle of the process, while the patient stands
						erect. The exercises of the neck and shoulders, <hi rend="ital"
							>chironomy</hi>, and the others mentioned by me under the treatment of
						Vertigo, with sufficient fulness of detail; only the exercises should be
						sharper, so as to induce sweat and heat, for all these attenuate. During the
						whole of his life he should cultivate a keen temper without
						irascibility.</p>
					<p>All kinds of food derived from gross pulse are bad; but we are to give
						frumentaceous things, the drier sorts of bread, washed alica, and the drinks
						prepared from them. The medicines added for relish the same as before; but
						there should be more of acrid things, such as pepper, ginger, and lovage.
						Sauces of vinegar and cumin are both pleasant and useful. From fleshes in
						particular the patient is to be entirely restricted, or at least during the
						cure; for the restoration, those things are to be allowed which are
						naturally light, such as all sorts of winged animals, with the exception of
						the duck, and such as are light in digestion, such as hares, swines' feet,
						and pickled fish, after which thirst is good. A white, thin, fragrant, and
						diuretic wine is to be drunk in small quantity. Of boiled pot-herbs, such as
						are possessed of acrid powers, attenuate and prove diuretic, as the cabbage,
						asparagus, and nettle; of raw, the lettuce in the season of summer. The
						cucumber and ripe melon are unsuitable to a strong man; but certain persons
						may have just a tasting of them. But being of a cold and humid nature, much
						of them is bad. The seasonable use may be granted of the green fig and the
						grape. Promenades; after these, recreation to dispel grief.</p>
					<p>Passion is bad, as also sexual enjoyment; for the act itself bears the
						symptoms of the disease. Certain physicians have</p>
					<pb n="473"/>
					<p>fallen into a mistake respecting coition; for seeing that the physical change
						to manhood produces a beneficial effect, they have done violence to the
						nature of children by unseasonable coition, as if thus to bring them sooner
						to manhood. Such persons are ignorant of the spontaneous law of nature by
						which all cures are accomplished; for along with every age she produces that
						which is proper for it in due seasons. At a given time there is the maturity
						of semen, of the beard, of hoary hairs; for on the one hand what physician
						could alter Nature's original change in regard to the semen, and, on the
						other, the appointed time for each? But they also offend against the nature
						of the disease; for being previously injured by the unseasonableness of the
						act, they are not possessed of seasonable powers at the proper commencement
						of the age for coition.</p>
					<p>The patients ought to reside in hot and dry places, for the disease is of a
						cold and humid nature.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="5">
					<head>CHAPTER V. CURE OF MELANCHOLY.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> cases of melancholy, there is need of
						consideration in regard to the abstraction of blood, from which the disease
						arises, but it also springs from cacochymy in no small amount thereof. When,
						therefore, the disease seizes a person in early life, and during the season
						of spring we are to open the median vein at the right elbow, so that there
						may be a seasonable flow from the liver; for this viscus is the fountain of
						the blood, and the source of the formation of the bile, both which are the
						pabulum of melancholy. We must open a vein even if the patients be spare and
						have deficient blood, but abstract little, so that the strength may feel the
						evacuation</p>
					<pb n="474"/>
					<p>but may not be shaken thereby; for even though the blood be thick, bilious,
						coagulated, and black as the lees of oil, yet still it is the seat and the
						pabulum of Nature. If, then, you abstract more than enough, Nature, by the
						loss of nourishment, is ejected from her seat. But if the patient has much
						blood, for the most part in such cases it is not much vitiated, but still we
						must open a vein, and not abstract all the blood required the same day, but
						after an interval, or, if the whole is taken the same day, the strength will
						indicate the amount. During the interval, the patient is to be allowed a
						fuller diet than usual, in order to prepare him for enduring the evacuation;
						for we must assist the stomach, it being in a state of disease, and distress
						from the black bile lodging there. Wherefore, having kept the patient on a
						restricted diet for one day previously, we must give black hellebore to the
						amount of two drams with honeyed-water, for it evacuates black bile. And
						likewise the capillary leaves of Attic thyme, for it also evacuates black
						bile. But it is best to mix them together, and give a part of each, to the
						amount of two drams altogether. After the purging we are to administer the
						bath, and give a little wine and any other seasoner in the food; for purging
						fatigues the powers of the stomach. We are, then, to come down to the middle
						parts, and having first relaxed by cataplasms and bathing, we are to apply a
						cupping-instrument over the liver and stomach, or the mouth of it; for this
						evacuation is much more seasonable than venesection. We are also to apply it
						to the back between the scapulæ, for to this place the stomach is adjacent.
						Then again we are to recruit; and if the strength be restored by the
						regimen, we are to shave the head, and afterwards apply the
						cupping-instrument to it, for the primary and greatest cause of the disease
						is in the nerves. But neither are the senses free from injury, for hence are
						their departure and commencement. Wherefore these also are changed, by
						participating in the affection. Some, likewise,</p>
					<pb n="475"/>
					<p>from alienation of the senses have perverted feelings. It is necessary, then,
						especially to cure the stomach as being disordered of itself, and from black
						bile being lodged in it. Wherefore we must give to drink continuously of the
						juice of wormwood from a small amount to a cupful (<hi rend="ital"
							>cyathus</hi>), for it prevents the formation of bile. Aloe also is a
						good thing, for it brings down the bile into the lower gut. If, then, the
						disease be of recent origin, and the patient be not much changed, he will
						require no other treatment in these circumstances. There is a necessity,
						however, for the remaining part of the regimen to the restoration of the
						habits, and the complete purification of the affection, and the
						strengthening of the powers, so that the diseases may not relapse. I will
						explain afterwards the course of life during convalescence.</p>
					<p>But if the disease, having yielded a little to these means, should be seen
						relapsing, there will be need of greater remedies. Let there, then, be no
						procrastination of time, but if the disease appear after suppression of the
						catamenial discharge in women, or the hemorrhoidal flux in men, we must
						stimulate the parts to throw off their accustomed evacuation. But if it is
						delayed and does not come, the blood having taken another direction, and if
						the disease progress rapidly, we must make evacuations, beginning from the
						ankles. And if you cannot get away from this place so much blood as you
						require, you must also open the vein at the elbow. And after pursuing the
						restorative process for three or four days, we are to give the purgative
						medicine, the hiera. Then we are to apply the cupping-instrument to the
						middle parts of the body, bringing it near to the liver, and do those things
						which speedily prove effectual; for melancholy does not yield to small
						remedies, and, if long continued, it remains fixed in a spot. And if the
						disease lodge in all parts of the body,--in the senses, the understanding,
						the blood, and the bile,--and if it seize on the nerves, and turn to an
						incurable</p>
					<pb n="476"/>
					<p>condition, it engenders in the system a progeny of other diseases,--spasms,
						mania, paralysis. And if they arise from melancholy, the newly-formed
						diseases are incurable. Wherefore we are to use hellebore for the cure of
						the ailment. But before the administration of the hellebore, we must train
						the stomach to vomiting, attenuate the humours, and render the whole system
						freely perspirable; emetics will accomplish these things sometimes those
						which are given with an empty stomach, and sometimes those which consist of
						radishes. I will describe the mode and materials of it; and I will also
						describe the species of hellebore and the modes of using it; and how we
						ought to judge of everything beforehand, and how to render assistance during
						the operation of the emetics. It cannot be doubted that by these means the
						disease has either been entirely removed or had intervals of several years.
						For generally melancholy is again engendered. But if it be firmly
						established, we are no longer to hesitate, but must have recourse to
						everything relating to the hellebore. It is impossible, indeed, to make all
						the sick well, for a physician would thus be superior to a god; but the
						physician can produce respite from pain, intervals in diseases, and render
						them latent. In such cases, the physician can either decline and deny his
						assistance, alleging as an excuse the incurable nature of the disease, or
						continue to the last to render his services. The hiera from aloe is to be
						given again and again; for this is the important medicine in melancholy,
						being the remedy for the stomach, the liver, and the purging of bile. But
						experience has proved, that the seed of mallow, to the amount of a dram,
						when taken in a drink with water answers excellently. But there are many
						other simple medicines which are useful, some in one case, and some in
						another.</p>
					<p>After these sufferings, the patient is to be recruited. For, in certain
						cases, during the time of this treatment, the disease has been removed; but
						if the patient come to a renewal of his</p>
					<pb n="477"/>
					<p>flesh and of his strength, all traces of the disease become eradicated. For
						the strength of nature produces health, but her weakness, disease. Let the
						patient, then, proceed to the process of restoration by frequenting the
						natural hot baths; for the medicinal substances in them are beneficial, such
						as bitumen, or sulphur, or alum, and many others besides these which are
						possessed of remedial powers. For, after the parching heat of the disease,
						and the annoyance of the treatment, dilution is a good thing. Moreover, rare
						and soft flesh most readily throws off the disease; but in melancholy the
						flesh is dry and dense. An oily liniment, by gentle friction, with much oil
						containing . . . . . . . . . . . . washed bread, with something sweet, as
						the Cretan must, and the Scybelitic from Pamphylia, or wine and honey which
						have been mixed up together for some time. Eggs, both cold and hot, which
						have been stripped of their shells. Of fleshes, such as are not fatty, and
						are detergent. Of swine, the feet and the parts about the head. Of fowls,
						the wings, which are not fatty. Of wild animals, hares, goats, and deer. Of
						autumnal fruits, whatever is excellent in its kind. When the stomach rejects
						the food, we must consider beforehand that what is taken be not vomited up.
						Wherefore, before giving food, we are to administer honeyed-water to the
						amount of half a cyathus, which, being drunk, is vomited up again for
						cleansing the stomach. For, in this way, the food remains in the stomach.
						Medicines which are purgative of the necessary discharges are--the fruit of
						the pine, of the nettle, and seeds of the <hi rend="ital"
							>coccalus,</hi><note n="1">Galen identifies the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>KO/KKALOS</foreign> of Hippocrates (<hi rend="ital">de vict.
								Acut.</hi>) with <foreign xml:lang="grc">KW=NOS</foreign>, or the
							fruit of the <hi rend="ital">pinus pinea.</hi> Our author would seem to
							make them distinct substances. There being several species of the pine
							tribe, it is not always easy to distinguish them from one
							another.</note> and pepper; bitter almonds; and let honey give it
						consistence. But if you wish to dry, the best thing is myrrh, or the root of
						iris, the medicine from vipers, and that of Vestinus, of Mithridates,
						and</p>
					<pb n="478"/>
					<p>many others. For the epithemes, the <hi rend="ital">materiel</hi> of
						cataplasms, melilot and poppies, and the tear (gum?) of turpentine, and
						hyssop, and the oil of roses, or of vine-flowers; wax should give
						consistence to all these. Liniments of oil; gestation, promenades, and
						whatever promotes the reproduction of flesh, and the strength of the powers,
						and the restoration of nature to its pristine state of * * * * * * * * * * *
						* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="6">
					<head>CHAPTER VIII. CURE OF PHTHISIS.</head>
					<p>. . . . . as in a ship and in a calm. And if the patient have it fortunately
						at his command, gestation and living on the sea will be beneficial. For the
						sea-water contributes something desiccant to the ulcers. After the
						gestation, having rested, the patient is now to be anointed with fat oil.
						After the frictions . . . . . . . . . . . from a small dose gradually up to
						five or six heminæ, or even much more; or if not, as much as one can, for
						often this alone sufficeth in place of all food. For milk is pleasant to
						take, is easy to drink, gives solid nourishment, and is more familiar than
						any other food to one from a child. In colour it is pleasant to see: as a
						medicine it seems to lubricate the windpipe, to clean, as if with a feather,
						the bronchi, and to bring off phlegm, improve the breathing, and facilitate
						the discharges downwards. To ulcers it is a sweet medicine, and milder than
						anything else. If one, then, will only drink plenty of this, he will not
						stand in need of anything else. For it is a good thing that, in a disease,
						milk should prove both food and medicine. And, indeed, the races of men
						called <hi rend="ital">Galactophagi</hi></p>
					<pb n="479"/>
					<p>use no food from grain. But yet it is a very good thing to use porridge,
						pastry, washed groats of spelt (<hi rend="ital">alica</hi>), and the other
						edibles prepared with milk. And if other food is required, let it be of the
						same nature, as the juice of ptisan, well-concocted and plain; but it is to
						be so seasoned as that it may become easy to swallow; or if anything be
						added as a seasoner, let it be something medicinal, as the hair (<hi
							rend="ital">capillary leaves</hi>?) of lovage, penny-royal, mint, and a
						little of salts, vinegar, or honey. If the stomach suffer from dyspepsia,
						this is to be given; but if there be no such necessity, ptisan is of all
						things the best. One may also change the ptisan for alica, for this is less
						flatulent, and of easier digestion, and becomes detergent if, when used in
						the ptisan, the grain be bruised. When the sputa are unusually fluid, the
						bean cleanses the ulcers, but is flatulent. The pea and the <hi rend="ital"
							>pisum ochrys</hi>, in so far as they are less flatulent, are in the
						same degree inferior as cleansers of the ulcers. Forming a judgment, then,
						from present symptoms, select accordingly. Their condiments are to be such
						as described respecting the ptisan. Eggs from the fire, in a liquid state,
						but hot; they are best when newly laid, before the * * * * * * * * * * * * *
						* * * * * * * * *</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="7">
					<head>CHAPTER XIII. CURE OF THE LIVER.</head>
					<p>. . . in the liver the ulcer may be dangerous. But the most troublesome is a
						defluxion of pus on the stomach, when it makes the stomach its route in the
						course of being distributed upwards. For the food is the cause of life, but
						the stomach is</p>
					<pb n="480"/>
					<p>the leader in the process of nutrition, and it also sometimes conveys
						medicines to the internal parts. If, then, in addition to all the other
						evils, a difficulty of deglutition come on, the patient must speedily die of
						disease and famine. But the indications by which it is discovered in what
						direction the pus will be diverted are diversified. If it pass by the
						intestines, there are tormina, watery discharges from the bowels, phlegm,
						and bile; then clots of blood floating in a fluid, or a thin discharge like
						the washings of raw flesh. But, if it pass by the bladder, there is a weight
						in the kidneys and loins; at first, therefore, the evacuations are copious,
						and tinged with bile; then turbid, which do not deposit their sediment, nor
						get settled. In all cases the sediment should become white. But if it be
						determined upwards to the stomach, nausea, loss of appetite, vomitings of
						phlegm or of bile, deliquium, and vertigo supervene, until it burst.</p>
					<p>This, then, is to be especially avoided, as being a bad course. But if the
						defluxion of pus be more violent, we must take every means, assisting the
						stomach by food, and medicines, and regimen, all in a mild way. We must
						administer the medicines for bursting the abscess; give to drink of the herb
						hyssop with honeyed-water, and the juice of the hair of horehound, and this
						with honeyed-water and the juice of the wormwood. These things must be given
						before food to dilute the fluids, to lubricate the parts, and facilitate the
						rupture of the abscesses. We are also to give the milk of an ass, which is
						soft, not bilious, nutritious, does not admit of being made into cheese,
						which is the perfection of milk. We should gratify the patient in regard to
						food and drink. And we are even to give things inferior to other more
						beneficial articles (for we thereby afford a passage to the fluid which
						occasions nausea and loathing of food, and many are hurt by the transit of
						the pus), lest they should come to loathe their food. And if they should
						take anything, they readily</p>
					<pb n="481"/>
					<p>vomit. It is necessary, also, in the other defluxions, to have especial care
						of the stomach, for it is the passage to all sorts of medicine. It is
						necessary to keep in mind the liver, which is the root of the
							ulcerations.<note n="1">See the note on the text. The sense would be
							evidently much improved by reading "blood-vessels" in place of
							"ulcerations."</note> But if the defluxion be to the bladder, we are to
						promote it by diuretics, as the root of asarabacca, valerian, maiden-hair,
						spignel, in drinks; for these things are to be given to drink in
						honeyed-water. The compound medicine of Vestinus is also very good, and that
						from alkekengi, and such others as from trial have acquired reputation. But
						if you determine to draw off the discharge by the bowels, you can do this
						with milk, especially that of the ass, or otherwise of the goat or sheep.
						Give, also, juices of a lubricating nature and detergent, as the juice of
						ptisan; condiments, as pepper, ginger, and lovage. In a word, with regard to
						every method of diet in any case of abscess tending to rupture, the food
						should consist of things having wholesome juices, of savoury things, things
						of easy digestion, either juices, or the gruels with milk, starch, pastry
						with milk * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="8">
					<head>CHAPTER XIV. CURE OF THE SPLEEN.</head>
					<p>R<hi rend="smallcaps">ESOLUTION</hi> of scirrhus of the spleen is not easy to
						accomplish. But if the diseases engendered by it come on, as dropsy and
						cachexia, the ailment tends to an incurable condition . . . . . . . the
						physician to cure the scirrhus; we must try then to avert it when it is
						coming on, and to remove it when just commencing; and attend to the
						inflammations, and if the</p>
					<pb n="482"/>
					<p>scirrhus be the substitute . . . . . . . . are brought by suppuration . . . .
						. the abscess. For these, if the inflammation . . . . . we are to use the
						remedies described by me among the acute diseases. But if, while you are
						doing everything, the scirrhus remain in an inflammatory state, you must use
						also the means resembling fire to soften the hardness; lotions of vinegar,
						oil, and honey; but, instead of wool, use compresses of linen; add to them,
						in powder, nut-ben sifted; and to the most emollient cataplasms * * * * * *
						* * * * * *</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="book" n="2">
				<pb n="485"/>
				<head>OF ARETÆUS, THE CAPPADOCIAN, ON THE THERAPEUTICS OF CHRONIC DISEASE BOOK
					II.</head>
				<p>* * * * * * * *</p>
				<div type="chapter" n="1">
					<head>CHAPTER II. CURE OF DIABETES.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> affection of diabetes is a species of dropsy,
						both in cause and in condition, differing only in the place by which the
						humour runs. For, indeed, in ascites the receptacle is the peritonæum, and
						it has no outlet, but remains there and accumulates. But in diabetes, the
						flow of the humour from the affected part and the melting are the same, but
						the defluxion is determined to the kidneys and bladder; and in dropsical
						cases this is the outlet when the disease takes a favourable turn; and it is
						good when it proves a solution of the cause, and not merely a lightening of
						the burden. In the latter disease the thirst is greater; for the fluid
						running off dries the body.</p>
					<pb n="486"/>
					<p>But the remedies for the stoppage of the melting are the same as those for
						dropsy. For the thirst there is need of a powerful remedy, for in kind it is
						the greatest of all sufferings; and when a fluid is drunk, it stimulates the
						discharge of urine; and sometimes as it flows off it melts and carries away
						with it the particles of the body. Medicines, then, which cure thirst are
						required, for the thirst is great with an insatiable desire of drink, so
						that no amount of fluid would be sufficient to cure the thirst. We must,
						therefore, by all means strengthen the stomach, which is the fountain of the
						thirst. When, therefore, you have purged with the hiera, use as epithemes
						the nard, mastich, dates, and raw quinces; the juice of these with nard and
						rose-oil is very good for lotions; their pulp, with mastich and dates, form
						a cataplasm. And the mixture of these with wax and the nard ointment is
						good; or the juice of acacia and of hypocistis, both for lotions and
						cataplasms.</p>
					<p>But the water used as drink is to be boiled with autumn fruit. The food is to
						be milk, and with it the cereals, starch, groats of spelt (<hi rend="ital"
							>alica</hi>), gruels. Astringent wines to give tone to the stomach, and
						these but little diluted, in order to dissipate and clear away the other
						humours; for thirst is engendered by saltish things. But wine, which is at
						the same time astringent and cooling, proves beneficial by inducing a change
						and good temperament; for to impart strength, sweet wine is like blood,
						which also it forms. The compound medicines are the same, as that from
						vipers, the Mithridate, that from autumn fruit, and the others which are
						useful in dropsy. But the whole regimen and course of life is the same.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="2">
					<pb n="487"/>
					<head>CHAPTER III. CURE OF CALCULUS AND ULCERATION OF THE KIDNEYS.</head>
					<p>W<hi rend="smallcaps">HATEVER</hi> relates to inflammation, hemorrhage, and
						such other affections about the kidneys as quickly prove fatal, has been
						treated of under the Acute Diseases. But regarding ulceration thereof, and
						the formation of stones, and the many other affections which accompany old
						persons until death, I am now especially to treat, mostly in order to effect
						their cure; but, if not, to show how they may be alleviated.</p>
					<p>Wherefore, then, it is impossible to eradicate the disposition to form
						stones. It were easier to render the uterus unfruitful, than to destroy the
						tendency to engender stones in kidneys wherein it is already formed. We must
						strive, then, to facilitate the passage of them. If, therefore, the calculi
						be fixed in a place, I will tell what the remedies are which facilitate
						their passage; for they are attended with great pain, and sometimes patients
						die with tormina, volvulus of the colon, and retention of urine; for the
						kidneys and colon are adjacent to one another. Wherefore if there be a
						stoppage of the stones, and, along with it, retention of urine and tormina,
						we are to open the vein at the ankle, on the same side as the kidney
						affected; for the flow of blood from the kidneys relieves the constriction
						of the calculi, for inflammation detains them by binding all the parts; and
						an evacuation of the vessels produces resolution of the inflammation. We are
						also to bathe the loins where the region of the kidneys is placed. Let the
						oil which is used either be old, or if recent, let rue be boiled in it. The
						hair of dill is also diuretic, and rosemary, and marjoram. With these you
						are to bathe the parts as if with plain water; for mere inunction is a small
						affair. But you are also to foment with these things,</p>
					<pb n="488"/>
					<p>by means of the bladders of cattle filled with the oil of camomile. The
						materials of the cataplasms along with meal are to be the same. Dry-cupping
						also has sometimes removed the stoppage of the stones; but in the case of
						inflammation, it is best to have recourse to scarifications. If, when you
						have done these things, the calculi still remain fixed, you must place the
						patient in a bath of oil: for this at once fulfils every indication, it
						relaxes by its heat, in so far lubricates; while its acrimony stimulates to
						a desire of making water. These are the means which contribute to the
						expulsion of calculi. The patient is to take drinks prepared from the roots
						of certain simple medicines, as valerian, spignel, and asarabacca; and
						herbs, the <hi rend="ital">prionitis</hi>, parsley, and water-parsnip: and
						of compounds such ointments as contain nard, cassia, myrrh, cinnamon * * * *
						* * * * * for the cicatrization mustard, and eschars produced by fire, and
						epithemes as formerly described by me. A regulated diet, unction with oil,
						sailing and living on the sea,--all these things are remedies for affections
						of the kidneys. * * * * * * * *</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="3">
					<head>CHAPTER V. CURE OF GONORRHŒA.</head>
					<p>F<hi rend="smallcaps">ROM</hi> the unseemly nature of the affection, and from
						the danger attending the colliquative wasting, and in consideration of the
						want of it for the propagation of the species, we must not be slow to stop a
						flow of semen, as being the cause of all sorts of evil. In the first place,
						therefore, we are to treat it like a common defluxion, by astringents
						applied to the parts about the bladder and the seat of the flux, and with
						refrigerants</p>
					<pb n="489"/>
					<p>to the loins, groin, genital parts, and testicles, so that the semen may not
						flow copiously; and then again, apply calefacients to the whole system, so
						as to dry up the passages; this is to be done by styptics and lotions; wool
						then from the sheep with its sordes, and for oil, the rose ointment, or that
						from vine flowers, with a light-coloured and fragrant wine; but, gradually
						warming, by means of common oil, and melilot boiled with it, and marjoram,
						and rosemary or flea-bane; and a very excellent thing is the hair of dill,
						and still more, the rue. Use these for the cataplasms, with the meal of
						barley and vetches, and of hedge-mustard seed, and natron; but honey is to
						be added, so as to make all combine and mix together. Such also are the
						cataplasms which redden, and raise pustules, and thereby produce derivation
						of the flux, and warm the parts. Such is the Green plaster, and that from
						the fruit of the bay. Frequent draughts too are to be given, prepared from
						castor and winter cherry,<note n="1"><hi rend="ital">Physalis
								alkekengi.</hi> See under <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>STRU/XNOS</foreign>, in Appendix to the Edinburgh Greek
							Lexicon.</note> to the amount of one dram, and the decoction of mint; of
						compounds, that from the two peppers, that of Symphon, that of Philo, the
						liquid medicine from the wild creature the skink, that of Vestinus, that
						from the reptiles the vipers. Every attention is to be paid to diet, and he
						is to be permitted and encouraged to take gymnastics, promenades, and
						gestation; for these things impart warmth to the constitution, which is
						needed in this affection. And if the patient be temperate as to venereal
						matters, and take the cold bath, it may be hoped that he will quickly
						acquire his virility.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="4">
					<pb n="490"/>
					<head>CHAPTER VI. CURE OF STOMACHICS.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">N</hi> the other affections, after the treatment, the
						diet contributes to the strength and force of the body, by good digestion;
						but in stomachics alone it is at fault.<note n="1">Although Ermerins thinks
							otherwise, I must say I agree with Wigan, that something is wanting near
							the beginning of this chapter.</note> How it should be, I will now
						declare. For gestation, promenades, gymnastics, the exercise of the voice,
						and food of easy digestion, are sufficient to counteract the vitiated
						appetite of the stomach; but it is impossible that these things could remove
						protracted indigestion, and convert the emaciated condition of the body to
							<hi rend="ital">embonpoint.</hi> But in these cases, much more than
						usual, the patients should be indulged, and everything done towards them
						liberally, the physician gratifying their appetites whenever the objects of
						them are not very prejudicial; for this is the best course, provided they
						have no desire of those things which would do them much good. Medicines are
						to be given in the liquid form--decoctions, as of wormwood; and nard
						ointment and the Theriac, and the fruit of stone-parsley, and of ginger, and
						of pepper, and of hartwort;<note n="2"><hi rend="ital">Tordyllium
								officinale.</hi></note> these things are of a digestive nature. And
						an epitheme is to be applied to the breast for the purpose of astringency,
						containing nard, mastich, aloe, the acacias, and the juice of quinces, and
						the pulps of the apples bruised with dates, so as to form an astringent
						epitheme. Also such other things as have been enumerated by me under
						diabetes, for the cure of the thirst. For the same causes produce thirst in
						them, and yet in stomachics the tone of the stomach is not inclined to
						thirst.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="5">
					<pb n="491"/>
					<head>CHAPTER VII. CURE OF CŒLIACS.</head>
					<p>I<hi rend="smallcaps">F</hi> the stomach be irretentive of the food, and if
						it pass through undigested, unchanged and crude, so that nothing ascends
						into the body, we call such persons <hi rend="ital">cœliacs;</hi> being
						connected with refrigeration of the innate heat which performs digestion,
						along with atony of the faculty of distribution.</p>
					<p>In the first place then, the stomach is to be relieved from its sufferings by
						rest and abstinence from food, for in this way the natural powers are
						restored. And if there also be a feeling of fulness in the stomach, we are
						to administer emetics, in the fasting state, with water or honeyed-water;
						and the abdomen is to be enveloped and bathed, for the purpose of
						astringency, with unwashed wool from the sheep, with oily things, as the <hi
							rend="ital">unguentum rosaceum, œnanthemum</hi>, and <hi rend="ital"
							>melinum</hi>, or what is best, with that from the lentisk, with
						hypocistis and the unripe grape.<note n="1">For all these compositions, see
							Paulus Ægineta, t. iii. pp. 589-599, Syd. Soc. Edit.</note> But, along
						with these, cataplasms, hot to the touch, but astringent in powers. And if
						there be distension or inflammation anywhere about the liver or mouth of the
						stomach, we are to apply the cupping-instrument, and scarify; and there are
						cases in which this alone is sufficient. But when, by means of cerates, the
						wounds have cicatrised and ended in hardness, we are to apply leeches to it,
						then digestive epithemes, such as that from seeds, if you possess the root
						of the chamæleon. The best thing here is the fruit of the bay, and the
						Malagma by name the Green, and mine--the Mystery. For these soften,
						irritate, rouse heat, discuss flatulence of the bowels, of which there is
						need for the sake of astringency. But likewise mustard, lemnestis,
						euphorbium, and all such</p>
					<pb n="492"/>
					<p>prevent refrigeration indeed, and procure resuscitation of the heat. Such
						medicines also the patient must drink for astringency. In the first place,
						there is need . . . . . . . . . . the juice of plaintain with water made
						astringent by myrtles or quinces. The stone of an unripe grape is also a
						very good thing, and wines of a very astringent character. Then the
						medicines which warm the bowels, namely such potions as are made with
						ginger, and pepper, and the fruit of the wild parsley which is found among
						rocks, and the very digestive medicine made from the reptiles the vipers.
						But if it does not yield at all or slightly to these means, use emetics from
						radishes; and if you will put into them the root of the white hellebore, for
						a single night, the purging will thus become very strong, for purging away
						and removing the cold humours and for kindling up the heat.</p>
					<p>And likewise the diet and manner of life should be moderate. Sleep by night,
						by day walks, vociferation, gestation among myrtles, bays, or thyme; for the
						exhalation and respiration of such things prove a digestive remedy.
						Gymnastics, friction, chironomy, exercises of the chest and abdomen by
						throwing the <hi rend="ital">halteres.</hi> Propomata; for bread alone
						contributes little towards strength. After these, rubefacients, walking * *
						* * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * * *</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="6">
					<head>CHAPTER XII. CURE OF ARTHRITIS AND ISCHIATIC DISEASES.</head>
					<p>. . . . . . from food and radishes frequently. Then to have recourse to the
						hellebore. The diet after these the same as</p>
					<pb n="493"/>
					<p>in the other affections, and after the diet, anointing with oil and the cold
						sea-bath. These in an especial manner are the common remedies in all
						arthritic diseases, for in gouty cases hellebore is the great remedy, yet
						only in the first attacks of the affection. But if it has subsisted for a
						long time already, and also if it appear to have been transmitted from the
						patient's forefathers, the disease sticks to him until death. But for the
						paroxysms in the joints, we are to do this: let unscoured wool from the
						sheep be applied; bathe with rose-oil and wine; and in certain case sponging
						with oxycrate has done good. Then as a cataplasm, bread with the cooling
						parts of gourd and pompion, and simple cucumber, and the herb plantain and
						rose leaves. And the <hi rend="ital">sideritis</hi><note n="1"><hi
								rend="ital">Sideritis scordioides.</hi></note> mitigates pain, along
						with bread, also lichen, and the root of comfrey, and the herb cinque-foil,
						and the species of horehound having narrow leaves: of this the decoction
						makes a fomentation which allays pain, and it forms a cataplasm with crumbs
						of bread or barley-meal. And the part of citrons which is not fit for food,
						is excellent with toasted barley-meal. Dried figs and almonds with some of
						the flours. These form the <hi rend="ital">materiel</hi> for refrigeration;
						and, indeed, this is sometimes beneficial to one, and sometimes to another.
						In certain cases calefacients are beneficial, and the same is sometimes
						useful to another. It is said that the following application is powerfully
						anodyne; let a goat feed on the herb iris, and when it is filled therewith,
						having waited until the food it has taken be digested in the stomach, let
						the goat be slaughtered, and bury the feet in fæces within the belly. The
						medicines for the disease are innumerable; for the calamity renders the
						patients themselves expert druggists. But the medicines of the physicians
						will be described in works devoted to these things.</p>
				</div>
				<div type="chapter" n="7">
					<pb n="494"/>
					<head>CHAPTER XIII. CURE OF ELEPHAS.</head>
					<p>T<hi rend="smallcaps">HE</hi> remedies ought to be greater than the diseases,
						for the relief of them. But what method of cure could be able to overcome
						such a malady as elephas? For the illness does not attack one part or
						viscus, nor prevail only internally or externally, but inwardly it possesses
						the whole person, and outwardly, covers the whole surface--a spectacle
						unseemly and dreadful to behold! for it is the semblance of the wild animal.
						And, moreover, there is a danger in living or associating with it no less
						than with the plague, for the infection is thereby communicated by the
						respiration. Wherefore what sufficient remedy for it shall we find in
						medicine? But yet it is proper to apply every medicine and method of diet,
						-- even iron and fire, -- and these, indeed, if you apply to a recent
						disease there is hope of a cure. But if fully developed, and if it has
						firmly established itself in the inward parts, and, moreover, has attacked
						the face, the patient is in a hopeless condition.</p>
					<p>Wherefore we are to open the veins at the elbow, and on both sides; and also
						those at the ankles, but not the same day, for an interval is better both in
						order to procure a greater flow of blood, and for the resuscitation of the
						strength; for it is necessary to evacuate the blood frequently and
						copiously, as being the nutriment of the disease, but the good portion of it
						which is the natural nourishment is small. Wherefore while abstracting the
						vitiated portion, consisting of melted matters, we must form an estimate of
						the suitable part mixed up with it, until the disease has given way from
						want of pabulum; for the new part being incorporated with the body, in the
						course of a long time, obliterates the old. Then we are to</p>
					<pb n="495"/>
					<p>give the hiera in a potion not once only, but let everything be done several
						times after recovery and recurrence. And let the other medicinal purgation
						by the food be practised; and let the treatment be that which I have
						described under Ischiatic disease, and let the patient drink undivided
						milk--and that in great quantity--for opening the bowels. Let it receive the
						fifth part of water, so that the whole of the milk may pass through. They
						are quickly to be treated with emetics, at first those given when fasting,
						next, those after food, then those by radishes. Let all things be done
						frequently and continuously; administering the hellebore at all seasons, but
						especially in spring and autumn, giving it every alternate day, and again
						next year. And if the disease has acquired strength, we must give whatever
						liquid medicines any one has had experience of; for it is a good thing to
						administer medicines frequently as a remedy. And I will now describe those
						with which I am acquainted. Mix one cyathus of cedria<note n="1">Probably
								<hi rend="ital">gum vernix.</hi> See Paulus Ægineta, t. iii. p.
							452.</note> and two of brassica, and give. Another: Of the juice of
							sideritis,<note n="2">Probably the <hi rend="ital">sideritis scordioides
								L.</hi> See Appendix to Dunbar's Lexicon <hi rend="ital">in
								voce.</hi></note> of trefoil one cyathus, of wine and honey two
						cyathi. Another: Of the shavings of an elephant's tooth one dram with wine,
						to the amount of two cyathi. But likewise the flesh of the wild reptiles,
						the vipers, formed into pastils,<note n="3">Or Troches. See Paulus Ægineta
							t. iii. p. 535.</note> are taken in a draught. From their heads and tail
						we must cut off to the extent of four fingers' breadth, and boil the
						remainder to the separation of the back-bones; and having formed the flesh
						into pastils, they are to be cooled in the shade; and these are to be given
						in a draught in like manner as the squill. The vipers, too, are to be used
						as a seasoner of food at supper, and are to be prepared as fishes. But if
						the compound medicine from vipers be at hand, it is to</p>
					<pb n="496"/>
					<p>be drunk in preference to all others, for it contains together the virtues of
						all the others, so to cleanse the body and smooth down its asperities. There
						are many other medicines . . . . . . of the Celts, which are men called
						Gauls, those alkaline substances made into balls, with which they cleanse
						their clothes, called soap, with which it is a very excellent thing to
						cleanse the body in the bath. And purslain and houseleek with vinegar, and
						also the decoction of the roots of dock with the sulphur vivum proves an
						excellent detergent. The compound medicine from levigated alcyonium,<note
							n="4">A marine zoophyte. See Appendix to the Edinburgh Greek Lexicon,
							and Paulus Ægineta, tom. iii., Syd. Soc. Ed.</note> natron, the burnt
						lees of wine, alum, sulphur vivum, costus, iris, and pepper, these things
						are all to be mixed together in each case according to the power, but in
						proportionate quantities, and this compound is to be sprinkled on the body
						and rubbed in. For the callous protuberances of the face, we are to rub in
						the ashes of vine branches, mixed up with the suet of some wild animal, as
						the lion, the panther, the bear; or if these are not at hand, of the
						barnacle goose;<note n="5">See Appendix to the Edinburgh Greek Lexicon in
								<foreign xml:lang="grc">NH=SSA</foreign>: also Aristot. H. N. viii.
							5, and Ælian. N. A. v. 30. The remark which follows turns on this point,
							that the bird in question called the <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>XHNALW/PHX</foreign>, is to quadrupeds what the ape is to man. See
							the ingenious observations of Petit.</note> for like in the unlike, as
						the ape to man, is most excellent. Also the ammoniac perfume with vinegar
						and the juice of plantain, or of knot-grass, and hypocistis and lycium.<note
							n="6">An electuary from the <hi rend="ital">Berberis lycium.</hi> See
							Paulus Ægineta, <hi rend="ital">in voce.</hi> It has been re-introduced
							lately from India in Ophthalmic practice.</note> But if the flesh be in
						a livid state, scarifications are to be previously made for the evacuation
						of the humours. But if you wish to soothe the parts excoriated by the acrid
						defluxions, the decoction of fenugreek, or the juice of ptisan, will form an
						excellent detergent application; also the oil of roses or of lentisk.
						Continued</p>
					<pb n="497"/>
					<p>baths are appropriate for humectating the body, and for dispelling the
						depraved humours.</p>
					<p>The food should be pure, wholesome, of easy digestion, and plain; and the
						regimen every way well adjusted, as regards sleeping, walking, and places of
						residence. As to exercises, running, tumbling, and the exercise with the
							leather-bag;<note n="7">See Oribasius Med. Collect., vi. 33, and Paulus
							Ægineta, t.i. p. 24.</note> all these with well-regulated intensity, but
						not so as to induce lassitude. Let vociferation also be produced, as being a
						seasonable exercise of the breath (<hi rend="ital">pneuma</hi>). The
						clothing should be clean, not only to gratify the sight, but because filthy
						things irritate the skin. While fasting, the patients are to drink the wine
						of wormwood. Barley-bread is a very excellent thing, and a sausage in due
						season, and a little of mallows or cabbage half-boiled, with soup of cumin.
						For supper, the root of parsnip and granulated spelt (<hi rend="ital"
							>alica</hi>), with wine and old honey adapted for the mixing; and such
						marine articles as loosen the bowels--the soups of limpets, oysters,
						sea-urchins, and such fishes as inhabit rocky places. And of land animals,
						such as are wild, as the hare and the boar. Of winged animals, all sorts of
						partridges, wood-pigeons, domestic-pigeons, and the best which every
						district produces. Of fruits, those of summer; sweet wines are preferable to
						such as are strong. The natural hot-baths of a sulphureous nature, a
						protracted residence in the waters, and a sea-voyage.</p>
					<p><hi rend="ital">Courses of Hellebore:</hi>--White hellebore is purgative of
						the upper intestines, but the black of the lower; and the white is not only
						emetic, but of all purgatives the most powerful, not from the quantity and
						variety of the excretion--for this cholera can accomplish--nor from the
						retching and violence attending the vomitings, for in this respect
						sea-sickness is preferable; but from a power and quality of no mean
						description, by which it restores the sick to health, even with little
						purging</p>
					<pb n="498"/>
					<p>and small retching. But also of all chronic diseases when firmly rooted, if
						all other remedies fail, this is the only cure. For in power the white
						hellebore resembles fire; and whatever fire accomplishes by burning, still
						more does hellebore effect by penetrating internally--out of dyspnœa
						inducing freedom of breathing; out of paleness, good colour; and out of
						emaciation, plumpness of flesh.</p>
				</div>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
