<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - 2 Timothy</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <editor role="editor">Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor role="editor">
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="verse"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and verse</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="chapter"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            
            <refsDecl>
                <!--<refState delim=" " unit="book"/>-->
                <refState delim=":" unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>
            
            <!--<refsDecl>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>-->
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-10-26" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion</change>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2010-06-29" who="student">fixing place tags AD</change>
            <change when="2009-10-08" who="rsingh04">began reorganizing texts module by collection.created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files</change>
            <change when="2009-05-27" who="rsingh04">added/fixed cvs log keyword</change>
            <change when="1999-10-14" who="Anne Mahoney">Initial markup from flat ASCII text</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0031.tlg016.perseus-eng2">
                <head>Paul's Second Letter to Timothy</head>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
                

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                
                        Paul, an apostle of Jesus Christ through the will of God,
according to the promise of the life which is in Christ Jesus,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        to Timothy, my beloved child: Grace, mercy, and peace, from God the Father
and Christ Jesus our Lord.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        I thank God, whom I serve as my forefathers did, with a pure
conscience. How unceasing is my memory of you in my petitions, night
and day
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        longing to see you, remembering your tears, that I may be
filled with joy;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        having been reminded of the unfeigned faith that
is in you; which lived first in your grandmother Lois, and your mother
Eunice, and, I am persuaded, in you also.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        For this cause, I remind you that you should stir up the gift
of God which is in you through the laying on of my hands.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        For God
didn't give us a spirit of fear, but of power, love, and self-control.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        Therefore don't be ashamed of the testimony of our Lord, nor of
me his prisoner; but endure hardship for the gospel according to the
power of God,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        who saved us and called us with a holy calling, not
according to our works, but according to his own purpose and grace,
which was given to us in Christ Jesus before times eternal,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        but
has now been revealed by the appearing of our Savior, Christ Jesus, who
abolished death, and brought life and immortality to light through the
gospel.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        For this, I was appointed as a preacher, an apostle, and
a teacher of the Gentiles.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        For this cause I suffer also these
things.

   Yet I am not ashamed, for I know him whom I have believed, and I am
persuaded that he is able to guard that which I have committed to him
against that day.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        Hold the pattern of sound words which you have heard from me,
in faith and love which is in Christ Jesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        That good thing
which was committed to you, guard through the Holy Spirit who dwells in
us.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        This you know, that all who are in Asia turned away from me;
of whom are Phygelus and Hermogenes.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        May the Lord grant mercy to
the house of Onesiphorus, for he often refreshed me, and was not
ashamed of my chain,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        but when he was in Rome, he sought me
diligently, and found me
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        (the Lord grant to him to find the
Lord's mercy in that day); and in how many things he served at Ephesus,
you know very well.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                  
                        You therefore, my child, be strengthened in the grace that is
in Christ Jesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        The things which you have heard from me among
many witnesses, commit the same to faithful men, who will be able to
teach others also.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        You therefore must endure hardship, as a good
soldier of Christ Jesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        No soldier on service entangles himself
in the affairs of life, that he may please him who enrolled him as a
soldier.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Also, if anyone competes in athletics, he isn't crowned
unless he has competed by the rules.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        The farmers who labor must
be the first to get a share of the crops.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        Consider what I say,
and may the Lord give you understanding in all things.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        Remember Jesus Christ, risen from the dead, of the seed of
David, according to my gospel,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        in which I suffer hardship to the
point of chains as a criminal. But God's word isn't chained.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        Therefore I endure all things for the elect's sake, that they also may
obtain the salvation which is in Christ Jesus with eternal glory.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        This saying is faithful:
For if we died with him,
   We will also live with him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        If we endure,
   We will also reign with him.
If we deny him,
   He also will deny us.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        If we are faithless,
   He remains faithful. He can't deny himself.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Remind them of these things, charging them in the sight of
the Lord, that they don't argue about words, to no profit, to the
subverting of those who hear.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        Give diligence to present yourself approved by God, a workman
who doesn't need to be ashamed, properly handling the Word of Truth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        But shun empty chatter, for they will proceed further in
ungodliness,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        and their word will consume like gangrene, of whom
is Hymenaeus and Philetus;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        men who have erred concerning the
truth, saying that the resurrection is already past, and overthrowing
the faith of some.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        However God's firm foundation stands, having
this seal, "The Lord knows those who are his," and, "Let every one who
names the name of the Lord depart from unrighteousness."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        Now in
a great house there are not only vessels of gold and of silver, but
also of wood and of clay. Some are for honor, and some for dishonor.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        If anyone therefore purges himself from these, he will be a
vessel for honor, sanctified, and suitable for the master's use,
prepared for every good work.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        Flee from youthful lusts; but pursue righteousness, faith,
love, and peace with those who call on the Lord out of a pure heart.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        But refuse foolish and ignorant questionings, knowing that they
generate strife.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        The Lord's servant must not quarrel, but be
gentle towards all, able to teach, patient,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        in gentleness
correcting those who oppose him: perhaps God may give them repentance
leading to a full knowledge of the truth,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        and they may recover
themselves out of the devil's snare, having been taken captive by him
to his will.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
                 

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                  
                        But know this, that in the last days, grievous times will
come.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        For men will be lovers of self, lovers of money, boastful,
arrogant, blasphemers, disobedient to parents, unthankful, unholy,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        without natural affection, unforgiving, slanderers, without
self-control, fierce, no lovers of good,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        traitors, headstrong,
conceited, lovers of pleasure rather than lovers of God;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        holding
a form of godliness, but having denied the power thereof. Turn away
from these, also.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        For of these are those who creep into houses,
and take captive gullible women loaded down with sins, led away by
various lusts,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        always learning, and never able to come to the
knowledge of the truth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        Even as Jannes and Jambres opposed Moses,
so do these also oppose the truth; men corrupted in mind, reprobate
concerning the faith.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        But they will proceed no further. For their
folly will be evident to all men, as theirs also came to be.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        But
you did follow my teaching, conduct, purpose, faith, patience, love,
steadfastness,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        persecutions, and sufferings: those things that
happened to me at Antioch, Iconium, and Lystra. I endured those
persecutions. Out of them all the Lord delivered me.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        Yes, and
all who desire to live godly in Christ Jesus will suffer persecution.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        But evil men and impostors will grow worse and worse, deceiving
and being deceived.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        But you remain in the things which you have
learned and have been assured of, knowing from whom you have learned
them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        From infancy, you have known the sacred writings which are
able to make you wise for salvation through faith, which is in Christ
Jesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        Every writing inspired by God is profitable for teaching,
for reproof, for correction, and for instruction which is in
righteousness,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        that the man of God may be complete, thoroughly
equipped for every good work.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
                    

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        I charge you therefore before God and the Lord Jesus Christ,
who will judge the living and the dead at His appearing and His
kingdom:
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        preach the word; be urgent in season and out of season;
reprove, rebuke, and exhort, with all patience and teaching.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        For
the time will come when they will not listen to the sound doctrine,
but, having itching ears, will heap up for themselves teachers after
their own lusts;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        and will turn away their ears from the truth,
and turn aside to fables.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        But you be sober in all things, suffer
hardship, do the work of an evangelist, and fulfill your ministry.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        For I am already being offered, and the time of my departure
has come.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        I have fought the good fight. I have finished the
course. I have kept the faith.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        From now on, there is stored up
for me the crown of righteousness, which the Lord, the righteous judge,
will give to me on that day; and not to me only, but also to all those
who have loved his appearing.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        Be diligent to come to me soon,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        for Demas left me, having loved this present world, and went to
Thessalonica; Crescens to Galatia, and Titus to Dalmatia.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        Only
Luke is with me. Take Mark, and bring him with you, for he is useful to
me for ministering.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        But I sent Tychicus to Ephesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        Bring
the cloak that I left at Troas with Carpus when you come, and the
books, especially the parchments.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Alexander, the coppersmith,
did much evil to me. The Lord will repay him according to his works,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        of whom you also must beware; for he greatly opposed our words.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        At my first defense, no one came to help me, but all left me.
May it not be held against them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        But the Lord stood by me, and
strengthened me, that through me the message might be fully proclaimed,
and that all the Gentiles might hear; and I was delivered out of the
mouth of the lion.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        And the Lord will deliver me from every evil
work, and will preserve me for his heavenly kingdom; to whom be the
glory forever and ever. Amen.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        Greet Prisca and Aquila, and the house of Onesiphorus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        Erastus remained at Corinth, but I left Trophimus at Miletus sick.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        Be diligent to come before winter. Eubulus salutes you, as do
Pudens, Linus, Claudia, and all the brothers.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        The Lord Jesus
Christ be with your spirit. Grace be with you. Amen.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
