<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Epigrams</title>
                <author>Homer</author>
                <editor role="translator">Hugh G. Evelyn-White</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
                <funder n="org:Tufts">Tufts University</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">2019</date>
            </publicationStmt> 			
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Homer (Homerica)</author>
                        <title>Hesiod, The Homeric Hymns and Homerica. With an English translation by Hugh. G. Evelyn-White, M.A.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA. William Heinemann Ltd., London.</publisher>
                            <date type="printing">1914</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/hesiodhomerichym00hesiuoft/page/n7">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="line" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']//tei:l[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts epigram and line.</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="epigram" matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts epigram.</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <editorialDecl>
                <quotation marks="none"/>
            </editorialDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2019-01-10" who="Lisa Cerrato">converted to EpiDoc and CTS</change>
            <change when="1990-08-17" who="unknown">initial data entry capture and file creation</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
        <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0012.tlg003.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="1">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Have<note resp="editor" xml:lang="eng">The Epigrams are
                            preserved in the pseudo-Herodotean <title>Life of Homer</title>. Nos.
                            III, XIII, and XVII are also found in the <title>Contest of Homer and
                                Hesiod</title>, and No. I is also extant at the end of some MSS. of
                            the <title>Homeric Hymns</title>.</note> reverence for him who needs a
                        home and stranger’s dole,</l> 
                <l n="2">all ye who dwell in the high city of Cyme, the lovely maiden,</l> 
                <l n="3">hard by the foothills of lofty Sardene, </l>
                <l n="4">ye who drink the heavenly water of the divine stream,</l> 
                <l n="5">eddying Hermus, whom deathless Zeus begot.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="2">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Speedily may my feet bear me to some town of righteous men;</l> 
                <l n="2">for their hearts are generous and their wit is best.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="3">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">I am a maiden of bronze and am set upon the tomb of Midas.</l> 
                <l n="2">While the waters flow and tall trees flourish, </l>
                <l n="3">and the sun rises and shines and the bright moon also; </l>
                <l n="4">while rivers run and the sea breaks on the shore, </l>
                <l n="5">ever remaining on this mournful tomb, </l>
                <l n="6">I tell the passer-by that Midas here lies buried.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="4">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">To what a fate did Zeus the Father give me a prey </l>
                <l n="2">even while he made me to grow, a babe at my mother’s knees!</l>
                <l n="3">By the will of Zeus who holds the aegis </l>
                <l n="4">the people of Phricon, riders on wanton horses, </l>
                <l n="5">more active than raging fire in the test of war, </l>
                <l n="6">once built the towers of Aeolian Smyrna, wave-shaken neighbor to the sea, </l>
                <l n="7">through which glides the pleasant stream of sacred Meles; </l>
                <l n="8">thence<note resp="editor" xml:lang="eng"><emph>sc.</emph> from Smyrna,
                            Homer’s reputed birth-place.</note> arose the daughters of Zeus,
                        glorious children, </l>
                <l n="9">and would fain have made famous that fair country and the city of its people.</l>
                <l n="10">But in their folly those men scorned the divine voice and renown of song, </l>
                <l n="11">and in trouble shall one of them remember this hereafter—</l>
                <l n="12">he who with scornful words to them<note resp="editor" xml:lang="eng">The councillors of Cyme who refused to support Homer at the public expense.</note> contrived my fate. </l>
                <l n="13">Yet I will endure the lot which heaven gave me even at my birth, </l>
                <l n="14">bearing my disappointment with a patient heart. </l>
                <l n="15">My dear limbs yearn not to stay in the sacred streets </l>
                <l n="16">of Cyme, but rather my great heart urges me</l>
                <l n="17">to go unto another country, small though I am.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="5">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Thestorides, full many things there are that mortals cannot sound; </l>
                <l n="2">but there is nothing more unfathomable than the heart of man.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="6">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Hear me, Poseidon, strong shaker of the earth, </l>
                <l n="2">ruler of wide-spread, tawny Helicon! </l>
                <l n="3">Give a fair wind and sight of safe return </l>
                <l n="4">to the shipmen who speed and govern this ship. </l>
                <l n="5">And grant that when I come to the nether slopes of towering Mimas </l>
                <l n="6">I may find honorable, god-fearing men. </l>
                <l n="7">Also may I avenge me on the wretch who deceived me </l>
                <l n="8">and grieved Zeus the lord of guests and his own guest-table.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="7">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Queen Earth, all bounteous giver of honey-hearted wealth, </l>
                <l n="2">how kindly, it seems, you are to some, </l>
                <l n="3">and how intractable and rough for those with whom you are angry.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="8">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Sailors, who rove the seas and whom a hateful fate has made as </l>
                <l n="2">the shy sea-fowl, living an unenviable life, </l>
                <l n="3">observe the reverence due to Zeus who rules on high, the god of strangers; </l>
                <l n="4">for terrible is the vengeance of this god afterwards for whosoever has sinned.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="9">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Strangers, a contrary wind has caught you: </l>
                <l n="2">but even now take me aboard and you shall make your voyage.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="10">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Another sort of pine shall bear a better fruit<note resp="editor" xml:lang="eng">The <q type="mentioned">better fruit</q> is apparently the iron smelted out in fires of pine-wood.</note> </l>
                <l n="2">than you upon the heights of furrowed, windy Ida. </l>
                <l n="3">For there shall mortal men get the iron that Ares loves </l>
                <l n="4">so soon as the Cebrenians shall hold the land.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="11">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Glaucus, watchman of flocks, a word will I put in your heart. </l>
                <l n="2">First give the dogs their dinner at the courtyard gate, </l>
                <l n="3">for this is well. The dog first hears </l>
                <l n="4">a man approaching and the wild-beast coming to the fence.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="12">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Goddess-nurse of the young,<note resp="editor" xml:lang="eng">Hecate: cp. Hesiod, <title>Theogony</title>, 450.</note> give ear to my prayer, and grant that this woman </l>
                <l n="2">may reject the love-embrace of youth </l>
                <l n="3">and dote on grey-haired old men </l>
                <l n="4">whose powers are dulled, but whose hearts still desire.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="13">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Children are a man’s crown, towers of a city; </l>
                <l n="2">horses are the glory of a plain, and so are ships of the sea; </l>
                <l n="3">wealth will make a house great, and reverend princes </l>
                <l n="4">seated in assembly are a goodly sight for the folk to see. </l>
                <l n="5">But a blazing fire makes a house look more comely upon a winter’s day, </l>
                <l n="6">when the Son of Cronos sends down snow.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="14">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Potters, if you will give me a reward, I will sing for you. </l>
                <l n="2">Come, then, Athena, with hand upraised<note resp="editor" xml:lang="eng"><emph>i.e.</emph> in protection.</note> over the kiln. </l>
                <l n="3">Let the pots and all the dishes turn out well </l>
                <l n="4">and be well fired: let them fetch good prices </l>
                <l n="5">and be sold in plenty in the market, and plenty in the streets. </l>
                <l n="6">Grant that the potters may get great gain and grant me so to sing to them. </l>
                <l n="7">But if you turn shameless and make false promises, </l>
                <l n="8">then I call together the destroyers of kilns, </l>
                <l n="9">Shatter and Smash and Charr and Crash </l>
                <l n="10">and Crudebake who can work this craft much mischief. </l>
                <l n="11">Come all of you and sack the kiln-yard and the buildings: let the </l>
                <l n="12">whole kiln be shaken up to the potter’s loud lament. </l>
                <l n="13">As a horse’s jaw grinds, so let the kiln grind </l>
                <l n="14">to powder all the pots inside. </l>
                <l n="15">And you, too, daughter of the Sun, Circe the witch, </l>
                <l n="16">come and cast cruel spells; hurt both these men and their handiwork. </l>
                <l n="17">Let Chiron also come and bring many Centaurs—</l>
                <l n="18">all that escaped the hands of Heracles and all that were destroyed: </l>
                <l n="19">let them make sad havoc of the pots and overthrow the kiln, </l>
                <l n="20">and let the potters see the mischief and be grieved; </l>
                <l n="21">but I will gloat as I behold their luckless craft. </l>
                <l n="22">And if anyone of them stoops to peer in, let all his face </l>
                <l n="23">be burned up, that all men may learn to deal honestly.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="15">
                <l n="1" rend="indent"><note resp="editor" xml:lang="eng">This song is called by pseudo-Herodotus <foreign xml:lang="grc">Εἰρησιώνη</foreign>. The word properly indicates a garland wound with wool which was worn at harvest-festivals, but came to be applied first to the harvest song and then to any begging song. The present is akin to the Swallow-Song (<foreign xml:lang="grc">Χελιδόνισμα</foreign>), sung at the beginning of spring, and answering to the still surviving English May-Day songs. Cp. Athenaeus, viii. 360 B.</note> Let us betake us to the house of some man of great power,—</l>
                <l n="2">one who bears great power and is greatly prosperous always. </l>
                <l n="3">Open of yourselves, you doors, for mighty Wealth will enter in, </l>
                <l n="4">and with Wealth comes jolly Mirth </l>
                <l n="5">and gentle Peace. May all the corn-bins be full </l>
                <l n="6">and the mass of dough always overflow the kneading-trough. </l>
                <l n="7">Now (set before us) cheerful barley-pottage, full of sesame </l>
                <gap reason="lost" rend=". . ."/>
                <l n="8" rend="indent">Your son’s wife, driving to this house with strong-hoofed
                        mules, </l>
                <l n="9">shall dismount from her carriage to greet you; <note resp="perseus">Lines 8 and 9 do not correspond well with the Greek.</note></l>
                <l n="10">may she be shod with golden shoes as she stands weaving at the loom.</l>
                <l n="11" rend="indent">I come, and I come yearly, like the swallow </l>
                <l n="12">that perches light-footed in the fore-part of your house. But quickly bring <gap reason="lost" rend=". . ."/></l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="16">
                <l n="1" rend="indent">If you will give us anything (well). But if not, we will not wait, </l>
                <l n="2">for we are not come here to dwell with you.</l></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="epigram" n="17">
                <sp><speaker>HOMER</speaker>
                <l n="1" rend="indent">Hunters of deep sea prey, have we caught anything?</l></sp>
                <sp><speaker>FISHERMEN</speaker>
                <l n="2" rend="indent">All that we caught we left behind, and all that we did not catch we carry home.<note resp="editor" xml:lang="eng">The lice which they caught in their clothes they left behind, but carried home in their clothes those which they could not catch.</note></l></sp>
                <sp><speaker>HOMER</speaker>
                <l n="3">Ay, for of such fathers you are sprung </l>
                <l n="4">as neither hold rich lands nor tend countless sheep.</l></sp>
               </div> 
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
