<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Callimachus</title>
        
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">Larue Van Hook</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by Larue Van Hook, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
          <date type="print">1945</date>
          <date type="reprint">1968</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
      <change when="2016-01-26" who="TDBuck">epidoc and CTS</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg002.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If any others had employed in litigation such a special plea of exception, I should have
          begun my discourse with the facts themselves; but as the situation is, I am compelled
          first to speak of the law in accordance with which we have come before the court, that you
          may cast your votes with an understanding of the issues in our dispute and that no one of
          you may be surprised that I, although defendant in the case, am speaking prior to the
          plaintiff. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now after your return to the city from Piraeus,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A
            reference to the citizens of the democratic party who returned from exile to Athens in
              <date when="-0403">403 B.C.</date> after the defeat of the Thirty Tyrants. They had
            taken their stand under Thrasybulus in the harbor-city, Piraeus.</note> you saw that
          some of the citizens were bent upon bringing malicious prosecutions and were attempting to
          violate the Amnesty<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An act passed in <date when="-0403">403
              B.C.</date> by the citizens, after the expulsion of the Thirty Tyrants to put an end
            to civic discord and to re-establish the democracy.</note>; so, wishing to restrain
          these persons and to show to all others that you had not made these agreements under
          compulsion, but because you thought them of advantage to the city, you enacted a law, on
          the motion of Archinus, to the effect that, if any person should commence a lawsuit in
          violation of the oaths, the defendant should have the power to enter a plea of exception,
          the magistrates should first submit this question to the tribunal, and that the defendant
          who had entered the plea should speak first; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and further, that the loser should pay a penalty of one-sixth of the sum at stake. The
          purpose of the penalty was this—that persons who had the effrontery to rake up old grudges
          should not only be convicted of perjury but also, not awaiting the vengeance of the gods,
          should suffer immediate punishment. I thought, therefore, that it was absurd if, under the
          existing laws, I was to permit my calumniator to risk only thirty drachmas, while I myself
          am contesting a suit in which my whole property is at stake. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I intend to prove that Callimachus not only is bringing a suit in violation of the terms
          of the Amnesty agreement, but that he is also guilty of falsehood in his charges, and
          furthermore, that we have already resorted to arbitration in the matter at issue. But I
          wish to relate the facts to you from the beginning; for if you learn that he has suffered
          no wrong at my hands, I think that you will be more inclined to defend the Amnesty and be
          more incensed with him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The government of the Ten, who had succeeded the Thirty, was then in control when
          Patrocles, a friend of mine, was the King-Archon,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The most
            important of the Athenian nine archons was not the King-Archon, as the name might
            suggest, but the Archon Eponymus, who gave his name to the year in which he held office.
            The King-Archon had charge of public worship and the conduct of certain criminal
            processes.</note> and with him one day I happened to be walking. Patrocles, an enemy of
          Callimachus who is now prosecuting me in this suit, met him as he was carrying a sum of
          money, laid hold of him, and claimed that this money had been left by Pamphilus and
          belonged to the government; for Pamphilus was a member of the party of the Piraeus.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 18.2">Isoc. 18.2</bibl> note 1.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Callimachus denied this and as a violent quarrel ensued many others came running up;
          among them by chance Rhinon, who had become one of the Ten, approached. So Patrocles
          immediately laid information with him concerning the money and Rhinon led them both before
          his colleagues. These officials referred the matter to the Council<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">During the rule of the Thirty, and of their successors the Ten, the judicial
            functions of the Athenian juries were usurped by the Council.</note>; after an
          adjudication, the money was declared the property of the state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Later, after the return of the citizen-exiles from Piraeus, Callimachus brought a charge
          against Patrocles and instituted proceedings against him on the ground that he was
          responsible for his loss. And when he had effected with him a settlement of the matter and
          had exacted from him ten minas of silver, Callimachus maliciously accused Lysimachus.
          Having obtained two hundred drachmas from him, he began to make trouble for me. At first
          he charged me with being the accomplice of the others; in the end, he came to such a pitch
          of impudence that he accused me as responsible for everything that had been done, and it
          may be that even now he will have the effrontery to make just such an accusation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In rebuttal, however, I will present to you as witnesses, first, those who were present
          at the beginning of the affair, who will testify that I did not arrest Callimachus nor did
          I touch the money; second, Rhinon and his colleagues, who will tell you that it was
          Patrocles, and not I, who denounced him to them; and finally, the members of the Council,
          who will attest that Patrocles was the accuser.&amp; Please call witnesses of these facts.
            <quote type="Witnesses"> </quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Although so many persons had been present when the events took place, Callimachus here,
          as if no one had any knowledge of the matter, himself mixed with the crowds, sat in the
          workshops, and related again and again his story, how he had suffered outrageous treatment
          at my hands and had been of his money. And some of his friends came to me and advised me
          to settle the dispute with him, and not deliberately to risk defamation and great
          financial loss, even though I had the greatest confidence in my cause; and they went on to
          say that many decisions rendered in the tribunals were contrary to the expectation of
          litigants, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and that chance rather than justice determined the issue in your courts. Consequently,
          they asserted, it was in my interest to be freed of serious charges by paying a petty sum,
          rather than by paying nothing to run the risk of penalties of such gravity. Why need I
          relate to you all the details? They omitted none of the arguments which are customarily
          urged in such cases. In any case I was finally prevailed upon (for I will tell you the
          whole truth) to give him two hundred drachmas. But in order that it might not be in his
          power to blackmail me again, we committed the arbitration under stated terms<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">A similar example of arbitration under the stated terms(i.e.,
            limited arbitration, where the arbitrator had no discretonary power) is found in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 17.19">Isoc. 17.19</bibl>. Cf. Jebb. <title>Attic Orators</title> ii. p.
            234.</note> to Nicomachus of Bat<gap reason="lost"/><note anchored="true" resp="ed">A lacuna is here
            indicated by Blass, perhaps <foreign xml:lang="grc">kai\ moi ka/lei tou/twn
              ma/rturas</foreign>“Please call witnesses to these facts”</note>
          <quote type="Witnesses"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> At first Callimachus kept his agreement, but later in complicity with Xenotimus—that
          falsifier of the laws, corrupter of our tribunals, vilifier of the authorities, and author
          of every evil—he brought suit against me for the sum of ten thousand drachmas. But when I
          brought forward in my defense a witness to show that the suit was not within the
          jurisdiction of the court by reason of the previous arbitration, he did not attack my
          witness— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for he knew that, if he did not receive the fifth of the votes cast, he would be assessed
          a penalty of one-sixth of the amount demanded—but having won over the magistrate, he again
          brought the same suit, in the belief that he risked only his court deposit-fee. And since
          I was at a loss how to cope with my difficulties, I judged that it was best to make the
          hazard equal for us both<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See Introduction to this
            speech.</note> and to come before you. And these are the facts. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I learn that Callimachus not only intends to speak falsely in the matter of his
          complaint, but will also deny that the arbitration took place, and that he is prepared to
          go so far as to assert that he never would have entrusted an arbitration to Nicomachus,
          whom he knew to be an old friend of ours, and further, that it is improbable that he was
          willing to accept two hundred drachmas instead of ten thousand. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>You must reflect, however, first, that we were not in dispute in the matter of the
          arbitration, but we committed it as an arbitration under stated terms, so that it is not
          at all strange that Callimachus chose Nicomachus as arbiter; it would have been far
          stranger if, after he had come to an agreement about the matter, he had then made
          difficulty about the choice of arbiter. In the next place, it is not reasonable to assume
          that, if ten thousand drachmas had been owing to him, he would have settled for two
            minas<note anchored="true" resp="ed">10,000 drachmas=about $1800 or approximately 360
            sterling; two minas (200 drachmas)=about $36 or between seven and eight pounds.</note>;
          but since his charges were unjust and in the nature of blackmail, it is not astonishing
          that he was willing to take so little. Furthermore, if, after exorbitant demands, he
          exacted little, this is no proof in favor of his contention that the arbitration did not
          take place on the contrary, it confirms all the more our contention that his claim was
          unjust in the first place. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I am astonished that, while he judges himself capable of recognizing that it was not
          probable that he was willing to take two hundred drachmas instead of the ten thousand, yet
          believes that I am incapable of discovering, if I had wished to lie, that I ought to have
          asserted that I had given him more. But this I ask—that in so far as it would have been an
          indication in his favor that the arbitration did not take place, if he had proved the
          falsity of the testimony, to that same extent it shall be proof in favor of my contention
          that I tell the truth concerning the arbitration, inasmuch as it is clearly shown that he
          did not dare to proceed against my witness. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I think, however, that even if there had been neither arbitration nor witnesses to the
          actual facts and you were under the necessity of considering the case in the light of the
          probabilities, not even in this event would you have difficulty in arriving at a just
          verdict. For if I were so audacious a man as to wrong others, you would with good reason
          condemn me as doing wrong to him also; but as it is, I shall be found innocent of having
          harmed any citizen in regard to his property, or of jeopardizing his life, or of having
          expunged his name from the list of active citizens, or of having inscribed his name on
          Lysander's list.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A list of citizens who were deprived of
            their civic rights; cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 21.2">Isoc. 21.2</bibl> and <bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 2.3.17">Xen. Hell. 2.3.17-19</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet the wickedness of the Thirty<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the crimes of the
            Thirty see the vivid account by Lysias in his speech <title>Against
            Eratosthenes</title>.</note> impelled many to act in this way for they not only did not
          punish the evil-doers but they even commanded some persons to do wrong. So as for me, not
          even when they had control of the government, shall I be found guilty of any such misdeed;
          yet Callimachus says that he was wronged after the Thirty had been expelled, the Piraeus
          had been taken, and when the democracy was in power, and the terms of reconciliation were
          being discussed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet do you think that a man who was well behaved under the Thirty put off his
          wrongdoing until that period when even those who had formerly transgressed were repentant?
          But the most absurd thing of all would be this—that although I never saw fit to avenge
          myself on anyone of my existing enemies, I was attempting to injure this man with whom I
          have never had any business dealings at all! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> That I am not responsible for the confiscation of the money of Callimachus I think I
          have sufficiently proved. But that it was not legally in his power to bring a suit
          pertaining to events which occurred then, not even if I had done everything he says I did,
          you will learn from the covenant of Amnesty.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 18.2">Isoc. 18.2</bibl> note 1.</note> Please take the document.<quote
            type="Amnesty"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Was it, then, a weak defense of my rights I trusted in when I entered this demurrer? On
          the contrary, do not the terms of the Amnesty explicitly exculpate any who have laid
          information against or denounced any person or have done any similar thing, and am I not
          able to prove that I have neither committed these acts nor transgressed in any other way?
          Please read the Oaths also. <quote type="Oaths"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Is it not outrageous, men of the jury, that, although such were the terms of the
          covenant and the oaths which were sworn were of such nature, Callimachus is so convinced
          of his own eloquence that he believes he will persuade you to vote in opposition to them?
          If he saw that the city regretted its past action, his conduct should not occasion
          surprise; but as a matter of fact you have shown the importance you attach to the
          covenant, not only in the enactment of the laws, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but when Philon of Coele was indicted for malversation on an embassy, and although he
          could offer no defense but merely cited the covenant in exoneration, you decided to
          dismiss his case and not even hold him for trial. And although the city does not think it
          proper to punish even confessed transgressors, yet this man has the effrontery to bring
          malicious charges against those who have done no wrong at all. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, he is certainly not unaware of this either—that Thrasybulus and Anytus, men
          of the greatest influence in the city, although they have been robbed of large sums of
          money and know who gave in lists of their goods, nevertheless are not so brazen as to
          bring suit against them or to bring up old grudges against them; on the contrary, even if,
          in respect to all other claims, they have greater power than others to accomplish their
          ends, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>yet in matters covered by the covenant at least they see fit to put themselves on terms
          of equality with the other citizens. And it is not these men alone who have accepted this
          point of view; no, not even one of you has dared to bring such an action. And yet it would
          be outrageous if you, while honoring your oaths where your own affairs are concerned,
          shall attempt to violate them in connexion with the calumnious charges of Callimachus, and
          if, while insisting that private agreements must be held valid by public authority, shall
          allow anyone who so desires, on his own private authority, to break the covenants of the
          state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But it would be the most astounding outcome of all if, while it was still uncertain
          whether or not the reconciliation would be of advantage to the city, you strengthened it
          with such oaths that, even if it proved disadvantageous, you were forced to abide by your
          agreements, yet now, when the results have been so happy for you that, even if you had not
          given any solemn pledge to do so, it is right for you scrupulously to preserve the
          existing government,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., the Democracy.</note> you are
          going to seize that moment to violate your oaths! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And although you were incensed with those who have said that the covenant of Amnesty
          should be repealed, yet this man, who has the effrontery to transgress it after its
          official promulgation, you are going to discharge without a penalty! No, should you do so,
          you would neither be rendering justice nor acting in a manner worthy of yourselves or
          consistent with your former decisions. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I beg you, however, to bear in mind that you have come to pass judgement on matters of
          the highest importance; for you are going to cast your votes on the question of a
          covenant, and covenants have never been violated to the advantage of either yourselves in
          relation to the other parties or of others in relation to you; and they have such binding
          force that almost all the daily activities of Greeks and of barbarians are governed by
          covenants. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it is through our reliance on them that we visit one another's lands and procure
          those things of which we both have need; with the aid of these we make our contracts with
          each other and put an end to both our private animosities and our common wars. This is the
          only universal institution which all we of the human race constantly employ. It is,
          therefore, the duty of all men to uphold them, and, above all, yours. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It is your duty, I say, for recently, when we had been conquered and had fallen into the
          power of enemies at home and many wished to destroy the city, we took refuge in the oaths
          and covenants; and if the Lacedaemonians should dare to violate these, every man of you
          would be exceedingly indignant. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet how can one accuse the other party of transgressions of which he is himself
          guilty? Who would regard us as victims of injustice when suffering injury through a
          violation of covenants, if even we ourselves were manifestly holding them in slight
          esteem? What pledges shall we find binding in our relations with other peoples if we so
          lightly disregard those which we have made among ourselves? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>This, too, is worthy of our remembrance that, although our forefathers performed many
          glorious deeds in war, not the least of its glory our city has won through these treaties
          of reconciliation. For whereas many cites might be found which have waged war gloriously,
          in dealing with civil discord there is none which could be shown to have taken wiser
          measures than ours. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, the great majority of all those achievements that have been accomplished by
          fighting may be attributed to Fortune; but for the moderation we showed towards one
          another no one could find any other cause than our good judgement. Consequently it is not
          fitting that we should prove false to this glorious reputation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And let no one think that I exaggerate or pass due bounds, because I, a defendant in a
          private suit, have spoken in this fashion. For this law-suit is concerned not merely with
          the sum of money specified in the indictment; for me, it is true, this is the issue, but
          for you it is that of which I have just spoken; on this subject no one would be able to
          speak in fitting fashion nor could he fix an adequate penalty. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For this law-suit difiers so greatly from other private suits in this respect that, while
          the latter are of concern to the litigants only, in this private law-suit common interests
          of the city are likewise at stake. In trying this case you are bound by two oaths: one is
          the customary judicial oath which you take in all ordinary cases, and the other is that
          oath which you swore when you ratified the covenant of Amnesty. If in render an unjust
          verdict in this case, you will be violating not only the laws of the city, but also the
          laws common to all men. Consequently, it is not fitting that your votes should be based
          upon favor, or upon mere equity, nor upon anything else than upon the oaths you took when
          you made the covenant of Amnesty. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now that it is right, and is expedient and just that you should decide thus concerning
          the covenant of Amnesty not even Callimachus himself, I think, will gainsay; but he
          intends, I suppose, to bewail his present poverty and the misfortune which has befallen
          him and to say that his fate will be dreadful and cruel if now under the democracy he must
          pay the assessed fine for the money of which under the oligarchy he was deprived,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">If Callimachus lost the suit, he would be liable to a fine
              (<foreign xml:lang="greek">h( e)pwbeli/a</foreign>) of one-sixth of the sum at which
            the damages were laid.</note> and also if then because he possessed property he was
          forced to go into exile, yet now, at a time when he ought to get satisfaction for wrongs
          done him, he is to be deprived of his civic rights.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">If the
            fine should not be paid within the appointed period of time, Callimachus would lose his
            rights as a citizen.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And he will accuse also those who took part in the revolution, in the hope that in this
          way especially he will arouse you to wrath; for perhaps he has heard it said that whenever
          you fail to apprehend the guilty, you punish any who cross your path. But I for my part do
          not think that you are so disposed, and I believe that it is easy to controvert the pleas
          just suggested. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>As for his lamentations, it is fitting that you give aid, not to those who try to show
          that they are the most miserable of men, but to those whose statements concerning the
          facts to which they have sworn in their affidavits are manifestly the more just. And in
          regard to the penalty assessed against the loser, if I were responsible for this action,
          you might reasonably sympathize with him as about to be penalized; but the truth is, it is
          he who brings in a calumnious accusation and therefore you cannot in justice accept
          anything he says. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In the second place, you should consider this point—that all the exiles who returned to
          the city from the Peiraeus would be able to use the very same arguments as he; but no one
          except Callimachus has had the audacity to introduce such a suit. And yet you ought to
          hate such persons and regard them as bad citizens who, although they have suffered the
          same misfortunes as the part of the people, think fit to exact exceptional punishments.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, it is possible for him even now, before he has made trial of your decision,
          to drop the suit and to be entirely rid of all his troubles. And yet is it not stupid of
          him to seek to win your pity while in this jeopardy, for which he himself is responsible,
          and in which he has involved himself, a jeopardy which even now it is possible for him to
          avoid? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And if he does mention events which occurred under the oligarchy, demand of him that,
          instead of accusing persons whom no one will defend,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e.,
            the oligarchs.</note> he prove that it was I who took his money; for this is the issue
          upon which you must cast your votes. And demand that he, instead of showing that he has
          suffered cruel wrongs, prove that it is I who have committed them, I, from whom he seeks
          to recover what he has lost; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>since the fact of his evil plight he can readily establish in a suit brought against any
          other citizen whatever. And yet the accusations which should have great weight with you
          are not those which may be made even against those who are entirely guiltless, but those
          only which cannot be brought against any persons except those who have committed an act of
          injustice. To these allegations, this will perhaps be a sufficient reply and a further
          rebuttal soon will be possible. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Also bear in mind, I ask you—even though I may be thought by someone to be repeating
          myself—that many persons are attentively watching the outcome of this case; not because
          they are interested in affairs, but because they believe that the covenant of Amnesty is
          on trial. Such persons, if your decision is just, you will enable to dwell in the city
          without fear; otherwise, how do you expect those who remained in the city to feel, if you
          show that you are angry with all alike who obtained the rights of citizenship? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And what will those think who are conscious of even slight error on their part, when they
          see that not even persons whose conduct as citizens has been decent obtain justice? What
          confusion must be expected to ensue when some<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The former
            oligarchs.</note> are encouraged to bring malicious accusations in the belief that your
          sentiments are now the same as theirs, and when others<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Those of democratic principles.</note> fear the present form of government on the
          ground that no place of refuge is any longer left to them? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>May we not rightly fear that, once your oaths have been violated, we shall again be
          brought to the same state of affairs which compelled us to make the covenant of Amnesty?
          Certainly you do not need to learn from others how great is the blessing of concord or how
          great a curse is civil war; for you have experienced both in so extreme a form that you
          yourselves would be best qualified to instruct all others regarding them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But lest it be thought that the reason I am dwelling long on the covenant of Amnesty is
          merely because it is easy when speaking on that subject to make many just observations, I
          urge you to remember when you cast your votes only one thing more—that before we entered
          into those agreements we Athenians were in a state of war, some of us occupying the circle
          enclosed by the city's walls, others Piraeus after we had captured it,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The oligarchs were in power in the city; the democratic party
            after their occupation of Phyle (the fort on Mt. Parnes in Attica), captured and held
            Piraeus.</note> and we hated each other more than we did the enemies bequeathed to us by
          our ancestors. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But after we came together and exchanged the solemn pledges, we have lived so uprightly
          and so like citizens of one country that it seemed as if no misfortune had ever befallen
          us. At that time all looked upon us as the most foolish and ill-fated of mankind; now,
          however, we are regarded as the happiest and wisest of the Greeks. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore it is incumbent upon us to inflict upon those who dare to violate the covenant,
          not merely the heavy penalties prescribed by the treaty, but the most extreme, on the
          ground that these persons are the cause of the greatest evils, especially those who have
          lived as Callimachus has lived. For during the ten years<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A
            reference to the so-called Decelean War (<date from="-0413" to="-0404">413-404
              B.C.</date>) when the Spartans occupied Decelea in Attica.</note> when the
          Lacedaemonians warred upon you uninterruptedly, not for one single day's service did he
          present himself to the generals; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>on the contrary, all through that period he continued to evade service and to keep his
          property in concealment. But when the Thirty came to power, then it was that he sailed
          back to Athens. And although he professes to be a friend of the people, yet he was so much
          more eager than anybody else to participate in the oligarchical government that, even
          though it meant hardship, he saw fit not to depart, but preferred to be besieged in
          company with those who had injured him rather than to live as a citizen with you, who
          likewise had been wronged by them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And he remained as a participant in their government until that day on which you were on
          the point of attacking the walls of Athens; then he left the city, not because he had come
          to hate the present regime, but because he was afraid of the danger which threatened, as
          he later made evident. For when the Lacedaemonians came and the democracy was shut up in
          the Piraeus,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By Pausanias, king of Sparta and his general,
            Lysander.</note> again he fled from there and resided among the Boeotians; it is far
          more fitting, therefore, that his name should be enrolled in the list of the deserters
          than that he should be called one of the “exiles.” </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And although he has proved to be a man of such character by his conduct toward the people
          who occupied the Piraeus, toward those who remained in the city, and toward the whole
          state, he is not content to be on equal terms with the others, but seeks to be treated
          better than you, as if either he alone had suffered injury, or was the best of the
          citizens, or had met with the gravest misfortunes on your account, or had been the cause
          of the most numerous benefits to the city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I could wish that you knew him as well as I do, in order that, instead of commiserating
          with him over his losses, you might bear him a grudge for what he has left. The fact is,
          though, that if I should try to tell of all the others who have been the objects of his
          plots, of the private law-suits in which he has been involved, of the public suits which
          he has entered, of the persons with whom he has conspired or against whom he has borne
          false witness, not even twice as much water<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The time
            allotted to the litigant for his speech in the Athenian law-courts was regulated by an
            official water-clock (the klepsydra). One has been found; cf. <title>Hesperia</title>
            viii., 1939.</note> as has been allotted me would prove sufficient. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But when you have heard only one of the acts which he has committed you will readily
          recognize the general run of his villainy. Cratinus once had a dispute over a farm with
          the brother-in-law of Callimachus. A personal encounter ensued. Having concealed a female
          slave, they accused Cratinus of having crushed her head, and asserting that she had died
          as a result of the wound, they brought suit against him in the court of the Palladium<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The tribunal for cases of unpremeditated homicide; also for
            trials involving the murder of slaves, resident-aliens, and foreigners. Cf. <bibl
              n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57.3">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57.3</bibl>.</note> on the charge of
          murder. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Cratinus, learning of their plots, remained quiet for a long time in order that they
          might not change their plans and concoct another story, but instead might be caught in the
          very act of committing a crime. When the brother-in-law of Callimachus had made accusation
          and Callimachus had testified on oath that the woman was actually dead, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Cratinus and his friends went to the house where she had been hidden, seized her by force
          and, bringing her into court, presented her alive to all present. The result was that, in
          a tribunal of seven hundred judges, after fourteen witnesses had given the same testimony
          as that of Callimachus, he failed to receive a single vote. Please call witnesses to these
          facts. <quote type="Witnesses"/>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Who, therefore, would be able to condemn his acts as they deserve? Or who would be able
          to find a more flagrant example of wrongdoing, of malicious prosecution, and of villainy?
          Some misdeeds, it is true, do not reveal in its entirety the character of the evil-doers,
          but from acts such as his it is easy to discern the whole life of the culprits. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For any man who testifies that the living are dead, from what villainy do you think that
          he would abstain? What outrageous deed would a man not have the effrontery to commit in
          his own interest who is so knavish a villain in the interest of others ? How is it right
          to trust this man when he speaks in his own behalf, who is proved guilty of perjury in his
          testimony on behalf of another? Who was ever more convincingly proved to be a giver of
          false testimony? You judge all other defendants by what is said of them, but this man's
          testimony the jurors themselves saw was false. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And after the commission of such crimes he will dare to say that it is we who are lying.
          Why that would be as if Phrynondas<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A notorious swindler;
            cf. <bibl n="Aristoph. Thes. 861">Aristoph. Thes. 861</bibl> and <bibl
              n="Aeschin. 3.137">Aeschin. 3.137</bibl>.</note> should reproach a man with villainy,
          or as if Philurgos, who stole the Gorgon's head,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The golden
            relief of the head, the work of Pheidias, was affixed to the shield of the gold and
            ivory statue of Athena in the Parthenon.</note> had called everybody else
          temple-robbers! Who is more likely to present witnesses of events which have not occurred
          than my antagonist here, who himself has the hardihood to testify falsely for others? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But against Callimachus it will be possible to bring accusations time and again, for he
          has contrived his life as a citizen that way; but as for myself, I shall say nothing of
          all my other contributions to the state, but I will merely remind you of that one, a
          service for which, if you would do me justice, you would not only be grateful, but you
          would take it even as evidence bearing upon the case as a whole. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now when the city had lost its ships in the Hellespont<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At
            Aegospotami, <date when="-0405">405 B.C.</date></note> and was shorn of its power, I so
          far surpassed the majority of the trierarchs that I was one of the very few who saved
          their ships: and of these few I alone brought back my ship to the Piraeus and did not
          resign my duties as trierarch; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but when the other trierarchs were glad to be relieved of their duties and were
          discouraged over the situation, and not only regretted the loss of what they had already
          spent, but were trying to conceal the remainder and, judging that the commonwealth was
          completely ruined, were looking out for their private interests, my decision was not the
          same as theirs; but after persuading my brother to be joint-trierarch with me, we paid the
          crew out of our own means and proceeded to harass the enemy. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And finally, when Lysander<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The general of the victorious
            Spartan army of occupation.</note> proclaimed that if anyone should import grain to you
          he would be punished with death, we were so zealous for the city's welfare that, although
          no one else dared to bring in even his own, we intercepted the grain that was being
          brought in to them and discharged it at the Piraeus. In recognition of these services you
          voted that we should be honored with crowns, and that in front of the statues of the
          eponymous heroes<note anchored="true" resp="ed">These were statues of those heroes who
            gave their names to the ten Attic tribes. The probable site of these statues is near the
            north-center of the Agora, near the statues of Harmodius and Aristogeiton and in the
            neighborhood of the temple of Ares.</note> we should be proclaimed as the authors of
          great blessings. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Yet surely men who should now be regarded as friends of the people are not those who,
          when the people were in power, were eager to participate in affairs, but those who, when
          the state was suffering misfortune, were willing to brave the first dangers in your
          behalf, and gratitude is due, not to him who has suffered personal hardships, but to him
          who has conferred benefits upon you; and in the case of those who have become poor, pity
          should be felt, not for those who have lost their property, but for those who have spent
          their fortune for your good. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Of these last named it will be found that I have been one; and I should be the most
          miserable of all men, if, after I have spent much of my fortune for the good of the city,
          it should be thought that I plot against the property of others, and that I care naught
          for your poor opinion of me; when it is obvious that I set less store, not merely on my
          property, but even on my life, than on your good opinion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Who among you would not feel remorse, even if not immediately, yet soon hereafter, if you
          should see the calumniator enriched, but me despoiled even of that which I left remaining
          when serving you as trierarch: and if you should see this man, who never even ran a risk
          on your behalf, influential enough to override both the laws and the covenant of Amnesty,
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and me, who have been so zealous in serving the state, adjudged unworthy of obtaining
          even my just rights? And who would not reproach you, if, cajoled by the words of
          Callimachus, you should find me of such baseness, you who, when you judged us on the
          strength of our deeds, crowned us for our bravery at a time when it was not so easy as it
          is now to win that honor? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It has come to pass that our appeal is the opposite of that which other litigants
          generally make; for everybody else reminds the recipients of the benefactions they have
          received, whereas we ask you, the donors, to bear your gifts in mind, that they may serve
          you as corroboration of all I have said and of our principles of conduct. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And it is evident that we showed ourselves worthy of this honor, not for the purpose of
          plundering the property of others after the oligarchy had been established, but in order
          that, after the city had been saved, not only all the citizens might keep their own
          possessions, but also that in the hearts of our fellow-citizens at large there might be a
          feeling of gratitude to us as a debt to be paid. It is this that we beg of you now, not
          seeking to have more than is just, but offering proof that we are guilty of no wrongdoing
          and asking you to abide by the oaths and the covenant of Amnesty. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it would be outrageous if those covenants should be held valid for the exculpation of
          the evil-doers, but should be made invalid for us, your benefactors! And it is prudent for
          you to guard well your present fortune, remembering that while in the past such agreements
          have increased civic discord in other cities, yet to ours they have brought a greater
          degree of concord.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In §§ 67-68 the manuscripts offer a text
            both illegible in places and corrupt otherwise; see the critical notes.</note> So you,
          keeping these considerations in mind, should cast your votes for that which is at the same
          time just and also expedient.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
