<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>

      <fileDesc>

         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ion</title>
            <author>Plato</author>
            <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
            <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
               <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
               <name>William Merrill</name>
               <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
               <name>David Smith</name>
            </respStmt>
            <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
         </titleStmt>

         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
            <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
         </publicationStmt>


         <notesStmt>
             <note anchored="true">Text was scanned at St. Olaf Spring, 1992.</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plato</author>
                  <title>Plato in Twelve Volumes, translated by W. R. M. Lamb</title>
                  
                  <imprint>
                     <biblScope unit="volume">8</biblScope>
                     <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date>1925</date>
                  </imprint>
               </monogr>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>


      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
               replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">           
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>

       <!--  <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="text"/>
            <state unit="section"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
            <state unit="text"/>
            <state unit="page"/>
         </refsDecl>-->
      </encodingDesc>

      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
         <particDesc>
            <person><persName>Socrates</persName></person>
            <person><persName>Ion</persName></person>
         </particDesc>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2017-07-17" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion.</change> 
         <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
         <change when="1992-07-01" who="WPM">Tagged in conformance with Prose.e dtd.</change>
     </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0059.tlg027.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="530">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="530"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="530a"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Welcome, Ion.  Where have you come from now, to pay us this visit?  From your home in <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName>?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, no, Socrates;  from <placeName key="tgn,7011116">Epidaurus</placeName> and the festival there of Asclepius.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Do you mean to say that the Epidaurians honor the god with a contest of rhapsodes also?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Certainly, and of music <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><q type="soCalled">Music</q> with the Greeks included poetry.</note> in general.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Why then, you were competing in some contest, were you?  And how went your competition?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>We carried off the first prize, Socrates.</p></said>
            
 <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="530b"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well done:  so now, mind that we win too at the Panathenaea. <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The Athenian festival of the Great Panathenaea was held every fourth year, and the Small Panathenaea probably every year, about July.</note>
               </p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Why, so we shall, God willing.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>I must say I have often envied you rhapsodes, Ion, for your art:  for besides that it is fitting to your art that your person should be adorned and that you should look as handsome as possible, the necessity of being conversant with a number of good poets, and especially with Homer, the best and divinest poet of all, and of apprehending <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="530c"/> his thought and not merely learning off his words, is a matter for envy;  since a man can never be a good rhapsode without understanding what the poet says.  For the rhapsode ought to make himself an interpreter of the poet’s thought to his audience;  and to do this properly without knowing what the poet means is impossible.  So one cannot but envy all this.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>What you say is true, Socrates:  I at any rate have found this the most laborious part of my art;  and I consider I speak about Homer better than anybody, for neither <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="530d"/> Metrodorus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A friend of the philosopher Anaxagoras who wrote allegorical interpretations of Homer in the first part of the fifth century B.C.</note> of <placeName key="tgn,7002579">Lampsacus</placeName>, nor Stesimbrotus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A rhapsode, interpreter of Homer, and historian who lived in the time of Cimon and Pericles.</note> of <placeName key="tgn,7011078">Thasos</placeName>, nor Glaucon, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Perhaps the Homeric commentator mentioned by Aristotle, <title>Poet.</title> 25. 16.</note> nor any one that the world has ever seen, had so many and such fine comments to offer on Homer as I have.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>That is good news, Ion;  for obviously you will not grudge me an exhibition of them.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>And indeed it is worth hearing, Socrates, how well I have embellished Homer;  so that I think I deserve to be crowned with a golden crown by the Homeridae. <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">There was a society or clan in <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName> called Homeridae (<gloss>sons of Homer</gloss>), but the name seems to be used here and elsewhere in Plato for any persons specially devoted to Homer’s poetry.  See Jebb, <title>Homer</title>, p. 78.</note>
               </p></said></div>
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="531">
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Yes, and I must find myself leisure some time to listen to you; <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="531"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="531a"/> but for the moment, please answer this little question:  are you skilled in Homer only, or in Hesiod and Archilochus as well?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, no, only in Homer;  for that seems to me quite enough.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And is there anything on which Homer and Hesiod both say the same?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes, I think there are many such cases.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then in those cases would you expound better what Homer says than what Hesiod says?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>I should do it equally well in those cases, Socrates, where they say the same.</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="531b"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But what of those where they do not say the same?  For example, about the seer’s art, on which both Homer and Hesiod say something.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Quite so.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well then, would you, or one of the good seers, expound better what these two poets say, not only alike but differently, about the seer’s art?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>One of the seers.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And if you were a seer, would you not, with an ability to expound what they say in agreement, know also how to expound the points on which they differ?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Of course.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then how is it that you are skilled in Homer, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="531c"/> and not in Hesiod or the other poets?  Does Homer speak of any other than the very things that all the other poets speak of?  Has he not described war for the most part, and the mutual intercourse of men, good and bad, lay and professional, and the ways of the gods in their intercourse with each other and with men, and happenings in the heavens and in the underworld, and origins of gods and heroes?  <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="531d"/> Are not these the subjects of Homer’s poetry?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>What you say is true, Socrates.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And what of the other poets?  Do they not treat of the same things?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes;  but, Socrates, not on Homer’s level.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>What, in a worse way?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Far worse.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And Homer in a better?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Better indeed, I assure you.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well now, Ion, dear soul;  when several people are talking about number, and one of them speaks better than the rest, I suppose there is some one who will distinguish the good speaker?</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="531e"/>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>I agree.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And will this some one be the same as he who can distinguish the bad speakers, or different?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>The same, I suppose.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And he will be the man who has the art of numeration?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And again, when several are talking about what kinds of foods are wholesome, and one of them speaks better than the rest, will it be for two different persons to distinguish the superiority of the best speaker and the inferiority of a worse one, or for the same?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Obviously, I should say, for the same.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Who is he?  What is his name?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>A doctor.</p></said></div>
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="532">
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And so we may state, in general terms, that the same person will always distinguish, given the same subject and several persons talking about it, <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="532"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="532a"/> both who speaks well and who badly:  otherwise, if he is not going to distinguish the bad speaker, clearly he will not distinguish the good one either, where the subject is the same.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>That is so.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And the same man is found to be skilled in both?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And you say that Homer and the other poets, among whom are Hesiod and Archilochus, all speak about the same things, only not similarly;  but the one does it well, and the rest worse?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes, and what I say is true.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And since you distinguish the good speaker, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="532b"/> you could distinguish also the inferiority of the worse speakers.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>So it would seem.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then, my excellent friend, we shall not be wrong in saying that our Ion is equally skilled in Homer and in the other poets, seeing that you yourself admit that the same man will be a competent judge of all who speak on the same things, and that practically all the poets treat of the same things.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Then what can be the reason, Socrates, why I pay no attention when somebody discusses any other poet, and am unable to offer any remark at all of any value, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="532c"/> but simply drop into a doze, whereas if anyone mentions something connected with Homer I wake up at once and attend and have plenty to say?</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>That is not difficult to guess, my good friend;  anyone can see that you are unable to speak on Homer with art and knowledge.  For if you could do it with art, you could speak on all the other poets as well;  since there is an art of poetry, I take it, as a whole, is there not?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="532d"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And when one has acquired any other art whatever as a whole, the same principle of inquiry holds through all the arts?  Do you require some explanation from me, Ion, of what I mean by this?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes, upon my word, Socrates, I do;  for I enjoy listening to you wise men.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>I only wish you were right there, Ion:  but surely it is you rhapsodes and actors, and the men whose poems you chant, who are wise;  whereas I speak but the plain truth, as a simple layman might.  <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="532e"/> For in regard to this question I asked you just now, observe what a trifling commonplace it was that I uttered—a thing that any man might know—namely, that when one has acquired a whole art the inquiry is the same.  Let us just think it out thus:  there is an art of painting as a whole?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And there are and have been many painters, good and bad?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Certainly.</p></said></div>
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="533">
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Now have you ever found anybody who is skilled in pointing out the successes and failures among the works of Polygnotus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A celebrated painter who came 488 B.</note> son of Aglaophon, but unable to do so with the works of the other painters;  <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="533"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="533a"/> and who, when the works of the other painters are exhibited, drops into a doze, and is at a loss, and has no remark to offer;  but when he has to pronounce upon Polygnotus or any other painter you please, and on that one only, wakes up and attends and has plenty to say?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, on my honor, I certainly have not.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Or again, in sculpture, have you ever found anyone who is skilled in expounding the successes of Daedalus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">According to legend, the first sculptor:  cf. <title>Euthyphro</title> 11, <title>Meno</title> 97 D.</note> son of Metion, or Epeius <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The maker of the wooden horse at <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>  (Homer, <title>Od.</title> 8.493).</note> son of Panopeus, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="533b"/> or Theodorus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A metal-worker (Herodot. 1. 51, 3. 41).</note> of <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>, or any other single sculptor, but in face of the works of the other sculptors is at a loss and dozes, having nothing to say?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, on my honor, I have not found such a man as that either.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But further, I expect you have also failed to find one in fluting or harping or minstrelsy or rhapsodizing who is skilled in expounding the art of <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>
                   <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">One of the mythical inventors of music:  cf. <title>Symp.</title> 215 E.</note> <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="533c"/> or Thamyras, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A Thracian Bard.</note> or Orpheus, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A Thracian Bard.</note> or Phemius, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The minstrel who was forced to sing to the suitors of Penelope (<title>Od</title> 1. 154, 22. 330).</note> the rhapsode of <placeName key="tgn,1007519">Ithaca</placeName>, but is at a loss and has no remark to offer on the successes or failures in rhapsody of Ion of <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName>.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>I cannot gainsay you on that, Socrates:  but of one thing I am conscious in myself—that I excel all men in speaking on Homer and have plenty to say, and everyone else says that I do it well;  but on the others I am not a good speaker.  Yet now, observe what that means.</p></said>
            <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>I do observe it, Ion, and I am going to point out to you <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="533d"/> what I take it to mean.  For, as I was saying just now, this is not an art in you, whereby you speak well on Homer, but a divine power, which moves you like that in the stone which Euripides named a magnet, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Probably referring to <placeName key="tgn,7002751">Magnesia</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002358">Caria</placeName>, south of which was one of the many places called <placeName key="tgn,7008299">Heraclea</placeName>. <foreign xml:lang="grc">Μαγνῆτις λίθος</foreign>  occurs in a fragment of Euripides’ <title>Oeneus.</title>
            </note> but most people call <q type="soCalled"><placeName key="tgn,7008299">Heraclea</placeName> stone.</q>  For this stone not only attracts iron rings, but also imparts to them a power whereby they in turn are able to do the very same thing as the stone, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="533e"/> and attract other rings;  so that sometimes there is formed quite a long chain of bits of iron and rings, suspended one from another;  and they all depend for this power on that one stone.  In the same manner also the Muse inspires men herself, and then by means of these inspired persons the inspiration spreads to others, and holds them in a connected chain.</p></said></div> 
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="534">  
               <said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>For all the good epic poets utter all those fine poems not from art, but as inspired and possessed, and the good lyric poets likewise;  <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="534"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="534a"/> just as the Corybantian <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The Corybantes were priests of Cybele or Rhea, mother of Zeus and other Olympian gods, and she was worshipped with wild music and frenzied dancing which, like the bacchic revels or orgies of women in honor of Dionysus, carried away the participants despite and beyond themselves.  Cf.  Eurip. <title>Bacchae.</title></note> worshippers do not dance when in their senses, so the lyric poets do not indite those fine songs in their senses, but when they have started on the melody and rhythm they begin to be frantic, and it is under possession—as the bacchants are possessed, and not in their senses, when they draw honey and milk from the rivers—that the soul of the lyric poets does the same thing, by their own report.  For the poets tell us, I believe, that the songs they bring us are the sweets they cull from honey-dropping founts <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="534b"/> in certain gardens and glades of the Muses—like the bees, and winging the air as these do. <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A beginning of this comparison appears in Aristophanes’ praise of the early tragedian Phrynichus—<cit><quote>he sipped the fruits of ambrosial lays, ever bringing away sweet song.</quote> <bibl>Aristoph. Birds 750f.</bibl></cit></note> And what they tell is true.  For a poet is a light and winged and sacred thing, and is unable ever to indite until he has been inspired and put out of his senses, and his mind is no longer in him:  every man, whilst he retains possession of that, is powerless to indite a verse or chant an oracle.  Seeing then that it is not by art that they compose and utter so many fine things about the deeds of men—<milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="534c"/> as you do about Homer—but by a divine dispensation, each is able only to compose that to which the Muse has stirred him, this man dithyrambs, another laudatory odes, another dance-songs, another epic or else iambic verse;  but each is at fault in any other kind.  For not by art do they utter these things, but by divine influence;  since, if they had fully learnt by art to speak on one kind of theme, they would know how to speak on all.  And for this reason God takes away the mind of these men and uses them as his ministers, just as he does soothsayers and godly seers, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="534d"/> in order that we who hear them may know that it is not they who utter these words of great price, when they are out of their wits, but that it is God himself who speaks and addresses us through them.  A convincing proof of what I say is the case of Tynnichus, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Nothing else is known of this poet.</note> the Chalcidian, who had never composed a single poem in his life that could deserve any mention, and then produced the paean <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A hymn in honor of a god, usually Apollo.</note> which is in everyone’s mouth, almost the finest song we have, simply—as he says himself—<quote>an invention of the Muses.</quote>  For the god, as it seems to me, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="534e"/> intended him to be a sign to us that we should not waver or doubt that these fine poems are not human or the work of men, but divine and the work of gods;  and that the poets are merely the interpreters of the gods, according as each is possessed by one of the heavenly powers.  To show this forth, the god of set purpose sang the finest of songs through the meanest of poets:  <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="535"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="535a"/> or do you not think my statement true, Ion?</p></said></div> 
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="535">
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes, upon my word, I do:  for you somehow touch my soul with your words, Socrates, and I believe it is by divine dispensation that good poets interpret to us these utterances of the gods.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And you rhapsodes, for your part, interpret the utterances of the poets?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Again your words are true.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And so you act as interpreters of interpreters?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Precisely.</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="535b"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Stop now and tell me, Ion, without reserve what I may choose to ask you:  when you give a good recitation and specially thrill your audience, either with the lay of Odysseus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">
                     <title>Od.</title> 22.2ff.</note> leaping forth on to the threshold, revealing himself to the suitors and pouring out the arrows before his feet, or of Achilles <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">
                     <title>Il.</title> 22.312ff.</note> dashing at Hector, or some part of the sad story of Andromache <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">
                     <title>Il.</title> 6.370-502;  22.437-515.</note> or of Hecuba, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">
                     <title>Il.</title> 22.430-36;  24.747-59.</note> or of Priam, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">
                     <title>Il.</title> 22.408-28;  24.144-717.</note> are you then in your senses, or are you carried out of yourself, and does your soul in an ecstasy suppose <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="535c"/> herself to be among the scenes you are describing, whether they be in <placeName key="tgn,7013803">Ithaca</placeName>, or in <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName>, or as the poems may chance to place them?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>How vivid to me, Socrates, is this part of your proof!  For I will tell you without reserve:  when I relate a tale of woe, my eyes are filled with tears;  and when it is of fear or awe, my hair stands on end with terror, and my heart leaps.
</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="535d"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well now, are we to say, Ion, that such a person is in his senses at that moment,—when in all the adornment of elegant attire and golden crowns he weeps at sacrifice or festival, having been despoiled of none of his finery;  or shows fear as he stands before more than twenty thousand friendly people, none of whom is stripping or injuring him?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, on my word, not at all, Socrates, to tell the strict truth.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And are you aware that you rhapsodes produce these same effects on most of the spectators also?
</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="535e"/>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes, very fully aware:  for I look down upon them from the platform and see them at such moments crying and turning awestruck eyes upon me and yielding to the amazement of my tale.  For I have to pay the closest attention to them;  since, if I set them crying, I shall laugh myself because of the money I take, but if they laugh, I myself shall cry because of the money I lose.</p></said></div> 
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="536">
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And are you aware that your spectator is the last of the rings which I spoke of as receiving from each other the power transmitted from the Heraclean lodestone? <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="536"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="536a"/> You, the rhapsode and actor, are the middle ring;  the poet himself is the first;  but it is the god who through the whole series draws the souls of men whithersoever he pleases, making the power of one depend on the other.  And, just as from the magnet, there is a mighty chain of choric performers and masters and under-masters suspended by side-connections from the rings that hang down from the Muse.  One poet is suspended from one Muse, another from another: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="536b"/> the word we use for it is <q type="emph">possessed,</q> but it is much the same thing, for he is held.  And from these first rings—the poets—are suspended various others, which are thus inspired, some by Orpheus and others by Musaeus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A legendary bard to whom certain oracular verses were ascribed.</note>;  but the majority are possessed and held by Homer.  Of whom you, Ion, are one, and are possessed by Homer;  and so, when anyone recites the work of another poet, you go to sleep and are at a loss what to say;  but when some one utters a strain of your poet, you wake up at once, and your soul dances, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="536c"/> and you have plenty to say:  for it is not by art or knowledge about Homer that you say what you say, but by divine dispensation and possession;  just as the Corybantian worshippers are keenly sensible of that strain alone which belongs to the god whose possession is on them, and have plenty of gestures and phrases for that tune, but do not heed any other.  And so you, Ion, when the subject of Homer is mentioned, have plenty to say, but nothing on any of the others.  And when you ask me the reason <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="536d"/> why you can speak at large on Homer but not on the rest, I tell you it is because your skill in praising Homer comes not by art, but by divine dispensation.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Well spoken, I grant you, Socrates;  but still I shall be surprised if you can speak well enough to convince me that I am possessed and mad when I praise Homer.  Nor can I think you would believe it of me yourself, if you heard me speaking about him.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>I declare I am quite willing to hear you, but not until <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="536e"/> you have first answered me this:  on what thing in Homer’s story do you speak well?  Not on all of them, I presume.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>I assure you, Socrates, on all without a single exception.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Not, of course, including those things of which you have in fact no knowledge, but which Homer tells.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>And what sort of things are they, which Homer tells, but of which I have no knowledge?</p></said></div> 
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="537">

<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="537"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="537a"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Why, does not Homer speak a good deal about arts, in a good many places?  For instance, about chariot-driving:  if I can recall the lines, I will quote them to you.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, I will recite them, for I can remember.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Tell me then what Nestor says to his son Antilochus, advising him to be careful about the turning-post in the horse-race in honor of Patroclus.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>
                  <cit>
                     <quote type="verse">
                     <l met="dactylic">Bend thyself in the polished car slightly to the left of them; <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e. one of the two white stones, set up at each end of the course, which had been mentioned six lines before.</note> and call to the right-hand horse <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="537b"/> and goad him on, while your hand slackens his reins.  And at the post let your left-hand horse swerve close, so that the nave of the well-wrought wheel may seem to come up to the edge of the stone, which yet avoid to touch.</l></quote>
                     <bibl>Hom. Il. 23.335 ff.</bibl>
                  </cit>
               </p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Enough.  Now, Ion, will a doctor or a charioteer be the better judge <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="537c"/> whether Homer speaks correctly or not in these lines?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>A charioteer, of course.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Because he has this art, or for some other reason?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, because it is his art.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And to every art has been apportioned by God a power of knowing a particular business?  For I take it that what we know by the art of piloting we cannot also know by that of medicine.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, to be sure.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And what we know by medicine, we cannot by carpentry also?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, indeed.</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="537d"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And this rule holds for all the arts, that what we know by one of them we cannot know by another?  But before you answer that, just tell me this:  do you agree that one art is of one sort, and another of another?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Do you argue this as I do, and call one art different from another when one is a knowledge of one kind of thing, and another a knowledge of another kind?</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="537e"/>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Since, I suppose, if it were a knowledge of the same things—how could we say that one was different from another, when both could give us the same knowledge?  Just as I know that there are five of these fingers, and you equally know the same fact about them;  and if I should ask you whether both you and I know this same fact by the same art of numeration, or by different arts, you would reply, I presume, that it was by the same?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said></div> 
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="538">
            
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="538"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="538a"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then tell me now, what I was just going to ask you, whether you think this rule holds for all the arts—that by the same art we must know the same things, and by a different art things that are not the same;  but if the art is other, the things we know by it must be different also.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>I think it is so, Socrates.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then he who has not a particular art will be incapable of knowing aright the words or works of that art?</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="538b"/>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>True.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then will you or a charioteer be the better judge of whether Homer speaks well or not in the lines that you quoted?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>A charioteer.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Because, I suppose, you are a rhapsode and not a charioteer.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And the rhapsode’s art is different from the charioteer’s?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then if it is different, it is also a knowledge of different things.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Now, what of the passage where Homer tells how Hecamede, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="538c"/> Nestor’s concubine, gives the wounded Machaon a posset?  His words are something like this: 
               <quote type="verse">
               <l met="dactylic">Of Pramneian wine it was, and therein she grated cheese of goat’s milk with a grater of bronze;  and thereby an onion as a relish for drink.</l>
                  </quote>
                  <bibl n="Hom. Il. 11.639">Hom. Il. 11.639-40</bibl>
                   <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The quotation, as Plato indicates, is not accurate.  Machaon was the son of Asclepius and physician to the Greeks at <placeName key="tgn,7014164">Troy</placeName>.  Nothing is known of <q type="mentioned">Pramneian wine,</q> except that it was <quote>thick and nutritious</quote> (<bibl n="Ath. 1.10b">Athen.  1.10b</bibl>).</note>  Is it for the doctor’s or the rhapsode’s art to discern aright whether Homer speaks correctly here or not?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>For the doctor’s.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well now, when Homer says: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="538d"/>
                  
                  <quote type="verse">
                     <l met="dactylic">And she passed to the bottom like a plummet which, set on a horn </l>
                  </quote> 977) supports Aristotle’s view that the horn acted as a sheath to protect the line from being bitten through by the fish. are we to say it is for the fisherman’s or for the rhapsode’s art to decide what he means by this, and whether it is rightly or wrongly spoken?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Clearly, Socrates, for the fisherman’s art.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then please observe:  suppose you were questioning me and should ask: <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="538e"/> <q type="spoken">Since therefore, Socrates, you find it is for these several arts to appraise the passages of Homer that belong to each, be so good as to make out those also that are for the seer and the seer’s art, and show me the sort of passages that come under his ability to distinguish whether they are well or ill done</q>;  observe how easily and truly I shall answer you.  For he has many passages, both in the <bibl>Odyssey</bibl>, as for instance the words of Theoclymenus, the seer of the line of Melampus, to the suitors:</p></said></div>
            
         
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="539">
            <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="539"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="539a"/>
            <said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>
                  <quote type="verse">
                     <l met="dactylic">Hapless men, what bane is this afflicts you?  Your heads and faces and limbs below are shrouded in night, and wailing is enkindled, and cheeks are wet with tears:  of ghosts the porch is full, and the court full of them also, hastening hell-wards ’neath the gloom:  and the sun is perished out of heaven, and an evil mist is spread abroad;</l>
                  </quote>
                  <bibl n="Hom. Od. 20.351">Hom. Od. 20.351-57</bibl>
                   <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Melampus, the ancestor of Theoclymenus (cf. <bibl n="Hom. Od. 15.225">Hom. Od. 15.225-56</bibl>), was supposed to have been the first mortal who possessed the gift of prophecy.</note>
               
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="539b"/>
              and there are many passages in the <title>Iliad</title> also, as in the fight at the rampart, where he says:
                  <cit><quote type="verse">
                     <l met="dactylic">For as they were eager to pass over, a bird had crossed them, an eagle of lofty flight, pressing the host at the left hand, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="539c"/> and bearing a blood-red monster of a snake, alive and still struggling;  nor had it yet unlearnt the lust of battle.  For bending back it smote its captor on the breast by the neck, and the bird in the bitterness of pain cast it away to the ground, and dropped it down in the midst of the throng; and then with a cry flew off on the wafting winds.</l></quote>
                     <bibl>Hom. Il. 12.200-7</bibl>
                  </cit>
                  
                  This passage, and others of the sort, are those that I should say the seer has to examine and judge.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>And you speak the truth, Socrates.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And so do you, Ion, in saying that.  Now you must do as I did, and in return for my picking out and the <title>Iliad</title> the kinds of passage that belong severally to the seer, <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="539e"/> the doctor, and the fisherman, you have now to pick out for me—since you are so much more versed in Homer than I—the kinds which belong to the rhapsode, Ion, and the rhapsode’s art, and which he should be able to consider and distinguish beyond the rest of mankind.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>What I say, Socrates, is—<q type="emph">all passages.</q></p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Surely you do not say <q type="emph">all,</q> Ion!  Can you be so forgetful?  And yet forgetfulness would ill become a rhapsode.</p></said></div>
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="540">
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="540"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="540a"/>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Why, how am I forgetting?</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Do you not remember that you said that the art of the rhapsode was different from that of the charioteer?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>I remember.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And you also admitted that, being different, it would know different things?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then by your own account the rhapsode’s art cannot know everything, nor the rhapsode either.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Let us say, everything except those instances, Socrates.</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="540b"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>By <q type="mentioned">those instances</q> you imply the subjects of practically all the other arts.  Well, as he does not know all of them, which kinds will he know?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Those things, I imagine, that it befits a man to say, and the sort of thing that a woman should say;  the sort for a slave and the sort for a freeman;  and the sort for a subject or for a ruler.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Do you mean that the rhapsode will know better than the pilot what sort of thing a ruler of a storm-tossed vessel at sea should say?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No, the pilot knows better in that case.
</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="540c"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well, will the rhapsode know better than the doctor what sort of thing a ruler of a sick man should say?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Not in that case either.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But he will know the sort for a slave, you say?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>For instance, if the slave is a cowherd, you say the rhapsode will know what the other should say to pacify his cows when they get fierce, but the cowherd will not?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>That is not so.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well, the sort of thing that a woman ought to say—a spinning-woman—about the working of wool?
</p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="540d"/>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But he will know what a man should say, when he is a general exhorting his men?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes, that sort of thing the rhapsode will know.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Well, but is the art of the rhapsode the art of the general?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>I, at any rate, should know what a general ought to say.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Yes, since I daresay you are good at generalship also, Ion.  For in fact, if you happened to have skill in horsemanship as well as in the lyre, you would know when horses were well or ill managed:  <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="540e"/> but if I asked you, <q type="spoken">By which art is it, Ion, that you know that horses are being well managed, by your skill as a horseman, or as a player of the lyre?</q> what would your answer be?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>I should say, by my skill as a horseman.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And if again you were distinguishing the good lyre-players, you would admit that you distinguished by your skill in the lyre, and not by your skill as a horseman.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Yes.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And when you judge of military matters, do you judge as having skill in generalship, or as a good rhapsode?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>To my mind, there is no difference.</p></said></div>
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="541">
            
<milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="541"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="541a"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>What, no difference, do you say?  Do you mean that the art of the rhapsode and the general is one, not two?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>It is one, to my mind.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>So that anyone who is a good rhapsode is also, in fact, a good general?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Certainly, Socrates.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And again, anyone who happens to be a good general is also a good rhapsode.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>No there I do not agree.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>But still you agree that anyone who is a good rhapsode <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="541b"/> is also a good general?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>To be sure.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>And you are the best rhapsode in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Far the best, Socrates.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Are you also, Ion, the best general in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>Be sure of it, Socrates and that I owe to my study of Homer.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then how, in Heaven’s name, can it be, Ion, that you, who are both the best general and the best rhapsode in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, go about performing as a rhapsode to the Greeks, but not as a general?  <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="541c"/> Or do you suppose that the Greeks feel a great need of a rhapsode in the glory of his golden crown, but of a general none at all?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>It is because my city, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">
                     <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName>.</note> Socrates, is under the rule and generalship of your people, and is not in want of a general;  whilst you and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> would not choose me as a general, since you think you manage well enough for yourselves.</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>My excellent Ion, you are acquainted with Apollodorus <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Nothing else is known of this general.</note> of <placeName key="perseus,Cyzicus">Cyzicus</placeName>, are you not?</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>What might he be?</p></said>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>A man whom the Athenians have often chosen as their general, though a foreigner;  <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="541d"/> and Phanosthenes <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Captured the Thurian admiral Dorieus, <date when="-0407">407</date> B. C.</note> of <placeName key="tgn,7010719">Andros</placeName>, and Heracleides <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Nothing else is known of this general.</note> of Clazomenae, whom my city invests with the high command and other offices although they are foreigners, because they have proved themselves to be competent.  And will she not choose Ion of <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName> as her general, and honor him, if he shows himself competent?  Why, you Ephesians are by origin Athenians, <note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Androclus of <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> founded <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName> as the Ionian city known to the Greeks of Plato’s time.</note> are you not, and <placeName key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName> is inferior to no city?  <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="541e"/> But in fact, Ion, if you are right in saying it is by art and knowledge that you are able to praise Homer, you are playing me false:  you have professed to me that you know any amount of fine things about Homer, and you promise to display them;  but you are only deceiving me, and so far from displaying the subjects of your skill, you decline even to tell me what they are, for all my entreaties.</p></said></div>
            
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" resp="perseus" n="542">
               <said who="#Socrates" rend="merge"><label>Soc.</label> <p>You are a perfect Proteus in the way you take on every kind of shape, twisting about this way and that, until at last you elude my grasp in the guise of a general, so as to avoid displaying your skill <milestone unit="page" resp="Stephanus" n="542"/><milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="542a"/> in Homeric lore.  Now if you are an artist and, as I was saying just now, you only promised me a display about Homer to deceive me, you are playing me false;  whilst if you are no artist, but speak fully and finely about Homer, as I said you did, without any knowledge but by a divine dispensation which causes you to be possessed by the poet, you play quite fair.  Choose therefore which of the two you prefer us to call you, dishonest or divine.</p></said>
               <said who="#Ion"><label>Ion.</label> <p>The difference is great, Socrates;  for it is far nobler to be called divine.
    </p></said>
            
            <milestone unit="section" resp="Stephanus" n="542b"/>
               <said who="#Socrates"><label>Soc.</label> <p>Then you may count on this nobler title in our minds, Ion, of being a divine and not an artistic praiser of Homer.</p></said></div>
            
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>

</TEI>
