<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Nicocles or the Cyprians from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg014.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> There are people who frown upon eloquence and censure men who study philosophy,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For Isocrates' use of the word “philosophy” as covering what
            we mean by “culture” and his identification of “discourse” with the cultivated life see
            General Introduction, pp. xxiii ff.</note> asserting that those who engage in such
          occupations do so, not for the sake of virtue, but for their own advantage. Now, I should
          be glad if those who take this position would tell me why they blame men who are ambitious
          to speak well, but applaud men who desire to act rightly; for if it is the pursuit of
          one's own advantage which gives them offense, we shall find that more and greater
          advantages are gained from actions than from speech. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Moreover, it is passing strange if the fact has escaped them that we reverence the gods
          and practice justice, and cultivate the other virtues, not that we may be worse off than
          our fellows, but that we may pass our days in the enjoyment of as many good things as
          possible. They should not, therefore, condemn these means by which one may gain
            advantage<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Advantage (in the good sense) which works no
            disadvantage to others. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.275">Isoc. 15.275</bibl>.</note> without
          sacrifice of virtue, but rather those men who do wrong in their actions or who deceive by
          their speech and put their eloquence to unjust uses. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I am astonished that those who hold the view to which I have just referred do not rail
          also against wealth and strength and courage; for if they are really hostile to eloquence
          because there are men who do wrong and speak falsehood, they ought to disparage as well
          all other good things; for there will be found also among men who possess these some who
          do wrong and use these advantages to the injury of many.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Good things are bad if badly used. See <bibl n="Aristot. Nic. Eth. 1094b">Aristot. Nic.
              Eth. 1094b 17</bibl>. Cf. Seneca, <title>Ep.</title> i. 5. 9: “multa bona nostra nobis
            nocent.”</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, it is not fair to decry strength because there are persons who assault
          people whom they encounter, nor to traduce courage because there are those who slay men
          wantonly, nor in general to transfer to things the depravity of men, but rather to put the
          blame on the men themselves who misuse the good things, and who, by the very powers which
          might help their fellow-countrymen, endeavor to do them harm.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The same argument is made at length in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.251">Isoc.
              15.251-252</bibl>, also in defense of eloquence.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But the fact is that since they have not taken the trouble to make distinctions after
          this manner in each instance, they are ill-disposed to all eloquence; and they have gone
          so far astray as not to perceive that they are hostile to that power which of all the
          faculties that belong to the nature of man is the source of most of our blessings. For in
          the other powers which we possess we are in no respect superior to other living creatures;
          nay, we are inferior to many in swiftness and in strength and in other resources; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but, because there has been implanted in us the power to persuade each other and to make
          clear to each other whatever we desire, not only have we escaped the life of wild beasts,
          but we have come together and founded cities and made laws and invented arts; and,
          generally speaking, there is no institution devised by man which the power of speech has
          not helped us to establish.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the power of speech as the
            faculty which has raised us from the life of beasts to that of civilized man see <bibl
              n="Xen. Mem. 4.3.11">Xen. Mem. 4.3.11 ff.</bibl> Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.273">Isoc.
              15.273</bibl>, <bibl n="Isoc. 4.48">Isoc. 4.48 ff.</bibl>, and Shelley: “He gave man
            speech and speech created thought.” Isocrates refers to this passage in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.253">Isoc. 15.253</bibl>, and quotes exactly from sections 5-9.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For this it is which has laid down laws concerning things just and unjust, and things
          base and honorable; and if it were not for these ordinances we should not be able to live
          with one another. It is by this also that we confute the bad and extol the good. Through
          this we educate the ignorant and appraise the wise; for the power to speak well is taken
          as the surest index of a sound understanding, and discourse which is true and lawful and
          just is the outward image of a good and faithful soul. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>With this faculty we both contend against others on matters which are open to dispute and
          seek light for ourselves on things which are unknown; for the same arguments which we use
          in persuading others when we speak in public, we employ also when we deliberate in our own
          thoughts; and, while we call eloquent those who are able to speak before a crowd, we
          regard as sage those who most skilfully debate their problems in their own minds. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And, if there is need to speak in brief summary of this power, we shall find that none of
          the things which are done with intelligence take place without the help of speech, but
          that in all our actions as well as in all our thoughts speech is our guide, and is most
          employed by those who have the most wisdom. Therefore, those who dare to speak with
          disrespect of educators and teachers of philosophy deserve our opprobrium no less than
          those who profane the sanctuaries of the gods. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I, myself, welcome all forms of discourse which are capable of benefiting us even in a
          small degree; however, I regard those as the best and most worthy of a king, and most
          appropriate to me, which give directions on good morals and good government;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The aim of the worthy orator is proper conduct in private and
            in public life. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.4">Isoc. 4.4</bibl>, and General Introduction, pp.
            xxiv ff.</note> and especially those which teach how men in power should deal with the
          people, and how the rank and file should be disposed to their rulers. For I observe that
          it is through such discourses that states attain the highest prosperity and greatness.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> On the former topic, how a ruler should act, you have heard Isocrates speak; on the
          following topic, what his subjects must do, I shall attempt to discourse, not with any
          thought of excelling him, but because this is the most fitting subject for me to discuss
          with you. For if I did not make clear what I desire you to do, I could not reasonably be
          angry with you if you were to mistake my purpose; but if, after I have announced my policy
          beforehand, none of my desires are carried out, then I should justly blame those who fail
          to obey me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And I believe that I should most effectively exhort you and urge you to remember my
          words and heed them, not if I should confine myself to giving you advice and then, after
          counting out my precepts, make an end, but if, before doing this, I should prove to you,
          first, that you ought to be content with our present government, not only from necessity,
          nor because we have lived under it all our lives, but because it is the best of all
          governments; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and, second, that I hold this office, not illegally nor as a usurper, but with the just
          sanction of gods and men, and by virtue of my earliest ancestors, and of my father and of
          myself. For, once these claims have been established, who will not condemn himself to the
          severest punishment if he fails to heed my counsels and commands? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Speaking, then, of forms of government (for this was the subject I set out to lay before
          you), I imagine that we all believe that it is altogether monstrous<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">A protest against the new “equality.” Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.14">Isoc.
              2.14</bibl>. In <bibl n="Isoc. 7.21">Isoc. 7.21-22</bibl> Isocrates praises the old
            democracy of <placeName key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName> for recognizing ability and
            worth.</note> that the good and the bad should be thought worthy of the same privileges,
          and that it is of the very essence of justice that distinctions should be made between
          them, and that those who are unlike should not be treated alike but should fare and be
          rewarded in each case according to their deserts. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now oligarchies and democracies seek equality for those who share in the administration
          of them; and the doctrine is in high favor in those governments that one man should not
          have the power to get more than another—a principle which works in the interest of the
          worthless! Monarchies, on the other hand, make the highest award to the best man, the next
          highest to the next best, and in the same proportion to the third and the fourth and so
          on. Even if this practice does not obtain everywhere, such at least is the intention of
          the polity. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And, mark you, monarchies more than other governments keep an appraising eye upon the
          characters and actions of men, as everyone will admit. Who, then, that is of sound mind
          would not prefer to share in a form of government under which his own worth shall not pass
          unnoticed, rather than be lost in the hurly-burly of the mob and not be recognized for
          what he is? Furthermore, we should be right in pronouncing monarchy also a milder
          government, in proportion as it is easier to give heed to the will of a single person than
          to seek to please many and manifold minds. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now one might multiply arguments to prove that this form of government is more agreeable
          and mild and just than others; yet, even from those I have advanced it is easy to see this
          at a glance. As for its other advantages, we can best appreciate how far monarchies excel
          other governments in planning and carrying out any course of action required of them if we
          place their most important practices side by side and try to review them. In the first
          place, then, men who enter upon office for an annual term are retired to private life
          before they have gained any insight into public affairs or any experience in handling
          them; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>while men who are permanently in charge of the same duties, even though they fall short
          of the others in natural ability, at any rate have a great advantage over them in
          experience. In the next place, the former neglect many things, because each looks to the
          others to do them; while the latter neglect nothing, knowing that whatever is done depends
          upon their own efforts. Then again, men who live in oligarchies or democracies are led by
          their mutual rivalries to injure the commonwealth<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Party
            rivalry in the old Athenian democracy was carried on for the good of the state according
            to <bibl n="Isoc. 4.79">Isoc. 4.79</bibl>. Not so in contemporary <placeName
              key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>, <bibl n="Isoc. 4.167">Isoc. 4.167</bibl>.</note>
          while those who live in monarchies, not having anyone to envy, do in all circumstances so
          far as possible what is best. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, the former are dilatory in action,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
            Demosthenes' contrast between the checks and delays which were put upon him as leader of
            the Athenians and <placeName key="tgn,2578607">Phillip</placeName>'s freedom to act and
            strike quickly, <bibl n="Dem. 18.294.">Dem. 18.294.</bibl> Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 4.40">Dem.
              4.40-46</bibl>.</note> for they spend most of their time over their private concerns;
          and when they do assemble in council, you will find them more often quarrelling<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For the selfish bickerings of the platform orators see <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.12">Isoc. 12.12</bibl></note> with each other than deliberating together;
          while the latter, for whom no councils or times of meeting are prescribed, but who apply
          themselves to the state's business both day and night, do not let opportunities pass them
          by, but act in each case at the right moment. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Again, the former are ill-disposed toward each other and would rather have their
          predecessors and their successors in office administer the state as badly as possible, in
          order that they may win for themselves as much credit as possible; while the latter,
          because they are in control of affairs throughout their lives, are at all times actuated
          by feelings of good will. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the greatest difference is this: men under other governments give attention to the
          affairs of state as if they were the concern of others; monarchs, as if they were their
          own concern;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">But it was, he says elsewhere, the virtue of
            the old democracy that they did not slight the commonwealth, but cared for it as their
            personal concern, <bibl n="Isoc. 4.76">Isoc. 4.76</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 7.24">Isoc.
              7.24-25</bibl>.</note> and the former employ as their advisers on state affairs the
          most self-assertive of their citizens, while the latter single out and employ the most
          sagacious; and the former honor those who are skilful in haranguing the crowd, while the
          latter honor those who understand how to deal with affairs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And not only in matters of ordinary routine and of daily occurrence do monarchies excel,
          but in war they have compassed every advantage;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The same
            point is made by <bibl n="Dem. 1.4">Dem. 1.4</bibl>.</note> for in raising troops, and
          handling them so as to mislead and forestall the enemy, and in winning people over, now by
          persuasion, now by force, now by bribery, now by other means of conciliation, one-man rule
          is more efficient than the other forms of government. And of this one may be assured by
          facts no less than by words; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for, in the first place, we all know that the empire of the Persians attained its great
          magnitude, not because of the intelligence of the population, but because they more than
          other peoples respect the royal office; secondly, that Dionysius,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Dionysius, the elder, became tyrant of <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse"
              >Syracuse</placeName> in <date when="-0406">406 B.C.</date></note> the tyrant, taking
          charge of <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> when the rest of it had been
          devastated by war and when his own country, <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse"
            >Syracuse</placeName>, was in a state of siege, not only delivered it from the dangers
          which then threatened, but also made it the greatest of Hellenic states; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and again, we know that while the Carthaginians and the Lacedaemonians, who are the best
          governed peoples of the world,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Socrates and his followers
            idealized, in contrast to the slackness of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName>, the rigorous rule of such states as <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7012056"
              >Crete</placeName>. See, for example, <bibl n="Plat. Crito 52e">Plat. Crito
            52e</bibl>. Aristotle couples in his praise, as Isocrates here, the Spartans and the
            Carthaginians: <bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 2.1272b.24">Aristot. Pol. 1272b 24
            ff.</bibl></note> are ruled by oligarchies at home, yet, when they take the field, they
          are ruled by kings. One might also point out that the state<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
              ><placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> which more than any other
          abhors absolute rule meets with disaster when it sends out many generals,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">As in the disasters at <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse"
              >Syracuse</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>.</note>
          and with success when it wages war under a single leader. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And, indeed, how could any one show more convincingly than through these instances that
          monarchy is the most excellent of governments? For we see that those who are permanently
          ruled by kings have the greatest powers; that those who live in well- conducted
          oligarchies, when it comes to matters about which they are most concerned, appoint one
          man, in some cases a general, in others a king, to have full powers over their armies in
          the field; and that those who abhor absolute rule, whenever they send out many leaders,
          fail to accomplish a single one of their designs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And, if there is need to speak also of things old in story, it is said that even the gods
          are ruled by Zeus as king. If the saying is true, it is clear that the gods also prefer
          this regime; but if, on the other hand, no one knows the truth about this matter, and we
          by our own conjecture have simply supposed it to be so, it is a proof that we all hold
          monarchy in the highest esteem; for we should never have said that the gods live under it
          if we did not believe it to be far superior to all other governments. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now as to polities, while it is not possible either to search out or declare every
          detail in which they differ from each other, yet for our present purpose, at least, enough
          has been said. But to show that I hold my office by natural right is a story much sooner
          told and less open to dispute. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For who does not know how Teucer, the founder of our race, taking with him the ancestors
          of the rest of our people, came hither over seas and built for them a city and portioned
          out the land; and that, after his other descendants had lost the throne, my father,
          Evagoras, won it back again by undergoing the greatest dangers, and wrought so great a
          change that Phoenicians no longer rule over Salaminians, while they, to whom it belonged
          in the beginning, are today in possession of the kingdom?<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >For this history, see introd. to II; Grote, <title>History of <placeName
                key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName></title> (new edition), ix. pp. 228 ff.; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 9.29">Isoc. 9.29-35</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now, of the matters which I proposed to discuss, it remains for me to speak to you about
          myself, in order that you may realize that I, who rule over you, am of such character
          that, not only on account of my ancestors, but of myself also, I might justly claim even
          greater honor than I now enjoy. For I I think you would all agree that the most sovereign
          of the virtues are temperance and justice, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>since not only do they benefit us in themselves, but, if we should be minded to look into
          the natures, powers, and uses of human relations, we would find that those which do not
            partake<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Almost the language of the Platonic doctrine of
            ideas.</note> of these qualities are the causes of great evils, whereas those which are
          attended by temperance and justice are greatly beneficial to the life of man. If, then,
          any of my predecessors have gained renown for these virtues, I consider that it is also my
          right to enjoy the same renown. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> As to my sense of justice, you can best observe it from these facts:<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">We may surmise that the death of the strong resourceful
            Evagoras plunged the affairs of Salimis and of <placeName key="tgn,1000112"
              >Cyprus</placeName> into a state of confusion which was with difficulty reduced to
            order by his successor, but we possess no further details of this history than those
            which are here set down.</note> When I was established in power I found the royal
          treasury empty, all the revenues squandered, the affairs of the state in utter disorder
          and calling for great care, watchfulness, and outlay of money; and, although I knew that
          rulers of the other sort in similar straits resort to every shift in order to right their
          own affairs, and that they feel constrained to do many things which are against their
          nature, nevertheless I did not fall a victim to any of these temptations; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>nay, I attended so devotedly and honorably to my duties that I left nothing undone which
          could contribute to the greatness of the state and advance its prosperity; and toward the
          citizens of the state I behaved with such mildness that no one has suffered exile or death
          or confiscation of property or any such misfortune during my reign. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And though <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> was closed to us because of
          the war which had arisen, and though we were being robbed on every side, I solved most of
          these difficulties, paying to some their claims in full, to others in part, asking some to
          postpone theirs, and satisfying others as to their complaints by whatever means I could.
          Furthermore, though the inhabitants of the island were hostile to me, and the Great King,
          while outwardly reconciled, was really in an ugly mood, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I calmed and appeased both parties by assisting the King zealously and by treating the
          islanders justly. For I am so far from coveting what belongs to others that, while rulers
          of the other sort, when they are stronger than their neighbors by ever so little, cut off
          portions of their territory and seek to get the advantage of them, I did not think it
          right to take even the land which was offered to me, but prefer rather to hold through
          just means what is my own than to acquire through base means territory many times greater
          than that which I now possess. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But why need I take the time to speak in detail, especially when I can make clear in a
          word the truth about myself? For it will be acknowledged that I have never wronged any
          man; that, on the contrary, I have been of service to many more of my own citizens and of
          the Hellenes at large and have bestowed upon them both greater gifts than all who have
          ruled before me put together. And surely those who pride themselves on justice and who
          profess to be above considerations of money ought to be able to speak in such high terms
          of their own conduct. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And now on the subject of temperance, also, I have still more important things to
          recount. For, since I realized that all men are most jealous for their wives and children,
          being above all quick to resent offenses against them, and that wantonness in these
          relations is responsible for the greatest evils—many ere now, of princely rank as well as
          of private station, having lost their lives because of it—, I so strictly avoided all
          these grounds of offense that, from the time when I became king, no one can charge me with
          having approached any woman but my own wife. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I was not, of course, unaware that those kings also are highly thought of by the
          multitude who are just in their dealings with their citizens, even though they provide
          themselves with pleasures from outside their households; but I desired both to put myself
          as far above such suspicions as possible and at the same time to set up my conduct as a
          pattern to my people, knowing that the multitude are likely to spend their lives in
          practices in which they see their rulers occupied. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Then again, I considered that it is also the duty of kings to be as much better than
          private citizens as they are superior to them in rank; and that those kings act contrary
          to all reason who compel their subjects to live decently but are themselves less continent
          than those over whom they rule. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Moreover, I saw that while the majority of people are masters of themselves in other
          matters, even the best are slaves to the passions whose objects are boys and women; and
          therefore I wanted to show that I could be strong in those things in which I should be
          superior, not merely to people in general, but even to those who pride themselves on their
          virtue. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, I had no patience with the perversity of men who take women in marriage and
          make them partners in all the relations of life, and then are not satisfied with the
          compacts which they have made but by their own lawless pleasures bring pain to those whom
          they expect never to cause them pain and who, though honest in all other partnerships, are
          without conscience in the partnership of marriage, when they ought to cherish this
          relationship the more faithfully inasmuch as it is more intimate and more precious than
          all others. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>More than that, they are unconsciously storing up for themselves feuds and factions at
          home in the royal palace. And yet, if kings are to rule well, they must try to preserve
          harmony, not only in the states over which they hold dominion, but also in their own
          households and in their places of abode; for all these things are the works of temperance
          and justice. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nor was I of the same mind as most kings in regard to the begetting of children. I did
          not think I should have some children by a woman of humbler station and others by one of
          higher degree, nor that I should leave after me bastard progeny, as well as progeny of
          legitimate birth; but that all my children should be able to trace their lineage back
          through the same father and the same mother to Evagoras, my father, among mortals, to the
          Aeacides among the demigods, and to Zeus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Aeacus, a
            descendant of Zeus, was father of Telamon, the father of Teucer.</note> among the gods,
          and that not one of the children sprung from my loins should be cheated of this noble
          origin. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Though many motives impelled me to abide by these principles, not the least incentive
          was that I saw that courage and cleverness and the other qualities which are held in high
          esteem are shared by many even among the base, whereas justice and temperance are the
          possessions of the good and noble alone. I conceived, therefore, that the noblest thing
          that I could do was to be able to excel my fellows in those virtues in which the bad have
          no share, and which are the truest and the most abiding and deserve the greatest praise.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For these reasons, and with these thoughts in mind, I was more assiduous than anyone else
          in the practice of temperance, and I chose for my pleasures, not those which are found in
          acts which yield no honor, but those which are found in the good repute which rewards
          nobility of character. However, we ought not to test all the virtues in the same set of
          conditions, but should test justice when a man is in want, temperance when he is in power,
          continence when he is in the prime of youth. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now in all these situations no one will deny that I have given proof of my nature. When I
          was left by my father without means, I was so just in my dealings as to injure not one of
          my citizens; but when I gained the power to do whatever I pleased, I proved myself more
          temperate than men in private station; and I showed my self-control in both circumstances
          at an age in which we find that the great majority of men most frequently go morally
          astray. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I should probably hesitate to say all this before an audience of other people, not that
          I lack pride in what I have accomplished, but because I might fail to convince them on the
          evidence of my words alone; you, however, are yourselves my witnesses that all I have said
          is true. Now men who are moral by nature deserve our praise and admiration, but still more
          do those deserve it who are such in obedience to reason; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for those who are temperate by chance and not by principle may perchance be persuaded to
          change, but those who, besides being so inclined by nature, have formed the conviction
          that virtue is the greatest good in the world, will, it is evident, stand firm in this
          position all their lives. But the reason why I have spoken at some length both about
          myself and the other subjects which I have discussed is that I might leave you no excuse
          for not doing willingly and zealously whatever I counsel and command. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I declare it to be the duty of each one of you to perform whatever tasks you are
          assigned with diligence and justice for if you fall short in either of these qualities,
          your conduct must needs suffer by that defect. Do not belittle nor despise a single one of
          your appointed tasks, thinking that nothing depends upon it; but, knowing that the whole
          depends for its success or failure on each of the parts, be careful in everything. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Display no less concern in my interests than in your own, and do not think that the
          honors enjoyed by those who successfully administer my affairs are a small reward. Keep
          your hands off the possessions of others in order that you may be more secure in the
          possession of your own estates. You should be such in your dealings with others as you
          expect me to be in my dealings with you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Do not strive to gain riches rather than a good name, knowing that both among the
          Hellenes and the barbarians as well those who have the highest reputation for virtue have
          at their command the greatest number of good things. Consider that the making of money
          unjustly will produce, not wealth, but danger. Do not think that getting is gain or
          spending is loss; for neither the one nor the other has the same significance at all
          times, but either, when done in season and with honor, benefits the doer. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And do not regard any one of my orders as a hardship; for those of you who make
          themselves most serviceable to my interests will most advance the interests of their own
          households. Let none of you imagine that even what he secretly thinks in his own heart
          will be hidden from me; nay, let him believe that, though I may be absent in body, yet my
          thoughts are present at what goes on; for, being of this opinion, you will be more
          restrained in your deliberations on all matters. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Never conceal from me anything that you possess, or that you are doing, or that you
          intend to do, knowing that where there are things hidden, fears in great number must needs
          arise. Seek not to be artful nor underhand in your public life, but to be so honest and
          open that, even if anyone wants to slander you, it will not be easy to do so. Scrutinize
          your actions and believe that they are evil when you wish to hide from me what you do, and
          good when my knowledge of them will be likely to make me think better of you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Do not keep silent if you see any who are disloyal to my rule, but expose them and
          believe that those who aid in concealing crime deserve the same punishment as those who
          commit it. Consider fortunate, not those who escape detection when they do evil, but those
          who are innocent of all wrongdoing for it is probable that the former will suffer such
          ills as they themselves inflict, while the latter will receive the reward which they
          deserve. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Do not form political societies or unions<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Political clubs
            may have been patriotic in old <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> (
              <bibl n="Isoc. 4.79">Isoc. 4.79</bibl>) but they had now degenerated into secret
            associations conspiring against popular government. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.167">Isoc.
              4.167</bibl>; <bibl n="Thuc. 8.54">Thuc. 8.54</bibl>; <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 34"
              >Aristot. Ath. Pol. 34</bibl>.</note> without my sanction; for such associations may
          be an advantage in the other forms of government, but in monarchies they are a danger.
          Abstain not merely from wrongdoing, but also from such conduct as must needs arouse
          suspicion. Believe that my friendship is very sure and abiding. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Preserve the present order and do not desire any change, knowing that revolutions
          inevitably destroy states and lay waste the homes of the people. Do not think that it is
          their natural dispositions alone which make rulers harsh or gentle, but the character of
          the citizens as well; for many before now have been compelled by the depravity of their
          subjects to rule more harshly than they wished. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Be confident, but less because of my mildness than because of your own goodness. Consider
          that in my safety lies your own security; for while my fortunes are on a firm foundation,
          your own will be likewise. You should be self-effacing in your attitude toward my
          authority, abiding by our customs and preserving the royal laws, but conspicuous in your
          services on behalf of the state and in the other duties which are assigned to you by my
          command. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Exhort the young to virtue not only by your precepts but by exemplifying in your conduct
          what good men ought to be. Teach your children to be obedient, and habituate them to
          devote themselves above all to the discipline which I have described; for if they learn to
          submit to authority they will be able to exercise authority over many; and if they are
          faithful and just they will be given a share in my privileges; but if they turn out to be
          bad they will be in danger of losing all the privileges which they possess. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Consider that you will pass on to your children the greatest and surest wealth if you can
          leave them my good will. Consider that the most miserable and unfortunate of men are those
          who have proved faithless to those who put their faith in them; for such men are doomed to
          despair and to fear of everything and to distrust of friends no less than of foes
          throughout the remainder of their lives. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Emulate, not those who have most possessions, but those who in their hearts know no evil;
          for with such a conscience one can live out his life most happily. Do not imagine that
          vice can profit more than virtue, and that it is only its name which is uglier; but
          consider that even as are the names which things have received, so, also, are their
            qualities.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 5.16">Isoc. 5.16
            ff.</bibl></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Do not be jealous of those who are highest in my favor, but emulate them, and by making
          yourselves serviceable try to rise to the level of those who are above you. Believe that
          you should love and honor those whom your king loves and honors, in order that you may win
          from me these same distinctions. Even as are the words which you speak about me in my
          presence, so let your thoughts of me be in my absence. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Manifest your good will towards me in deeds rather than in words. Do not do to others
          that which angers you when they do it to you.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 1.14">Isoc. 1.14</bibl> and note.</note> Practice nothing in your deeds for
          which you condemn others in your words. Expect to fare well or ill according as you are
          disposed well or ill toward me. Be not satisfied with praising good men, but imitate them
          as well. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Regard my words as your law, and try to abide by them, knowing that those of you who most
          faithfully do what I desire will most quickly be able to live as they themselves desire.
          This is the conclusion of the whole matter: just as you think those who are ruled by you
          should conduct themselves toward you, so you also should conduct yourselves toward my
          rule. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And if you do this, why need I speak at length of what the results will be? For if I
          continue to treat you as in time past, and you continue to give me your service and
          support, you will soon see your own life advanced, my empire increased, and the state made
          happy and prosperous. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>You could, therefore, well afford, for the sake of blessings so great, to spare no effort
          and even to undergo all manner of toil and peril; and yet it lies in your power, without
          suffering any hardship, but merely by being loyal and true, to bring all these things to
          pass.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
