<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Dead Come to Life, or the Fisherman</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
    <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
    <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
    <date>1921</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
</monogr>
    <series>
        <title>Loeb Classical Library</title>
    </series>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianhar03luciuoft/page/4/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202137?urlappend=%3Bseq=16">HathiTrust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">

<head>The Dead Come to Life, or the Fisherman<note xml:lang="eng"><p>This is Lucian’s reply to the storm of angry protest which
he had evoked from the schoolmen with his Philosophies for
Sale (II. 450 ff.), wherein, to their mind, he had unwarrantably and outrageously ridiculed the ancient philosophers and
their doctrines.</p>
<p>The scene is in Athens. The dead who have come to life
are the ancient philosophers, bent upon wreaking vengeance
on Frankness, which is Lucian’s alias here.
Eventually conceded a formal trial before Philosophy, he
is acquitted on the plea that his ridicule had not been aimed
at the ancient worthies but at their unworthy successors of
his own time, As these impostors cannot induced to
stand trial, Frankness is empowered to go about and brand
them, so that people can tell them from the genuine philosophers. Before departing on his mission, he fishes up, with a
bait of figs and gold, typical representatives of the chief
schools for the inspection of their founders.</p>
<p>Lucian’s plea is specious, for in Philosophies for Sale he
had certainly shown scant regard for those whom he now
professes to hold in such high esteem. But it is not meant
to be taken seriously ; it is put forward with a wink at the
audience for the sake of turning the tables on his critics.
His new-found deference, moreover, is well seasoned with
irony, and quite offset by the pose of urbane and patronizing
superiority which he assumes in feigned unconsciousness.
e piece is almost all persiflage, and maddeningly unanswerable for that reason.</p>
<p>The dialogue is strikingly like an Aristophanic comedy in
its construction, especially in the fact that it has a clearly
marked second part, somewhat loosely attached to the first,
which develops a series of incidents after the plot has been
worked out. Because of this similarity, and for many other
reasons too, none of Lucian’s writings better serves to introduce and illustrate the Double Indictment, which follows it.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>
<label>SOCRATES</label>
Pelt, pelt the scoundrel with plenty of stones!
Heap him with clods! Pile him up with broken
dishes, too! Beat the blackguard with your sticks!
Look out he doesn’t get away! Throw, Plato; you
too, Chrysippus ; you too; everybody at once! Let’s
charge him together.
“Let wallet to wallet give succour, and cudgel to
cudgel,” <note xml:lang="eng"><cit>
<quote>    <l>κρῖν᾽ ἄνδρας κατὰ φῦλα, κατὰ φρήτρας, ᾿Ἀγάμεμνον,</l>    <l>ὡς φρήτρη φρήτρηφιν ἀρήγῃ, φῦλα δὲ φύλοις.</l> </quote> <bibl>Iliad2, 363</bibl></cit></note>
for he is our joint enemy, and there is not a man
of us whom he has not outraged. Diogenes, ply
your stick, if ever you did before; let none of you
weaken; let him pay the penalty for his ribaldry.
What is this? Have yon given out, Epicurus and
Aristippus? Come, that is too bad!

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Show yourselves men, ye sages, and call up the
fury of battle.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad6, 112; Homer has “friends,” not “sages.”</bibl>
</cit>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

Aristotle, make haste! Still faster! That’s well; the
game is bagged. We have you, villain! you shall
soon find out what sort of men you have been






<pb n="v.3.p.5"/>

insulting. But how are we to punish him, to be
sure? Let us invent a complex death for him, such
as to satisfy us all; in fact he deserves to die seven
times over for each of us.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHER</label>
I suggest he be crucified.
</p>
<p><label>ANOTHER</label>
Yes, by Heaven; but flogged beforehand.
</p>
<p><label>ANOTHER</label>
Let him have his eyes put out long beforehand
</p>
<p><label>ANOTHER</label>
Let him have that tongue of his cut off, even
longer beforehand.
</p>
<p><label>SOCRATES</label>
And you, Empedocles—what do you suggest ?

</p>
<p><label>EMPEDOCLES</label>
That he be thrown into my crater,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.5.n.1"><p>Aetna, into which Eimpedocles is said to have leapt. </p></note> so that he may
learn not to abuse his betters.
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
Indeed, the best suggestion would have been for
him, like another Pentheus or Orpheus,
“To find among the crags a riven doom,”<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.5.n.2"><p>Both Pentheus and Orpheus were torn to ieces by Maenads. The verse is from a lost tragedy (Nauck, Fr Fragm. p. 895). </p></note>
so that each of us might have gone off with a scrap
of him.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
<label>FRANKNESS</label>
No, no! In the name of Him who hears the suppliant,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.5.n.3"><p>Zeus.  </p></note> spare me!




<pb n="v.3.p.7"/>

<label>PLATO</label>
Your doom is sealed: you cannot be let go now.
You know, of course, what Homer says:
<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Since between lions and men there exist no bonds
of alliance.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad22, 262.</bibl>
</cit>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Indeed, I myself will quote Homer in begging you
for mercy. Perhaps you will revere his verses and
will not ignore me when I have recited them :

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Save me, for I am no churl, and I receive what is
fitting in ransom,</l>
<l>Copper and gold, that in truth are desirable even
to sages.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>A cento; Iliad6, 46, 48; 20, 65.</bibl>
</cit>


<label>PLATO</label>
But we ourselves shall not be at a loss for a
Homeric reply to you ; listen to this, for instance :

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Think not now in your heart of escape, you
speaker of slander,</l>
<l>Even by talking of gold, oncé into our hands you
have fallen.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad10, 447-8, with alterations.</bibl>
</cit>


<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Oh, what wretched luck! Homer, in whom I had
my greatest hope, is useless to me. I suppose I
must take refuge with Euripides ; perhaps he might
save me :

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Slay not! The suppliant thou shalt not skay.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Nauck, p. 663. Cf. Ion1553. </bibl>
</cit>

<label>PLATO</label>
Ah, but is not this by Euripides, too?

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>No harm for them that wrought to suffer harm.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Orestes413.</bibl>
</cit>






<pb n="v.3.p.9"/>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>hen will ye slay me now, because of words?</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Euripides? Nauck, p. 663.</bibl>
</cit>


<label>PLATO</label>
Yes, by Heaven! Anyhow, he himself says :


<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Of mouths that are curbless</l>
    <l>And fools that are lawless</l>
    <l>The end is mischance.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Bacchae386 ff.</bibl>
</cit>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Well, then, as you are absolutely determined to
kill me and there is no possibility of my escaping,
do tell me at least who you are and what irreparable
injuries you have received from me that you’ are
irreconcilably angry and have seized me for execution.
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
What dreadful wrongs you have done us you may
ask yourself, you rascal, and those precious dialogues
of yours in which you not only spoke abusively of
Philosophy herself, but insulted us by advertising for
sale, as if in a slave-market, men who are learned,
and what is more, free-born. Indignant at this, we
requested a brief leave of absence from Pluto and
have come up to get you—Chrysippus here, Epicurus,
Plato (myself), Aristotle over there, Pythagoras here,
who says nothing, Diogenes, and everyone that you
vilified in your dialogues.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
<label>FRANKNESS</label>
I breathe again, for you will not put me to death
if you understand how I have acted as regards you.
So throw away your stones; or better, keep them.
You will make use of them against those who
deserve them.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.9.n.1"><p>It is curious that this suggestion, though emphasized by being repeated (§ 11), is not worked out. </p></note>


<pb n="v.3.p.11"/>



<label>PLATO</label>
Nonsense: you must die to-day. Yes, forthwith

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Don your tunic of stone on account of the wrongs
you have done us!</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad3, 57.</bibl>
</cit>


<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Truly, gentlemen, you will put to death, you may
depend upon it, the one man in the world whom you
ought to commend as your friend, well-wisher, comrade in thought, and, if it be not in bad taste to say
so, the defender of your teachings, if you put me to
death after I have laboured so earnestly in your
behalf. Take care, then, that you yourselves are not
acting like most of our present-day philosophers by
showing yourselves ungrateful and hasty and inconsiderate toward a benefactor.
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
O what impudence! So we really owe you gratitude
for your abuse, into the bargain? Are you so convinced that you are truly talking to slaves? Will you
actually set yourself down as our benefactor, on top
of all your insolent and intemperate language ?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Where, pray, and when have I insulted you? I have
always consistently admired philosophy and extolled
you and lived on intimate terms with the writings
that you have left behind. These very phrases that
I utter—where else but from you did I get them?
Culling them like a bee, I make my show with them
before men, who applaud and recognize where and


<pb n="v.3.p.13"/>

from whom and how I gathered each flower; and
although ostensibly it is I whom they admire for the
bouquet, as a matter of fact it is you and your garden,
because you have put forth such blossoms, so gay and
varied in their hues—if one but knows how to select
and interweave and combine them so that they will
not be out of harmony with one another. Would any
man, after receiving this kindly treatment at your
hands,-attempt to speak ill of benefactors to whom
he owes his reputation? Not unless he be like Thamyris or Eurytus in his nature, so as to raise his voice
against the Muses from whom he had the gift of song,
or to match himself against Apollo in archery—and
he the giver of the bow !

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
<label>PLATO</label>
That speech of yours is good rhetoric, my fine
fellow ; but it is directly against your case and only
makes your presumptuousness appear more staggering,
since ingratitude is now added to injustice. For you
got your shafts from us, as you admit, and then turned
them against us, making it your only aim to speak
ill of us all. That is the way you have paid us for
opening that garden to you and not forbidding you
to pick flowers and go away with your arms full.
For that reason, then, above all else, you deserve
to die.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
<label>FRANKNESS</label>
See! You give me an angry-hearing, and you
reject every just plea! Yet I should never have
supposed that anger could affect. Plato or Chrysippus
or Aristotle or the rest of you; it seemed to me that

<pb n="v.3.p.15"/>

you, and you alone, were surely far away from anything of that kind. But, however that may be, my
masters, do not put me to death unsentenced and
unheard. This too was once a trait of yours, not to
deal with fellow-citizens on a basis of force and
superior strength, but to settle your differences by
course of law, according, a hearing and in your
turn receiving one. So let us choose a judge, and
then you may bring your complaint either jointly
or through anyone whom you may elect to represent you all; and I will defend.myself against
your charges. Then, if I am proven guilty, and the
court passes that verdict upon me, I will submit, of
course, to the punishment that I deserve, and you
will not have taken it upon yourselves to do anything
high-handed. But if after I have undergone my
investigation I am found innocent and irreproachable,
the jury will discharge me, and you will turn your
anger against those who nave misled you and set
you against me.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

<label>PLATO</label>
There we have it! “Cavalry into the open,” so that
you may give the slip to the jury and get away.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.15.n.1"><p>As cavalry seeks open country to maneuvre in, so the lawyer seeks the courtroom. Compare Plato, Theaetetus, 183d: ἱππέας εἰς πεδίον προκαλεῖ, Σωκράτη εἰς λόγους προκαλούμενος.  </p></note> At
any rate, they say that you are an orator and a
lawyer and a wizard at making speeches. And whom
do you wish to be judge, what is more? It must be
someone whom you cannot influence by a bribe, as your
sort often do, to cast an unjust ballot in your favour.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Do not be alarmed on that score. I should not
care to have any such referee of suspicious or doubtful


<pb n="v.3.p.17"/>

character, who would sell me his vote. See, for my
part I nominate Philosophy herself to the bench, and
you yourselves also!
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
And who can conduct the prosecution if we are
to be jurors ?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Be prosecutors and jurors at the same time. Even
that arrangement has no terrors for me, since I have
so much the better of you in the justice of my case
and expect to be so over-stocked with pleas.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
<label>PLATO</label>
What shall we do, Pythagoras and Socrates ?
Really, the man seems to be making a reasonable
request in demanding a trial.
</p>
<p><label>SOCRATES</label>
What can we do but go to court, taking Philosophy _
with us, and hear his defence, whatever it may be.
Prejudgment is not our way ; it is terribly unprofessional, characteristic of hot-headed fellows who
hold that might is right. We shall lay ourselves
open to hard words from those who like to deal in
them if we stone a man who has had no opportunity
even to plead his case, especially as we ourselves
maintain that we delight in just dealing. What
could we say of Anytus and Meletus, who prosecuted me, or of the jurors on that occasion, if this
fellow is to die without getting any hearing at all?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.17.n.1"><p>Literally, "without getting any water at all"; i.e. any of the time ordinarily allowed for court speeches, which was apportioned with a water-clock.  </p></note>
<label>PLATO</label>
Excellent advice, Socrates; so let us go and get
Philosophy. She shall judge, and we shall be content
with her decision, whatever it may be.


<pb n="v.3.p.19"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Well done, most learned sirs; this course is better
and more legal. Keep your stones, however, as I
said ; for you will need them presently at court.
But where is Philosophy to be found? For my part
I do not know where she lives. Yet I wandered very
long in search of her dwelling, so that I might study
with her. Then I met men with short cloaks and
long beards who professed to come directly from her ;
and thinking that they knew, I questioned them.
But they were far more at a loss than I, and either
made no answer, in order that they might not ‘be
convicted of ignorance, or else pointed out one door
after another. Even to this day I have been unable
to find her house.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
Often, either by guesswork on my own part or
under the guidance of someone else; I would go to a
door in the firm belief that at last I had found it,
drawing my conclusion from the number of men that
came and went, all solemn of countenance, decorous
in dress, and studious in looks. So I would thrust
myself among them and enter also. Then I always
saw a hussy who was far from ingenuous, however
much she strove to bring herself into harmony
with simplicity and plainness. On the contrary, I
perceived at once that she did not leave the apparent
disorder of her hair unenhanced by art, nor let her
mantle hang about her in unstudied folds. It was
patent that she used it all asa make-up and employed
her seeming negligence to heighten her attractiveness. There were also evidences of enamel and
rouge; her talk was quite that of a courtesan; she
delighted in being praised by her lovers for her

<pb n="v.3.p.21"/>

beauty; she took eagerly any presents that were
offered; and she would let her wealthy lovers sit
close beside her, but would not even look at those
who were poor. And often when she exposed her
throat as if by accident, I saw gold necklaces thicker
than shackles. Qn observing all this I would withdraw at once, pitying, as you may well believe, those
poor unfortunates whom she was leading, not by the
nose, but by the beard, and who, like Ixion, embraced but a phantom and not Hera.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
<label>PLATO</label>
You are right in one point: the door is not
conspicuous and not known to all. However, there
will be no need to go to her house. We shall wait
for her here in the Potters’ Quarter. She will come
here presently, no doubt, on her way back from the
Academy, to stroll in the Painted Porch also, for
it is her custom to do so every day. In fact, here
she comes now. Do you see her, the mannerly one,
the one in the mantle, soft of eye, walking slowly,
rapt in thought?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
I see many who are alike in mantle, walk, and
fashion. Yet surely only one, even among then, is
the true Philosophy.
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
Right, but she will show you who she is, just by
speaking.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Ah! What are you all doing in the upper world,
Plato and Chrysippus and Aristotle and the rest of


<pb n="v.3.p.23"/>

you, the very fore-front of my studies? Why have
you come back to life? Did anything in the underworld ‘distress you? You certainly appear to be
angry. And who is this man whom you have taken
into custody? Some ghoul or murderer or profaner
of holiness, I suppose.
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
“Yes, indeed, Philosophy, the most impious of all
profaners, for he made bold to speak ill of you, than
whom nothing is more holy, and of us, one and all,
who learned something from you and have left it to
those who came after us.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Then it made you angry to be vituperated ? And
yet you knew that in spite of the hard names which
Comedy calls me during the festival of Dionysus, I have
held her my friend, and neither sued her at law nor
berated her in private, but permit her to make the
fun that is in keeping and customary at the festival.
I am aware, you see, that no harm can be done by a
joke; that, on the contrary, whatever is beautiful
shines brighter and becomes more conspicuous, like
gold cleansed by its minting. But you, for some
reason or other, have grown hot-tempered and violent.
Tell me, why do you throttle him?
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
"Obtaining leave of absence for this one day, we
came to get him, so that he may pay the penalty for
what he has done; for rumours repeatedly told us
what sort of language he used in public against us.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Then you intend to put him to death before
trial, without even a chance to defend himself? It
is certainly clear that he wants to make.a statement.

<pb n="v.3.p.25"/>

<label>PLATO</label>
No: we have referred the whole matter to you,
and you are to conclude the trial as you think best.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
You, there, what do you say?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Precisely what they do, my Lady Philosophy ; for.
you, even without aid, could discover the truth. In
fact, it was only with difficulty, after a deal of
entreaty, that I secured the reservation of the case
for you.
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
Now, you scoundrel, you call her “My Lady,” do
you? Just the other day you made her out to be .
utterly contemptible by offering every form of her
doctrines for sale at two obols apiece before so large
an audience!
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Careful! Perhaps fis abuse was not directed
against Philosophy, but against impostors who do
much that is vile in oyr name.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
You shall see at once, if you will only hear my
defence.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Let us go to the Areopagus, or-rather, to the
Acropolis itself, so that at the same time we may
get a bird’s eye view of everything in the city.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>

You, my dears, may walk about in the Painted
Porch meanwhile: I shall join you after concluding
the trial.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Who are they, Philosophy? They too seem very
mannerly.

<pb n="v.3.p.27"/>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
This one with the masculine air is Virtue;
yonder is Temperance, and there beside her Justice ;
the one in advance is Culture, and she that is faint
and indistinct in colour is Truth.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
I do not see which one you really mean.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Do you not see the unadorned one over there,
naked, always shrinking into the background and
slipping away? :
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
I can just see her now. But why not bring them
also, in order that the meeting may be full and
perfect? As to Truth, indeed, I wish to introduce
her into the trial as an advocate.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
To be sure. (To the others) Come with us also.
It is not a hard matter to try a single case,
particularly one that will involve our own interests.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
<label>TRUTH</label>
You others go: I do not-need to hear what I
have long known all about.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
But it would help us, Truth, if you should join in
the trial and give us information on each point.
</p>
<p><label>TRUTH</label>
Then shall I bring along these two waitingwomen, who are in very close sympathy with me?
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Yes, indeed, as many as you wish.

<pb n="v.3.p.29"/>

<label>TRUTH</label>
Come with us, Liberty and Free-speech, so that
we may be able to rescue this poor creature, our
admirer, who is facing danger for no just reason.
You, Investigation, may stay where you are.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Hold, my lady: let him come too, if anyone is to
come. Those whom I shall have to fight to-day are
none of your ordinary cattle, but pretentious
fellows, hard to argue down, always finding some
loophole or other, so that Investigation is necessary.
</p>
<p><label>INVESTIGATION</label>
Yes, most necessary: and you had better take
Proof along too. :
</p>
<p><label>TRUTH</label>
Come, all of you, since you appear to be necessary
to the case.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>
<label>PLATO</label>
Do you see that? He is suborning Truth against
us, Philosophy.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Then you, Plato and Chrysippus and Aristotle,
are afraid that she, Truth, may tell some lie ‘in his
behalf?
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
It isn’t that, but he is terribly unprincipled and
smooth-tongued, so that he will seduce her.

<pb n="v.3.p.31"/>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Have no fear. No injustice will be done while we
have Justice here with us.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
Let us go up, then.
But tell me, what is your name ?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Mine?  Frankness, son of Truthful, son of
Renowned Investigator.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
And your country?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
I am a Syrian, Philosophy, from the banks of the
Euphrates. But what of that? I know that some
of my opponents here are just as foreign-born as I:
but in their manners and culture they are not like
men of Soli or Cyprus or Babylon or Stageira.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.31.n.1"><p>Although they were born there: Chrysippus in Soli, Aristotle in Stageira. No philosopher. mentioned: by name in this piece came from Cyprus or from Babylon, and these allusions are not clear. Perhaps Lucian has in mind Zeno of Citium and Poseidonius of Seleucia on the Tigris.  </p></note> Yet
as far as you are concerned it would make no difference even if a man’s speech were foreign, if only his
way of thinking were manifestly right and just.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
True: it was a needless question, to be sure. But
what is your calling? That at least is worth
knowing.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Iam a bluff-hater, cheat-hater, liar-hater, vanityhater, and hate all that sort of scoundrels, who are
very numerous, as you know.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Heracles! You follow a hateful calling !


<pb n="v.3.p.33"/>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
You are right. You see, in fact, how many have
come to dislike me and how I am imperilled because
I follow it.
However, I am very well up in the opposite
calling, too: I mean the one with love for a base ;
for I am a truth-lover, a beauty-lover, a simplicitylover, and a lover of all else that is kindred to love.
But there are very few who deserve to have this
calling practised upon them, while those who come
under the other and are closer akin to hatefulness
number untold thousands. So the chances are
that by this time I have lost my skill in the pne
calling for lack of practice, but have become very
expert in the other.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
But that ought not to be so, for if a man can do
the one, they say, he can do the other. So do not
distinguish the two callings; they are but one,
though they seem two.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
You know best as to that, Philosophy. For my
part, however, I am so-constituted as to hate rascals
and to commend and love honest men.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Come, now, since we are where we planned to be,
let us hold our court somewhere hereabouts in the
portico of Our Lady of the Citadel.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.33.n.1"><p>Athena Polias, who shared with Erechtheus the temple now known as the Erechtheum.  </p></note> Priestess,
arrange the benches for us. Let us in the meantime
pay our homage to the goddess.


<pb n="v.3.p.35"/>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Lady of the Citadel, come to my aid against the
pretenders, remembering how many oaths thou dost
hear them make and break each day, and what they
do thou alone seest, dwelling as thou dost upon a
lookout. Now is thine hour to requite them. If
thou seest that I am being overborne, and that the
black ballots are more than the half, add thou thine
own and set me free.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.35.n.1"><p>Frankness aske of Athena more aid than she generally gave ; for the proverbial ballot of Athena merely decided a tie vote in favour of the defendant, as in the trial of Orestes.  </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Well and good. Here we are for you, gentlemen,
all seated in readiness to hear the speeches. Choose
one of your number who in your opinion can best
conduct the prosecution, and when you have done so,
build up your complaint and establish your charge ;
it is not feasible for all to speak at once. You,
Frankness, shall make your defence thereafter.
PLATO Which. of us, I wonder, would be the best fitted
to handle the case?
</p>
<p><label>CHRYSIPPUS</label>
You, Plato. Marvellous sublimity, superlatively
Attic elegance, charm and _ persuasiveness, insight,
subtlety, opportune seductiveness in demonstration—
all this is yours to the full. Accept the spokesmanship, therefore, and say whatever is appropriate
in behalf of us all. Remember now all your former
successes and put together any points you have urged
against Gorgias or Polos or Hippias or Prodicus: this
man is more able than they. So apply a light


<pb n="v.3.p.37"/>

sprinkling of irony, too, put those clever, incessant
questions of yours, and if you think best, also slip it
in somewhere that “great Zeus in heaven driving
his winged car” would be angry if this man should
not be punished.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
<label>PLATO</label>
No, let us make use of someone more strenuous—
Diogenes here, or Antisthenes, or Crates, or you
yourself, Chrysippus. For surely what the occasion
demands now is not elegance and literary distinction,
but some degree of argumentative and forensic
equipment: Frankness is a professional speaker.
</p>
<p><label>DIOGENES</label>
Well, then, I will be prosecutor, for we shall not
require speeches of any great length, I suppose: and
besides, I have been insulted beyond all of you, since
I was auctioned off the other day for two obols.
</p>
<p><label>PLATO</label>
Diogenes will make the speech, Philosophy, for all
of us. Remember, friend, not just to speak for
yourself in the complaint, but to keep our common
interests in view. If we do disagree with one
another a little in our doctrines, you must not
examine into that, or attempt to say who is the
nearer right, but, in general, make an impassioned
plea for Philosophy herself, because she has been
heaped with insult and shamefully abused in the
dialogues of Freespeaker ; ignore the personal views
wherein we differ, and fight for what we all have
in common. Take note, you are our sole representative and it rests with you whether all our teachings
are to seem worthy of high reverence or to be thought
no better than this man made them out to be.

<pb n="v.3.p.39"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

<label>DIOGENES</label>
Do not be alarmed ; we shall not come short: I
will speak in behalf of all. Even if Philosophy,
swayed by his eloquence—for she is naturally kindly
and gentle—determines to acquit him, I for my part
shall not be found wanting, for I will show him that
we do not carry sticks for nothing !
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Not by .any means! Use arguments, rather, for
that is better. Butdo notdelay. The water already
has been poured in,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.39.n.1"><p>i.e, the water-clock has been filled. </p></note> and the jury has its eyes upon
you.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Let the others<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.39.n.2"><p>The rest of the philosophers, who are to sit on the jury (§ 9).  </p></note> take seats, Philosophy, and cast
their votes with your company, and let Diogenes be
the only prosecutor.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Then are you not afraid they may find you guilty ?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Not at all. In fact, I wish to win by a larger
majority.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
That is handsome of you. Well, then, take your
seats, and you, Diogenes, begin your speech.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>

<label>DIOGENES</label>
What sort of men we were in life, Philosophy, you
know right well, and I need not discuss that point
at all; for who is not aware how much beauty was
brought into life by Pythagoras here, Plato, Aristotle,
Chrysippus and the others, to say nothing of myself?



<pb n="v.3.p.41"/>

I shall proceed to speak of the insults which, in spite
of our merit, this double-dyed scoundrel Frankness
has dealt us.
He is a public speaker, they say: but abandoning
the courts and the successes to be gained therein, he
concentrated upon us all thé eloquence and power
that he had acquired .in rhetoric, and not only
unceasingly abuses us himself by calling us cheats
and liars, but induces the public to laugh and sneer
at us as if we amounted to nothing at all. More
than that, he has at last made people actually hate
you, Philosophy, as well as us by dubbing your
doctrines stuff and nonsense and rehearsing in
mockery all that is most serious in what you taught
us, so as to get applause and praise from his audience
for himself and contumely for us. The common sort
are that way by nature; they delight in jesters and
buffoons, and most of all when they criticise what is
held in high reverence. Just so in days gone by
they took delight in Aristophanes and Eupolis, who
brought Socrates on the stage to make fun of him
and got up monstrous farces about him.
The playwrights, however, showed their boldness
against only one man, and at the Dionysia, when it
was’ permissible to do so, and the joking was
considered part of the holiday, and
<quote><l>The god, who loves his joke, no doubt was pleased.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.41.n.1"><p>Author unknown.  </p></note></l></quote>



</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>

But this man brings the best people together, after a
long period of thinking and preparing and writing


<pb n="v.3.p.43"/>

down slanders in a thick roll, and then loudly abuses
Plato, Pythagoras, Aristotle here, Chrysippus there,
myself,and in a word, one and all, without the sanction
of a holiday and without having. had anything done
to him personally by us. He would have some excuse
for the thing, of course,if he had acted in self-defence
instead of starting the quarrel.</p>

<p>
What is worst of all, in doing this sort of thing,
Philosophy, he shelters himself under your name,
and he has suborned Dialogue, our serving-man, employing him against us as a helper and a spokesman.
Moreover, he has actually bribed Menippus,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.43.n.1"><p>The Cynic, of Gadara: Lucian’s chief predecessor in satirical prose.  </p></note>a comrade
of ours, to take part in his farces frequently ; he is
the only one who is not here and does not join us
in the prosecution, thereby playing traitor to our
common cause.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>

For all this he ought to be punished. What, pray,
can he have to say for himself after ridiculing all that
is most holy before so many witnesses? In fact, it
would be a good thing for them, too, if they were to
see him punished, so that no other man might ever
again sneer at Philosophy; for to keep quiet and
pocket insults might well be thought to betoken
weakness and simplicity rather than self-control.
And who could put up with his last performances ?
Bringing us like slaves to the auction-room and
appointing a crier, he sold us off, they say, some for
a high price, some for an Attic mina, and me, arrant
scoundrel that he is, for two obols! And those
present laughed!</p>

<p>
On account of this, we ourselves have come up
here in a rage, and we think it right that you for
your part should avenge us because we have been
insulted to the limit.


<pb n="v.3.p.45"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>
<label>PLATO</label>
Good, Diogenes! You have splendidly said all
that you ought on behalf of us all.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Stop applauding! Pour in the water for the
defendant. Now, Frankness, make your speech in
turn, for the water now is running for you. Don’t
delay, then.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Diogenes did not complete the complaint against
me, Philosophy. He left out, for some reason or
other, the greater part of what I said, and everything
that was very severe. But I am so far from denying.
that I said it all and from appearing with a studied
defence that whatever he passed over in silence or
I neglected previously to say, I purpose to include
now. In that way you can find out whom I put up
for sale and abused, calling them pretenders and
cheats. And I beg you merely to note throughout
whether what I say about them is true. If my
speech should prove to contain anything shocking
or offensive, it is not I, their critic, but they, I think,
whom you would justly blame for it, acting as
they do.</p>

<p>
As soon as I perceived how many disagreeable
attributes a public speaker must needs acquire, such
as chicanery, lying, impudence, loudness of mouth,
sharpness of elbow, and what all besides, I fled from
all that, as was natural, and set out to attain your
high ideals, Philosophy, expecting to sail, as it
were, out of stormy waters into a peaceful haven

<pb n="v.3.p.47"/>

and to live out the rest of my life under your
protection.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>

Hardly had I caught a glimpse of “your doctrines
when I conceived admiration for you, as was inevitable,
and for all these men, who are the lawgivers of the
higher life and lend a helping hand to those who
aspire to it by giving advice which is extremely good
and extremely helpful if one does not act contrary to
it or falter, but fixedly regards the principles which
you have established and tries to bring his life into
harmony and agreement with them—a thing, to be
sure, which very few, even of your own disciples, do !<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.47.n.1"><p>I give Fritzsche’s interpretation of this last clause, though I fear it strains the Greek and is foreign to Lucian’s thought. Another, and I think a better, solution is to excise the clause as an early gloss, reading jas and interpreting it more naturally, “a thing which very few, even in our own time, do.” Compare the late gloss in β:  τί ταῦτατοῖς καθ' ἡμᾶς ἔοικε μονάχοις.  </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p>
When I saw, however, that many were not in love
with Philosophy, but simply coveted the reputation
of the thing, and that although in all the obvious,
commonplace matters which anyone can easily copy
they were very like worthy men (in beard, I mean,
and walk and garb), in their life and actions, however, they contradicted their outward appearance
and reversed your practice and sullied the dignity of
the profession, I became angry. The case seemed
to me to be as if some actor in tragedy who was
soft and womanish should act the part of Achilles
or Theseus, or even Heracles himself, without either
walking or speaking as a hero should, but showing
off airs and graces in a mask of such dignity. Even
Helen or Polyxena would never suffer such a man
to resemble them too closely, let alone Heracles, the
conquering hero, who, in my opinion, would very soon


<pb n="v.3.p.49"/>

smash both man and mask with a few strokes of his
club for making him out so disgracefully effeminate.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="32"><p>

Just so with me; when I saw you so treated by
those others, I could not brook the shame, of their
impersonation when they made bold, though but apes,
to wear heroic masks, or to copy the ass of Cumae
who put on a lion’s skin and claimed to be himself a
lion, braying in a very harsh and fearsome way at the
ignorant Cumaeans, until at length a foreigner, who
had often seen lions and asses, exposed him and
chased him away by beating him with sticks.</p>

<p>
But what seemed to me most shocking, Philosophy,
was this, that if people saw any one of these fellows
engaged in any wicked or unseemly or indecent
practice, every man of them at once laid the blame
upon Philosophy herself, and upon Chrysippus or
Plato or Pythagoras or whichever one of you
furnished that sinner with a name for himself and a
model for his harangues; and from him, because he
was leading an evil life, they drew sorry conclusions
about you others, who died long ago. For as you were
not alive, he could not be compared with you. You
were not there, and they all clearly saw him following
dreadful and discreditable practices, so that you
suffered judgment by default along with him and
became involved in the same scandal.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="33"><p>
I could not endure this spectacle, but set about
exposing them and distinguishing them from you ;
and you, who ought to reward me for it, bring me
into court! Then if I observed one of the initiates
disclosing the mysteries of the Goddesses Twain and
rehearsing them in public, and became indignant and
showed him up, would you consider me the impious

<pb n="v.3.p.51"/>

one: It would not be just. Certainly the officials
of the games always flog an actor if he takes the part
of Athena or Poseidon or Zeus and does not play it
well and in accordance with the dignity of the gods ;
and the gods themselves are surely not angry at them
for letting the scourgers whip a man. wearing their
masks and dressed in their clothing. On the contrary,
they would be gratified, I take it, if he were flogged
more soundly. Not to act a servant’s or a messenger’s part cleverly is a trivial fault, but not to present
Zeus or Heracles to the spectators worthily—Heaven
forfend! how shameful !

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="34"><p>

It is most extraordinary, too, that most of them
are thoroughly up in your writings, but live as if they
read and studied them simply to practise the reverse.
Their book tells them they must despise wealth and
reputation, think that only what is beautiful is good,
be free from anger, despise these people of eminence,
and talk with them as man to man; and its advice
is beautiful, as Heaven is my witness, and wise and
wonderful, in all truth. But they teach these very
doctrines for pay, and worship the rich, and are agog
after money; they are more quick-tempered than curs,
more cowardly than hares, more servile than apes,
more lustful than jackasses, more thievish than cats,
more quarrelsome than game-cocks. Consequently,
they let themselves in for ridicule when they hustle


<pb n="v.3.p.53"/>

after it all and elbow one another at the portals of the
rich and take part in great banquets, where they pay
vulgar compliments, stuff themselves beyond decency,
grumble openly at their portions, vent their philosophy disagreeably and discordantly over their cups,
and fail to carry their drink well. All those present
who are not of the profession laugh at them,
naturally, and spit philosophy to scorn for breeding
up such beasts.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="35"><p>

Most shameless of all, though each one of them
says he needs nothing and bawls it abroad that only
the wise man is rich, after a little he presents
himself and asks for something, and is angry if he
does not get it. It is just as if someone in royal
robes, with a high turban and a diadem and all the
other marks of kingly dignity, should play the
mendicant, begging of men worse off than himself.</p>

<p>
When they must needs receive a present, there is a
great deal of talk to the effect that a man should be
ready to share what he has, and that money does not
matter: “What, pray, does gold or silver amount
to, since it’ is not in any way better than pebbles
on the sea-shore!”” But when someone in want
of help, an old-time comrade and friend, goes and
asks for a little of their plenty, he encounters silence,
hesitancy, forgetfulness, and complete recantation
of doctrines. Their numerous speeches about friendship, their “virtue’”’ and their “honour” have all
gone flying off, I know not whither, winged words
for certain, idly bandied about by them daily in their
class-rooms.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="36"><p>
 Each of them is your friend as long
as silver and gold are not in sight on the table;
but if you merely give them a glimpse of an obol,
the peace is broken, it is war without truce or parley

<pb n="v.3.p.55"/>

everywhere, the pages of their books have become
blank, and Virtue has taken to her heels. So it is
with dogs, when you toss a bone among them; they
spring to their feet and begin biting each other and
barking at the one that was first to snatch the bone.</p>

<p>
It is said, too, that a king of Egypt once taught
apes to dance, and that the animals, as they are very
apt at imitating human ways, learned quickly and
gave an exhibition, with purple mantles about them
and masks on their faces. For a long time the show,
they say, went well, until a facetions spectator,
having nuts in his pocket, tossed them into the midst.
On catching sight of them, the monkeys forgot their
dance, changed from artists of the ballet to the
simians that they really were, smashed their masks,
tore their costumes, and fought with each other for
the nuts; whereby the carefully planned ballet was
entirely broken up, and was laughed at by the
spectators.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="37"><p>

These self-styled philosophers do just that, and I
for my part abused their sort, and shall never
stop criticizing and ridiculing them. But as for you
and those who resemble you—for there are, there are
some who truly cultivate philosophy and abide by
your laws—may I never be so insane as to say anything abusive or unkind of you! What could I say?
What is there of that nature in the lives that you
have led? But those pretenders and miscreants
deserve in my opinion to be hated. Come, now,
Pythagoras, Plato, Chrysippus, Aristotle—what do
you say? Have their sort anything to do with you,

<pb n="v.3.p.57"/>

ov have they displayed any similarity or kinship in
their mode of life ? Aye, “Heracles and the monkey,
as the proverb has it!<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.57.n.1"><p>You are no more like these men than Heracles was like the monkey that wore the lion’s skin. Cf. § 32, and Lover of Lies, § 5.  </p></note> Because they have long
beards and claim to be philosophers and look sour,
ought they to be compared with you? [could have:
put up with it if they were at least convincing in
their roles, but as things are, it would be easier for a
buzzard to imitate a nightingale than for them to
imitate philosophers.</p>

<p>
I have said all that I had to say in my own
defence. Truth, tell them whether it is true.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="38"><p>
<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Stand aside, Frankness ; still farther ... What are
we to do? What did you think of the man’s speech ?
</p>
<p><label>TRUTH</label>
For my part, Philosophy, while he was speaking I
prayed that I might sink into the earth, so true was
everything that he said. In fact, as I listened, I
recognized each of the men who act that way and
applied his remarks to them: “That refers to this
man; so-and-so does that.” In short, he portrayed
the gentlemen to the life, as in a painting, accurate
likenesses in every respect, depicting not only their
persons, but their very souls‘as faithfully as could be.
</p>
<p><label>VIRTUE</label>
I, Virtue, also had to blush for shame.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
And what say you ?


<pb n="v.3.p.59"/>

<label>PLATO</label>
What else but to acquit him of the charge and set
him down as our friend and benefactor? Indeed, just
what happened to the Ilians<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.59.n.1"><p>The latter-day Trojans.  </p></note> has happened to us—
we have brought down upon ourselves an actor of
tragedies to hold forth about the woes of the Trojans !
Let him hold forth, then, and make tragedies out
of these miscreants.
</p>
<p><label>DIOGENES</label>
I, too, Philosophy, commend the man highly, take
back my complaint and count him a friend, for he is
a gallant fellow.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="39"><p>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Good! Come, Frankness. We acquit you of the
charge; you have an unanimous verdict in your
favour, and from now on you may count yourself one
of my household.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
I pay my homage at once. (He kisses his hand.)
But no! I think I shall do it more as they do in a
play, for that will be more reverential :

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>O Victory, goddess so greatly revered,</l>
    <l>Take my life in thy care</l>
    <l>And cease not to crown me with garlands.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Euripides, close of Phoenissac, Orestes, Iphigenia om
Tauris.</bibl>
</cit>


<label>VIRTUE</label>
Well, then, let us now initiate our second bowl of
wine. Let us summon up those others to be punished
for the insults they are inflicting upon us. Frankness
shall accuse each of them.


<pb n="v.3.p.61"/>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Quite right, Virtue; so slip down into the town,
Syllogism, my lad, and summon the philosophers.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="40"><p>

<label>SYLLOGISM</label>
Oyez! Silence! Let the philosophers come to the
Acropolis to present their defence before Virtue,
Philosophy, and Justice.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Do you see! Very few of them understood the
summons and are coming up. Besides, they fear
Justice, and most of them are actually too busy because of their attentions to the rich. If you wish
them all to come, Syllogism, make your proclamation
like this—
</p>
<p><label>SYLLOGISM</label>
No! You summon them, Frankness. in the way
you think best.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="41"><p>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Nothing hard about that. Oyez! Silence! All
who assert that they are philosophers, and all who
think that they have any connection with the name,
come tothe Acropolis for a distribution of gifts! Two
minas will be given to every man, and a seed-cake
also; and whoever displays a Jong beard shall receive
a basket of figs into the bargain. Never mind temperance or justice or self-control, as these qualities
are not essential if they are not available; but let
each bring with him five syllogisms by all means, for
without these it is impossible to be wise.
<cit>
<quote>
<l>Lo, we have set up as prize two talents of gold for the contest ;</l>
<l>These shall we give unto him who prevails over all in debating!</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Cf. Iliad18, 507-8.</bibl>
</cit>


<pb n="v.3.p.63"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="42"><p>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Aha! What a lot of them! The road up to the gate
is full of men hustling after the two minas, as soon
as they heard of them; others are coming up beside
the Pelasgicon;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.63.n.1"><p>The prehistoric wall of the Acropolis. Only tumble-down pieces were then to be seen (cf. § 47). The bit. referred to here was at the north-west corner, by the cave of Pan (Double Indictment, § 9). </p></note> others by the precinct of Asclepius;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.63.n.2"><p>On the south slope, near the theatre of Dionysus. </p></note>
even more of them along the Areopagus ;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.63.n.3"><p>To the west, near the main entrance. </p></note> some, too,
by the tomb of Talus ;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.63.n.4"><p>Talus (or Calus) was nephew of Daedalus, who out of jealousy threw him down the cliff. Certain stones at the back of the theatre of Dionysus are thought to belong to his tomb. </p></note> and some have set ladders
against the temple of the Twin Brethren<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.63.n.5"><p>North side: exact site uncertain. </p></note> and are
climbing up with a hum, by Heaven, and “in clusters” like swarming bees, to use the words of Homer ;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.63.n.6"><p>Iliad 2, 89.   </p></note> from that side right many, and from the other

<cit><quote><l>Thousands of men, like the leaves and the flowers
that come in the springtime.</l></quote><bibl>Iliad2, 468.</bibl></cit>

The Acropolis is full in a trice as they

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>noisily settle
in place,</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad2, 463.</bibl>
</cit>

and everywhere are begging-bags and
flattery, beards and shamelessness, staves and gluttony,
syllogisms and avarice. The few that came up in
answer to the first summons are obscure and inconspicuous, intermingled with the crowd of others, and
they escape the eye in the general similarity of garb.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
In fact, that is the worst feature of it all, Philosophy, and the one for which you could be most
criticized, that you have set no mark and token upon
them. These cheats are often more convincing than
the genuine philosophers.







<pb n="v.3.p.65"/>

<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
That shall be seen to presently; but let us welcome them now.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="43"><p>

<label>PLATONIST</label>
We Platonists should get our share first.
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
No! we Pythagoreans, for Pythagoras was earlier.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Nonsense! we of the Porch are better.
</p>
<p><label>PERIPATETIC</label>
Not at all; in matters of money we of the Walk
should be first.
</p>
<p><label>EPICUREAN</label>
Give us Epicureans the cakes and the figs, but we
will wait for the money, even if we have to be the
last to get it.
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
Where are the two talents? We Academics will
show you how much better debaters we are than
the rest !
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Not while we Stoics are here!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="44"><p>
<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Stop your bickering! You Cynics, do not jostle
one another or strike each other with your staves.
You were asked here for a different purpose, let me
assure you! And now I, Philosophy, and Virtue
here and Truth will decide who are the genuine
philosophers. Then all who are found to be living
by our rules shall be pronounced superior and will be
happy ever after, but as for the cheats and all those
who have nothing in common with us, we shall put


<pb n="v.3.p.67"/>

the wretches to a wretched end, so that they may
not claim any part in things that are over their heads,
false pretenders that they are! What is this? Are
you running away? By Heaven, they are, most of
them jumping over the cliffs! The Acropolis is empty
except for these few who have remained because
they did not fear the trial.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="45"><p>

Attendants, pick up the
bag which the Cynic threw away in the rout. Come,
let me see what is in it; probably lupines, or a book,
or some whole-wheat bread.
</p>
<p><label>ATTENDANT</label>
No! gold—see here !—perfume, a razor, a mirror,
and a set of dice!
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Good for you, my fine fellow! Were these your
instruments for the mortification of the flesh, and did’
_ you think that with the aid of these you could abuse
all mankind and instruct the rest of the world ?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Well, there you see what they are like. You must
consider how all this is to stop going on unobserved,
and how those who come into contact with them are
to tell which of them are the good and which, on the
contrary, the followers of thte other life.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Invent a plan, Truth ; for it would be in your own
interest to do so, in order that Falsehood may not
prevail over you, and bad men, under the cloak of
Ignorance, escape your eye when they imitate the
good.

<pb n="v.3.p.69"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="46"><p>

<label>TRUTH</label>
If you think best, let us empower Frankness himself to do this, since we have seen that he is honest
and in sympathy with us, and that he particularly
admires you, Philosophy—to take along Investigation and put himself in the way of all who claim
to be philosophers. Then, whenever he finds a truly
legitimate son of Philosophy, let him crown the
man with a wreath of green olive and invite him
to the Prytaneum;<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.69.n.1"><p>To be maintained at public expense, as Socrates thought he should have been.  </p></note> and if he meets a scoundrel
whose philosophy is but stage-play—there are many
of that sort—let him tear his mantle, cut off his
beard close to the skin with goat-shears, and stamp or
brand a mark on his forehead, between the eyebrows ;
let the pattern of the brand be a fox or an ape.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Good for you, Truth! Let the test, Frankness, be
like the test of the eaglets against the sun. Not that
they, like the eaglets, are to stare at the light and
be put to the proof in that way; but set gold and
fame and pleasure in their view, and whomsoever of
them you see paying no attention and in no way
attracted to the spectacle, let him be the one to wear
the crown of green olive; but whomever you see
gazing fixedly at the gold and reaching his hand out
after it, hale him off to the branding-place, after first
cutting off his beard in accordance with our decision.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="47"><p>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
It shall be done, Philosophy. You shall very soon
see most of them wearing the fox-brand or the ape-


<pb n="v.3.p.71"/>

brand, and but few crowned with wreaths. If you
like, however, I will bring you up some of them here
and now.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
What! you will bring up the runaways ?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Yes, indeed, if the priestess will be good enough to
lend me for a moment that hook and line which the
fisherman from the Peiraeus dedicated.
</p>
<p><label>PRIESTESS</label>
There, take it, and the rod too, so that you may
have a complete outfit.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
And now, priestess, give me some figs quickly
and a little of your gold.
</p>
<p><label>PRIESTESS</label>
Take them.
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
What does the man intend to do? Baiting the
hook with the fig and the gold, and taking his seat
on the crest of the wall, he has made a cast into the
town! Why are you doing that, Frankness? Have
you made up your mind to fish up the stones out of
the Pelasgicon ?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Hush, Philosophy ; wait and see my catch. Poseidon, god of fishermen, and dear Amphitrite, send us
up quantities of fish!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="48"><p>

Ah! I see a fine big pike, or
rather, a golden carp.—No, it is a cat-fish. Anyhow,
he is coming up to the hook with his mouth open.
He has scented the gold; now he is close by; he

<pb n="v.3.p.73"/>

struck ; he is on; let’s pull him up. You pull too,
Investigation. Investigation, take hold of the line
with me!
</p>
<p><label>INVESTIGATION</label>
He isup! Come, let me see what you are, my
good fish. A dogfish !<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.73.n.1"><p>i.e, a Cynic.  </p></note> Heracles, what teeth! How
about it, my fine fellow? Caught, were you, gormandizing about the rocks, where you hoped to slip
under cover and keep out of sight? But now you
will be in public view, hung up by the gills! Let
us take out the hook and the bait. No, by Zeus, he
has swallowed it! Here is your hook, all bare; the
fig and the gold are secure in his insides.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Let him spew them up, by Zeus, so that we may
bait for others. That’s well. What say you, Diogenes ;
do you know who this fellow is, and has he anything
in common with you?
</p>
<p><label>DIOGENES</label>
Not in the least !
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Well, how much ought we to call him worth? For
my part, I valued him at two obols the other day.
</p>
<p><label>DIOGENES</label>
A high price. He is inedible and ugly and tough
and worthless. Throw him down the cliff head first.
Let down your hook and pull up another. But I
say: look out, Frankness, not to let your rod bend
till it breaks.


<pb n="v.3.p.75"/>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
Have no fear, Diogenes. They are light, and pull
no harder than weakfish.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.75.n.1"><p>Lucian puns upon ἀφύη (a small fish, sprat) and ἀφυή (dull, stupid). </p></note>
<label>DIOGENES</label>
Aye, they are mighty weak, for certain ; pull them
up, however.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="49"><p>
<label>FRANKNESS</label>
See! Here comes another fish that looks like a
plate,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.75.n.2"><p>The pun here is upon Πλάτων and πλατύς (flat). </p></note> as if he were sliced lengthways, a sort of
flatfish, opening his mouth for the hook. He has
swallowed it; he is caught. Up with him! What
is he?
</p>
<p><label>INVESTIGATION</label>
The kind that styles itself Platonic.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
So you came to get the gold too, confound you ?
What do vou say, Plato? What are we to do with
him?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="50"><p>


<label>PLATO</label>
Over the same cliff with him! Let down for
another.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Ah, I see a very handsome one coming up, as far as
can be judged in the deep water ; of many colours,
with golden stripes on his back.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.75.n.3"><p>The Peripatetics were criticized for love of gay clothing and gold.  </p></note> Do you see him,
Investigation ?
</p>
<p><label>INVESTIGATION</label>
He is the kind that claims the name of Aristotle.




<pb n="v.3.p.77"/>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
He came up and then swam away again. He is
making a careful survey. Now he has come back
again ; he has opened his mouth; he is caught. Up
with him.
</p>
<p><label>ARISTOTLE</label>
Don’t ask me about him, Frankness. I don’t
know who he is.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Then he too shall go over the cliff, Aristotle.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="51"><p>

But
look here! I see a great number of fish closely alike
in colour, spiny and rough-skinned, harder to grasp
than sea-urchins.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.3.p.77.n.1"><p>Stoics, then the most numerous school. They themselves were uncouth, and their doctrines spiny.  </p></note> Shall we need a seine for them?
</p>
<p><label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
But we haven't any. It will be enough if we
land only one out of the school. The one that
comes to the hook will of course be the boldest of
them.
</p>
<p><label>INVESTIGATION</label>
Let down your line, if you want, but first arm it
with iron for some distance, so that he may. not saw
it off with his teeth after he has swallowed the gold.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
It is down. Poseidon, grant us a quick catch!
Aha! _ they are fighting over the bait; some are
nibbling the fig in schools and some have taken firm
hold of the gold. Good! A very powerful one is on
the hook! Come, let me see whose namesake you


<pb n="v.3.p.79"/>

say you are. But itis silly of me to try to make a
fish talk; these anyhow are certainly dumb! Come,
Investigation, tell us whom he has for master.
</p>
<p><label>INVESTIGATION</label>
Chrysippus here.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
I understand : because there was gold in the name,
I take it. Well, Chrysippus, in the name of the
Goddess of Wisdom tell us, do you know these
fellows, and do you advise them to do as they do?
</p>
<p><label>CHRYSIPPUS</label>
By Zeus, your questions are insulting, Frankness,
if you imply that we have anything in common with
that sort.
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
Good, Chrysippus : that is handsome of you. He too
shall go head first after the rest, as he is.spiny and
there is danger that anyone who should try to eat
him might get a hole in his gullet.


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="52"><p>


<label>PHILOSOPHY</label>
Enough of fishing, Frankness. One of them—
there are many capable of it—may snatch off the gold
and the hook and make away with them, and then
you will have to settle with the priestess. So let
us go away to take our stroll, and as for you (to the.
Philosophers), it is high time you went where you
came from, that you may not overstay your leave.
Frankness, you and Investigation seek them all out
on every hand and either crown or brand them, as I
said.

<pb n="v.3.p.81"/>

<label>FRANKNESS</label>
It shall be done, Philosophy. Good-bye, gentlemen. Let us go down into the town, Investigation,
and carry out our orders.
</p>
<p><label>INVESTIGATION</label>
Where shall we go first? To the Academy, or to
the Porch? Or shall we begin with the Lyceum ?
</p>
<p><label>FRANKNESS</label>
It will make no difference. I am sure, however,
that wherever we go we shall need few crowns of
olive, but many brands.




</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>

