<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Fisher</title>
<sponsor>Tufts University</sponsor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal xml:id="GRC">Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>

</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Tufts University</authority>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date type="release">2023-08-01</date>
<publisher>Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Medford, MA, USA</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl xml:lang="eng">
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<editor role="translator">
<persName>
<name>Henry Watson Fowler</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<editor role="translator">

<persName>
<name>Francis George Fowler</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author>Lucian</author>
<title xml:lang="eng">The works of Lucian of Samosata</title>
<imprint>
<publisher>Clarendon Press</publisher>
<pubPlace>Oxford</pubPlace>
<date>1905</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref
target="https://archive.org/details/worksoflucianofs01luciuoft/page/206/mode/1up" >Internet Archive</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture.</p>
 <refsDecl n="CTS">
  <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
   replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
   <p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
  </cRefPattern>
 </refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="en">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="eng">
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4" xml:lang="eng">
<head>THE FISHER</head>


<head>A RESURRECTION PIECE</head>
<head><label>Lucian</label> or <label>Parrhesiades</label>. <label>Socrates</label>. <label>Empedocles</label>, <label>Plato</label>, <label>Chrysippus</label>. <label>Diogenes</label>. <label>Aristotle</label>. Other Philosophers. <label>Academics</label>. <label>Philosophy</label>. <label>Truth</label>. <label>Temperance</label>. <label>Virtue</label>. <label>Syllogism</label>, <label>Exposure</label>. <label>Priestess of Athene</label>. <label>Resurgents</label>. <label>Platonists</label>. <label>Peripatetics</label>. <label>Pythagoreans</label>. <label>Stoics</label>. <label>Epicureans</label></head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="1">
<p></p>

<p><label>Socrates</label> Stone the miscreant; stone him with many stones; clod him with clods; pot him with pots; let the culprit feel your sticks; leave him no way out. At him, Plato! come, Chrysippus, let him have it! Shoulder to shoulder, close the ranks;

<l>Let wallet succour wallet, staff aid staff!</l>

We are all parties in this war; not one of us but he has assailed. You, Diogenes, now if ever is the time for that stick of yours; stand firm, all of you. Let him reap the fruits of his revilings. What, Epicurus, Aristippus, tired already? ’tis too soon; ye sages,

<l>Be men; relume that erstwhile furious wrath!</l>

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="2">
<p><label>Aristotle</label> one more sprint. There! the brute is caught; we have you, villain. You shall soon know a little more about the



<pb n="v.1.p.207"/>


characters you have assailed. Now, what shall we do with him? it must be rather an elaborate execution, to meet all our claims upon him; he owes a separate death to every one of us.

First Phil. Impale him, say I.

Second Phil. Yes, but scourge him first.

Third Phil. Tear out his eyes.

Fourth Phil, Ah, but first out with the offending tongue.</p>

<p><label>Socrates</label> What say you, Empedocles?</p>

<p><label>Empedocles</label> Oh, fling him into a crater; that will teach him to vilify his betters..</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> ’Twere best for him, Orpheus or Pentheus like, to -

<l>Find death, dashed all to pieces on the rock;</l>

so each might have taken a piece home with him.
</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="3">
<p><label>Lucian</label> Forbear; spare me; I appeal to the God of suppliants.</p>

<p><label>Socrates</label> Too late; no loophole is left you now. And you know your Homer:

<l>'Twixt men and lions, covenants are null.</l></p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Why, it is in Homer’s name that I ask my boon. You will perhaps pay reverence to his lines, and listen to a selection from him:

<l>Slay not; no churl is he; a ransom take</l>
<l>Of bronze and gold, whereof wise hearts are fain.</l></p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Why, two can play at that game; exempli gratia,

<l>Reviler, babble not of gold, nor nurse</l>
<l>Hope of escape from these our hands that hold thee.</l></p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Ah me, ah me! my best hopes dashed, with Homer!
Let me fly to Euripides; it may be he will protect me:

Leave him his life; the suppliant’s life is sacred.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Does this happen to be Euripides too—
<l>Evil men evil treated is no evil?</l>



<pb n="v.1.p.208"/></p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> And will you slay me now for nought but words?</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Most certainly; our author has something on that point too:

<l>Unbridled lips</l>
<l>And folly’s slips</l>
<l>Invite Fate’s whips.</l>

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="4">
<p><label>Lucian</label> Oh, very well; as you are all set on murdering me, and escape is impossible, do at least tell me who you are, and what harm I have done you; it must be something irreparable, to judge by your relentless murderous pursuit.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> What harm you have done us, vile fellow? your own conscience and your fine dialogues will tell you; you have called Philosophy herself bad names, and as for us, you have subjected us to the indignity of a public auction, and put up wise men— ay, and free men, which is more—for sale. We have reason to be angry; we have got a short leave of absence from Hades, and come up against you—Chrysippus here, Epicurus and myself, Aristotle yonder, the taciturn Pythagoras, Diogenes and all of us that your dialogues have made so free with.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="5">
<p><label>Lucian</label> Ah, I breathe again. Once hear the truth about my conduct to you, and you will never put me to death. You can throw away those stones. Or, no, keep them; you shall have a better mark for them presently.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> This is trifling. This day thou diest; nay, even now,

<l>A suit of stones shalt don, thy livery due.</l></p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Believe me, good gentlemen, I have been at much pains on your behalf; to slay me is to slay one who should rather be selected for commendation; a kindred spirit, a well-wisher, a man after your own heart, a promoter, if I may be bold to say it, of your pursuits, See to it that you catch not the tone of our latter-day philosophers, and be thankless, petulant, and hard of heart, to him that deserves better of you.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Talk ofa brazen front! So to abuse us is to oblige


<pb n="v.1.p.209"/>


us. I believe you are under the delusion that you are really talking to slaves; after the insolent excesses of your tongue, do you propose to chop gratitude with us?

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="6">
<p><label>Lucian</label> How or when was I ever insolent to you? I have always been an admirer of philosophy, your panegyrist, and a student of the writings you left. All that comes from my pen is but what you give me; I deflower you, like a bee, for the behoof of mankind; and then there is praise and recognition; they know the flowers, whence and whose the honey was, and the manner of my gathering; their surface feeling is for my selective art, but deeper down it is for you and your meadow, where you put forth such bright blooms and myriad dyes, if one knows but how to sort and mix and match, that one be not in discord with another. Could he that had found you such have the heart to abuse those benefactors to whom his little fame was due? then he must be a Thamyris or Eurytus, defying the Muses who gave his gift of song, or challenging Apollo with the bow, forgetful from whom he had his marksmanship.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="7">
<p><label>Platonists</label> All this, good sir, is quite according to the principles of rhetoric; that is to say, it is clean contrary to the facts; your unscrupulousness is only emphasized by this adding of insult to injury; you confess that your arrows are from our quiver, and you use them against us; your one aim is to abuse us. This is our reward for showing you that meadow, letting you pluck freely, fill your bosom, and depart. For this alone you richly deserve death.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="8">
<p><label>Lucian</label> There; your ears are partial; they are deaf to the right. Why, I would never have believed that personal feeling could affect a Plato, a Chrysippus, an Aristotle; with you, of all men, I thought there was dry light. But, dear sirs, do not condemn me unheard; give me trial first. Was not the principle of your establishing—that the law of the stronger was not the law of the State, and that differences should be settled in court after due





<pb n="v.1.p.210"/>


hearing of both sides? Appoint a judge, then; be you my accusers, by your own mouths or by your chosen representative; and let me defend my own case; then if I be convicted of wrong, and that be the court’s decision, I shall get my deserts, and you will have no violence upon your consciences. But if examination shows me spotless and irreproachable, the court will acquit me, and then turn you your wrath upon the deceivers who have excited you against me.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="9">
<p><label>Platonists</label> Ah, every cock to his own dunghill! You think you will hoodwink the jury and get off. I hear you are a lawyer, an advocate, an old hand at a speech. Have you any judge to suggest who will be proof against such an experienced corrupter as you?</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Oh, be reassured. The official I think of proposing is no suspicious, dubious character likely to sell a verdict. What say you to forming the court yourselves, with Philosophy for your President?</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Who is to prosecute, if we are the jury?</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Oh, you can do both; I am not in the least afraid; so much stronger is my case; the defence wins, hands down.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="10">
<p><label>Platonists</label> Pythagoras, Socrates, what do you think? perhaps the man’s appeal to law is not unreasonable.</p>

<p><label>Socrates</label> No; come along, form the court, fetch Philosophy, and I see what he has to say for himself. To condemn unheard is a sadly crude proceeding, not for us; leave that to the hasty people with whom might is right. We shall give occasion to the enemy to blaspheme if we stone 2 man without a hearing, professed lovers of justice as we are. We shall have to keep quiet about Anytus and Meletus, my accusers, and the jury on that occasion, if we cannot spare an hour to hear this fellow before he suffers.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Very true, Socrates. We will go and fetch Philosophy. The decision shall be hers, and we will accept it, whatever it is.



<pb n="v.1.p.211"/>




</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="11">
<p><label>Lucian</label> Why, now, my masters, you are in a better and more law-abiding mood. However, keep those stones, as I said; you will need them in court. But where is Philosophy to be found?
I do not know where she lives, myself. I once spent a long time wandering about in search of her house, wishing to make her acquaintance. Several times I met some long-bearded people in threadbare cloaks who professed to be fresh from her presence; I took their word for it, and asked them the way; but they knew considerably less about it than I, and either declined to answer, by way of concealing their ignorance, or else pointed to one door after another. I have never been able to find the right one to this day.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="12">
<p>Many a time, upon some inward prompting or external offer of guidance, I have come to a door with the confident hope that this time I really was right; there was such a crowd flowing in and out, all of solemn persons decently habited and thoughtfulfaced; I would insinuate myself into the press and go in too. What I found would be a woman who was not really natural, however skilfully she played at beauty unadorned; I could see at once that the apparent négligé of her hair was studied for effect, and the folds of her dress not so careless as they looked. One could tell that nature was a scheme of decoration with her, and artlessness an artistic device. The white lead and the rouge did not absolutely defy detection, and her talk betrayed her real vocation; she liked her lovers to appreciate her beauty, had a ready hand for presents, made room by her side for the rich, and hardly vouchsafed her poorer lovers a distant glance. Now and then, when her dress came a little open by accident, I saw that she had on a massive gold necklace heavier than a penal collar. That was enough for me; I would retrace my steps, sincerely pitying the unfortunates whom she led by the—beard, and their Ixion-embracings of a phantom.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="13">
<p><label>Platonists</label> You are right there; the door is not conspicuous, nor



<pb n="v.1.p.212"/>


generally known. However, we need not go to her house; we will wait for her here in the Ceramicus. I should think it is near her hour for coming back from the Academy, and taking her walk in the Poecile; she is very regular; to be sure, here she comes. Do you see the orderly, rather prim lady there, with the kindly look in her eyes, and the slow meditative walk?</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> I see several answering the description so far as looks and walk and clothes go. Yet among them all the real lady Philosophy can be but one.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> True; but as soon as she opens her lips you will know.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="14">
<p><label>Philosophy</label> Dear me, what are Plato and Chrysippus and Aristotle doing up here, and the rest of them—a living dictionary of my teachings? Alive again? how is this? have things been going wrong down there? you look angry. And whois your prisoner? a rifler of tombs? a murderer? a temple-robber?</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Worse yet, Philosophy. He has dared to slander your most sacred self, and all of us who have been privileged to impart anything from you to posterity.:</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> And did you lose your tempers over abusive words? did you forget how Comedy handled me at the Dionysia, and how I yet counted her a friend? Did I ever sue her, or go and remonstrate? or did I let her enjoy her holidays in the harmless old-fashioned way? I know very well that a jest spoils no real beauty, but rather improves it; so gold is polished by hard rubs, and shines all the brighter for it. But you seem to have grown passionate and censorious. Come, why are you strangling him like that?</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> We have got this one day’s leave, and come after him to give him his deserts. Rumours had reached us of the things he used to say about us in his lectures.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="15">
<p><label>Philosophy</label> And are you going to kill him without a trial or a hearing? I can see he wishes to say something.



<pb n="v.1.p.213"/></p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> No; we decided to refer it all to you. If you will accept the task, the decision shall be yours,</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Sir, what is your wish?</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> The same, dear Mistress; for none but you can find the truth. It cost me much entreaty to get the case reserved for you.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> You call her Mistress now, scoundrel; the other day you were making out Philosophy the meanest of things, when before that great audience you let her several doctrines go for a pitiful threepence apiece.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> It may be that it was not Ourself he then reviled, but some impostors who practised vile arts in our name.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> The truth will soon come to light, if you will hear his defence.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Come we to the Areopagus—or better, to the Acropolis, where the panorama of Athens will be before us.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="16">
<p>Ladies, will you stroll in the Poecile meanwhile? I will join you when I have given judgement.</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Who are these, Philosophy? methinks their appearance is seemly as your own.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> This with the masculine features is Virtue; then there is Temperance, and Justice by her side. In front is Culture; and this shadowy creature with the indefinite complexion is Truth.</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> I do not see which you mean.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Not see her? over there, all naked and unadorned, shrinking from observation, and always slipping out of sight.</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Now just discern her. But why not bring them all with you? there would be a fullness and completeness about that commission. Ah yes, and I should like to brief Truth on my behalf. </p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Well thought of; come, all of you; you will not mind sitting through a single case—in which we have a personal interest, too?



<pb n="v.1.p.214"/>




</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="17">
<p><label>Truth</label> Go on, the rest of you; it is superfluous for me to hear what I know all about before.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> But, Truth dear, your presence will be useful to us; you will show us what to think.</p>

<p><label>Truth</label> May I bring my two favourite maids, then?</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> And as many more as you like.</p>

<p><label>Truth</label> Come with me, Freedom and Frankness; this poor little adorer of ours is in trouble without any real reason; we shall be able to get him out of it. Exposure, my man, we shall not want you.</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Ah yes, Mistress, let us have him, of all others; my opponents are no ordinary ruffians; they are people who make a fine show and are hard to expose; they have always some back way out of a difficulty; we must have Exposure.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Yes, we must, indeed; and you had better bring Demonstration too.</p>

<p><label>Truth</label> Come all of you, as you are such important legal persons.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="18">
<p><label>Aristotle</label> What is this? Philosophy, he is employing Truth against us!</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> And are Plato and Chrysippus and Aristotle afraid of her lying on his behalf, being who she is?</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Oh, well, no; only he i is a sad plausible- rogue; he will take her in. </p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Never fear; no wrong will be done, with madam Justice on the bench by us.  Let us go up.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="19">
<p>Prisoner, your name?</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Parrhesiades, son of Alethion, son of Elenxicles.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.1.p.214.n.1">i.e., Free-speaker, son of Truthful, son of Exposure.</note></p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> And your country?</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> I am a Syrian from the Euphrates, my lady. But is the question relevant? Some of my accusers I know to be as much barbarians by blood as myself; but character and culture do




<pb n="v.1.p.215"/>


not vary as a man comes from Soli or Cyprus, Babylon or Stagira. However, even one who could not talk Greek would be none the worse in your eyes, so long as his sentiments were right and just.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> True, the question was unnecessary.

But what is your profession? that at least is essential.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="20">
<p><label>Lucian</label> I profess hatred of pretension and imposture, lying, and pride; the whole loathsome tribe of them I hate; and you know how numerous they are.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Upon my word, you must have your hands full at this profession!</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> I have; you see what general dislike and danger it brings upon me. However, I do not neglect the complementary branch, in which love takes the place of hate; it includes love of truth and beauty and simplicity and all that is akin to love. But the subjects for this branch of the profession are sadly few; those of the other, for whom hatred is the right treatment, are reckoned by the thousand. Indeed there is some danger of the one feeling being atrophied, while the other is over-developed.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> That should not be; they run in couples, you know. Do not separate your two branches; they should have unity in diversity.</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> You know better than I, Philosophy. My way is just to hate a villain, and love and praise the good.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="21">
<p><label>Philosophy</label> Well, well. Here we are at the appointed place. We will hold the trial in the forecourt of Athene Polias: Priestess, arrange our seats, while we salute the Goddess.</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Polias, come to my aid against these pretenders, mindful of the daily perjuries thou hearest from them. Their deeds too are revealed to thee alone, in virtue of thy charge. Thou hast now thine hour of vengeance. If thou see me in evil case, if blacks be more than whites, then cast thou thy vote and save me!



<pb n="v.1.p.216"/>




</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="22">
<p><label>Philosophy</label> So. Now we are seated, ready to hear your words. Choose one of your number, the best accuser you may, make your charge, and bring your proofs. Were all to speak, there would be no end. And you, Parrhesiades, shall afterwards make your defence.</p>

<p><label>Chrysippus</label> Plato, none of us will conduct the prosecution better than you. Your thoughts are heaven-high, your style the perfect Attic; grace and persuasion, insight and subtlety, the cogency of welltordered proof—all these are gathered in you. Take the spokesman’s office and say what is fitting on our behalf. Call to memory and roll in one all that ever you said against Gorgias, Polus, Hippias, Prodicus; you have now to do with a worse than them. Let him taste your irony; ply him with your keen incessant questions; and if you will, perorate with the mighty Zeus charioting his winged car through Heaven, and grudging if this fellow get not his deserts.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="23">
<p><label>Platonists</label> Nay, nay; choose one of more strenuous temper—</p>

<p><label>Diogenes</label> Antisthenes, Crates, or yourself, Chrysippus. It is no time now for beauty or literary skill; controversial and forensic resource is what we want. This Parrhesiades is an orator.</p>

<p><label>Diogenes</label> Let me be accuser; no need for long speeches here. Moreover, I was the worst treated of all; threepence was my price the other day.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Philosophy, Diogenes will speak for us. But mind, friend, you are not to represent yourself alone, but think of us all. If we have any private differences of doctrine, do not go into that; never mind now which of us is right, but keep your indignation for Philosophy’s wrongs and the names he has called her. Leave alone the principles we differ about, and maintain what is common to us al, Now mark, you stand for us all; on you our whole fame depends; shall it come out majestic, or in the semblance he has given it?

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="24">
<p><label>Diogenes</label> Never fear; nothing shall be omitted; I speak for all.



<pb n="v.1.p.217"/>




Philosophy may be softened by his words—she was ever gentle and forgiving—she may be minded to acquit him; but the fault shall not be mine; I will show him that our staves are more than ornaments.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Nay, take not that way; words, not bludgeons; ’tis better so. But no delay now; your time-allowance has begun; and the court is all attention.</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> Philosophy, let the rest take their seats and vote with you, leaving Diogenes as sole accuser.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Have you no fears of their condemning you?</p>

<p><label>Lucian</label> None whatever; I wish to increase my majority, that is all.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> I commend your spirit. Gentlemen, take your seats. Now, Diogenes.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="25">
<p><label>Diogenes</label> With our lives on earth, Philosophy, you are acquainted;
I need not dwell long upon them. Of myself I say nothing; but Pythagoras, Plato, Aristotle, Chrysippus, and the rest— who knows not the benefits that they conferred on mankind?
I will come at once, then, to the insults to which we have been subjected by the thrice accursed Parrhesiades. He was, by his own account, an advocate; but he has left the courts and the fame there to be won, and has availed himself of all the verbal skill and proficiency so acquired for a campaign of abuse against us. We are impostors and deceivers; his audiences must ridicule and scorn us for nobodies. Did I say ‘nobodies’? he has made us an abomination, rather, in the eyes of the vulgar, and yourself with us, Philosophy. Your teachings are balderdash and rubbish; the noblest of your precepts to us he parodies, winning for himself applause and approval, and for us humiliation, For so it is with the great public; it loves a master of flouts and jeers, and loves him in proportion to the grandeur of what he assails; you know how it delighted long ago in Aristophanes and Eupolis, when they caricatured our Socrates on



<pb n="v.1.p.218"/>


the stage, and wove farcical comedies around him. But they at least confined themselves to a single victim, and they had the charter of Dionysus; a jest might pass at holiday time, and the laughing God might be well pleased.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="26">
<p>But this fellow gets together an upper-class aydience, gives long thought to his preparations, writes down his slanders in a thick notebook, and uplifts his voice in vituperation of Plato, Pythagoras, Aristotle, Chrysippus, and in short all of us; be cannot plead holiday time, nor yet any private grievance; he might perhaps be forgiven if he had done it in self-defence; but it was he that opened hostilities. Worst of all, Philosophy, he shelters himself under your name, entices Dialogue from our company to be hig ally and mouthpiece, and induces our good comrade Menippus to collaborate constantly with him; Menippus, more by token, is the one deserter and absentee on this occasion.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="27">
<p>Does he not then abundantly deserve his fate? What conceivable defence is open to him, after his public defamation of all that is noblest? On the public which listened to him, too, the spectacle of his condign punishment will have a healthy effect; we shall see no more ridicule of Philosophy. Tame submission to insult would naturally enough be taken, not for moderation, but for insensibility and want of spirit. Who could be expected to put up with his last performance? He brought us to market like a gang of slaves, and handed us over to the auctioneer. Some, I believe, fetched high prices; but others went for four or five pounds, and as for me—confound his impudence, threepence! And fine fun the audience had out of it!
We did well to be angry; we have come from Hades; and we ask you to give us satisfaction for this abominable outrage.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="28">
<p><label>Resurgents</label> Hear, hear! well spoken, Diogenes; well and loyally.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Silence in court! Time the defence. Parrhesiades, it is now your turn; they are timing you; so proceed.



<pb n="v.1.p.219"/>




</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="29">
<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Philosophy, Diogenes has been far indeed from exhausting his material; the greater part of it, and the more strongly expressed, he has passed by, for reasons best known to himself, I refer to statements of mine which I am as far from denying that I made as from having provided myself with any elaborate defence of them. Any of these that have been omitted by him, and not previously emphasized by myself, I propose now to quote; this will be the best way to show you who were the persons that I sold by auction and inveighed against as pretenders and impostors; please to concentrate your vigilance on the truth or falsehood of my descriptions. If what I say is injurious or severe, your censure will be more fairly directed at the perpetrators than at the discoverer of such iniquities. I had no sooner realized the odious practices which his profession imposes qn an advocate—the deceit, falsehood, bluster, clamour, pushing, and all the long hateful list, than I fled as a matter of course from these, betook myself to your dear service, Philosophy, and pleased myself with the thought of a remainder of life spent far from the tossing waves in a calm haven beneath your shadow.
</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="30">
<p> At my first peep into your realm, how could I but admire yourself and all these your disciples? there they were, legislating for the perfect life, holding out hands of help to those that would reach it, commending all that was fairest and best; fairest and best—but a man must keep straight on for it and never slip, must set his eyes unwaveringly on the laws that you have laid down, must tune and test his life thereby; and that, Zeus be my witness, there are few enough in these days of ours to do.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="31">
<p>So I saw how many were in love, not with Philosophy, but with the credit it brings; in the vulgar externals, so easy for any one to ape, they showed a striking resemblance to the real article, perfect in beard and walk and attire; but in life and



<pb n="v.1.p.220"/>


conduct they belied their looks, read your lessons backwards, and degraded their profession. Then I was wroth; methought it was as though some soft womanish actor on the tragic stage should give us Achilles or Theseus or Heracles himself; he cannot stride nor speak out as a Hero should, but minces along under his enormous mask; Helen or Polyxena would find him too realistically feminine to pass for them; and what shall an invincible Heracles say? Will he not swiftly pound man and mask together into nothingness with his club, for womanizing and disgracing him?

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="32">
<p>Well, these people were about as fit to represent you, and the degradation of it all was too much for me, Apes daring to masquerade as heroes! emulators of the ass at Cyme! The Cymeans, you know, had never seen ass or lion; so the ass came the lion over them, with the aid of a borrowed skin and his most awe-inspiring bray; however, a stranger who had often seen both brought the truth to light with a stick. But what most distressed me, Philosophy, was this: when one of these people was detected in rascality, impropriety, or immorality, every one put it down to philosophy, and to the particular philosopher whose name the delinquent took in vain without ever acting on his principles; the living rascal disgraced you, the long dead; for you were not there in the flesh to point the contrast; so, as’ it was clear enough that his life was vile and disgusting, your case was given away by association with his, and you had to share his disgrace.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="33">
<p>This spectacle, I say, was too much for me; I began exposing them, and distinguishing between them and you; and for this good work you now arraign me. So then, if I find one of the Initiated betraying and parodying the Mysteries of the two Goddesses, and if I protest and denounce him, the transgression will be mine? There is something wrong there; why, at the Games, if an actor who has to present Athene or Posidon or



<pb n="v.1.p.221"/></p>

<p><label>Zeus</label> plays his part badly, derogating from the divine dignity, the stewards have him whipped; well, the Gods are not angry with them for having the officers whip the man who wears their mask and their attire; I imagine they approve of the punishment. To play a slave or a messenger badly is a trifling offence, but to represent Zeus or Heracles to the spectators in an unworthy manner—that is a crime and a sacrilege.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="34">
<p>I canindeed conceive nothing more extraordinary than that so many of them should get themselves absolutely perfect in your words, and then live precisely as if the sole object of reading and studying them had been to reverse them in practice. All their professions of despising wealth and appearances, of admiring nothing but what is noble, of superiority to passion, of being proof against splendour, and associating with its owners only on equal terms—how fair and wise and laudable they all are!
But they take pay for-imparting them, they are abashed in presence of the rich, their lips water at sight of coin; they are dogs for temper,- hares for cowardice, apes for imitativeness, asses for lust, cats for thievery, cocks for jealousy. They are a perfect laughing-stock with their strivings after vile ends, their jostling of each other at rich men’s doors, their attendance at crowded dinners, and their vulgar obsequiousness at table. They swill more than they should and would like to swill more than they do, they spoil the wine with unwelcome and untimely disquisitions, and they cannot carry their liquor. The ordinary people who are present naturally flout them, and are revolted by the philosophy which breeds such brutes.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="35">
<p>What is so monstrous is that every man’ of them says he has no needs, proclaims aloud that wisdom is ‘the only wealth, and directly afterwards comes begging and makes a fuss if he is refused; it would hardly be stranger to see one in kingly attire, with tall tiara, crown, and all the attributes of royalty, asking his inferiors for a little something more. When they want to



<pb n="v.1.p.222"/>


get something, we hear a great deal, to be sure, about community of goods—how wealth is a thing indifferent—and what is gold and silver?—neither more nor less worth than pebbles on the beach. But when an old comrade and tried friend needs help and comes to them with his modest requirements, ah, then there is silence and searchings of heart, unlearning of tenets and flat renunciation of doctrines. All their fine talk of friendship, with Virtue and The Good, have vanished and flown, who knows whither? they were winged words in sad truth, empty phantoms, only meant for daily conversational use.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="36">
<p>These men are excellent friends so long as there is no gold or silver for them to dispute the possession of; exhibit but a copper or two, and peace is broken, truce void, armistice ended; their books are blank, their Virtue fled, and they so many dogs; some one has flung a bone into the pack, and up they spring to bite each other and snarl at the one which has pounced successfully. There is a story of an Egyptian king who taught some apes the sword-dance; the imitative creatures very soon picked it up, and used to perform in purple robes and masks; for some time the show was a great success, till at last an ingenious spectator brought some nuts in with him and threw them down. The apes forgot their dancing at the sight, dropped their humanity, resumed their apehood, and, smashing masks and tearing dresses, had a free fight for the provender. Alas for the corps de ballet and the gravity of the audience!

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="37">
<p>These people are just those apes; it is they that I reviled; and I shall never cease exposing and ridiculing them; but about you and your like—for there are, in spite of all, some true lovers of philosophy and keepers of your laws—about you or them may I never be mad enough to utter an injurious or rude word! Why, what could I find to say? what is there in your lives that lends itself to such treatment? but those pretenders deserve my detestation, as they have that of heaven. Why, tell me, ail



<pb n="v.1.p.223"/>


of you, what have such creatures to do with you? Is there a trace in their lives of kindred and affinity? Does oil mix with water? If they grow their beards and call themselves philosophers and look solemn, do these things make them like you?
I could have contained myself if there had been any touch of plausibility in their acting; but the vulture is more like the nightingale than they like philosophers. And now I have pleaded my cause to the best of my ability. Truth, I rely upon you to confirm my words.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="38">
<p><label>Philosophy</label> Parrhesiades, retire to a further distance. Well, and our verdict? How think you the man has spoken?</p>

<p><label>Truth</label> Ah, Philosophy, while he was speaking I was ready to sink through the ground; it was all so true. As I listened, I could identify every offender, and I was fitting caps all the time—this is so-and-so, that is the other man, all over. I tell you they were all as plain as in a picture—speaking likenesses not of their bodies only, but of their very souls.</p>

<p><label>Temperance</label> Yes, Truth, I could not help blushing at it.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> What say you, gentlemen?</p>

<p><label>Resurgents</label> Why, of course, that he is acquitted of the charge, and stands recorded as our friend and benefactor. Our case is just that of the Trojans, who entertained the tragic actor only to find him reciting their own calamities. Well, recite away, our tragedian, with these pests of ours for dramatis personae.</p>

<p><label>Diogenes</label> I too, Philosophy, give him my meed of praise; I withdraw my charges, and count him a worthy friend.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="39">
<p><label>Philosophy</label> congratulate you, Parrhesiades; you are unanimously acquitted, and are henceforth one of us.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Your humble servant. Or no, I must find more tragic words to fit the solemnity of the occasion:

<l>Victorious might</l>
<l>My life’s path light,</l>
<l>And ever strew with garlands bright!</l>



<pb n="v.1.p.224"/></p>

<p><label>Virtue</label> Well, now we come to our second course; let us have in the other people and try them for their insults. Parrhesiades shall accuse them each in turn.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Well said, Virtue. Syllogism, my boy, put your head out over the city and summon the philosophers.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="40">
<p><label>Syllogism</label> Oyez, oyez! All philosophers to the Acropolis to make their defence before Virtue, Philosophy, and Justice.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> The proclamation does not bring them in flocks, does it? They have their reasons for keeping clear of Justice. And a good many of them are too busy with their rich friends. If you want them all to come, Syllogism, I will tell you what to say.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> No, no; call them yourself, Parrhesiades, in your own way.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="41">
<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Quite a simple matter. Oyez, oyez! All who profess philosophy and hold themselves entitled to the name of philosopher shall appear on the Acropolis for largesse; £8, with a sesame cake, to each. A long beard shall qualify for a square of compressed figs, in addition. Every applicant to have with him, of temperance, justice, and self-control, any __ that he is in possession of, it being clearly understood that these are not indispensable, and, of syllogisms, a complete set of five, these being the condition precedent of wisdom.

<l>Two golden talents in the midst are set,</l>
<l>His prize who wrangles best amongst his peers.</l>

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="42">
<p>Just look! the ascent packed with a pushing crowd, at the very first sound of my £8. More of them along the Pelasgicum, more by the temple of Asclepius, a bigger crowd still over the Areopagus. Why, positively there are a few at the tomb of Talos; and see those putting ladders against the temple of Castor and Pollux; up they climb, buzzing and clustering like



<pb n="v.1.p.225"/>


a swarm of bees. In Homeric phrase, on this side are exceeding many, and on that

<l>Ten thousand, thick as leaves and flowers in spring.</l>

Noisily they settle, the Acropolis is covered with them in a trice; everywhere wallet and beard, flattery and effrontery, staves and greed, logic and avarice. The little company which came up at the first proclamation is swamped beyond recovery, swallowed up in these later crowds; it is hopeless to find them, because of the external resemblance. That is the worst of it, Philosophy; you are really open to censure for not marking and labelling them; these impostors are often more convincing than the true philosophers.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> It shall be done before long; at present let us receive them.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="43">
<p><label>Platonists</label> Platonists first!</p>

<p><label>Pythagoreans</label> No, no; Pythagoreans first; our master is senior.</p>

<p><label>Stoics</label> Rubbish! the Porch is the best.</p>

<p><label>Peripatetics</label> Now, now, this is a question of money; Peripatetics first there!</p>

<p><label>Epicureans</label> Hand over those cakes and fig-squares; as to the money, Epicureans will not mind waiting till the last.</p>

<p><label>Academics</label> Where are the two talents? none can touch the Academy at a wrangle; we will soon show you that.</p>

<p><label>Stoics</label> Not if we know it.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="44">
<p><label>Philosophy</label> Cease your strife. Cynics there, no more pushing! and keep those sticks quiet. You have mistaken the nature of this summons. We three, Philosophy, Virtue, and Truth, are about to decide which are the true philosophers; that done, those whose lives are found to be in accord with our pleasure will be made happy by our award; but the impostors who are not truly of our kin we shall crush as they deserve, that they may no more make vain claims to what is too high for them.





<pb n="v.1.p.226"/>




Ha! you fly? In good truth they do, jumping down the crags, most of them. Why, the Acropolis is deserted, except for—yes, a few have stood their ground and are not afraid of the judgement.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="45">
<p>Attendants, pick up the wallet which yonder flying Cynic has dropped. Let us see what it contains—beans? a book? some coarse crust?</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Ohdear no. Here is gold; some scent; a mirror; dice.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Ah, good honest man! such were his little necessaries for the philosophic life, such his title to indulge in general abuse and instruct his neighbours.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> There you have them. The problem before you is, how the general ignorance is to be dispersed, and other people enabled to discriminate between the genuine and the other sort. Find the solution, Truth; for indeed it concerns you; Falsehood must not prevail; shall Ignorance shield the base while they counterfeit the good, and you never know it?

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="46">
<p><label>Truth</label> I think we had better give Parrhesiades this commission; he has been shown an honest man, our friend and your true admirer, Philosophy. Let him take Exposure with him and have interviews with all who profess philosophy; any genuine scion that he finds let him crown with olive and entertain in the Banqueting Hall; and for the rascals—ah, how many!—who are only costume philosophers, let him pull their cloaks off them, clip their beards short with a pair of common goatshears, and mark their foreheads or brand them between the eyebrows; the design on the branding iron to be a fox or an ape.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> Well planned, Truth. And, Parrhesiades, here is a test for you; you know how young eagles are supposed to bé tested by the sun; well, our candidates have not got to satisfy us that they can look at light, of course; but put gold, fame, and pleasure before their eyes; when you see one remain


<pb n="v.1.p.227"/>


unconscious and unattracted, there is your man for the olive; but when one looks hard that way, with a motion of his hand in the direction of the gold, first off with his beard, and then off with him to the brander.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="47">
<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> I will follow your instructions, Philosophy; you will soon find a large majority ornamented with fox or ape, and very few with olive. If you like, though, I will get some of them up here for you to see.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> What do you mean? bring them back after that stampede?</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Oh yes, if the priestess will lend me the line I see there and the Piraean fisherman’s votive hook; I will not keep them long.</p>

<p><label>Priestess of Athene</label> You can have them; and the rod to complete the equipment.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Thanks; now quickly, please, a few dried figs and a handful of gold.</p>

<p><label>Priestess of Athene</label> There.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> What is all this about?</p>

<p><label>Priestess of Athene</label> He has baited his hook with the figs and gold, and is sitting on the parapet dangling it over the city.</p>

<p><label>Philosophy</label> What are you doing, Parrhesiades? do you think you are going to fish up stones from the Pelasgicum?</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Hush! wait till I get a bite. Posidon, the fisherman’s friend, and you, dear Amphitrite, send me good fishing!

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="48">
<p>Ah, a fine bass; no, it is not; it is a gilthead.</p>

<p><label>Exposure</label> A shark, you mean; there, see, he is getting near the hook, open-mouthed too. He scents the gold; now he is close—touching—he has it; up with him!</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Give me a hand with the line, Exposure; here he is. Now, my best of fishes, what do we make of you? Salmo Cynicus, that is what you are. Good gracious, what teeth! Aha, my brave fish, caught snapping up trifles in the rocks,





<pb n="v.1.p.228"/>


where you thought you could lurk unobserved? But now you shall hang by the gills for every one to look at you. Pull out hook and bait. Why, the hook is bare; he has not been long assimilating the figs, eh? and the gold has gone down too.</p>

<p><label>Diogenes</label> Make him disgorge; we want the bait for some more.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> There, then. Now, Diogenes, do you know who it is? has the fellow anything to do with you?</p>

<p><label>Diogenes</label> Nothing whatever.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Well, what do you put him at? threepence was the price fi I the other day.</p>

<p><label>Diogenes</label> Too much. His flavour and his looks are intolerable— a coarse worthless brute. Drop him head first over the rock, and catch another. But take care your rod does not bend to breaking point.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> No fear; they are quite light—about the weight of a gudgeon.</p>

<p><label>Diogenes</label> About the weight and about the wit. However, up with them.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="49">
<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Look; what is this one? a sole? flat as a plate, thin as one of his own fillets; he gapes for the hook; down it goes; we have him; up he comes.</p>

<p><label>Diogenes</label> What is he?</p>

<p><label>Exposure</label> His plateship would be a Platonist.</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> You too after the gold, villain?</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Well, Plato? what shall we do with him?</p>

<p><label>Platonists</label> Off with him from the same rock.
</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="50">
<p><label>Diogenes</label> Try again.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Ah, here is a lovely one coming, as far as one can judge in deep water, all the colours of the rainbow, with gold bars across the back. Do you see, Exposure? this is the sham Aristotle. There he is; no, he has shied. He is having a good look round; here he comes again; his jaws open; caught! haul up.



<pb n="v.1.p.229"/></p>

<p><label>Aristotle</label> You need not apply to me; I do not know him.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Very well, Aristotle; over he goes.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="51">
<p>Hullo! I see a whole school of them together, all one colour, and covered with spines and horny scales, as tempting to handle as a hedgehog. We want a net for these; but we have not got one. Well, it will do if we pull up one out of the lot. The boldest of them will no doubt try the hook.</p>

<p><label>Exposure</label> You had better sheathe a good bit of the line before you let it down; else he will gorge the gold and then saw the line through.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> There it goes. Posidon grant me a quick ca...: There now! they are fighting for the bait, a lot of them together nibbling at the figs, and others with their teeth well in the gold. That is right; one soundly hooked. Now let me see, what do you call yourself? and yet how absurd to try and make a fish speak; they are dumb. Exposure, tell us who is his master.</p>

<p><label>Exposure</label> Chrysippus.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Ah, he must have a master with gold in his name, must he? Chrysippus, tell me seriously, do you know these men? are you responsible for the way they live?</p>

<p><label>Chrysippus</label> My dear Parrhesiades, I take it ill that you should suggest any connexion between me and such creatures.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Quite right, and like you. Over he goes head first like the others; if one tried to eat him, those spines might stick in one’s throat.

</p></div>


<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg025.perseus-eng4:" n="52">
<p><label>Philosophy</label> You have fished long enough, Parrhesiades; there are so many of them, one might get away with gold, hook and all, and you have the priestess to pay. Let us go for our usual stroll; and for all you it is time to be getting back to your place, if you are not to outstay your leave. Parrhesiades, you and Exposure can go the rounds now, and crown or brand as I told you.



<pb n="v.1.p.230"/></p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Good, Philosophy. Farewell, ye best of men. Come, Exposure, to our commission. Where shall we go first? the Academy, do you think, or the Porch?</p>

<p><label>Exposure</label> We will begin with the Lyceum.</p>

<p><label>Parrhesiades</label> Well, it makes no difference. I know well enough that wherever we go there will be few crowns wanted, and a good deal of branding. H.

</p></div></div>





</body></text></TEI>

