<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>The Law</title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 20, 2003</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							              <date>1886</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="eng">English</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-29" who="Thibault Clérice">Bumped URN</change>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng"
              type="translation"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg014.perseus-eng2">

			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 1</head>
				           <p> Medicine is of all the Arts the most noble; but, not withstanding, owing to the
					ignorance of those who practice it, and of those who, inconsiderately, form a
					judgment of them, it is at present far behind all the other arts. Their mistake
					appears to me to arise principally from this, that in the cities there is no
					punishment connected with the practice of medicine (and with it alone) except
						disgrace<note>In this passage it would seem to be asserted, that in the time
						of the writer there was no punishment of <hi rend="ital">mala praxis</hi>
						except the disgrace which it entailed. Many other passages in the
						Hippocratic treatises would lead to the inference that a more severe
						responsibility attached to the physciian for unfortunate practice; as we
						often find the practitioner warned not to have anything to do with certain
						cases. Here the author of this treatise seems to regret the want of a proper
						medical police.</note>, and that does not hurt those who are familiar with
					it. Such persons are like the figures which are introduced in tragedies, for as
					they have the shape, and dress, and personal appearance of an actor, but are not
					actors, so also physicians are many in title but very few in reality. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 2</head>
				           <p> Whoever is to acquire a competent knowledge of medicine, ought to be possessed
					of the following advantages: a natural disposition; instruction; a favorable
					position for the study; early tuition; love of labor; leisure. First of all, a
					natural talent is required; for, when Nature opposes, everything else is in
					vain; but when Nature leads the way to what is most excellent, instruction in
					the art takes place, which the student must try to appropriate to himself by
					reflection, becoming an early pupil in a place well adapted for instruction. He
					must also bring to the task a love of labor and perseverance, so that the
					instruction taking root may bring forth proper and abundant fruits. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 3</head>
				           <p> Instruction in medicine is like the culture of the productions <pb n="p.332"/>of
					the earth. For our natural disposition is, as it were, the soil; the tenets of
					our teacher are, as it were, the seed; instruction in youth is like the planting
					of the seed in the ground at the proper season; the place where the instruction
					is communicated is like the food imparted to vegetables by the atmosphere;
					diligent study is like the cultivation of the fields; and it is time which
					imparts strength to all things and brings them to maturity. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 4</head>
				           <p> Having brought all these requisites to the study of medicine, and having
					acquired a true knowledge of it, we shall thus, in traveling through the cities,
					be esteemed physicians not only in name but in reality. But inexperience is a
					bad treasure, and a bad fund to those who possess it, whether in opinion or
					reality, being devoid of self-reliance and contentedness, and the nurse both of
					timidity and audacity. For timidity betrays a want of powers, and audacity a
					want of skill. There are, indeed, two things, knowledge and opinion, of which
					the one makes its possessor really to know, the other to be ignorant. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 5</head>
				           <p> Those things which are sacred, are to be imparted only to sacred persons; and it
					is not lawful to import them to the profane until they have been initiated in
					the mysteries of the science.<pb n="p.333"/>
               </p>
			         </div>

		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
