<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Ulcers</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 20, 2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							<date>1886</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Aph.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Epid.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="section" n="1">
				<head>Part 1</head>
				<p> We must avoid wetting all sorts of ulcers except with wine, unless the ulcer be
					situated in a joint. For, the dry is nearer to the sound, and the wet to the
					unsound, since an ulcer is wet, but a sound part is dry. And it is better to
					leave the part without a bandage unless a unless a cataplasm be applied. Neither
					do certain ulcers admit of cataplasms, and this is the case with the recent
					rather than the old, and with those situated in joints. A spare diet and water
					agree with all ulcers, and with the more recent rather than the older; and with
					an ulcer which either is inflamed or is about to be so; and where there is
					danger of gangrene; and with the ulcers an inflammation in joints; and where
					there is danger of convulsion; and in wounds of the belly; but most especially
					in fractures of the head and thigh, or any other member in which a fracture may
					have occurred. In the case of an ulcer, it is not expedient to stand; more
					especially if the ulcer be situated in the leg; but neither, also, is it proper
					to sit or walk. But quiet and rest are particularly expedient. Recent ulcers,
					both the ulcers themselves and the surrounding parts, will be least exposed to
					inflammation, if one shall bring them to a suppuration as expeditiously as
					possible, and if the matter is not prevented from escaping by the mouth of the
					sore; or, if one should restrain the suppuration, so that only a small and
					necessary quantity of pus may be formed, and the sore may be kept dry by a
					medicine which does not create irritation. For the part becomes inflamed when
					rigor and throbbing supervene; for ulcers then get inflamed when suppuration is
					about to form. A sore suppurates when the blood is changed and be-<pb n="p.334"
					/>comes heated; so that becoming putrid, it constitutes the pus of such ulcers.
					When you seem to require a cataplasm, it is not the ulcer itself to which you
					must apply the cataplasm, but to the surrounding parts, so that the pus may
					escape and the hardened parts may become soft. Ulcers formed either from the
					parts having been cut through by a sharp instrument, or excised, admit of
					medicaments for bloody wounds (<hi rend="ital">'enaima</hi>), and which will
					prevent suppuration by being desiccant to a certain degree. But, when the flesh
					has been contused and roughly cut by the weapon, it is to be so treated that it
					may suppurate as quickly as possible; for thus the inflammation is less, and it
					is necessary that the pieces of flesh which are bruised and cut should melt away
					by becoming putrid, being converted into pus, and that new flesh should then
					grow up. In every recent ulcer, except in the belly, it is expedient to cause
					blood to flow from it abundantly, and as may seem seasonable; for thus will the
					wound and the adjacent parts be less attacked with inflammation. And, in like
					manner, from old ulcers, especially if situated in the leg, in a toe or finger,
					more than in any other part of the body. For when the blood flows they become
					drier and less in size, as being thus dried up. It is this (<hi rend="ital">
						blood?</hi>) especially which prevents such ulcers from healing, by getting
					into a state of putrefaction and corruption. But, it is expedient, after the
					flow of the blood, to bind over the ulcer a thick and soft piece of sponge,
					rather dry than wet, and to place above the sponge some slender leaves. Oil, and
					all things of an emollient and oily nature, disagree with such ulcers, unless
					they are getting nearly well. Neither does oil agree with wounds which have been
					recently inflicted, nor yet do medicines formed with oil or suet, more
					especially if the ulcer stands in need of more cleansing. And, in a word, it is
					in summer and in winter that we are to smear with oil these sores that require
					such medicines. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="2">
				<head>Part 2</head>
				<p> Gentle purging of the bowels agrees with most ulcers, and in wounds of the head,
					belly, or joints, where there is danger of gangrene, in such as require sutures,
					in phagedaenic, spreading and in otherwise inveterate ulcers. And when you want
					to apply a bandage, no plasters are to be used until you have rendered the <pb
						n="p.335"/>sore dry, and then indeed you may apply them. The ulcer is to be
					frequently cleaned with a sponge, and then a dry and clean piece of cloth is to
					be frequently applied to it, and in this way the medicine which it is supposed
					will agree with it is to be applied, either with or without a bandage. The hot
					season agrees better than winter with most ulcers, except those situated in the
					head and belly; but the equinoctial season agrees still better with them. Ulcers
					which have been properly cleansed and dried as they should be, do not usually
					get into a the state. When a bone has exfoliated, or has been burned, or sawed,
					or removed in any other way, the cicatrices of such ulcers become deeper than
					usual. Ulcers which are not cleansed, are not disposed to unite if brought
					together, nor do the lips thereof approximate of their own accord. When the
					points adjoining to an ulcer are inflamed, the ulcer is not disposed to heal
					until the inflammation subside, nor when the surrounding parts are blackened by
					mortification, nor when a varix occasions an overflow of blood in the part, is
					the ulcer disposed to heal, unless you bring the surrounding parts into a
					healthy condition. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="3">
				<head>Part 3</head>
				<p> Circular ulcers, if somewhat hollow, you must scarify all along their edges, or
					to the extent of half the circle, according to the natural stature of the man.
					When erysipelas supervenes upon any sore, you must purge the body, in the way
					most suitable to the ulcer, either upward or downward. When swelling arises
					around an. ulcer, and if the ulcer remain free from inflammation, there will be
					a deposit of matter in process of time. And whatever ulcer gets swelled along
					with inflammation and does not subside as the other parts subside which became
					inflamed and swelled at the same time, there is a danger that such an ulcer may
					not unite. When from a fall, or in any other way, a part has been torn or
					bruised, and the parts surrounding the ulcer have become swelled, and, having
					suppurated, matter flows from the swelling by the ulcer, if in such cases a
					cataplasm be required, it should not be applied to the sore itself, but to the
					surrounding parts, so that the pus may have free exit, and the indurated parts
					may be softened. But when the parts are softened as the inflammation ceases,
					then the parts which are separated are to be <pb n="p.336"/>brought toward one
					another, binding on sponges and applying them, beginning from the sound parts
					and advancing to the ulcer by degrees. But plenty of leaves are to be bound
					above the sponge. When the parts are prevented from coming together by a piece
					of flesh full of humors, it is to be removed. When the ulcer is deep seated in
					the flesh, it is swelled up, both from the bandaging and the compression. Such
					an ulcer should be cut up upon a director (specillum) if possible, at the proper
					time, so as to admit a free discharge of the matter, and then the proper
					treatment is to be applied as may be needed. For the most part, in every hollow
					ulcer which can be seen into which can be seen into direct without being any
					swelling present, if there be putrefaction in it, or if the flesh be flabby and
					putrid, such an ulcer, and the parts which surround it, will be seen to be black
					and somewhat livid. And of corroding ulcers, those which are phagedaenic, spread
					and corrode most powerfully, and, in this case, the parts surrounding the sore
					will have a black and sub-livid appearance. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="4">
				<head>Part 4</head>
				<p> Cataplasms for swellings and inflammation in the surrounding parts. Boiled
					mullein, the raw leaves of the trefoil, and the boiled leaves of the epipetrum,
					and the poley, and if the ulcer stand in need of cleansing, all these things
					also cleanse; and likewise the leaves of the fig-tree, and of the olive, and the
					horehound, all these are to be boiled; and more especially the chaste-tree, and
					the fig, and the olive, and the leaves of the pomegranate are to be boiled in
					like manner. These are to be used raw: and the leaves of the mallow pounded with
					wine, and the leaves of rue, and those of the green origany. With all these,
					linseed is to be boiled up and mixed by pounding it as a very fine powder. When
					there is danger of erysipelas seizing the ulcers, the leaves of woad are to be
					pounded and applied raw in a cataplasm along with linseed, or the linseed is to
					be moistened with the juice of strychnos or of woad, and applied as a cataplasm.
					When the ulcer is clean, but both it and the surrounding parts are inflamed,
					lentil is to be boiled in wine and finely triturated, and, being mixed with a
					little oil, it is to be applied as a cataplasm; and the leaves of the hip-tree
					are to be boiled in water and pounded in a fine powder and made into a
					cataplasm; and apply below a thin, clean<pb n="p.337"/> piece of cloth wetted in
					wine and oil; and when you wish to produce contraction, prepare the leaves of
					the hip-tree like the lentil, and the cress; wine and finely-powdered linseed
					are to be mixed together. And this is proper: linseed, and raw chaste-tree, and
					Melian alum, all these things being macerated in vinegar. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="5">
				<head>Part 5</head>
				<p> Having pounded the white unripe grape in a mortar of red bronze, and passed it
					through the strainer, expose it to the sun during the day, but remove it during
					the night, that it may not suffer from the dew; rub it constantly during the
					day, so that it may dry equally, and may contract as much virtue as possible
					from the bronze: let it be exposed to the sun for as great a length of time as
					till it acquire the thickness of honey; then put it into a bronze pot with the
					fresh honey and sweet wine, in which turpentine resin has been previously
					boiled, boil the resin in the wine until it become hard like boiled honey; then
					take out the resin and pour off the wine: there should be the greatest
					proportion of the juice of unripe grape, next of the wine, and third of the
					honey and myrrh, either the liquid (<hi rend="ital">stacte</hi>) or otherwise.
					The finest kind is to be levigated and moistened by having a small quantity of
					the same wine poured on it; and then the myrrh is to be boiled by itself,
					stirring it in the wine; and when it appears to have attained the proper degree
					of thickness, it is to be poured into the juice of the unripe grape; and the
					finest natron is to be toasted, and gently added to the medicine, along with a
					smaller quantity of the flowers of copper (<hi rend="ital">flos aeris</hi>) than
					of the natron. When you have mixed these things, boil for not less than three
					days, on a gentle fire made with fuel of the fig-tree or with coals, lest it
					catch fire. The applications should all be free from moisture, and the sores
					should not be wetted when this medicine is applied in the form of liniment. This
					medicine is to be used for old ulcers, and also for recent wounds of the glans
					penis, and ulcers on the head and ears. Another medicine for the same
					ulcers:-The dried gall of an ox, the finest honey, white wine, in which the
					shavings of the lotus have been boiled, frankincense, of myrrh an equal part, of
					saffron an equal part, the flowers of copper, in like manner of liquids, the
					greatest proportion of wine, next of honey, and least of the gall.
					Another:-Wine, a little cedar honey, of dried things, <pb n="p.338"/>the flowers
					of copper, myrrh, dried pomegranate rind. Another:-Of the roasted flower of
					copper half a drachm, of myrrh two half-drachms, of saffron three drachms, of
					honey a small quantity, to be boiled with wine. Another:-Of frankincense a
					drachm, of gall a drachm, of saffron three drachms; let each of these be dried
					and finely levigated, then, having mixed, triturate in a very strong sun,
					pouring in the juice of an unripe grape, until it become of a gelatinous
					consistence, for three days; then let them be allowed to macerate in an austere,
					dark-colored, fragrant wine, which is gradually poured upon them. Another:-Boil
					the roots of the holmoak in sweet white wine; and when it appears to be properly
					done, having poured off two parts of the wine, and of the lees of wine as free
					of water as possible one part; then boil, stirring it, so that it may not be
					burnt, at a gentle fire, until it appear to have attained the proper
					consistence. Another:-The other things are to be the same; but, not
					withstanding, instead of the wine, use the strongest white vinegar, and dip into
					it wool as greasy as can be procured, and then, moistening it with the lees of
					oil, boil, and pour in the juice of the wild fig-tree, and add Melian alum, and
					natron, and the flowers of copper, both toasted. This cleanses the ulcers better
					than the former, but the other is no less desiccant. Another:-Dip the wool in a
					very little water; and then, having added a third part of wine, boil until it
					attain the proper consistence. By these, recent ulcers are most speedily
					prevented from getting into a state of suppuration. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="6">
				<head>Part 6</head>
				<p> Another:-Sprinkle on it dried wakerobin, and add the green bark of the fig-tree,
					pounding it in the juice: do this with or without wine, and along with honey.
					Another:-Boiling the shavings of lotus with vinegar (the vinegar should be
					white); then mix the lees of oil and raw tar-water, and use it as a liniment or
					wash, and bandage above. These things in powder prevent recent wounds from
					suppurating, or they may be used for cleansing the sore along with vinegar, or
					for sponging with wine. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="7">
				<head>Part 7</head>
				<p> Another:-Sprinkle (<hi rend="ital">on the sore?</hi>) lead finely triturated
					with the recrement of copper; and sprinkle on it, also, the shavings of lotus,
					and the scales of copper, and alum, and chalcitis, with copper, both alone, and
					with the shavings of lotus. And other-<pb n="p.339"/>wise, when it is wanted to
					use these in a dry state, do it with the Illyrian spodos triturated with the
					shavings, and with the shavings alone. And the flowers of silver alone, in the
					finest powder; and birthwort, when scraped and finely pounded, may be sprinkled
					on the part. Another, for bloody sores myrrh, frankincense, galls, verdigris the
					roasted flower of copper, Egyptian alum roasted, vine flowers, grease of wool,
					plumbago, each of these things is to be diluted, in equal proportions, with wine
					like the former. And there is another preparation of the same:-The strongest
					vinegar of a white color, honey, Egyptian alum, the finest natron; having
					toasted these things gently, pour in a little gall; this cleanses fungous
					ulcers, renders them hollow, and is not pungent. Another:-The herb with the
					small leaves, which gets the name of Parthenium parviflorum, and is used for
					removing thymia (<hi rend="ital">warts?</hi>) from the glans penis, alum,
					chalcitis, a little crude Melian alum (?); sprinkle a little dried elaterium,
					and a little dried pomegranate rind in like manner. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="8">
				<head>Part 8</head>
				<p> The herb which has got the name of lagopyrus, fills up hollow and clean ulcers;
					(when dried it resembles wheat; it has a small leaf like that of the olive, and
					more long;) and the leaf of horehound, with oil. Another:-The internal fatty
					part, resembling honey, of a fig much dried, of water two parts, of linseed not
					much toasted and finely levigated, one part. Another:-Of the dried fig, of the
					flower of copper levigated a little, and the juice of the fig. The preparation
					from dried fig:-The black chamaeleon, the dried gall of an ox, the other things
					the same. Of the powders:-Of the slender cress in a raw state, of horehound, of
					each equal parts; of the dried fig, two parts; of linseed, two parts; the juice
					of the fig. When you use any of these medicines, apply above it compresses
					wetted in vinegar, apply a sponge about the compresses and make a If the
					surrounding parts be in an inflamed state, apply to them any medicine which may
					appear suitable. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="9">
				<head>Part 9</head>
				<p> If you wish to use a liquid application, the medicine called <hi rend="ital"
						>caricum</hi> may be rubbed in, and the bandages may be applied as formerly
					described upon the same principle. The medicine is prepared of the following
					ingredients:-Of black hellebore, of <pb n="p.340"/>sandarach, of the flakes of
					copper, of lead washed, with much sulphur, arsenic, and cantharides. This may be
					compounded so as may be judged most proper, and it is to be diluted with oil of
					juniper. When enough has been rubbed in, lay aside the medicine, and apply
					boiled wakerobin in a soft state, either rubbing it in dry, or moistening it
					with honey. But if you use the caricum in a dry state, you must abstain from
					these things, and sprinkle the medicine on the sore. The powder from hellebore
					and sandarach alone answers. Another liquid medicine:-The herb, the leaf of
					which resembles the arum (wakerobin) in nature, but is white, downy, of the size
					of the ivy-leaf: this herb is applied with wine, or the substance which forms
					upon the branches of the ilex, when pounded with wine, is to be applied.
					Another:-The juice of the grape, the strongest vinegar, the flower of copper,
					natron, the juice of the wild fig-tree. Alum, the most finely levigated, is to
					be put into the juice of the wild grape, and it is to be put into a red bronze
					mortar and stirred in the sun, and removed when it appears to have attained
					proper consistence. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="10">
				<head>Part 10</head>
				<p> These are other powders:-Black hellebore, as finely levigated as possible, is to
					be sprinkled on the sore while any humidity remains about it, and while it
					continues to spread. The bandaging is the same as when plasters are used.
					Another, in like manner:-The driest lumps of salt are to be put into a copper,
					or earthen pot, of equal size, as much as possible, and not large, and the
					finest honey, of double the size of the salt, as far as can be guessed, is to be
					poured upon the lumps of salt, then the vessel is to be put upon coals and
					allowed to sit there until the whole is consumed. Then, having sponged the ulcer
					and cleansed it, bandage it as before, and compress it a little more. Next day,
					wherever the medicine has not been taken in, sprinkle it on, press it down, and
					bandage. But when you wish to remove the medicine, pour in hot vinegar until it
					separate, and again do the same things, sponging it away, if necessary. Another
					corrosive powder:-Of the most finely-levigated misy, sprinkle upon the moist and
					gangrenous parts, and a little of the flower of copper, not altogether
					levigated. Another powder equally corrosive:-Having sponged the ulcer, burn the
					most greasy wool upon a shell <pb n="p.341"/>placed on the fire until the whole
					be consumed; having reduced this to a fine powder, and sprinkled it on the sore,
					apply the bandage in the same manner. Another powder for the same ulcers:-The
					black chamaeleon, when prepared with the juice of the fig. It is to be prepared
					roasted, and alkanet mixed with it. Or, pimpernel, and Egyptian alum roasted,
					and sprinkle on them the Orchomenian powder. For spreading ulcers:-Alum, both
					the Egyptian roasted, and the Melian; but the part is to be first cleansed with
					roasted natron and sponged; and the species of alum called chalcitis roasted. It
					is to be roasted until it catch fire. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="11">
				<head>Part 11</head>
				<p> For old ulcers which occur on the fore part of the legs; they become bloody and
					black:-Having pounded the flower of the melilot and mixed it with honey, use as
					a plaster. For nerves (<hi rend="ital">tendons?</hi>) which have been cut
					asunder:-Having pounded, sifted, and mixed with oil the roots of the wild
					myrtle, bind on the part; and the herb cinquefoil (it is white and downy, and
					more raised above the ground than the black cinquefoil), having pounded this
					herb in oil bind it on the part, and then remove it on the third day. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="12">
				<head>Part 12</head>
				<p>
					<hi rend="ital">Emollients</hi> (?):-These medicines are to be used in winter
					rather than in summer. Emollient medicines which make the cicatrices fair:-Pound
					the inner mucous part of the squill and pitch, with fresh swine's seam, and a
					little oil, and a little resin, and ceruse. And the grease of a goose, fresh
					swine's seam, and squill, and a little oil. The whitest wax, fresh clean grease,
					or squill and white oil, and a little resin. Wax, swine's seam (old and fresh),
					and oil, and verdigris, and squill and resin. Let there be two parts of the old
					grease to the fresh, and of the other things, q. s. Having melted the grease
					that is fresh, pour it into another pot; having levigated plumbago finely and
					sifted it, and mixed them together, boil and stir at first; boil until when
					poured upon the ground it concretes; then taking it off the fire, pour it all
					into another vessel, with the exception of the stony sediment, and add resin and
					stir, and mix a little oil of juniper, and what has been taken off. In all the
					emollient medicines to which you add the resin, when you remove the medicine
					from the fire, pour in and mix the resin while it is still warm. Another:-Old
					swine's seam, wax, and oil, the dried shavings of the lotus, frankincense,
					plumbago,-namely, of the frankincense one part, and of the other one part, and
					of the shavings of the lotus one part; but let there be two parts of the old
					grease, one of wax, and of fresh swine's seam one part. Another:-Or old swine's
					seam along with the fresh grease of a goat; when cleaned, let it retain as
					little as possible of its membrane: having triturated or pounded it smooth, pour
					in oil, and sprinkle the lead with the spodium and half the shavings of the
					lotus. Another:-Swine's seam, spodium, blue chalcitis, oil. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="13">
				<head>Part 13</head>
				<p>
					<hi rend="ital">For Burns:</hi>-You must boil the tender roots of the ilex, and
					if their bark be very thick and green, it must be cut into small parts, and
					having poured in white wine, boil upon a gentle fire, until it appear to you to
					be of the proper consistence, so as to be used for a liniment. And it may be
					prepared in water after the same manner. Another, not corrosive:-Old swine's <pb
						n="p.342"/>seam is to be rubbed in by itself, and it is to be melted along
					with squill, the root of which is to be divided and applied with a bandage. Next
					day it is to be fomented; and having melted old swine's seam and wax, and mixed
					with them oil, frankincense, and the shavings of lotus and vermilion, this is to
					be used as a liniment. Having boiled the leaves of the wakerobin in wine and
					oil, apply a bandage. Another:-When you have smeared the parts with old swine's
					seam let the roots of asphodel be pounded in wine and triturated, and rubbed in.
					Another:-Having melted old swine's seam, and mixed with resin and bitumen, and
					having spread it on a piece of cloth and warmed it at the fire, apply a bandage.
					When an ulcer has formed on the back from stripes or otherwise, let squill,
					twice boiled, be pounded and spread upon a linen cloth and bound on the place.
					Afterward the grease of a goat, and fresh swine's seam, spodium, oil, and
					frankincense are to be rubbed in. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="14">
				<head>Part 14</head>
				<p> Swellings which arise on the feet, either spontaneously or otherwise, when
					neither the swellings nor the inflammation subside under the use of cataplasms,
					and although sponges or wool, or anything else be bound upon the sound part; but
					the swelling and inflammation return of themselves again, an influx of blood <pb
						n="p.343"/>into the veins is the cause, when not occasioned by a bruise. And
					the same story applies if this happen in any other part of the body. But blood
					is to be abstracted, especially the from the veins, which are the seat of the
					influx, if they be conspicuous; but if not, deeper and more numerous
					scarifications are to be made in the swellings; and whatever part you scarify,
					this is to be done with the sharpest and most slender instruments of iron. When
					you have removed the blood, you must not press hard upon the part with the
					specillum, lest you produce contusion. Bathe with vinegar, and do not allow a
					clot of blood to remain between the lips of the wounds, and having spread greasy
					wool with a medicine for bloody wounds, and having carded the woof and made it
					soft, bind it on, having wetted it with wine and oil. And let the scarified part
					be so placed that the determination of the blood may be upward and not downward;
					and do not wet the part at all, and let the patient be put upon a restricted
					diet and drink water. If upon loosing the bandages you find the scarifications
					inflamed, apply a cataplasm of the fruit of the chaste-tree and linseed. But if
					the scarifications become ulcerated and break into one another, we must be
					regulated by circumstances, and otherwise apply whatever else appears to be
					proper. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="15">
				<head>Part 15</head>
				<p> When a varix is on the fore part of the leg, and is very superficial, or below
					the flesh, and the leg is black, and seems to stand in need of having the blood
					evacuated from it, such swellings are not, by any means, to be cut open; for,
					generally, large ulcers are the consequence of the incisions, owing to the
					influx from the varix. But the varix itself is to be punctured in many places,
					as circumstances may indicate. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="16">
				<head>Part 16</head>
				<p> When you have opened a vein and abstracted blood, and although the fillet be
					loosed the bleeding does not stop, the member, whether the arm or leg, is to be
					put into the reverse position to that from which the blood flows; so that the
					blood may flow backward, and it is to be allowed to remain in this position for
					a greater or less space of time. Then bind up the part while matters are so, no
					clots of blood being allowed to remain in the opening. Then having applied a
					double compress, and wetted it with wine, apply above it clean wool which has
					been smeared with <pb n="p.344"/>oil. For, although the flow of blood be
					violent, it will be stopped in this way. If a thrombus be formed in the opening,
					it will inflame and suppurate. Venesection is to be practiced when the person
					has dined more or less freely and drunk, and when somewhat heated, and rather in
					hot weather than in cold. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="17">
				<head>Part 17</head>
				<p> When in cupping, the blood continues to flow after the cupping-instrument has
					been removed, and if the flow of blood, or serum be copious, the instrument is
					to be applied again before the part is healed up, so as to abstract what is left
					behind. Otherwise coagula of blood will be retained in the incisions and
					inflammatory ulcers will arise from them. In all such cases the parts are to be
					bathed with vinegar, after which they are not to be wetted; neither must the
					person lie upon the scarifications, but they are to be anointed with some of the
					medicines for bloody wounds. When the cupping instrument is to be applied below
					the knee, or at the knee, it should be done, if possible, while the man stands
					erect. <pb n="p.345"/></p>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
