<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>The Erotic Essay</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <editor role="translator">Norman W. DeWitt</editor>
                <editor role="translator">Norman J. DeWitt</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">1996</date>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes Vol. VII. Funeral Speech, Erotic Essay, LX, LXI, Exordia and Letters. With an English translation by Norman W. DeWitt, Ph.D., Norman J. DeWitt, Ph.D.</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date type="printing">1949</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.183487">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="section"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
<head></head>
            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>Well, since you wish to hear the essay, I shall bring it out and read it aloud;
                    but first you must understand its purpose. The writer’s desire is to praise
                        Epicrates,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">It was at the house of a certain
                        Epicrates that Lysias was supposed to have delivered his love-speech; <bibl
                            n="Plat. Phaedrus 227b">Plat. Phaedrus 227b</bibl>.</note> whom he
                    thought to be the most charming young man in the city, although there were many
                    fine gentlemen among those of his own age, and to surpass him more in
                    understanding than in beauty of person. Observing also that, generally speaking,
                    most erotic compositions attach shame rather than honor to those about whom they
                    are written, he has taken precautions that this should not happen in his case,
                    and has written only what he says he is convinced of by his judgement, believing
                    that an honest lover would neither do anything shameful nor request it.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This topic is treated by <bibl n="Cic. Amic. 12"
                            >Cicero De Amic. 12</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>Now, that part of my essay which you may find to be the most erotic, so to speak,
                    is on this topic, but the rest of it in part praises the lad himself and in part
                    counsels about his education and his design for living.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The author plainly hints at a threefold partition of his
                        theme: the erotic part, <bibl n="Dem. 61.3">Dem. 61.3-9</bibl>, eulogy,
                            <bibl n="Dem. 61.10">Dem. 61.10-32</bibl>, and the protrepticus, <bibl
                            n="Dem. 61.36">Dem. 61.36-55</bibl>. Blass sees a twofold division only,
                        eulogy and protrepticus. In either case the remaining sections serve as
                        introduction, transition and epilogue. Exhortations to the study of
                        philosophy were called <q type="">protreptics.</q></note> whole essay is written as one
                    would put it into a book, because discourses intended to be delivered ought to
                    be written simply and just as one might speak offhand, while those of the other
                    kind, which are planned to last longer, are properly composed in the manner of
                    poetry and ornately.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There is a reference to
                        these two styles in <bibl n="Isoc. 4.11">Isoc. 4.11</bibl>, as Blass notes.
                        The epideictic is akin to poetry in the use of figures of speech (see <bibl
                            n="Dem. 61.11">Dem. 61.11</bibl>); the reference of <q type="">ornately</q> is
                        chiefly to rhythm. In both the <title>Funeral Speech</title> (<bibl
                            n="Dem. 60">Dem. 60</bibl>) and the <title>Erotic Essay</title> there is
                        careful avoidance of hiatus; rhythmical clausulae are not infrequent;
                        Gorgianic parallel clausulae occur (<bibl n="Dem. 61.32">Dem.
                        61.32</bibl>).</note> For it is the function of the former to win converts
                    and of the latter to display one’s skill. Accordingly, to avoid spoiling the
                    essay for you or rehearsing my own opinions about these questions, I ask you to
                    lend your attention, since you are immediately going to hear the essay itself,
                    because Epicrates is also at hand, whom I wished to hear it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>Observing that certain of those who are loved and possess their share of good
                    looks make the right use of neither one of these blessings, but put on grand
                    airs because of the comeliness of their appearance and exhibit reluctance to
                    associate with their admirers,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Greek word
                        means <q type="">lover</q> or <q type="">sweetheart,</q> applied to men as well as women.</note> and
                    so far fail in judging what is best that, because of those who pervert the
                    thing, they assume a surly attitude toward those also who desire to associate
                    with them from pure motives, I concluded that such young men not only defeat
                    their own interests but also engender evil habits in the rest, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>and that the high-minded should not follow their foolish example, bearing in mind
                    particularly that, since actions are not absolutely either honorable or shameful
                    but for most part vary according to the persons concerned,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The same distinction is made in synonymous terms, <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 6.60">Isoc. 6.60</bibl>.</note> it is unreasonable to adopt the
                    same attitude toward both classes of men, and secondly, that it is the height of
                    absurdity to envy those who have a host of firm friends but to repulse their
                    admirers, who are a separate group and alone feel drawn by nature, not toward
                    all, but only to the beautiful and modest. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>Moreover, although those who have never yet seen such a friendship turn out well
                    or have severely condemned themselves on the ground that they would be incapable
                    of associating innocently with casual acquaintances, it is perhaps not
                    unreasonable to entertain this prejudice<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">He
                        means the prejudice against any compromise with associations that might lead
                        to homosexuality, variously known as boy-love, Greek love or Doric
                        love.</note>; but for those so disposed as yourself, who have not utterly
                    refused to hear how very many benefits accrue through love without shame and
                    have lived the rest of their lives with the utmost circumspection, it is not
                    reasonable to have even a suspicion that they would do anything shameful. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>Consequently I have felt all the more a moved to write this essay, feeling sure I
                    should not fail to secure two most honorable rewards.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The use of the dual savors of poetry.</note> For when I have
                    described the good qualities you possess, I hope that at one and the same time I
                    shall prove you to be worthy of admiration and myself not senseless if I love
                    you, being what you are; and secondly, in tendering the advice that is most
                    urgently needed I believe I shall present proof of my own goodwill and furnish a
                    basis for our mutual friendship. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>And yet it does not escape me that it is difficult to describe your character in
                    keeping with your deserts and that it is more hazardous still to give advice
                    when the adviser is bound to make himself answerable for his advice to the one
                    who accepts it.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass notes a parallel in <bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.189">Dem. 18.189</bibl>, but it is remote.</note> It is my
                    judgement, however, that, while it becomes the recipients of merited eulogies to
                    baffle by the excess of their real virtue the ability of those who praise them,
                    yet in my counsel I shall not miss the mark, being well aware that no advice
                    could be innocently carried out if proffered by men who are senseless and quite
                    ruined by incontinence, not even if they advise supremely well, but that not
                    even the advice that is only moderately pondered can altogether miss the mark if
                    tendered by men who choose to live pure and self disciplined lives. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>Cherishing such hopes I enter upon my theme. All men would agree with me, I
                    believe, that it is of the utmost importance for young men of your age to
                    possess beauty in respect of person, self-discipline in respect of soul, and
                    manliness in respect of both, and consistently to possess charm in respect of
                    speech. As for these two kinds of qualities, natural and acquired, Fortune has
                    so generously blessed you with nature’s gifts that you consistently enjoy
                    distinction and admiration, and the other kind you are bringing to such
                    perfection through your own diligence that no fair-minded person could have
                    fault to find with you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>And yet what ought he to possess who is worthy of the highest eulogies?<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">These identical words are found in <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 16.30">Isoc. 16.30</bibl>.</note> Must he not manifestly be
                    loved by the gods and among men be admired, for some qualities on his own
                    account, for others because of his good fortune? Now the longer list of your
                    virtuous qualities it will perhaps be fitting to describe summarily later on,
                    but the praise I have to utter for each of the gifts of Fortune I shall now try
                    to declare with truthfulness. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>I shall begin by praising that quality of yours which all who see you will
                    recognize first, your beauty, and the hue of your flesh, by virtue of which your
                    limbs and your whole body are rendered resplendent. Wondering what fitting
                    comparison for this I may offer, I find none, but it is my privilege to request
                    those who read this essay to see you and contemplate you, so that I may be
                    pardoned for declaring that I have no suitable simile. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>For to what could anyone liken something mortal which arouses immortal longing in
                    the beholder, the sight of which does not satiate, and when removed from sight
                    lingers in the memory, which in human form possesses a natural beauty worthy of
                    the gods, like a flower in its comeliness, beyond suspicion of imperfections?
                    Furthermore, it is impossible to impute to your person even those blemishes
                    which in the past have marred many another who has shared in beauty. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>For either through ungainliness of mien they have ruined all their natural
                    comeliness or through some unfortunate mannerism have involved their natural
                    attractions in the same disfavor. By none of these could we find your person
                    afflicted, for whichever of the gods it was that took forethought for your
                    person has so diligently guarded you against all such mishaps as to leave
                    nothing calling for criticism and to render your general appearance superb. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>Moreover, since the face is the most conspicuous of the parts that are seen, and
                    of the face itself the eyes, even more in these did the god reveal the goodwill
                    that he had toward you. For he not only furnished you with eyes adequate to
                    perform the necessary functions but, although the virtue of some men is not
                    recognized even from their actions, of your character he has placed in a clear
                    light the fine qualities through the evidence of your glance, displaying it as
                    gentle and kind toward those who look at you, dignified and serious toward those
                    who converse with you, manly and proper to all men. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>And here is a matter that may be particularly surprising. For while other men are
                    assumed to be mean-spirited because they are gentle and to be arrogant because
                    they are dignified, and are thought overbearing because they are manly, and
                    stupid because they keep quiet, Fortune in your case has taken qualities so
                    mutually contradictory and caused them all to be properly harmonized, as if
                    fulfilling a prayer or wishing to set an example for others, but not framing a
                    mere mortal nature, as was her usual way. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Now if it were possible to do justice to such beauty as yours in words, or if
                    this were the only quality of yours worthy of praise, we should think it
                    necessary to omit praise of none of your good points; but as things are, I am
                    afraid that we may find our bearers refusing to hear praise of your other merits
                    and that we may defeat ourselves by harping on this theme. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>For how could anyone overdo the verbal description of your appearance, since not
                    even works of art executed by the skill of the best masters could do more than
                    justice to it? Nor is this astonishing; for works of art have a motionless
                    aspect, so that it is uncertain what they would look like if they possessed
                    life, but your personality enhances in your every action the superb comeliness
                    of your body. Only this much, therefore, I have to say in praise of your beauty,
                    omitting a great deal. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>As for discreetness of conduct, it is my privilege to pass the finest of
                    compliments, namely, that though such youthfulness readily invites scandal, it
                    has been your lot to be praised instead. For so far from overstepping the mark,
                    you have chosen to live more prudently than is expected of your years. Of this
                    the most convincing evidence is your deportment toward others; for although many
                    make your acquaintance, and reveal characters of every kind and sort, and all
                    seek to entice you into intimacies, you have so managed such people that all are
                    content to feel friendship for you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>This is an index of those whose choice it is to live in the esteem and affection
                    of men. And yet some men in the past have been well thought of who have advised
                    against welcoming the company of all comers, as is also true of some who have
                    taken their advice. For they claim that it is necessary either to humor
                    low-minded people and so be maligned among the multitude, or else to be
                    constantly on guard against such reproaches and so incur the dislike of such
                    acquaintances themselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>Personally I think you deserve to be eulogized all the more for this reason,
                    that, while the other lads think it one of the impossible things to please men
                    of every type,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass calls attention to this
                        same thought in <bibl n="Dem. L. 3.27">Dem. L. 3.27</bibl>, but <bibl
                            n="Thgn. 23">Theog. 23-26</bibl> shows it to be an ancient
                        commonplace.</note> you have so surpassed these as to have risen superior to
                    all the difficult and troublesome people, allowing the others no reason even for
                    suspecting immoral relations with any and overcoming your annoyance with them by
                    the adaptability of your manners. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>Now touching your admirers, if it is right to speak also of these, you seem to me
                    to deport yourself so admirably and sensibly toward them, that, though most of
                    them cannot be patient even with the object of their preference, you succeed in
                    pleasing them all exceedingly. And this is a most unmistakable proof of your
                    goodness; for not one finds himself disappointed of favors from you which it is
                    just and fair to ask, but no one is permitted even to hope for such liberties as
                    lead to shame. So great is the latitude your discreetness permits to those who
                    have the best intentions; so great is the discouragement it presents to those
                    who would fling off restraint. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, while the majority of men, when young, seek a reputation for
                    prudence by keeping silent, you are so superior to them in natural gifts that
                    you gain men’s good opinion of you not less by your speech and demeanor in
                    casual company than by all your other merits; so great is the grace and charm of
                    your words whether in jest or in earnest. For you are ingenuous without doing
                    wrong, clever without being malicious, kindly without sacrifice of independence,
                    and, taking all in all, like a child of Virtue sired by Love.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This is the language of poetry as predicted in <bibl
                            n="Dem. 61.2">Dem. 61.2</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>Turning now to courage—for it will not do to omit this either, not because I
                    would intimate that your character does not still admit of great development nor
                    that the future will fail to furnish richer material for eulogy to those who
                    wish to praise you, but rather that words of praise mean most at your age when
                    to do no wrong is the best hope for other lads—your courage a man might extol on
                    many other grounds but especially because of your training for athletic sports,
                    of which you have a multitude of witnesses. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>And perhaps it is in place first to say that you have done well in choosing this
                    kind of contest. For to judge rightly when one is young what line of action one
                    should pursue<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass notes a similarity in the
                            <bibl n="Dem. 60.17">Dem. 60.17</bibl>; not impressive.</note> is the
                    token of an honest soul and of sound judgement alike, and on neither ground
                    would it be right to omit praise of your choice.</p>
                <p>You, therefore, being well aware that slaves and aliens share in the other sports
                    but that dismounting is open only to citizens and that the best men aspire it,
                    have eagerly applied yourself to this sport.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >The contestants were called <q type="">apobates,</q> desultores, i.e. <q type="">dismounters.</q> The
                        drivers seem to have dismounted at times and raced with the teams. <bibl
                            n="D.H. 7.73">Dion. Halicarn. Roman Antiq. 7.73</bibl>; E. Norman
                        Gardiner, <title>Greek Athletic Sports and Festivals</title>, pp.
                        237-239.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>Discerning, moreover, that those who train for the footraces add nothing to their
                    courage nor to their morale either, and that those who practice boxing and the
                    like ruin their minds as well as their bodies, you have singled out the noblest
                    and grandest of competitive exercises and the one most in harmony with your
                    natural gifts, one which approximates to the realities of warfare through the
                    habituation to martial weapons and the laborious effort of running, in the
                    magnificence and majesty of the equipment simulates the might of the gods,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Certain gods were represented as using chariots,
                        particularly Ares and Poseidon.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>presents the number and the greatest variety of features and has been deemed
                    worthy of the most valuable prizes. For, apart from those offered, getting the
                    drill and practice in such exercises itself will possess glamor as no paltry
                    prize in the eyes of those who are even moderately ambitious for excellence. The
                    best evidence for this may be found in the poetry of Homer, in which he
                    represents the Greeks and barbarians warring against one another with this
                        equipment.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Homeric warriors employed
                        charioteers, dashed recklessly among the foe to spread dismay, and finally
                        dismounted to engage in single combat; <bibl n="Hom. Il. 16.712">Hom. Il.
                            16.712-867</bibl>.</note> I may add that even now it is customary to
                    employ it in contests in Greek cities, and not in the meanest cities but in the
                        greatest.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Athens and Thebes.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>So admirable is your choice of sport and so approved among all men. Believing
                    also, as you do, that it is futile to desire the things most worth while, or yet
                    to be physically endowed for all sorts of feats, unless the soul has been
                    prepared for an ambitious career, at the very outset you exhibited diligence in
                    the training grounds, nor in the real tests were you disappointing, but you gave
                    extraordinary proof of the distinction of your natural gifts and particularly of
                    the courage of your soul in the games. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>I hesitate to begin treating this topic for fear words may fail me in the
                    description of what took place on that occasion, but nevertheless I shall not
                    pass it over; for it is a shame to refuse a report of what enthralls us as
                    spectators.</p>
                <p>Were I to describe all the contests an unseemly length would perhaps accrue to
                    this essay,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass notes the expression of a
                        similar fear in the <bibl n="Dem. 60.6">Dem. 60.6</bibl> and in <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 4.66">Isoc. 4.66</bibl>, but surely it is a commonplace.</note>
                    but by recalling a single example in which you especially distinguished yourself
                    I shall demonstrate the same truth and be found to make a more reasonable use of
                    the patience of my hearers. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>When the teams had been started and some had leaped to the fore and some were
                    being reined in, you, prevailing over both, first one and then the other,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass notes the same phrase in <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 4.72">Isoc. 4.72</bibl>; it may have been technical in the
                        language of ancient sport.</note> in proper style, seized the victory,
                    winning that envied crown in such fashion that, glorious as it was to win it, it
                    seemed the more glorious and astounding that you came off safely. For when the
                    chariot of your opponents was bearing down upon you head-on and all thought the
                    momentum of your horses beyond checking, you, aware that some drivers, though no
                    danger should threaten, become overanxious for their own safety, not only did
                    not lose your head or your nerve, but by your courage got control of the impetus
                    of your team and by your speed passed even those contenders whose luck had
                    suffered no setback. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>What is more, you caused such a revolution in men’s minds that, though many keep
                    insisting that nothing in equestrian contests affords such delight as a crash,
                    and seem to speak the truth, in your case all the spectators, on the contrary,
                    were afraid that some such accident might befall you. Such goodwill and
                    eagerness for your success did your personality awaken in them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>They had good reason to feel so, for while it is a splendid thing to become
                    distinguished for some one excellence, it is still more splendid to combine all
                    the qualities of which a man of sense might justly feel proud. From the
                    following examples this will be clear: we shall find that Aeacus and
                    Rhadamanthys were beloved by the gods for their discretion, Heracles, Castor and
                    Pollux for their courage, and Ganymedes, Adonis, and others like them for their
                    beauty, so that I at any rate am not astonished at those who covet your
                    friendship but at those who are not so disposed. For when some, through sharing
                    in one or another of the qualities I have mentioned, have been deemed worthy of
                    the company of the gods, surely to a mere mortal it is the heights of desire to
                    become the friend of one who has become the proud possessor of all good
                    qualities. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>Certainly your father and mother and the rest of your kinsmen are rightly envied
                    because you so far surpass those of your own age in excellence, but still more
                    enviable are those whom you, who have been deemed worthy of such blessings,
                    select from the whole number to be your friends, judging them worthy of your
                    companionship. And since Fortune has appointed the former to share your
                    affection, but the latter their own fine qualities have recommended in addition,
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>I do not know whether to call these young men admirers or unique for their sound
                    judgement. For, as I think, Fortune, scorning base men and wishing to arouse the
                    minds of the good, at the very outset made your nature beautiful, not for a life
                    of pleasure, to be beguiled thereto, but serviceable for a virtuous life, to
                    have happiness therein.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This sentence exhibits
                        rhythmical clausulae and Gorgianic parallelism of structure along with
                        assonance of the vowel e. It is suggested that the Greek version be read
                        aloud.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>Although I have still much to say in praise of you, I think I shall cease my
                    eulogy at this point, fearing that I may seem to plead your cause in terms
                    exceeding human limitations. For so far, as it seems, does the power of words
                    fall short of that of vision that, while none would think of mistrusting the
                    evidence of his eyes, people think the praise of things men say they have seen,
                    even if it falls short of the truth, to be incredible. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>Accordingly, I shall leave this topic and now endeavor to counsel you on the
                    means of rendering your life still more worthy of esteem. To the words I am
                    about to utter I would not have you give heed as to a matter of trivial
                    importance, nor to leap to the conclusion that I have, after all, addressed you
                    thus, not for your good, but from a desire to display my skill; otherwise you
                    may miss the truth and, by choosing haphazard counsel in place of the best, fall
                    short of the best in judging your own interests. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>For we do not reproach men of humble and insignificant natural gifts even when
                    they commit a dishonorable act, but to those who, like yourself, have attained
                    distinction, even a bit of negligence in some matter of high honor brings
                        disgrace.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note on <bibl n="Dem. 61.32"
                            >Dem. 61.32</bibl></note> Again, those who go astray in other domains
                    fail merely t make the best decision in some single, isolated matter, but those
                    who miss the right advice on the conduct of life, or scorn it, have reminders of
                    their own folly to live with their whole life long. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>Now you must not fall into any of these errors but rather seek to discover what
                    is of supreme consequence in human affairs, and what it is that turning out well
                    would do us the most good, but turning out badly would hurt us most along life’s
                    pathway. For it requires no proof that upon this factor we must expend the
                    greatest care, which more than anything else possesses the power to tip the
                    scale to one side or the other. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>Now of the powers residing in human beings we shall find that intelligence leads
                    all the rest and that philosophy alone is capable of educating this rightly and
                    training it. In this study I think you ought to participate, and not balk at or
                    flee from the labors involved in it, reflecting that through idleness and
                    indolence even quite superficial things become difficult, while through
                    persistence and diligence none of the worthwhile things is unattainable, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>and that of all things the most irrational is to be ambitious for wealth, bodily
                    strength, and such things, and for their sakes to submit to many hardships, all
                    of which prizes are perishable and usually slaves to intelligence, but not to
                    aim at the improvement of the mind, which has supervision over all other powers,
                    abides continually with those who possess it, and guides the whole life.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The oldest of the Greek-letter fraternities in
                        the universities of the U.S. (<date when="1776">1776</date>), <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">ΦΒΚ</foreign>, took its name from <foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">φιλοσοφία βίου κυβερνήτης</foreign>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>And yet, although it is a fine thing to be admired among high-minded people even
                    on account of fortuitous success, it is much finer through care bestowed upon
                    one’s self to gain a share in all the accomplishments that are esteemed; for
                    often it has fallen to the lot of vulgar men to share in the former but none
                    have a part in the latter except those who excel in real manliness. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>However, touching the subject of philosophy, some future occasion will afford me
                    more suitable opportunities to review carefully the particulars, but the
                    outlines of it nothing will prevent me from running over at once. This one
                    point, therefore, you must grasp clearly at the outset, that all education
                    consists in understanding something and then putting it into practice,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This idea recurs in <bibl n="Dem. 61.41">Dem.
                            61.41</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 61.47">Dem. 61.47</bibl>.</note> and this
                    is even more true of philosophy than of any other studies, for the synthesis of
                    learning and practice is likely to be more perfect in proportion as the
                    instructors are more clear on this point. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>And yet, since intelligence commands the province of speaking and deliberating,
                    and philosophy confers facility in each of these, what reason can there be why
                    we should refuse to get a firm grasp of this study, through which we shall
                    become masters of both alike? Because life may then too be expected to make a
                    great advance for us when we reach out for the things of supreme importance and
                    find ourselves able to secure by rule and precept such as can be taught and the
                    rest by practice and habituation. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>It certainly is not permissible to make the assertion that it is not through
                    acquired knowledge that we surpass one another in sound judgement; for, speaking
                    generally, all natural ability is improved by the addition of the appropriate
                        education,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass compares <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 15.189">Isoc. 15.189-192</bibl>, with which may be compared in
                        turn <bibl n="Cic. Arch. 7.15">Cicero Pro Archia 7.15</bibl>.</note> and
                    this is especially true of talents which at the outset are inherently superior
                    to the rest, because the one kind is capable only of improving upon itself while
                    the other may also surpass the rest. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>Be well assured also that the facility acquired solely from practical experience
                    is treacherous and useless for subsequent needs of life, but the education
                    secured through the pursuit of philosophy is happily blended in all these needs.
                    There is no denying, of course, that in the past some men who got practical
                    training just by good luck in action have won admiration, but for you the proper
                    thing is to disregard these men and to take yourself seriously in hand. For in
                    matters of the utmost importance you should not be extemporizing instead of
                    really knowing what to do or in emergencies be studying your arguments instead
                    of really knowing how to debate an issue on its merits. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>Be convinced too that all philosophical learning confers precious benefits upon
                    those who take advantage of it, but especially is this true of the knowledge
                    that deals with practical affairs and political discussions. No doubt it is
                    disgraceful to be quite ignorant of geometry and other such subjects of study,
                    but to become a topmost contender in this field is too low an ambition for merit
                    like yours.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass cites <bibl n="Isoc. 15.267"
                            >Isoc. 15.267</bibl>, where the statement is made that cultural studies
                        do not directly prepare the candidate for public life but do increase his
                        power to learn.</note> In that kind of philosophy, however, not only is it a
                    worthy ambition to excel, but to remain ignorant is altogether ridiculous. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>You may infer this to be true on many other grounds and especially by scanning
                    the careers of those who have become eminent before your time. You will hear
                    first that Pericles, who is thought to have far surpassed all men of his age in
                    intellectual grasp, addressed himself to Anaxagoras of Clazomenae and only after
                    being his pupil<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass notes the same
                        information in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.235">Isoc. 15.235</bibl>.</note> acquired
                    this power of judgement. You will next discover that Alcibiades, though his
                    natural disposition was far inferior in respect to virtue and it was his
                    pleasure to behave himself now arrogantly, now obsequiously,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Isocrates employs the same words of Persian satraps, <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 4.152">Isoc. 4.152</bibl>, as Blass notes.</note> now
                    licentiously, yet, as a fruit of his association with Socrates, he made
                    correction of many errors of his life and over the rest drew a veil of oblivion
                    by the greatness of his later achievements. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>But not to spend our time rehearsing ancient examples while others are available
                    closer to our own times,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The phrase <q type="">closer to
                        our own times</q> is defined by the mention of Timotheus, who died in <date
                            when="-0355">355</date> B.C., just after Demosthenes entered public
                        life. The author, whether the orator or a forger, belongs to the second half
                        of the fourth century.</note> you will discover that Timotheus was deemed
                    worthy of the highest repute and numerous honors, not because of his activities
                    as a younger man, but because of his performances after he had studied with
                        Isocrates.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Timotheus, son of Conon, was
                        called by Cornelius Nepos the last Athenian general worthy of mention.
                        Demosthenes regularly spoke of him with admiration.</note> You will discover
                    also that Archytas of Tarentum became ruler of his city and managed its affairs
                    so admirably and so considerately as to spread the record of that achievement to
                    all mankind; yet at first he was despised and he owed his remarkable progress to
                    studying with Plato.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There is a brief life of
                        Archytas which may be consulted in the Loeb translation. It is not known
                        positively that he was a pupil of Plato, but he was his friend: <bibl
                            n="Plat. L. 7.338a">Plat. L. 7.338c,350a</bibl>; <bibl
                            n="Plat. L. 13.360c">Plat. L. 13.360c</bibl>. His adherence was to the
                        school of Pythagoras.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>Of these examples not one worked out contrary to reason<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">With a difference of one word this sentence is found in
                            <bibl n="Isoc. 4.150">Isoc. 4.150</bibl>, as Blass notes. It looks,
                        however, like a commonplace.</note>; for it would be much stranger if we
                    were obliged to achieve paltry ends through acquiring knowledge and putting it
                    into practice, but were capable of accomplishing the big things without this
                    effort.</p>
                <p>Now I do not know what call there is to say more on these topics, for not even at
                    the outset did I introduce them because I assumed you were absolutely ignorant,
                    but because I thought that such exhortations both arouse those who lack
                    knowledge and spur on those who possess it;.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Writings that urged young men to study philosophy formed a distinct
                        literary genre among the ancients under the name <q type="">protreptics.</q> The
                            <title>Epistle to Menoeceus</title> of Epicurus is an extant
                        example.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>And do not make any such assumption as this, that in speaking these words I am
                    presumably offering to teach you any of these branches myself, for I should feel
                    no shame in saying that there is still much I need myself to learn, and that I
                    have chosen rather to be a contender in political life than a teacher of the
                    other arts.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This self-characterization has been
                        thought by some to point to Androtion as the author, but the grounds seem
                        slight to Blass, p. 407 and note 2.</note> Not that in disavowing these
                    subjects of instruction I am impugning the reputation of those who have chosen
                    the profession of sophist, but my reason is that the truth of the matter happens
                    to be as follows: </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>for I am aware, of course, that many men have risen to eminence from humble and
                    obscure estate through the practice of this art, and that Solon, both living and
                    dead, was deemed worthy of the highest renown. He was not disqualified for the
                    other honors<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This statement hints at the long
                        contested question, whether practical statesmanship could be combined with
                        philosophical insight.</note> but left behind him a memorial of his courage
                    in the trophy of victory over the Megarians, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>of his astuteness in the recovery of Salamis, and of general sagacity in the laws
                    which the majority of the Greeks continue using to this day. Yet in spite of
                    these great claims to distinction he set his heart upon nothing as much as
                    becoming one of the Seven Sages,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This statement
                        is absurd. The legend of the Seven Sages became current only in the fourth
                        century: <bibl n="Plat. Prot. 343a">Plat. Prot. 343a</bibl>. In <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 15.235">Isoc. 15.235</bibl> also Solon is called <q type="">one of the
                        seven sophists.</q> Originally this term suggested no disrespect.</note>
                    believing that philosophy was no reproach but that it brought honor to those who
                    pursued it, having been no less wise in this very judgement than in the others
                    in which he showed himself superior. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>My own judgement is not different from Solon’s and I recommend to you to study
                    philosophy, bearing in mind the advantages you have possessed from the
                    beginning. Indeed it was with this purpose in view I ran through the list of
                    them myself in the first part of my essay,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            ><bibl n="Dem. 61.10">Dem. 61.10-32</bibl>.</note> not expecting to make
                    a conquest of you by praising your natural gifts, but that I may the better urge
                    you to take up philosophy if you shall escape the error of putting a low value
                    on it, or, through pride in your present advantages, of under-valuing the
                    advantages yet to be gained. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>Again, even if you are better than the common run of men,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true"><bibl n="Isoc. 9.81">Isoc. 9.81</bibl> begins with similar
                        words, as Blass notes: <q type="">nor must you be content if you are already superiors
                        to those who are here present . . .</q></note> do not seek to be superior in no
                    respect to the talented remainder, but deem it the highest purpose to be first
                    among all, and that it is more to your advantage to be seen striving for this
                    than merely being foremost among the rank and file. And do not bring shame upon
                    your natural gifts or cause to be cheated of their hopes those who are proud of
                    you, but endeavor by your own ability to surpass the desires of those who have
                    your interests most at heart. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>And bear in mind that speeches of the other kinds, when they fulfil their
                    purpose, only crown their authors with glory, but that good counsels attach
                    benefit and honor to those who hearken to them; and that the decisions we make
                    about all other matters make plain the power of perception we possess, but that
                    the choices we make of careers put our whole character to the test. And as you
                    pass judgement in these matters, count upon being judged at the same time
                    yourself by all men, and do not forget that I, who have been so ready to praise
                    you, will also be involved in the hazard of the test. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>The proofs by which you must be judged worthy of my praises must also acquit me
                    of all censure for the friendship I bear you.</p>
                <p>I would not be pressing you so urgently to study philosophy<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Blass notes the occurrence of this sentence in <bibl
                            n="Isoc. 6.87">Isoc. 6.87</bibl>, with <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπὶ
                                τὸν πόλεμον</foreign> instead of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπὶ τὴν
                                    φιλοσοφίαν</foreign>.</note> unless I thought that in this I was making
                    you a most precious contribution as evidence of my goodwill, and unless I
                    observed that our city often makes use of ordinary men for lack of men of the
                    best type, and through their bungling incurs the gravest misfortunes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>So, then, in order that our city may enjoy abilities such as yours and you the
                    honors which these abilities deserve, I have urged you with some vehemence.
                    Neither do I think that it will be in your power to live as chance decrees, but
                    that the City will appoint you to be in charge of some department of her
                    business, and in proportion as your natural gifts are the more conspicuous it
                    will judge you worthy of greater responsibilities and will the sooner desire to
                    make trial of you. The wise plan, therefore is to train your mind that you may
                    not fail when that day comes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now it has been my part to tell you<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Blass notes a similarity in <bibl n="Isoc. 9.80"
                            >Isoc. 9.80</bibl>; seemingly a commonplace of the protreptic
                        genre.</note> what studies I think it is to your advantage to have pursued,
                    but it is yours to decide concerning them. There is an obligation also on the
                    rest, those who seek to be on intimate terms with you, not to be content with
                    superficial pleasures and pastimes, nor to summon you to these, but to consider
                    diligently how they may render your career most brilliant. By so doing they
                    would bring most credit to themselves and become instruments of the greatest
                    service to you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>Neither am I now finding fault with any one of those who keep company with you,
                    for this also seems to me one element of your general good fortune, that you
                    have found no base admirer, but select as friends from the young men of your own
                    age such only as any man would gladly choose. I urge you, however, while being
                    friendly and agreeable to all of these, to heed those of them who have the most
                    sense, so that you may seem even more worthy of respect to this particular group
                    and to the rest of the citizens. Farewell.</p>
            </div>
       
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
