<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>For the People of Megalopolis</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <editor role="translator">J. H. Vince</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">1996</date>
            </publicationStmt> 			
            <notesStmt><note>Perseus 2.0</note></notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes. Vol. I. Olynthiacs, Philippics, Minor Public Speeches, Speech Against Leptines, I-XVII, XX. With an English translation by J. H. Vince</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date type="printing">1930</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.12682">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
            <change when="1992-06-02" who="David Smith">inserted quotedtext tag around verse</change>
        </revisionDesc>    
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>Both sides seem to be in error, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, both those who have spoken in favor of the Arcadians
                    and those who have done the same for the Lacedaemonians; for, just as though
                    they had come from one or other of those states and were not citizens of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to which both embassies
                    are addressed, they are indulging in mutual abuse and recrimination. That,
                    indeed, might be a task for our visitors; but to take a broad view of the
                    question and to explore the best policy, with a regard for your interests and
                    yet without party-spirit, that is the task of men who claim to offer advice in
                    this Assembly. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>As it is, apart from the fact that they were known persons and spoke Attic, I
                    think myself that many would have taken them for Arcadians or Laconians. But I
                    see how difficult it is to recommend the wisest course, because, when you share
                    the delusions of your advisers, some wanting this and others that, anyone who
                    attempts to suggest a middle course and finds you too impatient to be
                    instructed, will please neither party and will be discredited with both. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>All the same, if that is to be my fate, I will choose rather to be charged with
                    talking nonsense than allow you to be misled by certain speakers, contrary to
                    what I judge to be best for the city. Other points I will, with your permission,
                    discuss later, but now, starting from principles admitted by all, I will try to
                    explain what I consider the best policy. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>Now no one would deny that our city is benefited by the weakness of the
                    Lacedaemonians and of the Thebans yonder.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A
                        gesture reminds his hearers how near neighbors the Thebans were.</note> The
                    position of affairs, then, if one may judge from statements repeatedly made in
                    your Assembly, is such that the Thebans will be weakened by the refounding of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011034">Orchomenus</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Plataea"
                        >Plataea</placeName>, but the Lacedaemonians will regain their power, if
                    they get <placeName key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName> into their hands and
                    destroy <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>Our duty, then, is to take care lest the Lacedaemonians grow strong and
                    formidable before the Thebans are weaker, and lest their increase of power
                    should, unperceived by us, out-balance the diminution of the power of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, which our interests demand. For
                    this at least we should never admit, that we would sooner have the
                    Lacedaemonians for our rivals than the Thebans, nor is that our serious aim, but
                    rather to put it out of the power of either to do us harm, for in that way we
                    shall enjoy the most complete security. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>But perhaps we shall admit that that is how matters ought to stand, but feel that
                    it is monstrous to choose as our allies the men whose ranks we faced at
                        <placeName key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName>,<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">The Athenians fought on the left wing of the Lacedaemonians at
                            <placeName key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName> against Thebans,
                        Arcadians and other allies of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName>.</note> and even to help them against those with
                    whom we shared the dangers of that battle. And I too am of that opinion, but I
                    think we must add the saving clause, “if the others consent to do what is just.”
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>If, then, all the powers consent to keep peace, we will not help the
                    Megalopolitans, for it will be unnecessary, so that there will be no question of
                    our opposing our comrades in arms; some of them, indeed, already profess to be
                    our allies, and the others will now come into line. And what more could we
                    desire? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>But if the Lacedaemonians act unjustly and insist on fighting, then, on the one
                    hand, if the only question to be decided is whether we shall abandon <placeName
                        key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName> to them or not, just
                    indeed it is not, but I for my part agree to allow it and to offer no opposition
                    to the people who shared the same dangers with us<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">At <placeName key="perseus,Mantinea"
                        >Mantinea</placeName>.</note>; but, on the other hand, if you are all aware
                    that the capture of <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName>
                    will be followed by an attack on <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
                        >Messene</placeName>, I ask any of those who are now so hard on the
                    Megalopolitans to tell me what he will advise us to do then. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>But I shall get no answer. Yet you all know that, whether these speakers advise
                    it or not, you are bound to help the Messenians, both for the sake of your sworn
                    agreement with them and for the advantage that you derive from the preservation
                    of their city. Just ask yourselves at what point you would begin to make your
                    stand against Lacedaemonian injustice with more honor and generosity—with the
                    defence of <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName> or with
                    the defence of <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>In the one case, you will show yourselves ready to help the Arcadians and eager
                    to confirm the peace for which you faced danger on the field of battle. In the
                    other case, everyone will see clearly that you wish to preserve <placeName
                        key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> less for the sake of justice than
                    for fear of the Lacedaemonians. But the proper course is in all things to find
                    out what is right and then do it, though at the same time we must take care that
                    what we do is expedient as well. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>Now my opponents argue that the recovery of Oropus is something that we ought to
                    attempt, but that if we make enemies of those who would have helped us to
                    recover it, we shall have no allies. I too think that we ought to recover
                    Oropus, but to say that the Lacedaemonians will be our enemies as soon as we
                    make allies of those Arcadians who are willing to be our friends—I think the
                    only men who have no right even to suggest that are the men who persuaded you to
                    help the Lacedaemonians in their hour of danger. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>For when all the Peloponnesians came to you and called on you to lead them
                    against the Lacedaemonians, it was not by such arguments that these men
                    persuaded you not to receive them—(and that was why they took the only remaining
                    course of applying to the Thebans)—but to contribute funds and risk your lives
                    for the safety of the Lacedaemonians. Yet you would surely never have consented
                    to save them, if they had announced to you that when saved they would owe you no
                    thanks for your help, unless you allowed them as before to commit whatever act
                    of injustice they chose. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>Moreover, even if our alliance with the Arcadians is a serious impediment to the
                    designs of the Lacedaemonians, yet surely they ought to be more grateful for the
                    safety that we won for them, when they were in the gravest peril, than angry
                    because of the wrongs that they are now prevented from committing. How, then,
                    can they refuse to help us at Oropus without proving themselves the basest of
                    mankind? By heavens! I see no escape for them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>Then there is another argument that astonishes me; that if we make an alliance
                    with the Arcadians and act upon it, our city will seem to be changing its policy
                    and breaking faith. For to me, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, the exact opposite seems to be the case. How so?
                    Because I do not think any one man would deny that <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> has saved the Lacedaemonians, and
                    the Thebans before them, and the Euboeans recently,<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">The references are to the battle of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName> (362), the alliance with
                            <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> against <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> in 378, and the deliverance of
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> from the Thebans in
                        357.</note> and has afterwards made alliance with them, having always one
                    and the same object in view. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>And what is that? To save the victims of injustice. If, then, this is so, it is
                    not we who are inconsistent, but those who refuse to abide by the principles of
                    justice; and it will be manifest that the circumstances are always changing,
                    through the policy of ambitious men, but our city changes not. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>The policy of the Lacedaemonians seems to me to be very sharp practice. For they
                    now say that <placeName key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName> ought to receive
                    parts of Triphylia, and Phlius the district of Tricaranum, and certain Arcadian
                    tribes the land belonging to them, and that we ought to have Oropus, not because
                    they want to see each of us enjoying our own, far from it—(that would be a tardy
                    exhibition of philanthropy)— </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>but they want it to be generally supposed that they are co-operating with each
                    state to recover the territory that it claims, so that when they march against
                        <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> on their own account,
                    all the others will join heartily in the expedition, or else will put themselves
                    in the wrong by making no adequate return for the support they have enjoyed in
                    regaining what each state claimed as its own. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>But my own impression is that, in the first place, without subjecting any of the
                    Arcadians to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, our city may
                    recover Oropus with the help both of the Lacedaemonians, if they choose to act
                    justly, and of all who think they ought not to let the Thebans keep other
                    people's property. But supposing, on the other hand, it should become clear to
                    us that unless we let the Lacedaemonians subdue the whole of the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>, we shall not be able to take
                    Oropus, then I think it the better policy, if I may say so, to let Oropus go,
                    rather than sacrifice <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> and
                    the rest of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> to the
                    power of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. For I do not think
                    that Oropus would be the only subject of dispute between us, but also—. However,
                    I will pass over what I intended to say; only I fancy there are many dangers
                    ahead of us.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">He seems to contemplate a renewed
                        attempt of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> to establish
                        her supremacy, involving perhaps a second Peloponnesian war. He
                        over-estimates <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>'s power of
                        recovery.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>But further, with regard to any acts which they say the Megalopolitans have
                    committed for the sake of the Thebans somewhat against your interests, it is
                    ridiculous to make these now the count of an indictment, but when they want to
                    become friends and make you some reparation, to look askance at them and devise
                    means of preventing this, and not to realize that the more zealous they show
                    themselves to have been in the cause of the Thebans, the more justly would these
                    very speakers incur your anger, if they deprived the city of such useful allies,
                    when they came to you before applying to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>But these, I take it, are the allegations of men who want once again to drive the
                    Megalopolitans elsewhere for an alliance. Now I know, as far as reasoning and
                    conjecture can teach me, and I think that most of you will agree with me, that
                    if the Lacedaemonians take <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis"
                        >Megalopolis</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
                        >Messene</placeName> will be in danger; and if they take <placeName
                        key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> also, I say that we shall find
                    ourselves in alliance with <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>Surely it is more honorable and satisfactory that we should win the alliance of
                    the Thebans on our own account and resist Spartan ambition, than that we should
                    shrink from rescuing the allies of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName> and abandon them now, only to rescue the Thebans in the
                    end, and to be kept moreover in perpetual alarm for ourselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>For I cannot regard it as a pledge of our security, that the Lacedaemonians
                    should seize <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName> and
                    grow great once more, seeing as I do that even now they have not taken up arms
                    to avenge an injury, but to recover the power that once was theirs; and what
                    their ambition was in the day of their power, you know perhaps better than I,
                    and will distrust them accordingly. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>I should like to ask those speakers who profess hatred of the Thebans and of the
                    Lacedaemonians, whether they hate them in either case for your sake and in your
                    interests, or whether they hate the Thebans for the sake of the Lacedaemonians
                    and the Lacedaemonians for the sake of the Thebans respectively. If the latter,
                    you must not take the advice of either party, because they are both mad; but if
                    they allege your interests, why do they unduly forward the interests of those
                    other states? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>For it is surely possible to humble the Thebans without strengthening the
                    Lacedaemonians; nay, it is much easier. How it can be done, I will try to
                        explain.<milestone unit="para" ed="P"/> Everyone knows this much, that all
                    men, even against their wishes, are, up to a certain point, ashamed not to do
                    what is just, but make a display of opposition to injustice, especially in cases
                    where there are definite victims; and we shall find that what ruins
                    everything—the root in fact of all evil—is unwillingness to act justly under all
                    circumstances. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>In order, then, that this unwillingness may not stand in the way of the weakening
                    of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, let us admit that
                        <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011034">Orchomenus</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName> ought to be restored, and let us
                    co-operate with their inhabitants and appeal to the other states, for it is a
                    just and honorable policy not to allow ancient cities to be uprooted; but at the
                    same time let us not abandon <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis"
                        >Megalopolis</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
                        >Messene</placeName> to their oppressors, nor allow the restoration of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName> to blind us to the destruction of
                    existing and established states. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>Moreover, if we proclaim this policy, there is none but will be glad that the
                    Thebans should cease to hold other people's territory; if we do not, we shall
                    not only find the Thebans, naturally enough, hostile to the other proposal, as
                    soon as they reflect that the restoration of those cities means ruin to
                    themselves, but we shall also involve ourselves in endless trouble; for what
                    limit indeed can there be, if we are always sanctioning the destruction of
                    existing cities, and demanding the restoration of those that are destroyed? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>Now those who seem to argue most fairly demand of the Megalopolitans that they
                    shall destroy the pillars<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The terms of an
                        alliance were inscribed on a slab or pillar, set up in some public place,
                        and to take down the pillar was symbolically to dissolve the alliance (cf.
                            <bibl n="Dem. 20.37">Dem. 20.37</bibl>). The Arcadians are unwilling to
                        risk a complete rupture with the Thebans.</note> that record their treaty
                    with the Thebans, if they are to be our trusted allies. But they reply that with
                    them friendship is based, not on inscribed pillars, but on mutual advantage, and
                    they count as their allies those who are their helpers. But, granting the
                    fairness of these speakers, my own view is this. I say that we must at the same
                    time call upon them to destroy the pillars and upon the Lacedaemonians to keep
                    the peace. If they refuse—whichever of the two it may be—then at once we side
                    with those who consent. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>If the Megalopolitans, though peace is secured for them, still cling to the
                    Theban alliance, it will of course be obvious to all that they prefer the
                    ambition of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> to the claims of
                    justice; or if, while the Megalopolitans join our alliance in all sincerity, the
                    Lacedaemonians refuse to keep the peace, then it will be equally obvious that
                    the object of their activities is not merely to restore <placeName
                        key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName>, but to subjugate the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> while the Thebans are engrossed in
                    the war. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>I am surprised that some of you are afraid of the enemies of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> becoming allies of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, and yet see nothing to fear in
                    their subjugation by the Lacedaemonians, forgetting the practical lesson to be
                    learned from the past, that the Thebans always use these allies against the
                    Lacedaemonians, whereas the Lacedaemonians, when they had them at command, used
                    them against us. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>Then again I think that you must bear this in mind, that if you reject the
                    Megalopolitans and they are overthrown and decentralized,<note anchored="true"
                        resp="Loeb">By destroying their metropolis and compelling them to live in
                        scattered and unwalled villages.</note> the Lacedaemonians can at once be a
                    great power, or if they do escape destruction—for such miracles have happened
                    before now—they are bound to be the staunch friends of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>; but if you accept them as allies,
                        <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName> will indeed owe
                    its immediate deliverance to you, but we must put on one side all calculation of
                    risk, and consider what will be the effect upon our relations with <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
                        >Sparta</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="31">
                <p>Now if the Thebans are finally beaten, as they deserve to be, there will be no
                    undue increase in the power of the Lacedaemonians, because there are their
                    neighbors, the Arcadians, to balance it; but if the Thebans after all recover
                    and are saved, at any rate they will be the weaker because we shall have gained
                    these allies, saved by our help. Therefore it is in every way expedient that the
                    Arcadians should not be abandoned, and that if they do survive, they should not
                    seem to owe their preservation to themselves or to any other people than you.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="32">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I solemnly assure you
                    that I am not prompted by private friendship or enmity for either party, but
                    have said what I consider expedient for you; and I urge you not to abandon the
                    Megalopolitans, and, as a general principle, never to sacrifice the weak to the
                    strong.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
