<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against The Subversion of the Ancestral Constitution from Speeches (English). Machine
          readable text</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="Intro, Narr, Proof" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>At the very moment when we
        were supposing, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that the
        disasters that have befallen her have left behind them sufficient reminders to the city to
        prevent even our descendants from desiring a change of constitution, these men are seeking
        to deceive us, after our grievous sufferings and our experience of both systems, with the
        selfsame decrees with which they have tricked us twice before. <milestone n="2"
          unit="section"/>It is not at them that I wonder, but at you who listen to them, for being
        the most forgetful of mankind, or the readiest to suffer injury from such men as these; who
        shared by mere chance in the operations at the Peiraeus, but whose feelings were with the
        party of the town. What, I ask, was the object of returning from your exile, if by your
        votes you are to enslave yourselves? <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>Now I, men of
          <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, am not debarred on account either of
        means or of birth, but in both respects have the advantage of my opponents; and I consider
        that the only deliverance for the city is to let all Athenians share the citizenship. For
        when we possessed our walls, our ships, and money and allies, far from proposing to exclude
        any Athenian, we actually granted the right of marriage to the Euboeans.<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Normally the marriage tie was only recognized as between
          persons of Athenian birth.</note> Shall we debar today even our existing citizens?
          <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>No, if you will be advised by me; nor, after losing our
        walls, shall we denude ourselves of our forces,—large numbers of our infantry, our cavalry
        and our archers: for, if you hold fast to these, you will make your democracy secure, will
        be more victorious over your enemies, and will be more useful to your allies. You are well
        aware that in the previous oligarchies of our time it was not the possessors of land who
        controlled the city: many of them were put to death, and many were expelled from the city;
          <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>and the people, after recalling them, restored your city
        to you, but did not venture to participate in it themselves. Thus, if you take my advice,
        you will not be depriving your benefactors, so far as you may, of their native land, nor be
        placing more confidence in words than in deeds, in the future than in the past, especially
        if you remember the champions of oligarchy, who in speech make war on the people,<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e., they pretend to be battling with the principle of
          democracy, but are really busy with robbery.</note> but in fact are aiming at your
        property; and this they will acquire when they find you destitute of allies. <milestone
          n="6" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And then they ask us, when such is
        our plight, what deliverance there can be for the city, unless we do as the Lacedaemonians
        demand. But I call upon them to tell us what profit will accrue to the people if we obey
        their orders. If we do not, it will be far nobler to die fighting than to pass a manifest
        sentence of death upon ourselves. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>For I believe that if I
        can persuade you, the danger will be common to both sides<gap reason="lost"/><note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">There is probably a gap here in the text.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"
        />And I observe the same attitude in both the Argives and the Mantineans, each inhabiting
        their own land,—the former bordering on the Lacedaemonians, the latter dwelling near them;
        in the one case, their number is no greater than ours, in the other it is less than three
        thousand. <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>For their enemies know that, often as they may
        invade the territories of these peoples, as often will they march out to oppose them under
        arms, so that they see no glory in the venture: if they should be victorious, they could not
        enslave them, and if they should be defeated, they must deprive themselves of the advantages
        that they already possess. The more they prosper, the less is their appetite for risk.
          <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>We also, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
          >Athens</placeName>, held these views, when we had command over the Greeks; and we deemed
        it a wise course to suffer our land to be ravaged without feeling obliged to fight in its
        defence. For our interest lay in neglecting a few things in order to conserve many
        advantages. But today, when the fortune of battle has deprived us of all these, and our
        native land is all that is left to us, we know that only this venture holds out hopes of our
        deliverance. <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>But surely we ought to remember that
        heretofore, when we have gone to the support of others who were victims of injury, we have
        set up many a trophy over our foes on alien soil, and so ought now to act as valiant
        defenders of our country and of ourselves: let us trust in the gods, and hope that they will
        stand for justice on the side of the injured. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>Strange
        indeed would it be, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, if after
        fighting the Lacedaemonians, in the time of our exile, to achieve our return, we should take
        to flight, when we have returned, to avoid fighting! And will it not be shameful if we sink
        to such a depth of baseness that, whereas our ancestors risked their all merely for the
        freedom of their neighbors, you do not dare even to make war for your own?<gap reason="lost"/>
        <milestone n="Concl" unit="part"/></p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
