<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Pancleon</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="Narr" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To speak at length upon this
        matter, gentlemen of the jury, is both beyond my powers and, to my mind, unnecessary; but
        that I am correct in obtaining leave for my suit against this man Pancleon as being no
        Plataean, I will attempt to prove to you. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>As he continued to injure me for a long time, I went to the fuller’s where he
        was working and summoned him before the Polemarch,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The
          third archon, who had to decide whether proceedings should be taken against an
          alien.</note> supposing him to be a resident alien. On his stating that he was a Plataean,
        I asked to what township he belonged, since one of my witnesses there advised me to summon
        him also before the court of the tribe of which he might pretend to be a member. When he
        replied “to Decelea,” I summoned him before the court of tribe Hippothontis; <milestone
          n="3" unit="section"/>I then went and asked at barber’s in the street of the Hermae,<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">These figures stood in a covered way beside the
          marketplace.</note> where the Deceleans resort, and I inquired of such Deceleans as I
        could discover if they knew a certain Pancleon belonging to the township of Decelea. As
        nobody spoke to knowing him, and I learnt that he was then a defendant in some other suits
        before the Polemarch, and had been cast in some, I took proceedings on my own part.
          <milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>So now, in the first
        place, I will produce to you as witnesses some Deceleans whom I questioned, and after them
        the other persons who have taken proceedings against him before the Polemarch and have
        obtained a conviction,—as many as chance to be present. Please stop the water.<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Which ran from a globe, measuring the time allotted to the
          speaker, and was stopped during the reading or speaking of evidence.</note>
        <label>Witnesses</label> 
        <milestone n="5" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Relying on this evidence I
        took proceedings against him before the Polemarch: but he then put in a demurrer against the
        admissibility of my suit; and as I felt it important to avoid any imputation of oppressive
        aims, instead of a desire to get satisfaction for my wrongs, I first asked Euthycritus, whom
        I knew as the oldest citizen of <placeName key="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName> and
        whom I supposed to be best informed, whether he knew a certain Pancleon, son of
        Hipparmodorus, a Plataean. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>Then, on his answering me that
        he knew Hipparmodorus, but was not aware of his having any son, either Pancleon or any
        other, I went on to ask all the other persons whom I knew as Plataeans. Well, they were all
        ignorant of his name; but they told me that I should get the most definite information if I
        went to the fresh-cheese market on the last day of the month: for on that day in each month
        the Plataeans collected there. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>So I went on that day to the
        cheese market and inquired of the people if they knew a certain Pancleon, their
        fellow-citizen. They all denied knowledge of him, except one who said that, although he knew
        no citizen of that name, there was a slave of his own called Pancleon, who had deserted,
          <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>and he told me his age and his business, which is that of
        this man. To show the truth of all this, I will produce as witnesses Euthycritus whom I
        questioned first, all the other Plataeans to whom I applied, and the man who said he was
        this person’s master. So please stop the water. <label>Witnesses</label>
        <milestone n="9" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then, not many days
        later, I saw this man Pancleon being arrested by Nicomedes, who has testified to being his
        master; and I went up to them, desiring to know what it could be that was going to done with
        him. So, when they had ceased fighting some of his witnesses said that he had a brother who
        would vindicate him as a freeman: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>on this understanding
        they gave security for producing him the morrow, and departed and went their way. On the
        following day, in view of the present demurrer and the suit itself, I decided that I ought
        to appear there with witnesses, in order that I might know the man who was to vindicate him,
        and what plea he would urge for his discharge. Now, as regards the condition on which
        security was taken for his release, neither a brother nor anyone else appeared; but a woman
        asserted that he was her slave, in dispute of Nicomedes’ claim, and she said that she would
        not allow him to be arrested. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>Well, to recount all that
        was spoken in that place would make this a long story; but with such violence did his
        supporters and the man himself behave that, while Nicomedes on his part, and the woman on
        hers, were both willing to let him go if somebody should either vindicate him as a freeman
        or arrest him on the claim of owning him as a slave, they did nothing of the sort, but
        carried him off and departed. Now, to prove that security was taken for him on that
        condition the day before, and that they then carried him off with them by force, I will
        produce to you witnesses. So please stop the water.<label>Witnesses</label> 
        <milestone n="Concl" unit="part"/><milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>It is easy, then, to make sure that even Pancleon himself, far from regarding
        himself as a Plataean, does not suppose himself to be even a freeman. For when a man has
        chosen, on being carried off by force, to make his own associates liable to action for
        assault rather than to be vindicated as a freeman by legal process and to get damages from
        those who were arresting him, nobody can have difficulty in perceiving that he was so
        conscious of his being a slave that he was afraid to provide guarantors and to face a trial
        concerning his civil status. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"
        />Now, that he is far from being a Plataean, I think you perceive pretty clearly from these
        statements; and that even the man himself, who is most fully aware of his own position, did
        not expect you to believe that he was a Plataean, will be readily impressed on you by his
        own conduct. For in his counter-deposition at the proceedings brought against him by
        Aristodicus, here present, when he contended that his case did not lie before the Polemarch,
        he was declared on evidence<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In certain disputes the
          evidence itself sufficed for the decision, unless the convicted person could incriminate
          the witness: the first step to this was a denunciation <foreign xml:lang="greek"
            >e)pi/skhyis</foreign>.</note> not to be a Plataean. <milestone n="14" unit="section"
        />But although he denounced this witness, he did not pursue the matter, but allowed
        Aristodicus to obtain a verdict against him. And when he failed to pay on the appointed
        date, he discharged the debt on such terms as he could arrange. To prove the truth of all
        this, I will produce to you witnesses. So please stop the water. <label>Witnesses</label>
        <milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, before making this
        agreement with him, he had removed from the city through fear of Aristodicus, and was living
        as an alien in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. But I think you
        understand that, if he was a Plataean, he might be expected to live as an alien anywhere
        rather than in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. Well, to prove that he
        lived there a long time, I will produce to you witnesses. So please stop the water. <label>Witnesses</label>
        <milestone n="16" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I consider, gentlemen of
        the jury, that the statements I have made are sufficient. For if you will bear the whole of
        them in mind, I know that you will give the just and true decision, which is all I ask of
        you.</p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
