<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Tyrannicide</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:1lg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1936</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianhar05luciuoft/page/444/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202111?urlappend=%3Bseq=456">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.5.p.445"/>
<head>The Tyrannicide<note xml:lang="eng"><p>This piece and the next are typical productions of the
rhetorical school, where fictitious cases, often highly imaginative and improbable, were debated. The themes were common
property, transmitted from one rhetorician to another. The
one that underlies this declamation, outlined in the argument
which precedes it, was later employed by Libanius (Or. VII)
and still later by Choricius (XXV1). Erasmus, who was the
author of the Latin translation of Tyrannicide and Disowned
in its original form, wrote in Latin a companion-piece to
Tyrannicide, a mock pleading in opposition to it, which is to
be found in several of the old editions of Lucian.
If Lucian abandoned rhetoric at forty, as he says in the
Double Indictment (32: III, 142), both these declamations
should be early works. Of the two, T'yrannicide seems the
earlier, as Disowned more closely approximates the style of his
maturity.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="0"><p>

A man went to the Acropolis to slay the tyrant. He did
not find him, but slew his son and left his sword in the body.
When the tyrant came and saw his son already dead, he
slew himself with the same sword. The man who went up
and slew the tyrant’s son claims the reward for slaying the
tyrant.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>
Two tyrants, gentlemen of the jury,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.5.p.445.n.1"><p>The form of procedure posited is analogous to dokimasia at Athens. The claimant’s right to the reward offered by the state has been challenged by one of his fellow-citizens, and the authorities have referred the question to a jury. The adversary, as plaintiff, has already spoken. </p></note> have been
done to death by me in a single day, one already
past his prime, the other in the ripeness of his years
and in better case to take up wrongdoing in his turn.
Yet I have come to claim but one reward for both,
as the only tyrant-slayer of all time who has done
away with two malefactors at a single blow, killing
the son with the sword and the father by means of
his affection for his son. The tyrant has paid us a
sufficient penalty for what he did, for while he still
lived he saw his son, prematurely slain, in the toils
of death, and at last (a thing incomparably strange)
he himself was constrained to become his own executioner. And his son not only met death at my
hands, but even after death assisted me to slay
another ; for though while he still lived he shared his
father’s crimes, after his death he slew his father as
best he might.


<pb n="v.5.p.447"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
It was I, then, who put an end to the tyranny, and
the sword that accomplished everything was mine.
But I inverted the order of executions, and made an
innovation in the method of putting criminals to
death, for I myself destroyed the stronger, the one
capable of self-defence, and resigned the old man to
my unaided sword.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
It was my thought, therefore, that I should get for
this a still more generous gift from you, and should
receive rewards to match the number of the slain,
because I had freed you not only from your present
ills, but from your expectation of those that were to
come, and had accorded you established liberty,
since no successor in wrongdoing had been left alive.
But now there is danger that after all these achievements I may come away from you unrewarded and
may be the only one to be excluded from the recompense afforded by those laws which I maintained.</p>

<p>
My adversary here seems to me to be taking this
course, not, as he says, because of his concern for the
interests of the state, but because of his grief over
the dead men, and in the endeavour to avenge them
upon the man who caused their death.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
On your
part, however, gentlemen of the jury, bear with me
for a moment while I recount the history of their
tyranny, although you know it well; for then you
can appreciate the greatness of my benefaction and
you yourselves will be more exultant, thinking of
all that you have escaped.
</p>

<p>
It is not as it has often before been with others ;
it is not a simple tyranny and a single slavery that we
have endured, nor a single master’s caprice that we
have borne. Nay, of all those who have ever experienced such adversity we alone had two masters

<pb n="v.5.p.449"/>

instead of one and were torn asunder, unlucky folk!
between two sets of wrongs. The elder man was
more moderate by far, less acrimonious in his fits of
anger, less hasty in his punishments, and less
headlong in his desires, because by now his age was
staying the excessive violence of his impulses and
curbing his appetite for pleasures. It was said,
indeed, that he was reluctantly impelled to begin
his wrongdoings by his son, since he himself was not
at all tyrannical but yielded to the other. For he was
excessively devoted to his children, as he has shown,
and his son was all the world to him; so he gave way
to him, did the wrongs that he bade, punished the
men whom he designated, served him in all things,
and in a word was tyrannised by him, and was mere
minister to his son’s desires.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
The young man conceded the honour to him by
right of age and abstained from the name of sovereignty, but only from that; he was the substance
and the mainspring of the tyranny. He gave the
government its assurance and security, and he alone
reaped the profit of its crimes. It was he who kept
their guardsmen together, who maintained their
defences in strength, who terrorised their subjects and
extirpated conspirators; it was he who plucked lads
from their homes, who made a mockery of marriages;
it was for him that maids were carried off; and whatever deeds of blood there were, whatever banishments, confiscations of property, applications of
torture, and outrages—all these were a young man’s
emprises. The old man followed him and shared his



<pb n="v.5.p.451"/>

wrongdoing, and had but praise for his son’s misdeeds.
So the thing became unendurable to us; for when the
desires of the will acquire the licence of sovereignty,
they recognise no limit to wrongdoing.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
What hurt us most was to know that our slavery
would be long, nay unending, that our city would be
handed down by succession from despot to despot,
and that our folk would be the heritage of villains.
To other peoples it is no slight comfort to think, and
to tell one another, “But it will stop soon,” “But
he will die soon, and in a little while we shall be
free.’ In their case, however, there was no such
comfort; we saw the successor to the sovereignty
already at hand. Therefore not one of the brave
men who entertained the same purpose as myself
even ventured to make an attempt. Liberty was
wholly despaired of, and the tyranny was thought
invincible, because any attempt would be directed
against so many.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
This, however, did not frighten me; I did not
draw back when I estimated the difficulty of the
achievement, nor play the coward in the face of
danger. Alone, alone, I climbed the hill to front the
tyranny that was so strong and many-headed—yet,
not alone but with my sword that shared the fray
with me and in its turn was tyrant-slayer too. I had
my death in prospect, but sought to purchase our
common liberty with the shedding of my own blood.
I met the first guard-post, routed the guardsmen with
no little difficulty, slew whomsoever I encountered,
destroyed whatsoever blocked my path. Then I
assailed the very forefront of my tasks, the sole

<pb n="v.5.p.453"/>

strength of the tyranny, the cause of our calamities.
I came upon the warden of the citadel, I saw him
offer a brave defence and hold out against many
wounds; and yet I slew him.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
The tyranny, therefore, had at last been overthrown, my undertaking had attained fulfilment,
and from that moment we all were free. Only an
old man still remained, unarmed, his guards lost,
that mighty henchman of his gone, deserted, no
longer even worthy of a valiant arm.</p>

<p>
Thereupon, gentlemen of the jury, I thus reasoned
with myself; “All has gone well for me, everything
is accomplished, my success is complete. How shall
the survivor be punished? Of me and my right
hand he is unworthy, particularly if his slaying were
to follow a glorious, daring, valiant deed, dishonouring that other mortal thrust. He must seek a fitting
executioner, a change of fate, and not profit by
having the same one. Let him behold, suffer his
punishment, have the sword lying at hand; I commit
the rest to him.” This plan formed, I myself withdrew, and he, as I had presaged, carried through
with it, slew the tyrant, supplied the ending to my
lay.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
I am here, then, to bring you democracy, to notify
all that they may now take heart, and to herald the
glad tidings of liberty. Even now you are enjoying
the results of my achievements. The acropolis, as
you see, is empty of malefactors, and nobody issues

<pb n="v.5.p.455"/>

orders; you may bestow honours, sit in judgement,
and plead your cases in accordance with the laws.
All this has come about for you through me and my
bold deed, and in consequence of slaying that one
man, after which his father could no longer continue
in life. Therefore I request that you give me the
reward which is my due, not because I am greedy or
avaricious, or because it was my purpose to benefit
my native land for hire, but because I wish that my
achievements should be confirmed by the donative
and that my undertaking should escape misrepresentation and loss of glory on the ground that it
was not fully executed and has been pronounced
unworthy of a reward.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
This man, however, opposes my plea, and says
that I am acting unreasonably in desiring to be
honoured and to receive the gift, since I am not a
tyrant-slayer, and have not accomplished anything in
the eyes of the law; that my achievement is in some
respect insufficient for claiming the reward. I ask
him, therefore: “What more do you demand of me?
Did I not form the purpose? Did I not climb the hill?
DidI not slay? Did I not bring liberty? Does anyone issue orders? Does anyone give commands?
Does any lord and master utter threats? Did any of
the malefactors escape me? Youcannot say so. No,
everything is full of peace, we have all our laws,
liberty is manifest, democracy is made safe, marriages
are free from outrage, boys are free from fear,
maidens are secure, and the city is celebrating its
common good fortune. Who, then, is responsible for
it all? Who stopped all that and caused all this?
If there is anyone who deserves to be honoured in
preference to me, I yield the guerdon, I resign the

<pb n="v.5.p.457"/>

gift. But if I alone accomplished it all, making the
venture, incurring the risks, going up to the citadel,
taking life, inflicting punishment, wreaking vengeance
upon them through one another, why do you misrepresent my achievements? Why, pray, do you
make the people ungrateful towards me?”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
“Because you did not slay the tyrant himself;
and the law bestows the reward upon the slayer of a
tyrant!” Is there any difference, tell me, between
slaying him and causing his death? For my part I
think there is none. All that the lawgiver had
in view was simply liberty, democracy, freedom from
dire ills. He bestowed honour upon this, he considered this worthy of compensation; and you
cannot say that it has come about otherwise than
through me. For if I caused a death which made it
impossible for that man to live, I myself accomplished his slaying. The deed was mine, the hand was
his. Then quibble no longer about the manner of
his end; do not enquire how he died, but whether
he no longer lives, whether his no longer living is
due to me. Otherwise, it seems to me that you
will be likely to carry your enquiry still further, to
the point of carping at your benefactors if one of
them should do the killing with a stone or a staff or
in some other way, and not with a sword.</p>

<p>
What if I had starved the tyrant out of his hold and
thus occasioned the necessity of his death? Would
you in that case require me to have killed him with
my own hand, or say that I failed in any respect of
satisfying the law, even though the malefactor had
been done to death more cruelly? Enquire into one
thing only, demand this alone, disturb yourself about
this alone, whether any one of the villains is left, any

<pb n="v.5.p.459"/>


expectation of fearfulness, any reminder of our woes.
If everything is uncontaminated and peaceful, only
a cheat would wish to utilise the manner of accomplishing what has been done in order to take
away the gratuity for the hard-won results.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
I remember, moreover, this statement in the laws
(unless, by reason of our protracted slavery, I have
forgotten what is said in them), that there are two
sorts of responsibility for manslaughter, and if,
without taking life himself or doing the deed with
his own hand, a man has necessitated and given rise
to the killing, the law requires that in this case
too he himself receive the same punishment—quite
justly, for it was unwilling to be worsted by his
deed through his immunity. It would be irrelevant, therefore, to enquire into the manner of the
killing.</p>

<p>
Can it, then, be that you think fit to punish as a
murderer one who has taken life in this manner, and
are not willing under any circumstances to acquit
him, yet when a man has conferred a boon upon the
city in the same way, you do not propose to hold him
worthy of the same treatment as your benefactors?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
For you cannot even say that I did it at haphazard,
and that a result followed which chanced to be beneficial, without my having intended it. What else did
I fear after the stronger was slain, and why did I
leave the sword in my victim if I did not absolutely
prefigure exactly what would come to pass! You
have no answer, unless you maintain that the dead
man was not a tyrant and did not have that

<pb n="v.5.p.461"/>

name; and that the city would not have been glad
to make many presents on his account if he should
lose his life. But you cannot say so.</p>

<p>
Can it be that, now the tyrant has been slain,
you are going to refuse the reward to the man who
caused his death? What pettiness! Does it concern you how he died, as long as you enjoy your
liberty? Do you demand any greater boon of the
man who gave back your democracy? “But the
law,” you say, “‘scrutinises only the main point
in the facts of the case, ignoring all the incidentals
and raising no further question!” What! was
there not once a man who obtained the guerdon of
a tyrannicide by just driving a tyrant into exile?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.5.p.461.n.1"><p>The allusion is to Harmodius, who slew Hipparchus, the brother of the tyrant Hippias. </p></note>
Quite rightly, too; for he bestowed liberty in
exchange for slavery. But what I have wrought
is not exile, or expectation of a second uprising,
but complete abolition, extinction of the entire
line, extirpation, root and branch, of the whole
menace.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
Do, in the name of the gods, make a full enquiry,
if you like, from beginning to end, and see whether
anything that affects the law has been left undone,
and whether any qualification is wanting that a
tyrant-slayer ought to have. In the first place, one
must have at the outset a will that is valiant, patriotic,
disposed to run risks for the common weal, and ready
to purchase by its own extinction the deliverance of
the people. Then did I fall short of that, play the
weakling, or, my purpose formed, shrink from any
of the risks that lay ahead? You cannot say so.
Then confine your attention for a moment to this


<pb n="v.5.p.463"/>

point, and imagine that simply on account of my
willing and planning all this, even if the result had
not been favourable, I presented myself and demanded that in consequence of the intention itself
I should receive a guerdon as a benefactor. Because I myself had not the power and someone
else, coming after me, had slain the tyrant, would
it be unreasonable, tell me, or absurd to give it
me? Above all, if I said: “Gentlemen, I wanted
it, willed it, undertook it, essayed it; simply for my
intention I deserve to be honoured,” what answer
would you have made in that case?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
But as things are, that is not what I say; no, I
climbed the acropolis, I put myself in peril, I accomplished untold labours before I slew the young
man. For you must not suppose that the affair was
so easy and simple—to pass a guard, to overpower
men-at-arms, to rout so many by myself; no, this
is quite the mightiest obstacle in the slaying of a
tyrant, and the principal of its achievements. For of
course it is not the tyrant himself that is mighty and
impregnable and indomitable, but what guards and
maintains his tyranny; if anyone conquers all this,
he has attained complete success, and what remains
is trivial. Of course the approach to the tyrants
would not have been open to me if I had not overpowered all the guards and henchmen about them,
conquering all these to begin with. I add nothing
further, but once more confine myself to this point:
I overpowered the outposts, conquered the bodyguards, rendered the tyrant unprotected, unarmed,
defenceless. Does it seem to you that I deserve
honour for that, or do you further demand of me the
shedding of his blood?

<pb n="v.5.p.465"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
But even if you require bloodshed, that is not
wanting either, and I am not unstained with blood;
on the contrary, I have done a great and valiant
deed in that I slew a young man in the fullness of
his strength, terrible to all, through whom that
other was unassailed by plots, on whom alone he
relied, who sufficed him instead of many guardsmen.
Then am I not deserving of a reward, man? Am I
to be devoid of honours for such deeds? What if I
had killed a bodyguard, or some henchman of the
tyrant, or a valued slave? Would not even this
have seemed a great thing, to go up and slay one of
the tyrant’s friends in the midst of the citadel, in
the midst of arms? But as it is, look at the slain
man himself! He was a tyrant’s son, nay more, a
harsher tyrant, an inexorable despot, a more cruel
chastiser, a more violent oppressor; what is most
important, he was heir and successor to everything,
and capable of prolonging vastly the duration of our
misery.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
Suppose, if you will, that this was my sole achievement—that the tyrant has made his escape and is
still alive. Well and good, I demand a guerdon for
this. What do you all say? Will you not vouchsafe it? Did you not view the son, too, with
concern? Was he notadespot? Was he not cruel,
unendurable?</p>

<p>
As it is, however, think of the crowning feat itself.
What this man requires of me I accomplished in the
best possible way. I killed the tyrant by killing
someone else, not directly nor at a single blow, which
would have been his fondest prayer after misdeeds
so monstrous. No, first I tortured him with profound
grief, displayed full in his view. all that was dearest


<pb n="v.5.p.467"/>

to him lying exposed in pitiable case, a son in his
youth, wicked, to be sure, but in the fullness of his
strength and the image of his sire, befouled with
blocd and gore. Those are the wounds of fathers,
those the swords of tyrannicides who deal justly,
that is the death deserved by savage tyrants, that
the requital befitting misdeeds so great. To die
forthwith, to know nothing, to see no such spectacle
has in it nothing worthy of a tyrant’s punishment.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>
For I was not unaware, man—I was not unaware, nor was anyone else, how much love he had for
his son, and that he would not have wanted to outlive
him even a little while. To be sure, all fathers no
doubt have such feelings toward their children;
‘but in his case there was something more than in the
case of others; naturally, for he discerned that it
was his son who alone cherished and guarded the
tyranny, who alone faced danger in his father’s
stead, and gave security to his rule. Consequently
I knew that he would lay down his life at once, if
not through his love, then at all events through his
despair, considering that there was no profit in life
now that the security derived from his son had been
abolished. I encompassed him, therefore, with all
manner of toils at once—his nature, his grief, his
despair, his misgivings about the future; I used
these allies against him, and forced him to that final
decision. He has gone to his death childless, griefstricken, in sorrow and in tears, after mourning but
a little while, it is true, yet long enough for a
father; gone (and that is most horrible) by his own


<pb n="v.5.p.469"/>

hand, the most pitiable of deaths, far more bitter
than as if it should come about at the hand of
another.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
Where is my sword? Does anyone else recognise
this? Was this any other man’s weapon? Who
carried it up to the citadel? Who preceded the
tyrant in its use? Who commissioned it against
him? Good sword, partner and promoter of my
successes, after so many perils, after so many slayings,
we are disregarded and thought unworthy of a reward! If it were for the sword alone that I sought
the meed of honour trom you—if I were pleading:
“Gentlemen, when the tyrant wished to die and
at the moment found himself unarmed, this sword of
mine served him and did its part in every way
towards the attainment of liberty—account it worthy
of honour and reward,” would you not have requited
the owner of a possession so valuable to the state?
Would you not have recorded him among your benefactors? Would you not have enshrined the sword
among your hallowed treasures? Would you not
have worshipped it along with the gods?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
Now then, imagine, I beg you, what the tyrant
no doubt did and what he said before his end. When
I sought to slay the son and wounded him again
and again in those parts of his body which could be
seen, that so I might grieve the parent most, that
so I might rend his heart through the first sight, he
raised a doleful cry, calling his parent to him, not to
aid him or share the conflict—for he knew him to
be old and weak—but to behold his own calamities.
Before I slipped away, I had myself composed the


<pb n="v.5.p.471"/>

whole plot of the tragedy, but had left to the actor the
body, the stage-setting, the sword, and the remainder
of the play. When the other made his appearance
and saw his only son with but little breath in him,
bloodied, covered with gore, his wounds close
together, numerous, and vital, he raised this cry:
“My child, we are destroyed, assassinated, fallen
victims to the tyrant-slayer! Where is the executioner? For what purpose is he keeping me, for
what purpose reserving me, now that I am already
destroyed through you, my child? Or is it perhaps
that he contemns me as an old man, and also by his
dilatoriness (since I must be punished) protracts my
death and makes my execution longer?”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
With these words he sought a sword; for he was
unarmed on account of his complete reliance upon
his son. But that too was not wanting; long
beforehand, that too had been provided by me and
left behind for the bold deed that was to come.
So, withdrawing the sword from the victim, plucking
it from the wound, he said: “A little while ago you
gave me death; now give me repose, Osword. Come
to console a mourning father; lighten the task of an
aged hand beset by adversity; let my blood; be
tyrant-slayer to me; quit me of my woe. Had I
but encountered you first! had I but inverted the
order of deaths! I should have perished; but
simply as tyrant—but thinking still that I should
have an avenger, while now I die as one who is
childless, as one who can hardly so much as find a
man to take his life!” Thereupon he hastened his
despatch, trembling, incapable, craving it, to be
sure, but lacking the strength to serve his bold
purpose.

<pb n="v.5.p.473"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg051.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
How many punishments were there in all this?
How many wounds? How many deaths? How
many tyrant-slayings? How many rewards? And
at the end you have all seen not only the young
man exposed in death (no slight accomplishment or
easy to achieve), but the old man prostrate upon
him, you have seen the blood of both intermingled
(that thank-offering for liberty and for victory),
and the havoc of my sword; aye, the sword itself
between them both, evincing that it has not been
unworthy of its owner and testifying that it served me
faithfully. Had this been done by me, it would be
less of an achievement ; but now it is more splendid
by reason of its novelty. It is I, to be sure, who
overthrew the entire tyranny; but the performance
has been distributed among many people as in a
play; the leading part was played by me, the second
by the son, the third by the tyrant himself, and the
sword served all.

</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>

