<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The First Epistle of Clement to the Corinthians</title>
        <author>Clement of Rome</author>
        <editor role="translator">Kirsopp Lake</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
          <funder n="org:Tufts">Tufts University</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <date type="release">2019</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Clement of Rome</author>
            <title>The Apostolic Fathers with an English translation by Kirsopp Lake. In Two Volumes. Vol. I.</title>
            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date type="printing">1912</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
            <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.232411">Internet Archive</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation marks="none"/>
          <correction method="silent" status="medium"><p>Perseus OCR in house AbbyyFR; single pass proofreading</p></correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-03-18" who="Lisa Cerrato">basic structural markup and single pass editing</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text xml:lang="eng">
		<body>
		  <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg1271.tlg001.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
		      <pb xml:id="p.9"/>
<head>THE FIRST EPISTLE OF CLEMENT TO THE CORINTHIANS</head>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="pref">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="sal"><p>The Church of God which sojourns in Rome to the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Salutation.</note> Church of God which sojourns in Corinth, to those who are called and sanctified by the will of God through our Lord Jesus Christ. Grace and peace from God Almighty be multiplied to you through Jesus Christ.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Owing to the sudden and repeated misfortunes<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Reason for delay in writing</note> and calamities<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or, with Knopf’s text <q type="translation">critical circumstances.</q></note> which have befallen us, we consider that our attention has been somewhat delayed in turning to the questions disputed among you, beloved, and especially the abominable and unholy sedition, alien and foreign to the elect of God, which a few rash and self-willed persons have made blaze up to such a frenzy that your name, venerable and famous, and worthy as it is of all men’s love, has been much slandered.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For who has stayed with you without making<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The ancient fame of Corinth</note> proof of the virtue and stedfastness of your faith? Who has not admired the sobriety and Christian gentleness of your piety? Who has not reported your character so magnificent in its hospitality? And who has not blessed your perfect and secure <pb xml:id="p.11"/> knowledge?</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For you did all things without respect of persons, and walked in the laws of God, obedient to your rulers, and paying all fitting honour to the older among you. On the young, too, you enjoined temperate and seemly thoughts, and to the women you gave instruction that they should do all things with a blameless and seemly and pure conscience, yielding a dutiful affection to their husbands. And you taught them to remain in the rule of obedience and to manage their households with seemliness, in all circumspection.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And you were all humble-minded and in no wise arrogant, yielding subjection rather than demanding it, <q>giving more gladly than receiving,</q> satisfied with the provision of Christ, and paying attention to his words you stored them up carefully in your hearts, and kept his sufferings before your eyes.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Thus a profound and rich peace was given to all, you had an insatiable desire to do good, and the Holy Spirit was poured out in abundance on you all.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>You were full of holy plans, and with pious confidence you stretched out your hands to Almighty God in a passion of goodness, beseeching him to be merciful towards any unwilling sin.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Day and night you strove on behalf of the whole brotherhood <pb xml:id="p.13"/> that the number of his elect should be saved with mercy and compassion.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The MS. reading means <q>conscience,</q> which gives no sense. There is also a variant in the previous word: the inferior MS. (C) reads <q>fear</q> instead of <q>mercy.</q></note></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>You were sincere and innocent, and bore no malice to one another.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>All sedition and all schism was abominable to you. You mourned over the transgressions of your neighbours; you judged their shortcomings as your own.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>You were without regret in every act of kindness, <q>ready unto every good work.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>You were adorned by your virtuous and honourable citizenship and did all things in the fear of God.<note resp="editor" type="footnote"><q>God</q> is found only in L; the other authorities have <q>his fear,</q> but the meaning is plain.</note> The commandments and ordinances of the Lord were <q>written on the tables of your heart.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">All glory and enlargement was given to you,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The troubles at Corinth</note> and that which was written was fulfilled, <q>My Beloved ate and drank, and he was enlarged and waxed fat and kicked.</q></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>From this arose jealousy and envy, strife and sedition, persecution and disorder, war and captivity.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Thus <q>the worthless</q> rose up <q>against those who were in honour,</q> those of no reputation against the renowned, the foolish against the prudent, the <q>young against the old.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For this cause righteousness and peace are far removed, while each deserts the fear of God and the eye of faith in him has grown dim, and men walk neither in the ordinances of his commandments nor <pb xml:id="p.15"/> use their citizenship worthily of Christ, but each goes according to the lusts of his wicked heart, and has revived the unrighteousness and impious envy, by which also <q>death came into the world.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">For it is written thus:—<q>And it came to pass<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Examples of jealousy. Cain and Abel</note> after certain days that Cain offered to God a sacrifice of the fruits of the earth, and Abel himself also offered of the first-born of the sheep and of their fat.</q></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><q rend="merge">And God looked on Abel and his gifts, but he had no respect to Cain and his sacrifices.</q></p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q rend="merge">And Cain was greatly grieved and his countenance fell.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">And God said to Cain, Why art thou grieved, and why is thy countenance fallen? If thou offeredst rightly, but didst not divide rightly, didst thou not sin?<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This is unintelligible, and does not agree with the Hebrew, which is also unintelligible. It is dealt with at length in all commentaries on Genesis.</note></q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">Be still: he shall turn to thee, and thou shalt rule over him.</q></p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">And Cain said to Abel his brother, Let us go unto the plain. And it came to pass that, while they were in the plain, Cain rose up against Abel his brother and slew him.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>You see, brethren,—jealousy and envy wrought fratricide.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>Through jealousy our father Jacob ran from the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Jacob and Esau</note> face of Esau his brother.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>Jealousy made Joseph<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Joseph</note> to be persecuted to the death, and come into slavery.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p>Jealousy forced Moses to fly from the face of<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Moses</note> Pharaoh, King of Egypt, when his fellow countryman <pb xml:id="p.17"/> said to him, <q>Who made thee a judge or a ruler over us? Wouldest thou slay me as thou didst slay the Egyptian yesterday?</q></p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p>Through<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Aaron and Miriam</note> jealousy Aaron and Miriam were lodged outside the camp.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p>Jealousy brought down Dathan and<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Dathan and Abiram</note> Abiram alive into Hades, because they rebelled against Moses the servant of God.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p>Through jealousy David incurred envy not only from<note resp="editor" type="marginal">David</note> strangers, but suffered persecution even from Saul, King of Israel.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But, to cease from the examples of old time, let<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Peter and Paul</note> us come to those who contended in the days nearest to us; let us take the noble examples of our own generation.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Through jealousy and envy the greatest and most righteous pillars of the Church were persecuted and contended unto death.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us set before our eyes the good apostles: </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Peter, who because of unrighteous jealousy suffered not one or two but many trials, and having thus given his testimony went to the glorious place which was his due.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Through jealousy and strife Paul showred the way to the prize of endurance;	</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>seven	times	he was in bonds, he was exiled, he was stoned, he was a herald both in the East and in the West, he gained the noble fame of his faith, </p></div>
	<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>he taught righteousness to all the world, and when he had reached the limits of the West he gave his testimony before the rulers, and thus passed from the world and was taken up into the Holy Place,—the greatest example of endurance.</p></div></div>

<pb xml:id="p.19"/>
		      
    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">To these men with their holy lives was gathered<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The Christian martyrs</note> a great multitude of the chosen, who were the: victims of jealousy and offered among us the fairest example in their endurance under many indignities and tortures.</p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Through jealousy women were persecuted as Danaids and Dircae,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">No satisfactory interpretation has ever been given of this phrase: either it refers to theatrical representations by condemned Christians, or the text is hopelessly corrupt.</note> suffering terrible and unholy indignities; they stedfastly finished the course of faith, and received a noble reward, weak in the body though they were.</p></div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Jealousy has estranged wives from husbands, and made of no effect the saying of our father Adam, <q>This is now bone of my bone and flesh of my flesh.</q></p></div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Jealousy and strife have overthrown great cities, and rooted up mighty nations.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">We are not only writing these things to you,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Instances of repentance</note> beloved, for your admonition, but also to remind ourselves; for we are in the same arena, and the same struggle is before us.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Wherefore let us put aside empty and vain cares, and let us come to the glorious and venerable rule of our tradition, </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>and let us see what is good and pleasing and acceptable in the sight of our Maker.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Let us fix our gaze on the Blood of Christ, and let us <pb xml:id="p.21"/> know that it is precious to his Father,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The Greek MSS. insert <q>his God,</q> but in different places, and the evidence of the versions confirms Lightfoot’s view that the words are interpolated.</note> because it was poured out for our salvation, and brought the grace of repentance to all the world. </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Let us review all the generations, and let us learn that in generation after generation the Master has given a place of repentance to those who will turn to him.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Noah preached repentance and those who obeyed<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Noah</note> were saved.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Jonah foretold destruction to the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Jonah and the Ninevites</note> men of Nineveh, but when they repented they received forgiveness of their sins from God in answer to their prayer, and gained salvation, though they were aliens to God.</p></div></div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">The ministers of the grace of God spoke<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Repentance in the Prophets</note> through the Holy Spirit concerning repentance, </p></div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>and even the Master of the universe himself spoke with an oath concerning repentance; <q>For as I live, said the Lord, I do not desire the death of the sinner so much as his repentance,</q> and he added a gracious declaration, </p></div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q>Repent, O house of Israel, from your iniquity. Say to the sons of my people. If your sins reach from the earth to Heaven, and if they be redder than scarlet, and blacker than sackcloth, and ye turn to me with all your hearts and say ‘Father,’ I will listen to you as a holy people.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">The origin of this quotation is obscure: possibly Clement’s text of Ezekiel was different from ours and really contained it.</note></p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And in another place he speaks thus, <q>Wash <pb xml:id="p.23"/> you, and make you clean, put away your wickedness from your souls before my eyes, cease from your wickedness, learn to do good, seek out judgment, rescue the wronged, give judgment for the orphan, do justice to the widow, and come and let us reason together, saith the Lord; and if your sins be as crimson, I will make them white as snow, and if they be as scarlet, I will make them white as wool, and if ye be willing and hearken to me, ye shall eat the good things of the land, but if ye be not willing, and hearken not to me, a sword shall devour you, for the mouth of the Lord has spoken these things.</q></p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Thus desiring to give to all his beloved a share in repentance, he established it by his Almighty will.</p></div></div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p>Wherefore let us obey his excellent and glorious will; let us fall before him as suppliants of <note resp="editor" type="marginal">Examples of obedience</note>his mercy and goodness; let us turn to his pity, and abandon the vain toil and strife and jealousy which leads to death.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let us fix our gaze on those who have rendered perfect service to his excellent glory.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us take Enoch, who was<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Enoch</note> found righteous in obedience, and was translated, and death did not befall him.</p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Noah was found<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Noah</note> faithful in his service, in foretelling a new beginning to the world, and through him the Master saved the living creatures which entered in concord into the Ark.</p></div></div>

<pb xml:id="p.25"/>

 <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p>Abraham, who was called <q>the Friend</q>, was<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Abraham</note> found faithful in his obedience to the words of God.</p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>He in obedience went forth from his country and from his kindred and from his father’s house, that by leaving behind a little country and a feeble kindred and a small house he might inherit the promises of God. For God says to him, </p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q>Depart from thy land and from thy kindred and from thy father’s house to the land which I shall show thee, and I will make thee a great nation, and I will bless thee, and I will magnify thy name, and thou shalt be blessed; and I will bless those that bless thee, and I will curse those that curse thee, and all the tribes of the earth shall be blessed in thee.</q></p></div> 
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And again, when he was separated from Lot, God said to him, <q>Lift up thine eyes and look from the place where thou art now, to the North and to the South and to the East and to the West; for all the land which thou seest, to thee will I give it and to thy seed for ever.</q></p></div> 
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">And I will make thy seed as the dust of the earth. If a man can number the dust of the earth thy seed shall also be numbered.</q></p></div> 
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>And again he says, <q>God led forth Abraham, and said to him, ‘Look up to the Heaven and number the stars, if thou canst number them; so shall thy seed be.’ And Abraham believed God, and it was counted unto him for righteousness.</q></p></div> 
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Because of his faith and hospitality a son was given him in <pb xml:id="p.27"/> his old age, and in his obedience he offered him as a sacrifice to God on the mountain<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or possibly, with the other reading, <q>on one of the mountains.</q></note> which he showed him.</p></div></div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p>For his hospitality and piety Lot was saved out<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Lot</note> of Sodom when the whole countryside was judged by fire and brimstone, and the Master made clear that he does not forsake those who hope in him, but delivers to punishment and torture those who turn aside to others.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For of this a sign was given<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Lot’s wife</note> when his wife went with him, but changed her mind and did not remain in agreement with him, so that she became a pillar of salt unto this day, to make known to all, that those who are double-minded, and have doubts concerning the power of God, incur judgment and become a warning to all generations.</p></div></div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p>For her faith and hospitality Rahab the harlot<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or possibly <q>who was called a harlot,</q></note><note resp="editor" type="marginal">Rahab</note> was saved.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For when the spies were sent to Jericho by Joshua the son of Nun, the King of the land knew that they had come to spy out his country, and sent men to take them, that they might be captured and put to death.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>So the hospitable Rahab took them in, and hid them in the upper room under the stalks of flax.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And when the <pb xml:id="p.29"/> king’s men came and said, <q>The spies of our land came in to thee, bring them out, for the king orders thus,</q> she answered <q>The men whom ye seek did indeed come to me, but they went away forthwith, and are proceeding on their journey,</q> and pointed in the wrong direction.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And she said to the men, <q>I know assuredly that the Lord God is delivering to you this land; for the fear and dread of you has fallen on those who dwell in it. When therefore it shall come to pass, that ye take it, save me and my father’s house.</q></p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>And they said to her, <q>It shall be as thou hast spoken to us; when therefore thou knowest that we are at hand, thou shalt gather all thy folk under thy roof, and they shall be safe; for as many as shall be found outside the house shall perish.</q></p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>And they proceeded to give her a sign, that she should hang out a scarlet thread from her house, foreshowing that all who believe and hope on God shall have redemption through the blood of the Lord.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>You see, beloved, that the woman is an instance not only of faith but also of prophecy.</p></div></div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p>Let us, therefore, be humble-minded, brethren,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The need of humble-mindedness</note> putting aside all arrogance and conceit and foolishness and wrath, and let us do that which is written (for the Holy Spirit says, <q>Let not the wise man boast himself in his wisdom, nor the strong man in his strength, nor the rich man in his riches, but he <pb xml:id="p.31"/> that boasteth let him boast in the Lord, to seek him out and to do judgment and righteousness</q>), especially remembering the words of the Lord Jesus which he spoke when he was teaching gentleness and longsuffering.</p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For lie spoke thus: <q>Be merciful, that ye may obtain mercy. Forgive, that ye may be forgiven. As ye do, so shall it be done unto you. As ye give, so shall it be given unto you. As ye judge, so shall ye be judged. As ye are kind, so shall kindness be shewn you. With wliat measure ye mete, it shall be measured to you.</q></p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>With this commandment and with these injunctions let us strengthen ourselves to walk in obedience to his hallowed words and let us be humble-minded, for the holy word says, </p></div> 
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q>On whom shall I look, but on the meek and gentle and him who trembles at my oracles.</q></p></div></div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p>Therefore it is right and holy, my brethren,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Obedience to God, and abstinence from sedition.</note> for us to obey God rather than to follow those who in pride and unruliness are the instigators of an abominable jealousy.</p></div> 
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For we shall incur no common harm, but great danger, if we rashly yield ourselves to the purposes of men who rush into strife and sedition, to estrange us from what is right.</p></div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us be kind to one another, according to the compassion and sweetness of our Maker.</p></div> 
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For it is written, <q>The kind shall inhabit the land, and the guiltless shall be left on it, but they who transgress shall be destroyed from off it.</q></p></div>
<pb xml:id="p.33"/>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And again he says: <q>I saw the ungodly lifted high, and exalted as the cedars of Lebanon. And I went by, and behold he was not; and I sought his place, and I found it not. Keep innocence, and look on uprightness; for there is a remnant for a peaceable man.</q></p></div></div>

        <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p>Moreover let us cleave to those whose<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Cleaving to the peaceable</note> peacefulness is based on piety and not to those whose wish for peace is hypocrisy. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For it says in one place: <q>This people honoureth me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And again, <q>They blessed with their mouth, but cursed in their hearts.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And again it says <q>they loved him with their mouth, and they lied unto him with their tongue, and their heart was not right with him, nor were they faithful in his covenant.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Therefore <q>let the deceitful lips be dumb which speak iniquity against the righteous.</q> And again, <q>May the Lord destroy all the deceitful lips, a tongue that speaketh great things, those who say. Let us magnify our tongue, our lips are our own, who is lord over us?</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">For the misery of the poor and groaning of the needy, now will I arise, saith the Lord, I will place him in safety, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p><q rend="merge">I will deal boldly with him.</q></p></div></div>
<pb xml:id="p.35"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">For Christ is of those who are humble-minded,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The humility of Christ</note> not of those who exalt themselves over His flock.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>The sceptre of the greatness of God, the Lord Jesus Christ, came not with the pomp of pride or of arrogance, for all his power, but was humble-minded, as the Holy Spirit spake concerning him. For it says, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q>Lord, who has believed our report, and to whom was the arm of the Lord revealed? We declared him before the Lord as a child, as a root in thirsty ground; there is no form in him, nor glory, and we saw him, and he had neither form nor beauty, but his form was without honour, less than the form of man, a man living among stripes and toil, and acquainted with the endurance of weakness; for his face was turned away, he was dishonoured, and not esteemed.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">He it is who beareth our sins, and is pained for us, and we regarded him as subject to pain, and stripes and affliction,</q> </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">but he was wounded for our sins and he has suffered for our iniquities. The chastisement of our peace was upon him; with his bruises were we healed.</q> </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">All we like sheep went astray, each man went astray in his path;</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p><q rend="merge">and the Lord delivered him up for our sins, and he openeth not his mouth because of his affliction. As a sheep he was brought to the slaughter, and as a lamb dumb before its shearer, so he openeth not his mouth. In humiliation his judgment was taken away.</q> </p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p><q rend="merge">Who shall declare <pb xml:id="p.37"/> his generation? For his life is taken away from the earth.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p><q rend="merge">For the iniquities of my people is he come to death.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p><q rend="merge">And I will give the wicked for his burial, and the rich for his death; for he wrought no iniquity, nor was guile found in his mouth. And the Lord’s will is to purify him from stripes.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p><q rend="merge">If ye make an offering for sin, your soul shall see a long-lived seed.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p><q rend="merge">And the Lord’s will is to take of the toil of his soul, to show him light and to form him with understanding, to justify a righteous man who serveth many well. And he himself shall bear their sins.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p><q rend="merge">For this reason shall he inherit many, and he shall share the spoils of the strong; because his soul was delivered to death, and he was reckoned among the transgressors.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"><p><q rend="merge">And he bore the sins of many, and for their sins was he delivered up.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15"><p>And again he says himself, <q>But I am a worm and no man, a reproach of men, and despised of the people.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16"><p><q rend="merge">All they who saw me mocked me, they spoke with their .lips, they shook their heads; He hoped on the Lord, let him deliver him, let him save him, for he hath pleasure in him.</q></p></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17"><p>You see. Beloved, what is the example which is given to us; for if the Lord was thus humble-minded, what shall we do, who through him have come under the yoke of his grace?</p></div></div>

<pb xml:id="p.39"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us also be imitators of those who went<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Humility in the Old Testament</note> about <q>in the skins of goats and sheep,</q> heralding the coming of Christ; we mean Elijah and Elisha, and moreover Ezekiel, the prophets, and in addition to them the famous men of old.</p></div>
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Great fame was given to Abraham, and he was called the Friend of God,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Abraham</note> and he, fixing his gaze in humility on the Glory of God, says <q>But I am dust and ashes.</q></p></div>
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Moreover it is also written thus concerning Job:—<q>Now Job<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Job</note> was righteous and blameless, true, a worshipper of God, and kept himself from all evil.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>But he accuses himself, saying, <q>No man is clean from defilement, not even if his life be but for a single day.</q></p></div>
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Moses was called <q>Faithful with all his<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Noah</note> house,</q> and through his ministry God judged Egypt with their scourges and tormen ts; but he, though he was given great glory, did not use great words, but, when an oracle was given to him from the bush, said:—<q>Who am I that thou sendest me? Nay, I am a man of feeble speech, and a slow tongue.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>And again he says, <q>But I am as smoke from a pot.</q></p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But what shall we say of the famous David?<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The humility of David</note> Of him said God, <q>I have found a man after my own heart, David the son of Jesse, I have anointed him with eternal mercy;</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>but he too says to God <q>Have mercy upon me, O God, according to thy <pb xml:id="p.41"/> great mercy, and according to the multitude of thy compassions, blot out my transgression.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q rend="merge">Wash me yet more from mine iniquity, and cleanse me from my sin; for I know my iniquity, and my sin is ever before me.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">Against thee only did I sin, and did evil before thee, that thou mightest be justified in thy words, and mightest overcome when thou art judged.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">For, lo, I was conceived in iniquity, and in sin did my mother bear me.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">For, behold, thou hast loved truth, thou didst make plain to me the secret and hidden things of thy wisdom.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p><q rend="merge">Thou shalt sprinkle me with hyssop, and I shall be cleansed; tliou shalt wash me, and I shall be whiter than snow.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p><q rend="merge">Thou shalt make me hear joy and gladness; the bones which have been humbled shall rejoice.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p><q rend="merge">Turn thy face from my sins, and blot out all mine iniquities.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p><q rend="merge">Create a clean heart in me, O God, and renew a right spirit in my inmost parts.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p><q rend="merge">Cast me not away from thy presence, and take not thy Holy Spirit from me.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p><q rend="merge">Give me back the gladness of thy salvation, strengthen me with thy governing spirit.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p><q rend="merge">I will teach the wicked thy ways, and the ungodly shall be converted unto thee.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"><p><q rend="merge">Deliver me from blood-guiltiness, O God, the God of my salvation.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15"><p><q rend="merge">My tongue shall rejoice in thy righteousness. O Lord, thou shalt open my mouth, and my lips shall tell of thy praise.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16"><p><q rend="merge">For if thou hadst desired sacrifice, I would have given it; in whole burnt offerings thou wilt not delight.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17"><p><q rend="merge">The sacrifice unto God is a broken spirit, a broken and a humbled heart God shall not despise.</q></p></div></div>

<pb xml:id="p.43"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">The humility and obedient submission of so<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to peace</note> many men of such great fame, have rendered better not only us, but also the generations before us, who received his oracles in fear and truth.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Seeing then that we have received a share in many great and glorious deeds, let us hasten on to the goal of peace, which was given us from the beginning, and let us fix our gaze on the Father and Creator of the whole world and cleave to his splendid and excellent gifts of peace, and to his good deeds to us.</p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us contemplate him with our mind, let us gaze with the eyes of our soul on his long-suffering purpose, let us consider how free from wrath he is towards all his creatures.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">The heavens moving at his appointment are<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The peace and harmony of the Universe</note> subject to him in peace;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>day and night follow the course allotted by him without hindering each other.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Sun and moon and the companies of the stars roll on, according to his direction, in harmony, in their appointed courses, and swerve not from them at all.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>The earth teems according to his will at its proper seasons, and puts forth food in full abundance for men and beasts and all the living things that are on it, with no dissension, and changing <pb xml:id="p.45"/> none of his decrees.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>The unsearchable places of the abysses and the unfathomable realms of the lower world are controlled by the same ordinances.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>The hollow of the boundless sea is gathered by his working into its allotted places, and does not pass the barriers placed around it, but does even as he enjoined on it;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>for he said <q>Thus far shalt thou come, and thy waves shall be broken within thee.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>The ocean, which men cannot pass, and the worlds beyond it, are ruled by the same injunctions of the Master.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>The seasons of spring, summer, autumn, and winter give place to one another in peace.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p>The stations of the winds fulfil their service without hindrance at the proper time. The everlasting springs, created for enjoyment and health, supply sustenance for the life of man without fail; and the smallest of animals meet together in concord and peace.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p>All these things did the great Creator and Master of the universe ordain to be in peace and concord, and to all things does he do good, and more especially to us who have fled for refuge to his mercies through our Lord Jesus Christ,</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p>to whom<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The Latin has <foreign xml:id="lat">per quem deo et patri</foreign>, <q>through whom to God and the Father.</q></note> be the glory and the majesty for even and ever. Amen.</p></div></div>
<pb xml:id="p.47"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="21">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Take heed, beloved, lest his many good works<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Christian values</note> towards us become a judgment on us, if we do not good and virtuous deeds before him in concord, and be citizens worthy of him.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For he says in one place:—<q>The Spirit of the Lord is a lamp searching the inward parts.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let	us	observe	how near he is, and that nothing escapes him of oui thoughts or of the devices which we make.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>It is right, therefore, that we should not be deserters from his will.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Let us offend foolish and thoughtless men, who are exalted and boast in the pride of their words, rather than God.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Let us reverence the Lord Jesus Christ, whose blood was given for us, let us respect those who rule us, let us honour the aged,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or possibly <q>the Presbyters,</q> but the context makes this improbable.</note> let us instruct the young in the fear of God, let us lead our wives to that which is good.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Let them exhibit the lovely habit of purity, let them show forth the innocent will of meekness, let them make the gentleness of their tongue manifest by their silence, let them not give their affection by factious preference, but in holiness to all equally who fear God.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>Let our children share in the instruction which is in Christ, let them learn the strength of humility before God, the powTer of pure love before God, how beautiful and great is his fear and how it <pb xml:id="p.49"/> gives salvation to all who live holily in it with a pure mind.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>For he is a searcher of thoughts and desires; his breath is in us, and when he will he shall take it away.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="22">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Now the faith which is in Christ confirms all<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The confirmation of this teaching in the Scriptures</note> these things, for he himself through his Holy Spirit calls us thus:—<q>Come, Children, hearken to me, I will teach you the fear of the Lord.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><q rend="merge">Who is the man that desireth life, that loveth to see good days?</q></p></div>	
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q rend="merge">Make thy tongue cease from evil, and thy lips that they speak no guile.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">Depart from evil, and do good.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">Seek peace, and pursue it.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">The eyes of the Lord are upon the righteous, and his ears are open to their petition; but the face of the Lord is against those that do evil, to destroy the memory of them from off the earth.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p><q rend="merge">The righteous cried, and the Lord heard him, and delivered him out of all his afflictions.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The Editors (except Knopf) add as v. 8, <q>Many are the afflictions of the righteous and out of them all will the Lord deliver him.</q></note></q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p><q rend="merge">Many are the scourges of the sinner, but mercy shall encompass those that hope on the Lord.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="23">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">The all-merciful and beneficent Father has<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Humility and sincerity</note> compassion on those that fear him, and kindly and lovingly bestows his favours on those that draw near <pb xml:id="p.51"/> to him with a simple mind.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Wherefore let us not be double-minded, nor let our soul be fanciful concerning his excellent and glorious gifts.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let this Scripture be far from us in which he says <q>Wretched are the double-minded, who doubt in their soul and say <q>We have heard these things even in the days of our fathers, and behold we have grown old, and none of these things has happened to us.</q></q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">Oh, foolish men, compare yourself to a tree: take a vine, first it sheds its leaves, then there comes a bud, then a leaf, then a flower, and after this the unripe grape, then the full bunch.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">This quotation which is also found in II. Clem. 11, 2, cannot be identified. Some think it is from the lost apocalypse of Eldad and Modad. Cf. Hermas, <title>Vis.</title> 2, 3.</note> See how in a little time the fruit of the tree comes to ripeness.</p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Truly his will shall be quickly and suddenly accomplished, as the Scripture also bears witness that <q>he shall come quickly and shall not tarry; and the Lord shall suddenly come to his temple, and the Holy One for whom ye look.</q></p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="24">
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us consider, beloved, how the Master continually<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The resurrection foreshadowed in Nature</note> proves to us that there will be a future resurrection, of which he has made the first-fruits, by raising the Lord Jesus Christ from the dead.</p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let us look, beloved, at the resurrection which is taking place at its proper season.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Day and night show us a resurrection. The night sleeps, the day arises: the day departs, night comes on.</p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Let us take the crops: how and in what way does the <pb xml:id="p.53"/> sowing take place?</p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q>The sower went forth</q> and cast each of the seeds into the ground,, and they fall on to the ground, parched and bare, and suffer decay; then from their decay the greatness of the providence of the Master raises them up, and from one grain more grow and bring forth fruit.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="25">
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us consider the strange sign which takes<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The Phoenix as a sign of the resurrection</note> place in the East, that is in the districts near Arabia.</p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>There is a bird which is called the Phoenix. This is the only one of its kind, and lives 500 years; and when the time of its dissolution in death is at hand, it makes itself a sepulchre of frankincense and myrrh and other spices, and when the time is fulfilled it enters into it and dies.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Now, from the corruption of its flesh there springs a worm, which is nourished by the juices of the dead bird, and puts forth wings. Then, wrhen it has become strong, it takes up that sepulchre, in which are the bones of its predecessor, and carries them from the country of Arabia as far as Egypt until it reaches the city called Heliopolis,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>and in the daylight in the sight of all it flies to the altar of the Sun, places them there, and then starts back to its former home.</p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Then the priests inspect the registers of dates, and they find that it has come at the fulfilment of the 500th year.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The same story, with variations, is found in Herodotus (ii. 73), Pliny (<title>Nat. Hist.</title> x. 2), etc. It was supposed by Christians to be sanctioned by the LXX version of Ps. xcii. 12, where there is a confusion between <foreign xml:lang="grc">φοῖνιξ</foreign> = <gloss>phoenix</gloss>, and <foreign xml:lang="grc">φοῖνιξ</foreign> = <gloss>palm tree</gloss>.</note></p></div></div>

		      <pb xml:id="p.55"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="26">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Do we then consider it a great and wonderful<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The resurrection promised in the Scriptures</note> thing that the creator of the universe will bring about the resurrection of those who served him in holiness, in the confidence of a good faith, when he shows us the greatness of his promise even through a bird?</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For he says in one place <q>And thou shalt raise me up, and I will praise thee,</q> and <q>I laid me down and slept, I rose up, for thou art with me.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And again Job says <q>And thou shalt raise up this my flesh which has endured all these things.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="27">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">In this hope then let our souls be bound to<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The necessity of cleaving to God</note> him who is faithful in his promises and righteous in his judgments.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>He who has commanded not to lie shall much more not be a liar himself; for nothing is impossible with God save to lie.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let therefore faith in him be kindled again in us, and let us consider that all things are near him.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>By the word of his majesty did he establish all things, and by his word can he destroy them.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q>Who shall say to him what hast thou done, or who shall resist the might of his strength?</q> When he will, and as he will, he will do all things, and none of his decrees shall pass away.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>All is in his sight and nothing has escaped from his counsel,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>since <q>The heavens declare the glory of God and the firmament <pb xml:id="p.57"/> telleth his handiwork, day uttereth speech unto day, and night telleth knowledge to night. And there are neither words nor speeches, and their voices are not heard.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="28">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Since then all things are seen and heard by<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The omniscience of God</note> him, let us fear him, and leave off from foul desires of evil deeds, that we may be sheltered by his mercy from the judgments to come.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For whither can any of us fly from his mighty hand? And what world shall receive those who seek to desert from him?</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For the Writing<note resp="editor" type="footnote">An accurate quotation of an unintelligible sentence, <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὸ γραφεῖον</foreign> means the third division of the Jewish bible, sometimes called the <q>Hagiographa</q>; it was in a sense <q>Scripture</q> but not considered as important as the <q>Law</q> and the <q>Prophets.</q></note> says in one place: <q>Where shall I go and where shall I hide from thy presence? If I ascend into heaven thou art there, if I depart to the ends of the earth there is thy right hand; If I make my bed in the abyss there is thy spirit.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Whither then shall a man depart or where shall he escape from him who embraces all things?</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="29">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then approach him in holiness of soul,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The privileges of Christians</note> raising pure and undefiled hands to him, loving our gracious and merciful Father, who has made us the portion of his choice for himself.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For thus it is written: <q>When the most high divided the nations, <pb xml:id="p.59"/> when he scattered the sons of Adam, he established the bounds of the nations according to the number of the angels of God. His people Jacob became the portion of the Lord, Israel was the lot of his inheritance.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And	in	another place he says <q>Behold the Lord taketh to himself a nation from the midst of nations, as a man taketh the first-fruit of his threshing-floor, and the Holy of Holies shall come forth from that nation.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">The passages quoted in the margin are those which most nearly resemble this quotation, but the difference is considerable, and Clement may be referring to some lost source.</note></p></div></div>

 <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="30">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Seeing then that we are the portion of one<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The duties of their privileges</note> who is holy, let us do all the deeds of sanctification, fleeing from evil speaking, and abominable and impure embraces, drunkenness and youthful lusts, and abominable passion, detestable adultery, and abominable pride.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><q>For God,</q> he says, <q>resisteth the proud but giveth grace to the humble.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us then join ourselves to those to whom is given grace from God; let us put on concord in meekness of spirit and continence, keeping ourselves far from all gossip and evil speaking, and be justified by deeds, not by words.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For he says <q>He that speaketh much shall also hear much; or doth he that is a good speaker think that he is righteous?</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">Blessed is he that is born of woman and hath a short life. Be not profuse in speech.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">The text is here obviously corrupt; but the corruption is in the LXX, not in Clement.</note></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Let our praise be with God, and not from ourselves, for God hates <pb xml:id="p.61"/> those who praise themselves.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Let testimony to our good deeds be given by others, as it was given to our fathers, the righteous.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>Frowardness and arrogance and boldness belong to those that are accursed by God, gentleness and humility and meekness are with those who are blessed by God.</p></div></div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="31">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us cleave, then, to his blessing and let us<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The faith of the Patriarchs</note> consider what are the paths of blessing. Let us unfold the deeds of old.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Why was our father Abraham blessed? Was it not because he wrought righteousness and truth through faith?</p></div>	
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Isaac in confident knowledge of the future was gladly led as a sacrifice.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Jacob departed from his country in meekness because of his brother, and went to Laban and served him, and to him was given the sceptre of the twelve tribes of Israel.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="32">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And if anyone will candidly consider this<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The greatness of Jacob’s blessing</note> in detail, he will recognize the greatness of the gifts given by him.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For from him<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The obscurity of this passage is partly due to an ambiguity in the Greek, partly to the faultiness of the chapter-divisions. The first verse of this chapter ought really to be closely connected with the last verse of Chapter XXXI; the <q>by him</q> in XXXII, 1 means <q>by God,</q> and the <q>from him</q> in XXXII, 2 means from Jacob.</note> come the priests and all the Levites, who serve the altar <pb xml:id="p.63"/> of God, from him comes the Lord Jesus according to the flesh, from him come the kings and rulers and governors in the succession of Judah, and the other sceptres of his tribes are in no small renown seeing that God promised that <q>thy seed shall be as the stars of heaven.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>All of them therefore were all renowned and magnified, not through themselves or their own works or the righteous actions which they had wrought, but through his will;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>and therefore we who by his will have been called in Christ Jesus, are not made righteous by ourselves, or by our wisdom or understanding or piety or the deeds which we have wrought in holiness of heart, but through faith, by which Almighty God has justified all men from the beginning of the world; to him be glory for ever and ever. Amen.</p></div></div>

 <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="33">
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">What shall we do, then, brethren? Shall we be<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Continuance in good works</note> slothful in well-doing (ind cease from love? May the Master forbid that this should happen, at least to us, but let us be zealous to accomplish every good deed with energy and readiness.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For the Creator and Master of the universe himself rejoices in his works.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For by his infinitely great might did he establish the heavens, and by his incomprehensible understanding did he order them; and he separated the earth from the water that surrounds it, and fixed it upon the secure foundation of his own will; and the animals <pb xml:id="p.65"/> that move in it did he command to exist by his own decree; the sea and the living things in it did he make ready, and enclosed by his own power.</p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Above all, man, the most excellent and from his intellect the greatest of his creatures, did he form in the likeness of his own image by his sacred and faultless hands.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or perhaps <q>did he form in accordance with his intellect.</q></note></p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>For God spake thus: <q>Let us make man according to our image and likeness; and God made man, male and female made he them.</q></p></div>
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>So when he had finished all these things he praised them and blessed them and said, <q>Increase and multiply.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Let us observe that all the righteous have been adorned with good works; and the Lord himself adorned himself with good works and rejoiced.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>Having therefore this pattern let us follow his will without delay, let us work the work of righteousness with all our strength.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="34">
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">The good workman receives the bread of his<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The reward of good works</note> labour with boldness; the lazy and careless cannot look his employer in the face.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Therefore we must be prompt in well-doing: for all things are from him.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For he warns us: <q>Behold the Lord cometh, and his reward is before his face, to pay to each according to his work.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>He exhorts us therefore if we believe on him with our whole heart not to be lazy or careless <q>in every good work.</q></p></div>
<pb xml:id="p.67"/>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Let our glorying and confidence be in him; let us be subject to his will; let us consider the whole multitude of his angels, how they stand ready and minister to his will.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>For the Scripture says <q>Ten thousand times ten thousand stood by him, and thousand thousands ministered to him, and they cried Holy, Holy, Holy is the Lord of Sabaoth, the whole creation is full of his glory.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Therefore, we too must gather together with concord in our conscience<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Others translate <q>in concord and a good conscience</q>; but it is not certain that <foreign xml:lang="grc">συνείδησις</foreign> can be the synonym of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀγαθὴ συνείδησις</foreign>.</note> and cry earnestly to him, as it were with one mouth, that we may share in his great and glorious promises,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>for he says: <q>Eye hath not seen, and ear hath not heard, and it hath not entered into the heart of man, what things the Lord hath prepared for them that wait for him.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="35">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">How blessed and wonderful, beloved, are the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The reward of good works, and how it may be gained</note> gifts of God!</p></div>	
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Life in	immortality, splendour in righteousness, truth in boldness, faith in confidence, continence in holiness: and all these things are submitted to our understanding.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>What, then, are the things which are being prepared for those who wait for him? The Creator and Father of the ages, the All-holy one, himself knows their greatness and beauty.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Let us then strive to be found among the number of those that wait, that we may receive a share of the promised gifts.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>But how <pb xml:id="p.69"/> shall this be, beloved? If our understanding be fixed faithfully on God; if we seek the things which are well-pleasing and acceptable to him; if we fulfil the things which are in harmony with his faultless will, and follow the way of truth, casting away from ourselves all iniquity and wickedness, covetousness, strife, malice and fraud, gossiping and evil speaking, hatred of God, pride and arrogance, vain-glory and inhospitality.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>For those who do these things are hateful to God, and <q>not only those who do them, but also those who take pleasure in them.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>For the Scripture says: <q>But to the sinner said God: Wherefore dost thou declare my ordinances, and takest my covenant in thy mouth?</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p><q rend="merge">Thou hast hated instruction, and cast my words behind thee. If thou sawest a thief thou didst run with him, and thou didst make thy portion with the adulterers. Thy mouth hath multiplied iniquity, and thy tongue did weave deceit. Thou didst sit to speak evil against thy brother, and thou didst lay a stumbling-block in the way of thy mother’s son.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p><q rend="merge">Thou hast done these things and I kept silent; thou didst suppose, O wicked one, that I shall be like unto thee.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p><q rend="merge">I will reprove thee and set thyself before thy face.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The Syriac reads <q>Set thy sins before thy face.</q> This is no doubt a guess, but it gives the meaning.</note></q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p><q rend="merge">Understand then these things, ye who forget God, lest he seize you as doth a lion, and there be none to deliver.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p><q rend="merge">The sacrifice of praise shall glorify me, and therein is a way in which I will show to him the salvation of God.</q></p></div></div>
<pb xml:id="p.71"/>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="36">
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">This is the way, beloved, in which we found<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The reward is given through Christ</note> our salvation, Jesus Christ, the high priest of our offerings, the defender and helper of our weakness.</p></div>
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Through him we fix our gaze on the heights of heaven, through him we see the reflection of his faultless and lofty countenance, through him the eyes of our hearts were opened, through him our foolish and darkened understanding blossoms towards the light, through him the Master willed that we should taste the immortal knowledge; <q>who, being the brightness of his majesty is by so much greater than angels as he hath inherited a more excellent name.</q></p></div>
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For it is written thus <q>Who maketh his angels spirits, and his ministers a flame of fire.</q></p></div>
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>But of his son the Master said thus <q>Thou art my son: to-day have I begotten thee. Ask of me, and I will give thee the heathen for thine inheritance, and the ends of the earth for thy possession.</q></p></div>
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And again he says to him <q>Sit thou on my right hand until I make thine enemies a footstool of thy feet.</q></p></div>
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Who then are the enemies? Those who are wicked and oppose his will.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="37">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then serve in our army, brethren, with<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The necessity for subordination</note> all earnestness, following his faultless commands.</p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let us consider those who serve our generals, with <pb xml:id="p.73"/> what good order, habitual readiness, and submissiveness they perform their commands.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Not all are prefects, nor tribunes, nor centurions, nor in charge of fifty men, or the like, but each carries out in his own rank the commands of the emperor and of the generals.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>The great cannot exist without the small, nor the small without the great; there is a certain mixture among all, and herein lies the advantage.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Let us take our body; the head is nothing without the feet, likewise the feet are nothing withr out the head; the smallest members of our body are necessary and valuable to the whole body, but all work together and are united in a common subjection to preserve the whole body.</p></div></div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="38">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let, therefore, our whole body be preserved in<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The duties of mutual help</note> Christ Jesus, and let each be subject to his neighbour, according to the position granted to him.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let the strong care for the weak and let the weak reverence the strong. Let the rich man bestow help on the poor and let the poor give thanks to God, that he gave him one to supply his needs; let the wise manifest his wisdom not in words but in good deeds; <pb xml:id="p.75"/> let him who is humble-minded not testify to his own humility, but let him leave it to others to bear him witness; let not him who is pure in the flesh be boastful, knowing that it is another who bestows on him his continence.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us consider, then, brethren, of what matter we were formed, who we are, and with what nature we came into the world, and how he who formed and created us brought us into his world from the darkness of a grave, and prepared his benefits for us before we were born.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Since, therefore, we have everything from him we ought in everything to give him thanks, to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="39">
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Foolish, imprudent, silly, and uninstructed men<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation against those who act otherwise</note> mock and deride us, wishing to exalt themselves in their own conceits.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For what can mortal man do, or what is the strength of him who is a child of earth?</p></div>	
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For it is written <q>There was no shape before mine eyes, but I heard a sound and a voice.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">What then? Shall a mortal be pure before the Lord? Or shall a man be blameless in his deeds, seeing that he believeth not in his servants, and hath noted perversity in his angels?</q></p></div>	
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">Yea, the heaven is not pure before him. Away then, ye who inhabit houses of clay, of which, even of the same clay, we ourselves were made. He smote them as a <pb xml:id="p.77"/> moth, and from morning until evening they do not endure; they perished, without being able to help themselves.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">He breathed on them and they died because they had no wisdom.</q></p></div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p><q rend="merge">But call now, if any shall answer thee, or if thou shalt see any of the holy angels; for wrath destroyeth the foolish, and envy putteth to death him that is in error.</q></p></div>
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p><q rend="merge">I have seen the foolish taking root, but their habitation was presently consumed.</q></p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p><q rend="merge">Let their sons be far from safety; let them be mocked in the gates of those less than they, with none to deliver; for what was prepared for them the righteous shall eat, and they themselves shall not be delivered from evil</q></p></div></div>

		          <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="40">
		              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Since then these things are manifest to us,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The duty of observing order in religious services</note> and we have looked into the depths of the divine knowledge, we ought to do in order all things which the Master commanded us to perform at appointed times.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>He commanded us to celebrate sacrifices and services, and that it should not be thoughtlessly or disorderly, but at fixed times and hours.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>He has himself fixed by his supreme will the places and persons whom he desires for these celebrations, in order that all things may be done piously according to his good pleasure, and be acceptable to his will.</p></div>
		              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>So then those who offer their oblations at the appointed seasons are acceptable and blessed, for <pb xml:id="p.79"/> they follow the laws of the Master and do no sin.</p></div>
		              <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>For to the High Priest his proper ministrations are allotted, and to the priests the proper place has been appointed, and on Levites their proper services have been imposed. The layman is bound by the ordinances for the laity.</p></div></div>

    <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="41">
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let each one of us, brethren, be well<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The necessity for a diversity of functions in the church</note> pleasing to God in his own rank, and have a good conscience, not transgressing the appointed rules of his ministration, with all reverence.</p></div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Not in every place, my brethren, are the daily sacrifices offered or the free-will offerings,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">If the reading of C be adopted, <q>Sacrifices of prayers.</q></note> or the sin-offerings and trespass-offerings, but only in Jerusalem; and there also the offering is not made in every place, but before the shrine, at the altar, and the offering is first inspected by the High Priest and the ministers already mentioned.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Those therefore who do anything contrary to that which is agreeable to his will suffer the penalty of death.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>You see, brethren, that the more knowledge we have been entrusted with, the greater risk do we incur.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="42">
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">The Apostles received the Gospel for us from<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The Apostolic foundation of church organisation</note> the Lord Jesus Christ, Jesus the Christ was sent from <pb xml:id="p.81"/> God.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>The Christ therefore is from God and the Apostles from the Christ. In both ways,<note resp="editor" type="footnote"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἀμφότερα</foreign> <q>both</q> is probably adverbial rallior than the subject of <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐγένοντο</foreign>.</note>
        then, they were in accordance with the appointed order of God’s will.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Having· therefore received their commands, and being fully assured by the resurrection of our Lord Jesus Christ, and with faith confirmed by the word of God, they went forth in the assurance of the Holy Spirit preaching the good news that the Kingdom of God is coming.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>They preached from district to district, and from city to city, and they appointed their first converts, testing them by the Spirit, to be bishops and deacons of the future believers.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And this was no new method, for many years before had bishops and deacons been written of; for the scripture says thus in one place <q>I will establish their bishops in righteousness, and their deacons in faith.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="43">
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And what wonder is it if those who were in<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The action of Moses as a type of church organisation</note> Christ, and were entrusted by God with such a duty, established those who have been mentioned? Since the blessed Moses also <q>A faithful servant in all his house</q> noted down in the sacred books all the injunctions which were given him; and the other prophets follow ed him, bearing witness with him to the laws which he had given.</p></div>
  <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For when jealousy arose concerning the priesthood, and the tribes w ere quarrelling as to which of them was adorned with that glorious title, Moses himself commanded the <pb xml:id="p.83"/> rulers of the twelve tribes to bring him rods, with the name of a tribe written on each; and he took them, and bound them, and sealed them with the rings of the rulers of the tribes, and put them away in the Tabernacle of Testimony on the table of God.</p></div>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And he shut the Tabernacle, and sealed the keys, as he had done with the rods,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>and he said to them, <q>Brethren, of whichsoever tribe the rod shall bud, this has God chosen for his priesthood and ministry.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And when it was daylight he called together all Israel, six hundred thousand men, and showed the seals- to the rulers of the tribes, and opened the Tabernacle of Testimony, and took forth the rods, and the rod of Aaron was found not only to have budded, but also to be bearing fruit.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>What do you think, beloved? That Moses did not know beforehand that this was going to happen? Assuredly he knew, but he acted thus that there should be no disorder in Israel, to glorify the name of the true and only God, to whom be the glory for ever and ever. Amen.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="44">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Our Apostles also knew through our Lord<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The application of these facts to the situation at Corinth</note> Jesus Christ that there would be strife for the title of bishop.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For this cause, therefore, since they had received perfect foreknowledge, they appointed <pb xml:id="p.85"/> those who have been already mentioned, and afterwards added the codicil that if they should fall asleep, other approved men should succeed to their ministry.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>We consider therefore that it is not just to remove from their ministry those who were appointed by them, or later on by other eminent men, with the consent of the whole Church, and have ministered to the flock of Christ without blame, humbly, peaceably, and disinterestedly, and for many years have received a universally favourable testimony.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For our sin is not small, if we eject from the episcopate those who have blamelessly and liolily offered its sacrifices.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Blessed are those Presbyters who finished their course before now, and have obtained a fruitful and perfect release in the ripeness of completed work, for they have now no fear that any shall move them from the place appointed \o them.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>For we see that in spite of their good service you have removed some from the ministry which they fulfilled blamelessly.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">It is doubtful if this translation is right, and the Greek is perhaps corrupt. Lightfoot emends <foreign xml:lang="grc">τετιμημένης</foreign> to <foreign xml:lang="grc">τετηρημένης</foreign> <q>which they preserved.</q> The translation given is supported by L <foreign xml:lang="lat">facto</foreign> (probably a corruption of <foreign xml:lang="lat">functo</foreign>).</note></p></div></div>

  <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="45">
	 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">You are contentious,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or possibly, <q>Be contentious.</q></note> brethren, and zealous for<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The persecution of the just in the Old Testament</note> the things which lead to salvation.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>You have studied the Holy Scriptures, which are true, and given by <pb xml:id="p.87"/> the Holy Spirit.</p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>You know that nothing unjust or counterfeit is written in them. You will not find that the righteous have been cast out by holy men.</p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>The righteous were persecuted; but it was by the wicked. They were put in prison; but it was by the unholy. They were stoned by law-breakers, they were killed by men who had conceived foul and unrighteous envy.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>These things they suffered, and gained glory by their endurance.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>For what shall we say, brethren? Was Daniel cast into the lions’ den by those who feared God?</p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Or were Ananias, Azarias, and Misael shut up in the fiery furnace by those who ministered to the great and glorious worship of the Most High? God forbid that this be so.  Who then were they who did these things? Hateful men, full of all iniquity, were roused to such a pitch of fury, that they inflicted torture on those who served God with a holy and faultless purpose, not knowing that the Most High is the defender and protector of those who serve his excellent name with a pure conscience, to whom be glory for ever and ever. Amen.</p></div>
      <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>But they who endured in confidence obtained the inheritance of glory and honour; they were exalted, and were enrolled by God in his memorial for ever and ever. Amen.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="46">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">We also, brethren, must therefore cleave to such<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation against schism</note> examples.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For it is written, <q>Cleave to the holy, for they who cleave to them shall be made holy.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">The source of this quotation is unknown.</note></p></div> <pb xml:id="p.89"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And again in another place it says, <q>With the innocent man thou shalt be innocent, and with the elect man thou shalt be elect, and with the perverse man thou shalt do perversely.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">Clement takes the word for <q>with</q> (<foreign xml:lang="grc">μετά</foreign>) to mean <q>in the company of</q>: in Ps. 17 (in Hebrew and English Ps. 18) it means <q>in the case of,</q> and the subject of the verbs is God.</note></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Let us then cleave to the innocent and righteous, for these are God’s elect.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Why are there strife and passion and divisions and schisms and war among you?</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Or have we not one God, and one Christ, and one Spirit of grace poured out upon us? And is there not one calling in Christ?</p></div>	
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>Why do we divide and tear asunder the members of Christ, and raise up strife against our own body, and reach such a pitch of madness as to forget that we are members one of another? Remember the words of the Lord Jesus;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>for he said, <q>Woe unto that man: it were good for him if he had not been born, than that he should offend one of my elect; it were better for him that a millstone be hung on him, and he be cast into the sea, than that he should turn aside one of my elect.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>Your schism has turned aside many, has cast many into discouragement, many to doubt, all of us to grief; and your sedition continues.</p></div></div>

 <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="47">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Take up the epistle of the blessed Paul the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The example and teaching of St. Paul, and the early parties at Corinth</note> Apostle.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>What did he first write to you at the <pb xml:id="p.91"/> beginning of his preaching?</p></div>	
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>With true inspiration he charged you concerning himself and Cephas and Apollos, because even then you had made yourselves partisans.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>But that partisanship entailed less guilt on you; for you were partisans of Apostles of high reputation, and of a man approved by them.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>But now consider who they are who have perverted you, and have lessened the respect due to your famous love for the brethren.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>It is a shameful report, beloved, extremely shameful, and unworthy of your training in Christ, that on account of one or two persons the stedfast and ancient church of the Corinthians is being disloyal to the presbyters.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>And this report has not only reached us, but also those who dissent from us, so that you bring blasphemy on the name of the Lord through your folly, and are moreover creating danger for yourselves.</p></div></div>

     <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="48">
     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then quickly put an end to this, and let<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to be reconciled</note> us fall down before the Master, and beseech him with tears that he may have mercy upon us, and be reconciled to us, and restore us to our holy and seemly practice of love for the brethren.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For this is the gate of righteousness which opens on to life, as it is written <q>Open me the gates of righteousness, that I may enter into them and praise the Lord; </q></p></div> <pb xml:id="p.93"/>
 <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q rend="merge">this is the gate of the Lord, the righteous shall enter in by it.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>So then of the many gates which are opened, that which is in righteousness is the one in Christ, in which are blessed all who enter and make straight their way in holiness and righteousness, accomplishing all things without disorder.</p></div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Let a man be faithful, let him have power to utter <q>Knowledge,</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote"><q>Knowledge</q> is hero no doubt used in the almost technical sense of <q>secret knowledge, conveying power, and specially revealed,</q> approaching closely to the meaning which it had in the various <q>Gnostic</q> systems and in the Mystery religions.</note> let him be wise in the discernment of arguments, let him be pure in his deeds;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>for the more he seems to be great, the more ought he to be humble-minded, and to seek the common good of all and not his own benefit.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="49">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let him who has love in Christ perform the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Panegyric on love</note> commandments of Christ.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Who is able to explain the bond of the love of God?</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Who is sufficient to tell the greatness of its beauty?</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>The height to which love lifts us is not to be expressed.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Love unites us to God. <q>Love covereth a multitude of sins. Love beareth all things, is long-suffering in all things. There is nothing base, nothing haughty in love; love admits no schism, love makes no sedition, love does all things in concord. In love were all the elect of God made perfect. Without love is nothing well pleasing to God.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">In love did the Master receive us; for the sake of the love which he <pb xml:id="p.95"/> had towards us did Jesus Christ our Lord give his blood by the will of God for us, and his flesh for our flesh, and his soul<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or, perhaps <q>life for our lives</q>; but there seems to be an antithesis in the Greek between <foreign xml:lang="grc">σάρξ</foreign>, flesh, and <foreign xml:lang="grc">ψυχή</foreign>, soul.</note> for our souls.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="50">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">See, beloved, how great and wonderful is love,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to pray for love</note> and that of its perfection there is no expression.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Who is able to be found in it save those to whom God grants it? Let us then beg and pray of his mercy that we may be found in love, without human partisanship, free from blame.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>All the generations from Adam until this day have passed away; but those who were perfected in love by the grace of God have a place among the pious who shall be made manifest at the visitation of the Kingdom of Christ.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For it is written, <q>Enter into thy chambers for a very little while, until my wrath and fury pass away, and I will remember a good day, and will raise you up out of your graves.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Blessed are we, beloved, if we perform the commandments of God in the concord of love, that through love our sins may be forgiven.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>For it is written <q>Blessed are they whose iniquities are forgiven, and whose sins are covered; blessed is the man whose sin the Lord will not reckon, and in whose mouth is no guile.</q></p></div>
<pb xml:id="p.97"/>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>This blessing was given to those who have been chosen by God through Jesus Christ our Lord, to whom be the glory for ever and ever. Amen.</p></div></div>

	<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="51">
	    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then pray that for our transgressions,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">And for forgiveness</note> and for what we have done through any attacks of the adversary, forgiveness may be granted to us. And those also who were the leaders of sedition and disagreement are bound to consider the common hope.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For those who live in fear and love are willing to suffer torture themselves rather than their neighbours, and they suffer the blame of themselves, rather than that of our tradition of noble and righteous harmony,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>for it is better for man to confess his transgressions than to harden his heart, even as the heart of those was hardened who rebelled against God’s servant Moses, and their condemnation was made manifest,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>for <q>they went down into Hades alive</q> and <q>death shall be their shepherd.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Pharaoh and his army and all the rulers of Egypt, <q>the chariots and their riders,</q> were sunk in the Red Sea, and perished for no other cause than that their foolish hearts were hardened, after Unit signs and wonders had been wrought in the land of Egypt by God’s servant Moses.</p></div></div>
		       
<pb xml:id="p.99"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="52">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">The Master, brethren, is in need of nothing: he<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Let the wrongdoers confess their sins</note> asks nothing of anyone, save that confession be made to him.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For David the chosen says:—<q>I will confess to the Lord, and it shall please him more than a young calf that groweth horns and hoofs: let the poor see it and be glad.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And again he says <q>Sacrifice to God a sacrifice of praise, and pay to the Highest thy vows; and call upon me in the day of thy affliction, and I will deliver thee and thou shalt glorify me.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">For the sacrifice of God is a broken spirit.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="53">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">For you have understanding, you have a good<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The example of Moses</note> understanding of the sacred Scriptures, beloved, and you have studied the oracles of God. Therefore we write these things to remind you.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For when Moses went up into the mountain, and passed forty days and forty nights in fasting and humiliation, God said to him:—<q>Go down hence quickly, for thy people, whom thou didst bring out of the land of Egypt, have committed iniquity; they have quickly gone aside out of the way which thou didst command them; they have made themselves molten images.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And the Lord said to him:—<q>I have spoken to thee once and twice, saying, I have seen this people, and behold it is stiffnecked; suffer <pb xml:id="p.101"/> me to destroy them, and I will wipe out their name from under heaven, and thee will I make into a nation great and wonderful and much more than this.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And Moses said, <q>Not so. Lord; pardon the sin of this people, or blot me also out of the book of the living.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>O great love! O unsurpassable perfection! The servant is bold with the Lord, he asks forgiveness for the people, or begs that he himself may be blotted out together with them.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="54">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Who then among you is noble, who is compassionate,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Application to the Corinthians</note> who is filled with love?</p></div>	
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let	him cry:—<q>If sedition and strife and divisions have arisen on my account, I will depart, I will go away whithersoever you will, and I will obey the commands of the people; only let the flock of Christ have peace with the presbyters set over it.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>He who does this will win for himself great glory in Christ, and every place will receive him, for <q>the earth is the Lord’s, and the fullness of it.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>This has been in the past, and will be in the future, the conduct of those who live without regrets as citizens in the city of God.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="55">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us also bring forward examples from<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Other examples of loving self-sacrifice</note> the heathen. Many kings and rulers, when a time of pestilence has set in, have followed the counsel of oracles, and given themselves up to death, that they might rescue their subjects through their own blood. <pb xml:id="p.103"/> Many have gone away from their own cities, that sedition might have an end.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>We know that many among ourselves have given themselves to bondage that they might ransom others. Many have delivered themselves to slavery, and provided food for others with the price they received for themselves.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Many women have received power through the grace of God and have performed many deeds of manly valour.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>The blessed Judith, when her city was besieged, asked the elders to suffer her to go out into the camp of the strangers.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>So she gave herself up to danger, and went forth for love of her country and her people in their siege, and the Lord delivered over Holofernes by the hand of a woman.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Not less did Esther also, who was perfect in faith, deliver herself to danger, that she . might rescue the nation of Israel from the destruction that awaited it; for with fasting and humiliation she besought the all-seeing Master of the Ages, and he saw the meekness of her soul, and rescued the people for whose sake she had faced peril.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="56">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let then us also intercede for those who have<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to humility</note> fallen into any transgression, that meekness and humility be given to them, that they may submit, not to us, but to the will of God; for so will they have fruitful and perfect remembrance before God <pb xml:id="p.105"/> and the saints, and find compassion.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let us receive correction, which none should take amiss, beloved. The admonition which we make one to another is good and beyond measure helpful, for it unites us to the will of God.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For the holy word<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The teaching of the Scriptures</note> says thus: <q>With chastisement did the Lord chastise me, and he delivered me not over unto death;</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">for whom the Lord loveth he chasteneth, and scourgeth every son whom he receiveth.</q></p></div> 
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q>For,</q> he says, <q>the righteous shall chasten me with mercy, and reprove me, but let not the oil of sinners anoint my head.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>And again he says <q>Blessed is the man whom the Lord did reprove; and reject not thou the admonition of the Almighty, for he maketh to suffer pain and again he restoreth;</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p><q rend="merge">he wounded, and his hands healed.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p><q rend="merge">Six times shall he deliver thee from troubles, and the seventh time evil shall not touch thee.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p><q rend="merge">In famine he shall rescue thee from death, and in war he shall free thee from the hand of the sword.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p><q rend="merge">And he shall hide thee from the scourge of the tongue and thou shalt not fear when evils approach.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p><q rend="merge">Thou shalt laugh at the unrighteous and wicked, and thou shalt not be afraid of wild beasts;</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12"><p><q rend="merge">for wild beasts shall be at peace with thee.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13"><p><q rend="merge">Then thou shalt know that thy house shall have peace, and the habitation of thy tabernacle shall not fail.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14"><p><q rend="merge">And thou shalt know that thy seed shall be many and thy children like the herb of the field.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15"><p><q rend="merge">And thou shalt come to the grave like ripened corn that is harvested in its due season, or like a heap on the threshing-floor <pb xml:id="p.107"/> which is gathered together at the appointed time.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16"><p>You see, beloved, how great is the protection<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Application to the Corinthians</note> given to those that are chastened by the Master, for he is a good father and chastens us that we may obtain mercy through his holy chastisement.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="57">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">You therefore, who laid the foundation of the sedition, submit to the presbyters, and receive the correction of repentance, bending the knees of your hearts.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Learn to be submissive, putting aside the boastful and the haughty self-confidence of your tongue, for it is better for you to be found small but honourable in the flock of Christ, than to be preeminent in repute but to be cast out from his hope.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For <q>the excellent wisdom</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote"><q>The excellent wisdom</q> is a title used (a) of Proverbs, (b) of Proverbs, Ecclesiasticus, and Ecclesiastes, (c) of the third division of the O.T. (Hagiographa or <q>Writings</q>) as a whole. Cf. note on p. 57.</note> says thus:—<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Warning from Scripture</note><q>Behold I will bring forth to you the words of my spirit,</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">and I will teach you my speech, since I called and ye did not obey, and I put forth my words and ye did not attend, but made my counsels of no effect, and disobeyed my reproofs; therefore will I also laugh at your ruin, and I will rejoice when destruction cometh upon you, and when sudden confusion overtaketh you and catastrophe cometh as a storm, or when persecution or siege cometh upon you.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p><q rend="merge">For it shall come to pass when ye call upon me, I will not hear you. The evil shall seek me and they shall not find me. For they hated wisdom and they <pb xml:id="p.109"/> chose not the fear of the Lord, neither would they attend to my counsels but mocked my reproofs.</q></p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q rend="merge">Therefore shall they eat the fruits of their own way, and shall be filled with their own wickedness;</q> </p></div>
        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p><q rend="merge">for because they wronged the innocent they shall be put to death, and inquisition shall destroy the wicked. But he who heareth me shall tabernacle with confidence in his hope, and shall be in rest with no fear of any evil.</q></p></div></div>

	 <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="58">
	     <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then be obedient to his most holy and<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Further application and exhortation to the Corinthian dissidents</note>
	         glorious name, and escape the threats which have been spoken by wisdom aforetime to the disobedient, that we may tabernacle in confidence on the most sacred name of his majesty.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Receive our counsel, and there shall be nothing for you to regret, for as God lives and as the Lord Jesus Christ lives and the Holy Spirit, the faith and hope of the elect, he who with lowliness of mind and eager gentleness has without backsliding performed the decrees and commandments given by God shall be enrolled and chosen in the number of those who are saved through Jesus Christ, through whom is to him the glory for ever and ever. Amen.</p></div></div>

<pb xml:id="p.111"/>
		          
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="59">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But if some be disobedient to the words which<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Warnings to the dissidents</note> have been spoken by him through us, let them know that they will entangle themselves in transgression and no little danger;</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>but we shall be innocent of this sin, and will pray with eager entreaty and supplication that the  Creator of the Universe may guard unhurt the number of his elect that has been numbered in all the world through his beloved child Jesus Christ, through whom he called us from darkness to light, from ignorance to the full knowledge of the glory of his name.
</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p rend="indent">Grant us<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Some such addition, though not in any authority for the text, appears to be necessary. </note> to hope on thy name, the source of<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Prayer to God</note> all creation, open the eyes of our heart to know thee, that thou alone art the highest in the highest and remainest holy among the holy. Thou dost humble the pride of the haughty, thou dost destroy the imaginings of nations, thou dost raise up the humble and abase the lofty, thou makest rich and makest poor, thou dost slay and make alive, thou alone art the finder of spirits and art God of all flesh, thou dost look on the abysses, thou seest into the works of man, thou art the helper of those in danger, the saviour of those in despair, the <pb xml:id="p.113"/> creator and watcher over every spirit; thou dost multiply nations upon earth and hast chosen out from them all those that love thee through Jesus Christ thy beloved child, and through him hast thou taught us, made us holy, and brought us to honour.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>We beseech thee, Master, to be our <q>help and<note resp="editor" type="marginal">For help</note> succour.</q> Save those of us who are in affliction, have mercy on the lowly, raise the fallen, show thyself to those in need, heal the sick, turn again the wanderers of thy people, feed the hungry, ransom our prisoners, raise up the weak, comfort the faint-hearted; let all <q>nations know thee, that thou art God alone,</q> and that Jesus Christ is thy child, and that <q>we are thy people and the sheep of thy pasture.</q></p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="60">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">For thou through thy operations didst make manifest the eternal fabric of the world; thou, Lord, didst create the earth. Thou that art faithful in all generations, righteous in judgment, wonderful in strength and majesty, wise in thy creation, and prudent in establishing thy works, good in the things which are seen, and gracious among those that trust in thee, O <q>merciful and compassionate,</q> forgive us our iniquities and unrighteousness, and transgressions, and short-comings.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Reckon not<note resp="editor" type="marginal">For mercy</note> every sin of thy servants and handmaids, but <pb xml:id="p.115"/> cleanse us with the cleansing of thy truth, and <q>guide our steps to walk in holiness of heart, to do the things which are good and pleasing before thee</q> and before our rulers.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Yea, Lord, <q>make thy face to shine upon us</q> in peace <q>for our good</q> that we may be sheltered by thy mighty hand, and delivered from all sin by <q>thy uplifted arm,</q> and deliver us from them that hate us wrongfully.</p></div>
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Give<note resp="editor" type="marginal">For peace</note> concord and peace to us and to all that dwell on the earth, as thou didst give to our fathers who called on thee in holiness with faith and truth, and grant that we may be obedient to thy almighty and glorious name, and to our rulers and governors upon the earth.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="61">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Thou, Master, hast given the power of<note resp="editor" type="marginal">On behalf of rulers</note> sovereignty to them through thy excellent and inexpressible might, that we may know the glory and honour given to them by thee, and be subject to them, in nothing resisting thy will. And to them. Lord, grant health, peace, concord, firmness that they may administer the government which thou hast given them without offence.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For thou, heavenly Master, king of eternity, hast given to the sons of men glory and honour and power over the things which are on the earth; do thou, O Lord, direct their counsels according to that which is <q>good and pleasing</q> before thee, that they may administer with piety in peace and gentleness the power given to them by thee, and may find mercy <pb xml:id="p.117"/> in thine eyes.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>O thou who alone art able to do these things and far better things for us, we praise thee through Jesus Christ, the high priest and guardian of our souls, through whom be glory and majesty to thee, both now and for all generations and for ever and ever. Amen.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="62">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">We have now written to you, brethren, sufficiently<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Summary of letter</note> touching the things which befit our worship, and are most helpful for a virtuous life to those who wish to guide their steps in piety and righteousness.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For we have touched on every aspect of faith and repentance and true love and self-control and sobriety and patience, and reminded you that you are bound to please almighty God with holiness in righteousness and truth and long-suffering, and to live in concord, bearing no malice, in love and peace with eager gentleness, even as our fathers, whose example we quoted, were well-pleasing in their humility towards God, the Father and Creator, and towards all men.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And we had the more pleasure in reminding you of this, because we knew quite well that we were writing to men who were faithful and distinguished and had studied the oracles of the teaching of God.</p></div></div>

<pb xml:id="p.119"/>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="63">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">It is therefore right that we should respect so many and so great examples, and bow the neck, and take up the position of obedience, so that ceasing from vain sedition we may gain without any fault the goal set before us in truth.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For you will give us joy and gladness; if you are obedient to the things which we have written through the Holy Spirit, and root out the wicked passion of your jealousy according to the entreaty for peace and concord which we have made in this letter.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And we have sent faithful<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Introduction for representatives from Rome</note> and prudent men, who have lived among us without: blame from youth to old age, and they shall be witnesses between you and us.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>We have done this that you may know that our whole care has been and is directed to your speedy attainment of peace.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="64">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Now may God, the all-seeing, and the master<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Blessing</note> of spirits, and the Lord of all flesh, who chose out the Lord Jesus Christ, and us through him for <q>a peculiar people,</q> give unto every soul that is called after his glorious and holy name, faith, fear, peace, patience and long-suffering, self-control, purity, sobriety, that they may be well-pleasing to his <pb xml:id="p.121"/> name through our high priest and guardian Jesus Christ, through whom be to him glory and majesty, might and honour, both now and to all eternity. Amen.</p></div></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="65">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Send back quickly to us our messengers Claudius<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Message as to Roman representatives</note> Ephebus and Valerius Vito and Fortunatus, in peace with gladness, in order that they may report the sooner the peace and concord which we pray for and desire, that we also may the more speedily rejoice in your good order.</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with you<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Final blessing and doxology</note> and with all, in every place, who have been called ! by God through him, through whom be to him glory, honour, power and greatness and eternal dominion, from eternity to eternity. Amen.</p><p rend="center">The Epistle of the Romans to the Corinthians.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This form of subscription is found only in the Coptic version, though it was probably also known to Clement of Alexandria, and is undoubtedly correct. The other MSS. a11 attribute it directly to Clement.</note></p></div></div>
</div></body></text></TEI>

