<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI.2>
  <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hymn 19 To Pan</title>
	           <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
	           <editor role="translator">Hugh G. Evelyn-White</editor>
	           <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
		          <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
		          <respStmt>
		             <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
		             <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
		             <name>William Merrill</name>
		             <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
		             <name>David Smith</name>
		          </respStmt>
	           <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
         </titleStmt>

         <extent>about 159Kb</extent>

         <publicationStmt>
		          <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
		          <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
		          <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
		       </publicationStmt>

         <sourceDesc>
	           <bibl>	  
               <author>Anonymous</author>
	              <title>The Homeric Hymns and Homerica
with an English Translation by Hugh G. Evelyn-White.
Homeric Hymns</title>
	              <publisher>Cambridge, MA.,Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
	              <date>1914</date>
	           </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>

      </fileDesc>

      <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI.2/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
                <p>This pointer pattern extracts line</p>
            </cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
         <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
	           <state delim="." n="chunk" unit="hymn"/>
	           <state unit="line"/>
         </refsDecl>
         <!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
	<state n="chunk" unit="card"/>
      </refsDecl>-->
      </encodingDesc>

      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
	           <language id="en">English</language>
	           <language id="greek">Greek</language>
	           <language id="xgreek">Transliterated Greek</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>

      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>1988</date>
	           <respStmt>
               <resp>tagging</resp>
               <name>Bill Merrill</name>
            </respStmt>
	           <item>Text keyboarded in the Philippines.  Basic SGML tagging by Bill Merrill</item>
         </change>
         <change>
	           <date>8/93</date>
	           <respStmt>
               <resp>ed.</resp>
               <name>EM</name>
            </respStmt>
	           <item>Go over text, check cardbreaks, and change tags to be more TEI conformant.</item>
         </change>
         <change when="2015-12-11" who="Lisa Cerrato">fixing titles and headers</change>
      </revisionDesc>

  </teiHeader>
   <text urn="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0013.tlg019.perseus-eng1"
         xml:lang="eng"
         n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0013.tlg019.perseus-eng1">
      <body>
		          <head>To Pan</head>
		          <milestone ed="P" n="1" unit="card"/>

               <div type="line" ed="P" n="1">
                  <p>Muse, tell me about Pan, the dear son of Hermes, with his goat's feet and two horns —a lover of merry noise. Through wooded glades he wanders with dancing nymphs who foot it on some sheer cliff's edge, </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="5">
                  <p>calling upon Pan, the shepherd-god, long-haired, unkempt. He has every snowy crest and the mountain peaks and rocky crests for his domain; hither and thither he goes through the close thickets, now lured by soft streams, </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="10">
                  <p>and now he presses on amongst towering crags and climbs up to the highest peak that overlooks the flocks. Often he courses through the glistening high mountains, and often on the shouldered hills he speeds along slaying wild beasts, this keen-eyed god. Only at evening, </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="15">
                  <p>as he returns from the chase, he sounds his note, playing sweet and low on his pipes of reed: not even she could excel him in melody —that bird who in flower-laden spring pouring forth her lament utters honey-voiced song amid the leaves. At that hour the clear-voiced nymphs are with him and </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="20">
                  <p>move with nimble feet, singing by some spring of dark water, while Echo wails about the mountain-top, and the god on this side or on that of the choirs, or at times sidling into the midst, plies it nimbly with his feet. On his back he wears a spotted lynx-pelt, and he delights in high-pitched songs </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="25">
                  <p>in a soft meadow where crocuses and sweet-smelling hyacinths bloom at random in the grass.</p>
                  <p>They sing of the blessed gods and high <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName> and choose to tell of such an one as luck-bringing Hermes above the rest, how he is the swift messenger of all the gods, </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="30">
                  <p>and how he came to <placeName key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>, the land of many springs and mother of flocks, there where his sacred place is as god of Cyllene. For there, though a god, he used to tend curly-fleeced sheep in the service of a mortal man, because there fell on him and waxed strong melting desire to wed the rich-tressed daughter of Dryops, </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="35">
                  <p>and there he brought about the merry marriage. And in the house she bare Hermes a dear son who from his birth was marvellous to look upon, with goat's feet and two horns —a noisy, merry-laughing child. But when the nurse saw his uncouth face and full beard, she was afraid and sprang up and fled and left the child. </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="40">
                  <p>Then luck-bringing Hermes received him and took him in his arms: very glad in his heart was the god. And he went quickly to the abodes of the deathless gods, carrying his son wrapped in warm skins of mountain hares, and set him down beside Zeus </p>
               </div>
               <div type="line" ed="P" n="45">
                  <p>and showed him to the rest of the gods. Then all the immortals were glad in heart and Bacchic Dionysus in especial; and they called the boy Pan<note anchored="yes" resp="ed" place="unspecified">The name Pan is here derived from<foreign lang="greek">πάντες</foreign>“all.” Cp. <bibl n="Hes. WD 80-82">Hesiod, <title>Works and Days</title> 80-82</bibl>, <bibl n="HH 5.198">
                           <title>Hymn to Aphrodite</title> (v) 198</bibl>, for the significance of personal names.</note> because he delighted all their hearts.</p>
               </div>         
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI.2>
