<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title>The Dream</title>
 <author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Emily James Smith</editor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
 <respStmt>
  <persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
 <date type="release" when="2023-08-11">Perseus 5.0</date>
 <idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5.xml</idno>
 <availability>
 <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
 </availability>
</publicationStmt><sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr>
<title>Selections from Lucian</title>
  <editor role="translator">Emily James Smith</editor>
  <author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
  <imprint>
   <publisher>Harper and Brothers</publisher>
	<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
	<date>1892</date>
  </imprint>
 </monogr>
  <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/hvd.hw3j0n?urlappend=%3Bseq=19">The Hathi Trust</ref>
 </biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
 <p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
 <refsDecl n="CTS">
  <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
   replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
   <p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
  </cRefPattern>
 </refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="Gregory Crane" when="2023-08-11">Created initial file in repository. The major task was adding section breaks. There are missing sections because the translator silently skipped passages that did not conform with contemporary standards of propiety.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="eng">
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5" xml:lang="eng">
<head>THE DREAM.</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="1"><p>


<pb n="p.2"/>





<pb n="p.3"/>


When I had just left school, and was
beginning to grow up, my father consulted with his friends as to what further training he should give me. The
majority decided against a liberal education; it would demand, they said, great labor,
much time, considerable expense, and brilliant
good-luck; whereas our means were small and
called for some speedy succor. Now, if I should
learn one of the industrial arts, I would, in the
first place, be immediately able to support myself
by my trade, and live no longer at my father's expense, great boy that I was. And in a short time
I could gladden his heart by bringing home my
earnings every day.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="2">
<p>
Accordingly, this question was made the theme
of a second deliberation: What trade is the best
and the easiest to learn, is becoming to a free citizen, and calls for least expense in tools while it
furnishes a sufficient income? Each member of
the council recommended a different trade, according to his theory or experience. But my father looked towards my uncle-for my mother's
brother was there, reputed to be a master of the


<pb n="p.4"/>



statuary's art—and said, “It would be unseemly
if
any
other craft should carry the day when you
are present. So take him" (pointing to me), “receive him in charge, and teach him to be a good
stone-worker and mason and sculptor. He has
ability to become even this last, and a natural
skill in that direction, as you know."
The ground of his opinion was my childish play
at modelling in wax. Whenever the school-masters let me go, I would fall to scraping the wax
from my writing-tablets and fashioning cows and
horses, and, upon my word, even men, too, and
with some truth to nature--at least my father
thought so. The school-masters used to flog me
for them; but now this very thing won me praise
for my talents, and great hopes that I would
speedily master my trade were based on my prowess in modelling.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="3">
<p>

As soon as a propitious day was
settled on for beginning my trade, I was handed
over to my uncle, with no very strong objection
on my part, for it seemed to me to offer a delightful form of play and a chance to cut a figure
before my mates, if I should be seen carving
gods and making little statues for myself and my
chosen favorites. The first thing I did was what
might have been expected of a beginner. My
uncle gave me a chisel of some sort and bade me
work gently at a flat block that lay in the middle
of the room, addressing me in the words of the


<pb n="p.5"/>


proverb: "Well begun is half done." But in my
ignorance I bore down too hard and broke the
block. My uncle, in a fury, caught up a stick
that lay to his hand and struck at my devoted
head in no gentle or persuasive fashion, so that
tears were my introduction to art.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="4">
<p>

I ran away from him and came home, bawling
all the way with streaming eyes, and I related the
story of the stick and denounced what I called
my uncle's brutality, adding that he treated me
thus from jealousy lest I should surpass him in
his art. My mother was greatly incensed, and
called her brother all manner of hard names, and
when night came I fell asleep, still in tears, and
my mind was busy all night long.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="5">
<p>

Now, up to this point all that I have told is
the laughable history of a hobbledehoy; but listen, my friends, to a sequel no longer contemptible, but calling for close attention. For, to quote
Homer,

<quote>The gods sent me a vision in my sleep
through the ambrosial night,</quote>

so vivid that it fell
in nowise short of reality. To this day, after so
great a lapse of time, the forms I saw remain in
my eyes and the sounds I heard ring in my ears,
and this shows how distinct it all was.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="6">
<p>

Two
women laid hold of me, each taking a hand and
dragging me towards herself with great energy
and strength; indeed, they almost tore me asunder in their contention. For first one of them


<pb n="p.6"/>



would prevail and all but get possession of me,
and then I would be plucked away again by her
rival. And they screamed in concert, one of
them crying that it was her property she wished
to get hold of, and the other that the first was
vainly striving for what did not belong to her.
This first woman was masculine and workmanlike, with rough hair and callous hands. Her garments were girded up and full of marble chips,
just as my uncle's were wont to be when he was
polishing stone. But the other was of a very fair
countenance, and her figure was shapely and her
clothing well-ordered. Now at last they left it
to me to decide which of them I would fain join.
And first the harsh, man-like one spoke :

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="7">
<p>
"My child," she said, "I am the Art of Stonecutting, which you began yesterday to learn,
friendly to you and a relative by blood, inasmuch
as your grandfather"—naming my mother's father-" was a stone-cutter, and your two uncles,
and both of them are very well thought of on my
account. If you are willing to hold aloof from
this woman's folly and nonsense "-pointing to
her rival" and to come and dwell with me, you
will in the first place be generously nurtured and
have strong shoulders, and you will be a stranger
to all jealousy; you will never leave your fatherland and family to go out into foreign countries,
and it is not for mere words that you will win praise


<pb n="p.7"/>

from every one.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="8">
<p>

Do not be repelled by my shabby exterior and my soiled garments, for it was
after beginning thus that the great Pheidias, too,
showed the world his Zeus, and Polykleitos fashioned his Hera, and Myron won praise and Praxiteles wonder. Now these men are worshipped
with the gods. If, then, you should become one
of these, you, too, would certainly be famous
throughout the world. You will make your father, too, an object of envy, and turn all eyes
towards the land that bore you."
Thus, and at even greater length, spoke Handicraft, sprinkling her speech from end to end with
stammering and rusticities in her eager argument
and effort to persuade me. But I can no longer
call it to mind, for most of it has already escaped
my memory. When she now had made an end,
the other began, somewhat in this way:

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="9">
<p>

"I, my child, am Culture, an acquaintance and
familiar of yours already, although you have not
yet made full trial of me. This person has told
you in advance what you will gain, forsooth, by
becoming a stone-cutter; namely, that you will be
nothing but a workman, toiling with your body,
on which all your hopes of a livelihood will depend. You will be yourself obscure; your gains
will be small and sordid, your mind dwarfed,
your progress despicable. Your friends will not
seek you out, your enemies will not fear you,


<pb n="p.8"/>



your townsfolk will not envy you. You will be
simply an artisan, one of the undistinguished
crowd, tripping over every obstacle, and the obedient servant of every one capable of expressing
himself, while you live the life of a dumb beast,
a treasure-trove for any stronger man than you.
And even if you should become a Pheidias or a
Polykleitos, and should produce many marvellous
works, it is your art that the world will praise,
and not one of those who behold them, if he has
sense, would pray to become like you.
For they
will deem you just what you are, a mechanic, an
artisan, living by the sweat of your brow.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="10">
<p>
But if you will hearken to me, I will display
before you, to begin with, many works and wondrous doings of men of old, and I will report
their sayings to you and make you master, so to
speak, of all learning. I will adorn your soul,
which is the dominant power within you, with
many graces to wit, self-control, righteousness,
reverence, gentleness, equity, wisdom, strength,
love of beauty, taste for the worthiest pursuits.
For these are the things that really make the
spotless beauty of the soul. No sequence of
events in the past or present will escape you;
nay, by my help you will behold even the future,
and I will teach you erelong the nature of the
whole universe, the divine as well as the human.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="11">
<p>

You who are now poor, the son of a nobody,


<pb n="p.9"/>


meditating the adoption of such an ignoble craft,
shall be shortly felicitated and envied by the
world; you shall have honor and praise and glory
among the noblest; you shall be clad like this
-here she indicated her own garments, which
were splendid in the extreme-" and you shall
be deemed worthy of office and eminence. When
you go abroad you will not be unknown and obscure in a foreign land. I will set such marks
upon you that every one who sees you will nudge
his neighbor and point you out with his finger,
saying, 'That is he.'

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="12">
<p>

"If any serious thing befall your friends, or
even the state at large, all will look to you.
When you chance to say anything the crowd will
listen open-mouthed and marvel at you, and envy
your gift and your father's good-fortune. And
this immortality which they say is sometimes bestowed on men I will store up for you. For even
when you yourself perish from the world you will
never cease from companionship with the cultured and conversation with the noblest. You
know whose son Demosthenes was, and yet I
made him the man he was. You know that
Aischines' mother was a dancer, and yet Philip
paid court to him for my sake. Sokrates himself
was brought up under the eye of this Art of Stonecutting, but you hear how his praises are sung on
all sides from the moment when he perceived the



<pb n="p.10"/>



better part and ran away from her and deserted
to me.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="13">
<p>

But if you reject such men as these, and
brilliant achievements and ennobling words and
a seemly guise, and honor and glory and fame
and distinction, and political power and office,
and respect as an orator and envy as a wit, you
will wear a dirty shirt and take on the look of a
slave; your hands will be full of crowbars and
gravers and chisels and picks; you will stoop
over your work, grovelling, prostrate, and altogether stunted; you will never look up or fix
your thoughts on any manly, liberal theme; and
you will ponder how to make your works symmetrical and well-shaped, but for your own symmetry and shapeliness you will take no care at all,
making yourself of less worth than your stones."

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="14">
<p>

While she was still speaking thus, and without
waiting to hear her to the end, I seemed to spring
up and leave the ugly woman in laborer's guise,
and cross over to Culture right joyfully, particularly since that stick came into my head, and how
the other had caused me a beating only yesterday
on my first acquaintance with her. When she
was deserted she at first went into a passion,
smiting her hands together and grinding her
teeth; but finally she grew rigid and turned to
stone, as we hear Niobe did. Now even if this
experience of her's seems extraordinary, do not
disbelieve it, for dreams work wonders.


<pb n="p.11"/>

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="15">
<p>
The other woman looked at me and said, "Now
I will repay you for the justice of your judgment.
Come forthwith and mount this car "-pointing to
a car drawn by winged horses resembling Pegasus
-"so that you may see what you would have
missed knowing if you had not followed me."
Thereupon I mounted the car, and she drove;
and borne aloft I beheld, from the east to the
west, cities and nations and peoples, and I sowed
something upon the earth like Triptolemos.


However, what it was that I sowed I do not now remember, but only this, that the people looked up
at me from beneath and praised me, and sped me
on my way wherever I passed in my flight.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="16">
<p>
When she had shown these things to me, and
me to these admiring people, she brought me
down again, no longer dressed as I was when I
flew away, but seeming to myself to arrive like a
grandee born to the purple. She came upon my
father himself, who was standing by and waiting
for me, showed him my clothes and me, in what
state I came, and reminded him, too, of the decision they had come near making about me.
These are the things that I remember seeing
when hardly more than a boy, I think, and still
terrified at the thought of a flogging.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="17">
<p>

But in the midst of my narrative some one says,
"Dear me, how tedious and long-winded his
dream is." Or another interrupts with, "This is


<pb n="p.12"/>



a mid-winter night's dream, when the nights are
longest; or perhaps he is a three-night man himself, like Hercules. How did it enter his head
to spin out this nonsense for us and recall the
nights of his childhood and old, decrepit dreams,
served up with the chill of death on them and
stale already? Does he take us, forsooth, for
interpreters of dreams?"
No, my friend, and neither did Xenophon relate
his dream when he thought his father's house
was afire and the rest of it—you know his dream
-as a bit of acting, nor was he consciously talking nonsense, seeing that he was in the midst of
warfare and distress and surrounded by enemies.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg029.perseus-eng5:" n="18">
<p>
No, his narrative had a useful purpose, and so I,
too, have related this dream to you to the end
that young men may turn to the better part and
lay hold of culture, particularly those who are
tempted by poverty to play truant and sink to the
worse life, to the destruction of what may have
been noble natures. I am sure that these will
be fortified by hearing my story, and will take
me for a sufficient example if they bear in mind.
the origin whence I set forth after the higher life,
and that my desire was for culture, so that I never
lost heart in my old poverty, and, lastly, the guise
in which I have come to you, certainly, to say the
least of it, not less famous than any of the statuaries.


<pb n="p.13"/>
</p></div>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>

