<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>On Fistulae</title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 20, 2003</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							              <date>1886</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="eng">English</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-29" who="Thibault Clérice">Bumped URN</change>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng"
              type="translation"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg030.perseus-eng2">

			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 1</head>
				           <p> Fistulae are produced by contusions and tubercles, and they are also occasioned
					by rowing, on horseback, when blood accumulates in the nates near the anus. For,
					having become putrid, it spreads to the soft parts (the breech being of a humid
					nature, and the flesh in which it spreads being soft), until the tubercle break
					and corrupt below at the anus. When this happens, a fistula is formed, having an
					ichorous discharge, and faeces pass by it, with flatus and much and abomination.
					It is produced, then, by contusions when any of the parts about the anus are
					bruised by a blow, or a fall, or a wound, or by riding, or rowing, or any such
					cause. For blood is collected, and it, becoming corrupted, suppurates; and the
					from the the same accidents happen, as have been described in the case of
					tubercles. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 2</head>
				           <p> In the first place, then, when you see any such tubercle formed, you must cut it
					open while still unripe, before it suppurate and burst into the rectum. But if a
					fistula be already formed when you undertake the case, take a stalk of fresh
					garlic, and having laid the man on his back, and separated his thighs on both
					sides, push down the stalk as far as it will go, and thereby measure the depth
					of the fistula. Then, having bruised the root of seseli to a very fine powder,
					and poured in some water, let it macerate for four days, and, mixing the water
					with honey, let the patient drink it, fasting, to the amount of three cyathi,
					and at the same time purge away the ascarides. Those who are left without
					treatment die. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 3</head>
				           <p> In the next place, having moistened the strip of cotton cloth, <pb n="p.346"/>with the juice of the great tithymallus, and sprinkling on it the flos aeris,
					roasted and triturated, and having made it into a tent equal in length to the
					fistula, and having passed a thread through the ends of the tent again through
					the stalk, and having placed the patient in a reclining position, and having
					examined the ulcerated parts of the rectum with a speculum, pass the stalk by
					it, and when it reaches the rectum, take hold of it and draw it out until the
					tent be pushed through, and be brought on a level above and below. When it (<hi rend="ital">the tent?</hi>) has been pushed inward, introduce a ball of horn
					into the rectum (the rectum having been previously smeared with Cimolian chalk),
					and leave it there, and when the patient wants to go to stool, let it be taken
					out and again replaced, and let this practice be continued for five days. On the
					sixth day let it be removed, and drawing the tent out of the flesh, and
					afterwards pounding alum and filling the ball (<hi rend="ital">pessary</hi>) and
					introducing it into the rectum, leave it until the alum melts. Anoint the rectum
					with myrrh until the parts appear to be united. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 4</head>
				           <p> Another method of cure:-Taking a very slender thread of raw lint, and uniting it
					into five folds of the length of a span, and wrapping them round with a horse
					hair; then having made a director (specillum) of tin, with an eye at its
					extremity, and having passed through it the end of raw lint wrapped round as
					above described, introduce the director into the fistula, and, at the same time,
					introduce the index finger of the left hand <hi rend="ital">per anum;</hi> and
					when the director touches the finger, bring it out with the finger, bending the
					extremity of the director and the end of the threads in it, and the director is
					to be withdrawn, but the ends of the threads are to be knotted twice or thrice,
					and the rest of the raw threads is to be twisted around and fastened into a
					knot. Then the patient is to be told that he may go and attend to his matters.
					The rest of the treatment:-Whenever any part of the thread gets loose owing to
					the fistula becoming putrid, it is to be tightened and twisted every day; and
					should the raw thread rot before the fistula is eaten through, you must attach
					another piece of raw thread to the hair, pass it through, and tie it, for it was
					for this purpose that the hair was rolled round the raw lint, as it is not <pb n="p.347"/>liable to rot. When the fistula has sloughed through, a soft
					sponge is to be cut into very slender pieces and applied, and then the flowers
					of copper, roasted, are to be frequently applied with a director; and the sponge
					smeared with honey is to be introduced with the index finger of the left hand,
					and pushed forward; and another bit of added, it is to be bound on in the same
					manner as in the operation for hemorrhoids. Next day, having loosed the
					bandages, the fistula is to be washed with hot water, and cleansed, as far as
					possible, with the finger of the left hand by means of the sponge, and again the
					flos aeris is to be applied. This is to be done for seven days, for generally
					the coat of the fistula takes that time to fistula takes that time to slouch
					through. The same mode of bandaging is to be persevered in afterwards, until the
					cure be completed. For in this way, the fistula being forcibly expanded by the
					sponge will not fill up and heal unequally, but it will all become whole
					together. During the treatment, the part should be bathed with plenty of warm
					water, and the patient kept on a spare diet. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 5</head>
				           <p> When the fistula does not get eaten through, having first examined it with a
					sound, cut down as far as it passes, and sprinkle with the flos aeris, and let
					it remain for five days. Then pour warm water upon it, and above lay flour mixed
					with water, and bind on it the leaves of beet. When the flos aeris comes away,
					and the fistulous sore becomes clean, cure it as before described. But if the
					fistula be in a part which does not admit of this treatment, and if it be deep,
					syringe it with the flowers of copper, and myrrh, and natron, diluted with
					urine, and introduce a piece of lead into the orifice of the fistula so that it
					may not close. Syringe the fistula by means of a quill attached to a bladder, so
					that the injection may distend the fistula. But it does not heal unless it be
					cut open. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 6</head>
				           <p> If the anus gets inflamed, and there is pain, fever, a frequent desire of going
					to stool without passing anything, and the anus appears to protrude, owing to
					the inflammation, and if at times strangury come on, this disease is formed,
					when phlegm, collected from the whole body, is determined to the rectum. Warm
					things are beneficial in this case; for these, when applied, can attenuate <pb n="p.348"/>and dissolve the phlegm, and dilute the acrid and salt particles,
					so that the heat subsides, and the irritation in the rectum is removed.
					Wherefore it is to be treated thus: The patient is to be put into a hip-bath of
					hot water, and sixty grains of the grana gnidia are to be pounded and infused in
					a hemina of wine, with half a hemina of oil, and injected. This brings away
					phlegm and faeces. When the patient does not take the hip-bath, boil eggs in
					dark-colored fragrant wine, and apply to the anus, and spread to the anus, and
					spread something warm below, either a bladder filled with warm water, or linseed
					toasted and ground, and its meal stirred up and mixed equally with dark,
					fragrant wine, and oil, and this applied very warm as a cataplasm; or, having
					mixed barley and Egyptian alum pulverized, form into an oblong ball (<hi rend="ital">suppository?</hi>) and warming it gently at the fire, make it
					into a cataplasm, foment, form it into shape with the fingers, and then making
					it quite tepid, introduce it into the anus. The external parts are to be
					anointed with cerate, and a cataplasm of boiled garlic, with dark wine diluted,
					is to be applied. But if you remove these things, let him take the hip-bath of
					hot water, and having mixed together the juice of srychnos, the grease of a
					goose, swine's seam, chrysocolla, resin, and white wax, and then having melted
					in the same and mixed together, anoint with these things, and while the
					inflammation lasts, use the cataplasm of boiled garlic. And if by these means he
					be freed from the pain, it is enough; but if not, give him the white meconium
						(<hi rend="ital">Euphorbia peplus?</hi>), or, if not it, any other
					phlegmagogue medicine. While the inflammation lasts, the diet should be light.
				</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 7</head>
				           <p> The strangury comes on in this way:-The bladder being heated from the rectum,
					phlegm is attracted by the heat, and by the phlegm (<hi rend="ital">inflammation?</hi>) the strangury is occasioned. If, then, as is frequently
					the case, it cease with the disease, well; but, not withstanding, if not, give
					any of the medicines for strangury. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 8</head>
				           <p>If procidentia ani take place, having fomented the part with a soft sponge, and
					anointed it with a snail, bind the man's hands together, and suspend him for a
					short time, and the gut will return. But if it still prolapse, and will not
					remain up, fasten a girdle round his loins and attach a shawl behind, and having
						<pb n="p.349"/>pushed up the anus, apply to it a soft sponge, moistened with
					hot water in which the shavings of lotus have been boiled; pour of this
					decoction upon the anus by squeezing the sponge, then, bringing the shawl below
					between the legs, fasten it at the navel. But if he wish to evacuate the bowels,
					let him do so upon a very narrow night-stool. Or, if the patient be a child, let
					him be placed on the feet of a woman, with his back reclined to her knees, and
					when the bowels are evacuated, let the legs be extended. In this way the anus
					will be the least disposed to fall out. When a watery and ichorous discharge
					flows from the rectum, wash it out with burnt lees of wine, and water from
					myrtle, and having dried maiden-hair, pound and sift it, and apply as a
					cataplasm. But if there be a discharge of blood, having washed with the same,
					and pounded chalcitis, and the shavings of cypress, or of juniper, or of
					stone-pine, or of turpentine, the in equal proportions the apply as a cataplasm.
					Anoint the external parts with thick cerate. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 9</head>
				           <p> When the gut protrudes and will not remain in its place, scrape the finest and
					most compact silphium (<hi rend="ital">assafoetida?</hi>) into small pieces and
					apply as a cataplasm, and apply a sternutatory medicine to the nose and provoke
					sneezing, and having moistened pomegranate rind with hot water, and having
					powdered alum in white wine, pour it on the gut, then apply rags, bind the
					thighs together for three days, and let the patient fast, only he may drink
					sweet wine. If even thus matters do not proceed properly, having mixed
					vermillion with honey, anoint. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 10</head>
				           <p> If procidentia ani be attended with a discharge of blood, pare off the rind of
					the root of wakerobin, then pound and mix flour with it, and apply it warm as a
					cataplasm. Another: Having scraped off the rind of the most tender roots of the
					wild vine, which some call <hi rend="ital">psilothrion</hi>, boil in a dark
					austere wine undiluted; then having pounded, apply as a tepid cataplasm; but mix
					also flour and stir it up with white wine and oil in a tepid state.
					Another:-Having pounded the seed of hemlock, pour on it a fragrant white wine,
					and then apply in a tepid state as a cataplasm. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 11</head>
				           <p> But if it be inflamed, having boiled in water the root of the <pb n="p.350"/>ivy, finely powdered, and mixing the finest flour, and stirring it up with
					white wine, apply as a cataplasm, and mix up some fat with these things.
					Another:-Take the root of the mandrake, especially the green (fresh) root, but
					otherwise the dried, and having cleaned the green root and cut it down, boil in
					diluted wine, and apply as a cataplasm; but the dry may be pounded and applied
					as a cataplasm in the manner. Another:-Having bruised the inner part of a ripe
					cucumber to a soft state, apply as a cataplasm. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
				           <head>Part 12</head>
				           <p> If there be pain without inflammation, having roasted red natron, and pounded it
					to a fine powder, and added alum and roasted salts, finely triturated, mix
					together in equal proportions; then having mixed it up with the best pitch and
					spread upon a rag, apply, and bind. Another:-Having pounded the green leaves of
					capers, put into a bag and bind on the part; and when it appears to burn, take
					it away and apply it afterward; or, if you have not the leaves of capers, pound
					the rind of its roots, and having mixed it up with dark-colored wine, bind on
					the part in the same manner. This is a good application also for pains of the
					spleen. Of these poultices, those which are cooling, stop the discharge; those
					which are emollient and heating, discuss; and those which are attractive, dry up
					and attenuate. This disease is formed when bile and phlegm become seated in the
					parts. When the anus is inflamed, it should be anointed with the ointment, the
					ingredients of which are resin, oil, wax, plumbago, and suet, these being all
					melted and applied quite hot as a cataplasm.<pb n="p.351"/>
               </p>
			         </div>

		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
