<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Philosophies for Sale</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1915</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianhar02luciuoft/page/450/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.b000604154?urlappend=%3Bseq=464">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.2.p.451"/>

<head>Philosophies for Sale<note xml:lang="eng"><p>This is not a sale of philosophers, nor yet, in any ordinary sense, a sale of lives; it is a sale of various types of the philosophic life, which are to serve their buyers as models for the shaping of their own careers. For a convenient rendering, perhaps "philosophies” will do as well as any
other single word.</p>
<p>Although Lucian makes it perfectly plain that he is not selling specific philosophers, some, if not all, the manuscripts and all the editors ascribe the words of the different types to definite individuals, whereby they not only introduce confusion into the dialogue (working special havoc in the case of the Academic or Platonist type), but they completely stultify the plea which Lucian puts forward in his own defence in the Fisherman, urging that he had not criticized the leading lights of philosophy, but only the common herd of pretended philosophers. This plea is rather specious, it must be admitted, for Lucian vivifies his types again and again with biographical traits ; but we should leave him a leg to stand on, and not make him sell Pythagoras, Chrysippus and the rest in their own persons. Therefore I have substituted the names of schools for the names of individual philosophers throughout, but only in the English version: for in the Greek I have not ventured to do this without commanding fuller evidence from the manuscripts.</p>
<p>Diogenes was once taken by pirates and sold into slavery, they say, and Menippus is known to have written a Sale of Diogenes. It may be that Lucian read it and took a hint from it: he could not have taken more.</p>
<p>The order in which the different types are brought on is very effective, as Helm points out, and well deserves attention as one reads. Interesting too are the prices which they bring.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>
<label>ZEUS</label>
(To an attendant.) You arrange the benches and
make the place ready for the men that are coming.
(To another avrenpant.) You bring on the philosophies and put them in line ; but first groom them up,
so that they will look well and will attract as many
as possible. (Zo nErmeEs.) You, Hermes, be crier
and call them together.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Under the blessing of Heaven, let the buyers
now appear at the sales-room. We shall put up for
sale philosophies of every type and all manner of
creeds; and if anyone is unable to pay cash, he is to
name a surety and pay next year.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

<label>ZEUS</label>
Many are gathering, so we must avoid wasting
time and delaying them. Let us begin the sale,
then.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Which do you want us to bring on first ?
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
This fellow with the long hair, the Ionian, for he
seems to be someone of distinction.
<pb n="v.2.p.453"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
You Pythagorean, come forward and let yourself
be looked over by the company.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Hawk him now.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
The noblest of philosophies for sale, the most
distinguished ; who'll buy ? Who wants to be more
than man? Who wants to apprehend the music of
the spheres and to be born again ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
For looks, he is not bad, but what does he know
best ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Arithmetic, astronomy, charlatanry, geometry,
music and quackery; you see in him a first-class
soothsayer.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
May I question him?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Yes, and good luck to you!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>

<label>BUYER</label>
Where are you from?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
From Samos.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.453.n.1">The birthplace of Pythagoras. Hence the “‘ Pythagorean philosophy” talks Ionic Greek.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
Where were you educated ?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
In Egypt, with the sages there.

<pb n="v.2.p.455"/>

<label>BUYER</label>
Come now, if I buy you, what will you teach me?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
I shall teach thee nothing, but make thee remember.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.455.n.1">Before centering upon its round of transmigrations, the soul was all-wise ; learning is merely remembering. Socrates expounds this theory in Plato’s Jeno.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
How will you make me remember ?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
First by making thy soul pure and purging off the
filth upon it.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Well, imagine that my purification is complete,
what will be your method of making me remember?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
In the first place, long silence and speechlessness,
and for five entire years no word of talk.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
My good man, you had better teach the son of
Croesus!?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.455.n.2">One of the sons of Crocsus was mute: Herod. 1. 34, 85.</note> I want to be talkative, not a graven
image. However, what comes after the silence and
the five years?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
Thou shalt be practised in music and geometry.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
That is delightful ; I am to become a fiddler before
being wise!
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

<label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
Then, in addition to this, in counting.

<pb n="v.2.p.457"/>

<label>BUYER</label>
I know how to count now.
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
How dost thou count ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
One, two, three, four—
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
Lo! what thou thinkest four is ten, and a perfect
triangle, and our oath.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.457.n.1">Four is ten, because it contains three, two and one, and 1 2 3 4 10.  The perfect triangle is <figure/></note>
<label>BUYER</label>
Well, by your greatest oath, by Four, I never
heard diviner doctrines or more esoteric.
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
Thereafter, my friend, thou shalt learn of earth
and air and water and fire, what their flux is, and
what form they have and how they move.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Why, has fire form, or air, or water ?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
Yea, very notably, for without shape and form
there can be no motion. And in addition thou
shalt learn that God is number and mind and
harmony.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What you say is wonderful.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>

<label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
And beside all that I have said, thou shalt learn

<pb n="v.2.p.459"/>

that thou, who thinkest thyself a single individual,
art one person in semblance and another in reality.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What’s that? I am another and not this man
who now talks to you!
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
Now thou art he, but erstwhile thou didst manifest thyself in another body and under another name,
and in time thou shalt again migrate into another
person.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
You mean that I shall be immortal, changing into
many forms? But enough of this.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

How do you
stand in the matter of diet ?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
I eat nothing at all that hath life, but all else save
beans.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Why so? Do you dislike beans?
</p>
<p><label>PYTHAGOREAN</label>
Nay, but they are holy, and wonderful is their
nature. First, they are nought but seed of man, and
if thou open a bean while it is still green, thou wilt
see that it resembleth in structure the member of a
man ; and again, if thou cook it and set it in the
light of the moon for a fixed number of nights, thou
wilt make blood. But more than this, the
Athenians are wont to choose their magistrates with
beans.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.459.n.1">The offices were filled by lot, and beans were used for lots. This appears to be Lucian’s own contribution to the Pythagorean mysticism, but the other particulars are not very remote from the actual teachings of the Neo-Pythagoreans, Cf. Porphyr. Vit. Pythag., 44.</note>

<pb n="v.2.p.461"/>

<label>BUYER</label>
You have explained everything duly and sacerdotally. Come, strip, for I want to see you unclothed.
Heracles! His thigh is of gold! He seems to be a
god and not a mortal, so I shall certainly buy him.
(Yo Hermes.) What price do you sell him for ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Ten minas.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
I'll take him at that figure.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Write down the buyer’s name and where he comes
from.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
He appears to be an Italian, Zeus, one of those
who live in the neighbourhood of Croton and
Tarentum and the Greek settlements in that
quarter of the world. But there is more than one
buyer; about three hundred have bought him in
shares.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.461.n.1">A reference to the brotherhood founded by Pythagoras in Magna Grecia, which wielded great political power until it was extirpated in a general revolt about fifty years after the death of Pythagoras.</note>
<label>ZEUS</label>
Let them take him away ; let us bring on another.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>

<label>HERMES</label>
Do you want the dirty one over yonder, from the
Black Sea ?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.461.n.2">Diogenes, chief of the Cynics, came from Sinope.</note>
<label>ZEUS</label>
By all means.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
You there with the wallet slung about you, you

<pb n="v.2.p.463"/>

with the sleeveless shirt, come and walk about the
room. I offer for sale a manly philosophy, a noble
philosophy, a free philosophy ; who'll buy ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Crier, what’s that you say? Are you selling
someone who is free ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
That I am.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Then aren’t you afraid he may have the law on
you for kidnapping or even summon you to the
Areopagus ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
He doesn’t mind being sold, for he thinks that
he is free anyhow.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER </label>
What use could a man make of him, filthy as he is,
and in such a wretched condition? However, he
might be made a shoveller or a drawer of water.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Not only that, but if you make him doorkeeper,
you will find him far more trusty than a dog. In
tact, he is even called a dog.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.463.n.1">The name of the sect in Greek means doggish.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
Where is he from, and what creed does he profess ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Ask the man himself; it is better to do so.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
I am afraid of his sullen, hang-dog look; he may
bark at me if I go near him, or even bite me, by
Zeus! Don’t you see how he has his cudgel poised

<pb n="v.2.p.465"/>

and his brows bent, and scowls in a threatening,
angry way?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Don’t be afraid ; he is gentle.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>

<label>BUYER</label>
First of all, my friend, where are you from?
</p>
<p><label>CYNIC</label>
Everywhere.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What do you mean ?
</p>
<p><label>CYNIC</label>
You see in me a citizen of the world.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Whom do you take for your pattern ?
</p>
<p><label>CYNIC</label>
Heracles.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Then why don’t you wear a lion’s skin? For as
to the cudgel, you are like him in that.
</p>
<p><label>CYNIC</label>
This short cloak is my lion-skin; and I am a
soldier like him, fighting against pleasures, no conscript but a volunteer, purposing to make life clean.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
A fine purpose! But what do you know best, and
what is your business?
</p>
<p><label>CYNIC</label>
I am a liberator of men and a physician to their
ills; in short I desire to be an interpreter of truth
and free speech.


<pb n="v.2.p.467"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

<label>BUVER</label>
Very good, interpreter! But if IT buy you, what
course of training will you give me ?
</p>
<p><label>CYNIC</label>
First, after taking you in charge, stripping you of
your luxury and shackling you to want, I will puta
short cloak on you. Next I will compel you to
undergo pains and hardships, sleeping on the ground,
drinking nothing but water and filling yourself with
any food that comes your way. As for your money,
in case you have any, if you follow my advice you
will throw it into the sea forthwith. You will take
no thought for marriage or children or native land:
all that will be sheer nonsense to you, and you will
leave the house of your fathers and make your home
in atomb or a deserted tower or even a jar.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.467.n.1">As did Diogenes ; for his “tub” was really a jar.</note> Your
wallet will be full of lupines, and of papyrus rolls
written on both sides. Leading this life you
will say that you are happier than the Great King ;
and if anyone flogs you or twists you on the rack,
you will think that there is nothing painful in it.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What do you mean by not feeling pain when I am
flogged? I am not enclosed in the carapace of a
turtle or a crab !
</p>
<p><label>CYNIC</label>
You will put in practice the saying of Euripides,
slightly revised.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What saying?

<pb n="v.2.p.469"/>

<label>CYNIC</label>
Your mind will suffer, but your tongue will not.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.469.n.1">Hippol. 612: ἡ γλῶσσ᾽ ὀμώμοχ᾽, ἡ δὲ φρὴν ἀνώμοτος. (My tongue took oath ; my mind has taken none).</note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
The traits that you should possess in particular are
these : you should be impudent and bold, and should
abuse all and each, both kings and commoners, for
thus they will admire you and think you manly. Let
your language be barbarous, your voice discordant
and just like the barking of a dog: let your expression be set, and your gait consistent with your
expression. In a word, let everything about you be
bestial and savage. Put off modesty, decency and
moderation, and wipe away blushes from your face
completely. Frequent the most crowded place, and
in those very places desire to be solitary and uncommunicative, greeting nor friend nor stranger; for to
do so is abdication of the empire.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.469.n.2">Cynic and Stoic cant, meaning that a man cannot mingle with his fellows freely and still be captain of his soul.</note> Do boldly in full
view of all what another would not do in secret ;
choose the most ridiculous ways of satisfying your
lust ; and at the last, if you like, eat a raw devilfish
or squid, and die.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.469.n.3">See Downward Journey, 7, and the note (p. 15).</note> That is the bliss we vouchsafe
you.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

<label>BUYER</label>
Get out with you! The life you talk of is
abominable and inhuman.
</p>
<p><label>CYNIC</label>
But at all events it is easy, man, and no trouble
for all to follow ; for you will not need education and
doctrine and drivel, but this road is a short cut to
fame. Even if you are an unlettered man,—a tanner

<pb n="v.2.p.471"/>

or a fish-man or a carpenter or a money-changer—
there will be nothing to hinder you from being
wondered at, if only you have impudence and _ boldness and learn how to abuse people properly.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
I do not want you for any such purpose, but you
might do at a pinch for a boatman or a gardener, and
only then if my friend here is willing to sell you for
two obols at the outside.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
He’s yours: take him. We shall be glad to get
rid of him because he is annoying and loud-mouthed
and insults and abuses everybody without exception.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
<label>ZEUS</label>
Call another; the Cyrenaic in the purple cloak,
with the wreath on his head.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.471.n.1">The Cyrenaic school, which made pleasure the highest good, was founded by Aristippus, who furnished a detail or two to this caricature.</note>
<label>HERMES</label>
Come now, attend, everyone! Here we have
high-priced wares, wanting a rich buyer. Here you
are with the sweetest philosophy, the thrice-happy
philosophy! Who hankers for high living? Who'll
buy the height of luxury?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Come here and tell me what you know ; I will buy
you if you are of any use.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Don’t bother him, please, sir, and don’t question
him, for he is drunk, and so can’t answer you
because his tongue falters, as you observe.

<pb n="v.2.p.473"/>

<label>BUYER</label>
Who that is in his senses would buy so corrupt and
lawless a slave? How he reeks of myrrh, and how
he staggers and reels in his gait! But you yourself,
Hermes, might tell me what traits he has and what
his object in life is.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
In general, he is accommodating to live with, satisfactory to drink with, and handy to accompany
an amorous and profligate master when he riots
about town with a flute-girl, Moreover, he is a
connoisseur in pastries and a highly expert cook: in
short, a Professor of Luxury. He was educated in
Athens, and entered service in Sicily, at the court of
the tyrants, with whom he enjoyed high favour.
The sum and substance of his creed is to despise
everything, make use of everything and cull pleasure
from every source.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
You had better look about for someone else, among
these rich and wealthy people ; for I can’t afford to
buy a jolly life.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
It looks as if this fellow would be left on our
hands, Zeus.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>

<label>ZEUS</label>
Remove him ; bring on another—stay ! those two,
the one from Abdera who laughs and the one from
Ephesus who cries, for I want to sell them together.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.473.n.1">The Schools of Democritus of Abdera, the propounder of the atomic theory, and of Heraclitus of Ephesus, who originated the doctrine of the flux; he held that fire is the first principle, and its manifestations continually change, so that nothing isstable. Both representatives talk Ionic Greck.</note>

<pb n="v.2.p.475"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
Come down among us, you two. I sell the two
best philosophies; we offer the two that are sagest
of all.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Zeus ! What a contrast! One of thei never stops
laughing, and the other is apparently mourning a
death, as he weeps incessantly. What is the matter,
man? Why are you laughing?
</p>
<p><label>DEMOCRITEAN</label>
Dost thou need to ask? Because to me it seemeth
that all your affairs are laughable, and yourselves as
well.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What, are you laughing at us all, and do you think
nothing of our affairs?
</p>
<p><label>DEMOCRITEAN</label>
Even so; for there is nothing serious in them, but
everything is a hollow mockery, drift of atoms,
infinitude.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
No indeed, but you yourself are a hollow mockery
in very truth and an infinite ass.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>

Oh, what effrontery! Will you never stop laughing? (Zo the other.)
But you, why do youcry? For I think it is much
more becoming to talk with you.
</p>
<p><label>HERACLITEAN</label>
Because I consider, O stranger, that the affairs of
man are woeful and tearful, and there is naught in
them that is not foredoomed; therefore I pity and
grieve for men. And their present woes I do not
consider great, but those to come in future will be
wholly bitter; I speak of the great conflagrations

<pb n="v.2.p.477"/>

and the collapse of the universe. It is for this that
I grieve, and because nothing is fixed, but all things are in a manner stirred up into porridge, and joy and joylessness, wisdom and unwisdom, great and small are all but the same, circling about, up and down, and interchanging in the game of Eternity.

</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
And what is Eternity ?
</p>
<p><label>HERACLITEAN</label>
A child playing a game, moving counters, in discord, in concord.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What are men?
</p>
<p><label>HERACLITEAN</label>
Mortal gods.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
And the Gods ?
</p>
<p><label>HERACLITEAN</label>
Immortal men.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Are you telling riddles, man, or making conundrums? You are just like Apollo, for you say
nothing plainly.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.477.n.1">Heraclitus was nicknamed ὁ σκοτεινός, “the Obscure.”</note>
<label>HERACLITEAN</label>
Because you matter naught to me.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Then nobody in his sense will buy you.
</p>
<p><label>HERACLITEAN</label>
I bid ye go weep, one and all, buy you or buy you
not.

<pb n="v.2.p.479"/>

<label>BUYER</label>
This fellow’s trouble is not far removed from
insanity. However, I for my part will not buy
either of them.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
They are left unsold also.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Put up another.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
<label>HERMES</label>
Do you want the Athenian over there, who has so
much to say?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.479.n.1">Both Socrates and Plato contribute to the picture of the typical Academic. Consequently some editors, misled by the manuscripts (see introductory note) ascribe the part of Academic to Socrates, some to Plato, and some divide it between the two.</note>
<label>ZEUS</label>
By all means.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Come here, sir. We are putting up a righteous
and intelligent philosophy. Who'll buy the height
of sanctity ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Tell me what you know best ?
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
I am a lover, and wise in matters of love.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
How am I to buy you, then? What I wanted was
a tutor for my son, who is handsome.
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
But who would be more suitable than I to associate
with a handsome lad? It is not the body I love, it
is the soul that I hold beautiful. As a matter of

<pb n="v.2.p.481"/>

fact, even if they lie beneath the same cloak with
me, they will tell you that I have done them no
wrong.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.481.n.1">See Plato’s Symposium, particularly 216 p-219 D.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
I can’t believe what you say, that you, though a
lover, take no interest in anything beyond the soul,
even when you have the opportunity, lying beneath
the same cloak.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>

<label>ACADEMIC</label>
But I swear to you by the dog and the plane-tree
that this is so.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Heracles! What curious gods!
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
What is that you say? Don’t you think the dog
is a god? Don’t you know about Anubis in Egypt,
how great he is, and about Sirius in the sky and
Cerberus in the world below ?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
<label>BUYER</label>
Quite right ; I was entirely mistaken. But what
is your manner of life?
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
I dwell in a city that I created for myself, using
an imported constitution and enacting statutes of
my own.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.481.n.2">The allusion is to Plato’s Republic.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
I should like to hear one of your enactments.
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
Let me tell you the most important one, the view


<pb n="v.2.p.483"/>

that I hold about wives ; it is that none of thei shall
belong solely to any one man, but that everyone who so
desires may share the rights of the husband.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
You mean by this that you have abolished the
laws against adultery ?
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
Yes, and in a word, all this pettiness about such
matters.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What is your attitude as to pretty boys?
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
Their kisses shall be a guerdon for the bravest
after they have done some splendid, reckless deed.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18">
<p><label>BUYER</label>
My word, what generosity! And what is the gist
of your wisdom ?
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
My “ideas”; I mean the patterns of existing
things: for of everything that you behold, the
earth, with all that is upon it, the sky, the sea,
invisible images exist outside the universe.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Where do they exist ?
</p>
<p><label>ACADEMIC</label>
Nowhere ; for if they were anywhere, they would
not be.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.483.n.1">As space cannot be predicated of anything outside the univerge, it cannot be predicated of the Platonic Ideas. To do so would be to make them phenomena instead of realities, for nothing in the universe is real.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
I do not see these patterns that you speak of.


<pb n="v.2.p.485"/>

<label>ACADEMIC</label>
Of course not, for the eye of your soul is blind ;
but I see images of everything,—an invisible “you,”
another “me,” and in a word, two of everything.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Then I must buy you for your wisdom and your
sharp sight. (Zo Hermes.) Come, let’s see what price
you will make me for him?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Give me two talents.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
He is sold to me at the price you mention, But
I will pay the money later on.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
<label>HERMES</label>
What is your name?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Dion of Syracuse.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.485.n.1">Chosen for mention, because he was Plato’s pupil.</note>
<label>HERMES</label>
He is yours; take him, with good luck to you.
Epicurean, I want you now. Who will buy him?
He is a pupil of the laugher yonder and of the
drunkard, both of whom we put up a short time ago.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.485.n.2">The Epicureans took over the atomic theory from Democritus and the idea that pleasure is the highest good from the Cyrenaics.</note>
In one way, however, he knows more than they,
because he is more impious. Besides, he is agreeable
and fond of good eating.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What is his price?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Two minas.

<pb n="v.2.p.487"/>

<label>BUYER</label>
Here you are. But, say! I want to know what
food he likes.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
He eats sweets and honey-cakes, and, above all,
figs.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
No trouble about that; we shall buy him cakes of
pressed figs from Caria.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
<label>ZEUS</label>
Call another, the one over there with the cropped
head, the dismal fellow from the Porch.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Quite right; at all events it looks as if the men
who frequent the public square were waiting for him
in great numbers.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.487.n.1">Lucian means that the Stoic philosophy was in high favour with statesmen, lawyers, and men of affairs generally.</note> I sell virtue itself, the most
perfect of philosophies. Who wants to be the only
one to know everything ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What do you mean by that?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
That he is the only wise man, the only handsome
man, the only just man, brave man, king, orator,
rich man, lawgiver, and everything else that
there is.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.487.n.2">Compare <cit><quote><l>Ad summam: sapiens uno minor est Jove, dives,</l> <l>Liber, honoratus, pulcher, rex denique regum,</l> <l>Praecipue sanus,— nisi cum pituita molestast !</l></quote> <bibl>Horace, Epp. 1, I 106 ff</bibl></cit></note>
<label>BUYER</label>
Then he is the only cook,—yes and the only
tanner or carpenter, and so forth ?


<pb n="v.2.p.489"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
So it appears.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
<label>BUYER</label>
Come here, my good fellow, and tell your buyer
what you are like, and first of all whether you are
not displeased with being sold and living in slavery?
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Not at all, for these things are not in our control,
and all that is not in our control is immaterial.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
I don’t understand what you mean by this.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
What, you do not understand that of such things
some are “approved,” and some, to the contrary,
“disapproved”’ ?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.489.n.1"> Just as things "in our control” were divided into the good and the bad, so those "not in our control” were divided into the “approved” and the "disapproved,” according as they helped or hindered in the acquirement of virtue.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
Even now I do not understand.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Of course not, for you are not familiar with our
vocabulary and have not the faculty of forming concepts; but a scholar who has mastered the science of
logic knows not only this, but what predicaments
and bye-predicaments are, and how they differ from
each other.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.489.n.2">The hair-splitting Stoics distinguished four forms of predication according to the case of the (logical) subject and the logical completeness of the predicate : the direct, complete predicate, or σύμβαμα (predicament), i.e. Σωκράτης βαδίζει; the indirect, complete predicate, or παρασύμβαμα (bye-predicament), i.e. Σωκράτει μεταμέλει ; the direct, incomplete predicate, e.g. Σωκράτης φιλεῖ, and the indirect, incomplete predicate, i.e. Σωκράτει μέλει.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
In the name of wisdom, don’t begrudge telling me



<pb n="v.2.p.491"/>

at least what predicaments and bye-predicaments are ;
for I am somehow impressed by the rhythm of the
terms.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Indeed, I do not begrudge it at all. If a man who
is lame dashes his lame foot against a stone and
receives an unlooked-for injury, he was already in a
predicament, of course, with his lameness, and with
his injury he gets into a bye-predicament too.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>

<label>BUYER</label>
Oh, what subtlety! And what else do you claim to
know best ?
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
The word-snares with which I entangle those who
converse with me and stop their mouths and make
them hold their peace, putting a very muzzle on
them. This power is called the syllogism of wide
renown.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.491.n.1">The Stoics were noted for their attention to logic and in especial to fallacies. Chrysippus wrote a book on syllogisms, mentioned in the Icuromenippus (311).</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
Heracles! An invincible and mighty thing, by
what you say.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
See for yourself. Have you a child?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What of it ?
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
If a crocodile should seize it on finding it straying
beside the river, and then should promise to give it
back to you if you told him truly what he intended

<pb n="v.2.p.493"/>

to do about giving it back, what would you say he
had made up his mind to do?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.493.n.1">The commentators do not seem to have noticed that Lucian has (intentionally) spoiled the sophism by using the words δέδοικα and ἐγνωκέναι. It is perfectly possible for the father to guess what the crocodile “had made up his mind” to do, and so to get the child back: for an intention need not be executed. The crocodile should ask, ‘* Am I going to (μέλλω) give up the child?” Then, if the father answers “Yes,” he will say ‘ You are wrong,” and eat it: and if the father says “No,” he will reply “You are right; therefore I am not going to give it up.”</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
Your question is hard to answer, for I don’t know
which alternative I should follow in my reply, in
order to get back the child. Come, in Heaven’s
name answer it yourself and save the child for me,
for fear the beast may get ahead of us and devour it !
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Courage! I'll teach you other things that are more
wonderful.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What are they ?
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
The Reaper, the Master,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.493.n.2">Neither of these are accurately known. The Reaper was based on the fallacious employment of the negative, and proved that a man who was going to reap a field could not possibly reap it. Zeno, the founder of the Stoic school, is said to have paid 200 minas to a logician who taught him seven varieties of this fallacy. The Master consisted of four propositions, of which you could take any three and disprove the fourth.</note> and above all, the Electra
and the Veiled Figure.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What do you mean by the Veiled Figure and the
Electra ?
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
The Electra is the famous Electra, the daughter of
Agamemnon, who at once knew and did not know
the same thing; for when Orestes stood beside her
before the recognition she knew that Orestes was



<pb n="v.2.p.495"/>

her brother, but did not know that this was Orestes.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.495.n.1">Here again Lucian does scant justice to the fallacy, which he really gives away by his statement of it. It should run: ‘she at once knew and did not know that Orestes was her brother, for she did not know that this man was her brother; but this man was Orestes.”</note>
As to the Veiled Figure, you shall hear a very
wonderful argument. Tell me, do you know your
own father ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Yes.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
But if I put a veiled figure before you and asked
you if you know him, what will you say?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
That I don’t, of course.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>

<label>STOIC</label>
But the veiled figure turns out to be your own
father ; so if you don’t know him, you evidently don’t
know your own father.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Not so: I should unveil him and find out the
truth! But to go on—what is the purpose of your
wisdom, and what shall you do when you reach the
summit of virtue ?
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
I shall then devote myself to the chief natural
goods, I mean wealth, health, and the like.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.495.n.2">As the Stoics set great store by “living in harmony with nature,” they divided “things which did not matter” into the “acceptable” and the ‘ unacceptable” according  as they were in or out of harmony with the natural wants of man. This did not supersede the classification alluded to above, but was convenient because it enabled them to dispose of certain things which were hard to classify on the other basis. For instance, a good complexion is neither “approved” nor "disapproved” as an aid to the acquirement of virtue, but it is in harmony with nature, and therefore “‘ acceptable.” Hence the Stoics were often accused (as they are constantly accused by indirection in this dialogue) of setting up a double standard.</note> But
first I must go through many preparatory toils,
whetting my eyesight with closely-written books,



<pb n="v.2.p.497"/>

collecting learned comments and stufting myself with
solecisms and uncouth words; and to cap all, a man
may not become wise until he has taken the hellebore
treatment three times running.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.497.n.1">A hit at Chrysippus. Hellebore was the specific for insanity, and rumour said that Chrysippus had taken the treatment three times (cf. True Story, 2, 18).</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
These projects of yours are noble and dreadfully
courageous. But tobe a Gnipho and a usurer—for I
see that this is one of your traits too—what shall we
say of this? That it is the mark of a man who has
already taken his hellebore-treatment and is consumuinate in virtue ?
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Yes; at any rate money-lending is especially
appropriate to a wise man, for as drawing inferences
is a specialty of his, and as money-lending and
drawing interest is next-door to drawing inferences,
the one, like the other, belongs particularly to the
scholar: and not only getting simple interest, like
other people, but interest upon interest. For don’t
you know that there is a first interest and a second
interest, the offspring,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.497.n.2">A play upon τάκος, which is literally "offspring.”</note> as it were, of the first? And
you surely perceive what logic says: “If he gets
the first interest, he will get the second; but he
will get the first, ergo he will get the second.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

<label>BUYER</label>
Then we are to say the same of the fees that you
get for your wisdom from young men, and obviously
none but the scholar will get paid for his virtue ?


<pb n="v.2.p.499"/>

<label>STOIC</label>
Your understanding of the matter is correct. You
see, I donot take pay on my own account, but for the
sake of the giver himself: for since there are two
classes of men, the disbursive and the receptive, I
train myself to be receptive and my pupil to be
disbursive.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
On the contrary, the young man ought to be
receptive and you, who alone are rich, disbursive !
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
You are joking, man. Look out that I don’t shoot
you with my indemonstrable syllogism.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.499.n.1">Indemonstrable in the sense that its propositions do not require demonstration, or indeed admit of it.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
What have I to fear from that shaft ?
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Perplexity and aphasia and a sprained intellect.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>

But the great thing is that if I wish I can turn you
into a stone forthwith.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
How will you turn me into a stone? You are not
a Perseus, I think, my dear fellow.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
In this way. Isa stone a substance?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Yes.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
And how about this—is not an animal a substance ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Yes.

<pb n="v.2.p.501"/>

<label>STOIC</label>
And you are an animal ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
So it appears, anyhow.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Then you are a substance, and therefore a stone !
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Don’t say that! Distribute my middle, for
Heaven’s sake, and make me a man again.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
That is not difficult. Be a man once more !—Tell
me, is every substance an animal?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
No.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Well, is a stone an animal?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
No.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
You are a substance?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Yes.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
But even if you are a substance, you are an animal.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Yes.
</p>
<p><label>STOIC</label>
Then you are not a stone, being an animal.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Thank you kindly ; my legs were already as cold
and solid as Niobe’s. Iwill buy you. (Zo uunmes.)
How much have I to pay for him?

<pb n="v.2.p.503"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
Twelve minas.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Here you are.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Are you the sole purchaser ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
No, indeed; there are all these men whom you
see.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Yes, there are many of them, heavy-shouldered
fellows, fit associates for the Reaper.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
<label>ZEUS</label>
Don’t delay ; call another, the Peripatetic.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
(To renivatetic.) I say, you who are handsome,
you who are rich! (Yo the buyers.) Come now,
buy the height of intelligence, the one who knows
absolutely everything !
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What is he like!
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Moderate, gentlemanly, adaptable in his way of
living, and, what is more, he is double.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What do you mean?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Viewed from the outside, he seems to be one man,
and from the inside, another ; so if you buy him, be
sure to call the one self “exoteric” and the
other “esoteric.”
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What does he know best ?

<pb n="v.2.p.505"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
That goods are threefold, in the soul, in the body,
and in things external.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.505.n.1">Aristotle, Hth. Nicom. A, 8, 1098 b.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
He has common sense. How much is he?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Twenty minas.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Your price is high.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Not so, bless you, for he himself appears to have a
bit of money, so you can’t be too quick about buying
him. Besides, he will tell you at once how long a
gnat lives, how far down into the sea the sunlight
reaches, and what the soul of an oyster is like.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Heracles, what insight !
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
What if I should tell you of other information
demanding far keener vision, about sperm and
conception and the shaping of the embryo in the
womb, and how man is a creature that laughs, while
asses do not laugh, and neither do they build houses
nor sail boats.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
This is high and helpful information that you tell
of, so I shall buy him for the twenty minas.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg024.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>

<label>HERMES</label>
Very well.
</p>
<p><label>ZEUS</label>
Whom have we left ?

<pb n="v.2.p.507"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
This Sceptic is still on our hands. Reddy,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.507.n.1">Pyrrhias (Reddy) is a slave name, brought in for the sake of the pun on the name of the founder of the Sceptic school, Pyrrho.</note> come
here and be put up without delay. The crowd
is already drifting away, and there will be but few
at his sale. However,—who'll buy this one?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
I will. But first tell me, what do you know?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
Nothing.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What do you mean by that?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
That in my opinion nothing at all exists.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Then do not we exist ?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
I don’t even know that.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Not even that you yourself exist ?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
I am far more uncertain about that.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Oh, what a state of doubt? But what are these
scales of yours for ?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
I weigh arguments in them and make them
balance one another, and when I see they are

<pb n="v.2.p.509"/>

precisely alike and equal in weight, then, ah! then
I do not know which is the truer.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
What else can you do fairly well ?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
Everything except catch a runaway slave.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Why can’t you do that?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
Because, my dear sir, I am unable to apprehend
anything.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.509.n.1">The same joke is cracked by Lucian in the True Story, 2, 18, at the expense of the New Academy.</note>
<label>BUYER</label>
Of course, for you look to be slow and lazy. But
what is the upshot of your wisdom ?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
Ignorance, and failure of hearing and vision.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Then you mean being both deaf and blind?
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
Yes, and devoid of judgement and feeling, and, in a
word, no better than a worm.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
I must buy you for that reason. (Zo uenmes.)
How much may I call him worth?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
An Attie mina.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Here you are. (Yo scertic.) What have you to
say, fellow? Have I bought you?

<pb n="v.2.p.511"/>

<label>SCEPTIC</label>
Doubtful.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
No, indeed, I have bought you and paid the price
in cash.
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
I am suspending judgement on that point and
thinking it over.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Come now, fellow, walk along behind me as my
servant should.
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
Who knows if what you say is true?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
The crier, the mina, and the men present.
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
Is there anyone here present ?
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
Come, I'll chuck you into the mill and convince
you that I am your master, with sorry logic!
</p>
<p><label>SCEPTIC</label>
Suspend judgement on that point.
</p>
<p><label>BUYER</label>
No, by Heaven! I have already affirmed my
judgement.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
(To scertic.) Stop hanging back and go with
your buyer. (Zo the company.) We invite you all
here to-morrow, for we intend to put up for sale the
careers of laymen, workingmen, and tradesmen.
</p>
</div></div>
</body></text></TEI>

