<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">On Salaried Posts in Great Houses</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor>Austin Morris Harmon, 1878-1950</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>OCRd, tagged and added initial corrections to  the text</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg001.1st1K-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1921</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202137">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
<head>On Salaried Posts in Great Houses<note><p>A Hogarthian sketch of the life led by educated Greeks
who attached themselves to the households of great Roman
lords—and ladies. Lucian feigns to be advising a young
friend, whom he dubs Timocles (Master Ambitious), against
such a career—a most effective stratagem, sirice by giving
him a pretext for his criticism, it relieves him from all
semblance of personal animus and even enables him to appear
sympathetic toward the varlets while he dusts their jackets.</p>
<p>In after years, when Lucian went into the. Roman civil
service in Egypt, this essay rose up to haunt him, and he
had to write his Apology in order to lay its ghost.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

"Where shall I make a beginning,” my friend,
“and where make an end of relating”<note n="v.3.p.413.n.1"><p>Cf. Odyssey9, 14.  </p></note> all that must
be done and suffered by those who take salaried posts
and are put on trial in the friendship of our wealthy
men—if the name of friendship may be applied to
that sort of slavery on their part? Iam familiar with
much, I may say most, of their experiences, not
because I myself have ever tried anything of that kind,
for it never became a necessity for me to try it, and,
ye gods! I pray it never may ; but many of those who
have blundered into this existence have talked to me
freely, some, who were still in their misery, bewailing
the many bitter sufferings which they were then
undergoing, and others, who had broken jail, as it
were, recalling not without pleasure those they had
undergone ; in fact they joyed in recounting what
they had escaped from.</p>

<p>
These latter were the more trustworthy because
they had gone through all the degrees of the ritual, so
to speak, and had been initiated into everything from
beginning to end. So it was not without interest
and attention that I listened to them while they
spun yarns about their shipwreck and unlooked-for
deliverance, just like the men with shaven heads who
gather in crowds at the temples and tell of third
waves, tempests, headlands, strandings, masts carried


<pb n="v.3.p.415"/>

away, rudders broken, and to cap it all, how the T win
Brethren appeared (they are peculiar to this sort
of rhodomontade), or how some other deus ex machina
sat on the masthead or stood at the helm and
steered the ship to a soft beach where she might
break up gradually and slowly and they themselves
get ashore safely by the grace and favour of the god.
Those men, to be sure, invent the greater part of
their tragical histories to meet their temporary need,
in order that they may receive alms from a greater
number of people by seeming not only unfortunate
but dear to the gods;

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

 but when the others told of
household tempests and third waves—yes, by Zeus,
fifth and tenth waves, if one may say so—and how
they first sailed in, with the sea apparently calm, and
how many troubles they endured through the whole
voyage by reason of thirst or sea-sickness or inundations of brine, and finally how they stove their unlucky lugger on a submerged ledge or a sheer
pinnacle and swam ashore, poor fellows, in a wretched
plight, naked and in want of every necessity—in
these adventures and their account of them it seemed
to me that they concealed the greater part out of
shame, and voluntarily forgot it.
</p>

<p>
For my part I shall not hesitate to tell you everything, my dear Timocles, not only their stories but
whatever else I find by logical inference to be
characteristic of such household positions ; for I think
I detected long ago that you are entertaining designs

<pb n="v.3.p.417"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
upon that life. I detected it first one time when our
conversation turned to that theme, and then someone
of the company praised this kind of wage-earning,
saying that men were thrice happy when, besides
having the noblest of the Romans for their friends,
eating expensive dinners without paying any scot,
living in a handsome establishment, and travelling in
all comfort and luxury, behind a span of white horses,
perhaps, with their noses in the air,<note n="v.3.p.417.n.1"><p>That this is the meaning of éurriaCovres, and not “lolling at ease,” is clear from Book-Collector 21 and Downward Journey 16.  </p></note> they could also
get no inconsiderable amount of pay for the friendship
which they enjoyed and the kindly treatment which
they received ; really everything grew without sowing
and ploughing for such as they. When you heard all
that and more of the same nature, I saw how you
gaped at it and held your mouth very wide open for
the bait.</p>

<p>
In order, then, that as far as I am concerned I may
be free from blame in future and you may not be
able to say that when I saw you swallowing up that
great hook along with the bait I did not hold you
back or pull it away before it got into your throat or
give you forewarning, but waited until I saw you
dragged along by it and forcibly haled away when at
last it was pulled and had set itself firmly, and then,
when it was no use, stood and wept—in order that you
may not say this, which would be a very sound plea if
you should say it, and impossible for me to controvert
on the ground that I had done no wrong by not
warning you in advance—listen to everything at the
outset; examine the net itself and the impermeability of the pounds beforehand, from the outside at


<pb n="v.3.p.419"/>

your leisure, not from the inside after you are in the
fyke ; take in your hands the bend of the hook and
the barb of its point, and the tines of the harpoon ;
puff out your cheek and try them on it, and if they
do not prove very keen and unescapable and painful
in one’s wounds, pulling hard and gripping irresistibly,
then write me down a coward who goes hungry for
that reason, and, exhorting yourself to be bold,
attack your prey if you will, swallowing the bait
whole like a gull!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

The whole story will be told for your sake, no
doubt, in the main, but it will concern not only
students of philosophy like yourself, and those who
have chosen one of: the more strenuous vocations in
life, but also grammarians, rhetoricians, musicians, and
ina word all who think fit to enter families and serve
for hire as educators. Since the experiences of all
are for the most part common and similar, it is clear
that the treatment accorded the philosophers, so far
from being preferential, is more contumelious for
being the same, if it is thought that what is good
enough for the others is good enough for them, and
they are not handled with any greater respect by
their paymasters. Moreover, the blame for whatever the discussion itself brings out in its advance
ought to be given primarily to the men themselves
who do such things and secondarily to those who put
up with them. I am not to blame, unless there is
something censurable in truth and frankness.</p>

<p>
As to those who make up the rest of the mob, such
as athletic instructors and parasites, ignorant, pettyminded, naturally abject fellows, it is not worth while
to try to turn them away from such household positions, for they would not heed, nor indeed is it proper
to blame them for not leaving their paymasters,


<pb n="v.3.p.421"/>

however much they may be insulted by them, for
they are adapted to this kind of occupation and not
too good for it. Besides, they would not have anything else to which they might turn in order to keep
themselves busy, but if they should be deprived ot
this, they would be without a trade at once and out
of work and superfluous. So they themselves cannot
suffer any wrong nor their employers be thought
insulting for using a pot, as the saying goes, for a
pot’s use. They enter households in the first instance
to encounter this insolence, and it is their trade to
bear and tolerate it. But in the case of the educated
men whom I mentioned before, it is worth while to
be indignant and to put forth every effort to bring
them back and redeem them to freedom.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
It seems to me that I should do well to examine in
advance the motives for which some men go into
this sort of life and show that they are not at all
urgent or necessary. In that way their defence and
the primary object of their voluntary slavery would
be done away with in advance. Most of them plead
their poverty and their lack of necessities, and think
that in this way they have set up an adequate screen
for their desertion to this life. They consider that it
quite suffices them if they say that they act pardonably in seeking to escape poverty, the bitterest thing
in life. Then Theognis comes to hand, and time and
again we hear :
“All men held in subjection to Poverty,”<note n="v.3.p.421.n.1"><p><cit> <quote> <l>ἄνδρ᾽ ἀγαθὸν πενίη πάντων δάμνησι μάλιστα,</l> <l>καὶ γήρως πολιοῦ, Κύρνε, καὶ ἠπιάλου,</l> <l>ἣν δὴ χρὴ φεύγοντα καὶ ἐς βαθυκήτεα πόντον</l> <l>ῥιπτεῖν καὶ πετρέων, Κύρνε, κατ᾽ ἠλιβάτων.</l> <l>καὶ γὰρ ἀνὴρ πενίῃ δεδμημένος οὔτε τι εἰπεῖν</l> <l>οὐθ᾽ ἕρξαι δύναται, γλῶσσα δέ οἱ δέδεται.</l></quote> <bibl>Theognis 173 ff.</bibl> </cit></p></note>


<pb n="v.3.p.423"/>

and all the other alarming statements about poverty
that the most spiritless of the poets have put forth.</p>

<p>
If I saw that they truly found any refuge from
poverty in such household positions, I should not
quibble with them in behalf of excessive liberty ; but
when they receive what resembles “the diet of invalids,” as our splendid orator once said,<note n="v.3.p.423.n.1"><p>Demosthenes3, 33.  </p></note> how can one
avoid thinking that even in this particular they are ill
advised, inasmuch as their condition in life always
remains the same? They are always poor, they must
continue to receive, there is nothing put by, no
surplus to save: on the contrary, what is given, even
if it is given, even if payment is received in full, is all
spent to the last copper and without satisfying their
need. It would have been better not to excogitate
any such measures, which keep poverty going by
simply giving first aid against it, but such as will do
away with it altogether—yes, and to that end perhaps
even .to plunge into the deep-bosomed sea if one
must, Theognis, and down precipitous cliffs, as you ~
say. But if a man who is always poor and needy
and on an allowance thinks that thereby he has
escaped poverty, I do not know how one can avoid
thinking that such a man deludes himself.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
Others say that poverty in itself would not frighten
or cow them.if they could get their daily bread by
working like the rest, but as things are, since their
bodies have been debilitated by old age or by illnesses,
they have resorted to this form of wage-earning,
which is the easiest. Come, then, let us see if what
they say is true and they secure their gifts easily,
without working much, or any more than the rest.
It would indeed be a godsend to get money readily


<pb n="v.3.p.425"/>

without toiling and moiling. As a matter of fact,
the thing cannot even be put into adequate words.
They toil and moil so much in their household positions that they need better health there and need
health more than anything else for that occupation,
since there are a thousand things every day that
fret the body and wear it down to the lowest depths
of despair. We shall speak of these at the proper
time, when we recount their other hardships. For —
the present it is enough to indicate that those
who allege this reason for selling themselves are not
telling the truth either.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
One motive remains, which is exceedingly genuine
but not mentioned at all by them, namely, that they
plunge into these households for the sake of pleasure
and on account of their many extravagant expectations, dazzled by the wealth of gold and silver,
enraptured over the dinners and the other forms of
indulgence, and assured that they will immediately
drink gold in copious draughts, and that nobody
will stop their mouths. That is what seduces them
and makes them slaves instead of freemen—not
lack of necessaries, as they alleged, but desire for unnecessaries and envy of that abundance and luxury.
Therefore, like unsuccessful and unhappy lovers,
they fall into the hands of shrewd, experienced
minions who treat them superciliously, taking good
care that they shall always love them, but not permitting them ta enjoy the objects of their affection
even to the extent of a meagre kiss; for they know
that success will involve the dissolution of love. So
they hold that under lock and key and guard it
jealously, but otherwise they keep their lover always
hopeful, since they fear that despair may wean him

<pb n="v.3.p.427"/>

from his overmastering desire, and that he may grow
out of love for them. They smile upon him, then,
and make promises, and are always on the point of
being good to him, and generous, and lavish with
their attentions. Then before they know it, they
both are old, the one has passed the season for
loving, the other for yielding to love. Consequently
they have done nothing in all their life except to
hope.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
Now to put up with everything on account of
desire for pleasure is perhaps not altogether blameworthy, even excusable, if a man likes pleasure and
makes it his aim above all else to partake of it. Yet
perhaps it is shameful and ignoble for him to sell
himself on that account ; for the pleasure of freedom
is far sweeter. Nevertheless, let us grant that he
would be excusable in a measure, if he obtained it.
But to put up with many unpleasantnesses just on
account of the hope of pleasure is ridiculous in my
opinion and senseless, particularly when men see
that the discomforts are definite and patent in
advance and inevitable, while the pleasure that is
hoped for, whatever it is, has never yet come in all
the past, and what is more, is not even likely to
come in the future, if one should figure the matter
out on the basis of hard fact. The companions: of
Odysseus neglected all else because they were eating
the lotus and found it sweet, and they contemned
what was honourable because they contrasted it
with their immediate pleasure ; therefore it was not
entirely unreasonable of them to forget honour while
their souls dwelt upon that sweetness. But for a
man in hunger to stand beside another who eats his
fill of lotus without giving him any, and to be chained

<pb n="v.3.p.429"/>

to the spot, forgetful of all that is honourable and
right, by the mere hope that he himself may get a
taste some day—Heracles! how ridiculous and in
very truth deserving of a proper Homeric thrashing!<note n="v.3.p.429.n.1"><p>Like that bestowed upon Thersites by Odysseus (Iliad2, 199, 265).  </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
Well, the motives which attract them to these
household positions, which cause them to put themselves eagerly into the power of the rich to treat as
they will, are these or as near as may be to these,
unless one should think it worth while to mention also
those men who are impelled by the mere name of
associating with men of noble family and high social
position. There are people who think that even
this confers distinction and exalts them above the
masses, just as in my own case, were it even the
Great King, merely to associate with him and to be
seen associating with him without getting any real
benefit out of the association would not be acceptable
to me.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
So much for their object. Let us now consider
between ourselves what they put up with before
they are received and gain their end, and what they
endure when they are fairly in the thing, and to cap
the climax, what the outcome of the drama proves to
be. For surely it cannot be said that even if all this
is unworthy, at least it is easy to get and will not
call for much trouble; that you need only wish, and
then the whole thing is accomplished for you without
any effort. No, it calls for much running hither and
thither, and for continual camping on doorsteps ;
you must get up early and wait about ; meanwhile
you are elbowed, you are kept locked out, you are
sometimes thought impudent and annoying, you are


<pb n="v.3.p.431"/>

subordinate to a door-man with a vile Syrian accent
and to a Libyan master of ceremonies, and you tip
them for remembering your name. Moreover you
must provide yourself with clothing beyond the
means at your command, to correspond with the
dignity of the man whom you are cultivating, and
choose whatever colours he likes in order that you
may not be out of harmony or in discord when he
looks at you, and you must follow him zealously, or
rather, lead the way, shoved on by the servants and
filling out a guard of honour, as it were.</p>
<p>
But your man does not even look at you for many
days on end. And if ever you have a rare stroke of
luck—

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
if he sees you, calls you up and asks you a
casual question, then, ah! then you sweat profusely,
your head swims confusedly, you tremble inopportunely, and the company laughs at you for your
embarrassment. Many a time, when you should
reply to the question: “Who was the king of the
Achaeans,” you say, “They had a thousand ships!”
Good men call this modesty, forward men cowardice,
and unkind men lack of breeding. So, having found
the beginning of friendly relations very unstable
footing, you go away doomed by your own verdict
to great despair.</p>

<p>
When “many a sleepless night you have pillowed”
and have lived through “many a blood-stained day,”<note n="v.3.p.431.n.1"><p>Iliad9, 325. </p></note>
not for the sake of Helen or of Priam’s Trojan
citadel, but the five obols that you hope for, and
when you have secured the backing of a tragedy
god,<note n="v.3.p.431.n.2"><p>Some person, as opportune and powerful as a deus ex machina, to press your suit.  </p></note> there follows an examination to see if you are
learned in the arts. For the rich man that way of



<pb n="v.3.p.433"/>

passing time is not unpleasant, since he is praised
and felicitated, but you feel that you have then
before you the struggle for your life and for your
entire existence, for the thought of course steals into
your mind that no one else would receive you if you
were rejected by his predecessor and considered
unacceptable. So you cannot help being infinitely
distracted then; for you are jealous of your rivals
(let us suppose that there are others competing with
you for the same object); you think that everything you yourself have said has been inadequate,
you fear, you hope, you watch his face with straining
eyes; if he scouts anything you say, you are in distress, but if he smiles as he listens, you rejoice and
become hopeful.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
No doubt there are many who side
against you and favour others in your stead, and
each of them stealthily shoots at you, so to speak,
from ambush. Then too imagine a man with a long
beard and grey hair undergoing examination to see
if he knows anything worth while, and some thinking that he does, others that he does not!</p>

<p>
Then a period intervenes, and your whole past life
is pried into. If a fellow-countryman. out of jealousy
or a neighbour offended for some insignificant reason
says, when questioned, that you are a follower of
women or boys, there they have it ! the witness speaks
by the book of Zeus; but if all with one accord
commend you, they are considered questionable,
dubious, and suborned. You must have great good
fortune, then, and no opposition at all; for that is
the only way in which you can win.</p>

<p>
Well, suppose you have been fortunate in everything beyond your fondest hopes. The master himself has commended your discussions, and those of


<pb n="v.3.p.435"/>

his friends whom he holds in the highest esteem
and trusts most implicitly in such matters have not
advised him against you. Besides, his wife is willing,
and neither his attorney nor his steward objects, nor
has anyone criticized your past; everything is
propitious and from every point of view the omens
are good.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
You have won, then, lucky man, and
have gained the Olympic crown—nay, you have
taken Babylon or stormed the citadel of Sardis ; you
shall have the horn of Plenty and fill your pails with
pigeon’s milk. It is indeed fitting that in return for
all your labours you should have the very greatest of
blessings, in order that your crown may not be mere
leaves ; that your salary should be set at a considerable figure and paid you when you need it, without
ado; that in other ways you should be honoured
beyond ordinary folk; that you should get respite
from your former exertions and muddiness and
running about and loss of sleep, and that in accordance
with your prayer you should “sleep with your legs
stretched out,”<note n="v.3.p.435.n.1"><p>A proverbial expression for ‘“taking it easy.”   </p></note> doing only what you were engaged
for at the outset and what you are paid for. That
ought to be the way of it, Timocles, and there would
be no great harm in stooping and bearing the yoke
if it were light and comfortable and, best of all, gilded'
But the case is very different—yes, totally different.
There are thousands of things insupportable to a free
man that take place even after one has entered the
household. Consider for yourself, as you hear a list
of them, whether anyone could put up with them
who is even to the slightest degree cultured.


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
I shall
begin, if you like, with the first dinner which will be


<pb n="v.3.p.437"/>

given you, no doubt, as a formal prelude to your
future intimacy.</p>

<p>
Very soon, then, someone calls, bringing an invitation to the dinner, a servant not unfamiliar with
the world, whom you must first propitiate by slipping
at least five drachmas into his hand casually so as not
to appear awkward. He puts on airs and murmurs:
“Tut, tut ! I take money from you?” ane : “Heracles!
I hope it may never come to that !"; but in the end
he is prevailed upon and goes away with a broad grin
at your expense. Providing yourself with clean
clothing and dressing yourself as neatly as you can,
you pay your visit to the bath and go, afraid of
getting there before the rest, for that would be
gauche, just as to come last would be ill-mannered. So
you wait until the middle moment of the right time,
and then go in. He receives you with much distinction, and someone takes you in charge and gives
you a place at table a little above the rich man, with
perhaps two of his old friends.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
As though you had
entered the mansion of Zeus, you admire everything
and are amazed at all that is done, for everything is
strange and unfamiliar to you. The servants stare
at you, and everybody in the company keeps an eye
on you to see what you are going to do. Even the
rich man himself is not without concern on this score ;
he has previously directed some of the servants to
watch whether you often gaze from afar at his sons
or his wife. The attendants of your fellow-guests,
seeing that you are impressed, crack jokes about
your unfamiliarity with what is doing and conjecture

<pb n="v.3.p.439"/>

that you have never before dined anywhere because
your napkin is new.<note n="v.3.p.439.n.1"><p>Guests brought their own napkins. </p></note>
As is natural, then, you inevitably break out in a
cold sweat for perplexity ; you do not dare to ask for
something to drink when you are thirsty for fear of
being thought a toper, and you do not know which
of the dishes that have been put before you in great
variety, made to be eaten in a definite order, you should
put out your hand to get first, or which second ; so you
will be obliged to cast stealthy glances at your neighbour, copy him, and find out the proper sequence of
the dinner.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="16"><p>

In general, you are in a chaotic state
and your soul is full of agitation, for you are lost in
amazement at everything that goes on. Now you
call Dives lucky for his gold and his ivory and all his
luxury, and now you pity yourself for imagining that
you are alive when you are really nothing at all.
Sometimes, too, it comes into your head that you are
going to lead an enviable life, since you will revel in
all that and share in it equally; you expect to enjoy
perpetual Bacchic revels. Perhaps, too, pretty boys
waiting upon you and faintly smiling at you paint the
picture of your future life in more attractive colours,
so that you are forever quoting that line of Homer:

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>Small blame to the fighters of Troy and the brightgreaved men of Achaea<note n="v.3.p.439.n.2"><p>Said of Helen by the Trojan elders. They continue, ; <cit> <quote>     <l>That for a woman like this they long have endured tribulations.</l> </quote> <bibl>Iliad 3, 157</bibl> </cit> </p></note></l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad3, 156</bibl>
</cit>


that they endure great toil and suffering for such
happiness as this.
Then come the toasts, and, calling for a large bowl,



<pb n="v.3.p.441"/>

he drinks your health, addressing you as “the
professor” or whatever it may be. You take the
bowl, but because of inexperience you do not know
that you should say something in reply, and you get
a bad name for boorishness.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="17"><p>

Moreover, that toast
has made many of his old friends jealous of you,
some of whom you had previously offended when the
places at table were assigned because you, who had
only just come, were given precedence over men
who for years had drained the dregs of servitude.
So at once they begin to talk about you after this
fashion: “That was still left for us in addition to
our other afflictions, to play second fiddle to men
who have just come into the household, and it is only
these Greeks who have the freedom of the city of
Rome. And yet, why is it that they are preferred
to us? Isn't it true that they think they confer a
tremendous benefit by turning wretched phrases ?”’
Another says: “Why, didn’t you see how much he
drank, and how he gathered in what was set before
him and devoured it? The fellow has no manners,
and is starved to the limit; even in his dreams he
never had his fill of white bread, not to speak of
guinea fowl] or pheasants, of which he has hardly
left us the bones:”’ A third observes: “You silly
asses, in less than five days you will see him here
in the midst of us making these same complaints.
Just now, like a new pair of shoes, he is receiving acertain amount of consideration and attention, but
when he has been used again and again and is
smeared with mud, he will be thrown under the bed
in a wretched state, covered with vermin like the
rest of us.”</p>

<p>
Well, as I say, they go on about you indefinitely in

<pb n="v.3.p.443"/>

that vein, and perhaps even then some of them are
getting ready for a campaign of slander.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

Anyhow,
that whole dinner-party is yours, and most of the
conversation is about you. For your own part, as you
have drunk more than enough subtle, insidious wine
because you ‘were not used to it, you have been
uneasy for a long time and are in a bad way: yet
it is not good form to leave early and not safe
to stay where you are. So, as the drinking is prolonged and subject after subject is discussed and
entertainment after entertainment is brought in (for
he wants to show you all his wealth !), you undergo
great punishment ; you cannot see what takes place,
and if this or that lad who is held in very great
esteem sings or plays, you cannot hear; you applaud
perforce while you pray that an earthquake may
tumble the whole establishment into a heap or that
a great fire may be reported, so that the party may
break up at last.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
So goes, then, my friend, that first and sweetest of
dinners, which to me at least is no sweeter than
thyme and white salt eaten in freedom, when I like
and as much as I like.</p>

<p>
To spare you the tale of the flatulency that follows
and the sickness during the night, early in the morning you two will be obliged to come to terms with
one another about your stipend, how much you are to
receive and at what time of year. So with two or
three of his friends present, he summons you, bids
you to be seated, and opens the conversation: ‘ You
have already seen what our establishment is like, and
that there is not a bit of pomp and circumstance in
it, but everything is unostentatious, prosaic, and ordiriary. You must feel that we shall have everything in

<pb n="v.3.p.445"/>

common ; for it would be ridiculous if I trusted you
with what is most important, my own soul or that of
my children”—suppose he has children who need
instruction—‘“and did not consider you equally free
to command everything else. But there should be
some stipulation. I recognise, to be sure, that you
are temperate and independent by nature, and am
aware that you did not join our household through
hope of pay but on account of the other things, the
friendliness that we shall show you and the esteem
which you will have from everyone. Nevertheless,
let there be some stipulation. Say yourself what you
wish, bearing in mind, my dear fellow, what we shall
probably give you on the annual feast-days. We
shall not forget such matters, either, even though we
do not now reckon them in, and there are many such
occasions in the year, as you know. So, if you take
all that into consideration, you will of course charge
us with a more moderate stipend. Besides, it would
well become you men of education to be superior to
money.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="20"><p>

By saying this and putting you all in a flutter
with expectations, he has made you submissive
to him. You formerly dreamed of thousands and
millions and whole farms and tenements, and you are
somewhat conscious of his meanness; nevertheless,
you welcome his promise with dog-like joy, and think
his “We shall have everything in common”’ reliable
and truthful, not knowing that this sort of thing

<cit>
<quote>
    <l>“Wetteth the lips, to be sure, but the palate it
leaveth unwetted.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad22, 495.</bibl>
</cit>

In the end, out of modesty, you leave it to him. He


<pb n="v.3.p.447"/>

himself refuses to say, but tells one of the friends
who are present to intervene in the business and
name a sum that would be neither burdensome to
~ him, with many other expenses more urgent than this,
nor paltry to the recipient. The friend, a sprightly
old man, habituated to flattery from his boyhood,
says: ‘* You cannot say, sir, that you are not the
luckiest man in the whole city. In the first place
you have been accorded a privilege which many who
covet it greatly would hardly be able to obtain from
Fortune ; I mean in being honoured with his company, sharing his hospitality, and being received into
the first household in the Roman Empire. This is
better.than the talents of Croesus and the wealth of
Midas, if you know how to be temperate. Perceiving
that many distinguished men, even if they had to
pay for it, would like, simply for the name of the
thing, to associate with this gentleman and be seen
about* him in the guise of companions and friends, I
cannot sufficiently congratulate you on your good luck,
since you are actually to receive pay for such felicity.
I think, then, that unless you are very prodigal,
~ about so and so much is enough”—and he names
a very scanty sum, in striking contrast to those
expectations of yours.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
You must be content, how-
“ever, for it would not even be possible for you to get
away, now that you are in the paddock. So you
take the bit with your eyes shut, and in the beginning you answer his touch readily, as he does not pull
hard or spur sharply until you have imperceptibly
grown quite used to him.</p>

<p>
People on the outside envy you after that, seeing
that you live within the pale and enter without let
and have become a notable figure in the inner circle.

<pb n="v.3.p.449"/>

You yourself do not yet see why you seem to them
to be fortunate. Nevertheless, you are joyous and
delude yourself, and are always thinking that the
future will turn out better. But the reverse of what
you expected comes about: as the proverb has it,
the thing goes Mandrobulus-wise,<note n="v.3.p.449.n.1"><p>"This Mandrobulus once found a treasure in Samos and dedicated to Hera a golden sheep, and in the second year one of silver, and in the third, one of bronze.” Scholia, </p></note> diminishing every
day, almost, and dropping back.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
Slowly and
gradually, therefore, as if you could then distinguish
things for the first time in the indistinct light, you
begin to realize that those golden hopes were
nothing but gilded bubbles, while your labours are
burdensome and genuine, inexorable and continuous.
“What are they?” perhaps you will ask me: “J.
do not see what there is in such posts that is
laborious, nor can I imagine what those wearisome
and insupportable things are that you spoke of.”<note n="v.3.p.449.n.2"><p>In chapter 13.   </p></note>
Listen, then, my worthy friend, and do not simply
try to find out whether there is any weariness im the
thing, but give its baseness and humility and general
slavishness more than incidental consideration in the
hearing.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
First of all, remember never again from that time
forward to think yourself free or noble. All that—
your pride of race, your freedom, your ancient
lineage—you will leave outside the threshold, let
me tell you, when you go in after having sold yourself into such service; for Freedom will refuse to
enter with you when you go in for purposes so base
and humble. So you will be a slave perforce,
however distasteful you may find the name, and not
the slave of one man but of many; and you will



<pb n="v.3.p.451"/>

drudge from morn till night: with hanging head, “for
shameful hire.”<note n="v.3.p.451.n.1"><p>Either a variation upon Homer (cf. Odyssey19, 341: Iliad 13, 84, 21, 444-5), or a quotation from a lost epic.  </p></note> Since you were not brought up in
the company of Slavery from your boyhood but
made her acquaintance late and are getting your
schooling from her at an advanced age, you will not
be very successful or highly valuable to your master, —
The memory of your freedom, stealing over you,
plays the mischief with you, sometimes causing you
to be skittish, and for that reason to come off badly
in slavery.</p>

<p>
Perhaps, however, you think it quite enough to
establish your freedom that you are not the son of a
Pyrrhias or a Zopyrion, and that you have not been
sold in the market like a Bithynian by a loud-voiced
auctioneer. But, my excellent friend, when the first
of the month arrives and side by side with Pyrrhias
and Zopyrion you stretch out your hand like the rest
of the servants and take your earnings, whatever
they are—that is sale! There was no need of an
auctioneer in the case of a man who put himself up
at auction and for a long time solicited a master.
</p>

<p>
Ah, scurvy outcast (that would be my language,
above all to a self-styled philosopher), if a wrecker
or a pirate had taken you at sea and were offering
you for sale, would you not pity yourself for being
ill-fated beyond your deserts; or if someone had
laid hands upon you and were haling you off,
saying that you were a slave, would you not invoke
the law and make a great stir and be wrathful and
shout ‘“Heavens and Earth!” at the top of your
voice? Then just for a few obols, at that age when,
even if you were a slave by birth, it would be high


<pb n="v.3.p.453"/>

time for you to look forward at last to liberty, have
you gone and sold yourself, virtue and wisdom
included ? Had you no respect, either, for all those
wonderful sermons that your noble Plato and
Chrysippus and Aristotle have preached in praise
of freedom and in censure of servility? Are you
not ashamed to undergo comparison with flatterers
and loafers and buffoons; to be the only person
in all that Roman throng who wears the incongruous cloak of a scholar and talks Latin with a
villainous accent; to take part, moreover, in uproarious dinners, packed with human flotsam that
is mostly vile? At these dinners you are vulgar
in your compliments, and you drink more than is
discreet. Then in the morning, roused by a bell,
you shake off the sweetest of your sleep and run
about town with the pack, up hill and down dale,
with yesterday's mud still on your legs. Were
you so in want of lupines and herbs of the field,
did even the springs of cold water fail you so completely, as to bring you to this pass out of desperation ?
No, clearly it was because you did not want water
and lupines, but cates and meat and wine with a
bouquet that you were caught, hooked like a pike
in the very part that hankered for all this—in the
gullet—and it served you quite right! You are
confronting, therefore, the rewards of this greediness,
and with your neck in a collar like a monkey you are
a laughing-stock to others, but seem to yourself to
be living in luxury because you can eat figs without
stint. Liberty and noblesse, with all their kith and
kin, have disappeared completely, and not even a
memory of them abides.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="24"><p>
Indeed, it would be lucky for you if the thing

<pb n="v.3.p.455"/>

involved only the shame of figuring as a slave
_ instead of a free man, and the labour was not like
that of an out-and-out servant. But see if what is
required of you is any more moderate than what is
required of a Dromo ora Tibius! To be sure, the
purpose for which he engaged you, saying that he
wanted knowledge, matters little to him; for,
as the proverb says, “What has a jackass to do
with a lyre?” Ah, yes, can’t you see? they
are mightily consumed .with longing for the
wisdom of Homer or the eloquence of Demosthenes
or the sublimity of Plato, when, if their gold and
’ their silver and their worries about them should be
taken out of their souls, all that remains is pride
and softness and self-indulgence and sensuality and
insolence and ill-breeding! Truly, he does not want
you for that purpose at all, but as you have a long
beard, present a distinguished appearance, are neatly
dressed in a Greek mantle, and everybody knows
you for a grammarian or a rhetorician or a philosopher, it seems to him the proper thing to have a
man of that sort among those who go before him
and form his escort; it will make people think
him a devoted student of Greek learning and in
general a person of taste in literary matters So the
chances are, my worthy friend, that instead of your
marvellous lectures it is your beard and mantle that
you have let for hire.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
You must therefore be seen with him always and
never be missing; you must get up early to let
yourself be noted in attendance, and you must not
desert your post. Putting his hand upon your
shoulder now and then, he talks nonsense at random,

<pb n="v.3.p.457"/>

showing those who meet him that even when he
takes a walk he is not inattentive to the Muses but
makes good use of his leisure during the stroll.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="26"><p>

For
your own part, poor fellow, now you run at his side,
and now you forge about at a foot’s pace, over many
ups and downs (the city is like that, you know),
until you are sweaty and out of breath, and then,
while he is indoors talking to a friend whom he
came to see, as you have no place to sit down, you
stand up, and for lack of employment read the
book with which you armed yourself.</p>

<p>
When night overtakes you hungry and thirsty, after
a wretched bath you go to your dinner at an unseasonable hour, in the very middle of the night; but you
are no longer held in the same esteem and admiration
by the company. If anyone arrives who is more of a
novelty, for you it is “Get back!” In this way
you are pushed off into the most unregarded corner
and take your place merely to witness the dishes
that are passed, gnawing the bones like a dog if
they get as far as you, or regaling yourself with
gratification, thanks to your hunger, on the tough
mallow leaves with which the other food is garnished,
if they should be disdained by those nearer the head
of the table.</p>

<p>
Moreover, you are not spared other forms of rudeness. You are the only one that does not have an egg.
There is no necessity that you should always expect
the same treatment as foreigners and strangers:
that would be unreasonable! Your bird, too, is
not like the others; your neighbour's is fat and
plump, and yours is half a tiny chick, or a tough
pigeon—out-and-out rudeness and contumely! Often,
if there is a shortage when another guest appears of

<pb n="v.3.p.459"/>

a sudden, the waiter takes up what you have before
you and quickly puts it before him, muttering:
“You are one of us, you know.” Of course when a
side of pork or venison is cut at table, you must by
all means have especial favour with the carver or
else get a Prometheus-portion, bones hidden in fat.
That the platter should stop beside the man above
you until he gets tired of stuffing himself, but speed
past you so rapidly—what free man could endure it
if he had even as much resentment as a deer? And
I have not yet mentioned the fact that while the
others drink the most delectable and oldest of wines,
you alone drink one that is vile and thick, taking good
care always to drink out of a gold or silver cup so
that the colour may not convict you of being such
an unhonoured guest. If only you might have your
fill, even of that! But as things are, though you ask
for it repeatedly, the page “hath not even the
semblance of hearing”!<note n="v.3.p.459.n.1"><p>Iliad23, 430. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="27"><p>
You are annoyed, indeed, by many things, a great
many, almost everything; most of all when your
favour is rivalled by a cinaedus or a dancing-master
or an Alexandrian dwarf who recites Ionics.<note n="v.3.p.459.n.2"><p>Anacreontics, Sotadeans, and in general, the “erotic ditties” mentioned below.  </p></note>, How
could you be on a par, though, with those who
render these services to passion and carry notes
about in their clothing ? So, couched in a far corner
of the dining-room and shrinking out of sight for
shame, you groan, naturally, and commiserate yourself and carp at Fortune for not besprinkling you
with at least a few drops of the amenities. You
would be glad, I think, to become a composer of



<pb n="v.3.p.461"/>

erotic ditties, or at all events to be able to sing
them properly when somebody else had composed
them : for you see where precedence and favour go!
You would put up with it if you had to act the part
of a magician or a soothsayer, one of those fellows
who promise legacies amounting to many thousands,
governorships, and tremendous riches ; you see that
they too get on well in their friendships and are
highly valued. So you would be glad to adopt one
of those réles in order not to be entirely despicable
and useless; but even in them, worse luck, you are
not convincing. Therefore you must needs be
humble and suffer in silence, with stifled groans and
amid neglect.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="28"><p>
If a whispering servant accuse you of being the
only one who did not praise the mistress’s page when
he danced or played, there is no little risk in the
thing. So you must raise your thirsty voice like a
stranded frog, taking pains to be conspicuous among
the claque and to lead the chorus; and often when
the others are silent you must independently let
drop a well-considered word of praise that will convey
great flattery.</p>

<p>
That a man who is famished, yes, and athirst,
should be perfumed with myrrh and have a wreath
on his head is really rather laughable, for then you
are like the gravestone of an ancient corpse that is
getting a feast to his memory. They drench the
stones with myrrh and crown them with wreaths,
and then they themselves enjoy the food and drink
that has been prepared !
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="29"><p>
If the master is of a jealous disposition and has
handsome sons or a young wife, and you are not
wholly estranged from Aphrodite and the Graces,

<pb n="v.3.p.463"/>

your situation is not peaceful or your danger to be
taken lightly. The king has many ears and eyes,
which not only see the truth but always add something more for good measure, so that they may not
be considered heavy-lidded. You must therefore
keep your head down while you are at table, as at a
Persian dinner, for fear that an eunuch may see
that you looked at one of the concubines ; for another
eunuch, who has had his bow bent this long time, is
ready to punish you for eyeing what you should not,
driving his arrow through your. cheek just as you are
taking a drink.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="30"><p>.
Then, after you have left the dinner-party, you
get a little bit of sleep, but towards cock-crow you
wake up and say: “Oh, how miserable and wretched
Iam! To think what I left—the occupations of
former days, the comrades, the easy life, the sleep
limited only by my inclination, and the strolls in
freedom—and what a pit I have impetuously flung
myself into! Why, in heaven’s name? What does
this splendid salary amount to? Was there no other
way in which I could have earned more than this
and could have kept my freedom and full independence? As the case stands now, I am pulled about
like a lion leashed with a thread, as the saying is, up
hill and down dale; and the most pitiful part of it
all is that I do not know how to be a success and
cannot be a favourite. I am an outsider in such
matters and have not the knack of it, especially
when I am put in comparison with men who have
‘made an art of the business. Consequently I am
unentertaining and not a bit convivial; I cannot
even raise a laugh. I am aware, too, that it often
actually annoys him to look at me, above all when he

<pb n="v.3.p.465"/>

wishes to be merrier than his wont, for Iseem to him
gloomy. I cannot suit him at all. If I keep to
gravity, I seem disagreeable and almost a person to
run away from ; and if I smile and make my features
as pleasant as I can, he despises me outright and
abominates me. The thing makes no better impression than as if one were to play a comedy in a
tragic mask! All in all, what other life shall I live
for myself, poor fool, after having lived this one for
another?”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="31"><p>
While you are still debating these matters the
bell rings, and you must follow the same routine, go
the rounds and stand up; but first you must rub
your loins and knees with ointment if you wish to
last the struggle out! Then comes a similar dinner,
prolonged to the same hour. In your case the diet
is in contrast to your former way of living; the
sleeplessness, too, and the sweating and the weariness
gradually undermine you, giving rise to consumption,
pneumonia, indigestion, or that noble complaint, the
gout. You stick it out, however, and often you
ought to be abed, but this is not permitted. They
think illness a pretext, and a way of shirking your
duties. The general consequences are that you are
always pale and look as if you were going to die any
minute.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="32"><p>
So it goes in the city. And if you have to go into the
country, I say nothing of anything else, but it often
rains; you are the last to get there—even in the
matter of horses it was your luck to draw that kind !—
and you wait about until for lack of accommodation
they crowd you in with the cook or the mistress’s
hairdresser without giving you even a generous
supply of litter for a bed !


<pb n="v.3.p.467"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="33"><p>
I make no bones of telling you a story that I was
told by our friend Thesmopolis, the Stoic, of something that happened to him which was very comical,
and it is not beyond the bounds of possibility that
the same thing may happen to someone else. He
was in the household of a rich and self-indulgent
woman who belonged to a distinguished family in
the city. Having to go into the country one time,
in the first place he underwent, he said, this highly
ridiculous experience, that he, a philosopher, was
given a favourite to sit by, one of those fellows who
have their legs depilated and their beards shaved off ;
the mistress held him in high honour, no doubt. He
gave the fellow’s name; it was Dovey!<note n="v.3.p.467.n.1"><p>Chelidonion : Little Swallow.   </p></note>_ Now what
a thing that was, to begin with, for a stern‘old man
with a grey beard (you know what a long, venerable
beard Thesmopolis used to have) to sit beside a
fellow with rouged cheeks, underlined eyelids, an
unsteady glance, and a skinny neck—no dove, by
Zeus, but a plucked vulture! Indeed, had it not
been for repeated entreaties, he would have worn a
hair-net on his head. In other ways too Thesmopolis
suffered numerous annoyances from him all the way,
for he hummed and whistled and no doubt would
even have danced in the carriage if Thesmopolis had
not held him in check.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="34"><p>
Then too, something else of a similar nature was
required of him. The woman sent for him and said:
“Thesmopolis, I am asking a great favour of you;


<pb n="v.3.p.469"/>

please do it for me without making any objections or
waiting to be asked repeatedly.” He promised, as
was natural, that he would do anything, and she
went on: “I ask this of you because I see that you
are kind and thoughtful and sympathetic—take my
dog Myrrhina (you know her) into your carriage and
look after her for me, taking care that she does not
want for anything. The poor thing is unwell and is
almost ready to have puppies, and these abominable,
disobedient servants do not pay much attention even
to me on journeys, let alone to her. So do not think
that you will be rendering me a trivial service if you
take good care of my precious, sweet doggie.”
Thesmopolis promised, for she plied him with many
entreaties and almost wept. The situation was as
funny as could be: a little dog peeping out of his
cloak just below his beard, wetting him often, even
if Thesmopolis did not add that detail, barking in a
squeaky voice (that is the way with Maltese dogs,
you know), and licking the philosopher’s beard,
especially if any suggestion of yesterday's gravy was
in it! The favourite ‘who had sat by him was joking
rather wittily one day at the expense of the company
in the dining-room, and when in due course his
banter reached Thesmopolis, he remarked: “As to
Thesmopolis,- I can only say that our Stoic has
finally gone to. the dogs!”<note n="v.3.p.469.n.1"><p>i.e. had become a Cynic.  </p></note> I was told, too, that
the doggie actually had her puppies in the cloak of
Thesmopolis.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="35"><p>
That is the way they make free with their dependants, yes, make game of them, gradually rendering
them submissive to their effrontery. I know a sharp-


<pb n="v.3.p.471"/>

tongued rhetorician who made a speech by request at
dinner in a style that was not by any means uncultivated, but very finished and studied. He was
applauded, however, because his speech, which was
delivered while they were drinking, was timed by
flasks of wine instead of measures of water! And he
took this venture on, it was said, for two hundred
drachmas.<note n="v.3.p.471.n.1"><p>It was not the fashion at ancient banquets for guests to make speeches. In consenting to deliver a selection from his repertory, the rhetorician put himself on a par with a professional entertainer. This was bad enough, but he made things still worse by allowing the company to time his speech with a substitute for a water-clock which they improvised out of a flask of wine. </p></note></p>

<p>
All this is not so bad, perhaps. But if Divesf
himself has a turn for writing poetry or prose and
recites his own compositions at dinner, then you
must certainly split yourself applauding and flattering
him and excogitating new styles of praise. Some
of them wish to be admired for their beauty also,
and they must hear themselves called an Adonis
or a Hyacinthus, although sometimes they have
a yard of nose. If you withhold your praise, off you
go at once to the quarries of Dionysius because
you are jealous and are plotting against your master.
They must be philosophers and rhetoricians, too,
and if they happen to commit a solecism, precisely
on that account their language must seem full of
the flavour of Attica and of Hymettus, and it must
be the law to speak that way in future.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="36"><p>
After all, one could perhaps put up with the conduct of the men. But the women—! That is another
thing that the women are keen about—to have men
of education living in their households on a salary


<pb n="v.3.p.473"/>

and following their litters. They count it as one
among their other embellishments if it is said that
they are cultured and have an interest in philosophy
and write songs not much inferior to Sappho’s. To
that end, forsooth, they too trail hired rhetoricians and
grammarians and philosophers about, and listen to
their lectures—when ? it is ludicrous !—either while
their toilet is being made and their hair dressed, or
at dinner ; at other times they are too busy! And
often while the philosopher is delivering a discourse
the maid comes up and hands her a note from her
lover, so that the lecture on chastity is kept waiting
until she has written a reply to the lover and hurries
back to hear it.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="37"><p>
At last, after a long lapse of time, when the feast
of Cronus<note n="v.3.p.473.n.1"><p>The Greek festival that corresponded to the Roman Saturnalia.  </p></note> or the Panathenaic festival comes, you are
sent a beggarly scarf or a flimsy undergarment. Then
by all means there must be a long and impressive
procession. The first man, who has overheard his
master still discussing the matter, immediately runs
and tells you in advance, and goes away with a
generous fee for his announcement, paid in advance.
In the morning a baker’s dozen of them come
bringing it, and each one tells you: “I talked about
it a great deal!” “I jogged his memory!” “It was
left to me, and I chose the finest one!’ So all
of them depart with a tip, and even grumble that
you did not give more.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="38"><p>
As to your pay itself, it is a matter of two obols,
or four, at a time, and when you ask for it you are
a bore and a nuisance. So, in order to get it you


<pb n="v.3.p.475"/>

must flatter and wheedle the master and pay court to
his steward too, but in another way; and you must
not neglect his friend and adviser, either. As what
you get is already owing to a clothier or doctor or
shoemaker, his gifts are no gifts and profit you
nothing.<note n="v.3.p.475.n.1"><p>An allusion to Sophocles, Ajax665 : ἐχθρῶν ἄδωρα δῶρα κοὺκ ὀνήσιμα.  </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="39"><p>
You are greatly envied, however, and perhaps some
slanderous story or other gradually gets afoot by
stealth and comes to a man who by now is glad to
receive charges against you, for he sees that you are
used up by your unbroken exertions and pay lame
and exhausted court to him, and that the gout is
growing upon you. To sum it up, after garnering all
that was most profitable in you, after consuming the
most fruitful years of your life and the greatest
vigour of your body, after reducing you to a thing of
_ rags and tatters, he is looking about for a rubbish-heap
on which to cast you aside unceremoniously, and for
another man to engage who can stand the work.
Under the charge that you once made overtures to a
page of his, or that, in spite of your age, you are trying
to seduce an innocent girl, his wife's maid, or something
else of that sort, you leave at night, hiding your face,
bundled out neck and crop, destitute of everything
and at the end of your tether, taking with you, in
addition to the burden of your years, that excellent
companion, gout. What you formerly knew you have
forgotten in all these years, and you have made your
belly bigger than a sack, an insatiable, inexorable
curse. Your gullet, too, demands what it is used to,
and dislikes to unlearn its lessons.


<pb n="v.3.p.477"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="40"><p>
Nobody else would take you in, now that you have
passed your prime and are like an old horse whose
hide, even, is not as serviceable as it was. Besides,
the scandal of your dismissal, exaggerated by conjecture, makes people think you an adulterer or
poisoner or something of the kind. Your accuser is
trustworthy even when he holds his tongue, while
you are a Greek, and easy-going in your ways and
prone to all sorts of wrong-doing. That is what they
think of us all, very naturally. For I believe I have
detected the reason for that opinion which they have
of us. Many who have entered households, to make
up for not knowing anything else that was useful,
have professed to supply predictions, philtres, lovecharms, and incantations against enemies ; yet they
assert they are educated, wrap themselves in the
philosopher’s mantle, and wear beards that cannot
lightly be sneered at. Naturally, therefore, they
entertain the same suspicion about all of us on seeing
that men whom they considered excellent are that
sort, and above all observing their obsequiousness at
dinners and in their other social relations, and their
servile attitude toward gain.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="41"><p>
Having shaken them off, they hate them, very
naturally, and endeavour in every way to destroy
them outright if possible; for they expect them to
betray the many hidden mysteries of their make-up, inasmuch as they are thoroughly acquainted with everything and have looked upon them unveiled. That
sticks in their throat, because they are all exactly like

<pb n="v.3.p.479"/>

the finest of papyrus rolls, of which the knobs are of
gold and the slip-cover of purple, but the content is
either Thyestes feasting on his children or Oedipus
married to his mother, or Tereus debauching two
sisters at once. They too are splendid and
universally admired, but inside, underneath their
purple, they hide a deal of tragedy ; in fact if you
unroll any one of them, you will find an ample drama
by an Euripides or a Sophocles, while on the outside
there is a gaudy purple laticlave and a golden bulla.
Conscious of all this, they hate and plot against any
renegade who, having become thoroughly familiar
with them, is likely to expose the plot and tell it
broadcast.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg033.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="42"><p>
I desire, nevertheless, in imitation of Cebes,<note n="v.3.p.479.n.1"><p>Reputed author of the Tabula, a description of an maginary allegorical painting representing human life.  </p></note> to
paint you a picture of this career that we have
discussed, so that you may look at it and determine.
whether you should enter it. I should gladly have
requisitioned an Apelles, or Parrhasius, or Aetion, or
Euphranor to paint it, but since it is impossible
nowadays to find anyone so excellent and so
thoroughly master of his craft, I shall show you the
picture as best I can in unembellished prose.</p>

<p>
Imagine painted a lofty, golden gateway, not down
on the level ground but above the earth on a hill ;
the slope is long and steep and slippery, so that many
a time those who hoped soon to be at the summit have
‘broken their necks by a slip of the foot. Within,
let Wealth himself be sitting, all golden, seemingly,
very beautiful and fascinating ; and let his lover,
afler ascending with great toil, draw near the door
and gaze spellbound at the gold. Let Hope, herself


<pb n="v.3.p.481"/>

tair of face and gaily dressed, take him in charge and
conduct him within, tremendously impressed by his
entrance. Then let Hope keep always in advance
of him, and let other women, Deceit and Servitude,
receive him successively and pass him on to Toil, who,
after breaking the wretch with hard labour, shall at
length deliver him, now sickly and faded, to Old
Age. Last of all, let Insolence lay hold of him and
drag him along to Despair; let Hope then fly away
and vanish, and instead of the golden portal by
which he entered, let him be ejected by some
remote and secret postern, naked, paunchy, pale, and
old, screening his nakedness with his left hand and
throttling himself with his right; and on the way
out, let him be met by Repentance, weeping to no
avail and helping to make an end of the poor man.</p>

<p>
“Let that be the conclusion of the painting. The
rest, my dear Timocles, is up to you; examine all the
details with care and make up your mind whether it
suits you to enter the pictured career by these doors
and be thrown out so disgracefully by that one
opposite. Whatever you do, remember the words of
the philosopher: “God is not at fault; the fault is
his who maketh the choice.”<note n="v.3.p.481.n.1">Plato Republic 10, 617.</note>

</p></div>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>
