<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>On the Murder of Herodes from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Antiphon</author>
        <editor role="translator">K. J. Maidment</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><idno type="OCLC">5331826</idno><idno type="ISBN">0674993403</idno></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=2">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=3">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=4">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.tetralogy">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Tetralogy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd
      </item></change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Checkmark
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/7/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed tetralogy names and div2s again, prior to importing
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>made some corrections to the SGML
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>also fixed quoted text which had no content, just the attribute.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>15 October 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: antiph_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-10-07 21:00:37  rsingh04
began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

Revision 1.6  2009/06/22 19:41:56  student
edited entity tags CEH

Revision 1.5  2008/11/21 21:38:13  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.4  2008/02/13 19:32:23  lcerrato
fixed incorrect bibl tags

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 21:10:04  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 15:48:40  packel
removed stray item tags

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:27:36  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:14:27  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2000/03/04 20:33:52  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.6  2000/01/28 23:23:50  dasmith
Made ID numbers be the tag content.

Revision 1.5  1999/10/15 23:08:23  dasmith
Make sure we get three sections at a time.

Revision 1.4  1999/10/15 21:20:01  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.


</item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="section">
        <p> I could have wished, gentlemen, that my powers of speech and my experience of the
            world<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign xml:lang="greek">tw=n pragma/twn</foreign>
            refers especially to the workings of the law, and is picked up by <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">ou(= me\n ga/r me e)/dei . . . e)mpeiri/a</foreign>. The speaker
            means that had he been less ignorant in such matters, he might have effectively
            protested against the employment of <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)/ndeicis</foreign> and
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)pagwgh/</foreign> which involved the close confinement of
            the defendant before his trial, instead of the more regular <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >di/kh fo/nou</foreign> before the Areopagus. See Introduction.</note> were as great
          as the misfortune and the severities with which I have been visited. Instead, I know more
          of the last two than I should, and am more wanting in the first than is good for me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" type="section">
        <p>When I had to submit to the bodily suffering which this unwarranted charge brought with
          it, experience afforded me no help; while now that my life depends upon my giving a
          truthful account of the facts, my case is being prejudiced by my inability to speak. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" type="section">
        <p>Poor speakers have often before now been disbelieved because they spoke the truth, and
          the truth itself has been their undoing because they could not make it convincing: just as
          clever speakers have often gained credit with lies, and have owed their lives to the very
          fact that they lied. Thus the fate of one who is not a practised pleader inevitably
          depends less upon the true facts and his actual conduct than upon the version of them
          given by his accusers. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" type="section">
        <p>I shall therefore ask you, gentlemen, not indeed for a hearing, as do the majority of
          those on trial, who lack confidence in themselves and presume you to be biassed; for with
          an honest jury the defence is naturally assured of a hearing even without appealing for
          it, seeing that that same jury accorded the prosecution a hearing unasked— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" type="section">
        <p>no, my request of you is this. If, on the one hand, I make any mistake in speaking,
          pardon me and treat it as due to inexperience rather than dishonesty; and if, on the other
          hand, I express a point well, treat it as due to truthfulness rather than skill. For it is
          no more right that mere words should be the undoing of a man who is in fact innocent than
          that they should be the salvation of a man who is in fact guilty; the tongue is to blame
          for a word whereas the will is to blame for an act. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" type="section">
        <p>Moreover, a man in personal danger is sure to make some mistake; he cannot help thinking
          of his fate as well as of his argument, as the decision of an issue which is still in
          doubt always depends more upon chance than upon human effort. Hence a man in danger is
          bound to be not a little distraught. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" type="section">
        <p>Even speakers with a long experience of the courts are far from being at their best, I
          notice, when in any danger; they are more successful when conducting a case in safety.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" type="section">
        <p>So much for my request, gentlemen; it breaks no law, human or divine: and it takes into
          account what you have a right to expect from me as much as what I have a right to expect
          from you. And now for the charges made, which I will answer one at a time. To begin with, I
          shall prove to you that the methods used to involve me in today's proceedings were
          entirely illegal and arbitrary. Not that I wish to evade trial before a popular court; as
          far as my belief in my innocence of the present charge and in the justice of your verdict
          is concerned, I would place my life in your hands even if you were not on oath and I were
          being tried under no particular law. No, my object is to let the arbitrary and illegal
          behavior of the prosecution furnish you with a presumption as to the character of the rest
          of their case against me.</p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" type="section">
        <p>First,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the meaning of this and the following paragraph
            see Introduction.</note> whereas an information has been lodged against me as a
          malefactor, I am being tried for murder: a thing which has never before happened to anyone
          in this country.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A deliberate ambiguity. <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">tw=n e)n th=| gh=| tau/th|</foreign> can mean (a) Athenian citizens,
            (b) persons who happen to be in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>. Taken
            in sense (a) the statement is true. Taken in sense (b) it is probably false.</note>
          Indeed, the prosecution have themselves borne witness to the fact that I am not a
          malefactor and cannot be charged under the law directed against malefactors, as that law
          is concerned with thieves and footpads, and they have omitted to prove my claim to either
          title. Thus, as far as this arrest of mine goes, they have given you every right and
          justification to acquit me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" type="section">
        <p>They object, however, that murder is a malefaction, and a grave one. I agree, a very
          grave one; so is sacrilege; so is treason; but the laws which apply to each of them
          differ. In my case the prosecution have first of all caused the trial to be held in the
          one place from which those charged with murder are always debarred by proclamation, the
          Agora: and secondly, although it is laid down by law that a murderer shall pay with his
          life, they have entered a claim for damages<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For an
            explanation of the phrase <foreign xml:lang="greek">ti/mhsin poiei=n</foreign> see
            Introduction pp. 155-156.</note>—not as a kindness to me, but for their own benefit—and
          by so doing they have grudged the dead man his lawful due. Their motives you will learn in
          the course of my speech.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A promise which is never
            adequately fulfilled. The only further reference to the subject is in <bibl
              n="Antiph. 5.79">Antiph. 5.79</bibl> ad fin.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" type="section">
        <p>Secondly, as of course you all know, every court judges cases of murder in the open air,
          and for good reasons: first, that the jurors may avoid entering the same building as those
          whose hands are unclean: and secondly, that he who is conducting the prosecution for
          murder may avoid being under the same roof as the murderer. No one but yourself has ever
          dreamed of evading this law. And not only that you should, as a preliminary, have taken
          the most solemn and binding oath known,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">diwmosi/a</foreign>, or preliminary oath, taken by the prosecutor,
            the defendant, and the witnesses of each, was peculiar to the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >di/kh fo/nou</foreign>; the equivalent elsewhere was the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >a)ntwmosi/a</foreign> taken by both plaintiff and defendant at the <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">a)na/krisis</foreign> before the Archon. From this witnesses were
            exempt.</note> swearing, under pain of causing yourself, your kin, and your house to
          perish from the earth, that you would accuse me only in connection with the murder itself,
          to the effect that I committed it; whereby, however numerous my crimes, I could have been
          condemned only on the charge before the court, and however numerous my good deeds, none of
          those good deeds could have gained me an acquittal. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" type="section">
        <p>This requirement you have evaded. You have invented laws to suit yourself. You, the
          prosecutor, are not on oath; nor are the witnesses, who are giving evidence against me
          which they should have given only after taking the same preliminary oath as yourself,
          their hands on the sacrifice as they did so. You bid the court, moreover, believe your
          witnesses, in spite of their not being on oath, and pass sentence for murder—when your own
          evasion of the laws of the land has destroyed the trustworthiness of those witnesses. Yes,
          you imagine that, in the eyes of the court, the laws themselves should have less authority
          than your own actions in defiance of them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" type="section">
        <p>You reply that if I had been allowed my freedom, I should have made off without awaiting
          my trial—as though you had forced me to enter this country against my will. Yet if I
          attached no importance to being debarred from <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> for the future, it was equally open to me either to disregard the
          summons to appear in court and so lose the case by default, or to avail myself of the
          right given to every one of leaving the country after making the first speech for the
            defense.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., the prosecution justify their choice of an
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)pagwgh/</foreign> rather than a <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >di/kh fo/nou</foreign> by claiming that only thus could the defendant be prevented
            from slipping through their fingers. The defendant objects to this on two grounds: (a)
            The prosecution have no reason to assume that they would not have faced a <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">di/kh fo/nou</foreign> if left at liberty. In fact, he cut himself
            off from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by so defaulting, and that
            was a strong deterrent. (b) In any case, it was recognized that the defendant in a
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">di/kh fo/nou</foreign> had the right of withdrawing into
            exile either before or during the trial. The speaker is of course careful not to remind
            the court that he is an alien, whose position is not necessarily the same as that of an
            Athenian citizen charged with murder.</note> You, however, for purely personal reasons,
          are trying to rob me, and me alone, of a privilege accorded to every Greek, by framing a
          law to suit yourself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" type="section">
        <p>Yet it would be unanimously agreed, I think, that the laws which deal with cases such as
          the present are the most admirable and righteous of all laws. Not only have they the
          distinction of being the oldest in this country, but they have changed no more than the
          crime with which they are concerned; and that is the surest token of good laws, as time
          and experience show mankind what is imperfect. Hence you must not use the speech for the
          prosecution to discover whether your laws are good or bad: you must use the laws to
          discover whether or not the speech for the prosecution is giving you a correct and lawful
          interpretation of the case.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This paragraph reappears in
              <bibl n="Antiph. 6.2">Antiph. 6.2</bibl> (cf. 87-89 and <bibl n="Antiph. 6.3">Antiph.
              6.3-4</bibl>). The employment of such loci communes was frequent, and there is no
            reason to suspect the genuineness of the present passage.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" type="section">
        <p>The laws concerned with the taking of life are thus excellent, and no one has ever before
          ventured to interfere with them. You alone have had the audacity to turn legislator and
          substitute worse for better; and the object of this arbitrary behavior of yours is to have
          me put to death without just cause. In fact, your infringement of the law is itself
          decisive evidence in my favor, because you well knew that you would find no one to testify
          to my guilt once he had taken that preliminary oath. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" type="section">
        <p>Furthermore, instead of acting like a man confident of his case and arranging that it
          should be tried once and indisputably, you have left yourself grounds for dispute and
          argument, as though you proposed to show your distrust of even the present court. The
          result is that even if I am acquitted today, I am no better off; you can say that it was
          as a malefactor that I was acquitted, not on a charge of murder. On the other hand, if you
          win your case, you will claim my life, on the ground that it is on a charge of murder that
          I have been tried and found guilty. Could any thing more unfair be devised? You and your
          associates have only to convince this court once, and your object is gained; whereas I, if
          I am acquitted once, am left in the same peril as before. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" type="section">
        <p>Then again, gentlemen, my imprisonment was an act of illegality quite without parallel. I
          was ready to furnish the three sureties required by law; yet the prosecution took steps to
          ensure that I should be prevented from doing so. Hitherto no alien willing to furnish
          sureties has ever been imprisoned; and, moreover, the law concerned applies to the
          custodians of malefactors<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., the Eleven, who were the
            magistrates concerned in the <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)/ndeicis</foreign> of a
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">kakou=rgos</foreign> and who were responsible for his safe
            custody pending trial.</note> as it does to others. Here again, then, we have a law by
          which every one benefits: and it has failed to release me, and me alone, from confinement.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" type="section">
        <p>The reason was that it was to the prosecution's advantage, first, that I should be
          prevented from looking after my interests in person, and so be quite unable to prepare for
          my trial: and secondly, that I should undergo bodily suffering, and by reason of that
          bodily suffering find my friends readier to tell lies as witnesses for the prosecution
          than the truth as witnesses for the defence.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Apparently on
            the assumption that the rats will leave a sinking ship.</note> In addition to which,
          lifelong disgrace has been brought upon me and mine. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" type="section">
        <p>Such are the manifold respects in which I have had to submit to a loss<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">From the reading <foreign xml:lang="greek">e(/los
              swqei\s</foreign> of the inferior Mss. the writer of a (late) Argument, which is found
            prefixed to the speech in A and N, made the curious deduction that the speaker's name
            was <foreign xml:lang="greek">*(/elos</foreign>.</note> of the rights accorded me by
          your laws and by justice before appearing in court. However, in spite of that
          disadvantage, I will try to prove my innocence: although it is hard to refute at a
          moment's notice false charges so carefully framed, as one cannot prepare oneself against
          the unexpected. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" type="section">
        <p>I sailed from <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>, gentlemen, as a
          passenger on the same boat as this Herodes whom, we are told, I murdered. We were bound
          for <placeName key="tgn,7007528">Aenus</placeName>, I to visit my father, who happened to
          be there just then, and Herodes to release some slaves<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Probably prisoners of war who were being ransomed by their relatives. It is surprising
            that no attempt is made to throw suspicion on one of these Thracians, as a motive would
            have been easy to find.</note> to certain Thracians. The slaves whom he was to release
          were also passengers, as were the Thracians who were to purchase their freedom. I will
          produce witnesses to satisfy you of this. <quote type="Witnesses"><text xml:lang="en">
              <body>
                <head>Witnesses</head>
                <p/>
              </body>
            </text></quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" type="section">
        <p>Such were our respective reasons for making the voyage. In the course of it, we happened
          to meet with a storm which forced us to put in at a place within the territory of
            <placeName key="perseus,Methymna">Methymna</placeName>, where the boat on to which
          Herodes transhipped, and on which the prosecution maintain that he met his end, lay at
          anchor. Now consider these circumstances in themselves to begin with; they were due to
          chance, not to any design on my part. It has nowhere been shown that I persuaded Herodes
          to accompany me; on the contrary, it has been shown that I made the voyage independently
          on business of my own. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" type="section">
        <p>Nor again, as is clear, was I making my voyage to <placeName key="tgn,7007528"
            >Aenus</placeName> without good reason. Nor did we put in at this particular spot by
          prearrangement of any sort; we were forced to do so. And the transhipment after coming to
          anchor was similarly forced upon us, and not part of any plot or ruse. The boat on which
          we were passengers had no deck, whereas that on to which we transhipped had one and the
          rain was the reason for the exchange. I will produce witnesses to satisfy you of this.
            <quote type="Witnesses"><text xml:lang="en">
              <body>
                <head>Witnesses</head>
                <p/>
              </body>
            </text></quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" type="section">
        <p>After crossing into the other boat, we fell to drinking. Now whereas it is established
          that Herodes quitted the boat and did not board it again, I did not leave the boat at all
          that night. Next day, when Herodes was missing, I joined in the search as anxiously as
          any; if anyone considered the matter serious, I did. Not only was I responsible for the
          dispatch of a messenger to <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>, that is
          to say, it was upon my suggestion that it was decided to send one, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" type="section">
        <p>but when none of the passengers or the personal companions of Herodes volunteered to go,
          I offered to send my own attendant; and I hardly imagine that I was deliberately proposing
          to send someone who would inform against me. Finally, when the search had failed to reveal
          any trace of Herodes either at <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> or
          anywhere else and, with the return of fair sailing-weather, the rest of the boats began
          standing out to sea, I likewise took my departure. I will produce witnesses to prove these
          statements to you. <quote type="Witnesses"><text xml:lang="en">
              <body>
                <head>Witnesses</head>
                <p/>
              </body>
            </text></quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" type="section">
        <p>Those are the facts; now draw the logical conclusions. First, in the interval before I
          put to sea for <placeName key="tgn,7007528">Aenus</placeName>, when Herodes was missing,
          not a soul accused me, although the prosecution had already heard the news; otherwise I
          should never have taken my departure. For the moment the true facts of the matter were too
          much for any charge which they could bring; and, moreover, I was still on the island. It
          was not until I had resumed my voyage, and the prosecution had conspired to form this plot
          of theirs upon my life, that they made their accusation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" type="section">
        <p>Their story is that it was on the shore that Herodes was killed, and that I, who did not
          leave the boat at all, struck him upon the head with a stone. Yet while they have detailed
          information of this, they cannot give any plausible account of how the man came to
          disappear. Clearly, the probabilities suggest that the crime was committed somewhere in
          the neighborhood of the harbor. On the one hand, Herodes was drunk; and on the other hand,
          it was at night that he left the boat. He probably would not have been in a condition to
          control his own movements, nor could anyone who wished to take him a long way off by night
          have found any plausible excuse for doing so. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" type="section">
        <p>Yet in spite of a two days' search both in the harbor and at a distance from it, no
          eyewitness, no bloodstain, and no clue of any other description was found. But I will go
          further. I accept the prosecution's story. I can indeed produce witnesses to prove that I
          did not quit the boat.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">These “witnesses” are not
            specifically referred to again. If they are included in those cited at the end of the
            paragraph, it is strange that nothing more is made of their evidence. In all probability
            the speaker is alluding to the witness for the prosecution who sturdily maintained that
            Euxitheus remained on board all night. See <bibl n="Antiph. 5.42">Antiph.
            5.42</bibl>.</note> But suppose as much as you please that I did quit it; it is still
          utterly improbable that the man should have remained undiscovered after his disappearance,
          if he did not go very far from the sea. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" type="section">
        <p>However, we are told that he was thrown into the sea. From what boat? Clearly, the boat
          came from the harbor itself; and in that case, why should it not have been identified? For
          that matter, we should also have expected to find some traces in the boat, seeing that a
          dead man had been placed in it and thrown overboard in the dark. The prosecution claim,
          indeed, to have found traces—but only in the boat on board of which he was drinking and
          which he quitted, the one boat on which they themselves agree that he was not murdered.
          The boat from which he was thrown into the sea they have not discovered; they have found
          neither it itself nor any trace of it. I will produce witnesses to prove these statements
          to you. <quote type="Witnesses">Witnesses</quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" type="section">
        <p>After I had departed for <placeName key="tgn,7007528">Aenus</placeName> and the boat on
          which Herodes and I had been drinking<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Weil's emendation is
            certain. Herodes and Euxitheus took shelter for the night on a boat bound for <placeName
              key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>. After the storm was over, the passengers
            returned to their own vessel.</note> had reached <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene"
            >Mytilene</placeName>, the prosecution first of all went on board and conducted a
          search. On finding the bloodstains,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign
              xml:lang="greek">to\ ai(=ma</foreign>(cf. <foreign xml:lang="greek">tw=n
              proba/twn</foreign>), because it had already been mentioned in the preceding evidence.
            Similarly with <foreign xml:lang="greek">tou\s a)nqrw/pous</foreign>(infr); they had
            been referred to in the speech for the presecution.</note> they claimed that this was
          where Herodes had met his end. But the suggestion proved an unfortunate one, as the blood
          turned out to be that of the animals sacrificed. So they abandoned that line, and instead
          seized the two men and examined them under torture.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            references in the course of the speech to the two witnesses for the prosecution are
            confusing. The relevant passages are 29, 42, 49, and 52. From 49 it is clear that one
            was a slave and the other a free man, although he cannot have been a Greek, as he was
            subjected to torture by the prosecution (ibid). 29 suggests that the two were members of
            the crew of the homeward bound vessel on which Euxitheus and Herodes sheltered form the
            rain, and that after the storm they continued their voyage to <placeName
              key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>, where the relatives of Herodes
            immediately came aboard and took them into custody. This is supported by 52, which
            implies that Euxitheus parted from the men after the storm, he proceeding the <placeName
              key="tgn,7007528">Aenus</placeName>, and they to <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene"
              >Mytilene</placeName>. 42, however, offers a difficulty. Euxitheus there says with
            reference to the free man: “he sailed in the same boat as myself, and was present and in
            my company throughout,” a statement which on the face of it should mean that he
            travelled with Euxitheus from <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> to
              <placeName key="tgn,7007528">Aenus</placeName>. There seems to be only one explanation
            of the inconsistency. Euxitheus must have been intentionally misrepresenting the facts
            in 42, as it was important to show that the favorable evidence of this witness was based
            upon a personal acquaintance with his movements and general behavior. If so, it seems
            not unlikely that the man was actually in the pay of Euxitheus. Can he have been the
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)ko/louqos</foreign> of 24, sent back to <placeName
              key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> by E. and there detained by the family of
            Herodes?</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" type="section">
        <p>The first, who was tortured there and then, said nothing to damage me. The second was
          tortured several days later, after being in the prosecution's company throughout the
          interval. It was he who was induced by them to incriminate me falsely. I will produce
          witnesses to confirm these facts. <quote type="Witnesses"> Witnesses </quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" type="section">
        <p>You have listened to evidence for the length of the delay before the man's examination
          under torture; now notice the actual character of that examination. The slave was
          doubtless promised his freedom: it was certainly to the prosecution alone that he could
          look for release from his sufferings. Probably both of these considerations induced him to
          make the false charges against me which he did; he hoped to gain his freedom, and his one
          immediate wish was to end the torture. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" type="section">
        <p>I need not remind you, I think, that witnesses under torture are biassed in favor of
          those who do most of the torturing; they will say anything likely to gratify them. It is
          their one chance of salvation, especially when the victims of their lies happen not to be
          present. Had I myself proceeded to give orders that the slave should be racked for not
          telling the truth, that step in itself would doubtless have been enough to make him stop
          incriminating me falsely. As it was, the examination was conducted by men who also knew
          what their own interests required. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" type="section">
        <p>Now as long as he believed that he had something to gain by falsely incriminating me, he
          firmly adhered to that course; but on finding that he was doomed, he at once reverted to
          the truth and admitted that it was our friends here who had induced him to lie about me.
          However, neither his persevering attempts at falsehood nor his subsequent confession of
          the truth helped him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" type="section">
        <p>They took him, took the man upon whose disclosures they are resting their case against
          me, and put him to death,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">It should be noted that the
            witness was a slave who had been purchased by the prosecution (cf. previous note and
              <bibl n="Antiph. 5.47">Antiph. 5.47</bibl>, init.).</note> a thing which no one else
          would have dreamed of doing. As a rule, informers are rewarded with money, if they are
          free, and with their liberty, if they are slaves. The prosecution paid for their
          information with death, and that in spite of a protest from my friends that they should
          postpone the execution until my return. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" type="section">
        <p>Clearly, it was not his person, but his evidence, which they required; had the man
          remained alive, he would have been tortured by me in the same way, and the prosecution
          would be confronted with their plot: but once he was dead, not only did the loss of his
          person mean that I was deprived of my opportunity of establishing the truth, but his false
          statements are assumed to be true and are proving my undoing. Call me witnesses to confirm
          these facts. <quote type="Witnesses">&lt;Witnesses&gt;</quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" type="section">
        <p>In my opinion, they should have produced the informer himself in court, if they wished to
          prove me guilty. That was the issue to which they should have brought the case. Instead of
          putting the man to death, they ought to have produced him in the flesh and challenged me
          to examine him under torture. As it is, which of his statements will they use, may I ask:
          his first or his second? And which is true: the statement that I committed the murder or
          the statement that I did not? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" type="section">
        <p>If we are to judge from probability, it is obviously the second which is the truer; he
          was lying to benefit himself, but on finding that those lies were proving fatal, he
          thought that he would be saved by telling the truth. However, he had no one to stand up
          for the truth, as I, who was vindicated by his second, true statement, was unfortunately
          not present; while there were those who were ready to put his first, his false one, beyond
          all reach of future correction. As a rule, it is the victim who quietly seizes an informer
          and then makes away with him. In this case, it is the very persons who arrested the slave
          in order to discover the truth who have done so; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" type="section">
        <p>and it is the very person who had supplied information against myself with whom they have
          made away. Had I myself been responsible for his disappearance, had I refused to surrender
          him to the prosecution or declined to establish the truth in some other way, they would
          have treated that very fact as most significant: it would have furnished the strongest
          presumption in their favor that I was guilty. So now that they themselves have declined to
          submit to an inquiry, in spite of a challenge from my friends to do so, that fact should
          in the same way furnish a presumption in my favor that the charge which they are bringing
          is a false one.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 1.11">Antiph.
              1.11</bibl>, <title>Prosecution of the Stepmother</title>, and <bibl n="Antiph. 6.27"
              >Antiph. 6.27</bibl>, <title>On the Choreutes</title>, for a similar line of
            argument.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" type="section">
        <p>They further allege that the slave admitted under torture that he had been my accomplice
          in the murder. I maintain that he did not say this; what he said was that he conducted
          Herodes and myself off the boat, and that after I had murdered him, he helped me pick him
          up and put him in the boat; then he threw him into the sea. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" type="section">
        <p>Also let me point out to you that at the start, before being placed on the wheel, in
          fact, until extreme pressure was brought to bear, the man adhered to the truth and
          declared me innocent. It was only when on the wheel, and when driven to it, that he
          falsely incriminated me, in order to put an end to the torture. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" type="section">
        <p>When it was over, he ceased affirming that I had had any part in the crime; indeed, at
          the end he bemoaned the injustice with which both I and he were being sent to our doom:
          not that he was trying to do me a kindness—hardly that, after falsely accusing me as he
          had done; no, the truth left him no choice: he was confirming as true the declaration
          which he had made to begin with. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" type="section">
        <p>Then there was the second man.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">e)leu/qeros</foreign> of <bibl n="Antiph. 5.49">Antiph. 5.49</bibl>.
            Since he is tortured, he cannot have been born a Greek. For further details as to both
            witnesses see <bibl n="Antiph. 5.29">Antiph. 5.29</bibl> note 3.</note> He had travelled
          on the same boat as I: had been present throughout the voyage: and had been constantly in
          my company. When tortured in the same way, he confirmed the first and last statements of
          the other as true; for he declared me innocent from start to finish. On the other hand,
          the assertions made by the other upon the wheel, made not because they were the truth, but
          because they were wrung from him, he contradicted. Thus, while the one said that it was
          not until I had left the boat that I killed Herodes, and that he had himself helped me to
          remove the body after the murder, the other maintained that I did not leave the boat at
          all. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" type="section">
        <p>And indeed, the probabilities are in my favor; I hardly imagine myself to have been so
          benighted that after planning the murder on my own to ensure that no one was privy to
          it—for there lay my one great danger—I proceeded to furnish myself with witnesses and
          confederates once the crime had been committed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" type="section">
        <p>Furthermore, Herodes was murdered very close to the sea and the boats, or so we are told
          by the prosecution. Was a man who was struck down by but one assailant not going to shout
          out or attract the attention of those on shore or on board? Moreover, sounds can be
            heard<note anchored="true" resp="ed">If the manuscript reading is retained, this
            sentence will be the supposed answer of the prosecution to the question just put by the
            defence; but the introductory <foreign xml:lang="greek">kai\ mh\n</foreign> argues
            against such an interpretation. In view of the frequent mis-copying of perfectly common
            words elsewhere in the manuscripts, it is less likely that <foreign xml:lang="greek">ge
              a)gnoei=n</foreign> arose through ignorance from the rarity <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >gegwnei=n</foreign>, than that it replaced <foreign xml:lang="greek">ge
              a)kou/ein</foreign> through carelessness.</note> over much greater distances by night
          than by day, on a beach than in a city. Moreover, it is admitted that the passengers were
          still awake when Herodes left the boat. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" type="section">
        <p>Again, he was murdered on shore and placed in the boat; yet no trace or bloodstain was
          found either on shore or in the boat, in spite of the fact that it was at night that he
          was picked up and at night that he was placed in the boat. Do you think that any human
          being in such circumstances would have been able to smooth out the traces on shore and
          wipe away the marks on the boat, clues which a calm and collected man could not have
          removed successfully even by daylight? What probability is there in such a suggestion,
          gentlemen? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" type="section">
        <p>One thing above all you must remember, and I hope that you will forgive me for repeatedly
          stressing the same point; but my danger is great, and only if you form a right judgement,
          am I safe; if you are misled, I am doomed. I repeat, let no one cause you to forget that
          the prosecution put the informer to death, that they used every effort to prevent his
          appearance in court and to make it impossible for me to take him and examine him under
          torture on my return; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" type="section">
        <p>although to allow me to do so was to their own advantage.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Since, if his statements were true, he would adhere to them when examined by Euxitheus,
            and the prosecution would be able to take advantage of the fact in court.</note>
          Instead, they bought the slave and put him to death, entirely on their own initiative—put
          the informer himself to death, without any official sanction, and without the excuse that
          he was guilty of the murder. They should of course have kept him in custody, or
          surrendered him to my friends on security, or else handed him over to the magistrates of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in order that his fate might be
          decided by a court. As it was, you sentenced him to death on your own authority and
          executed him, when even an allied state is denied the right of inflicting the
          death-penalty in such fashion without the consent of the Athenian people.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The evidence of inscriptions confirms this. Decrees regulating
            the relation between <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and certain
            members of her confederacy have survived, from which it would seem that while the
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">su/mmaxoi</foreign> were left with a limited civil
            jurisdiction of their own, criminal cases were transferred to the Athenian courts. Thus
            the Erythraean Decree (I.G. i2. 10 ff.) enacts that all cases of treason involving
            capital punishment shall be tried at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
            the Chalcidian Decree (I.G. i2. 39) that cases arising from the <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">eu)/qunai</foreign> of a magistrate and involving exile, death, or
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)timi/a</foreign>, shall likewise be tried at <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, while the Milesian Decree (I.G. i2. 22)
            allows the local courts a jurisdiction extending only to cases which do not involve a
            penalty of more than 100 drachmas. It should be borne in mind, however, that although
            the trial of Euxitheus himself took place at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName>, the choice of such a forum was not necessarily determined by a
            similar decree transferring the criminal jurisdiction of the Mytilenean courts to
              <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Such a decree doubtless existed;
            but those which have survived appear to envisage only those cases in which the parties
            were both members of a subject-state, and it is very probable, though nowhere explicitly
            stated, that Herodes was not a native Lesbian, but an Athenian citizen resident in
              <placeName key="tgn,7002672">Lesbos</placeName> as a cleruch. If so, there is nothing
            to prevent our supposing that the trial would have taken place in <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in any event.</note> You thought fit to let
          the present court decide the merits of his statements; but you pass judgement on his acts
          yourselves. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" type="section">
        <p>Why, even slaves who have murdered their masters and been caught red-handed are not put
          to death by the victim's own relatives; they are handed over to the authorities as the
          ancient laws of your country ordain. If it is a fact that a slave is allowed to give
          evidence that a free man is guilty of murder, if a master can seek vengeance for the
          murder of his slave, should he see fit, and if a court can sentence the murderer of a
          slave as effectively as it can the murderer of a free man,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >i.e., (1) The slave could have been cited as a witness in court. (2) It is a criminal
            offence to put to death a slave belonging to someone else. (3) Anyone who commits such
            an act can be prosecuted for murder. (2) is of course a deliberate distortion of the
            facts, as the slave in question had become the property of the prosecution by purchase
            (cf. 47); and with it (3) loses its force.</note> it follows that the slave in question
          should have had a public trial, instead of being put to death by you without a hearing.
          Thus it is you who deserve to be on trial far rather than I, who am being accused
          this day so undeservedly. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" type="section">
        <p>And now, gentlemen, consider further the statements of the two witnesses tortured. What
          are the fair and reasonable conclusions to be drawn from them? The slave gave two
          accounts: at one time he maintained that I was guilty, at another that I was not. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" type="section">
        <p>On the other hand, in spite of similar torture, the free man has not even yet said
          anything to damage me. He could not be influenced by offers of freedom, as his companion
          had been; and at the same time he was determined to cling to the truth, cost what it
          might. Of course, as far as his own advantage was concerned, he knew, like the other, that
          the torture would be over as soon as he corroborated the prosecution. Which, then, have we
          more reason to believe: the witness who firmly adhered to the same statement throughout,
          or the witness who affirmed a thing at one moment, and denied it at the next? Why, quite
          apart from the torture employed, those who consistently keep to one statement about one
          set of facts are more to be trusted than those who contradict themselves. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" type="section">
        <p>Then again, of the slave's statements half are in favor of one side, half in favor of the
          other: his affirmations support my accusers, and his denials support me. [;Similarly with
          the combined statements of both the witnesses examined: the one affirmed, and the other
          consistently denied.];<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Clearly an addition by a reader who
            thought that the argument ought to be pushed still further. The syntax is harsh and the
            reasoning itself unsound; B had denied throughout, it is true; but A, as we have just
            heard, spent half his time denying, and the other half affirming; so he cannot be set
            against B.</note> But I need not point out that any equal division is to the advantage
          of the defence rather than the prosecution, in view of the fact that an equal division of
          the votes of the jury similarly benefits the defence rather than the prosecution. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" type="section">
        <p>Such was the examination under torture on which the prosecution rely, gentlemen, when
          they say that they are convinced that I am the murderer of Herodes. Yet if I had had
          anything whatsoever on my conscience, if I had committed a crime of this kind, I should
          have got rid of both witnesses while I had the opportunity, either by taking them with me
          to <placeName key="tgn,7007528">Aenus</placeName> or by shipping them to the
            mainland.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., to <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia
              Minor</placeName>.</note> I should not have left the men who knew the truth behind to
          inform against me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" type="section">
        <p>The prosecution further allege that they discovered on board a note stating that I had
          killed Herodes, which I had intended to send to Lycinus. But what need had I to send a
          note, when the bearer himself was my accomplice? Not only would he, as one of the
          murderers, have told the story more clearly in his own words, but it would have been quite
          unnecessary to conceal the message from him, and it is essentially messages which cannot
          be disclosed to the bearer that are sent in writing. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" type="section">
        <p>Then again, an extensive message would have had to be written down, as its length would
          have prevented the bearer remembering it. But this one was brief enough to deliver—“The
          man is dead.” Moreover, bear in mind that the note contradicted the slave tortured, and
          the slave the note. The slave stated under torture that he had committed the murder
            himself,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The speaker forgets that he denied this in <bibl
              n="Antiph. 5.39">Antiph. 5.39</bibl>.</note> whereas the note when opened revealed the
          fact that I was the murderer. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" type="section">
        <p>Which are we to believe? The prosecution discovered the note on board only during a
          second search, not during their first one; they had not hit on the idea at the time. It
          was not until the first witness had said nothing to incriminate me when tortured that they
          dropped the note in the boat, in order to have that, if nothing else, as a ground for
          accusing me. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" type="section">
        <p>Then, once the note had been read and the second witness, when tortured, persisted in
          disagreeing with the note, it was impossible to spirit away the message read from it.
          Needless to say, had the prosecution supposed that they would induce the slave to lie
          about me immediately, they would never have devised the message contained in the note.
          Call me witnesses to confirm these facts. <quote type="Witnesses">Witnesses </quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" type="section">
        <p>Now what was my motive in murdering Herodes? For there was not even any bad feeling
          between us. The prosecution have the audacity to suggest that I murdered him as a favor.
          But who has ever turned murderer to oblige a friend? No one, I am sure. The bitterest
          feeling has to exist before murder is committed, while the growth of the design is always
          abundantly manifest. And, as I said, between Herodes and myself there was no bad feeling.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" type="section">
        <p>Well and good. Then was it that I was afraid of being murdered by him myself? A motive of
          that kind might well drive a man to the deed. No, I had no such fears with regard to him.
          Then was I going to enrich myself by the murder? No, he had no money. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" type="section">
        <p>Indeed, it would be more intelligible and nearer the truth for me to maintain that money
          was at the bottom of your own attempt to secure my death than it is for you to suggest it
          as my motive in murdering Herodes. You yourself deserve to be convicted of murder by my
          relatives for killing me far more than I by you and the family of Herodes. Of your designs
          on my life I have clear proof: whereas you, in seeking to make an end of me, produce only
          a tale of which proof is impossible. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" type="section">
        <p>I assure you that I personally can have had no motive for murdering Herodes; but I must
          apparently clear Lycinus as well as myself by showing the absurdity of the charge in his
          case also. I assure you that his position with regard to Herodes was the same as my own.
          He had no means of enriching himself by the murder; and there was no danger from which the
          death of Herodes released him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" type="section">
        <p>Further, the following consideration indicates most strikingly that he did not desire his
          death: had redress for some old injury been owing to Lycinus, he could have brought
          Herodes into court on a charge which endangered his life, and have enlisted the help of
          your laws in making an end of him. By proving him a criminal he could have gained both his
          own object and your city's gratitude. This he did not trouble to do: he did not even
          attempt to institute proceedings against him, in spite of the fact that he was running a
          more honorable risk &lt;by bringing Herodes into court than by engaging me to murder him.
          Call me witnesses to confirm these facts.&gt;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The occurence
            of the rubric <foreign xml:lang="greek">*ma/rtures</foreign> immediately after the words
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">o( ki/ndunos au)tw=|</foreign> in the Mss. has led the
            majority of edd. to suppose that one of the usual formulae introducing witnesses has
            dropped out. But there are grounds for suspecting a larger lacuna. If the words <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">kai/toi kalli/wn ge h)=n o( ki/ndunos au)tw=|</foreign> form a
            complete sentence in themselves, they are both obscure and ambiguous. <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">ki/ndunos</foreign> might refer (a) to <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >kindu/nw| mega/lw|</foreign> six lines above and bear the meaning “the danger into
            which L. would bring H. by prosecuting him.” The gist of the sentence would then be “to
            endanger H.'s life by legal methods was a more creditable course for L. than to murder
            him.” On the other hand, it might refer (b) to the risk (of failing to gain a verdict
            and so being fined) run by L. himself in prosecuting H. The speaker would then be saying
            in effect “it was more creditable for L. to risk losing a case at law against H. than to
            risk murdering him.” Of the two alternatives (b) is the more probable. But Antiphon is
            not in the habit of being terse to the point of obscurity; and it is hard to believe
            that the sentence as he wrote it ended at <foreign xml:lang="greek">au)tw=|</foreign>.
            For a suggested supplement see crit. note 3.</note><quote type="Witnesses"
            >Witnesses</quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" type="section">
        <p>So we are to understand that Lycinus left Herodes in peace as far as an action at law was
          concerned, and instead chose the one course which was bound to endanger both himself and
          me, that of plotting his death, notwithstanding the fact that, if discovered, he would
          have deprived me of my country and himself of his rights before heaven and mankind, and of
          all that men hold most sacred and most precious. I will go further: I will adopt the
          standpoint of the prosecution: I will admit as readily as you like that Lycinus did desire
          the death of Herodes. Does it follow that I should ever have been induced to perform in
          his stead a deed which he refused to commit with his own hand? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" type="section">
        <p>Was I, for instance, in a position to risk my life, and he in a position to hire me to do
          so? No, I had money, and he had none. On the contrary, the probabilities show that he
          would have been induced to commit the crime by me sooner than I by him; for even after
          suffering an execution for a debt of seven minae, he could not release himself from
          prison: his friends had to purchase his release. In fact, this affords the clearest
          indication of the relations between Lycinus and myself; it shows that my friendship with
          him was hardly close enough to make me willing to satisfy his every wish. I cannot suppose
          that I braved the enormous risk which murder involved to oblige him, after refusing to pay
          off seven minae for him when he was suffering the hardships of imprisonment. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" type="section">
        <p>I have proved, then, to the best of my ability that both Lycinus and I are innocent.
          However, the prosecution make endless play with the argument that Herodes has disappeared;
          and doubtless it is a fact which you want explained. Now if it is conjecture which is
          expected of me, you are just as capable of it as I am—we are both alike innocent of the
          crime; on the other hand, if it is the truth, the prosecution must ask one of the
          criminals: he would best be able to satisfy them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" type="section">
        <p>The utmost that I who am not guilty can reply is that I am not guilty; whereas the
          criminal can easily reveal the facts, or at least make a good guess. Criminals no sooner
          commit a crime than they invent an explanation to suit it<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >i.e., a culprit is the first to suggest that someone else is to blame.</note>; on the
          other hand, an innocent man can scarcely guess the answer to what is a mystery to him.
          Each of you yourselves, I am sure, if asked something which he did not happen to know,
          would simply reply to that effect; and if told to say more, you would find
          yourselves, I think, in a serious difficulty. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" type="section">
        <p>So do not present me with a difficulty which you yourselves would not find easy of
          solution. Furthermore, do not make my acquittal depend on my making plausible conjectures.
          Let it be enough for me to prove my innocence of the crime; and that depends not upon my
          discovering how Herodes disappeared or met his end, but upon my possessing no motive
          whatever for murdering him. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" type="section">
        <p>As I know from report, there have been similar cases in the past, when sometimes the
          victim, sometimes the murderer, has not been traced; it would be unfair, were those who
          had been in their company held responsible. Many, again, have been accused before now of
          the crimes of others, and have lost their lives before the truth became known. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" type="section">
        <p>For instance, the murderers of one of your own citizens, Ephialtes,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The murder had been committed some forty-five years before (first half of
            461). Ephialtes was an extreme radical, and in conjunction with Pericles was responsible
            for the violent attack made upon the prerogatives of the Areopagus in 462. His
            assassination was the result. Aristotle states that the crime was committed by
            Aristodicus of <placeName key="perseus,Tanagra">Tanagra</placeName>, employed for the
            purpose by Ephialtes' enemies. This may well be true, as it suited Antiphon's
            requirements here to assume that the mystery had never been satisfactorily solved. Cf.
              <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 25.4">Aristot. 35.5</bibl>, <bibl n="Diod. 11.77.6">Dio.
              Sic. 11.77.6</bibl>, <bibl n="Plut. Per. 10">Plut. Per. 10</bibl>.</note> have
          remained undiscovered to this day; it would have been unfair to his companions to require
          them to conjecture who his assassins were under pain of being held guilty of the murder
          themselves. Moreover, the murderers of Ephialtes made no attempt to get rid of the body,
          for fear of the accompanying risk of publicity—unlike myself, who, we are told, took no
          one into my confidence when planning the crime, but then sought help for the removal of
          the corpse. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="69" type="section">
        <p>Once more, a slave, not twelve years old, recently attempted to murder his master. Had he
          had the courage to stay where he was, instead of taking to his heels in terror at his
          victim's cries, leaving the knife in the wound, the entire household<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">i.e., of slaves.</note> would have perished, as no one would have dreamed him
          capable of such audacity. As it was, he was caught, and later confessed his own guilt. </p>
        <p>Then again, your Hellenotamiae<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Nothing further is known of
            the incident. The Hellenotamiae were ten in number and administered the funds of the
            Delian League.</note> were once accused of embezzlement, as wrongfully as I am accused
          today. Anger swept reason aside, and they were all put to death save one. Later the true
          facts became known. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="70" type="section">
        <p>This one, whose name is said to have been Sosias, though under sentence of death, had not
          yet been executed. Meanwhile it was shown how the money had disappeared. The Athenian
          people rescued him from the very hands of the Eleven<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            accusation must have taken the form of an impeachment (<foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >ei)saggeli/a</foreign>) before the Assembly. The task of the Eleven was to supervise
            the execution of the sentence.</note>: while the rest had died entirely innocent. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="71" type="section">
        <p>You older ones remember this yourselves, I expect, and the younger have heard of it like
          myself. </p>
        <p>Thus it is wise to let time help us in testing the truth of a matter. Perhaps the
          circumstances of Herodes' death will similarly come to light hereafter; so do not discover
          that you have put an innocent man to death when it is too late. Weigh the matter carefully
          while there is yet time, without anger and without prejudice: for they are the worst of
          counsellors; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="72" type="section">
        <p>it is impossible for an angry man to make a right decision, as anger destroys his one
          instrument of decision, his judgement. The lapse of one day after another, gentlemen, has
          a wondrous power of liberating the judgement from the sway of passion and of bringing the
          truth to light. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="73" type="section">
        <p>Remember too that it is pity which I deserve from you, not punishment. Wrongdoers should
          be punished: those wrongfully imperilled should be pitied. You must never let your power
          to satisfy justice by saving my life be overridden by my enemies' desire to outrage it by
          putting me to death. A delay will still allow you to take the awful step which the
          prosecution urge upon you; whereas haste will make a fair consideration of the case quite
          impossible. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="74" type="section">
        <p>I must also defend my father although, as my father, it would have been far more natural
          for him to be defending me. He is far older than I, and knows what my life has been
          whereas I am far younger than he, and cannot know what his has been. If my accuser were on
          trial, and I were giving evidence against him based on hearsay instead of certain
          knowledge, he would protest that he was being treated monstrously; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="75" type="section">
        <p>yet he sees nothing monstrous in forcing me to explain occurrences with which I am far
          too young to be acquainted save from hearsay. However, as a loyal son, I will use what
          knowledge I have to defend my father against the unwarranted abuse to which you have been
          listening. Possibly indeed I may fail. I may describe but faultily a life which was
          without fault. But none the less, I will accept that risk. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="76" type="section">
        <p>Before the revolt of <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName><note
            anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> had
            revolted from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> some ten years
            previously, in 428.</note> my father gave visible proof of his devotion to your
          interests. When, however, the city as a whole was so ill-advised as to commit the blunder
          of revolting,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Although the <foreign xml:lang="greek">th=s
              u(mete/ras gnw/mhs</foreign> of the Mss., if retained and taken with <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">h(/marte</foreign>, would give the sense “failed in what you expected
            of them,” an expression for which there are parallels, <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >sunecamartei=n</foreign> REQUIRES <foreign xml:lang="greek">h(/marte</foreign> alone
            to balance it, and the repetition of <foreign xml:lang="greek">gnw/mh</foreign> lines
            later is harsh in the extreme.</note> he was forced to join the city as a whole in that
          blunder. Not but what even then his feelings towards you remained unchanged: although he
          could no longer display his devotion in the old way. It was not easy for him to leave the
          city, as the ties which bound him, his children, and his property, were strong ones; nor
          yet could he set it at defiance as long as he remained there. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="77" type="section">
        <p>But from the moment that you punished the authors of the revolt—of whom my father was not
          found to be one—and granted the other citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene"
            >Mytilene</placeName> an amnesty which allowed them to continue living on their own
            land,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Thuc. 3.50">Thuc. 3.50</bibl>. The
            walls of <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> were rased, her fleet
            taken from her, and the entire island, except for <placeName key="perseus,Methymna"
              >Methymna</placeName>, divided among Athenian cleruchs. These drew a fixed rent from
            the inhabitants, who continued to work the land.</note> he has not been guilty of a
          single fault, of a single lapse from duty. He has failed neither the city of <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> nor that of <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene"
            >Mytilene</placeName>, when a public service was demanded of him; he regularly furnishes
          choruses, and always pays the imposts.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The choruses
            mentioned were of course local, and performed at the Mytilenean festivals. The “services
            to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>” amount to nothing more than the
            payment of <foreign xml:lang="greek">te/lh</foreign>(?harbor-dues). Professor Wade-Gery
            suggests to me that the <foreign xml:lang="greek">ei)kosth/</foreign> may be meant, a 5
            per cent impost which replaced the tribute early in <date>413</date> (<bibl
              n="Thuc. 7.28">Thuc. 7.28</bibl>). If so, the date of the speech must fall between the
            spring of 413 and the autumn, when news of the Sicilian disaster arrived.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="78" type="section">
        <p>If <placeName key="tgn,7007528">Aenus</placeName> is his favorite place of resort, that
          fact does not mean that he is evading any of his obligations towards <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Or possibly
              <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>.</note> or that he has become
          the citizen of another city, like those others, some of whom I see crossing to the
          mainland and settling among your enemies, while the rest actually litigate with you under
            treaty;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The text of the manuscript is clearly unsound
            here. (1) The <foreign xml:lang="greek">me\n</foreign> in the fourth line of <bibl
              n="Antiph. 5.78">Antiph. 5.78</bibl> has no answering <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >de\</foreign>. (2) The sense of the passage as it stands is in any case
            unsatisfactory. <foreign xml:lang="greek">su/mbola</foreign> (l. 6)were special treaties
            regulating the settlement of private disputes, generally commercial in character,
            between the citizens of different states. Fragments of two such treaties have survived :
              <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>-Phaseils (I.G.i2 16 ff.) and
              Athens-<placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName> (I.G. i2 60 ff.); and in
            the first of these there is a reference to a third, Athens-Chios. It is quite certain,
            however, that agreements of this sort did not extend to enemy states, as the passage
            would suggest if the manuscript reading be accepted. Various corrections have been
            proposed. A. Fraenkel and Wilamowitz suppose a considerable lacuna which contained the
            words <foreign xml:lang="greek">tou\s d' e)s po/lin summaxi/da diokizome/nous</foreign>,
            or the like. The objection to such a solution is that <foreign xml:lang="greek">kai\
              di/kas a)po\ sumbo/lwn u(mi=n dikazome/nous</foreign> in l. 6 becomes otiose, as it is
            known that <foreign xml:lang="greek">su/mbola</foreign> already existed between Athens
            and <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>. Better is Reiskes's <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">tou\s de\</foreign>. We then have a contrast between Euxitheus'
            father, who is a loyal citizen of Mytilene under Athenian rule, and other Mytileneans
            who, since the revolt of <placeName key="tgn,7002672">Lesbos</placeName> ten years
            previously, have either (a) shown their hostility to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> passively by settling on the Asiatic coast in towns under Persian
            control or (b) shown it actively by remaining in <placeName key="tgn,7002672"
              >Lesbos</placeName> and initiating an unending series of lawsuits against the Athenian
            cleruchs who have become their landlords.</note> nor does it mean that he desires to be
          beyond the reach of the Athenian courts. It means that he shares your own hatred of those
          who thrive on prosecution. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="79" type="section">
        <p>The act which my father joined his whole city in committing, which he committed not from
          choice but under compulsion, affords no just ground for punishing him individually. The
          mistake then made will live in the memory of every citizen of <placeName
            key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>. They exchanged great prosperity for great
          misery, and saw their country pass into the possession of others. Nor again must you be
          influenced by the distorted account of my father's conduct as an individual with which you
          have been presented. Nothing but money is at the bottom of this elaborate attack upon him
          and myself; and unfortunately there are many circumstances which favor those who seek to
          lay hands on the goods of others; my father is too old to help me: and I am far too young
          to be able to avenge myself as I should. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="80" type="section">
        <p>You must help me: you must refuse to reach those who make a trade of prosecution to
          become more powerful than yourselves. If they achieve their purpose when they appear
          before you, it will be a lesson to their victims to compromise with them and avoid open
          court; but if by appearing before you they succeed only in gaining an evil reputation for
          themselves, you will enjoy the honor and the power which it is right that you should. So
          give me and give justice your support. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="81" type="section">
        <p>Proof as complete as the presumptions and the evidence supplied by things human could
          make it has now been presented to you. But in cases of this nature the indications
          furnished by heaven must also have no small influence on your verdict.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The fact that an argument of this kind could be advanced in a
            court of law, shows, like the popular agitation over the mutilation of the Hermae, that
            the average Athenian of the time was far from being a rationalist.</note> It is upon
          them that you chiefly depend for safe guidance in affairs of state, whether in times of
          crisis or tranquillity; so they should be allowed equal prominence and weight in the
          settlement of private questions. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="82" type="section">
        <p>I hardly think I need remind you that many a man with unclean hands or some other form of
          defilement who has embarked on shipboard with the righteous has involved them in his own
            destruction.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Oddly reminiscent of <bibl
              n="Aesch. Seven 602">Aesch. Seven 602</bibl> ff.: <foreign xml:lang="greek">h)\ ga\r
              cuneisba\s ploi=on eu)sebh\s a)nh\r nau/taisi qermoi=s kai\ panourgi/a| tini\ o)/lwlen
              a)ndrw=n su\n qeoptu/stw| ge/nei</foreign>.</note> Others, while they have escaped
          death, have had their lives imperilled owing to such polluted wretches. Many, too, have
          been proved to be defiled as they stood beside a sacrifice, because they prevented the
          proper performance of the rites. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="83" type="section">
        <p>With me the opposite has happened in every case. Not only have fellow-passengers of mine
          enjoyed the calmest of voyages: but whenever I have attended a sacrifice, that sacrifice
          has invariably been successful. I claim that these facts furnish the strongest presumption
          in my favor that the charge brought against me by the prosecution is unfounded; I have
          witnesses to confirm them.<quote type="Witnesses">Witnesses</quote>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="84" type="section">
        <p>I know furthermore, gentlemen of the jury, that if the witnesses were testifying against
          me that my presence on shipboard or at a sacrifice had been the occasion of some unholy
          manifestation, the prosecution would be treating that fact as supremely significant; they
          would be showing that here, in the signs from heaven, was to be found the clearest
          confirmation of their charge. As, however, the signs have contradicted their assertions
          and the witnesses testify that what I say is true and that what the prosecution say is
          not, they urge you to put no credence in the evidence of those witnesses; according to
          them, it is their own statements which you should believe. Whereas every one else uses the
          facts to prove the worth of mere assertion, they use mere assertion for the purpose of
          discrediting the facts. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="85" type="section">
        <p>All the charges which I can remember, gentlemen, I have answered; and for your own sakes
          I think that you should acquit me. A verdict saving my life will alone enable you to
          comply with the law and your oath; for you have sworn to return a lawful verdict; and
          while the crime with which I am charged can still be tried legally, the laws under which I
          was arrested do not concern my case.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Another reference to
            the argument that his case could be preperly tried only by a <foreign xml:lang="greek"
              >di/kh fo/nou</foreign> before the Areopagus. The “laws under which I was arrested”
            are of course the <foreign xml:lang="greek">no/moi tw=n kakou/rgwn</foreign> defining
            the scope of <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)pagwgh/</foreign> for the <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">kakourgi/a</foreign>.</note> If two trials have been made out of one,
          it is not I, but my accusers, who are to blame; and I cannot suppose that if my bitterest
          enemies have involved me in two trials, impartial ministers of justice like yourselves
          will prematurely find me guilty of murder in the present one. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="86" type="section">
        <p>Beware of such haste, gentlemen; give time its opportunity; it is time which enables
          those who seek the truth to find it with certainty. In fact, gentlemen, I for one have
          always maintained that, while a case of this kind should certainly be tried according to
          law, the rights of the matter should be established as many times as the law will permit,
          since they would thus be the better understood; the repeated trial of a case is a good
          friend of the truth and the deadly foe of misrepresentation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="87" type="section">
        <p>In a trial for murder,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl n="Antiph. 5.87">Antiph.
              5.87-89</bibl> appear, with slight modifications, in <bibl n="Antiph. 6.3">Antiph.
              6.3-6</bibl>. It is clear that we have here one of those loci communes which were part
            of the stock in trade of every <foreign xml:lang="greek">logo/grafos</foreign> and could
            easily be adapted to different contexts (cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 5.14">Antiph. 5.14</bibl>
            ff. and <bibl n="Antiph. 5.38">Antiph. 5.38</bibl> ff., <bibl n="Antiph. 6.2">Antiph.
              6.2</bibl>, <bibl n="Antiph. 6.27">Antiph. 6.27</bibl>, <bibl n="Antiph. 1.12">Antiph.
              1.12</bibl> ff., and <bibl n="Andoc. 1.1">Andoc. 1.1</bibl>, 6, 7, 9). The present
            passage stresses the gravity and the finality of a <foreign xml:lang="greek">di/kh
              fo/nou</foreign>, a theme which was likely to find a place in most <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">fonikoi\ lo/goi</foreign>. Here, however, it is introduced a little
            awkwardly. The words <foreign xml:lang="greek">di/kh fo/nou</foreign> (87 init .) refer,
            not to the present trial, which is an <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)/ndeicis</foreign>,
            but to the trial before the Areopagus which Euxitheus hopes will follow; and the word
              <foreign xml:lang="greek">u(mei=s</foreign> in the third line of 87 is used in the
            same general sense as in 90 (cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 5.90">Antiph. 5.90</bibl> note
            1).</note> even if judgement is wrongly given against the defendant, justice and the
          facts cannot prevail against that decision. Once you condemn me, I must perforce obey your
          verdict and the law, even if I am not the murderer or concerned in the crime. No one would
          venture either to disregard the sentence passed upon him because he was sure that he had
          had no part in the crime, or to disobey the law if he knew in his heart that he was guilty
          of such a deed. He has to submit to the verdict in defiance of the facts, or submit to the
          facts themselves, as the case may be, above all if his victim has none to avenge him.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The speaker is here thinking of the master who has killed his
            slave; the slave has no family to institute proceedings on his behalf (cf. <bibl
              n="Antiph. 6.4">Antiph. 6.4</bibl> f.). The argument of 87 as a whole sounds odd to
            modern ears; but it should be remembered that at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> the defendant in a <foreign xml:lang="greek">di/kh
              fo/nou</foreign> always had the option of going into voluntary exile before the court
            passed sentence. Hence it was possible to speak of “disregarding the sentence
            imposed.”</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="88" type="section">
        <p>The laws, the oaths, the sacrifices, the proclamations, in fact the entire proceeding in
          connection with trials for murder differ as profoundly as they do from the proceedings
          elsewhere simply because it is of supreme importance that the facts at issue, upon which
          so much turns, should themselves be rightly interpreted. Such a right interpretation means
          vengeance for him who has been wronged; whereas to find an innocent man guilty of murder
          is a mistake, and a sinful mistake, which offends both gods and laws. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="89" type="section">
        <p>Nor is it as serious for the prosecutor to accuse the wrong person as it is for you
          jurors to reach a wrong verdict. The charge brought by the prosecutor is not in itself
          effective; whether it becomes so, depends upon you, sitting in judgement. On the other
          hand if you yourselves, when actually sitting in judgement, return a wrong verdict, you
          cannot rid yourselves of the responsibility for the mistake by blaming someone else for
          that verdict. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="90" type="section">
        <p>Then how can you decide the case aright? By allowing the prosecution to bring their
          charge only after taking the customary oath, and by allowing me to confine my defence to
          the question before the court. And how will you do this? By acquitting me today. For I do
          not escape your sentence even so: you will be the judges at the second hearing also.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">True only in a general sense. The present jury was composed of
            ordinary Heliasts; whereas the jury at a <foreign xml:lang="greek">di/kh
              fo/nou</foreign> would consist of ex-arkhons, sitting as members of the Areopagus.
            Euxitheus is speaking as an alien, and by <foreign xml:lang="greek">u(mei=s</foreign>
            means “you Athenians.”</note> If you spare me now, you can treat me as you will then;
          whereas once you put me to death, you cannot even consider my case further. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="91" type="section">
        <p>Indeed, supposing that you were bound to make some mistake, it would be less of an
          outrage to acquit me unfairly than to put me to death without just cause; for the one
          thing is a mistake and nothing more: the other is a sin in addition. You must exercise the
          greatest caution in what you do, because you will not be able to reconsider your action.
          In a matter which admits of reconsideration a mistake, whether made through giving rein to
          the feelings or through accepting a distorted account of the facts, is not so serious; it
          is still possible to change one's mind and come to a right decision. But when
          reconsideration is impossible, the wrong done is only increased by altering one's mind and
          acknowledging one's mistake. Some of you yourselves have in fact repented before now of
          having sent men to their death; but when you, who had been misled, felt repentance, most
          assuredly did those who had misled you deserve death. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="92" type="section">
        <p>Moreover, whereas involuntary mistakes are excusable, voluntary mistakes are not; for an
          involuntary mistake is due to chance, gentlemen, a voluntary one to the will. And what
          could be more voluntary than the immediate putting into effect of a carefully considered
          course of action? Furthermore, the wrongful taking of life by one's vote is just as
          criminal as the wrongful taking of life by one's hand. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="93" type="section">
        <p>Rest assured that I should never have come to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName>, had such a crime been on my conscience. I am here, as it is,
          because I have faith in justice, the most precious ally of the man who has no deed of sin
          upon his conscience and who has committed no transgression against the gods. Often at such
          an hour as this, when the body has given up the struggle, its salvation is the spirit,
          which is ready to fight on in the conscience that it is innocent. On the other hand, he
          whose conscience is guilty has no worse enemy than that conscience; for his spirit fails
          him which his body is still unwearied, because it feels that what is approaching him is
          the punishment of his iniquities. But it is with no such guilty conscience that I come
          before you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="94" type="section">
        <p>There is nothing remarkable in the fact that the prosecution are misrepresenting me. It
          is expected of them just as it is expected of you not to consent to do what is wrong. I
          say this because if you follow my advice, it is still open to you to regret your action,
          and that regret can be remedied by punishing me at the second trial: whereas if you
          obediently carry out the prosecution's wishes, the situation cannot be righted again. Nor
          is there a question of a long interval before the law will allow you to take the step to
          which the prosecution are today urging you to consent in defiance of it. It is not haste,
          but discretion which triumphs; so take cognizance of the case today: pass judgement on it
            later<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign xml:lang="greek">tw=n martu/rwn</foreign>
            is clearly an unintelligent gloss, added by a reader who felt that a genitive was needed
            to correspond to <foreign xml:lang="greek">th=s di/khs</foreign>.</note>; form an
          opinion as to the truth today: decide upon it later. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="95" type="section">
        <p>It is very easy, remember, to give false evidence against a man on a capital charge. If
          you are persuaded only for an instant to put him to death, he has lost his chance of
          redress with his life. A man's very friends will refuse to seek redress for him once he is
          dead; and even if they are prepared to do so, what good is it to one who has lost his
          life? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="96" type="section">
        <p>Acquit me, then, today and at the trial for murder the prosecution shall take the
          traditional oath before accusing me: you shall decide my case by the laws of the land: and
          I, if I am unlucky, shall have no grounds left for complaining that I was sentenced to
          death illegally. That is my request; and in making it I am not forgetting your duty as
          godfearing men or depriving myself of my rights, as my life is bound up with your oath.
          Respect which you will, and acquit me.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
