<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader type="text">

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Aristogiton </title>
                <author>Dinarchus</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Dinarchus</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>April and May 1992</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>SGML markup</item>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>There is nothing, it appears, Athenians, which we
                    must not expect either to hear or see in connection with the reports which have
                    been made; but the most remarkable fact of all, in my opinion, confronts us now.
                    The worst character in the city, I should say in the whole world, Aristogiton,
                    has come to pit himself in law against the Areopagus on the subject of truth and
                    justice; and the council which has made the report is now in greater danger than
                    this man who takes bribes against you and who sold for twenty minas the right of
                    free speech in the cause of justice. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>It will be no new or alarming experience for the defendant if he is convicted,
                    for he has committed in the past many other crimes meriting the death penalty
                    and has spent more time in prison than out of it. While he has been in debt to
                    the state he has prosecuted men with citizen rights, though not entitled to do
                    so, and has committed numerous other offences of which you have a more exact
                    knowledge than I. It is a most shameful and monstrous thing for this council to
                    be suspected of making a false report against Aristogiton and for him to be
                    considered among you as having more justice on his side than it has. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>For this reason, Athenians, thinking that the trial holds no dangers for him,
                    this man is coming forward, I believe, to test your attitude. He has often
                    undergone all sorts of suffering short of death, which, if God so wills it and
                    you are wise, he will undergo today. For you must assume, by Heracles, that
                    there will be no improvement in him if he is pardoned by you now, and that in
                    future he will not abstain from taking bribes against you if you now acquit him.
                    For when wickedness is in its infancy perhaps it can be checked by punishment,
                    but when it has grown old and has sampled the usual penalties, it is said to be
                    incurable. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>If therefore you wish depravity to grow up ingrained in <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you should preserve Aristogiton and
                    allow him to act there as he pleases. But if you hate the wicked and accursed
                    and can recall with resentment what this man has done in the past, kill him, for
                    he dared to take money from Harpalus, who he knew was coming to seize your city.
                    Cut short his excuses and deceptive arguments, on which he now depends when he
                    appears before you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Do you realize that, awkward though the arrival of
                    Harpalus was, it has been an advantage to the city in one respect, because it
                    has given you a sure means of testing those who give up everything to the
                    enemies of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> for a payment of
                    silver or gold? Do not be lax, Athenians, or weary of punishing the guilty;
                    purge the city of bribery to the utmost of your ability. Do not ask for
                    arguments from me when you see that the crimes have been plainly attributed to
                    those whom the council has reported. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>[;Or ought you to spare the defendant on account of his ancestry and his
                    moderation, or because he has done you many public and private services?];<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This sentence was excluded from the text by
                        Bekker. It is out of place in the argument here and its substance is given
                        at the beginning of <bibl n="Din. 2.8">Din. 2.8</bibl>.</note> What
                    information do you lack that makes you ask for arguments against the defendant
                    here before you? What if we, the accusers, all ten of us, use up all the water
                    in our clocks and proclaim that it is a terrible thing to release men who have
                    been caught with bribes against the city in their very hands; will that make the
                    council's report against Aristogiton true and just? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>Or suppose that each of us assumes that you are just as well aware as we on which
                    side justice lies in the present trials, and so leaves the platform after a
                    short speech; will the report then be a false one, unjustly made by the
                    Areopagites? Or don't you realize that to take bribes in order to betray the
                    city's interests is one of the greatest crimes causing the most irreparable harm
                    to cities? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>No doubt I shall be told that the defendant is
                    himself a man of sober character coming of a good family, that he has done you
                    many noble services in private and in public life and that therefore you are
                    justified in sparing him. You must all have often heard that, when Aristogiton's
                    father Cydimachus was condemned to death and fled from the city, this admirable
                    son allowed his own father to lack the bare necessities of life, while he
                    survived, and do without a proper burial when he died: a fact for which evidence
                    was often brought against him; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>or again, that the man himself, on being taken to prison for the first time,—no
                    doubt you realize that he has often been imprisoned—dared to behave in such a
                    way there that the inmates voted that no one should either light a fire for him
                    or sit at meals or share the usual sacrifices with him. Reflect, Athenians; what
                    sort of character must we suppose this man to have, who was thrown into prison
                    for criminal conduct </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>and when he was there, among those who had been segregated from the rest of the
                    world as felons, was looked upon as so debased that even there he was not
                    thought worthy of the same treatment as the rest? It is said, in fact, that he
                    was caught thieving among them and that, if there had been any other place more
                    degraded where they could have isolated men who stole in prison, this monster
                    would have been conducted there. These facts, as I said just now, were
                    established by evidence against Aristogiton, as is well known, when the lot fell
                    to him to be custodian of the exchange but he was rejected by those who then
                    decided the appointment to that office.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        custodians of the exchange were responsible for seeing that the laws
                        governing import and export trade were observed. Like most magistrates, they
                        were appointed by lot but were submitted to an examination in court
                            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">dokimasi/a</foreign>) before taking office and
                        could be rejected if unsuitable.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>Do you then feign ignorance among yourselves and give way to pity when the man
                    concerning whom you are about to vote is Aristogiton, who did not pity his own
                    father when reduced to starvation? Do you still wish to hear us talk about the
                    damages he must pay, when you know quite well that his whole life, as well as
                    his recent conduct, justifies the extreme penalty? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>Was it not Aristogiton, Athenians, who made in writing such lying assertions
                    about the priestess of Artemis Brauronia<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        shrine of Artemis at <placeName key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> in
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> was supposed to contain
                        the image of the goddess brought from the Tauri by Iphigenia. There was also
                        a temple of Artemis Brauronia, called <foreign xml:lang="grc">to\ i(ero\n
                            kunhge/sion</foreign>, on the Acropolis ( cf. arg. ad Demosthenem 25.;
                            <bibl n="Paus. 1.23.7">Paus. 1.23.7</bibl>).</note>and her relatives,
                    that when you discovered the truth from his accusers, you fined him five
                    talents, a sum equal to the fine set down in an indictment for illegal
                    proposals? Has he not persisted in maligning every one of you he meets, though
                    he has not yet paid up, and in speaking and proposing measures in the Assembly,
                    regardless of all the penalties against wrongdoers which the laws prescribe?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>And finally, when an information was lodged against him by Lycurgus,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Lyc. Fr. 13">Lyc. frag. 13</bibl>
                        and note.</note>and he was convicted, a debtor to the state without the
                    right to speak in public, when he had been handed over to the Eleven in
                    accordance with the laws, was he not seen<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">
                        Reiske's emendation is followed here.</note>walking about in the front of
                    the lawcourts, and used he not to sit on the seat of the Prytanes? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Well then, Athenians, if a man has often been
                    committed to you lawfully for punishment, condemned on information lodged by
                    citizens, if neither the Eleven nor the prison have been able to restrain him,
                    will you want to use him as a counsellor? The law demands that the herald shall
                    first pray, amid dead silence, before he surrenders to you the task of
                    deliberating on public affairs. Will you then allow an impious wretch, who has
                    proved wicked in his dealings with everyone, and in particular his own father,
                    to share in citizenship with you, with your families and kinsmen? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>After rejecting all thought of pardon for Demades and Demosthenes, because they
                    were proved to have been taking bribes against you, and punishing them,—quite
                    rightly, though you knew that they had served you during their administration,
                    certainly in many respects if not in everything,—will you acquit this accursed
                    man who has not done you a service ever since he has been in politics but has
                    been the greatest possible menace? Would not everyone reproach you if you
                    accepted such a person as your adviser? For when you are addressed by a man
                    whose wickedness is both notorious and undeniable and a byword among all
                    Athenians, the bystanders will wonder whether you who listen to him have no
                    better advisers or whether you enjoy hearing such people. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>Like the early lawgivers, Athenians, who made laws to deal with those addressing
                    your ancestors in the Assembly, you too should try, by your behavior as
                    listeners, to make the speakers who come before you better. What was the
                    attitude of the lawgivers to these men? In the first place, at every sitting of
                    the Assembly they publicly proclaimed curses against wrongdoers, calling down
                    destruction on any who, after accepting bribes, made speeches or proposals upon
                    state affairs, and to that class Aristogiton now belongs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>Secondly, they provided in the laws for indictments for bribery, and this is the
                    only offence for which they imposed a payment equal to ten times the assessment
                    of damages,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. note on <bibl n="Din. 1.60"
                            >Din. 1.60</bibl>. Aristotle (<bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 54">Aristot.
                            Const. Ath. 54</bibl>) states that theft was punished in the same
                        way.</note>in the belief that one who is ready to be paid for the opinions
                    which he is going to express in the Assembly has at heart, when he is speaking,
                    not the interests of the people but the welfare of those who have paid him. Now
                    the council has reported Aristogiton as guilty of this. Moreover, when choosing
                    a man for public office they used to ask what his personal character was,
                    whether he treated his parents well, whether he had served the city in the
                    field, whether he had an ancestral cult or paid taxes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>Aristogiton could not claim one of these qualifications for himself. So far from
                    treating his parents well this man has ill-treated his own father. When you were
                    all serving in the army he was in prison; and, far from being able to point to
                    any memorial of his father, Athenians, he did not give him a proper funeral even
                    in <placeName key="perseus,Eretria">Eretria</placeName> where he died.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 25.54">Dem.
                        25.54</bibl>.</note> While other Athenians are contributing from their own
                    purses this man has not even paid up all the money to defray the public debts
                    which he incurred. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>In fact he has never ceased to contravene all the laws, and his is the one case
                    of those on which the Areopagus has reported where you had inquired yourselves
                    and already knew the answer. For your knowledge that this man is a rogue and a
                    criminal was not gained from the council; you are all very well aware of his
                    wickedness, and hence the statement so often made applies here also, namely
                    that, while you are passing judgement on the defendant, the bystanders and
                    everyone besides are passing judgement on you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Therefore it is your duty as a sensible jury,
                    Athenians, not to vote against yourselves or the rest of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; you should sentence him unanimously
                    to be handed over to the executioners for the death penalty. Do not be traitors
                    and fail to give the honest verdict demanded by your oath. Remember that this
                    man has been convicted by the council of taking bribes against you, convicted of
                    ill-treating him, to use the mildest term, by his father during his life and
                    after his death, condemned by the people's vote and handed over to you for
                    punishment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Remember that this man has caused a deal of harm and has now been caught doing
                    wrong in circumstances which make it shameful for you, his judges, to release
                    him unpunished. For if you do so, how are you going to vote on the other
                    reports, Athenians? What justification will you give for having condemned those
                    men whom you have already tried? What reason will you have, when you were
                    clearly anxious for the council to report those who had taken the money, for
                    failing obviously to punish the men whose names they submit? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>You must not imagine that these trials are private issues concerning no one but
                    the men reported; they are public and concern the rest of us as well. A case of
                    bribery and treason tried before you will affect others in the future in two
                    possible ways: either it will make them accept bribes against you unhesitatingly
                    in the knowledge that they will not be brought to justice, or it will make them
                    afraid to take them, since they will know that those who are caught will be
                    punished in a manner suited to the crime. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>Do you not know that now the fear of what you will do restrains those who are
                    grasping for the money offered for use against you and often makes them turn
                    their backs on the bribe, and that the people's decree, ordering the council to
                    inquire about this money, has prevented even those who brought the gold into the
                    country from admitting their action? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>It was a noble decree, Athenians, a noble decree of your ancestors on this
                    question, providing for a pillar on the Acropolis at the time when Arthmius, son
                    of Pithonax, the Zelite, is said to have brought the gold from the Persians to
                    corrupt the Greeks.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Demosthenes (<bibl
                            n="Dem. 9.42">Dem. 9.42</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 19.271">Dem.
                            19.271</bibl>) refers to this pillar. Arthmius of Zelea was an Athenian
                        proxenus. He was sent by Artaxerxes to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
                            >Peloponnesus</placeName>, probably in 461, to stir up war against the
                        Athenians, who had been assisting a revolt in <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                            >Egypt</placeName>. (Cf. <bibl n="Thuc. 1.109">Thuc. 1.109</bibl>; <bibl
                            n="Diod. 11.74.5">Dio. Sic. 11.74. 5</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.258"
                            >Aeschin. 3.258</bibl>.)</note> For before anyone had accepted it or
                    given proof of his character they sentenced the man who had brought the gold to
                    exile and banished him completely from the country. This decision, as I said,
                    they engraved on a bronze pillar and set up on the Acropolis as a lesson for you
                    their descendants; for they believed that the man who accepted money in any way
                    at all had in mind the interests of the donors rather than those of the city.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>His was the only case in which they added the reason why the people banished him
                    from the city, explicitly writing on the pillar that Arthmius, son of Pithonax,
                    the Zelite, was an enemy of the people and its allies, he and his descendants,
                    and was exiled from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> because
                    he had brought the Persian gold to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
                        >Peloponnese</placeName>. And yet if the people regarded the gold in the
                        <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> as a source of great
                    danger to <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, how can we remain
                    unmoved at the sight of bribery in the city itself? Please attend to the
                    inscription on the pillar.<quote type="Inscription">
                        <title>Inscription</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now what do you think those men would have done,
                    Athenians, if they had caught a general or an orator, one of their own citizens,
                    accepting bribes against the interests of their country, when they so justly and
                    wisely expelled a man who was alien to <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName> in birth and character? That is the reason why they
                    faced danger against the barbarian worthily of the city and their
                        ancestors.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The conclusion of the speech is
                        lost.</note></p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
