<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>  
<title>Leviticus</title>
<author role="textgroup">Old Testament</author>
<editor role="translator">Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>Anne Mahoney</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
</titleStmt>

<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
<date type="release" notBefore="1999-10">Perseus 3.0</date>
<idno type="filename">tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence> 
</availability>
</publicationStmt>

<sourceDesc>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>World English Bible</title>
<editor>Michael Paul Johnson</editor>
<edition>Revision of the American Standard Version of 1901</edition>
<imprint>
<publisher>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</publisher>
<date>2000-2024</date>
</imprint>
</monogr>
<ref target="http://ebible.org/bible/web">The World English Bible</ref>
</biblStruct>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>

<encodingDesc>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])" n="verse">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and verse.</p>
</cRefPattern>
<cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])" n="chapter">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>

<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>

<revisionDesc>
<change when="2024-10-01" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS Conversion</change>
<change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
<change when="2010-06-29" who="student">fixing place tags - AD</change>
<change when="2009-10-08" who="rsingh04">began reorganizing texts module by collection. created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files</change>
<change when="2009-05-27" who="rsingh04">added/fixed cvs log keyword</change>
<change when="1999-10-14" who="Anne Mahoney">Initial markup from flat ASCII text</change>
 </revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>

<text> 
 <body> 
   <div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2"> 
   <head>Leviticus</head> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="1"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="1">
 <p>Yahweh called to Moses, and spoke to him out of the Tent of Meeting, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, When anyone of you offers an offering to Yahweh, you shall offer your offering of the cattle, from the herd and from the flock. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If his offering is a burnt offering from the herd, he shall offer a male without blemish. He shall offer it at the door of the Tent of Meeting, that he may be accepted before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall lay his hand on the head of the burnt offering, and it shall be accepted for him to make atonement for him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall kill the bull before Yahweh. Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall present the blood and sprinkle the blood around on the altar that is at the door of the Tent of Meeting. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall flay the burnt offering, and cut it into pieces. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The sons of Aaron the priest shall put fire on the altar, and lay wood in order on the fire; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall lay the pieces, the head, and the fat in order on the wood that is on the fire which is on the altar; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">but its innards and its legs he shall wash with water. The priest shall burn the whole on the altar, for a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If his offering is from the flock, from the sheep, or from the goats, for a burnt offering, he shall offer a male without blemish. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall kill it on the north side of the altar before Yahweh. Aaron’s sons, the priests, shall sprinkle its blood around on the altar. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall cut it into its pieces, with its head and its fat. The priest shall lay them in order on the wood that is on the fire which is on the altar, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">but the innards and the legs he shall wash with water. The priest shall offer the whole, and burn it on the altar. It is a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If his offering to Yahweh is a burnt offering of birds, then he shall offer his offering of turtledoves, or of young pigeons. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall bring it to the altar, and wring off its head, and burn it on the altar; and its blood shall be drained out on the side of the altar; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and he shall take away its crop with its filth, and cast it beside the altar on the east part, in the place of the ashes. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:1" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall tear it by its wings, but shall not divide it apart. The priest shall burn it on the altar, on the wood that is on the fire. It is a burnt offering, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor to Yahweh. </q></p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="2"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="1">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When anyone offers an offering of a meal offering to Yahweh, his offering shall be of fine flour; and he shall pour oil on it, and put frankincense on it. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="2">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall bring it to Aaron’s sons the priests; and he shall take his handful of its fine flour, and of its oil, with all its frankincense; and the priest shall burn the memorial of it on the altar, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">That which is left of the meal offering shall be Aaron’s and his sons’. It is a most holy thing of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When you offer an offering of a meal offering baked in the oven, it shall be unleavened cakes of fine flour mixed with oil, or unleavened wafers anointed with oil. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If your offering is a meal offering of the baking pan, it shall be of unleavened fine flour, mixed with oil. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall cut it in pieces, and pour oil on it. It is a meal offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If your offering is a meal offering of the frying pan, it shall be made of fine flour with oil. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall bring the meal offering that is made of these things to Yahweh: and it shall be presented to the priest, and he shall bring it to the altar. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall take from the meal offering its memorial, and shall burn it on the altar, an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">That which is left of the meal offering shall be Aaron’s and his sons’. It is a thing most holy of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">No meal offering, which you shall offer to Yahweh, shall be made with yeast; for you shall burn no yeast, nor any honey, as an offering made by fire to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">As an offering of firstfruits you shall offer them to Yahweh: but they shall not come up for a sweet savor on the altar. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Every offering of your meal offering you shall season with salt; neither shall you allow the salt of the covenant of your God to be lacking from your meal offering. With all your offerings you shall offer salt. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If you offer a meal offering of first fruits to Yahweh, you shall offer for the meal offering of your first fruits grain in the ear parched with fire, bruised grain of the fresh ear. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall put oil on it, and lay frankincense on it: it is a meal offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:2" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall burn as its memorial, part of its bruised grain, and part of its oil, along with all its frankincense: it is an offering made by fire to Yahweh. </q></p></div> </div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="3">
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="1"><p><q rend="double; merge">If his offering is a sacrifice of peace offerings; if he offers it from the herd, whether male or female, he shall offer it without blemish before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="2">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it at the door of the tent of meeting: and Aaron’s sons the priests shall sprinkle the blood on the altar round about. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall offer of the sacrifice of peace offerings an offering made by fire to Yahweh; the fat that covers the innards, and all the fat that is on the innards, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, he shall take away. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Aaron’s sons shall burn it on the altar on the burnt offering, which is on the wood that is on the fire: it is an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If his offering for a sacrifice of peace offerings to Yahweh is from the flock; male or female, he shall offer it without blemish. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he offers a lamb for his offering, then he shall offer it before Yahweh; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and he shall lay his hand on the head of his offering, and kill it before the tent of meeting: and Aaron’s sons shall sprinkle its blood on the altar round about. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall offer from the sacrifice of peace offerings an offering made by fire to Yahweh; its fat, the entire tail fat, he shall take away close to the backbone; and the fat that covers the inwards, and all the fat that is on the inwards, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, he shall take away. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall burn it on the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If his offering is a goat, then he shall offer it before Yahweh: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and he shall lay his hand on its head, and kill it before the tent of meeting; and the sons of Aaron shall sprinkle its blood on the altar round about. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall offer from it as his offering, an offering made by fire to Yahweh; the fat that covers the innards, and all the fat that is on the innards, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, he shall take away. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall burn them on the altar: it is the food of the offering made by fire, for a sweet savor; all the fat is Yahweh’s. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:3" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It shall be a perpetual statute throughout your generations in all your dwellings, that you shall eat neither fat nor blood. </q></p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="4"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, saying, If anyone sins unintentionally, in any of the things which Yahweh has commanded not to be done, and does any one of them: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">if the anointed priest sins so as to bring guilt on the people, then let him offer for his sin, which he has sinned, a young bull without blemish to Yahweh for a sin offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall bring the bull to the door of the Tent of Meeting before Yahweh; and he shall lay his hand on the head of the bull, and kill the bull before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The anointed priest shall take some of the blood of the bull, and bring it to the Tent of Meeting. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle some of the blood seven times before Yahweh, before the veil of the sanctuary. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar of sweet incense before Yahweh, which is in the tent of meeting; and he shall pour out all the blood of the bull out at the base of the altar of burnt offering, which is at the door of the Tent of Meeting. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall take all the fat of the bull of the sin offering off of it; the fat that covers the innards, and all the fat that is on the innards, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, he shall take away, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">as it is taken off of the ox of the sacrifice of peace offerings. The priest shall burn them on the altar of burnt offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The bull’s skin, all its flesh, with its head, and with its legs, its innards, and its dung, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">even the whole bull shall he carry forth outside the camp to a clean place, where the ashes are poured out, and burn it on wood with fire. Where the ashes are poured out it shall be burned. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the whole congregation of Israel sins, and the thing is hidden from the eyes of the assembly, and they have done any of the things which Yahweh has commanded not to be done, and are guilty; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">when the sin in which they have sinned is known, then the assembly shall offer a young bull for a sin offering, and bring it before the Tent of Meeting. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The elders of the congregation shall lay their hands on the head of the bull before Yahweh; and the bull shall be killed before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The anointed priest shall bring of the blood of the bull to the Tent of Meeting: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall dip his finger in the blood, and sprinkle it seven times before Yahweh, before the veil. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall put some of the blood on the horns of the altar which is before Yahweh, that is in the Tent of Meeting; and the rest of the blood he shall pour out at the base of the altar of burnt offering, which is at the door of the Tent of Meeting. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">All its fat he shall take from it, and burn it on the altar. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Thus shall he do with the bull; as he did with the bull of the sin offering, so shall he do with this; and the priest shall make atonement for them, and they shall be forgiven. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall carry forth the bull outside the camp, and burn it as he burned the first bull. It is the sin offering for the assembly. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When a ruler sins, and unwittingly does any one of all the things which Yahweh his God has commanded not to be done, and is guilty; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">if his sin, in which he has sinned, is made known to him, he shall bring as his offering a goat, a male without blemish. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall lay his hand on the head of the goat, and kill it in the place where they kill the burnt offering before Yahweh. It is a sin offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering. He shall pour out the rest of its blood at the base of the altar of burnt offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">All its fat he shall burn on the altar, like the fat of the sacrifice of peace offerings; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin, and he will be forgiven. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If anyone of the common people sins unwittingly, in doing any of the things which Yahweh has commanded not to be done, and is guilty; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">if his sin, which he has sinned, is made known to him, then he shall bring for his offering a goat, a female without blemish, for his sin which he has sinned. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering, and kill the sin offering in the place of burnt offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall take some of its blood with his finger, and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering; and the rest of its blood he shall pour out at the base of the altar. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">All its fat he shall take away, like the fat is taken away from off of the sacrifice of peace offerings; and the priest shall burn it on the altar for a sweet savor to Yahweh; and the priest shall make atonement for him, and he will be forgiven. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he brings a lamb as his offering for a sin offering, he shall bring a female without blemish. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall lay his hand on the head of the sin offering, and kill it for a sin offering in the place where they kill the burnt offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall take some of the blood of the sin offering with his finger, and put it on the horns of the altar of burnt offering; and all the rest of its blood he shall pour out at the base of the altar. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:4" n="35">
<p><q rend="double; merge">All its fat he shall take away, like the fat of the lamb is taken away from the sacrifice of peace offerings; and the priest shall burn them on the altar, on the offerings of Yahweh made by fire; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin that he has sinned, and he will be forgiven.</q> </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="5">
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="1"><p><q rend="double; merge">If anyone sins, in that he hears the voice of adjuration, he being a witness, whether he has seen or known, if he doesn’t report it, then he shall bear his iniquity. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="2">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Or if anyone touches any unclean thing, whether it is the carcass of an unclean animal, or the carcass of unclean cattle, or the carcass of unclean creeping things, and it is hidden from him, and he is unclean, then he shall be guilty. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Or if he touches the uncleanness of man, whatever his uncleanness is with which he is unclean, and it is hidden from him; when he knows of it, then he shall be guilty. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Or if anyone swears rashly with his lips to do evil, or to do good, whatever it is that a man might utter rashly with an oath, and it is hidden from him; when he knows of it, then he shall be guilty of one of these. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It shall be, when he is guilty of one of these, he shall confess that in which he has sinned: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and he shall bring his trespass offering to Yahweh for his sin which he has sinned, a female from the flock, a lamb or a goat, for a sin offering; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he can’t afford a lamb, then he shall bring his trespass offering for that in which he has sinned, two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, to Yahweh; one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall bring them to the priest, who shall first offer the one which is for the sin offering, and wring off its head from its neck, but shall not sever it completely. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall sprinkle some of the blood of the sin offering on the side of the altar; and the rest of the blood shall be drained out at the base of the altar. It is a sin offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall offer the second for a burnt offering, according to the ordinance; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin which he has sinned, and he shall be forgiven. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if he can’t afford two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, then he shall bring his offering for that in which he has sinned, the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a sin offering. He shall put no oil on it, neither shall he put any frankincense on it, for it is a sin offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall bring it to the priest, and the priest shall take his handful of it as the memorial portion, and burn it on the altar, on the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. It is a sin offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall make atonement for him concerning his sin that he has sinned in any of these things, and he will be forgiven; and the rest shall be the priest’s, as the meal offering.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="14">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="15">
<p><q rend="double">If anyone commits a trespass, and sins unwittingly, in the holy things of Yahweh; then he shall bring his trespass offering to Yahweh, a ram without blemish from the flock, according to your estimation in silver by shekels, after the shekel of the sanctuary, for a trespass offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall make restitution for that which he has done amiss in the holy thing, and shall add a fifth part to it, and give it to the priest; and the priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass offering, and he will be forgiven. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If anyone sins, and does any of the things which Yahweh has commanded not to be done; though he didn’t know it, yet he is guilty, and shall bear his iniquity. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall bring a ram without blemish from of the flock, according to your estimation, for a trespass offering, to the priest; and the priest shall make atonement for him concerning the thing in which he sinned and didn’t know it, and he will be forgiven. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:5" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It is a trespass offering. He is certainly guilty before Yahweh.</q></p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="6"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="1"> 
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying,</p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="2">
<p> <q rend="double">If anyone sins, and commits a trespass against Yahweh, and deals falsely with his neighbor in a matter of deposit, or of bargain, or of robbery, or has oppressed his neighbor, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">or has found that which was lost, and dealt falsely therein, and swearing to a lie; in any of all these things that a man does, sinning therein; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then it shall be, if he has sinned, and is guilty, he shall restore that which he took by robbery, or the thing which he has gotten by oppression, or the deposit which was committed to him, or the lost thing which he found, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">or any thing about which he has sworn falsely; he shall restore it even in full, and shall add a fifth part more to it. To him to whom it belongs he shall give it, in the day of his being found guilty. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall bring his trespass offering to Yahweh, a ram without blemish from the flock, according to your estimation, for a trespass offering, to the priest. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall make atonement for him before Yahweh, and he will be forgiven concerning whatever he does to become guilty.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="8">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="9">
<p><q rend="double">Command Aaron and his sons, saying, <q rend="single">This is the law of the burnt offering: the burnt offering shall be on the hearth on the altar all night until the morning; and the fire of the altar shall be kept burning on it. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The priest shall put on his linen garment, and he shall put on his linen breeches upon his body; and he shall remove the ashes from where the fire has consumed the burnt offering on the altar, and he shall put them beside the altar. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">He shall take off his garments, and put on other garments, and carry the ashes outside the camp to a clean place. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The fire on the altar shall be kept burning on it, it shall not go out; and the priest shall burn wood on it every morning: and he shall lay the burnt offering in order upon it, and shall burn on it the fat of the peace offerings. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Fire shall be kept burning on the altar continually; it shall not go out. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">This is the law of the meal offering: the sons of Aaron shall offer it before Yahweh, before the altar. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">He shall take from there his handful of the fine flour of the meal offering, and of its oil, and all the frankincense which is on the meal offering, and shall burn it on the altar for a sweet savor, as its memorial, to Yahweh. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">That which is left of it Aaron and his sons shall eat. It shall be eaten without yeast in a holy place. They shall eat it in the court of the Tent of Meeting </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">It shall not be baked with yeast. I have given it as their portion of my offerings made by fire. It is most holy, as the sin offering, and as the trespass offering. </q></q>
 <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every male among the children of Aaron shall eat of it, as their portion forever throughout your generations, from the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. Whoever touches them shall be holy.</q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="19">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="20">
<p><q rend="double">This is the offering of Aaron and of his sons, which they shall offer to Yahweh in the day when he is anointed: the tenth part of an ephah of fine flour for a meal offering perpetually, half of it in the morning, and half of it in the evening. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge"> It shall be made with oil in a baking pan. When it is soaked, you shall bring it in. You shall offer the meal offering in baked pieces for a sweet savor to Yahweh.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge"> The anointed priest that will be in his place from among his sons shall offer it. By a statute forever, it shall be wholly burnt to Yahweh.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge"> Every meal offering of a priest shall be wholly burned. It shall not be eaten.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="24">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="25">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to Aaron and to his sons, saying, <q rend="single">This is the law of the sin offering: in the place where the burnt offering is killed, the sin offering shall be killed before Yahweh. It is most holy. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The priest who offers it for sin shall eat it. It shall be eaten in a holy place, in the court of the Tent of Meeting. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whatever shall touch its flesh shall be holy. When there is any of its blood sprinkled on a garment, you shall wash that on which it was sprinkled in a holy place. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">But the earthen vessel in which it is boiled shall be broken; and if it is boiled in a brazen vessel, it shall be scoured, and rinsed in water. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every male among the priests shall eat of it: it is most holy. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:6" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">No sin offering, of which any of the blood is brought into the Tent of Meeting to make atonement in the Holy Place, shall be eaten: it shall be burned with fire.</q></q></p></div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="7">
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="1">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">This is the law of the trespass offering. It is most holy. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="2">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">In the place where they kill the burnt offering, he shall kill the trespass offering; and its blood he shall sprinkle on the altar round about. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">He shall offer all of its fat: the fat tail, and the fat that covers the innards, </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and the two kidneys, and the fat that is on them, which is by the loins, and the cover on the liver, with the kidneys, shall he take away; </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and the priest shall burn them on the altar for an offering made by fire to Yahweh: it is a trespass offering. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every male among the priests may eat of it. It shall be eaten in a holy place. It is most holy. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">As is the sin offering, so is the trespass offering; there is one law for them. Ihe priest who makes atonement with them, he shall have it. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The priest who offers any man’s burnt offering, even the priest shall have for himself the skin of the burnt offering which he has offered. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every meal offering that is baked in the oven, and all that is dressed in the frying pan, and on the baking pan, shall be the priest’s who offers it. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every meal offering, mixed with oil or dry, belongs to all the sons of Aaron, one as well as another. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">This is the law of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which one shall offer to Yahweh. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If he offers it for a thanksgiving, then he shall offer with the sacrifice of thanksgiving unleavened cakes mixed with oil, and unleavened wafers anointed with oil, and cakes mixed with oil. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">With cakes of leavened bread he shall offer his offering with the sacrifice of his peace offerings for thanksgiving. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Of it he shall offer one out of each offering for a heave offering to Yahweh. It shall be the priest’s who sprinkles the blood of the peace offerings. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings for thanksgiving shall be eaten on the day of his offering. He shall not leave any of it until the morning. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">But if the sacrifice of his offering is a vow, or a freewill offering, it shall be eaten on the day that he offers his sacrifice; and on the next day what remains of it shall be eaten: </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">but what remains of the flesh of the sacrifice on the third day shall be burned with fire. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If any of the flesh of the sacrifice of his peace offerings is eaten on the third day, it will not be accepted, neither shall it be imputed to him who offers it. It will be an abomination, and the soul who eats any of it will bear his iniquity. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The flesh that touches any unclean thing shall not be eaten. It shall be burned with fire. As for the flesh, everyone who is clean may eat it; </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">but the soul who eats of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, that belongs to Yahweh, having his uncleanness on him, that soul shall be cut off from his people. </q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">When anyone touches any unclean thing, the uncleanness of man, or an unclean animal, or any unclean abomination, and eats some of the flesh of the sacrifice of peace offerings, which belong to Yahweh, that soul shall be cut off from his people.</q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="22">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="23">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, saying, <q rend="single">You shall eat no fat, of ox, or sheep, or goat.</q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The fat of that which dies of itself, and the fat of that which is torn of animals, may be used for any other service, but you shall in no way eat of it.</q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">For whoever eats the fat of the animal, of which men offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh, even the soul who eats it shall be cut off from his people.</q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">You shall not eat any blood, whether it is of bird or of animal, in any of your dwellings.</q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whoever it is who eats any blood, that soul shall be cut off from his people.</q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="28">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="29">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, saying, <q rend="single">He who offers the sacrifice of his peace offerings to Yahweh shall bring his offering to Yahweh out of the sacrifice of his peace offerings. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">With his own hands he shall bring the offerings of Yahweh made by fire. He shall bring the fat with the breast, that the breast may be waved for a wave offering before Yahweh. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The priest shall burn the fat on the altar, but the breast shall be Aaron’s and his sons.</q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The right thigh you shall give to the priest for a heave offering out of the sacrifices of your peace offerings.</q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">He among the sons of Aaron who offers the blood of the peace offerings, and the fat, shall have the right thigh for a portion. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">For the waved breast and the heaved thigh I have taken from the children of Israel out of the sacrifices of their peace offerings, and have given them to Aaron the priest and to his sons as their portion forever from the children of Israel.</q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="35">
<p> This is the anointing portion of Aaron, and the anointing portion of his sons, out of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire, in the day when he presented them to minister to Yahweh in the priest’s office; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="36">
<p> which Yahweh commanded to be given them of the children of Israel, in the day that he anointed them. It is their portion forever throughout their generations. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="37">
<p> This is the law of the burnt offering, of the meal offering, and of the sin offering, and of the trespass offering, and of the consecration, and of the sacrifice of peace offerings; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:7" n="38">
<p> which Yahweh commanded Moses in Mount Sinai, in the day that he commanded the children of Israel to offer their offerings to Yahweh, in the wilderness of Sinai. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="8"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="2">
<p> <q rend="double">Take Aaron and his sons with him, and the garments, and the anointing oil, and the bull of the sin offering, and the two rams, and the basket of unleavened bread; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="3">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">and assemble all the congregation at the door of the Tent of Meeting.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="4">
<p> Moses did as Yahweh commanded him; and the congregation was assembled at the door of the Tent of Meeting. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="5">
<p> Moses said to the congregation, <q rend="double">This is the thing which Yahweh has commanded to be done.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="6">
<p> Moses brought Aaron and his sons, and washed them with water. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="7">
<p> He put the coat on him, tied the sash on him, clothed him with the robe, put the ephod on him, and he tied the skillfully woven band of the ephod on him, and fastened it to him with it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="8">
<p> He placed the breastplate on him; and in the breastplate he put the Urim and the Thummim. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="9">
<p> He set the turban on his head; and on the turban, in front, he set the golden plate, the holy crown; as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="10">
<p> Moses took the anointing oil, and anointed the tabernacle and all that was in it, and sanctified them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="11">
<p> He sprinkled it on the altar seven times, and anointed the altar and all its vessels, and the basin and its base, to sanctify them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="12">
<p> He poured some of the anointing oil on Aaron’s head, and anointed him, to sanctify him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="13">
<p> Moses brought Aaron’s sons, and clothed them with coats, and tied sashes on them, and put headbands on them; as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="14">
<p> He brought the bull of the sin offering, and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the bull of the sin offering. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="15">
<p> He killed it; and Moses took the blood, and put it on the horns of the altar round about with his finger, and purified the altar, and poured out the blood at the base of the altar, and sanctified it, to make atonement for it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="16">
<p> He took all the fat that was on the innards, and the cover of the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat; and Moses burned it on the altar. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="17">
<p> But the bull, and its skin, and its flesh, and its dung, he burned with fire outside the camp; as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="18">
<p> He presented the ram of the burnt offering: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="19">
<p> He killed it; and Moses sprinkled the blood on the altar round about. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="20">
<p> He cut the ram into its pieces; and Moses burned the head, and the pieces, and the fat. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="21">
<p> He washed the innards and the legs with water; and Moses burned the whole ram on the altar. It was a burnt offering for a sweet savor. It was an offering made by fire to Yahweh; as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="22">
<p> He presented the other ram, the ram of consecration: and Aaron and his sons laid their hands on the head of the ram. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="23">
<p> He killed it; and Moses took some of its blood, and put it on the tip of Aaron’s right ear, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the great toe of his right foot. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="24">
<p> He brought Aaron’s sons; and Moses put some of the blood on the tip of their right ear, and on the thumb of their right hand, and on the great toe of their right foot; and Moses sprinkled the blood on the altar round about. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="25">
<p> He took the fat, and the fat tail, and all the fat that was on the innards, and the cover of the liver, and the two kidneys, and their fat, and the right thigh; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="26">
<p> and out of the basket of unleavened bread, that was before Yahweh, he took one unleavened cake, and one cake of oiled bread, and one wafer, and placed them on the fat, and on the right thigh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="27">
<p> He put all these in Aaron’s hands and in his sons’ hands, and waved them for a wave offering before Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="28">
<p> Moses took them from their hands, and burned them on the altar on the burnt offering. They were a consecration for a sweet savor. It was an offering made by fire to Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="29">
<p> Moses took the breast, and waved it for a wave offering before Yahweh. It was Moses’ portion of the ram of consecration, as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="30">
<p> Moses took some of the anointing oil, and some of the blood which was on the altar, and sprinkled it on Aaron, on his garments, and on his sons, and on his sons’ garments with him, and sanctified Aaron, his garments, and his sons, and his sons’ garments with him. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="31">
<p> Moses said to Aaron and to his sons, <q rend="double">Boil the flesh at the door of the Tent of Meeting, and there eat it and the bread that is in the basket of consecration, as I commanded, saying, <q rend="single">Aaron and his sons shall eat it.</q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="32">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">What remains of the flesh and of the bread you shall burn with fire.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="33">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">You shall not go out from the door of the Tent of Meeting seven days, until the days of your consecration are fulfilled: for he shall consecrate you seven days.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="34">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">What has been done this day, so Yahweh has commanded to do, to make atonement for you.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="35">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">At the door of the Tent of Meeting you shall stay day and night seven days, and keep the charge of Yahweh, that you don’t die: for so I am commanded.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:8" n="36">
<p> Aaron and his sons did all the things which Yahweh commanded by Moses. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="9"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="1"> <p> It happened on the eighth day, that Moses called Aaron and his sons, and the elders of Israel; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="2">
<p> and he said to Aaron, <q rend="double">Take a calf from the herd for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering, without blemish, and offer them before Yahweh.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="3">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">You shall speak to the children of Israel, saying, <q rend="single">Take a male goat for a sin offering; and a calf and a lamb, both a year old, without blemish, for a burnt offering;</q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="4">
<p> <q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and an ox and a ram for peace offerings, to sacrifice before Yahweh; and a meal offering mixed with oil: for today Yahweh appears to you.</q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="5">
<p> They brought what Moses commanded before the Tent of Meeting: and all the congregation drew near and stood before Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="6">
<p> Moses said, <q rend="double">This is the thing which Yahweh commanded that you should do: and the glory of Yahweh shall appear to you.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="7">
<p> Moses said to Aaron, <q rend="double">Draw near to the altar, and offer your sin offering, and your burnt offering, and make atonement for yourself, and for the people; and offer the offering of the people, and make atonement for them; as Yahweh commanded.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="8">
<p> So Aaron drew near to the altar, and killed the calf of the sin offering, which was for himself. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="9">
<p> The sons of Aaron presented the blood to him; and he dipped his finger in the blood, and put it on the horns of the altar, and poured out the blood at the base of the altar: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="10">
<p> but the fat, and the kidneys, and the cover from the liver of the sin offering, he burned upon the altar; as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="11">
<p> The flesh and the skin he burned with fire outside the camp. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="12">
<p> He killed the burnt offering; and Aaron’s sons delivered the blood to him, and he sprinkled it on the altar round about. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="13">
<p> They delivered the burnt offering to him, piece by piece, and the head: and he burned them upon the altar. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="14">
<p> He washed the innards and the legs, and burned them on the burnt offering on the altar. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="15">
<p> He presented the people’s offering, and took the goat of the sin offering which was for the people, and killed it, and offered it for sin, like the first. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="16">
<p> He presented the burnt offering, and offered it according to the ordinance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="17">
<p> He presented the meal offering, and filled his hand from there, and burned it upon the altar, besides the burnt offering of the morning. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="18">
<p> He also killed the ox and the ram, the sacrifice of peace offerings, which was for the people: and Aaron’s sons delivered to him the blood, which he sprinkled on the altar round about, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="19">
<p> and the fat of the ox and of the ram, the fat tail, and that which covers the innards, and the kidneys, and the cover of the liver: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="20">
<p> and they put the fat upon the breasts, and he burned the fat on the altar: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="21">
<p> and the breasts and the right thigh Aaron waved for a wave offering before Yahweh, as Moses commanded. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="22">
<p> Aaron lifted up his hands toward the people, and blessed them; and he came down from offering the sin offering, and the burnt offering, and the peace offerings. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="23">
<p> Moses and Aaron went into the Tent of Meeting, and came out, and blessed the people: and the glory of Yahweh appeared to all the people. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:9" n="24">
<p> There came forth fire from before Yahweh, and consumed the burnt offering and the fat upon the altar: and when all the people saw it, they shouted, and fell on their faces. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="10"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="1"> <p> Nadab and Abihu, the sons of Aaron, each took his censer, and put fire in it, and laid incense on it, and offered strange fire before Yahweh, which he had not commanded them. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="2">
<p> And fire came forth from before Yahweh, and devoured them, and they died before Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="3">
<p> Then Moses said to Aaron, <q rend="double">This is what Yahweh spoke of, saying, <q rend="single">I will show myself holy to those who come near me, And before all the people I will be glorified.</q></q> Aaron held his peace. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="4">
<p> Moses called Mishael and Elzaphan, the sons of Uzziel the uncle of Aaron, and said to them, <q rend="double">Draw near, carry your brothers from before the sanctuary out of the camp.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="5">
<p> So they drew near, and carried them in their coats out of the camp, as Moses had said. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="6">
<p> Moses said to Aaron, and to Eleazar and to Ithamar, his sons, <q rend="double">Don’t let the hair of your heads go loose, neither tear your clothes; that you don’t die, and that he not be angry with all the congregation: but let your brothers, the whole house of Israel, bewail the burning which Yahweh has kindled.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="7">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">You shall not go out from the door of the Tent of Meeting, lest you die; for the anointing oil of Yahweh is on you.</q> They did according to the word of Moses. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="8">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Aaron, saying, 
 <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/> <q rend="double">Drink no wine nor strong drink, you, nor your sons with you, when you go into the Tent of Meeting, that you don’t die: it shall be a statute forever throughout your generations: </q>
 <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/><q rend="double; merge">and that you are to make a distinction between the holy and the common, and between the unclean and the clean; </q>
 <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/> <q rend="double; merge">and that you are to teach the children of Israel all the statutes which Yahweh has spoken to them by Moses.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="12">
<p> Moses spoke to Aaron, and to Eleazar and to Ithamar, his sons who were left, <q rend="double">Take the meal offering that remains of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire, and eat it without yeast beside the altar; for it is most holy; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="13">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">and you shall eat it in a holy place, because it is your portion, and your sons’ portion, of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire: for so I am commanded.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="14">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">The waved breast and the heaved thigh you shall eat in a clean place, you, and your sons, and your daughters with you: for they are given as your portion, and your sons’ portion, out of the sacrifices of the peace offerings of the children of Israel.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="15">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">The heaved thigh and the waved breast they shall bring with the offerings made by fire of the fat, to wave it for a wave offering before Yahweh: and it shall be yours, and your sons’ with you, as a portion forever; as Yahweh has commanded.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="16">
<p> Moses diligently inquired about the goat of the sin offering, and, behold, it was burned: and he was angry with Eleazar and with Ithamar, the sons of Aaron who were left, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="17">
<p> <q rend="double">Why haven’t you eaten the sin offering in the place of the sanctuary, seeing it is most holy, and he has given it you to bear the iniquity of the congregation, to make atonement for them before Yahweh?</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="18">
<p> <q rend="double; merge">Behold, its blood was not brought into the inner part of the sanctuary: you certainly should have eaten it in the sanctuary, as I commanded.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="19">
<p> Aaron spoke to Moses, <q rend="double">Behold, this day they have offered their sin offering and their burnt offering before Yahweh; and such things as these have befallen me: and if I had eaten the sin offering today, would it have been pleasing in the sight of Yahweh?</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:10" n="20">
<p> When Moses heard that, it was pleasing in his sight. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="11"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying to them, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="2">
<p> <q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, saying, <q rend="single">These are the living things which you may eat among all the animals that are on the earth. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whatever parts the hoof, and is cloven-footed, and chews the cud among the animals, that you may eat. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Nevertheless these you shall not eat of those that chew the cud, or of those who part the hoof: the camel, because he chews the cud but doesn’t have a parted hoof, he is unclean to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The coney, because he chews the cud but doesn’t have a parted hoof, he is unclean to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The hare, because she chews the cud but doesn’t part the hoof, she is unclean to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The pig, because he has a split hoof, and is cloven-footed, but doesn’t chew the cud, he is unclean to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Of their flesh you shall not eat, and their carcasses you shall not touch; they are unclean to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">These you may eat of all that are in the waters: whatever has fins and scales in the waters, in the seas, and in the rivers, that you may eat. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">All that don’t have fins and scales in the seas, and in the rivers, of all that move in the waters, and of all the living creatures that are in the waters, they are an abomination to you, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and you detest them. You shall not eat of their flesh, and you shall detest their carcasses. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whatever has no fins nor scales in the waters, that is an abomination to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">These you shall detest among the birds; they shall not be eaten, they are an abomination: the eagle, and the vulture, and the black vulture, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and the red kite, any kind of black kite, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">any kind of raven, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">the horned owl, the screech owl, and the gull, any kind of hawk, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">the little owl, the cormorant, the great owl, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">the white owl, the desert owl, the osprey, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">the stork, any kind of heron, the hoopoe, and the bat. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">All flying insects that walk on all fours are an abomination to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Yet you may eat these: of all winged creeping things that go on all fours, which have legs above their feet, with which to hop on the earth. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Even of these you may eat: any kind of locust, any kind of katydid, any kind of cricket, and any kind of grasshopper. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">But all winged creeping things which have four feet, are an abomination to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">By these you will become unclean: whoever touches the carcass of them shall be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whoever carries any part of their carcass shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every animal which parts the hoof, and is not cloven-footed, nor chews the cud, is unclean to you. Everyone who touches them shall be unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whatever goes on its paws, among all animals that go on all fours, they are unclean to you. Whoever touches their carcass shall be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">He who carries their carcass shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening. They are unclean to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">These are they which are unclean to you among the creeping things that creep on the earth: the weasel, the rat, any kind of great lizard, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">the gecko, and the monitor lizard, the wall lizard, the skink, and the chameleon. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">These are they which are unclean to you among all that creep. Whoever touches them when they are dead, shall be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">On whatever any of them falls when they are dead, it shall be unclean; whether it is any vessel of wood, or clothing, or skin, or sack, whatever vessel it is, with which any work is done, it must be put into water, and it shall be unclean until the evening; then it will be clean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every earthen vessel, into which any of them falls, all that is in it shall be unclean, and you shall break it. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">All food which may be eaten, that on which water comes, shall be unclean; and all drink that may be drunk in every such vessel shall be unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="35">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Everything whereupon part of their carcass falls shall be unclean; whether oven, or range for pots, it shall be broken in pieces: they are unclean, and shall be unclean to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="36">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Nevertheless a spring or a cistern in which water is a gathered shall be clean: but that which touches their carcass shall be unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="37">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If part of their carcass falls on any sowing seed which is to be sown, it is clean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="38">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">But if water is put on the seed, and part of their carcass falls on it, it is unclean to you. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="39">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If any animal, of which you may eat, dies; he who touches its carcass shall be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="40">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">He who eats of its carcass shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening. He also who carries its carcass shall wash his clothes, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="41">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every creeping thing that creeps on the earth is an abomination. It shall not be eaten. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="42">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whatever goes on its belly, and whatever goes on all fours, or whatever has many feet, even all creeping things that creep on the earth, them you shall not eat; for they are an abomination. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="43">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">You shall not make yourselves abominable with any creeping thing that creeps, neither shall you make yourselves unclean with them, that you should be defiled thereby. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="44">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">For I am Yahweh your God. Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be holy; for I am holy: neither shall you defile yourselves with any kind of creeping thing that moves on the earth. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="45">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">For I am Yahweh who brought you up out of the land of Egypt, to be your God. You shall therefore be holy, for I am holy. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="46">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">This is the law of the animal, and of the bird, and of every living creature that moves in the waters, and of every creature that creeps on the earth, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:11" n="47">
<p><q rend="double; merge">to make a distinction between the unclean and the clean, and between the living thing that may be eaten and the living thing that may not be eaten.</q> </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="12"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:12" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:12" n="2">
<p> <q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, saying, <q rend="single">If a woman conceives, and bears a male child, then she shall be unclean seven days; as in the days of her monthly period she shall be unclean.</q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:12" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">In the eighth day the flesh of his foreskin shall be circumcised.</q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:12" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">She shall continue in the blood of purification thirty-three days. She shall not touch any holy thing, nor come into the sanctuary, until the days of her purifying are completed. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:12" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">But if she bears a female child, then she shall be unclean two weeks, as in her period; and she shall continue in the blood of purification sixty-six days. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:12" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">When the days of her purification are completed, for a son, or for a daughter, she shall bring to the priest at the door of the Tent of Meeting, a year old lamb for a burnt offering, and a young pigeon, or a turtledove, for a sin offering: </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:12" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and he shall offer it before Yahweh, and make atonement for her; and she shall be cleansed from the fountain of her blood. This is the law for her who bears, whether a male or a female. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:12" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If she cannot afford a lamb, then she shall take two turtledoves, or two young pigeons; the one for a burnt offering, and the other for a sin offering: and the priest shall make atonement for her, and she shall be clean.</q> </q></p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="13"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">When a man shall have a rising in his body’s skin, or a scab, or a bright spot, and it becomes in the skin of his body the plague of leprosy, then he shall be brought to Aaron the priest, or to one of his sons the priests: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall examine the plague in the skin of the body: and if the hair in the plague has turned white, and the appearance of the plague is deeper than the body’s skin, it is the plague of leprosy; and the priest shall examine him, and pronounce him unclean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the bright spot is white in the skin of his body, and the appearance of it isn’t deeper than the skin, and the hair of it hasn’t turned white, then the priest shall isolate the infected person for seven days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall examine him on the seventh day, and, behold, if in his eyes the plague is arrested, and the plague hasn’t spread in the skin, then the priest shall isolate him for seven more days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall examine him again on the seventh day; and, behold, if the plague has faded, and the plague hasn’t spread in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean. It is a scab. He shall wash his clothes, and be clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if the scab spreads on the skin, after he has shown himself to the priest for his cleansing, he shall show himself to the priest again. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall examine him; and, behold, if the scab has spread on the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is leprosy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When the plague of leprosy is in a man, then he shall be brought to the priest; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall examine him. Behold, if there is a white rising in the skin, and it has turned the hair white, and there is raw flesh in the rising, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">it is a chronic leprosy in the skin of his body, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean. He shall not isolate him, for he is unclean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the leprosy breaks out all over the skin, and the leprosy covers all the skin of the infected person from his head even to his feet, as far as it appears to the priest; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall examine him; and, behold, if the leprosy has covered all his flesh, he shall pronounce him clean of the plague. It has all turned white: he is clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But whenever raw flesh appears in him, he shall be unclean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall examine the raw flesh, and pronounce him unclean: the raw flesh is unclean. It is leprosy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Or if the raw flesh turns again, and is changed to white, then he shall come to the priest; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall examine him; and, behold, if the plague has turned white, then the priest shall pronounce him clean of the plague. He is clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When the body has a boil on its skin, and it has healed, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and in the place of the boil there is a white rising, or a bright spot, reddish-white, then it shall be shown to the priest; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall examine it; and, behold, if the appearance of it is lower than the skin, and the hair of it has turned white, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. It has broken out in the boil. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if the priest examines it, and, behold, there are no white hairs in it, and it isn’t deeper than the skin, but is dim, then the priest shall isolate him seven days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it spreads in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is a plague. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if the bright spot stays in its place, and hasn’t spread, it is the scar from the boil; and the priest shall pronounce him clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Or when the body has a burn from fire on its skin, and the raw flesh of the burn becomes a bright spot, reddish-white, or white, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall examine it; and, behold, if the hair in the bright spot has turned white, and the appearance of it is deeper than the skin; it is leprosy. It has broken out in the burning, and the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if the priest examines it, and, behold, there is no white hair in the bright spot, and it isn’t lower than the skin, but is faded; then the priest shall isolate him seven days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall examine him on the seventh day. If it has spread in the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean. It is the plague of leprosy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the bright spot stays in its place, and hasn’t spread in the skin, but is faded, it is the swelling from the burn, and the priest shall pronounce him clean; for it is the scar from the burn. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When a man or woman has a plague on the head or on the beard, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall examine the plague; and, behold, if the appearance of it is deeper than the skin, and the hair in it is yellow and thin, then the priest shall pronounce him unclean: it is an itch, it is leprosy of the head or of the beard. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the priest examines the plague of itching, and, behold, its appearance isn’t deeper than the skin, and there is no black hair in it, then the priest shall isolate him the person infected with itching seven days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">On the seventh day the priest shall examine the plague; and, behold, if the itch hasn’t spread, and there is no yellow hair in it, and the appearance of the itch isn’t deeper than the skin, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then he shall be shaved, but he shall not shave the itch; and the priest shall shut him up who has the itch seven more days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge">On the seventh day, the priest shall examine the itch; and, behold, if the itch hasn’t spread in the skin, and its appearance isn’t deeper than the skin, then the priest shall pronounce him clean. He shall wash his clothes, and be clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="35">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if the itch spreads in the skin after his cleansing, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="36">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall examine him; and, behold, if the itch has spread in the skin, the priest shall not look for the yellow hair; he is unclean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="37">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if in his eyes the itch is arrested, and black hair has grown in it; the itch is healed, he is clean. The priest shall pronounce him clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="38">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When a man or a woman has bright spots in the skin of the body, even white bright spots; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="39">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall examine them; and, behold, if the bright spots on the skin of their body are a dull white, it is a harmless rash, it has broken out in the skin; he is clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="40">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man’s hair has fallen from his head, he is bald. He is clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="41">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If his hair has fallen off from the front part of his head, he is forehead bald. He is clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="42">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if there is in the bald head, or the bald forehead, a reddish-white plague; it is leprosy breaking out in his bald head, or his bald forehead. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="43">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Then the priest shall examine him; and, behold, if the rising of the plague is reddish-white in his bald head, or in his bald forehead, like the appearance of leprosy in the skin of the flesh, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="44">
<p><q rend="double; merge">he is a leprous man. He is unclean. The priest shall surely pronounce him unclean. His plague is on his head. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="45">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The leper in whom the plague is shall wear torn clothes, and the hair of his head shall hang loose. He shall cover his upper lip, and shall cry, <q rend="single">Unclean! Unclean!</q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="46">
<p><q rend="double; merge">All the days in which the plague is in him he shall be unclean. He is unclean. He shall dwell alone. Outside of the camp shall be his dwelling. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="47">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The garment also that the plague of leprosy is in, whether it is a woolen garment, or a linen garment; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="48">
<p><q rend="double; merge">whether it is in warp, or woof; of linen, or of wool; whether in a skin, or in anything made of skin; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="49">
<p><q rend="double; merge">if the plague is greenish or reddish in the garment, or in the skin, or in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything made of skin; it is the plague of leprosy, and shall be shown to the priest. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="50">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall examine the plague, and isolate the plague seven days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="51">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall examine the plague on the seventh day. If the plague has spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in the skin, whatever use the skin is used for, the plague is a destructive mildew. It is unclean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="52">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall burn the garment, whether the warp or the woof, in wool or in linen, or anything of skin, in which the plague is: for it is a destructive mildew. It shall be burned in the fire. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="53">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the priest examines it, and, behold, the plague hasn’t spread in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything of skin; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="54">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall command that they wash the thing in which the plague is, and he shall isolate it seven more days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="55">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Then the priest shall examine it, after the plague is washed; and, behold, if the plague hasn’t changed its color, and the plague hasn’t spread, it is unclean; you shall burn it in the fire. It is a mildewed spot, whether the bareness is inside or outside. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="56">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the priest looks, and, behold, the plague has faded after it is washed, then he shall tear it out of the garment, or out of the skin, or out of the warp, or out of the woof: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="57">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and if it appears again in the garment, either in the warp, or in the woof, or in anything of skin, it is spreading. You shall burn with fire that in which the plague is. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="58">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The garment, either the warp, or the woof, or whatever thing of skin it is, which you shall wash, if the plague has departed from them, then it shall be washed the second time, and it will be clean.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:13" n="59">
<p> This is the law of the plague of mildew in a garment of wool or linen, either in the warp, or the woof, or in anything of skin, to pronounce it clean, or to pronounce it unclean. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="14"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">This shall be the law of the leper in the day of his cleansing. He shall be brought to the priest, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall go forth out of the camp. The priest shall examine him, and, behold, if the plague of leprosy is healed in the leper, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall command them to take for him who is to be cleansed two living clean birds, and cedar wood, and scarlet, and hyssop. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall command them to kill one of the birds in an earthen vessel over running water. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">As for the living bird, he shall take it, and the cedar wood, and the scarlet, and the hyssop, and shall dip them and the living bird in the blood of the bird that was killed over the running water. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall sprinkle on him who is to be cleansed from the leprosy seven times, and shall pronounce him clean, and shall let the living bird go into the open field. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who is to be cleansed shall wash his clothes, and shave off all his hair, and bathe himself in water; and he shall be clean. After that he shall come into the camp, but shall dwell outside his tent seven days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It shall be on the seventh day, that he shall shave all his hair off his head and his beard and his eyebrows, even all his hair he shall shave off. He shall wash his clothes, and he shall bathe his body in water, then he shall be clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">On the eighth day he shall take two male lambs without blemish, and one ewe lamb a year old without blemish, and three tenths of an ephah of fine flour for a meal offering, mingled with oil, and one log of oil. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest who cleanses him shall set the man who is to be cleansed, and those things, before Yahweh, at the door of the Tent of Meeting. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall take one of the male lambs, and offer him for a trespass offering, with the log of oil, and wave them for a wave offering before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall kill the male lamb in the place where they kill the sin offering and the burnt offering, in the place of the sanctuary; for as the sin offering is the priest’s, so is the trespass offering. It is most holy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering, and the priest shall put it on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall take some of the log of oil, and pour it into the palm of his own left hand. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall dip his right finger in the oil that is in his left hand, and shall sprinkle some of the oil with his finger seven times before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall put some of the rest of the oil that is in his hand on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot, upon the blood of the trespass offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The rest of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall put on the head of him who is to be cleansed, and the priest shall make atonement for him before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall offer the sin offering, and make atonement for him who is to be cleansed because of his uncleanness: and afterward he shall kill the burnt offering; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall offer the burnt offering and the meal offering on the altar. The priest shall make atonement for him, and he shall be clean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he is poor, and can’t afford so much, then he shall take one male lamb for a trespass offering to be waved, to make atonement for him, and one tenth of an ephah of fine flour mingled with oil for a meal offering, and a log of oil; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, such as he is able to afford; and the one shall be a sin offering, and the other a burnt offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">On the eighth day he shall bring them for his cleansing to the priest, to the door of the Tent of Meeting, before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall take the lamb of the trespass offering, and the log of oil, and the priest shall wave them for a wave offering before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall kill the lamb of the trespass offering. The priest shall take some of the blood of the trespass offering and put it on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall pour some of the oil into the palm of his own left hand; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall sprinkle with his right finger some of the oil that is in his left hand seven times before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Then the priest shall put some of the oil that is in his hand on the tip of the right ear of him who is to be cleansed, and on the thumb of his right hand, and on the big toe of his right foot, on the place of the blood of the trespass offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The rest of the oil that is in the priest’s hand he shall put on the head of him who is to be cleansed, to make atonement for him before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall offer one of the turtledoves, or of the young pigeons, such as he is able to afford, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">even such as he is able to afford, the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering, with the meal offering. The priest shall make atonement for him who is to be cleansed before Yahweh.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="32">
<p> This is the law for him in whom is the plague of leprosy, who is not able to afford the sacrifice for his cleansing. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="33">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="34">
<p><q rend="double">When you have come into the land of Canaan, which I give to you for a possession, and I put a spreading mildew in a house in the land of your possession, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="35">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then he who owns the house shall come and tell the priest, saying, <q rend="single">There seems to me to be some sort of plague in the house.</q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="36">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall command that they empty the house, before the priest goes in to examine the plague, that all that is in the house not be made unclean: and afterward the priest shall go in to inspect the house. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="37">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall examine the plague; and, behold, if the plague is in the walls of the house with hollow streaks, greenish or reddish, and it appears to be deeper than the wall; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="38">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall go out of the house to the door of the house, and shut up the house seven days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="39">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall come again on the seventh day, and look. If the plague has spread in the walls of the house, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="40">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall command that they take out the stones in which is the plague, and cast them into an unclean place outside of the city: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="41">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and he shall cause the inside of the house to be scraped round about, and they shall pour out the mortar, that they scraped off, outside of the city into an unclean place. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="42">
<p><q rend="double; merge">They shall take other stones, and put them in the place of those stones; and he shall take other mortar, and shall plaster the house. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="43">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the plague comes again, and breaks out in the house, after he has taken out the stones, and after he has scraped the house, and after it was plastered; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="44">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall come in and look; and, behold, if the plague has spread in the house, it is a destructive mildew in the house. It is unclean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="45">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall break down the house, its stones, and its timber, and all the house’s mortar. He shall carry them out of the city into an unclean place. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="46">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Moreover he who goes into the house while it is shut up shall be unclean until the evening. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="47">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who lies down in the house shall wash his clothes; and he who eats in the house shall wash his clothes. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="48">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the priest shall come in, and examine it, and, behold, the plague hasn’t spread in the house, after the house was plastered, then the priest shall pronounce the house clean, because the plague is healed. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="49">
<p><q rend="double; merge">To cleanse the house he shall take two birds, and cedar wood, and scarlet, and hyssop. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="50">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall kill one of the birds in an earthen vessel over running water. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="51">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall take the cedar wood, and the hyssop, and the scarlet, and the living bird, and dip them in the blood of the slain bird, and in the running water, and sprinkle the house seven times. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="52">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall cleanse the house with the blood of the bird, and with the running water, with the living bird, with the cedar wood, with the hyssop, and with the scarlet; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="53">
<p><q rend="double; merge">but he shall let the living bird go out of the city into the open field. So shall he make atonement for the house; and it shall be clean.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="54">
<p> This is the law for any plague of leprosy, and for an itch, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="55">
<p> and for the destructive mildew of a garment, and for a house, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="56">
<p> and for a rising, and for a scab, and for a bright spot; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:14" n="57">
<p> to teach when it is unclean, and when it is clean. This is the law of leprosy. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="15"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses and to Aaron, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, <q rend="single">When any man has a discharge from his body, because of his discharge he is unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">This shall be his uncleanness in his discharge: whether his body runs with his discharge, or his body has stopped from his discharge, it is his uncleanness. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every bed whereon he who has the discharge lies shall be unclean; and everything he sits on shall be unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whoever touches his bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">He who sits on anything whereon the man who has the discharge sat shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">He who touches the body of him who has the discharge shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If he who has the discharge spits on him who is clean, then he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whatever saddle he who has the discharge rides on shall be unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whoever touches anything that was under him shall be unclean until the evening. He who carries those things shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whoever he who has the discharge touches, without having rinsed his hands in water, he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The earthen vessel, which he who has the discharge touches, shall be broken; and every vessel of wood shall be rinsed in water. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">When he who has a discharge is cleansed of his discharge, then he shall count to himself seven days for his cleansing, and wash his clothes; and he shall bathe his flesh in running water, and shall be clean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">On the eighth day he shall take two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, and come before Yahweh to the door of the Tent of Meeting, and give them to the priest: </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and the priest shall offer them, the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering. The priest shall make atonement for him before Yahweh for his discharge. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If any man has an emission of semen, then he shall bathe all his flesh in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every garment, and every skin, whereon the semen is, shall be washed with water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If a man lies with a woman and there is an emission of semen, they shall both bathe themselves in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If a woman has a discharge, and her discharge in her flesh is blood, she shall be in her impurity seven days: and whoever touches her shall be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Everything that she lies on in her impurity shall be unclean. Everything also that she sits on shall be unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whoever touches her bed shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whoever touches anything that she sits on shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If it is on the bed, or on anything whereon she sits, when he touches it, he shall be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If any man lies with her, and her monthly flow is on him, he shall be unclean seven days; and every bed whereon he lies shall be unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">If a woman has a discharge of her blood many days not in the time of her period, or if she has a discharge beyond the time of her period; all the days of the discharge of her uncleanness shall be as in the days of her period: she is unclean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every bed whereon she lies all the days of her discharge shall be to her as the bed of her period: and everything whereon she sits shall be unclean, as the uncleanness of her period. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whoever touches these things shall be unclean, and shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">But if she is cleansed of her discharge, then she shall count to herself seven days, and after that she shall be clean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">On the eighth day she shall take two turtledoves, or two young pigeons, and bring them to the priest, to the door of the Tent of Meeting. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The priest shall offer the one for a sin offering, and the other for a burnt offering; and the priest shall make atonement for her before Yahweh for the uncleanness of her discharge. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Thus you shall separate the children of Israel from their uncleanness, so they will not die in their uncleanness, when they defile my tabernacle that is in their midst.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="32">
<p> This is the law of him who has a discharge, and of him who has an emission of semen, so that he is unclean thereby; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:15" n="33">
<p> and of her who has her period, and of a man or woman who has a discharge, and of him who lies with her who is unclean. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="16"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, after the death of the two sons of Aaron, when they drew near before Yahweh, and died; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="2">
<p> and Yahweh said to Moses, <q rend="double">Tell Aaron your brother, not to come at all times into the Most Holy Place within the veil, before the mercy seat which is on the ark; lest he die: for I will appear in the cloud on the mercy seat. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Herewith shall Aaron come into the sanctuary: with a young bull for a sin offering, and a ram for a burnt offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall put on the holy linen coat, and he shall have the linen breeches on his body, and shall put on the linen sash, and he shall be dressed with the linen turban. They are the holy garments. He shall bathe his body in water, and put them on. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall take from the congregation of the children of Israel two male goats for a sin offering, and one ram for a burnt offering </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Aaron shall offer the bull of the sin offering, which is for himself, and make atonement for himself and for his house. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall take the two goats, and set them before Yahweh at the door of the Tent of Meeting. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Aaron shall cast lots for the two goats; one lot for Yahweh, and the other lot for the scapegoat. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Aaron shall present the goat on which the lot fell for Yahweh, and offer him for a sin offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But the goat, on which the lot fell for the scapegoat, shall be presented alive before Yahweh, to make atonement for him, to send him away for the scapegoat into the wilderness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Aaron shall present the bull of the sin offering, which is for himself, and shall make atonement for himself and for his house, and shall kill the bull of the sin offering which is for himself. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall take a censer full of coals of fire from off the altar before Yahweh, and two handfuls of sweet incense beaten small, and bring it within the veil: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and he shall put the incense on the fire before Yahweh, that the cloud of the incense may cover the mercy seat that is on the testimony, so that he will not die. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall take some of the blood of the bull, and sprinkle it with his finger on the mercy seat on the east; and before the mercy seat he shall sprinkle some of the blood with his finger seven times. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Then he shall kill the goat of the sin offering, that is for the people, and bring his blood within the veil, and do with his blood as he did with the blood of the bull, and sprinkle it on the mercy seat, and before the mercy seat: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and he shall make atonement for the Holy Place, because of the uncleanness of the children of Israel, and because of their transgressions, even all their sins; and so he shall do for the Tent of Meeting, that dwells with them in the midst of their uncleanness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">There shall be no one in the Tent of Meeting when he enters to make atonement in the Holy Place, until he comes out, and has made atonement for himself and for his household, and for all the assembly of Israel. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall go out to the altar that is before Yahweh and make atonement for it, and shall take some of the bull’s blood, and some of the goat’s blood, and put it on the horns of the altar round about. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall sprinkle some of the blood on it with his finger seven times, and cleanse it, and make it holy from the uncleanness of the children of Israel. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When he has made an end of atoning for the Holy Place, the Tent of Meeting, and the altar, he shall present the live goat. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Aaron shall lay both his hands on the head of the live goat, and confess over him all the iniquities of the children of Israel, and all their transgressions, even all their sins; and he shall put them on the head of the goat, and shall send him away into the wilderness by the hand of a man who is in readiness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The goat shall carry all their iniquities on himself to a solitary land, and he shall let the goat go in the wilderness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Aaron shall come into the Tent of Meeting, and shall take off the linen garments, which he put on when he went into the Holy Place, and shall leave them there. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Then he shall bathe himself in water in a holy place, and put on his garments, and come out and offer his burnt offering and the burnt offering of the people, and make atonement for himself and for the people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The fat of the sin offering he shall burn on the altar. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who lets the goat go for the scapegoat shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The bull for the sin offering, and the goat for the sin offering, whose blood was brought in to make atonement in the Holy Place, shall be carried forth outside the camp; and they shall burn their skins, their flesh, and their dung with fire. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who burns them shall wash his clothes, and bathe his flesh in water, and afterward he shall come into the camp. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It shall be a statute to you forever: in the seventh month, on the tenth day of the month, you shall afflict your souls, and shall do no manner of work, the native-born, or the stranger who sojourns among you: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">for on this day shall atonement be made for you, to cleanse you; from all your sins you shall be clean before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It is a Sabbath of solemn rest to you, and you shall afflict your souls; it is a statute forever. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest, who is anointed and who is consecrated to be priest in his father’s place, shall make the atonement, and shall put on the linen garments, even the holy garments. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Then he shall make atonement for the Holy Sanctuary; and he shall make atonement for the Tent of Meeting and for the altar; and he shall make atonement for the priests and for all the people of the assembly. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:16" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge">This shall be an everlasting statute for you, to make atonement for the children of Israel once in the year because of all their sins.</q> It was done as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="17"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to Aaron, and to his sons, and to all the children of Israel, and say to them: <q rend="single">This is the thing which Yahweh has commanded, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whatever man there is of the house of Israel, who kills an ox, or lamb, or goat, in the camp, or who kills it outside the camp, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and hasn’t brought it to the door of the Tent of Meeting, to offer it as an offering to Yahweh before the tabernacle of Yahweh: blood shall be imputed to that man. He has shed blood; and that man shall be cut off from among his people. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">This is to the end that the children of Israel may bring their sacrifices, which they sacrifice in the open field, that they may bring them to Yahweh, to the door of the Tent of Meeting, to the priest, and sacrifice them for sacrifices of peace offerings to Yahweh. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">The priest shall sprinkle the blood on the altar of Yahweh at the door of the Tent of Meeting, and burn the fat for a sweet savor to Yahweh. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">They shall no more sacrifice their sacrifices to the goat idols, after which they play the prostitute. This shall be a statute forever to them throughout their generations.</q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall say to them, <q rend="single">Any man there is of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn among them, who offers a burnt offering or sacrifice, </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">and doesn’t bring it to the door of the Tent of Meeting, to sacrifice it to Yahweh; that man shall be cut off from his people. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Any man of the house of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn among them, who eats any kind of blood, I will set my face against that soul who eats blood, and will cut him off from among his people. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">For the life of the flesh is in the blood; and I have given it to you on the altar to make atonement for your souls: for it is the blood that makes atonement by reason of the life. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Therefore I have said to the children of Israel, <q rend="single">No person among you shall eat blood, neither shall any stranger who sojourns among you eat blood.</q></q> </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Whatever man there is of the children of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn among them, who takes in hunting any animal or bird that may be eaten; he shall pour out its blood, and cover it with dust. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">For as to the life of all flesh, its blood is with its life: therefore I said to the children of Israel, <q rend="single">You shall not eat the blood of any kind of flesh; for the life of all flesh is its blood. Whoever eats it shall be cut off.</q></q></q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">Every person that eats what dies of itself, or that which is torn by animals, whether he is native-born or a sojourner, he shall wash his clothes, and bathe himself in water, and be unclean until the evening: then he shall be clean. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:17" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="single; merge">But if he doesn’t wash them, or bathe his flesh, then he shall bear his iniquity.</q></q></p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="18"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="1"> <p> Yahweh said to Moses, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, and say to them, I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not do as they do in the land of Egypt, where you lived: and you shall not do as they do in the land of Canaan, where I am bringing you; neither shall you walk in their statutes. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall do my ordinances, and you shall keep my statutes, and walk in them: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall therefore keep my statutes and my ordinances; which if a man does, he shall live in them: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">None of you shall approach anyone who are his close relatives, to uncover their nakedness: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father, nor the nakedness of your mother: she is your mother. You shall not uncover her nakedness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s wife: it is your father’s nakedness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your sister, the daughter of your father, or the daughter of your mother, whether born at home, or born abroad. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your son’s daughter, or of your daughter’s daughter, even their nakedness: for theirs is your own nakedness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s wife’s daughter, conceived by your father, since she is your sister. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s sister: she is your father’s near kinswoman. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mother’s sister: for she is your mother’s near kinswoman. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your father’s brother, you shall not approach his wife: she is your aunt. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your daughter-in-law: she is your son’s wife. You shall not uncover her nakedness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your brother’s wife: it is your brother’s nakedness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of a woman and her daughter. You shall not take her son’s daughter, or her daughter’s daughter, to uncover her nakedness; they are near kinswomen: it is wickedness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not take a wife to her sister, to be a rival, to uncover her nakedness, while her sister is yet alive. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not approach a woman to uncover her nakedness, as long as she is impure by her uncleanness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not lie carnally with your neighbor’s wife, and defile yourself with her. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not give any of your children to sacrifice to Molech; neither shall you profane the name of your God: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not lie with a man, as with a woman. That is detestible. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not lie with any animal to defile yourself with it; neither shall any woman give herself to an animal, to lie down with it: it is a perversion. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Don’t defile yourselves in any of these things: for in all these the nations which I am casting out before you were defiled. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The land was defiled: therefore I punished its iniquity, and the land vomitted out her inhabitants. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You therefore shall keep my statutes and my ordinances, and shall not do any of these abominations; neither the native-born, nor the stranger who sojourns among you; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">(for all these abominations have the men of the land done, that were before you, and the land became defiled); </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">that the land not vomit you out also, when you defile it, as it vomited out the nation that was before you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">For whoever shall do any of these abominations, even the souls that do them shall be cut off from among their people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:18" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Therefore you shall keep my charge, that you do not practice any of these abominable customs, which were practiced before you, and that you do not defile yourselves with them: I am Yahweh your God.</q> </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="19"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to all the congregation of the children of Israel, and tell them, You shall be holy; for I Yahweh your God am holy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall fear every man his mother, and his father; and you shall keep my Sabbaths: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Don’t turn to idols, nor make to yourselves molten gods: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When you offer a sacrifice of peace-offerings to Yahweh, you shall offer it that you may be accepted. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It shall be eaten the same day you offer it, and on the next day: and if anything remain until the third day, it shall be burnt with fire. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it be eaten at all on the third day, it is an abomination; it shall not be accepted: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">but everyone who eats it shall bear his iniquity, because he has profaned the holy thing of Yahweh: and that soul shall be cut off from his people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not wholly reap the corners of your field, neither shall you gather the gleaning of your harvest. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not glean your vineyard, neither shall you gather the fallen fruit of your vineyard; you shall leave them for the poor and for the sojourner: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not steal; neither shall you deal falsely, nor lie one to another. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not swear by my name falsely, and profane the name of your God: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not oppress your neighbor, nor rob him: the wages of a hired servant shall not remain with you all night until the morning. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not curse the deaf, nor put a stumbling block before the blind; but you shall fear your God: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall do no unrighteousness in judgment: you shall not respect the person of the poor, nor honor the person of the mighty; but in righteousness shall you judge your neighbor. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not go up and down as a talebearer among your people: neither shall you stand against the blood of your neighbor: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not hate your brother in your heart: you shall surely rebuke your neighbor, and not bear sin because of him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not take vengeance, nor bear any grudge against the children of your people; but you shall love your neighbor as yourself: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall keep my statutes. You shall not let your cattle breed with a diverse kind: you shall not sow your field with two kinds of seed: neither shall there come on you a garment of two kinds of stuff mixed together. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Whoever lies carnally with a woman, who is a bondmaid, pledged to be married to a husband, and not at all redeemed, nor freedom given her; they shall be punished; they shall not be put to death, because she was not free. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall bring his trespass-offering to Yahweh, to the door of the tent of meeting, even a ram for a trespass-offering. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall make atonement for him with the ram of the trespass-offering before Yahweh for his sin which he has sinned: and the sin which he has sinned shall be forgiven him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When you shall come into the land, and shall have planted all manner of trees for food, then you shall count the fruit of it as their uncircumcision: three years shall they be as uncircumcised to you; it shall not be eaten. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But in the fourth year all the fruit of it shall be holy, for giving praise to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">In the fifth year shall you eat of the fruit of it, that it may yield to you the increase of it: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not eat anything with the blood: neither shall you use enchantments, nor practice sorcery. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not cut the hair on the sides of your heads, neither shall you clip off the edge of your beard. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not make any cuttings in your flesh for the dead, nor print any marks on you: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Don’t profane your daughter, to make her a prostitute; lest the land fall to prostitution, and the land become full of wickedness. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary; I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Don’t turn to those who have familiar spirits, nor to the wizards; don’t seek them out, to be defiled by them: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall rise up before the gray head, and honor the face of the old man, and you shall fear your God: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a stranger sojourn with you in your land, you shall not do him wrong. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The stranger who sojourns with you shall be to you as the home-born among you, and you shall love him as yourself; for you were sojourners in the land of Egypt: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="35">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall do no unrighteousness in judgment, in measures of length, of weight, or of quantity. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="36">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Just balances, just weights, a just ephah, and a just hin, shall you have: I am Yahweh your God, who brought you out of the land of Egypt. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:19" n="37">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall observe all my statutes, and all my ordinances, and do them: I am Yahweh.</q> </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="20"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Moreover, you shall tell the children of Israel, Whoever he be of the children of Israel, or of the strangers who sojourn in Israel, who gives of his seed to Molech; he shall surely be put to death: the people of the land shall stone him with stones. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I also will set my face against that man, and will cut him off from among his people; because he has given of his seed to Molech, to defile my sanctuary, and to profane my holy name. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If the people at the land do at all hide their eyes from that man, when he gives of his seed to Molech, and don’t put him to death; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then I will set my face against that man, and against his family, and will cut him off, and all who play the prostitute after him, to play the prostitute with Molech, from among their people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The soul that turns to those who have familiar spirits, and to the wizards, to play the prostitute after them, I will even set my face against that soul, and will cut him off from among his people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Sanctify yourselves therefore, and be holy; for I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall keep my statutes, and do them: I am Yahweh who sanctifies you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">For everyone who curses his father or his mother shall surely be put to death: he has cursed his father or his mother; his blood shall be on him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The man who commits adultery with another man’s wife, even he who commits adultery with his neighbor’s wife, the adulterer and the adulteress shall surely be put to death. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The man who lies with his father’s wife has uncovered his father’s nakedness: both of them shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be on them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man lie with his daughter-in-law, both of them shall surely be put to death: they have created confusion; their blood shall be on them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man lie with mankind, as with womankind, both of them have committed abomination: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be on them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man take a wife and her mother, it is wickedness: they shall be burnt with fire, both he and they; that there be no wickedness among you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man lie with a animal, he shall surely be put to death: and you shall kill the animal. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a woman approach to any animal, and lie down thereto, you shall kill the woman, and the animal: they shall surely be put to death; their blood shall be on them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man shall take his sister, his father’s daughter, or his mother’s daughter, and see her nakedness, and she see his nakedness; it is a shameful thing; and they shall be cut off in the sight of the children of their people: he has uncovered his sister’s nakedness; he shall bear his iniquity. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man shall lie with a woman having her sickness, and shall uncover her nakedness; he has made naked her fountain, and she has uncovered the fountain of her blood: and both of them shall be cut off from among their people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not uncover the nakedness of your mother’s sister, nor of your father’s sister; for he has made naked his close relative: they shall bear their iniquity. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man shall lie with his uncle’s wife, he has uncovered his uncle’s nakedness: they shall bear their sin; they shall die childless. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man shall take his brother’s wife, it is impurity: he has uncovered his brother’s nakedness; they shall be childless. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall therefore keep all my statutes, and all my ordinances, and do them; that the land, where I bring you to dwell therein, not vomit you out. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not walk in the customs of the nation, which I cast out before you: for they did all these things, and therefore I abhorred them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But I have said to you, You shall inherit their land, and I will give it to you to possess it, a land flowing with milk and honey: I am Yahweh your God, who has separated you from the peoples. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall therefore make a distinction between the clean animal and the unclean, and between the unclean fowl and the clean: and you shall not make your souls abominable by animal, or by bird, or by anything with which the ground teems, which I have separated from you as unclean. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall be holy to me: for I, Yahweh, am holy, and have set you apart from the peoples, that you should be mine. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:20" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">A man also or a woman that has a familiar spirit, or that is a wizard, shall surely be put to death: they shall stone them with stones; their blood shall be on them. </q></p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="21"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="1"><p> Yahweh said to Moses, <q rend="double">Speak to the priests, the sons of Aaron, and say to them, There shall none defile himself for the dead among his people;</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="2">
<p><q rend="double; merge">except for his relatives, that is near to him, for his mother, and for his father, and for his son, and for his daughter, and for his brother, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and for his sister a virgin, that is near to him, that has had no husband; for her may he defile himself. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall not defile himself, [being] a chief man among his people, to profane himself. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">They shall not make baldness on their head, neither shall they shave off the corner of their beard, nor make any cuttings in their flesh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">They shall be holy to their God, and not profane the name of their God; for the offerings of Yahweh made by fire, the bread of their God, they do offer: therefore they shall be holy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">They shall not take a woman that is a prostitute, or profane; neither shall they take a woman put away from her husband: for he is holy to his God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall sanctify him therefore; for he offers the bread of your God: he shall be holy to you: for I Yahweh, who sanctify you, am holy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The daughter of any priest, if she profane herself by playing the prostitute, she profanes her father: she shall be burnt with fire. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who is the high priest among his brothers, on whose head the anointing oil is poured, and that is consecrated to put on the garments, shall not let the hair of his head go loose, nor tear his clothes; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">neither shall he go in to any dead body, nor defile himself for his father, or for his mother; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">neither shall he go out of the sanctuary, nor profane the sanctuary of his God; for the crown of the anointing oil of his God is on him: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall take a wife in her virginity. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">A widow, or one divorced, or a profane woman, a prostitute, these shall he not take: but a virgin of his own people shall he take as a wife. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall not profane his seed among his people: for I am Yahweh who sanctifies him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="16">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="17">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to Aaron, saying, Whoever he be of your seed throughout their generations that has a blemish, let him not approach to offer the bread of his God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">For whatever man he be that has a blemish, he shall not approach: a blind man, or a lame, or he that has a flat nose, or any deformity, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">or a man that is broken-footed, or broken-handed, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">or crook-backed, or a dwarf, or that has a blemish in his eye, or is scurvy, or scabbed, or has his stones broken; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">no man of the seed of Aaron the priest, that has a blemish, shall come near to offer the offerings of Yahweh made by fire: he has a blemish; he shall not come near to offer the bread of his God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall eat the bread of his God, both of the most holy, and of the holy: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">only he shall not go in to the veil, nor come near to the altar, because he has a blemish; that he not profane my sanctuaries: for I am Yahweh who sanctifies them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:21" n="24">
<p> So Moses spoke to Aaron, and to his sons, and to all the children of Israel. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="22"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to Aaron and to his sons, that they separate themselves from the holy things of the children of Israel, which they make holy to me, and that they not profane my holy name: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Tell them, Whoever he be of all your seed throughout your generations, that approaches to the holy things, which the children of Israel make holy to Yahweh, having his uncleanness on him, that soul shall be cut off from before me: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Whatever man of the seed of Aaron is a leper, or has an issue; he shall not eat of the holy things, until he is clean. Whoever touches anything that is unclean by the dead, or a man whose seed goes from him; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">or whoever touches any creeping thing, by which he may be made unclean, or a man of whom he may take uncleanness, whatever uncleanness he has; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">the soul that touches any such shall be unclean until the even, and shall not eat of the holy things, unless he bathe his flesh in water. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When the sun is down, he shall be clean; and afterward he shall eat of the holy things, because it is his bread. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">That which dies of itself, or is torn by animals, he shall not eat, to defile himself therewith: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">They shall therefore keep my charge, lest they bear sin for it, and die therein, if they profane it: I am Yahweh who sanctifies them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">There shall no stranger eat of the holy thing: a sojourner of the priest’s, or a hired servant, shall not eat of the holy thing. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if a priest buy any soul, the purchase of his money, he shall eat of it; and such as are born in his house, they shall eat of his bread. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a priest’s daughter be married to a stranger, she shall not eat of the heave-offering of the holy things. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if a priest’s daughter be a widow, or divorced, and have no child, and be returned to her father’s house, as in her youth, she shall eat of her father’s bread: but there shall no stranger eat of it. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man eat of the holy thing unwittingly, then he shall put the fifth part of it to it, and shall give to the priest the holy thing. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">They shall not profane the holy things of the children of Israel, which they offer to Yahweh, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and [so] cause them to bear the iniquity that brings guilt, when they eat their holy things: for I am Yahweh who sanctifies them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="17">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="18">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to Aaron, and to his sons, and to all the children of Israel, and tell them, Whoever he be of the house of Israel, or of the sojourners in Israel, that offers his offering, whether it be any of their vows, or any of their freewill-offerings, which they offer to Yahweh for a burnt offering; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">that you may be accepted, [you shall offer] a male without blemish, of the bulls, of the sheep, or of the goats. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But whatever has a blemish, that shall you not offer: for it shall not be acceptable for you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Whoever offers a sacrifice of peace-offerings to Yahweh to accomplish a vow, or for a freewill-offering, of the herd or of the flock, it shall be perfect to be accepted; there shall be no blemish therein. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Blind, or broken, or maimed, or having a wen, or scurvy, or scabbed, you shall not offer these to Yahweh, nor make an offering by fire of them on the altar to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Either a bull or a lamb that has any deformity or lacking in his parts, that may you offer for a freewill-offering; but for a vow it shall not be accepted. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">That which has its stones bruised, or crushed, or broken, or cut, you shall not offer to Yahweh; neither shall you do [thus] in your land. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Neither from the hand of a foreigner shall you offer the bread of your God of any of these; because their corruption is in them, there is a blemish in them: they shall not be accepted for you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="26">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="27">
<p><q rend="double">When a bull, or a sheep, or a goat, is brought forth, then it shall be seven days under the hen; and from the eighth day and thenceforth it shall be accepted for the offering of an offering made by fire to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Whether it be cow or ewe, you shall not kill it and its young both in one day. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When you sacrifice a sacrifice of thanksgiving to Yahweh, you shall sacrifice it that you may be accepted. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">On the same day it shall be eaten; you shall leave none of it until the morning: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Therefore shall you keep my commandments, and do them: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not profane my holy name; but I will be made holy among the children of Israel: I am Yahweh who makes you holy, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:22" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge">who brought you out of the land of Egypt, to be your God: I am Yahweh.</q> </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="23"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, The set feasts of Yahweh, which you shall proclaim to be holy convocations, even these are my set feasts. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Six days shall work be done: but on the seventh day is a Sabbath of solemn rest, a holy convocation; you shall do no manner of work: it is a Sabbath to Yahweh in all your dwellings. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">These are the set feasts of Yahweh, even holy convocations, which you shall proclaim in their appointed season. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">In the first month, on the fourteenth day of the month at even, is Yahweh’s Passover. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">On the fifteenth day of the same month is the feast of unleavened bread to Yahweh: seven days you shall eat unleavened bread. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">In the first day you shall have a holy convocation: you shall do no servile work. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But you shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh seven days: in the seventh day is a holy convocation; you shall do no servile work. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="9">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="10">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, When you are come into the land which I give to you, and shall reap the harvest of it, then you shall bring the sheaf of the first fruits of your harvest to the priest: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and he shall wave the sheaf before Yahweh, to be accepted for you: on the next day after the Sabbath the priest shall wave it. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">In the day when you wave the sheaf, you shall offer a he-lamb without blemish a year old for a burnt offering to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The meal-offering of it shall be two tenth parts [of an ephah] of fine flour mixed with oil, an offering made by fire to Yahweh for a sweet savor; and the drink-offering of it shall be of wine, the fourth part of a hin. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall eat neither bread, nor parched grain, nor fresh ears, until this same day, until you have brought the offering of your God: it is a statute forever throughout your generations in all your dwellings. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall count to you from the next day after the Sabbath, from the day that you brought the sheaf of the wave-offering; seven Sabbaths shall there be complete: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">even to the next day after the seventh Sabbath shall you number fifty days; and you shall offer a new meal-offering to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall bring out of your habitations two wave-loaves of two tenth parts [of an ephah]: they shall be of fine flour, they shall be baked with yeast, for first fruits to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall present with the bread seven lambs without blemish a year old, and one young bull, and two rams: they shall be a burnt offering to Yahweh, with their meal-offering, and their drink-offerings, even an offering made by fire, of a sweet savor to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall offer one male goat for a sin-offering, and two he-lambs a year old for a sacrifice of peace-offerings. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The priest shall wave them with the bread of the first fruits for a wave-offering before Yahweh, with the two lambs: they shall be holy to Yahweh for the priest. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall make proclamation on the same day; there shall be a holy convocation to you; you shall do no servile work: it is a statute forever in all your dwellings throughout your generations. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When you reap the harvest of your land, you shall not wholly reap the corners of your field, neither shall you gather the gleaning of your harvest: you shall leave them for the poor, and for the sojourner: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="23">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="24">
<p> Speak to the children of Israel, saying, In the seventh month, on the first day of the month, shall be a solemn rest to you, a memorial of blowing of trumpets, a holy convocation. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="25">
<p> You shall do no servile work; and you shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="26">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="27">
<p> <q rend="double">However on the tenth day of this seventh month is the day of atonement: it shall be a holy convocation to you, and you shall afflict your souls; and you shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall do no manner of work in that same day; for it is a day of atonement, to make atonement for you before Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">For whatever soul it be who shall not be afflicted in that same day; he shall be cut off from his people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Whatever soul it be who does any manner of work in that same day, that soul will I destroy from among his people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall do no manner of work: it is a statute forever throughout your generations in all your dwellings.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It shall be to you a Sabbath of solemn rest, and you shall afflict your souls: in the ninth day of the month at even, from even to even, shall you keep your Sabbath. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="33">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge"><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, saying, On the fifteenth day of this seventh month is the feast of tents for seven days to Yahweh. </q></q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="35">
<p><q rend="double; merge">On the first day shall be a holy convocation: you shall do no servile work. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="36">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Seven days you shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh: on the eighth day shall be a holy convocation to you; and you shall offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh: it is a solemn assembly; you shall do no servile work. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="37">
<p><q rend="double; merge">These are the set feasts of Yahweh, which you shall proclaim to be holy convocations, to offer an offering made by fire to Yahweh, a burnt offering, and a meal-offering, a sacrifice, and drink-offerings, each on its own day; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="38">
<p><q rend="double; merge">besides the Sabbaths of Yahweh, and besides your gifts, and besides all your vows, and besides all your freewill-offerings, which you give to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="39">
<p><q rend="double; merge">However on the fifteenth day of the seventh month, when you have gathered in the fruits of the land, you shall keep the feast of Yahweh seven days: on the first day shall be a solemn rest, and on the eighth day shall be a solemn rest. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="40">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall take on the first day the fruit of goodly trees, branches of palm trees, and boughs of thick trees, and willows of the brook; and you shall rejoice before Yahweh your God seven days. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="41">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall keep it a feast to Yahweh seven days in the year: it is a statute forever throughout your generations; you shall keep it in the seventh month. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="42">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall dwell in booths seven days; all who are home-born in Israel shall dwell in booths; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="43">
<p><q rend="double; merge">that your generations may know that I made the children of Israel to dwell in booths, when I brought them out of the land of Egypt: I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:23" n="44">
<p> Moses declared to the children of Israel the set feasts of Yahweh. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="24"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Command the children of Israel, that they bring to you pure olive oil beaten for the light, to cause a lamp to burn continually. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Outside of the veil of the testimony, in the tent of meeting, shall Aaron keep it in order from evening to morning before Yahweh continually: it shall be a statute forever throughout your generations. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall keep in order the lamps on the pure lampstand before Yahweh continually. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall take fine flour, and bake twelve cakes of it: two tenth parts [of an ephah] shall be in one cake. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall set them in two rows, six on a row, on the pure table before Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall put pure frankincense on each row, that it may be to the bread for a memorial, even an offering made by fire to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Every Sabbath day he shall set it in order before Yahweh continually; it is on the behalf of the children of Israel, an everlasting covenant. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">It shall be for Aaron and his sons; and they shall eat it in a holy place: for it is most holy to him of the offerings of Yahweh made by fire by a perpetual statute. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="10">
<p> The son of an Israelite woman, whose father was an Egyptian, went out among the children of Israel; and the son of the Israelite woman and a man of Israel strove together in the camp: </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="11">
<p> and the son of the Israelite woman blasphemed the Name, and cursed; and they brought him to Moses. His mother’s name was Shelomith, the daughter of Dibri, of the tribe of Dan. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="12">
<p> They put him in custody, that it might be declared to them at the mouth of Yahweh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="13">
<p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="14">
<p><q rend="double">Bring forth him who has cursed outside of the camp; and let all who heard him lay their hands on his head, and let all the congregation stone him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall speak to the children of Israel, saying, Whoever curses his God shall bear his sin. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who blasphemes the name of Yahweh, he shall surely be put to death; all the congregation shall certainly stone him: as well the sojourner, as the home-born, when he blasphemes the name [of Yahweh], shall be put to death. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who strikes any man mortally shall surely be put to death. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who strikes a animal mortally shall make it good, life for life. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man cause a blemish in his neighbor; as he has done, so shall it be done to him: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">breach for breach, eye for eye, tooth for tooth; as he has caused a blemish in a man, so shall it be rendered to him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He who kills a animal shall make it good: and he who kills a man shall be put to death. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall have one kind of law, as well for the sojourner, as for the home-born: for I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:24" n="23">
<p> Moses spoke to the children of Israel; and they brought forth him who had cursed out of the camp, and stoned him with stones. The children of Israel did as Yahweh commanded Moses. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="25"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses in Mount Sinai, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, When you come into the land which I give you, then shall the land keep a Sabbath to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Six years you shall sow your field, and six years you shall prune your vineyard, and gather in the fruits of it; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">but in the seventh year shall be a Sabbath of solemn rest for the land, a Sabbath to Yahweh: you shall neither sow your field, nor prune your vineyard. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">That which grows of itself of your harvest you shall not reap, and the grapes of your undressed vine you shall not gather: it shall be a year of solemn rest for the land. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The Sabbath of the land shall be for food for you; for you, and for your servant and for your maid, and for your hired servant and for your stranger, who sojourn with you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">For your cattle, and for the animals that are in your land, shall all the increase of it be for food. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall number seven Sabbaths of years to you, seven times seven years; and there shall be to you the days of seven Sabbaths of years, even forty-nine years. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Then shall you send abroad the loud trumpet on the tenth day of the seventh month; in the day of atonement shall you send abroad the trumpet throughout all your land. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall make the fiftieth year holy, and proclaim liberty throughout the land to all the inhabitants of it: it shall be a jubilee to you; and you shall return every man to his possession, and you shall return every man to his family. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">A jubilee shall that fiftieth year be to you: you shall not sow, neither reap that which grows of itself in it, nor gather [the grapes] in it of the undressed vines. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">For it is a jubilee; it shall be holy to you: you shall eat the increase of it out of the field. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">In this year of jubilee you shall return every man to his possession. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If you sell anything to your neighbor, or buy of your neighbor’s hand, you shall not wrong one another. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">According to the number of years after the jubilee you shall buy of your neighbor, [and] according to the number of years of the crops he shall sell to you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">According to the length of the years you shall increase the price of it, and according to the shortness of the years you shall diminish the price of it; for the number of the crops does he sell to you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not wrong one another; but you shall fear your God: for I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Therefore you shall do my statutes, and keep my ordinances and do them; and you shall dwell in the land in safety. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The land shall yield its fruit, and you shall eat your fill, and dwell therein in safety. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If you shall say, What shall we eat the seventh year? Behold, we shall not sow, nor gather in our increase; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then I will command my blessing on you in the sixth year, and it shall bring forth fruit for the three years. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall sow the eighth year, and eat of the fruits, the old store; until the ninth year, until its fruits come in, you shall eat the old store. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The land shall not be sold in perpetuity; for the land is mine: for you are strangers and sojourners with me. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">In all the land of your possession you shall grant a redemption for the land. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If your brother be grew poor, and sell some of his possession, then shall his kinsman who is next to him come, and shall redeem that which his brother has sold. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man have no one to redeem it, and he be grew rich and find sufficient to redeem it; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then let him reckon the years of the sale of it, and restore the surplus to the man to whom he sold it; and he shall return to his possession. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if he isn’t able to get it back for himself, then that which he has sold shall remain in the hand of him who has bought it until the year of jubilee: and in the jubilee it shall go out, and he shall return to his possession. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man sell a dwelling-house in a walled city, then he may redeem it within a whole year after it is sold; for a full year shall he have the right of redemption. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it isn’t redeemed within the space of a full year, then the house that is in the walled city shall be made sure in perpetuity to him who bought it, throughout his generations: it shall not go out in the jubilee. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But the houses of the villages which have no wall round about them shall be reckoned with the fields of the country: they may be redeemed, and they shall go out in the jubilee. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Nevertheless the cities of the Levites, the houses of the cities of their possession, may the Levites redeem at any time. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If one of the Levites redeem, then the house that was sold, and the city of his possession, shall go out in the jubilee; for the houses of the cities of the Levites are their possession among the children of Israel. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But the field of the suburbs of their cities may not be sold; for it is their perpetual possession. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="35">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If your brother has grown poor, and his hand fail with you; then you shall uphold him: [as] a stranger and a sojourner shall he live with you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="36">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Take no interest of him or increase, but fear your God; that your brother may live with you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="37">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not give him your money on interest, nor give him your victuals for increase. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="38">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I am Yahweh your God, who brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, to give you the land of Canaan, [and] to be your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="39">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If your brother has grown poor with you, and sell himself to you; you shall not make him to serve as a bond-servant. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="40">
<p><q rend="double; merge">As a hired servant, and as a sojourner, he shall be with you; he shall serve with you to the year of jubilee: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="41">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then shall he go out from you, he and his children with him, and shall return to his own family, and to the possession of his fathers shall he return. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="42">
<p><q rend="double; merge">For they are my servants, whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: they shall not be sold as bondservants. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="43">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall not rule over him with rigor, but shall fear your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="44">
<p><q rend="double; merge">As for your bondservants, and your bondmaids, whom you shall have; of the nations that are round about you, of them shall you buy bondservants and bondmaids. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="45">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Moreover of the children of the strangers who sojourn among you, of them shall you buy, and of their families who are with you, which they have conceived in your land: and they shall be your possession. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="46">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall make them an inheritance for your children after you, to hold for a possession; of them shall you take your bondservants forever: but over your brothers the children of Israel you shall not rule, one over another, with rigor. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="47">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a stranger or sojourner with you has grown rich, and your brother has grown poor beside him, and sell himself to the stranger [or] sojourner with you, or to the stock of the stranger’s family; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="48">
<p><q rend="double; merge">after that he is sold he may be redeemed: one of his brothers may redeem him; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="49">
<p><q rend="double; merge">or his uncle, or his uncle’s son, may redeem him, or any who is a close relative to him of his family may redeem him; or if he has grown rich, he may redeem himself. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="50">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall reckon with him who bought him from the year that he sold himself to him to the year of jubilee: and the price of his sale shall be according to the number of years; according to the time of a hired servant shall he be with him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="51">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If there be yet many years, according to them he shall give back the price of his redemption out of the money that he was bought for. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="52">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If there remain but few years to the year of jubilee, then he shall reckon with him; according to his years shall he give back the price of his redemption. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="53">
<p><q rend="double; merge">As a servant hired year by year shall he be with him: he shall not rule with rigor over him in your sight. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="54">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he isn’t redeemed by these [means], then he shall go out in the year of jubilee, he, and his children with him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:25" n="55">
<p><q rend="double; merge">For to me the children of Israel are servants; they are my servants whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt: I am Yahweh your God.</q> </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="26"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="1"><p><q rend="double; merge"> You shall make you no idols, neither shall you rear you up an engraved image, or a pillar, neither shall you place any figured stone in your land, to bow down to it: for I am Yahweh your God. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="2">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall keep my Sabbaths, and reverence my sanctuary: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If you walk in my statutes, and keep my commandments, and do them; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then I will give your rains in their season, and the land shall yield its increase, and the trees of the field shall yield their fruit. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Your threshing shall reach to the vintage, and the vintage shall reach to the sowing time; and you shall eat your bread to the full, and dwell in your land safely. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will give peace in the land, and you shall lie down, and none shall make you afraid: and I will cause evil animals to cease out of the land, neither shall the sword go through your land. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall chase your enemies, and they shall fall before you by the sword. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Five of you shall chase a hundred, and a hundred of you shall chase ten thousand; and your enemies shall fall before you by the sword. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will have respect to you, and make you fruitful, and multiply you, and will establish my covenant with you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall eat old store long kept, and you shall bring forth the old because of the new. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will set my tent among you: and my soul won’t abhor you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will walk among you, and will be your God, and you shall be my people. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I am Yahweh your God, who brought you forth out of the land of Egypt, that you should not be their bondservants; and I have broken the bars of your yoke, and made you go upright. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if you will not listen to me, and will not do all these commandments; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and if you shall reject my statutes, and if your soul abhor my ordinances, so that you will not do all my commandments, but break my covenant; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I also will do this to you: I will appoint terror over you, even consumption and fever, that shall consume the eyes, and make the soul to pine away; and you shall sow your seed in vain, for your enemies shall eat it. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will set my face against you, and you shall be struck before your enemies: those who hate you shall rule over you; and you shall flee when none pursues you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If you will not yet for these things listen to me, then I will chastise you seven times more for your sins. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will break the pride of your power: and I will make your sky as iron, and your earth as brass; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and your strength shall be spent in vain; for your land shall not yield its increase, neither shall the trees of the land yield their fruit. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If you walk contrary to me, and won’t listen to me, I will bring seven times more plagues on you according to your sins. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will send the animal of the field among you, which shall rob you of your children, and destroy your cattle, and make you few in number; and your ways shall become desolate. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If by these things you won’t be reformed to me, but will walk contrary to me; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then will I also walk contrary to you; and I will strike you, even I, seven times for your sins. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will bring a sword on you, that shall execute the vengeance of the covenant; and you shall be gathered together within your cities: and I will send the pestilence among you; and you shall be delivered into the hand of the enemy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When I break your staff of bread, ten women shall bake your bread in one oven, and they shall deliver your bread again by weight: and you shall eat, and not be satisfied. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If you won’t for all this listen to me, but walk contrary to me; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then I will walk contrary to you in wrath; and I also will chastise you seven times for your sins. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall eat the flesh of your sons, and the flesh of your daughters shall you eat. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will destroy your high places, and cut down your sun-images, and cast your dead bodies on the bodies of your idols; and my soul shall abhor you. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will make your cities a waste, and will bring your sanctuaries to desolation, and I won’t smell the savor of your sweet odors. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I will bring the land into desolation; and your enemies that dwell therein shall be astonished at it. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You will I scatter among the nations, and I will draw out the sword after you: and your land shall be a desolation, and your cities shall be a waste. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="34">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Then shall the land enjoy its Sabbaths, as long as it lies desolate, and you are in your enemies’ land; even then shall the land rest, and enjoy its Sabbaths. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="35">
<p><q rend="double; merge">As long as it lies desolate it shall have rest, even the rest which it didn’t have in your Sabbaths, when you lived on it. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="36">
<p><q rend="double; merge">As for those who are left of you, I will send a faintness into their heart in the lands of their enemies: and the sound of a driven leaf shall chase them; and they shall flee, as one flees from the sword; and they shall fall when none pursues. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="37">
<p><q rend="double; merge">They shall stumble one on another, as it were before the sword, when none pursues: and you shall have no power to stand before your enemies. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="38">
<p><q rend="double; merge">You shall perish among the nations, and the land of your enemies shall eat you up. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="39">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Those who are left of you shall pine away in their iniquity in your enemies’ lands; and also in the iniquities of their fathers shall they pine away with them. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="40">
<p><q rend="double; merge">They shall confess their iniquity, and the iniquity of their fathers, in their trespass which they trespassed against me, and also that, because they walked contrary to me, </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="41">
<p><q rend="double; merge">I also walked contrary to them, and brought them into the land of their enemies: if then their uncircumcised heart be humbled, and they then accept of the punishment of their iniquity; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="42">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then will I remember my covenant with Jacob; and also my covenant with Isaac, and also my covenant with Abraham will I remember; and I will remember the land. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="43">
<p><q rend="double; merge">The land also shall be left by them, and shall enjoy its Sabbaths, while it lies desolate without them: and they shall accept of the punishment of their iniquity; because, even because they rejected my ordinances, and their soul abhorred my statutes. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="44">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Yet for all that, when they are in the land of their enemies, I will not reject them, neither will I abhor them, to destroy them utterly, and to break my covenant with them; for I am Yahweh their God; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="45">
<p><q rend="double; merge">but I will for their sakes remember the covenant of their ancestors, whom I brought forth out of the land of Egypt in the sight of the nations, that I might be their God: I am Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:26" n="46">
<p> These are the statutes and ordinances and laws, which Yahweh made between him and the children of Israel in Mount Sinai by Moses. </p> </div></div> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2" n="27"> 
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="1"> <p> Yahweh spoke to Moses, saying, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="2">
<p><q rend="double">Speak to the children of Israel, and tell them, When a man shall accomplish a vow, the persons shall be for Yahweh by your estimation. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="3">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Your estimation shall be of the male from twenty years old even to sixty years old, even your estimation shall be fifty shekels of silver, after the shekel of the sanctuary. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="4">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it be a female, then your estimation shall be thirty shekels. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="5">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it be from five years old even to twenty years old, then your estimation shall be of the male twenty shekels, and for the female ten shekels. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="6">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it be from a month old even to five years old, then your estimation shall be of the male five shekels of silver, and for the female your estimation shall be three shekels of silver. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="7">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it be from sixty years old and upward; if it be a male, then your estimation shall be fifteen shekels, and for the female ten shekels. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="8">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if he be poorer than your estimation, then he shall be set before the priest, and the priest shall value him; according to the ability of him who vowed shall the priest value him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="9">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it be a animal, whereof men offer an offering to Yahweh, all that any man gives of such to Yahweh shall be holy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="10">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall not alter it, nor change it, a good for a bad, or a bad for a good: and if he shall at all change animal for animal, then both it and that for which it is changed shall be holy. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="11">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it be any unclean animal, of which they do not offer an offering to Yahweh, then he shall set the animal before the priest; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="12">
<p><q rend="double; merge">and the priest shall value it, whether it be good or bad: as you the priest value it, so shall it be. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="13">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if he will indeed redeem it, then he shall add the fifth part of it to your estimation. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="14">
<p><q rend="double; merge">When a man shall sanctify his house to be holy to Yahweh, then the priest shall estimate it, whether it be good or bad: as the priest shall estimate it, so shall it stand. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="15">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he who sanctified it will redeem his house, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of your estimation to it, and it shall be his. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="16">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man shall sanctify to Yahweh part of the field of his possession, then your estimation shall be according to the sowing of it: the sowing of a homer of barley [shall be valued] at fifty shekels of silver. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="17">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he sanctify his field from the year of jubilee, according to your estimation it shall stand. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="18">
<p><q rend="double; merge">But if he sanctify his field after the jubilee, then the priest shall reckon to him the money according to the years that remain to the year of jubilee; and an abatement shall be made from your estimation. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="19">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he who sanctified the field will indeed redeem it, then he shall add the fifth part of the money of your estimation to it, and it shall be assured to him. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="20">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he will not redeem the field, or if he has sold the field to another man, it shall not be redeemed any more: </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="21">
<p><q rend="double; merge">but the field, when it goes out in the jubilee, shall be holy to Yahweh, as a field devoted; the possession of it shall be the priest’s. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="22">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If he sanctify to Yahweh a field which he has bought, which is not of the field of his possession; </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="23">
<p><q rend="double; merge">then the priest shall reckon to him the worth of your estimation to the year of jubilee: and he shall give your estimation in that day, as a holy thing to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="24">
<p><q rend="double; merge">In the year of jubilee the field shall return to him of whom it was bought, even to him to whom the possession of the land belongs. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="25">
<p><q rend="double; merge">All your estimations shall be according to the shekel of the sanctuary: twenty gerahs shall be the shekel. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="26">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Only the firstborn among animals, which is made a firstborn to Yahweh, no man shall sanctify it; whether it be ox or sheep, it is Yahweh’s. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="27">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If it be of an unclean animal, then he shall ransom it according to your estimation, and shall add to it the fifth part of it: or if it isn’t redeemed, then it shall be sold according to your estimation. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="28">
<p><q rend="double; merge">Notwithstanding, no devoted thing, that a man shall devote to Yahweh of all that he has, whether of man or animal, or of the field of his possession, shall be sold or redeemed: every devoted thing is most holy to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="29">
<p><q rend="double; merge">No one devoted, who shall be devoted from among men, shall be ransomed; he shall surely be put to death. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="30">
<p><q rend="double; merge">All the tithe of the land, whether of the seed of the land, or of the fruit of the tree, is Yahweh’s: it is holy to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="31">
<p><q rend="double; merge">If a man will redeem anything of his tithe, he shall add to it the fifth part of it. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="32">
<p><q rend="double; merge">All the tithe of the herd or the flock, whatever passes under the rod, the tenth shall be holy to Yahweh. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="33">
<p><q rend="double; merge">He shall not search whether it be good or bad, neither shall he change it: and if he change it at all, then both it and that for which it is changed shall be holy; it shall not be redeemed. </q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0527.tlg003.perseus-eng2:27" n="34">
<p> These are the commandments, which Yahweh commanded Moses for the children of Israel in Mount Sinai. </p> </div></div> </div> </body> </text>
</TEI>
