<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Peace with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> from
					Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
				<author>Andocides</author>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>


			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Andocides</author>
						<title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes 1, Antiphon Andocides, with an
							English translation by K. J. Maidment, M.A.</title>

						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
								Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1968</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="speech" delim="."/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English </language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek </language>
				<language ident="latin">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--
<change><date>3/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>redo tagging</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
	<change><date>5/27/09</date><respStmt><name>RS</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt>
		<item>  
			$Log: andoc_eng.xml,v $
			Revision 1.1  2009-10-09 19:49:16  rsingh04
			more reorganizing of texts module by collection

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/07 21:00:34  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.10  2009/06/22 19:33:09  student
			edited entity tags CEH

			Revision 1.9  2009/05/27 15:55:16  rsingh04
			added cvs log keyword

		</item>
	</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
			<change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="section" n="1">
				<p>I think you all understand, gentlemen, that it is better to make peace on fair
					terms than to continue fighting. But some of you fail to see that although our
					political leaders have no objection to peace in the abstract, they are opposed
					to such measures as would lead to it, on the ground that the people would be in
					very grave danger of seeing the existing constitution overthrown once peace was
					concluded. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="2">
				<p>Now had the Athenian people never made peace with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName> in the past, our lack of previous experience and the
					untrustworthy character of the Spartans might have justified such fears. But you
					have done so on a number of occasions since the establishment of the democracy;
					and it is therefore only logical that you should first of all consider the
					results which followed at the time; one must use the past as a guide to the
					future, gentlemen. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="3">
				<p><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">3-12 of this speech were inserted by Aeschines,
						with slight alterations, in his <title>De Falsa Legatione</title>( <bibl
							n="Aeschin. 2.172">Aeschin. 2.172-176</bibl>), an interesting example of
						the plagiarism which is known to have been common in ancient times. The
							<title>De Falsa Legatione</title>was delivered in 343, almost fifty
						years after this.</note> Now take the days when we were fighting <placeName
						key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
						>Andocides is confused in his history here. He is referring to the revolt of
							<placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> which occurred in
							<date>446</date> B.C. and which was followed by a thirty years' peace
						with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. He is also
						inaccurate in stating that <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName> was still holding <placeName key="perseus,Megara"
							>Megara</placeName>; <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>
						revolted at the same time as <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
						>Euboea</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
						was left only with the two ports of Pegae and <placeName
							key="perseus,Nisaea">Nisaea</placeName>. The peace marked the end of her
						effort to acquire an empire on land. See <bibl n="Thuc. 1.112">Thuc.
							1.112</bibl>.</note> and controlled <placeName key="perseus,Megara"
						>Megara</placeName>, Pegae, and <placeName key="tgn,5004287"
						>Troezen</placeName>. We were seized with a longing for peace; and, in
					virtue of his being <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>'s
					representative at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, we
					recalled Cimon's son, Miltiades<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A double
						historical error. (a) Andocides means Cimon, son of Miltiades. (b) Cimon had
						been dead three years when the thirty years' peace was negotiated. A. is
						thinking of the truce of five years with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
							>Sparta</placeName> arranged by Cimon in 451 immediately upon his return
						from exile. It was at the time of its expiry that the revolt of <placeName
							key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> occurred. Cimon had been ostracized
						in 461 after his ignominious dismissal by the Spartans from <placeName
							key="perseus,Ithome">Ithome</placeName>. His exile marked the triumph of
						the advanced democrats headed by Ephialtes and Pericles.</note>,who had been
					ostracized and was living in the <placeName key="perseus,Chersonesos,Crete"
						>Chersonese</placeName>, for the one purpose of sending him to <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> to make overtures for an armistice.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="4">
				<p>On that occasion we secured a peace of fifty years with <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>; and both sides kept the treaty in
					question for thirteen. Let us consider this single instance first, gentlemen.
					Did the Athenian democracy ever fall during this peace? No one can show that it
					did. On the contrary, I will tell you how much you benefited by this peace. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="5">
				<p>To begin with, we fortified Peiraeus in the course of this period<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Again an error. Peiraeus was fortified by
						Themistocles immediately after the repulse of the Persians in
							<date>480</date>.</note>: secondly, we built the Long Wall to the
						north<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The northern Long Wall, connecting
							<placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> with Peiraeus, was in
						fact built in 457, over ten years before the negotiation of the peace which
						Andocides is discussing. Nothing is said of the wall to the south, running
						between <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and Phalerum,
						which was constructed at the same time.</note>: then the existing fleet of
					old, unseaworthy triremes with which we had won <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
						>Greece</placeName> her independence by defeating the king of <placeName
						key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> and his barbarians—these existing
					vessels were replaced by a hundred new ones<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">An
						obvious inaccuracy. The Athenian fleet had been growing steadily since the
						Persian Wars and the institution of the Delian League.</note>: and it was at
					this time that we first enrolled three hundred cavalry and purchased three
					hundred Scythian archers<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cavalry had been in
						existence since at least the seventh century. Solon, at the beginning of the
						sixth, formed his second property class of <foreign xml:lang="greek"
							>*(ippei=s</foreign>, citizens wealthy enough to provide themselves with
						a horse in time of war. Archers (<foreign xml:lang="greek"
							>toco/tai</foreign>) were imported for the first time shortly after
							<placeName key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus">Salamis</placeName> (480
						B.C.)</note>. Such were the benefits which <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
						>Athens</placeName> derived from the peace with <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, such the strength which was added
					thereby to the Athenian democracy. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="6">
				<p>Later we went to war on account of <placeName key="perseus,Aegina City"
						>Aegina</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There is bad confusion
						here. <placeName key="perseus,Aegina City">Aegina</placeName> lost her
						independence and was incorporated in the Athenian empire in 457. Under the
						Thirty Years' Peace of 446 she was guaranteed autonomy on condition that she
						continued to pay tribute. In 432, she made secret overtures to <placeName
							key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, alleging that her autonomy had
						not been respected. Thus Andocides may be thinking of her share in
						precipitating the Archidamian War. On the other hand, the peace which
						follows is not the Peace of Nicias; when talking of the benefits which
						ensued from it, Andocides seems to be referring once again to the Thirty
						Years' Peace (see <bibl n="Andoc. 3.3">Andoc. 3.3</bibl>). Probably he is
						thinking of the peace of 446, and assumes that because the status of
							<placeName key="perseus,Aegina City">Aegina</placeName> figured
						prominently in the negotiations, it was <placeName key="perseus,Aegina City"
							>Aegina</placeName> which had originally sent <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to war.</note>; and after both
					sides had suffered heavily, we were seized once more with a desire for peace. So
					a deputation of ten —among them my grandfather, Andocides — was chosen from the
					whole citizen body and dispatched to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName> with unlimited powers to negotiate a peace. They
					arranged a thirty years' peace with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName> for us. That is a long period, gentlemen; yet did the
					democracy ever fall in the course of it? Was any party, I ask you, ever caught
					plotting a revolution? No one can point to an instance. In fact just the
					opposite happened. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="7">
				<p>The peace in question exalted the Athenian democracy; it rendered it so powerful
					that during the years after we gained peace we first of all deposited a thousand
					talents on the Acropolis and passed a law which set them apart as a state
						reserve<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For Athenian finance between 446
						and 432 see I.G. i2. 91. According to Thucydides a reserve of 6000 talents
						had been accumulated on the Acropolis by the end of the period. One thousand
						were specially set apart against a naval crisis. It was forbidden to use
						this sum for any other purpose under pain of death. Andocides appears to be
						confusing the money earmarked for ships with the ships themselves</note>; in
					addition to that we built a hundred triremes, and decreed that they should be
					kept in reserve likewise: we laid out docks,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
						>Inaccurate. The docks had been built by Themistocles in the decade
						following the Persian Wars.</note> we enrolled twelve hundred cavalry and as
					many archers, and the Long Wall to the south was constructed.<note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true">i.e. the Middle Wall, running parallel to the wall on the
						north and connecting <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> with
						Peiraeus by a narrow corridor. It was built during the Thirty Years'
						Peace.</note> Such were the benefits which <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
						>Athens</placeName> derived from the peace with <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, such the strength which was added
					thereby to the Athenian democracy. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="8">
				<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Then we went to war again on account of <placeName
						key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
						>The famous Megarian decree which excluded <placeName key="perseus,Megara"
							>Megara</placeName> from the markets of Attica and the ports of the
						Athenian empire was passed in 432. It brought Peloponnesian discontent to a
						head, and the Archidamian War followed (431-<date>421</date>). See <bibl
							n="Thuc. 1.139">Thuc. 1.139</bibl>.</note> and allowed Attica to be laid
					waste; but the many privations which we suffered led us to make peace once more,
					this time through Nicias, the son of Niceratus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
						>In 421 B.C. It was a Fifty Years' Peace; but in 420 <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> allied herself with <placeName
							key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Elis"
							>Elis</placeName>, and Mantinea, who were aggressively anti-Spartan. By
						418 she was at war again.</note> As you are all aware, I imagine, this peace
					enabled us to deposit seven thousand talents of coined silver on the Acropolis
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="9">
				<p>and to acquire over three hundred ships<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The MSS.
						give four hundred. Markland's correction, based on the corresponding passage
						in Aeschines and <bibl n="Thuc. 2.13">Thuc. 2.13</bibl>, is now universally
						accepted.</note>: an annual tribute of more than twelve hundred talents was
					coming in<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">According to Thucydides (<bibl
							n="Thuc. 2.13">Thuc. 2.13</bibl>) the revenue from tribute at the
						beginning of the Archidamian War was 600 talents yearly. In 425 there was a
						re-assessment (known from I.G. i 2 . 63) which increased the total annual
						contribution of the allies to just over 960 talents. There is no good
						evidence to show that this figure was ever exceeded: and Andocides'
							<date>1200</date> must be treated as an exaggeration. The mention of a
						reserve of 7000 talents is suspicious. <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName> did, it is true, recover remarkably from the effects
						of the Archidamian War during the period between 421 and the Sicilian
						Expedition of 415. But Andocides is here talking of the years 421-419 only.
						He may be basing his figures on the financial reserve of <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> before the Archidamian
						War.</note>: we controlled the <placeName key="perseus,Chersonesos,Crete"
						>Chersonese</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Naxos City"
						>Naxos</placeName>, and over two-thirds of <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
						>Euboea</placeName>: while to mention our other settlements abroad
					individually would be tedious. But in spite of all these advantages we went to
					war with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> afresh, then as now
					at the instigation of <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>.<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>
						invaded the territory of <placeName key="perseus,Epidauros"
							>Epidaurus</placeName> in <date when="-419">419</date>, thereby bringing
						about an open breach with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName>. <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, at
						the instance of Alcibiades, gave <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
							>Argos</placeName> her support in virtue of the alliance of the previous
						year. “Then as now at the instigation of <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
							>Argos</placeName>,” i.e. <placeName key="tgn,5001993"
							>Argive</placeName> representatives are again present, while Andocides
						is speaking, to urge <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to
						continue war with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> (cf.
							<bibl n="Andoc. 3.24">Andoc. 3.24</bibl> ff.). This seems more probable
						than the other possible rendering: “Once again at the instigation of
							<placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>,” referring to the
						Athenian alliance with <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> in
							<date when="-462">462</date> B.C.</note>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="10">
				<p>Now first of all, gentlemen, call to mind what I originally said that I was
					setting out to show. It was, was it not, that peace has never yet caused the
					fall of the Athenian democracy. That has now been proved against all possible
					arguments to the contrary. However, I have heard some people saying before now
					that the result of our last peace with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In 404, after
							<placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>.</note> was the
					installment of the Thirty, the death of many citizens by the hemlock-cup, and
					the exile of others. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="11">
				<p>Those who talk in this fashion misapprehend matters. There is a wide difference
					between a peace and a truce. A peace is a settlement of differences between
					equals: a truce is the dictation of terms to the conquered by the conquerors
					after victory in war, exactly as the Spartans laid down after their victory over
					us that we should demolish our walls, surrender our fleet, and restore our
					exiles. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="12">
				<p>The agreement made then was a forced truce upon dictated terms: whereas today you
					are considering a peace. Why, look at the actual provisions of the two as they
					stand recorded; contrast the conditions of the truce inscribed upon the
						stone<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">It was customary to inscribe
						treaties, etc., upon upright slabs of stone (<foreign xml:lang="greek"
							>sth=lai</foreign>). At <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName> such <foreign xml:lang="greek">sth=lai</foreign>
						would stand for the most part on the Acropolis.</note> with the conditions
					on which you can make peace today. On the stone it is laid down that we shall
					demolish our walls: whereas under the present terms we can rebuild them. The
					truce allows us twelve ships: the peace as many as we like. Under the truce
						<placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>, Imbros, and Scyros remained
					in the possession of their occupants: under the peace they are to be ours. Nor
					is there today any obligation upon us to restore our exiles, as there was then,
					with the fall of the democracy as its consequence. Where is the similarity
					between the one and the other? Thus the general conclusion which I reach in the
					matter is this, gentlemen: peace means safety and power for the democracy,
					whereas war means its downfall. So much for that aspect of the question. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="13">
				<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now it is argued by some that present
					circumstances oblige us to continue fighting. Let us begin, then, gentlemen, by
					considering exactly why we are to fight. Everyone would agree, I think, that war
					is justified only so long as one is either suffering a wrong oneself or
					supporting the cause of another who has been wronged. Now we were both suffering
					a wrong ourselves and also supporting the cause of the Boeotians who had been
					wronged. If, then, <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> guarantees
					that our wrongs shall cease, and if the Boeotians have decided to allow
						<placeName key="perseus,Orchomenos">Orchomenus</placeName> its independence
					and make peace, why are we to continue fighting? </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="14">
				<p>To free <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>? She is free already.
					To be able to build ourselves walls? The peace gives us that right also. To be
					allowed to build new triremes, and refit and keep our old ones? That is assured
					us as well, since the treaty affirms the independence of each state. To recover
					the islands, <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName>, Scyros, and
					Imbros? It is expressly laid down that these shall belong to <placeName
						key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="15">
				<p>Well then, is it to get back the <placeName key="perseus,Chersonesos,Crete"
						>Chersonese</placeName>, our colonies, our landed property abroad, and the
					debts owed us?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. all that had been lost when
						the empire collapsed in 404.</note> A war for their recovery needs the
					support of the king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> and our
					allies, and they refuse that support. Or shall I be told that we must continue
					fighting until we have crushed <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName> and her allies? We are not adequately equipped, in my
					opinion, for a campaign on such a scale; and if we are successful, what must we
					ourselves expect from <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>
					afterwards? </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="16">
				<p>No, even if this were a justifiable ground for war, and we had sufficient money
					and the necessary men, we ought not to continue it. So if we have no reasons for
					prolonging the war, no enemy to fight, and no resources, why should we not make
					every effort to secure peace? </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="17">
				<p>Do not overlook another thing, gentlemen; you are negotiating today for the peace
					and independence of all Greeks alike: you are giving them all the opportunity of
					sharing in every advantage. Think of the circumstances in which the leading
					powers are ceasing hostilities. To begin with, take <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. When she first went to war with us
					and our allies,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In 395, when Pausanias and
						Lysander invaded <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>. This
						began the “Corinthian War.”</note> she controlled both land and sea; but the
					peace is leaving her mistress of neither. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="18">
				<p>And she is sacrificing this supremacy, not because we forced her to do so, but in
					order to give the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> its
					independence. The Spartans have now won three battles: the first at <placeName
						key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
						>July 394. The Spartans met the allied forces of <placeName
							key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Corinth"
							>Corinth</placeName>, and <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
							>Argos</placeName> at <placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName>,
						between <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> and <placeName
							key="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>, and heavily defeated them. The
						battle was fought before Agesilaus, who had been recalled from <placeName
							key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>, had reached <placeName
							key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>.</note> against the full allied
					forces, who were left with no excuse for their defeat, save only that the
					Spartans, with none to aid them, fought more bravely than all the rest together;
					the second in <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> under
						Agesilaus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The battle of <placeName
							key="tgn,7011235">Coronea</placeName>, fought a fortnight or so after
							<placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName>. The allied forces
						attempted to block the passage of Agesilaus as he marched southwards through
							<placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> on his homeward journey
						from <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>. The Spartans were
						victorious, but sustained heavy losses; and Agesilaus was content to
						continue his march without halting.</note> when they once more gained a
					similar victory; and the third at the capture of Lechaeum,<note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> was now
						fortified by Long Walls on the Athenian plan. In 393 <placeName
							key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> made a determined effort to
						break through the fortifications. She succeeded, and seized the Corinthian
						port of Lechaeum on the west and Sidus and Crommyon on the east in spite of
						strong opposition from the allied forces.</note> against the full <placeName
						key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> and Corinthian forces, together with
					the Athenians and Boeotians present. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="19">
				<p>But in spite of these amazing successes they, the victors in the field, are ready
					for a peace which will leave them with nothing save their own territory: they
					are recognizing the independence of the Greek states, and they are allowing
					their defeated opponents to share the freedom of the seas. Yet what terms of
					peace would they have gained from us, had they met with but a single defeat?
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="20">
				<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Again, what are the conditions under which
						<placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> is making peace? <placeName
						key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> went to war because she refused to
					allow <placeName key="perseus, Orchomenos">Orchomenus</placeName> its
						independence.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See Introduction.</note>
					today, after the loss of thousands of lives, after the devastation of a large
					part of her territory, after heavy public and private expenditure, which is now
					a dead loss, after four years of fighting, <placeName key="tgn,7002683"
						>Boeotia</placeName> is recognizing the independence of <placeName
						key="perseus,Orchomenos">Orchomenus</placeName> and making peace, thereby
					rendering her sufferings useless, as by acknowledging the independence of
						<placeName key="perseus,Orchomenos">Orchomenus</placeName> at the outset she
					need never have gone to war at all. Those are the circumstances in which
						<placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> is ceasing hostilities.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="21">
				<p>Now what are the terms available to ourselves, gentlemen? How is <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> disposed to us? Here, if I am about
					to cause distress to any of you, I ask his forgiveness, as I shall be stating
					nothing but the facts. To begin with, when we lost our fleet on the <placeName
						key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName> and were shut within our
						walls,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The siege of <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, which followed immediately
						after <placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>, lasted from
						September 405 to April 404.</note> what did our present allies,<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Notably the Thebans and Corinthians.</note> who
					were then on the Spartan side, propose to do with us? They proposed, did they
					not, to sell our citizens as slaves and make Attica a waste. And who was it who
					prevented this? The Spartans; they dissuaded the allies, and for their own part
					refused even to contemplate such measures. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="22">
				<p>Later we gave them our oath, were allowed to erect the column, and accepted a
					truce upon dictated terms, a hardship which was welcome enough at the time.
					Nevertheless we then proceeded, by means of an alliance, to detach <placeName
						key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Corinth"
						>Corinth</placeName> from <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
					>Sparta</placeName>, and to resume friendly relations with <placeName
						key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, thereby involving <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> in the battle of <placeName
						key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
						>i.e. <placeName key="perseus,Nemea">Nemea</placeName> in 394.</note> Who,
					again, turned the king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>
					against <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>? Who enabled Conon to
					fight the engagement at sea which lost her her maritime supremacy?<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">After Aegospotami Conon, the Athenian admiral,
						fled to the court of Evagoras of <placeName key="perseus,Salamis, Cyprus"
							>Salamis</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>.
						Through his influence he ultimately won the confidence of the satrap
						Pharnabazus. In 397 he was put in charge of the Persian fleet, and in 394
						utterly routed the Spartans under Peisander off <placeName key="tgn,5003757"
							>Cnidus</placeName>.</note>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="23">
				<p>Yet in spite of all that she has suffered at our hands, she agrees to the same
					concessions as those made us by our allies, and offers us our walls, our fleet,
					and our islands. What terms of peace do you expect representatives to bring you
					back, may I ask? Can they do better than obtain the same advantages from the
					enemy as our friends are offering us, the very advantages which we went to war
					to secure for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>? Whereas others
					make peace at a loss to themselves, we gain precisely what we most want. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="24">
				<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What, then, remains to be considered? <placeName
						key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, and the appeal which <placeName
						key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> is making to us. First as to
						<placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>. I should like to be
					informed of the value of <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> to
					us, if <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> leaves our ranks and
					makes peace with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. Recall the
					day on which we concluded our alliance with <placeName key="tgn,7002683"
						>Boeotia</placeName>, gentlemen: </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="25">
				<p>Recall the assumption on which we acted. We imagined, did we not, that once
						<placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> joined forces with us we
					could face the whole world. Yet here we are considering how we can continue
					fighting <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> without her help,
					now that she is making peace. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="26">
				<p>“Perfectly well,” say some, “provided that we protect <placeName
						key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> and are allied with <placeName
						key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>.” But if <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> attacks <placeName
						key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, shall we go to her help or not? For
					we shall assuredly have no choice but to follow the one course or the other. Yet
					should we withhold our help, we are left without a single argument wherewith to
					justify ourselves or to show that <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
						>Argos</placeName> has not the right to act as she pleases. On the other
					hand, should we give her our aid, is not a conflict with <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> inevitable? And to what end? To
					enable us to lose our own territory as well as that of <placeName
						key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> in the event of defeat, and to
					secure <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> for <placeName
						key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> in the event of victory. Will not that
					prove to be our object in fighting? </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="27">
				<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now let us examine the <placeName
						key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> proposals in their turn. <placeName
						key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> urges us to join <placeName
						key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> and herself in maintaining the
					war; yet in virtue of a private peace which she has negotiated,<note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true">Possibly a reference to the <placeName key="tgn,5001993"
							>Argive</placeName> trick of celebrating a <foreign xml:lang="greek"
							>i(eromhni/a</foreign>, or “sacred month,” when <placeName
							key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> was about to invade their
						territory. The <foreign xml:lang="greek">i(eromhni/a</foreign> was taken up
						with the festival of the Carneia, and it was traditional among Dorians that
						war could not be waged in the course of it. See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 4.7.2"
							>Xen. Hell. 4.7.2</bibl>.</note> she has withdrawn her own territory
					from the field of hostilities. She forbids us to place the least trust in
						<placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, although all our allies
					are joining us in making peace; yet she admits that <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>'s treaty with herself, which was
					made without any such support, has been faithfully observed. Again, <placeName
						key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> calls her own peace traditional, but
					forbids the other Greeks to secure a traditional peace for themselves: the
					reason being that she expects to annex <placeName key="perseus,Corinth"
						>Corinth</placeName> by prolonging the war, and after gaining control of the
					state which has always controlled her, she hopes to extend her influence over
					her partners in victory as well. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="28">
				<p>Such are the prospects to which we are committed; and we have a choice between
					two alternatives, that of joining <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
						>Argos</placeName> in fighting <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName>, and that of joining <placeName key="tgn,7002683"
						>Boeotia</placeName> in making common peace with her. Now what alarms me
					above all else, gentlemen, is our old, old fault of invariably abandoning
					powerful friends in preference for weak, and of going to war for the sake of
					others when, as far as we ourselves are concerned, we could perfectly well
					remain at peace. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="29">
				<p>Thus—and it is only by calling the past to mind that one can properly determine
					policy—we began by making a truce with the Great King and establishing a
					permanent accord with him, thanks to the diplomacy of my mother's brother,
					Epilycus, the son of Teisander.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Epilycus is not
						mentioned elsewhere. The last formal peace negotiated between <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7000231"
							>Persia</placeName> had been the Peace of Callias, c. <dateRange
							from="-462" to="-460">462</dateRange>-460 B.C. Andocides may have in
						mind the deputation which was sent to the Persian Court in 424 (<bibl
							n="Thuc. 4.50">Thuc. 4.50</bibl>).</note> But later the king's runaway
					slave, Amorges,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Amorges was the son of a rebel
						satrap of <placeName key="tgn,7016631">Lydia</placeName> named Pissuthnes.
						After the recovery of <placeName key="tgn,7016631">Lydia</placeName> by
						Tissaphernes Amorges took refuge in <placeName key="tgn,7002358"
							>Caria</placeName>. He was given shelter by Iasus, a member of the
						Athenian Confederacy. Iasus was stormed by the Spartans in 412 on the
						instigation of Tissaphernes, and Amorges was handed over to the Persians
							(<bibl n="Thuc. 8.5.5">Thuc. 8.5.5</bibl>).</note> induced us to discard
					the powerful support of his master as worthless. We chose instead what we
					imagined to be a more advantageous understanding with Amorges himself. The king
					in his anger replied by allying himself with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In 413. The sum
						mentioned is an exaggeration. From 413 to 407 Tissaphernes made it a point
						of policy to withhold subsidies from the Spartans as far as possible in
						order to prolong the war and weaken both combatants. In 407 he was
						superseded by Cyrus, who brought with him 500 talents for the improvement of
						the Spartan navy.</note> and furnished her with five thousand talents with
					which to prosecute the war; nor was he satisfied until he had overthrown our
					empire. That is one instance of such policy. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="30">
				<p>Again, an urgent request came to us from <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse"
						>Syracuse</placeName>; she was ready to end our differences by a pact of
					friendship, to end war by peace; and she pointed out the advantages of an
					alliance with herself, if only we would consent to it, over those of the
					existing alliance with Segesta and <placeName key="perseus,Catana"
						>Catana</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> had formed an alliance with
						Segesta as early as 453 (I.G. i 2 . 19-20). It was renewed in 424 by Laches.
						In 416 Segesta found herself ranged against the combined forces of
							<placeName key="perseus,Selinus">Selinus</placeName> and <placeName
							key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>. She appealed to <placeName
							key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> for help, and the disastrous
						Syracusan expedition resulted.</note> But once more we chose war instead of
					peace, Segesta instead of <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse"
					>Syracuse</placeName>; instead of staying at home as the allies of <placeName
						key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, we chose to send an armament to
						<placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>. The result was the loss of
					a large part of the Athenian and allied forces, the bravest being the first to
					fall; a reckless waste of ships, money, and resources: and the return of the
					survivors in disgrace. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="31">
				<p>Later,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Actually in 419. Andocides is thinking of
						Alcibiades' descent on <placeName key="perseus,Epidauros"
							>Epidaurus</placeName> in support of the Argives, who had already
						invaded her territory by land. The expedition was made in virtue of the
						alliance of the previous year between <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>,
							<placeName key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName>, and <placeName
							key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName>.</note> the same Argives who
					are here today to persuade us to continue the war, induced us to arouse
						<placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>'s anger by making a naval
					descent upon <placeName key="tgn,7002745">Laconia</placeName> while at peace
					with her, an act which was responsible for endless disasters; from it sprang a
					war which ended with our being forced to demolish our walls, to surrender our
					fleet, and to restore our exiles. Yet what help did we receive in our
					misfortunes from Argos who had drawn us into the war? What danger did she brave
					for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>? </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="32">
				<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Today, then, it remains for us to choose war
					instead of peace once again, the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName>
					instead of the Boeotian alliance, the present masters of <placeName
						key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> instead of <placeName
						key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. Gentlemen, I trust that no one will
					induce us to choose such a course. The examples furnished by our past mistakes
					are enough to prevent men of sense from repeating them. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="33">
				<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A number of you are extremely anxious to see peace
					concluded as quickly as possible. In fact, according to those in question, the
					forty days allowed you for consideration are a waste of time and a concession
					which we delegates have done wrong to obtain, as the one object of our being
					sent to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> with full powers was
					to avoid any further reference of the matter to the Assembly. Our desire to
					secure our position by such a reference they call nervousness, since no one,
					they argue, has ever yet saved the Athenian people by open persuasion: measures
					for its good must be secret or disguised. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="34">
				<p>Now I cannot praise this reasoning. I admit, gentlemen, that in time of war a
					patriotic and experienced general should employ secrecy or deception in leading
					the majority of men into danger; but when a peace to include the entire nation
					is being negotiated, an agreement to which sworn assent will be given and which
					will be recorded on public monuments, I deny that the negotiators should
					practise secrecy or deception. I maintain that we deserve praise much more than
					blame, if, in spite of our full powers of discretion, we still refer the
					question to you for consideration. Decisions should be reached with all the
					caution possible; then, once we have made our sworn compact, we should abide by
					it. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="35">
				<p>As delegates, we must be guided not only by your written instructions, but by
					your character, gentlemen. You have a way of suspecting and being dissatisfied
					with a thing if you can have it: while if there is anything which you have not,
					you airily talk as though it lay ready to your hand. If it is your duty to go to
					war, you want peace; if peace is arranged for you, you count up the benefits
					which war has brought you. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="36">
				<p>Thus there are those who are already complaining that they cannot see the meaning
					of the treaty, if it is walls and ships which <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
						>Athens</placeName> is to recover. They are not recovering their own private
					property from abroad: and walls cannot feed them. This objection also requires
					an answer. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="37">
				<p>There was once a time, gentlemen, when we had no walls or fleet: but it was when
					we acquired them that our prosperity began. If you have a similar desire for
					prosperity today, then make sure of your walls and your ships. It was with them
					that our forefathers started; and, partly by persuasion, partly by stealth,
					partly by bribery, and partly by force, they won for <placeName
						key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> a greater empire than any other
					state has ever gained. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="38">
				<p>Persuasion we used in arranging that Hellenotamiae should be appointed at
						<placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to control the joint
						funds,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">According to Thucydides (<bibl
							n="Thuc. 1.96">Thuc. 1.96</bibl>) the Hellenotamiae were Athenian
						officials from the very start. But the evidence of the Quota-lists rather
						indicates that the office first became purely Athenian in 454, after the
						transference of the treasury of the League from <placeName
							key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName>.</note> that the allied fleet should assemble in our
					own harbor, and that such states as possessed no ships should be supplied with
					them by us: stealth in building our walls unknown to the Peloponnesians<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Apparently a reference to the famous trick of
						Themistocles when rebuilding the walls of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
							>Athens</placeName> in the winter of 479 (<bibl n="Thuc. 1.90">Thuc.
							1.90</bibl>). Thucydides, however, does not suggest that there was any
						danger of war from <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> in
						consequence.</note>: bribery in purchasing <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName>'s acquiescence: and force in crushing our enemies; thus
					it was that we built up an empire over the whole nation. All these successes
					were achieved in eighty-five years.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e.
						between 490 and 405, Marathon and <placeName key="tgn,6000070"
							>Aegospotami</placeName>.</note>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="39">
				<p>Then came defeat; and not only did we lose our empire: our walls and our fleet
					were also seized as securities by <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
						>Sparta</placeName>. The fleet she confiscated, and the walls she
					demolished, to prevent our using them as the foundations of a fresh Athenian
					dominion. Thanks to the efforts of us delegates, representatives have today come
					from <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> with full powers,
					offering to restore those securities to us, to concede us our walls and our
					fleet, and to recognize the islands as ours. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="40">
				<p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now although we hold the very same key to
					prosperity as our forefathers, it is maintained by some that we must not
					acquiesce in this peace. Let such critics come forward in person, then, —we have
					ourselves made it possible for them to do so by securing a further forty days
					for discussion—and let them tell you on the one hand whether any of the clauses
					drafted is undesirable: if it is, it can be excised; on the other hand, if
					anyone wishes to make any additions, let him gain your approval and make them.
					If you accept all the clauses drafted, you can live in peace. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="41">
				<p>If you are satisfied with none of them, war is inevitable. The decision rests
					entirely with you, gentlemen; make your choice. Argives and Corinthians are here
					to show you that war is preferable: while Spartans have come to gain your
					consent to a peace. The final word in the matter rests with you instead of with
					Sparta—thanks to us. Thus we delegates are making delegates of you all; every
					man of you who is about to raise his hand to vote is a delegate whose business
					is peace and war, no matter which he prefers. So bear in mind all that I have
					said, gentlemen: and vote for that alternative which will never cause you
					regrets.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
