<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Aphobus 3 </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>If I were not conscious, men of the jury, that in a former suit against Aphobus I
                    had readily (so absolutely manifest were his wrongdoings) convicted him of lies
                    greater and more outrageous than these which he now utters, I should have grave
                    doubts of my ability to show how he seeks to lead you astray in regard to each
                    one of them. As it is, however (be it said with the favor of heaven), if you
                    prove fair and impartial hearers, I have strong hopes that you will become as
                    fully aware of the shamelessness of this man as were the jurors in the former
                    trial. If the case required eloquence or cleverness I should shrink through
                    distrust of my youth; but, as matters are, I need merely point out and rehearse
                    to you what the plaintiff's conduct toward us has been. From this it will be
                    easy, I think, for all of you to determine which of us is the villain. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I know that the plaintiff has instituted this
                    suit, not because he believes he can convict anyone of having borne false
                    witness against him, but because he thinks that the large amount of damages
                    which he was condemned to pay will give rise to a feeling of prejudice against
                    me, and of compassion toward himself. For this reason he is now seeking to
                    defend himself against charges made in a suit that has already been decided,
                    regarding which he had at the time no reasonable defence to make. I, for my
                    part, men of the jury, if I had proceeded to execute the judgement against him
                    and had been unwilling to make any reasonable concession, should even so have
                    done no wrong in exacting the damages awarded by your decision; but for all that
                    it might have been said that I had shown undue ruthlessness and enmity toward a
                    man who is a relative in depriving him of all his property. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>But, as it is, the precise contrary is the truth. This man with his co-trustees
                    has robbed me of my entire patrimony, and, even after being clearly convicted in
                    your court, he does not consider himself obliged to do anything reasonable. On
                    the contrary he has dispersed his property, giving his farm-buildings to Aesius
                    and his farm to Onetor, against whom he has forced me to engage in a troublesome
                    lawsuit. He himself stripped the house of its furniture, took away the slaves,
                    destroyed the wine-vat, tore off the doors, and all but set fire to the house
                    itself; then he made off to <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>,
                    where he has settled and paid the alien's tax. You would, therefore, with better
                    ground loathe this man for deeds like these, than judge me guilty of undue
                    severity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>Regarding the rapacity and vile character of the plaintiff I purpose to speak at
                    length before you later on, though what you have even now heard gives you a fair
                    idea of it. But I shall now undertake to show you, that the testimony which has
                    been given, about which you are going to cast your votes, is true. But one
                    request I make of you, men of the jury, and it is a reasonable one—that you will
                    give us both a fair hearing. This is as much in your interest as in mine, for
                    the more accurate your knowledge of the facts, the more just and in harmony with
                    your oaths will be the vote you will cast regarding them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>I shall show that Aphobus has not only acknowledged
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> to be a freeman, but has
                    even proved it by his actions; that, furthermore, about this matter he has
                    declined the absolutely sure test by torture,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >On the high value attributed by the Greeks to evidence extracted from a
                        slave by torture see <bibl n="Dem. 30.37">Dem. 30.37</bibl>, and <bibl
                            n="Aristot. Rh. 1.15">Aristot. Rh. 1.15</bibl></note> and does not wish
                    to have the truth brought to light that on the contrary he has recourse to
                    trickery, brings forward false witnesses, and by his own words distorts the
                    truth regarding what has taken place. So strong and so plain is the evidence by
                    which I shall prove these statements that you will all see clearly that it is I
                    who am speaking the truth, and that he has uttered not a word worthy of
                    credence. I shall begin at a point which will make it easiest for you to learn
                    the facts, and for me to instruct you regarding them in the briefest time. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>I instituted suit, men of the jury, against Demophon, Therippides and the
                    plaintiff for breach of trust in their guardianship, for I had been defrauded by
                    them of all my inheritance. When my suit against Aphobus in the first instance
                    came up for trial, I proved clearly to the jury, as I shall prove to you, that
                    he, in conjunction with the others, had robbed me of all the property that had
                    been left me; and I relied upon no false testimony. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>Here is a clear proof of this. A host of depositions was read at the trial, some
                    of the deponents declaring that they had given to the plaintiff property of
                    mine, others that he had received such property in their presence, still others
                    that they had purchased goods from him, and paid him the price; yet he has
                    charged not a single one of these with bearing false testimony. He has dared to
                    attack this one piece of testimony, and it alone, although in it he cannot show
                    that there was mention even of one single drachma. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>And yet for the computation of the sums of which I had been robbed, I relied not
                    so much on this man's testimony, for there was no mention of money in it, but on
                    the several statements of the others, against whom the plaintiff has made no
                    charges. Therefore the jurymen who at that time heard my plea, not only found
                    him guilty, but fixed the damages at the full amount stated in my complaint. Why
                    was it, then, that he passed over the other witnesses and sued the defendant
                    alone? I will tell you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>In regard to all the witnesses who testified that he had received the money, he
                    knew that the more discussion there should be over each separate point, the more
                    convincingly would he be convicted of possessing it, and this was bound to be
                    the case in a trial for false witness; for the accusations which I then made
                    along with all the others in a small part of the time allotted me, I should now
                    discuss severally and in detail in the time of an entire speech; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>whereas, if he attacked an answer given, he thought that as he had made an
                    admission before, so now it would be in his power to make a denial.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, in attacking the testimony of the
                        deponent he would deny his own previous admissions.</note> That is the
                    reason why he attacks the testimony of this witness, the truth of whose
                    testimony I mean to prove conclusively to you all, not on the basis of
                    probabilities, or of arguments made up to fit the occasion, but by reasoning
                    which, I am sure, will approve itself to you all as just and fair. Listen, and
                    judge. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>I knew, men of the jury, that I should find the whole contest centring about the
                    deposition inserted in the record, and that it would be regarding the truth or
                    falsehood of this that you would cast your votes, and I therefore determined
                    that the first step for me to take was to offer Aphobus a challenge. What, then,
                    did I do? I offered to surrender to him for examination by torture a slave who
                    knew how to read and write, and who had been present when Aphobus made the
                    admission in question, and who wrote down the statement of the witness. This man
                    had been ordered by me not to use any fraud or trickery, nor to write down some
                    and suppress others of the statements made by the plaintiff regarding the
                    matters at issue, but simply to write the absolute truth, and what Aphobus
                    actually said. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>What better opportunity could he have had of convicting us of falsehood than by
                    putting my slave to torture? But Aphobus knew better than anyone else that the
                    slave had borne true testimony, and therefore he declined the test. And in truth
                    it is not one or two only who know these facts; the challenge was not made in
                    secret, but in the midst of the agora where many were present.Call, please, the
                    witnesses to these facts.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>The fellow is so cunning, and so ready to pretend ignorance of what is right,
                    that, although he is pressing a suit for false witness, and although you are to
                    cast your votes regarding this, and have sworn so to do, he refused the
                    proffered examination by torture in regard to the testimony (the point to which
                    he should have devoted his argument), and declares that he requires the slave to
                    be given up for testing in regard to other matters. In this he is lying. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Is it not indeed monstrous that he should claim that he is being outrageously
                    treated by my refusal of his demand to have delivered to him for torture a
                    freeman (for such I shall conclusively prove
                        <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> to be), and should not
                    consider that my witnesses are being outrageously treated, when I offer him one
                    who is admittedly a slave, to be tested by torture regarding their testimony,
                    and he refuses? For he surely cannot maintain this, that for some matters, which
                    he himself desires, torture is a certain test, and for others not. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, men of the jury, the first witness to give this testimony was
                    Aesius, the brother of the plaintiff. He now denies it, because he has allied
                    himself in the suit with Aphobus; but at that time he gave this testimony along
                    with the other witnesses, for he had no desire to perjure himself, or to suffer
                    the penalty which would straightway follow. Surely now, if I had been getting up
                    false testimony, I should not have put this man in my list of witnesses, seeing
                    that he was more intimate with Aphobus than with anyone else in the world, and
                    knowing that he was going to plead for him in the suit, and that he was an
                    adversary of my own. It is not reasonable that one should call as witness to a
                    false statement one who is an opponent of his own, and a brother of his
                    adversary. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>I have many witnesses to these facts, and circumstantial proofs no fewer in
                    number than the witnesses. In the first place, if he did not in very truth give
                    this testimony, he would not be denying it now, but would have done so at once
                    in the courtroom, when the deposition was read, for it would have answered his
                    purpose better then than now. In the second place Aesius would not have kept
                    quiet, but would have sued me for damages, if without cause I had made him
                    liable to a charge of bearing false witness against his brother, a charge on
                    which men run the risk both of damages in money and the loss of citizenship.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>Again, in seeking to bring the truth of the matter to light, he would have
                    demanded of me the slave who wrote the depositions, in order that, if I refused
                    to give him up, I might seem to have no just ground for my statements. But, as
                    it is, so far from doing anything of the sort, he refused to accept the slave
                    for torture, when I, on his denial that he had given the evidence, offered him.
                    So plain is it that regarding this matter too both he and Aphobus as well were
                    alike unwilling to have recourse to torture. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>To prove that my words are true, that after Aesius had given his testimony with
                    the other witnesses, he made no denial of the fact, when, standing by the
                    plaintiff's side in the courtroom, he heard the deposition read, and that, when
                    I offered the slave to them to be questioned by torture regarding all these
                    matters, he refused to accept the offer—regarding each of these points severally
                    I shall produce witnesses. Please call them here.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>I wish now to set forth to you, men of the jury, what I consider a stronger proof
                    than all those that have been mentioned, to show that the plaintiff did give
                    this answer. When, despite the admissions which he is proved to have made, he
                    demanded of me <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> for torture, I was
                    so eager to show on the spot that this, too, was a subterfuge on his part, that
                    what do you think I did? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>I summoned Aphobus to give evidence against Demo, his uncle and a partner in his
                    crimes. I wrote out the testimony which he now attacks as false and ordered him
                    to make a deposition to it. At first he brazenly refused, but when the
                    arbitrator bade him depose, or deny the fact under oath, he deposed, sorely
                    against his will. And yet if the man was a slave, and had not been already
                    admitted by Aphobus here to be free, what in the world induced him to make this
                    deposition? Why did he not deny it on oath, and so get free of the affair? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Pray note that in regard to this matter also I was ready to give over to him for
                    torture the slave who had written the deposition, who would know his own
                    handwriting, and who clearly remembered that Aphobus had made the deposition. I
                    was ready to do this, not for want of witnesses who were present, for there were
                    some; but in order that he might not accuse these men of giving false testimony,
                    and that the result of the torture might support them. Yet it is not fair to
                    condemn the witnesses on his account. They alone of men who have as yet stood
                    trial before you can show that the plaintiff himself has borne witness to their
                    testimony as to these matters.To prove that I am speaking the truth, take the
                    challenge and the deposition.<quote type="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>Such are the legal tests which he has refused, and so numerous the proofs by
                    which he is shown to be acting with malice and insincerity; yet he demands that
                    you put credence in his own witnesses, and he slanders mine, and declares that
                    their testimony is false.I wish now to speak of the matter on the basis of
                    probabilities. I am certain that you would all agree that those who give false
                    testimony are led to do so by bribes through stress of poverty, or by
                    friendship, or else by enmity toward the opposite party in the suit. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>Now no one of these reasons would have led the men to testify in my favor. Not
                    friendship; how could that be, seeing that they are not engaged in the same
                    pursuits, nor are they of like age, I will not say with me, but with one
                    another? Not enmity against my adversary, that is plain; for one of them is his
                    brother and pleads on his side; Phanus is a close friend and a member of the
                    same tribe; and Philip is neither friend nor enemy, so that this motive, too,
                    cannot be justly charged against them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, no one could say that poverty was the ground, for they all possess
                    means so ample that they willingly assume the expense of public services, and
                    discharge whatever duties are laid upon them. Besides all this, they are well
                    known to you, and you know nothing to their discredit; for they are worthy
                    citizens. Yet, if they are not poor, nor enemies of the plaintiff, nor friends
                    of mine, how can it be right to suspect them of bearing false witness? I
                    certainly do not know. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>My opponent was aware of all this, and knew better than anybody else that their
                    testimony was true, but nonetheless he brings forward a malicious charge against
                    them, and not only declares that he did not make the statement which I have
                    proved in the most conclusive manner that he did make, but even asserts that the
                    man, <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName>, is in fact a slave. I wish
                    in a very few words to prove that in this, too, he is lying. I was ready, men of
                    the jury, regarding this point also to give over to him to be tested by torture
                    my female slaves, who remember that my father on his death-bed set this man
                    free. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>Besides this, my mother was ready to call to her side my sister and myself, and
                    swear, with imprecations on our heads if she spoke falsely—we were her only
                    children, and it was for our sakes that she gave herself up to a life of
                    widowhood—that my father when he was about to die had set this man free, and
                    that <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> was regarded by us as free
                    thereafter. Let no one of you assume that she would have been willing to make
                    this oath with imprecations on our heads if she had not known well that what she
                    was to swear to was true.Come now, to prove that I am speaking the truth and
                    that we were ready to do these things, call the witnesses thereto.<quote
                        type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>So many were the just arguments we had to urge, and so ready were we to have
                    recourse to the most infallible tests regarding the testimony given; and yet the
                    plaintiff evades all these, and fancies that by slandering me regarding the
                    trial which has already taken place, and bringing accusations against me, he can
                    induce you to convict the witness,—a piece of trickery the most unfair and the
                    most rapacious imaginable. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>For he has himself suborned men to bear false witness about these matters, having
                    as co-workers his brother-in-law Onetor, and Timocrates<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Timocrates: possibly the same as the Timocrates against whom
                        Demosthenes delivered <bibl n="Dem. 24">Dem. 24</bibl></note>; we had no
                    forewarning of this, and supposed that the contest would be regarding the
                    deposition alone, and therefore have not come prepared with witnesses regarding
                    the guardianship accounts. Nevertheless, despite the fellow's trickery, I think
                    that, simply by reciting the facts, I shall easily convince you that no man was
                    ever more justly convicted than he. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>It was not because I refused to allow
                        <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> to be put to the torture, nor
                    because he himself admitted the man to be a freeman, nor yet because these
                    witnesses gave their testimony; but because he was proved to have taken
                    possession of large sums belonging to me, and because he did not let the estate,
                    though the laws so ordered and my father had so directed in his will, as I shall
                    plainly show you. For these were things that anyone could see, the laws, namely,
                    and the amount of my property which these men had taken as plunder; but as for
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName>, nobody knew even who he
                    was. You will see from the charges brought against Aphobus that these things are
                    so. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>For, men of the jury, when I instituted my suit against him concerning his
                    guardianship, I did not fix the damages at a lump sum, as one bringing forward a
                    baseless charge out of malice would have done, but specified each item, stating
                    the source of each, the precise amount, and the person from whom it had been
                    received. In no case did I add mention of
                        <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> as having knowledge of any of
                    these matters. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>Hence this is the beginning of the complaint: “Demosthenes makes the following
                    charges against Aphobus. Aphobus has in his possession moneys of mine, received
                    by him in his capacity as guardian, as follows: eighty minae, which he received
                    as the marriage-portion of my mother in accordance with the terms of my father's
                    will.” This is the first of the sums of which I claim to have been defrauded.
                    Now what was the declaration of the witnesses? “That they were present before
                    the arbitrator, Notharchus, when Aphobus admitted that
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> was a freeman, having
                    been emancipated by the father of Demosthenes.” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>Consider now for yourselves whether in your judgement there could be an orator,
                    or sophist or magician so wondrously clever in speaking as by means of this
                    testimony to convince any man on earth that Aphobus is in possession of the
                    marriage-portion of the speaker's mother. What in heaven's name would he say?
                    “Aphobus has admitted that <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> is a
                    freeman.” And why on that account is he any the more in possession of the
                    marriage-portion? The statement would surely not seem to prove it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>But how was it proved? In the first place, Therippides, his co-trustee, testified
                    that he had given him the money. Secondly, Demo, his uncle, and the rest of the
                    witnesses who were present, testified that he agreed to supply my mother with
                    maintenance, as being in possession of her portion. Against these men he has
                    lodged no charges, plainly because he knew that their testimony was true.
                    Besides this, my mother was ready to call to her side my sister and myself, and
                    swear with imprecations on our heads, if she spoke falsely, that Aphobus had
                    received her marriage-portion according to the terms of my father's will. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>Shall we, then, say, or shall we not, that he has possession of these eighty
                    minae? And was it on the evidence of these witnesses here or of those that he
                    was convicted? I think it was on the evidence of truth. He has enjoyed the
                    interest on this sum for ten years, and even though judgement has been given
                    against him, cannot bring himself to pay it back. Despite this, he declares that
                    he has been outrageously treated and that he lost the suit by reason of these
                    witnesses. Yet not one of them testified that he had received the
                    marriage-portion. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>With regard to the maritime loan,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">With reference to these items see <bibl n="Dem. 27">Dem.
                            27</bibl></note> the sofa-makers, and the iron and the ivory that were
                    left me, and my sister's marriage-portion, at the purloining of which Aphobus
                    connived in order to secure for himself the right to take whatever he pleased of
                    my goods, listen, and see how just was the verdict given against him, and how
                    absurd it would have been to examine
                        <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> by torture regarding any of
                    these matters. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>For as regards the purloining of funds at which
                    you connived there is a law which expressly declares that you are responsible
                    for them exactly as if you had them in your own possession. So what has the law
                    to do with the testing of a slave by torture? But in the matter of the maritime
                    loan you made common cause with Xuthus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In the
                        inventory of the estate of the father of Demosthenes, given in <bibl
                            n="Dem. 27">Dem. 27</bibl>, there is mention of a bottomry loan to
                        Xuthus, amounting to seventy minae.</note> divided the money with him, and
                    destroyed the contract, and now that you have arranged everything to suit your
                    wish, and have done away with the documentary evidence (as Demo testified
                    against you), you have recourse to trickery, and endeavor to mislead these
                    gentlemen. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>Regarding the sofa-makers, if you took money, and made large profits for yourself
                    by making loans on security that was mine—you, who should rather have prevented
                    others from doing so—and finally made away with the slaves altogether, what,
                    pray, can the witnesses do in your behalf? These men at any rate have not
                    testified that you admitted lending money on the security of my slaves, and that
                    you appropriated the slaves to yourself. On the contrary, it was you who
                    acknowledged this in your account, and the witnesses testified to the fact
                    against you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now look you, as to the ivory and iron, I have
                    this to say: all the slaves of the household know that the plaintiff used to
                    sell these articles. I am ready now, as I was then, to give over to him any one
                    of these slaves whom he may choose to be examined by torture. If then, he
                    alleges that I refuse to surrender the man who has knowledge of the facts, and
                    offer him others who have no such knowledge, he will but show that he ought all
                    the more to have accepted my offer. For if those whom I offered to him as having
                    knowledge of the facts, declared that he had none of these articles in his
                    possession, he would of course have been acquitted of the charge. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>But nothing of the sort is the truth. It would have been proved past all question
                    that he had sold the goods, and appropriated the profits. Therefore, he passed
                    over those who were admittedly slaves, and demanded that a freeman be examined
                    by torture, whom it would have been a crime for me to surrender; for it was not
                    his purpose that he should sift out the matter, but that he might make a
                    specious argument out of the fact that his demand was refused.Regarding,
                    therefore, all these facts, first the marriage-portion, then his connivance with
                    fraud, then all the rest, there shall be read to you the laws and the
                    depositions, that you may have full knowledge.<quote type="Laws">
                        <title>Laws</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>Not only from the facts already adduced can you see that Aphobus was not in any
                    respect whatever prejudiced by my refusal to give the man up for torture, but
                    also from a consideration of the matter itself. Let us suppose that
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> is being racked upon the
                    wheel, and consider what Aphobus would most wish him to say. Would it not be
                    that he was not aware that the plaintiff had any of the property in his
                    possession? Well, suppose he says so. Does that prove that the plaintiff has
                    none? Far from it; for I produced men who knew, men who paid him the money, men
                    who were present in person, as witnesses. It is convincing proof, not if one is
                    ignorant that a man has something in his possession (for there might be many
                    such), but if one knows that he has it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>But of the many witnesses who testified against you, what one have you sued for
                    false testimony? Tell us. But you cannot. Yet you plainly convict yourself, and
                    prove that you lie when you declare that you have been outrageously treated, and
                    that you lost the suit unjustly, because this man was not given up to you—you
                    who made no charge of giving false testimony against the witnesses who testified
                    that you received and had in your possession the property, concerning which you
                    demanded <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> for torture to prove
                    that it was never left us. If you had really been wronged, it would have been
                    more fitting to proceed against them. But you were not wronged, and are bringing
                    a baseless suit out of malice. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>There are many points from which one may see your rascality, but most of all if
                    one hears how you acted regarding the will. For although my father, men of the
                    jury, wrote a will containing an inventory of all that he left, with
                    instructions for letting the property, this will Aphobus never gave up to me,
                    lest I should learn from it the value of the estate, and admitted possessing
                    only those items which were so well known that he could not deny that he had
                    them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>The will, according to his statement, contained these provisions: that Demophon
                    should at once receive two talents, and should marry my sister when she should
                    come of age (this would be in ten years); that Aphobus himself should have
                    eighty minae with my mother, and the house to live in; and that Therippides
                    should enjoy the interest on seventy minae until I should reach manhood. All the
                    rest of the property left to me apart from these items, and the clause regarding
                    the letting of the estate, he suppressed from the will, not thinking that it was
                    to his interest that these matters should be made known in your court. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>However, since it was admitted by Aphobus himself that my father on his death-bed
                    gave to each of these men such large sums of money, the jurymen at the former
                    trial considered these admissions to be a proof of the size of the estate. For
                    when a man gave out of his estate four talents and three thousand drachmae by
                    way of marriage-portion and legacy, it was plain that he took these sums, not
                    from a small estate, but from one (bequeathed to me) of more than double this
                    amount. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The following passage up to the middle of the
                        section is repeated almost verbatim from <bibl n="Dem. 27.45">Dem.
                            27.45</bibl></note> For it cannot be supposed that he would wish to
                    leave me, his son, in poverty, and be eager further to enrich these men, who
                    were already wealthy. No; it was because of the size of the estate left to me
                    that he gave to Therippides the interest on seventy minae, and to Demophon that
                    on the two talents—though he was not yet to marry my sister. These moneys it has
                    been proved that Aphobus never gave over to me, nor even an amount slightly
                    less. Part of it he said he had spent, part he had never received, part he knew
                    nothing about, part was in the hands of so-and-so, part was in the house, and of
                    part he could say anything except when and where he had paid it over. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>As to his story of money left in the house I shall clearly prove to you that he
                    is lying. This argument he speciously introduced, when it had become clear that
                    the property was large and was unable to show that he had paid it back, in order
                    that it might appear a reasonable inference that I was wrongfully seeking to
                    recover what was already in my possession. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This passage repeats very closely the language
                        of <bibl n="Dem. 27.55">Dem. 27.55-57</bibl></note> If my father had no
                    confidence in these men it is plain that he would neither have entrusted them
                    with the rest of his property, nor, if he had left this money in the way
                    alleged, would he have told them of it. How, then, do they know about it? But,
                    if he had confidence in them, he would not, I take it, have given into their
                    hands the bulk of his property, and not have put them in charge of the rest. Nor
                    would he have entrusted this remainder to my mother to keep and then have
                    pledged her herself in marriage to this man, who was one of the guardians. For
                    it is not reasonable that he should seek to make the money secure through her,
                    and yet put one of the men whom he distrusted in control both of her and of it.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, if there were any truth in all this, do you suppose that Aphobus
                    would not have taken my mother to wife, bequeathed to him as she was by my
                    father? He had already taken her marriage-portion—the eighty minae—as though he
                    were going to marry her; but he subsequently married the daughter of Philonides
                    of Melite, from motives of avarice, in order that, in addition to what he had
                    received from us, he might get from him other eighty minae. But, if there had
                    been four talents in the house, and in her custody, as he alleges, don't you
                    imagine he would have raced to get possession both of her and of them? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>Would he have joined with his co-trustees in so shamefully plundering my visible
                    property, which many of you knew had been left me, and have refrained, when he
                    had the chance, from seizing a fund to the existence of which you would not be
                    able to testify? Who can believe this? It is impossible, men of the jury; it is
                    impossible. No; all the money which my father left was indeed buried on the day
                    on which it came into the hands of these men; and the defendant, not being able
                    to tell when and where he paid back any of it, makes use of these arguments,
                    hoping that I may seem to be a rich man, and so meet with no compassion from
                    you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>I have many other charges to make against him, but I have not the right to speak
                    of the injuries I myself have suffered, when the witness is in danger of losing
                    his civic rights. Still I wish to read to you a challenge, for you will know,
                    when you have heard it, that the testimony was true, and that Aphobus, who now
                    declares that he demands <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> to be
                    examined about all the matters involved in the suit, at first demanded him only
                    in regard to a question of thirty minae; and, furthermore, that he has been put
                    to no disadvantage because of the testimony. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>For I, in my desire to refute him in every particular, and in my attempt to make
                    clear to you his tricks and his villainies, asked him how large the sum was
                    regarding which he demanded to examine
                        <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName>, as one who had knowledge of
                    the facts. To this he replied falsely, that it was in regard to the whole
                    amount. “Well then,” said I, “as to this I will give up to you for examination
                    by torture the slave who has the copy of your challenge to me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>If, when I have given oath that you acknowledged the man to be free, and that you
                    so testified against Demo, you will swear to the contrary with imprecations upon
                    your daughter, I release to you the entire sum, for which you shall be shown by
                    the examination of the slave to have at the first demanded
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName>; and the damages which
                    you were condemned to pay shall be lessened by thus much—that is, by the amount
                    in regard to which you demanded <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName>,
                    to the end that you may be found to have been put to no disadvantage by the
                    witnesses.” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>This challenge I made to him in the presence of many witnesses; but he said he
                    could not accept it. Yet, if a man refused to give this judgement in his own
                    favor, how can it be right for you, who are upon your oaths, to give credence to
                    his words and convict the witnesses, and not rather to regard this man as the
                    most shameless of humankind?To prove that my words are true, call the witnesses
                    to these facts.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>Do not suppose that while I was ready to take this course, the witnesses did not
                    hold the same opinion. No; they too were ready to place their children by their
                    side, and in confirmation of the testimony they had given, to take an oath with
                    imprecations upon them, if they swore falsely. But Aphobus did not see fit to
                    allow an oath to be given either to them or to me. Instead, he rests his case on
                    arguments subtly planned and on witnesses accustomed to perjury, and thinks
                    thereby easily to mislead you. So take and read to the jury this deposition
                        also.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>How could one prove more clearly than I have proved that we are the object of a
                    malicious charge; that the evidence brought forward against my opponent is true;
                    and that his condemnation was just? I have shown that he refused to examine by
                    torture the slave who wrote the testimony regarding the very things to which he
                    had testified; that his brother, Aesius, has attested the facts which he on his
                    part declares to be false; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>that Aphobus himself has, at my summons, given against Demo,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Demo was not actually a trustee, but in <bibl n="Dem. 28.15"
                            >Dem. 28.15</bibl> it is stated that the elder Demosthenes had called
                        him to be present, when, on his death-bed, he had entrusted his affairs and
                        the guardianship of his children to the three named as trustees. He was the
                        father of Demophon, and had very possibly taken part in the management of
                        the trust. Another alternative suggestion is that Demosthenes may have
                        instituted suit against Demo on quite other grounds of which we have no
                        knowledge. This complicated problem is ably discussed by Calhoun,
                            <title>l.c.</title> pp. 88 ff.</note> his uncle and co-trustee, the same
                    testimony as the witnesses whom he is suing; that he refused to examine my
                    women-servants as to the fact of <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName>
                    being a freeman; that my own mother was ready to give an oath regarding these
                    matters with imprecations upon us; that he refused to accept for examination any
                    one of my other slaves who knew all the circumstances better than
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> did; that he has not
                    brought a charge of false witness against any one of those who testified that he
                    had the money; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>that he did not give over the will, nor let the house, although the laws so bade;
                    and finally that he did not see fit to give an oath, after the witnesses and I
                    myself had sworn, whereby he could have secured release to the amount of the
                    sums regarding which he had demanded
                        <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> for torture. By heaven, I
                    certainly could think of no better way than this to establish these facts. Yet,
                    plain as it is that he falsely attacks the witnesses; that he suffers no damage
                    from the facts adduced; that he was justly condemned; he still tries to brazen
                    it out. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>If it were not that he uses his present language after having at the outset been
                    judged to be in the wrong by his own friends and by the arbitrator, there would
                    be less reason to wonder at all this. But the fact is, that after persuading me
                    to refer the matter to Archeneus and Dracontides and Phanus (the last of whom he
                    is now suing on a charge of giving false witness), he rejected them (having
                    heard them say that, if they decided on oath, they would condemn his conduct as
                    guardian), and appeared before the official arbitrator, who, since Aphobus was
                    unable to clear himself from the charges which I brought, gave judgement against
                    him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>The jury, to whom he then appealed, having heard the case, gave the same decision
                    that his own friends and the arbitrator had given, and fixed the damages at ten
                    talents. This was not, heaven knows, because he had admitted
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> to be a freeman (for this
                    was nothing to the point), but because, a fortune of fifteen talents having been
                    left me, he had not let the property; because further, he with his co-trustees
                    had the management of the estate for ten years, and agreed on behalf of me, a
                    child, to pay a property-tax at the rate of five minae,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">See notes <emph>b</emph> and <emph>c</emph> on <bibl
                            n="Dem. 27.7">Dem. 27.7</bibl></note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>the same rate at which Timotheus, son of
                        <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, and those possessing the
                    largest fortunes were assessed; and because, after administering for so long an
                    estate, on which he voluntarily chose to pay so high a tax, he turned over to
                    me, as the amount due from him, property not even of the value of twenty minae,
                    having together with those others robbed me of my whole estate, principal as
                    well as interest. The jurymen, therefore, although they allowed interest on the
                    whole property at the lowest rate, and not that at which estates are ordinarily
                    let, found that these men had robbed me of more than thirty talents, and
                    accordingly fixed the damages against Aphobus at ten talents.</p>
            </div>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
