<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>Aphorisms</title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 20, 2003</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							              <date>1886</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="">English</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng"
              type="translation"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg012.perseus-eng1">
			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="chapter">
				           <head>SECTION I</head>
				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 1</head>
					             <p> Life is short, and Art long; the crisis fleeting; experience perilous, and
						decision difficult. The physician must not only be prepared to do what is
						right himself, but also to make the patient, the attendants, and externals
						cooperate. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 2</head>
					             <p> In disorders of the bowels and vomitings, occurring spontaneously, if the
						matters purged be such as ought to be purged, they do good, and are well
						borne; but if not, the contrary. And so artificial evacuations, if they
						consist of such matters as should be evacuated, do good, and are well borne;
						but if not, the contrary. One, then, ought to look to the country, the
						season, the age, and the diseases in which they are proper or not.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 3</head>
					             <p> In the athletae, embonpoint, if carried to its utmost limit, is dangerous,
						for they cannot remain in the same state nor be stationary; and since, then,
						they can neither remain stationary nor improve, it only remains for them to
						get worse; for these reasons the embonpoint should be reduced without delay,
						that the body may again have a commencement of reparation. Neither should
						the evacuations, in their case, be carried to an extreme, for this also is
						dangerous, but only to such a point as the person's constitution can endure.
						In like manner, medicinal evacuations, if carried to an extreme, are
						dangerous; and again, a restorative course, if in the extreme, is
						dangerous.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 4</head>
					             <p> A slender restricted diet is always dangerous in chronic diseases, and also
						in acute diseases, where it is not requisite. And again, a diet brought to
						the extreme point of attenuation is<pb n="p.300"/> dangerous; and repletion,
						when in the extreme, is also dangerous. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 5</head>
					             <p>In a restricted diet, patients who transgress are thereby more hurt (than in
						any other?); for every such transgression, whatever it may be, is followed
						by greater consequences than in a diet somewhat more generous. On this
						account, a very slender, regulated, and restricted diet is dangerous to
						persons in health, because they bear transgressions of it more difficultly.
						For this reason, a slender and restricted diet is generally more dangerous
						than one a little more liberal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 6</head>
					             <p>For extreme diseases, extreme methods of cure, as to restriction, are most
						suitable. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 7</head>
					             <p>When the disease is very acute, it is attended with extremely severe symptoms
						in its first stage; and therefore an extremely attenuating diet must be
						used. When this is not the case, but it is allowable to give a more generous
						diet, we may depart as far from the severity of regimen as the disease, by
						its mildness, is removed from the extreme. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 8</head>
					             <p>When the disease is at its height, it will then be necessary to use the most
						slender diet. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 9</head>
					             <p>We must form a particular judgment of the patient, whether he will support
						the diet until the acme of the disease, and whether he will sink previously
						and not support the diet, or the disease will give way previously, and
						become less acute. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 10</head>
					             <p>In those cases, then, which attain their acme speedily, a restricted diet
						should be enjoined at first; but in those cases which reach their acme
						later, we must retrench at that period or a little before it; but previously
						we must allow a more generous diet to support the patient. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 11</head>
					             <p>We must retrench during paroxysms, for to exhibit food would be injurious.
						And in all diseases having periodical paroxysms, we must restrict during the
						paroxysms. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 12</head>
					             <p>The exacerbations and remissions will be indicated by the diseases, the
						seasons of the year, the reciprocation of the periods, whether they occur
						every day, every alternate day, or after a longer period, and by the
						supervening symptoms; as, for example, in pleuritic cases, expectoration, if
						it occur at the commencement, shortens the attack, but if it appear later,
						it prolongs the same; <pb n="p.301"/>and in the same manner the urine, and
						alvine discharges, and sweats, according as they appear along with favorable
						or unfavorable symptoms, indicate diseases of a short or long duration. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 13</head>
					             <p>Old persons endure fasting most easily; next, adults; young persons not
						nearly so well; and most especially infants, and of them such as are of a
						particularly lively spirit. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 14</head>
					             <p>Growing bodies have the most innate heat; they therefore require the most
						food, for otherwise their bodies are wasted. In old persons the heat is
						feeble, and therefore they require little fuel, as it were, to the flame,
						for it would be extinguished by much. On this account, also, fevers in old
						persons are not equally acute, because their bodies are cold. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 15</head>
					             <p>In winter and spring the bowels are naturally the hottest, and the sleep most
						prolonged; at these seasons, then, the most sustenance is to be
						administered; for as the belly has then most innate heat, it stands in need
						of most food. The well-known facts with regard to young persons and the
						athletae prove this. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 16</head>
					             <p>A humid regimen is befitting in all febrile diseases, and particularly in
						children, and others accustomed to live on such a diet. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 17</head>
					             <p>We must consider, also, in which cases food is to be given once or twice a
						day, and in greater or smaller quantities, and at intervals. Something must
						be conceded to habit, to season, to country, and to age. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 18</head>
					             <p>Invalids bear food worst during summer and autumn, most easily in winter, and
						next in spring. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 19</head>
					             <p>Neither give nor enjoin anything to persons during periodical paroxysms, but
						abstract from the accustomed allowance before the crisis. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 20</head>
					             <p>When things are at the crisis, or when they have just passed it, neither move
						the bowels, nor make any innovation in the treatment, either as regards
						purgatives or any other such stimulants, but let things alone. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 21</head>
					             <p>Those things which require to be evacuated should be evacuated, wherever they
						most tend, by the proper outlets. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 22</head>
					             <p>We must purge and move such humors as are concocted, not such as are
						unconcocted, unless they are struggling to get out, which is mostly not the
						case. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 23</head>
					             <p>The evacuations are to be judged of not by their quantity, <pb n="p.302"/>but
						whether they be such as they should be, and how they are borne. And when
						proper to carry the evacuation to <hi rend="ital">deliquium animi</hi>, this
						also should be done, provided the patient can support it. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 24</head>
					             <p>Use purgative medicines sparingly in acute diseases, and at the commencement,
						and not without proper circumspection. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 25</head>
					             <p>If the matters which are purged be such as should be purged, the evacuation
						is beneficial, and easily borne; but, not withstanding, if otherwise, with
						difficulty. </p>
				           </div>
			         </div>


			         <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="chapter">
				           <head>SECTION II</head>

				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 1</head>
					             <p>In whatever disease sleep is laborious, it is a deadly symptom; but if sleep
						does good, it is not deadly. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 2</head>
					             <p>When sleep puts an end to delirium, it is a good symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 3</head>
					             <p>Both sleep and insomnolency, when immoderate, are bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 4</head>
					             <p>Neither repletion, nor fasting, nor anything else, is good when more than
						natural. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 5</head>
					             <p>Spontaneous lassitude indicates disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 6</head>
					             <p>Persons who have a painful affection in any part of the body, and are in a
						great measure sensible of the pain, are disordered in intellect. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 7</head>
					             <p>Those bodies which have been slowly emaciated should be slowly recruited; and
						those which have been quickly emaciated should be quickly recruited. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 8</head>
					             <p>When a person after a disease takes food, but does not improve in strength,
						it indicates that the body uses more food than is proper; but if this happen
						when he does not take food, it is to be understood evacuation is required.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 9</head>
					             <p>When one wishes to purge, he should put the body into a fluent state. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 10</head>
					             <p>Bodies not properly cleansed, the more you nourish the more you injure. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 11</head>
					             <p>It is easier to fill up with drink than with food. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 12</head>
					             <p>What remains in diseases after the crisis is apt to produce relapses. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 13</head>
					             <p>Persons in whom a crisis takes place pass the night preced-<pb n="p.303"/>ing
						the paroxysm uncomfortably, but the succeeding night generally more
						comfortably. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 14</head>
					             <p>In fluxes of the bowels, a change of the dejections does good, unless the
						change be of a bad character. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 15</head>
					             <p>When the throat is diseased, or tubercles (<hi rend="ital">phymata</hi>) form
						on the body, attention must paid to the secretions; for if they be bilious,
						the disease affects the general system; but if they resemble those of a
						healthy person, it is safe to give nourishing food. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 16</head>
					             <p>When in a state of hunger, one ought not to undertake labor. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 17</head>
					             <p>When more food than is proper has been taken, it occasions disease; this is
						shown by the treatment. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 18</head>
					             <p>From food which proves nourishing to the body either immediately or shortly,
						the dejections also are immediate. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 19</head>
					             <p>In acute diseases it is not quite safe to prognosticate either death or
						recovery. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 20</head>
					             <p>Those who have watery discharges from their bowels when young have dry when
						they are old; and those who have dry discharges when they are young will
						have watery when they are old. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 21</head>
					             <p>Drinking strong wine cures hunger. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 22</head>
					             <p>Diseases which arise from repletion are cured by depletion; and those that
						arise from depletion are cured by repletion; and in general, diseases are
						cured by their contraries. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 23</head>
					             <p>Acute disease come to a crisis in fourteen days. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 24</head>
					             <p>The fourth day is indicative of the seventh; the eighth is the commencement
						of the second week; and hence, the eleventh being the fourth of the second
						week, is also indicative; and again, the seventeenth is indicative, as being
						the fourth from the fourteenth, and the seventh from the eleventh. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 25</head>
					             <p>The summer quartans are, for the most part, of short duration; but the
						autumnal are protracted, especially those occurring near the approach of
						winter. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 26</head>
					             <p>It is better that a fever succeed to a convulsion, than a convulsion to a
							fever.<pb n="p.304"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 27</head>
					             <p>We should not trust ameliorations in diseases when they are not regular, nor
						be much afraid of bad symptoms which occur in an irregular form; for such
						are commonly inconstant, and do not usually continue, nor have any duration.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 28</head>
					             <p>In fevers which are not altogether slight, it is a bad symptom for the body
						to remain without any diminution of bulk, or to be wasted beyond measure;
						for the one state indicates a protracted disease, and the other weakness of
						body. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 29</head>
					             <p>If it appear that evacuations are required, they should be made at the
						commencement of diseases; at the acme it is better to be quiet. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 30</head>
					             <p>Toward the commencement and end of diseases all the symptoms are weaker, and
						toward the acme they are stronger. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 31</head>
					             <p>When a person who is recovering from a disease has a good appetite, but his
						body does not improve in condition, it is a bad symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="32" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 32</head>
					             <p>For the most part, all persons in ill health, who have a good appetite at the
						commencement, but do not improve, have a bad appetite again toward the end;
						whereas, those who have a very bad appetite at the commencement, and
						afterward acquire a good appetite, get better off. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="33" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 33</head>
					             <p>In every disease it is a good sign when the patient's intellect is sound, and
						he is disposed to take whatever food is offered to him; but the contrary is
						bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="34" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 34</head>
					             <p>In diseases, there is less danger when the disease is one to which the
						patient's constitution, habit, age, and the season are allied, than when it
						is one to which they are not allied. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="35" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 35</head>
					             <p>In all diseases it is better that the umbilical and hypogastric regions
						preserve their fullness; and it is a bad sign when they are very slender and
						emaciated; in the latter case it is dangerous to administer purgatives. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="36" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 36</head>
					             <p>Persons in good health quickly lose their strength by taking purgative
						medicines, or using bad food. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="37" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 37</head>
					             <p>Purgative medicines agree ill with persons in good health. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="38" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 38</head>
					             <p>An article of food or drink which is slightly worse, but more palatable, is
						to be preferred to such as are better but less palatable.<pb n="p.305"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="39" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 39</head>
					             <p>Old have fewer complaints than young; but those chronic diseases which do
						befall them generally never leave them. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="40" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 40</head>
					             <p>Catarrhs and coryza in very old people are not concocted. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="41" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 41</head>
					             <p>Persons who have had frequent and severe attacks of swooning, without any
						manifest cause, die suddenly. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="42" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 42</head>
					             <p>It is impossible to remove a strong attack of apoplexy, and not easy to
						remove a weak attack. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="43" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 43</head>
					             <p>Of persons who have been suspended by the neck, and are in a state of
						insensibility, but not quite dead, those do not recover who have foam at the
						mouth. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="44" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 44</head>
					             <p>Persons who are naturally very fat are apt to die earlier than those who are
						slender. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="45" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 2</head>
					             <p>Epilepsy in young persons is most frequently removed by changes of air, of
						country, and of modes of life. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="46" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 46</head>
					             <p>Of two pains occurring together, not in the same part of the body, the
						stronger weakens the other. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="47" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 47</head>
					             <p>Pains and fevers occur rather at the formation of pus than when it is already
						formed. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="48" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 48</head>
					             <p>In every movement of the body, whenever one begins to endure pain, it will be
						relieved by rest. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="49" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 49</head>
					             <p>Those who are accustomed to endure habitual labors, although they be weak or
						old, bear them better than strong and young persons who have not been so
						accustomed. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="50" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 50</head>
					             <p>Those things which one has been accustomed to for a long time, although worse
						than things which one is not accustomed to, usually give less disturbance;
						but a change must sometimes be made to things one is not accustomed to. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="51" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 51</head>
					             <p>To evacuate, fill up, heat, cool, or otherwise, move the body in any way much
						and suddenly, is dangerous; and whatever is excessive is inimical to nature;
						but whatever is done by little and little is safe, more especially when a
						transition is made from one thing to another. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="52" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 52</head>
					             <p> When doing everything according to indications, although things may not turn
						out agreeably to indication, we should not change to another while the
						original appearances remain. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="53" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 53</head>
					             <p>Those persons who have watery discharges from the bowels <pb n="p.306"/>when
						they are young, come off better than those who have dry; but in old age they
						come off worse, for the bowels in aged persons are usually dried up. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="54" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 54</head>
					             <p>Largeness of person in youth is noble and not unbecoming; but in old age it
						is inconvenient, and worse than a smaller structure.</p>
				           </div>
			         </div>

			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="chapter">
				           <head>SECTION III</head>

				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 1</head>
					             <p>The changes of the season mostly engender diseases, and in the seasons great
						changes either of heat or of cold, and the rest agreeably to the same rule.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 2</head>
					             <p>Of natures (<hi rend="ital">temperaments?</hi>), some are well- or
						ill-adapted for summer, and some for winter. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 3</head>
					             <p>Of diseases and ages, certain of them are well- or ill-adapted to different
						seasons, places, and kinds of diet. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 4</head>
					             <p>In the seasons, when during the same day there is at one time heat and at
						another time cold, the diseases of autumn may be expected. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 5</head>
					             <p>South winds induce dullness of hearing, dimness of visions, heaviness of the
						head, torpor, and languor; when these prevail, such symptoms occur in
						diseases. But if the north wind prevail, coughs, affections of the throat,
						hardness of the bowels, dysuria attended with rigors, and pains of the sides
						and breast occur. When this wind prevails, all such symptoms may be expected
						in diseases. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 6</head>
					             <p>When summer is like spring, much sweating may be expected in fevers. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 7</head>
					             <p>Acute diseases occur in droughts; and if the summer be particularly such,
						according to the constitution which it has given to the year, for the most
						part such diseases maybe expected. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 8</head>
					             <p>In seasons which are regular, and furnish the productions of the season at
						the seasonable time, the diseases are regular, and come readily to a crisis;
						but in inconstant seasons, the diseases are irregular, and come to a crisis
						with difficulty. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 9</head>
					             <p>In autumn, diseases are most acute, and most mortal, on the whole. The spring
						is most healthy, and least mortal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 10</head>
					             <p>Autumn is a bad season for persons in consumption. <pb n="p.307"/>
                  </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 11</head>
					             <p>With regard to the seasons, if the winter be of a dry and northerly
						character, and the spring rainy and southerly, in summer there will
						necessarily be acute fevers, ophthalmies, and dysenteries, especially in
						women, and in men of a humid temperament. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 12</head>
					             <p>If the but the spring dry and northerly, women whose term of delivery should
						be in spring, have abortions from any slight cause; and those who reach
						their full time, bring forth children who are feeble, and diseased, so that
						they either die presently, or, if they live, are puny and unhealthy. Other
						people are subject to dysenteries and ophthalmies, and old men to catarrhs,
						which quickly cut them off. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 13</head>
					             <p>If the summer be dry and northerly and the autumn rainy and southerly,
						headaches occur in winter, with coughs, hoarsenesses, coryzae, and in some
						cases consumptions. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 14</head>
					             <p>But if the autumn be northerly and dry, it agrees well with persons of a
						humid temperament, and with women; but others will be subject to dry
						ophthalmies, acute fevers, coryzae, and in some cases melancholy. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 15</head>
					             <p>Of the constitutions of the year, the dry, upon the whole, are more healthy
						than the rainy, and attended with less mortality. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 16</head>
					             <p>The diseases which occur most frequently in rainy seasons are, protracted
						fevers, fluxes of the bowels, mortifications, epilepsies, apoplexies, and
						quinsies; and in dry, consumptive diseases, ophthalmies, arthritic diseases,
						stranguries, and dysenteries. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 17</head>
					             <p>With regard to the states of the weather which continue but for a day, that
						which is northerly, braces the body, giving it tone, agility, and color,
						improves the sense of hearing, dries up the bowels, pinches the eyes, and
						aggravates any previous pain which may have been seated in the chest. But
						the southerly relaxes the body, and renders it humid, brings on dullness of
						hearing, heaviness of the head, and vertigo, impairs the movements of the
						eyes and the whole body, and renders the alvine discharges watery. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 18</head>
					             <p>With regard to the seasons, in spring and in the commencement of summer,
						children and those next to them in age are most <pb n="p.308"/>comfortable,
						and enjoy best health; in summer and during a certain portion of autumn, old
						people; during the remainder of the autumn and in winter, those of the
						intermediate ages. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 19</head>
					             <p>All diseases occur at all seasons of the year, but certain of them are more
						apt to occur and be exacerbated at certain seasons. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 20</head>
					             <p>The diseases of spring are, maniacal, melancholic, and epileptic disorders,
						bloody flux, quinsy, coryza, hoarseness, cough, leprosy, lichen alphos,
						exanthemata mostly ending in ulcerations, tubercles, and arthritic diseases.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 21</head>
					             <p> Of summer, certain of these, and continued, ardent, and tertian fevers, most
						especially vomiting, diarrhoea, ophthalmy, pains of the ears, ulcerations of
						the mouth, mortifications of the privy parts, and the sudamina. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 22</head>
					             <p>Of autumn, most of the summer, quartan, and irregular fevers, enlarged
						spleen, dropsy, phthisis, strangury, lientery, dysentery, sciatica, quinsy,
						asthma, ileus, epilepsy, maniacal and melancholic disorders. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 23</head>
					             <p>Of winter, pleurisy, pneumonia, coryza, hoarseness, cough, pains of the
						chest, pains of the ribs and loins, headache, vertigo, and apoplexy. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 24</head>
					             <p>In the different ages the following complaints occur: to little and new-born
						children, aphthae, vomiting, coughs, sleeplessness, frights inflammation of
						the navel, watery discharges from the ears. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 25</head>
					             <p>At the approach of dentition, pruritus of the gums, fevers, convulsions,
						diarrhoea, especially when cutting the canine teeth, and in those who are
						particularly fat, and have constipated bowels. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 26</head>
					             <p>To persons somewhat older, affections of the tonsils, incurvation of the
						spine at the vertebra next the occiput, asthma, calculus, round worms,
						ascarides, acrochordon, satyriasmus, struma, and other tubercles (phymata),
						but especially the aforesaid. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 27</head>
					             <p>To persons of a more advanced age, and now on the verge of manhood, the most
						of these diseases, and, moreover, more chronic fevers, and epistaxis.<pb n="p.309"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 28</head>
					             <p>Young people for the most part have a crisis in their complaints, some in
						forty days, some in seven months, some in seven years, some at the approach
						to puberty; and such complaints of children as remain, and do not pass away
						about puberty, or in females about the commencement of menstruation, usually
						become chronic. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 29</head>
					             <p>To persons past boyhood, haemoptysis, phthisis, acute fevers, epilepsy, and
						other diseases, but especially the aforementioned. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 30</head>
					             <p>To persons beyond that age, asthma, pleurisy, pneumonia, lethargy, phrenitis,
						ardent fevers, chronic diarrhoea, cholera, dysentery, lientery, hemorrhoids.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 31</head>
					             <p>To old people dyspnoea, catarrhs accompanied with coughs, dysuria, pains of
						the joints, nephritis, vertigo, apoplexy, cachexia, pruritus of the whole
						body, insomnolency, defluxions of the bowels, of the eyes, and of the nose,
						dimness of sight, cataract (glaucoma), and dullness of hearing.</p>
				           </div>
			         </div>

			         <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="chapter">
				           <head>SECTION IV</head>

				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 1</head>
					             <p>We must purge pregnant women, if matters be turgid (in a state of orgasm?),
						from the fourth to the seventh month, but less freely in the latter; in the
						first and last stages of pregnancy it should be avoided. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 2</head>
					             <p>In purging we should bring away such matters from the body as it would be
						advantageous had they come away spontaneously; but those of an opposite
						character should be stopped. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 3</head>
					             <p>If the matters which are purged be such as should be purged, it is beneficial
						and well borne; but if the contrary, with difficulty. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 4</head>
					             <p>We should rather purge upward in summer, and downward in winter. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 5</head>
					             <p>About the time of the dog-days, and before it, the administration of
						purgatives is unsuitable. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 6</head>
					             <p>Lean persons who are easily made to vomit should be purged upward, avoiding
						the winter season. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 7</head>
					             <p>Persons who are difficult to vomit, and are moderately fat, should be purged
						downward, avoiding the summer season. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 8</head>
					             <p>We must be guarded in purging phthisical persons upward. <pb n="p.310"/>
                  </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 9</head>
					             <p>And from the same mode of reasoning, applying the opposite rule to
						melancholic persons, we must purge them freely downward. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 10</head>
					             <p>In very acute diseases, if matters be in a state of orgasm, we may purge on
						the first day, for it is a bad thing to procrastinate in such cases. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 11</head>
					             <p>Those cases in which there are tormina, pains about the umbilicus, and pains
						about the loins, not removed either by purgative medicines or otherwise,
						usually terminate in dry dropsy. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 12</head>
					             <p>It is a bad thing to purge upward in winter persons whose bowels are in a
						state of lientery. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 13</head>
					             <p>Persons who are not easily purged upward by the hellebores, should have their
						bodies moistened by plenty of food and rest before taking the draught. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 14</head>
					             <p>When one takes a draught of hellebore, one should be made to move more about,
						and indulge less in sleep and repose. Sailing on the sea shows that motion
						disorders the body. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 15</head>
					             <p>When you wish the hellebore to act more, move the body, and when to stop, let
						the patient get sleep and rest. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 16</head>
					             <p>Hellebore is dangerous to persons whose flesh is sound, for it induces
						convulsion. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 17</head>
					             <p>Anorexia, heartburn, vertigo, and a bitter taste of the mouth, in a person
						free from fever, indicate the want of purging upward. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 18</head>
					             <p>Pains seated above the diaphragm indicate purging upward, and those below it,
						downward. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 19</head>
					             <p>Persons who have no thirst while under the action of a purgative medicine, do
						not cease from being purged until they become thirsty. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 20</head>
					             <p>If persons free from fever be seized with tormina, heaviness of the knees,
						and pains of the loins, this indicates that purging downward is required.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 21</head>
					             <p>Alvine dejections which are black, like blood, taking place spontaneously,
						either with or without fever, are very bad; and the more numerous and
						unfavorable the colors, so much the worse; when with medicine it is better,
						and a variety of colors in this case is not bad. <pb n="p.311"/>
                  </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 22</head>
					             <p>When black bile is evacuated in the beginning of any disease whatever, either
						upward or downward, it is a mortal symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 23</head>
					             <p>In persons attenuated from any disease, whether acute or chronic, or from
						wounds, or any other cause, if there be a discharge either of black bile, or
						resembling black blood, they die on the following day. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 24</head>
					             <p>Dysentery, if it commence with black bile, is mortal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 25</head>
					             <p>Blood discharged upward, whatever be its character, is a bad symptom, but
						downward it is (more?) favorable, and so also black dejections. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 26</head>
					             <p>If in a person ill of dysentery, substances resembling flesh be discharged
						from the bowels, it is a mortal symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 27</head>
					             <p>In whatever cases of fever there is a copious hemorrhage from whatever
						channel, the bowels are in a loose state during convalescence. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 28</head>
					             <p>In all cases whatever, bilious discharges cease if deafness supervenes, and
						in all cases deafness ceases when bilious discharges supervene. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 29</head>
					             <p>Rigors which occur on the sixth day have a difficult crisis. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 30</head>
					             <p>Diseases attended with paroxysms, if at the same hour that the fever leaves
						it return again next day, are of difficult crisis. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 31</head>
					             <p>In febrile diseases attended with a sense of lassitude, deposits form about
						the joints, and especially those of the jaws. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="32" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 32</head>
					             <p>In convalescents from diseases, if any part be pained, there deposits are
						formed. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="33" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 33</head>
					             <p>But if any part be in a painful state previous to the illness, there the
						disease fixes. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="34" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 34</head>
					             <p>If a person laboring under a fever, without any swelling in the fauces, be
						seized with a sense of suffocation suddenly, it is a mortal symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="35" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 35</head>
					             <p>If in a person with fever, the become suddenly distorted, and he cannot
						swallow unless with difficulty, although no swelling be present, it is a
						mortal symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="36" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 36</head>
					             <p> Sweats, in febrile diseases, are favorable, if they set in on the third,
						fifth, seventh, ninth, eleventh, fourteenth, seventeenth, twenty-first,
						twenty-seventh, and thirty-fourth day, for these <pb n="p.312"/>sweats prove
						a crisis to the disease; but sweats not occurring thus, indicate pain, a
						protracted disease, and relapses. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="37" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 37</head>
					             <p>Cold sweats occurring with an acute fever, indicate death; and along with a
						milder one, a protracted disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="38" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 38</head>
					             <p>And in whatever part of the body there is a sweat, it shows that the disease
						is seated there. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="39" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 39</head>
					             <p>And in whatever part of the body heat or cold is seated, there is disease.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="40" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 40</head>
					             <p>And wherever there are changes in the whole body, and if the body be
						alternately cold and hot, or if one color succeed another, this indicates a
						protracted disease.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="41" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 41</head>
					             <p>A copious sweat after sleep occuring without any manifest cause, indicates
						that the body is using too much food. But if it occur when one is not taking
						food, it indicates that evacuation is required. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="42" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 42</head>
					             <p>A copious sweat, whether hot or cold, flowing continuously, indicates, the
						cold a greater, and the hot a lesser disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="43" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 43</head>
					             <p>Fevers, not of the intermittent type, which are exacerbated on the third day,
						are dangerous; but if they intermit in any form, this indicates that they
						are not dangerous. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="44" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 44</head>
					             <p>In cases attended with protracted fevers, tubercles (<hi rend="ital">phymata</hi>) or pains occur about the joints. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="45" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 45</head>
					             <p>When tubercles (<hi rend="ital">phymata</hi>) or pains attack the joints
						after fevers, such persons are using too much food. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="46" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 46</head>
					             <p>If in a fever not of the intermittent type a rigor seize a person already
						much debilitated, it is mortal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="47" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 47</head>
					             <p>In fevers not of the intermittent type, expectorations which are livid
						bloody, fetid and bilious, are all bad; but if evacuated properly, they are
						favorable. So it is with the alvine evacuations and the urine. But if none
						of the proper excretions take place by these channels, it is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="48" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 48</head>
					             <p>In fevers not of the intermittent type, if the external parts be cold, but
						the internal be burnt up, and if there be thirst, it is a mortal
						symptom.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="49" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 49</head>
					             <p>In a fever not of the intermittent type, if a lip, an eye-brow, an eye, or
						the nose, be distorted; or if there be loss of sight or <pb n="p.313"/>of
						hearing, and the patient be in a weak state-whatever of these symptoms
						occur, death is at hand. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="50" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 50</head>
					             <p>Apostemes in fevers which are not resolved at the first crisis, indicate a
						protracted disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="51" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 51</head>
					             <p>When in a fever not of the intermittent type dyspnoea and delirium come on,
						the case is mortal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="52" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 52</head>
					             <p>When persons in fevers, or in other illnesses, shed tears voluntarily, it is
						nothing out of place; but when they shed tears involuntarily, it is more so.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="53" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 53</head>
					             <p>In whatever cases of fever very viscid concretions form about the teeth, the
						fevers turn out to be particularly strong. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="54" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 54</head>
					             <p>In whatever case of ardent fever dry coughs of a tickling nature with slight
						expectoration are long protracted, there is usually not much thirst. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="55" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 55</head>
					             <p>All fevers complicated with buboes are bad, except ephemerals. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="56" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 56</head>
					             <p>Sweat supervening in a case of the fever ceasing, is bad, for the disease is
						protracted, and it indicates more copious humors. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="57" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 57</head>
					             <p>Fever supervening in a case of confirmed spasm, or of tetanus, removes the
						disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="58" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 58</head>
					             <p>A rigor supervening in a case of ardent fever, produces resolution of it.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="59" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 59</head>
					             <p>A true tertian comes to a crisis in seven periods at furthest. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="60" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 60</head>
					             <p>When in fevers there is deafness, if blood run from the nostrils, or the
						bowels become disordered, it carries off the disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="61" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 61</head>
					             <p>In a febrile complaint, if the fever do not leave on the odd days, it
						relapses. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="62" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 62</head>
					             <p>When jaundice supervenes in fevers before the seventh day, it a bad symptom,
						unless there be watery discharges from the bowels. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="63" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 63</head>
					             <p>In whatever cases of fever rigors occur during the day, the fevers come to a
						resolution during the day. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="64" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 64</head>
					             <p>When in cases of fever jaundice occurs on the seventh, the ninth, the
						eleventh, or the fourteenth day, it is a good symp-<pb n="p.314"/>tom,
						provided the hypochondriac region be not hard. Otherwise it is not a good
						symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="65" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 65</head>
					             <p>A strong heat about the stomach and cardialgia are bad symptoms in fevers.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="66" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 66</head>
					             <p>In acute fevers, spasms, and strong pains about the bowels are bad symptoms.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="67" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 67</head>
					             <p>In fevers, frights after sleep, or convulsions, are a bad symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="68" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 68</head>
					             <p>In fevers, a stoppage of the respiration is a bad symptom, for it indicates
						convulsions. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="68" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 68</head>
					             <p>When the urine is thick, grumoss, and scanty in cases not free from fever a
						copious discharge of thinner urine proves beneficial. Such a discharge more
						commonly takes place when the urine has had a sediment from the first, or
						soon after the commencement. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="70" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 70</head>
					             <p>When in fevers the urine is turbid, like that of a beast of burden, in such a
						case there either is or will be headache. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="71" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 71</head>
					             <p>In cases which come to a crisis on the seventh day, the urine has a red
						nubecula on the fourth day, and the other symptoms accordingly. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="72" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 72</head>
					             <p>When the urine is transparent and white, it is bad; it appears principally in
						cases of phrenitis. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="73" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 73</head>
					             <p>When the hypochondriac region is affected with meteorism and borborygmi,
						should pain of the loins supervene, the bowels get into a loose and watery
						state, unless there be an eruption of flatus or a copious evacuation of
						urine. These things occur in fevers. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="74" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 74</head>
					             <p>When there is reason to expect that an abscess will form in joints, the
						abscess is carried off by a copious discharge of urine, which is thick, and
						becomes white, like what begins to form in certain cases of quartan fever,
						attended with a sense of lassitude. It is also speedily carried off by a
						hemorrhage from the nose. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="75" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 75</head>
					             <p>Blood or pus in the urine indicates ulceration either of the kidneys or of
						the bladder. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="76" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 76</head>
					             <p>When small fleshy substances like hairs are discharged along with thick
						urine, these substances come from the kidneys. <pb n="p.315"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="77" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 77</head>
					             <p>In those cases where there are furfuraceous particles discharged along with
						thick urine, there is scabies of the bladder. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="78" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 78</head>
					             <p>In those cases where there is a spontaneous discharge of bloody urine, it
						indicates rupture of a small vein in the kidneys. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="79" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 79</head>
					             <p>In those cases where there is a sandy sediment in the urine, there is
						calculus in the bladder (or kidneys). </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="80" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 80</head>
					             <p>If a patient pass blood and clots in his urine, and have strangury, and if a
						pain seize the hypogastric region and perineum, the parts about the bladder
						are affected. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="81" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 81</head>
					             <p>If a patient pass blood, pus, and scales, in the urine, and if it have a
						heavy smell, ulceration of the bladder is indicated. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="82" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 82</head>
					             <p>When tubercles form in the urethra, if these suppurate and burst, there is
						relief. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="83" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 83</head>
					             <p>When much urine is passed during the night, it indicates that the alvine
						evacuations are scanty.</p>
				           </div>
			         </div>

			         <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="chapter">
				           <head>SECTION V</head>

				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 1</head>
					             <p>A spasm from taking hellebore is of a fatal nature. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 2</head>
					             <p>Spasm supervening on a wound is fatal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 3</head>
					             <p>A convulsion, or hiccup, supervening on a copious discharge of blood is bad.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 4</head>
					             <p>A convulsion, or hiccup, supervening upon hypercatharsis is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 5</head>
					             <p>If a drunken person suddenly lose his speech, he will die convulsed, unless
						fever come on, or he recover his speech at the time when the consequences of
						a debauch pass off. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 6</head>
					             <p>Such persons as are seized with tetanus die within four days, or if they pass
						these they recover. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 7</head>
					             <p>Those cases of epilepsy which come on before puberty may undergo a change;
						but those which come on after twenty-five years of age, for the most part
						terminate in death. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 8</head>
					             <p>In pleuritic affections, when the disease is not purged off in fourteen days,
						it usually terminates in empyema. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 9</head>
					             <p>Phthisis most commonly occurs between the ages of eighteen and thirty-five
						years. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 10</head>
					             <p>Persons who escape an attack of quinsy, and when the <pb n="p.316"/>disease
						is turned upon the lungs, die in seven days; or if they pass these they
						become affected with empyema. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 11</head>
					             <p>In persons affected with phthisis, if the sputa which they cough up have a
						heavy smell when poured upon coals, and if the hairs of the head fall off,
						the case will prove fatal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 12</head>
					             <p>Phthisical persons, the hairs of whose head fall off, die if diarrhoea set
						in. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 13</head>
					             <p>In persons who cough up frothy blood, the discharge of it comes from the
						lungs. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 14</head>
					             <p>Diarrhoea attacking a person affected with phthisis is a mortal symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 15</head>
					             <p>Persons who become affected with empyema after pleurisy, if they get clear of
						it in forty days from the breaking of it, escape the disease; but if not, it
						passes into phthisis. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 16</head>
					             <p>Heat produces the following bad effects on those who use it frequently:
						enervation of the fleshy parts, impotence of the nerves, torpor of the
						understanding, hemorrhages, deliquia, and, along with these, death. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 17</head>
					             <p>Cold induces convulsions, tetanus, mortification, and febrile rigors. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 18</head>
					             <p>Cold is inimical to the bones, the teeth, the nerves, the brain, and the
						spinal marrow, but heat is beneficial. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 19</head>
					             <p>Such parts as have been congealed should be heated, except where there either
						is a hemorrhage, or one is expected. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 20</head>
					             <p>Cold pinches ulcers, hardens the skin, occasions pain which does not end in
						suppuration, blackens, produces febrile rigors, convulsions, and tetanus.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 21</head>
					             <p>In the case of a muscular youth having tetanus without a wound, during the
						midst of summer, it sometimes happens that the allusion of a large quantity
						of cold water recalls the heat. Heat relieves these diseases. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 22</head>
					             <p>Heat is suppurative, but not in all kinds of sores, but when it is, it
						furnishes the greatest test of their being free from danger. It softens the
						skin, makes it thin, removes pain, soothes rigor, convulsions, and tetanus.
						It removes affections of the head, and heaviness of it. It is particularly
						efficacious in fractures of the bones, especially of those which have been
						exposed, and most <pb n="p.317"/>especially in wounds of the head, and in
						mortifications and ulcers from cold; in herpes exedens, of the anus, the
						privy parts, the womb, the bladder, in all these cases heat is agreeable,
						and brings matters to a crisis; but cold is prejudicial, and does mischief.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 23</head>
					             <p>Cold water is to be applied in the following cases; when there is a
						hemorrhage, or when it is expected, but not applied <hi rend="ital">to</hi>
						the spot, but <hi rend="ital">around</hi> the spot whence the blood flows;
						and in inflammations and inflammatory affections, inclining to a red and
						subsaguineous color, and consisting of fresh blood, in these cases it is to
						be applied but it occasions mortification in old cases; and in erysipelas
						not attended with ulceration, as it proves injurious to erysipelas when
						ulcerated. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 24</head>
					             <p>Cold things, such as snow and ice, are inimical to the chest, being
						provocative of coughs, of discharges of blood, and of catarrhs. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 25</head>
					             <p>Swellings and pains in the joints, ulceration, those of a gouty nature, and
						sprains, are generally improved by a copious affusion of cold water, which
						reduces the swelling, and removes the pain; for a moderate degree of
						numbness removes pain. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 26</head>
					             <p>The lightest water is that which is quickly heated and quickly cooled. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 27</head>
					             <p>When persons have intense thirst, it is a good thing if they can sleep off
						the desire of drinking. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 28</head>
					             <p>Fumigation with aromatics promotes menstruation, and would be useful in many
						other cases, if it did not occasion heaviness of the head. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 29</head>
					             <p>Women in a state of pregnancy may be purged, if there be any urgent necessity
							(<hi rend="ital">or</hi>, if the humors be in a state of orgasm?), from
						the fourth to the seventh month, but less so in the latter case. In the
						first and last periods it must be avoided. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 30</head>
					             <p>It proves fatal to a woman in a state of pregnancy, if she be seized with any
						of the acute diseases. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 31</head>
					             <p>If a woman with child be bled, she will have an abortion, and this will be
						the more likely to happen, the larger the foetus. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="32" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 32</head>
					             <p>Haemoptysis in a woman is removed by an eruption of the menses. <pb n="p.318"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="33" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 33</head>
					             <p>In a woman when there is a stoppage the menses, a discharge of blood from the
						nose is good. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="34" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 34</head>
					             <p>When a pregnant woman has a violent diarrhoea, there is danger of her
						miscarrying. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="35" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 35</head>
					             <p>Sneezing occurring to a woman affected with hysterics, and in difficult
						labor, is a good symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="36" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 36</head>
					             <p>When the menstrual discharge is of a bad color and irregular, it indicates
						that the woman stands in need of purging. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="37" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 37</head>
					             <p>In a pregnant woman, if the breasts suddenly lose their fullness, she has a
						miscarriage. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="38" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 38</head>
					             <p>If, in a woman pregnant with twins, either of her breasts lose its fullness,
						she will part with one of her children; and if it be the right breast which
						becomes slender, it will be the male child, or if the left, the female. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="39" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 39</head>
					             <p>If a woman who is not with child, nor has brought forth, have milk, her
						menses are obstructed. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="40" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 40</head>
					             <p>In women, blood collected in the breasts indicates madness. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="41" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 41</head>
					             <p>If you wish to ascertain if a woman be with child, give her hydromel to drink
						when she is going to sleep, and has not taken supper, and if she be seized
						with tormina in the belly, she is with child, but otherwise she is not
						pregnant. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="42" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 42</head>
					             <p>A woman with child, if it be a male, has a good color, but if a female, she
						has a bad color. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="43" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 43</head>
					             <p>If erysipelas of the womb seize a woman with child, it will probably prove
						fatal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="44" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 44</head>
					             <p>Women who are very lean, have miscarriages when they prove with child, until
						they get into better condition. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="45" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 45</head>
					             <p>When women, in a moderate condition of body, miscarry in the second or third
						month, without any obvious cause, their cotyledones are filled with
						mucosity, and cannot support the weight of the foetus, but are broken
						asunder. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="46" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 46</head>
					             <p>Such women as are immoderately fat, and do not prove with child, in them it
						is because the epiploon (<hi rend="ital">fat?</hi>) blocks up the mouth of
						the womb, and until it be reduced, they do not conceive. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="47" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 47</head>
					             <p>If the portion of the uterus seated near the hip-joint suppurate, it gets
						into a state requiring to be treated with tents. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="48" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 48</head>
					             <p>The male foetus is usually seated in the right, and the female in the left
						side. <pb n="p.319"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="49" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 49</head>
					             <p>To procure the expulsion of the secundines, apply a sternutatory, and shut
						the nostrils and mouth. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="50" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 50</head>
					             <p>If you wish to stop the menses in a woman, apply as large a cupping
						instrument as possible to the breasts. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="51" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 51</head>
					             <p>When women are with child, the mouth of their womb is closed. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="52" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 52</head>
					             <p>If in a woman with child, much milk flow from the breasts, it indicates that
						the foetus is weak; but if the breasts be firm, it indicates that the foetus
						is in a more healthy state. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="53" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 53</head>
					             <p>In women that are about to miscarry, the breasts become slender; but if again
						they become hard, there will be pain, either in the breasts, or in the
						hip-joints, or in the eyes, or in the knees, and they will not miscarry.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="54" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 54</head>
					             <p>When the mouth of the uterus is hard, it is also necessarily shut. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="55" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 55</head>
					             <p>Women with child who are seized with fevers, and who are greatly emaciated,
						without any (other?) obvious cause, have difficult and dangerous labors, and
						if they miscarry, they are in danger. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="56" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 56</head>
					             <p>In the female flux (<hi rend="ital">immoderate menstruation?</hi>), if
						convulsion and deliquium come on, it is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="57" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 57</head>
					             <p>When the menses are excessive, diseases take place, and when the menses are
						stopped, diseases from the uterus take place. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="58" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 58</head>
					             <p>Strangury supervenes upon inflammation of the rectum, and of the womb, and
						strangury supervenes upon suppuration of the kidney, and hiccup upon
						inflammation of the liver. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="59" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 59</head>
					             <p>If a woman do not conceive, and wish to ascertain whether she can conceive,
						having wrapped her up in blankets, fumigate below, and if it appear that the
						scent passes through the body to the nostrils and mouth, know that of
						herself she is not unfruitful. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="60" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 60</head>
					             <p>If woman with a child have her courses, it is impossible that the child can
						be healthy. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="61" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 61</head>
					             <p>If a woman's courses be suppressed, and neither rigor nor fever has followed,
						but she has been affected with nausea, you may reckon her to be with child.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="62" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 62</head>
					             <p>Women who have the uterus cold and dense (<hi rend="ital">compact?</hi>) do
						not conceive; and those also who have the uterus humid, do not conceive, for
						the semen is extinguished, and in women whose <pb n="p.320"/>uterus is very
						dry, and very hot, the semen is lost from the want of food; but women whose
						uterus is in an intermediate state between these temperaments prove fertile.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="63" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 63</head>
					             <p>And in like manner with respect to males; for either, owing to the laxity of
						the body, the pneuma is dissipated outwardly, so as not to propel the semen,
						or, owing to its density, the fluid (<hi rend="ital">semen?</hi>) does not
						pass outwardly; or, owing to coldness, it is not heated so as to collect in
						its proper place (<hi rend="ital">seminal vessels?</hi>), or, owing to its
						heat, the very same thing happens. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="64" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 64</head>
					             <p>It is a bad thing to give milk to persons having headache, and it is also bad
						to give it in fevers, and to persons whose hypochondria are swelled up, and
						troubled with borborygmi, and to thirsty persons; it is bad also, when given
						to those who have bilious discharges in acute fevers, and to those who have
						copious discharges of blood; but it is suitable in phthisical cases, when
						not attended with very much fever; it is also to be given in fevers of a
						chronic and weak nature, when none of the aforementioned symptoms are
						present, and the patients are excessively emaciated. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="65" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 65</head>
					             <p>When swellings appear on wounds, such cases are not likely to be attacked
						either with convulsions, or delirium, but when these disappear suddenly, if
						situated behind, spasms and tetanus supervene, and if before, mania, acute
						pains of the sides, or suppurations, or dysentery, if the swellings be
						rather red. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="66" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 66</head>
					             <p>When no swelling appears on severe and bad wounds, it is a great evil. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="67" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 67</head>
					             <p>In such cases, the soft are favorable; and crude, unfavorable. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="68" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 68</head>
					             <p>When a person is pained in the back part of the head, he is benefited by
						having the straight vein in the forehead opened. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="69" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 69</head>
					             <p>Rigors commence in women, especially at the loins, and spread by the back to
						the head; and in men also, rather in the posterior than the anterior side of
						the body, as from the arms and thighs; the skin there is rare, as is obvious
						from the growth of hair on them. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="70" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 70</head>
					             <p>Persons attacked with quartans are not readily attacked with convulsions, or
						if previously attacked with convulsions, they cease if a quartan
							supervene.<pb n="p.321"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="71" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 71</head>
					             <p>In those persons in whom the skin is stretched, and parched and hard, the
						disease terminates without sweats; but in those in whom the skin is loose
						and rare, it terminates with sweats. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="72" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 72</head>
					             <p>Persons disposed to jaundice are not very subject to flatulence.</p>
				           </div>
			         </div>


			         <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="chapter">
				           <head>SECTION VI</head>

				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 1</head>
					             <p>In cases of chronic lientery, acid eructations supervening when there were
						none previously, is a good symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 2</head>
					             <p>Persons whose noses are naturally watery, and their seed watery, have rather
						a deranged state of health; but those in the opposite state, a more
						favorable. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 3</head>
					             <p>In protracted cases of dysentery, loathing of food is a bad symptom, and
						still worse, if along with fever. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 4</head>
					             <p>Ulcers, attended with a falling off of the hair, are mali moris. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 5</head>
					             <p>It deserves to be considered whether the pains in the sides, and in the
						breasts, and in the other parts, differ much from one another. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 6</head>
					             <p>Diseases about the kidneys and bladder are cured with difficulty in old men.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 7</head>
					             <p>Pains occurring about the stomach, the more superficial they are, the more
						slight are they; and the less superficial, the more severe. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 8</head>
					             <p>In dropsical persons, ulcers forming on the body are not easily healed. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 9</head>
					             <p>Broad exanthemata are not very itchy. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 10</head>
					             <p>In a person having a painful spot in the head, with intense cephalalgia, pus
						or water running from the nose, or by the mouth, or at the ears, removes the
						disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 11</head>
					             <p>Hemorrhoids appearing in melancholic and nephritic affections are favorable.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 12</head>
					             <p>When a person has been cured of chronic hemorrhoids, unless one be left,
						there is danger of dropsy or phthisis supervening. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 13</head>
					             <p>Sneezing coming on, in the case of a person afflicted with hiccup, removes
						the hiccup. <pb n="p.322"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 14</head>
					             <p>In a case of dropsy, when the water runs by the veins into the belly, it
						removes the disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 15</head>
					             <p>In confirmed diarrhoea, vomiting, when it comes on spontaneously, removes the
						diarrhoea. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 16</head>
					             <p>A diarrhoea supervening in a confirmed case of pleurisy or pneumonia is bad.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 17</head>
					             <p>It is a good thing in ophthalmy for the patient to be seized with diarrhoea.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 18</head>
					             <p>A severe wound of the bladder, of the brain, of the heart, of the diaphragm,
						of the small intestines, of the stomach, and of the liver, is deadly. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 19</head>
					             <p>When a bone, cartilage, nerve, the slender part of the jaw, or prepuce, are
						cut out, the part is neither restored, nor does it unite. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 20</head>
					             <p>If blood be poured out preternaturally into a cavity, it must necessarily
						become corrupted. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 21</head>
					             <p>In maniacal affections, if varices or hemorrhoids come on, they remove the
						mania. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 22</head>
					             <p>Those ruptures in the back which spread down to the elbows are removed by
						venesection. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 23</head>
					             <p>If a fright or despondency lasts for a long time, it is a melancholic
						affection. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 24</head>
					             <p>If any of the intestines be transfixed, it does not unite. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 25</head>
					             <p>It is not a good sign for an erysipelas spreading outwardly to be determined
						inward; but for it to be determined outward from within is good. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part26</head>
					             <p>In whatever cases of ardent fever tremors occur, they are carried off by a
						delirium. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 27</head>
					             <p>Those cases of empyema or dropsy which are treated by incision or the
						cautery, if the water or pus flow rapidly all at once, certainly prove
						fatal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 28</head>
					             <p>Eunuchs do not take the gout, nor become bald. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 29</head>
					             <p>A woman does not take the gout, unless her menses be stopped. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 30</head>
					             <p>A young man does not take the gout until he indulges in coition. <pb n="p.323"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 31</head>
					             <p>Pains of the eyes are removed by drinking pure wine, or the bath, or a
						fomentation, or venesection, or purging. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="32" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 32</head>
					             <p>Persons whose speech has become impaired are likely to be seized with chronic
						diarrhoea. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="33" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 33</head>
					             <p>Persons having acid eructations are not very apt to be seized with pleurisy.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="34" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 34</head>
					             <p>Persons who have become bald are not subject to large varices; but should
						varices supervene upon persons who are bald, their hair again grows thick.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="35" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 35</head>
					             <p>Hiccup supervening in dropsical cases is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="36" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 36</head>
					             <p>Venesection cures dysuria; open the internal veins of the arm. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="37" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 37</head>
					             <p>It is a good symptom when swelling on the outside of the neck seizes a person
						very ill of quinsy, for the disease is turned outwardly. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="38" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 38</head>
					             <p>It is better not to apply any treatment in cases of occult cancer; for, if
						treated, the patients die quickly; but if not treated, they hold out for a
						long time. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="39" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 39</head>
					             <p>Convulsions take place either from repletion or depletion; and so it is with
						hiccup. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="40" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 40</head>
					             <p>When pains, without inflammation, occur about the hypochondria, in such
						cases, fever supervening removes the pain. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="41" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 41</head>
					             <p>When pus formed anywhere in the body does not point, this is owing to the
						thickness of the part. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="42" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 42</head>
					             <p>In cases of jaundice, it is a bad symptom when the liver becomes indurated.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="43" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 43</head>
					             <p>When persons having large spleens are seized with dysentery, and if the
						dysentery pass into a chronic state, either dropsy or lientery supervenes,
						and they die. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="44" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 44</head>
					             <p>When ileus comes on in a case of strangury, they prove fatal in seven days,
						unless, fever supervening, there be a copious discharge of urine. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="45" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 45</head>
					             <p>When ulcers continue open for a year or upward, there must necessarily be
						exfoliation of bone, and the cicatrices are hollow. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="46" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 46</head>
					             <p>Such persons as become hump-backed from asthma or cough before puberty, die.
							<pb n="p.324"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="47" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 47</head>
					             <p>Persons who are benefited by venesection or purging, should be bled or purged
						in spring. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="48" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 48</head>
					             <p>In enlargement of the spleen, it is a good symptom when dysentery comes on.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="49" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 49</head>
					             <p>In gouty affections, the inflammation subsides in the course of forty days.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="50" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 50</head>
					             <p>When the brain is severely wounded, fever and vomiting of bile necessarily
						supervene. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="51" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 51</head>
					             <p>When persons in good health are suddenly seized with pains in the head, and
						straightway are laid down speechless, and breathe with stertor, they die in
						seven days, unless fever come on. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="52" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 52</head>
					             <p>We must attend to the appearances of the eyes in sleep, as presented from
						below; for if a portion of the white be seen between the closed eyelids, and
						if this be not connected with diarrhaea or severe purging, it is a very bad
						and mortal symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="53" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 53</head>
					             <p>Delirium attended with laughter is less dangerous than delirium attended with
						a serious mood. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="54" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 54</head>
					             <p>In acute diseases, complicated with fever, a moaning respiration is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="55" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 55</head>
					             <p>For the most part, gouty affections rankle in spring and in autumn. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="56" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 56</head>
					             <p>In melancholic affections, determinations of the humor which occasions them
						produce the following diseases; either apoplexy of the whole body, or
						convulsion, or madness, or blindness. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="57" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 57</head>
					             <p>Persons are most subject to apoplexy between the ages of forty and sixty.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="58" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 58</head>
					             <p>If the omentum protrude, it necessarily mortifies and drops off. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="59" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 59</head>
					             <p>In chronic diseases of the hip-joint, if the bone protrude and return again
						into its socket, there is mucosity in the place. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="60" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 60</head>
					             <p>In persons affected with chronic disease of the hip-joint, if the bone
						protrude from its socket, the limb becomes wasted and maimed, unless the
						part be cauterized.</p>
				           </div>
			         </div>

			         <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="chapter">
				           <head>SECTION VII</head>

				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 1</head>
					             <p>In acute diseases, coldness of the extremities is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 2</head>
					             <p>Livid flesh on a diseased bone is bad. <pb n="p.325"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 3</head>
					             <p>Hiccup and redness of the eyes, when they supervene on vomiting, are bad.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 4</head>
					             <p>A chill supervening on a sweat is not good. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 5</head>
					             <p>Dysentery, or dropsy, or ecstacy coming on madness is good. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 6</head>
					             <p>In a very protracted disease, loss of appetite and unmixed discharges from
						the bowels are bad symptoms. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 7</head>
					             <p>A rigor and delirium from excessive drinking are bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 8</head>
					             <p>From the rupture of an internal abscess, prostration of strength, vomiting,
						and deliquium animi result. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 9</head>
					             <p>Delirium or convulsion from a flow of blood is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 10</head>
					             <p>Vomiting, or hiccup, or convulsion, or delirium, in ileus, is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 11</head>
					             <p>Pneumonia coming on pleurisy is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 12</head>
					             <p>Phrenitis along with pneumonia is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 13</head>
					             <p>Convulsion or tetanus, coming upon severe burning, is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 14</head>
					             <p>Stupor or delirium from a blow on the head is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 15</head>
					             <p>From a spitting of blood there is a spitting of pus. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 16</head>
					             <p>From spitting of pus arise phthisis and a flux; and when the sputa are
						stopped, they die. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 17</head>
					             <p>Hiccup in inflammation of the liver bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 18</head>
					             <p>Convulsion or delirium supervening upon insomnolency is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18a" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 18a</head>
					             <p>Trembling upon lethargus is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 19</head>
					             <p>Erysipelas upon exposure of a bone (is bad?). </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 20</head>
					             <p>Mortification or suppuration upon erysipelas is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 21</head>
					             <p>Hemorrhage upon a strong pulsation in wounds is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 22</head>
					             <p>Suppuration upon a protracted pain of the parts about the bowels is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 23</head>
					             <p>Dysentery upon unmixed alvine discharges is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 24</head>
					             <p>Delirium upon division of the cranium, if it penetrate into the cavity of the
						head, is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 25</head>
					             <p>Convulsion upon severe purging is mortal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 26</head>
					             <p>Upon severe pain of the parts about the bowels, coldness of the extremities
						coming on is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 27</head>
					             <p>Tenesmus coming on in a case of pregnancy causes abortion. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 28</head>
					             <p>Whatever piece of bone, cartilage, or nerve (<hi rend="ital">tendon?</hi>) is
						cut off, it neither grows nor unites. <pb n="p.326"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 29</head>
					             <p>When strong diarrhoea supervenes in a case of leucophlegmatia, it removes the
						disease. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 30</head>
					             <p>In those cases in which frothy discharges occur in diarrhoea there are
						defluxions from the head. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 31</head>
					             <p>When there is a farinaceous sediment in the urine during fever, it indicates
						a protracted illness. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="32" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 32</head>
					             <p>In those cases in which the urine is thin at first, and the sediments become
						bilious, an acute disease is indicated. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="33" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 33</head>
					             <p>In those cases in which the urine becomes divided there is great disorder in
						the body. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="34" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 34</head>
					             <p>When bubbles settle on the surface of the urine, they indicate disease of the
						kidneys, and that the complaint will be protracted. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="35" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 35</head>
					             <p>When the scum on the surface is fatty and copious, it indicates acute
						diseases of the kidneys. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="36" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 36</head>
					             <p>Whenever the aforementioned symptoms occur in nephritic diseases, and along
						with them acute pains about the muscles of the back, provided these be
						seated about the external parts, you may expect that there will be an
						abscess; but if the pains be rather about the internal parts, you may also
						rather expect that the abscess will be seated internally. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="37" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 37</head>
					             <p>Haematemesis, without fever, does not prove fatal, but with fever it is bad;
						it is to be treated with refrigerant and styptic things. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="38" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 38</head>
					             <p>Defluxions into the cavity of the chest suppurate in twenty days. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="39" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 39</head>
					             <p>When a patient passes blood and clots, and is seized with strangury and pain
						in the perineum and pubes, disease about the bladder is indicated. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="40" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 40</head>
					             <p>If the tongue suddenly lose its powers, or a part of the body become
						apoplectic, the affection is of a melancholic nature. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="41" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 41</head>
					             <p>In hypercatharsis, of old persons, hiccup supervening is not a good symptom.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="42" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 42</head>
					             <p>In a fever, is not of a bilious nature, a copious allusion of hot water upon
						the head removes the fever. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="43" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 43</head>
					             <p>A woman does not become ambidexterous. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="44" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 44</head>
					             <p>When empyema is treated either by the cautery or incision, <pb n="p.327"/>if
						pure and white pus flow from the wound, the patients recover; but if mixed
						with blood, slimy and fetid, they die. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="45" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 45</head>
					             <p>When abscess of the liver is treated by the cautery or incision, if the pus
						which is discharged be pure and white, the patients recover, (for in this
						case it is situated in the coats of the liver;) but if it resemble the lees
						of oil as it flows, they die. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="46" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 46</head>
					             <p>Pains of the eyes are removed by drinking undiluted wine, plenteous bathing
						with hot water, and venesection. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="47" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 47</head>
					             <p>If a dropsical patient be seized with hiccup the case is hopeless. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="48" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 48</head>
					             <p>Strangury and dysuria are cured by drinking pure wine, and venesection; open
						the vein on the inside. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="49" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 49</head>
					             <p>It is a good sign when swelling and redness on the breast seize a person very
						ill of quinsy, for in this case the disease is diverted outwardly. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="50" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 50</head>
					             <p>When the brain is attacked with sphacelus, the patients die in three days; or
						if they escape these, they recover. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="51" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 51</head>
					             <p>Sneezing arises from the head, owing to the brain being heated, or the cavity
							(<hi rend="ital">ventricle</hi>) in the head being filled with humors;
						the air confined in it then is discharged, and makes a noise, because it
						comes through a narrow passage. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="52" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 52</head>
					             <p>Fever supervening on painful affections of the liver removes the pain. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="53" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 53</head>
					             <p>Those persons to whom it is beneficial to have blood taken from their veins,
						should have it done in spring. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="54" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 54</head>
					             <p>In those cases where phlegm is collected between the diaphragm and the
						stomach, and occasions pain, as not finding a passage into either of the
						cavities, the disease will be carried off if the phlegm be diverted to the
						bladder by the veins. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="55" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 55</head>
					             <p>When the liver is filled with water and bursts into the epiploon, in this
						case the belly is filled with water and the patient dies. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="56" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 56</head>
					             <p>Anxiety, yawning, rigor,-wine drunk with an equal proportion of water,
						removes these complaints. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="57" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 57</head>
					             <p>When tubercles (<hi rend="ital">phymata</hi>) form in the urethra, if they
						suppurate and burst, the pain is carried off. <pb n="p.328"/>
					             </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="58" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 58</head>
					             <p>In cases of concussion of the brain produced by any cause, the patients
						necessarily lose their speech. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="59" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 59</head>
					             <p>In a person affected with fever, when there is no swelling in the fauces,
						should suffocation suddenly come on, and the patient not be able to swallow,
						except with difficulty, it is a mortal symptom. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="59a" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 59a</head>
					             <p>In the case of a person oppressed by fever, if the neck be turned aside, and
						the patient cannot swallow, while there is no swelling in the neck, it is a
						mortal sign. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="60" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 60</head>
					             <p>Fasting should be prescribed the those persons who have humid flesh; for
						fasting dries bodies. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="61" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 61</head>
					             <p>When there are changes in the whole body, and the body becomes sometimes cold
						and sometimes hot, and the color changes, a protracted disease is indicated.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="62" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 62</head>
					             <p>A copious sweat, hot or cold, constantly flowing, indicates a superabundance
						of humidity; we must evacuate then, in a strong person upward, and in a
						weak, downward. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="63" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 63</head>
					             <p>Fevers, not of the intermittent type, if they become exacerbated every third
						day are dangerous; but if they intermit in any form whatever, this shows
						that they are not dangerous. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="64" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 64</head>
					             <p>In cases of protracted fever, either chronic abscesses or pains in the joints
						come on. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="65" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 65</head>
					             <p>When chronic abscesses (<hi rend="ital">phymata</hi>) or pains in the joints
						take place after fevers, the patients are using too much food. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="66" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 66</head>
					             <p>If one give to a person in fever the same food which is given to a person in
						good health, what is strength to the one is disease to the other. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="67" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 67</head>
					             <p>We must look to the urinary evacuations, whether they resemble those of
						persons in health; if not at all so, they are particularly morbid, but if
						they are like those of healthy persons, they are not at all morbid. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="68" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 68</head>
					             <p>When the dejections are allowed to stand and not shaken, and a sediment is
						formed like scrapings (of the bowels), in such a case it is proper to purge
						the bowels; and if you give ptisans before purging, the more you give the
						more harm you will do. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="69" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 69</head>
					             <p>Crude dejections are the product of black bile; if abundant, of more copious,
						and if deficient, of less copious collections of it. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="70" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 70</head>
					             <p>The sputa in fevers, not of an intermittent type, which <pb n="p.329"/>are
						livid, streaked with blood, and fetid, are all bad, it is favorable when
						this evacuation, like the urinary and alvine, passes freely; and whenever
						any discharge is suppressed and not purged off it is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="71" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 71</head>
					             <p>When you wish to purge the body, you must bring it into a state favorable to
						evacuations; and if you wish to dispose it to evacuations upward, you must
						bind the belly; and if you wish to dispose it to evacuations downward, you
						must moisten the belly. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="72" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 72</head>
					             <p>Sleep and watchfulness, both of them, when immoderate, constitute disease.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="73" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 73</head>
					             <p>In fevers which do not intermit, if the external parts be cold, and the
						internal burning hot, and fever prevail, it is a mortal sign. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="74" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 74</head>
					             <p>In a fever which does not intermit, if a lip, the nose, or an eye be
						distorted, if the patient lose his sense of sight or of hearing, while now
						in a weak state,-whatever of these symptoms occurs it is mortal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="75" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 75</head>
					             <p>Upon leucophlegmatia dropsy supervenes. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="76" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 76</head>
					             <p>Upon diarrhoea dysentery. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="77" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 77</head>
					             <p>Upon dysentery lientery. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="78" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 78</head>
					             <p>Upon sphacelus exfoliation of the bone. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="79 and 80" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 79 and 80</head>
					             <p>Upon vomiting of blood consumption, and a purging of pus upward; upon
						consumption a defluxion from the head; upon a defluxion diarrhoea; upon
						diarrhoea a stoppage of the purging upward; upon the stoppage of it death.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="81" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 81</head>
					             <p>In the discharges by the bladder, the belly, and the flesh (<hi rend="ital">the skin?</hi>) if the body has departed slightly from its natural
						condition, the disease is slight; if much, it is great; if very much, it is
						mortal. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="82" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 82</head>
					             <p>Persons above forty years of age who are affected with frenzy, do not readily
						recover; the danger is less when the disease is cognate to the constitution
						and age. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="83" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 83</head>
					             <p>In whatever diseases the eyes weep voluntarily, it is a good symptom, but
						when involuntarily, it is a bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="84" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 84</head>
					             <p>When in quartan fevers blood flows from the nostrils it is a bad symptom.
					</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="85" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 85</head>
					             <p>Sweats are dangerous when they do not occur on critical <pb n="p.330"/>days,
						when they are strong, and quickly forced out of the forehead, either in the
						form of drops or in streams, and if excessively cold and copious; for such a
						sweat must proceed from violence, excess of pain, and prolonged squeezing
							(<hi rend="ital">affliction?</hi>). </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="86" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 86</head>
					             <p>In a chronic disease an excessive flux from the bowels is bad. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="87" subtype="section">
					             <head>Part 87</head>
					             <p>Those diseases which medicines do not cure, iron (<hi rend="ital">the
							knife?</hi>) cures; those which iron cannot cure, fire cures; and those
						which fire cannot cure, are to be reckoned wholly incurable.<pb n="p.331"/>
                  </p>
				           </div>
			         </div>

		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
