<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>For Phormio</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>Phormio's inexperience in speaking,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This is not
                        merely the conventional plea of inexperience (compare <bibl n="Dem. 34.1"
                            >Dem. 34.1</bibl>); Phormio was by now an old man, and further, since he
                        was a manumitted slave, he can have had no training which would equip him
                        for the task, and furthermore, he was, of course, of barbarian birth. His
                        friends, therefore, came to his aid, and one of them speaks in his
                        behalf.</note> and his utter helplessness, you all see for yourselves, men
                    of Athens. It is necessary for us, his friends, to state and set forth for you
                    the facts, which we know full well from having heard him often relate them; in
                    order that, when you have duly learned from us and have come to know the rights
                    of the case, you may give a verdict that is both just and in harmony with your
                    oaths. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>We have put in a special plea in bar of action, not that we may evade the issue
                    and waste time, but that, if the defendant<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        terms “plaintiff” and “defendant,” as used in the translation of this
                        oration, apply to the suit brought against Phormio.</note> shows that he has
                    committed no wrong whatsoever, he may win in your court an acquittal which will
                    be final. For all that in the minds of other people brings about a firm and
                    lasting settlement without engaging in a trial before you— </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>all this Phormio here has done; he has done many kindnesses to this man
                    Apollodorus; he has duly paid and delivered up to the plaintiff everything
                    belonging to him of which he had been left in control, and has since received a
                    discharge from all further claims; nevertheless, as you see, because Phormio can
                    no longer submit to his demands, Apollodorus has instituted this vexatious and
                    baseless suit for twenty talents. From the beginning, therefore, I shall try to
                    set forth for you as briefly as possible all the transactions Phormio has had
                    with Pasio and Apollodorus. From these, I am sure, the malicious conduct of the
                    plaintiff will become clear to you, and at the same time, having heard this
                    recital, you will determine that the action is not maintainable. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>First the clerk shall read to you the articles of agreement, in accordance with
                    which Pasio leased to the defendant the bank and the shield-factory. Take,
                    please, the articles of agreement, the challenge,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">It is not stated precisely what this challenge was; but it
                        may well have been a demand made to Apollodorus to produce the articles in
                        question.</note> and these depositions.<quote n="Articles of Agreement">
                        <title>Articles of Agreement</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>These, men of Athens, are the articles of agreement in accordance with
                    which Pasio leased the bank and the shield-factory to the defendant, after the
                    latter had now become his own master.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">He had
                        been given his freedom by Pasio.</note> But you must hear and understand how
                    it was that Pasio came to owe the eleven talents to the bank. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>He owed that amount, not because of poverty, but because of his thrift.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The word naturally denotes industry, but the
                        clause might possibly be rendered “because he did not wish capital to lie
                        idle”; so Dareste. In <bibl n="Dem. 45.33">Dem. 45.33</bibl>, Apollodorus
                        implies that the debt was due to mismanagement on the part of
                        Phormio.</note> For the real property of Pasio was about twenty talents, but
                    in addition to this he had more than fifty talents in money of his own lent<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">As eleven talents of this money belonged to the
                        bank, this phrase is open to question.</note> out at interest. Among these
                    were eleven talents of the bank's deposits, profitably invested. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>When, therefore, my client leased the business of the bank and took over the
                    deposits, realizing that, if he had not yet obtained the right of citizenship
                    with you, he would be unable to recover the monies which Pasio had lent on the
                    security of land and lodging-houses, he chose to have Pasio himself as debtor
                    for these sums, rather than the others to whom he had lent them. It was for this
                    reason that Pasio was set down as owing eleven talents, as has been stated to
                    you in the depositions.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>In what manner the lease was made, you know from the deposition of the manager of
                    the bank himself. After this, Pasio became ill; and observe how he disposed of
                    his estate. Take the copy of the will, and this challenge, and these depositions
                    made by those in whose custody the will is deposited.<quote n="Will">
                        <title>Will</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>When Pasio had died, after making this will, Phormio, the defendant, took his
                    widow to wife in accordance with the terms of the will and undertook the
                    guardianship of his son.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, of Pasicles,
                        who was a minor. That the guardian should marry the widow was a common
                        provision (so in the case of Demosthenes' own mother; See <bibl n="Dem. 33"
                            >Dem. 33</bibl>). In <bibl n="Dem. 45">Dem. 45</bibl> Apollodorus denies
                        that he had been challenged to produce the will, or that he had been left by
                        his father.</note> Inasmuch, however, as the plaintiff was rapacious, and
                    seemed to think it right that he should spend large sums out of the fund which
                    was as yet undivided, the guardians, calculating in their own minds that, if it
                    should be necessary under the terms of the will to deduct from the undivided
                    fund, share for share, an equivalent of what the plaintiff spent, and then
                    distribute the remainder, there would be nothing left to distribute, determined
                    in the interest of the boy to divide the property. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>And they did distribute all the estate except the property on which the defendant
                    had taken a lease; and of the revenue accruing from this they duly paid one-half
                    to the plaintiff. Up to that time, then, how is it possible for him to make
                    complaint regarding the lease? For it is not now that he should show his
                    indignation; he should at once have done so then. Moreover, he cannot say that
                    he has not received the rents which became due subsequently. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>For in that case, when Pasicles came of age and Phormio relinquished the lease,
                        you<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Addressed to the two brothers,
                        Apollodorus and Pasicles.</note> would never have freed him from all claims,
                    but would then instantly have demanded payment, if he had owed you anything.To
                    prove that I speak the truth in this and that the plaintiff did divide the
                    property with his brother, who was still a minor, and that they released Phormio
                    from his liability under the lease and from all other charges, take this
                        deposition.<quote n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>As soon, then, as they had released the defendant from the lease, men of Athens,
                    they at once divided between them the bank and the shield-factory, and
                    Apollodorus, having the choice,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">By right of
                        seniority.</note> chose the shield-factory in preference to the bank. Yet,
                    if the plaintiff had any private capital in the bank, why in the world should he
                    have chosen the factory by preference? The income was not greater; nay, it was
                    less (the factory produced a talent, and the bank, one hundred minae); nor was
                    the property more agreeable,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, the
                        conduct of a manufacturing business entailed more labor and trouble than the
                        management of a bank.</note> assuming that he had private capital in the
                    bank. But he had no such capital. So the plaintiff was wise in choosing the
                    factory. For that is a property which involves no risk, while the bank is a
                    business yielding a hazardous revenue from money which belongs to others. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Many proofs might one advance and set forth to
                    show that the plaintiff's claim to a sum of banking capital is malicious and
                    baseless. But the strongest proof of all that Phormio received no capital is, I
                    think, this: that Pasio is set down in the lease as debtor to the bank, not as
                    having given banking capital to the defendant. The second proof is that the
                    plaintiff is shown to have made no demands at the time of the distribution of
                    the property. The third is that when he subsequently leased the same business to
                    others for the same sum, he will be shown not to have leased any private capital
                    of his own along with it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>And yet, if he had been defrauded by the defendant of capital which his father
                    left, he would himself on that assumption have had to provide it from some other
                    source and given it to the new lessees.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If it
                        were true that Apollodorus had been defrauded by Phormio of capital which
                        Pasio had invested in the bank, then, when the bank was let to new lessees
                        on the same terms as before, Apollodorus would have had to make up the
                        missing capital from some other source.</note>To prove that I speak the
                    truth in this, and that Apollodorus subsequently leased the bank to Xeno and
                    Euphraeus, and Euphro, and Callistratus, and that he delivered no private
                    capital to them either, but that they leased only the deposits and the right to
                    the profits accruing from them, take, please, the deposition which proves these
                    matters, and proves also that he chose the shield-factory.<quote
                        type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Evidence has been submitted to you, men of Athens, that they<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The plural denotes the two brothers, Apollodorus and
                        Pasicles.</note> granted a lease to these men also, and gave over to them no
                    private banking-capital; and that they gave them their freedom,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">These men would appear to have been slaves originally, and,
                        like Phormio himself, were rewarded with emancipation. The alternative
                        rendering, “freed them from all claims,” seems less probable.</note> as if
                    having received great benefits from them; and at that time they went to law
                    neither with them nor with Phormio. Indeed, as long as his mother was living,
                    who had an accurate knowledge of all these matters, Apollodorus never made any
                    complaint against Phormio, the defendant; but after her death he brought a
                    malicious and baseless suit claiming three thousand drachmae in money, in
                    addition to two thousand drachmae which she had given to Phormio's
                        children,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Children, that is, whom she had
                        borne to Phormio.</note> and a bit of underwear and a serving-girl. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Yet even here he will be shown to have said nothing of the claims which he now
                    makes. He referred the matter for arbitration to the father of his own wife, and
                    the husband of his wife's sister, and to Lysinus and Andromenes,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The two first named represented Apollodorus; the
                        latter two, Phormio.</note> and they induced Phormio to make him a present
                    of the three thousand drachmae and the additional items, and thus to have him as
                    a friend rather than as an enemy because of this. So the plaintiff received in
                    all five thousand drachmae, and going to the temple of Athena,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The Parthenon, as it is stated below to have been on the
                        Acropolis.</note> gave Phormio for the second time a release from all
                    demands. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>Yet, as you see, he is suing him again, having trumped up all sorts of
                    accusations, and gathered from all past time charges (and this is the most
                    outrageous thing of all) which he had never made before. To prove that I am
                    speaking the truth in this, take, please, the award that was made in the
                    Acropolis, and the deposition of those who were present, when Apollodorus, on
                    receiving this money, gave a release from all claims.<quote n="Award">
                        <title>Award</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>You hear the award, men of the jury, which was rendered by Deinias, whose
                    daughter the plaintiff has married, and Nicias, who is husband to her sister.
                    However, even though he has received this money, and has given a release from
                    all claims, he has the audacity to bring suit for so many talents, just as if
                    all these people were dead, or as if the truth would not be brought to light.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>All the dealings, then, and transactions which Phormio has had with Apollodorus
                    you have heard, men of Athens, from the beginning. But I fancy that Apollodorus,
                    the plaintiff, being unable to advance any just grounds in support of his claim,
                    will repeat what he had the audacity to say before the arbitrator, that his
                    mother made away with the papers at Phormio's instigation, and that, owing to
                    the loss of these, he has no way of proving his claim strictly. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>But in regard to these statements and this accusation, observe what convincing
                    proofs one could advance to show that he is lying. In the first place, men of
                    Athens, what man would have accepted a distribution of his inheritance, if he
                    had not papers from which he could determine the amount of estate left him? No
                    man, assuredly. Yet it is eighteen years, Apollodorus, since you accepted the
                    distribution, and you cannot show that you at any time made any complaint about
                    the papers. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>In the second place, when Pasicles had come of age, and was receiving the report
                    of his guardians' administration, what man, even though he shrank from accusing
                    his mother with his own lips of having destroyed the papers, would have failed
                    to reveal the fact to his brother, so that through him it might have been
                    thoroughly investigated? In the third place, what were the papers upon which you
                    based the action which you brought? For the plaintiff has brought suits against
                    many citizens, and has recovered large sums of money, charging in his
                    complaints, “So and so has injured me by not paying back to me the money which
                    my father's papers show he owed the latter at his death.” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>But, if the papers had been made away with, on the basis of what papers did he
                    commence his suits?In proof that I am speaking the truth in this, you have heard
                    the distribution which he accepted, and the evidence in proof of it has been
                    presented to you. The clerk will now read you the depositions having to do with
                    these actions. Please take the depositions.<quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>In these complaints, then, he has admitted that he had received his
                    father's papers; for he surely would not say that he was bringing baseless
                    charges, or that he was suing these men for what they did not owe. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>There are many strong proofs from which one can see that the defendant Phormio is
                    not in the wrong; but the strongest of all, in my opinion, is this: that
                    Pasicles, though he is the brother of Apollodorus, the plaintiff, has neither
                    entered suit nor made any of the charges which the plaintiff makes. But surely
                    the defendant would not have abstained from wronging one who had been left a
                    minor by his father, and over whose property he had control, since he had been
                    left as his guardian, yet would have wronged you, who at your father's death
                    were left a man of four and twenty, and who on your own behalf would easily and
                    immediately have obtained justice, if any wrong had been done you. That is
                    impossible.To prove that I am speaking the truth in this, and that Pasicles
                    makes no complaint, take, please, the deposition regarding the matter.<quote
                        n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>The points which you should now consider in regard to my plea that the action is
                    not admissible, I beg you to recall from what has already been said. We, men of
                    Athens, inasmuch as an accounting had been made and a discharge given from the
                    lease of the bank and of the shield-factory; inasmuch as there had been an
                    arbitrator's award and again a discharge from all claims; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>inasmuch also as the laws do not allow suits to be brought in cases where a
                    discharge has once been given; and inasmuch as the plaintiff makes a baseless
                    and malicious claim, and brings suit contrary to the laws; we have put in a
                    special plea as allowed by the laws that his suit is not admissible. In order,
                    then, that you may understand the matter regarding which you are going to vote,
                    he shall read you this law and the depositions in sequence of those who were
                    present when Apollodorus discharged Phormio from the lease and from all other
                    claims.Take these depositions, please, and the law.<quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>You hear the law, men of Athens, stating other cases in which suit may not be
                    brought, and in particular those in which anyone has given a release or
                        discharge.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The two verbs <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">a)fie/nai</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >a)palla/tein</foreign> seem at times to be virtual synonyms, used
                        freely with the redundancy of legal usage. In some cases, however, <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">a)fie/nai</foreign> refers clearly to the creditor's act,
                        and <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)palla/tein</foreign> to the effect on the
                        debtor. Parallel passages are <bibl n="Dem. 37.1">Dem. 37.1</bibl> and <bibl
                            n="Dem. 37.19">Dem. 37.19</bibl>; and <bibl n="Dem. 38.1">Dem.
                            38.1</bibl>.</note> And with good reason. For if it is just that suit
                    may not be brought again for cases which have once been tried, it is far more
                    just that suit be not allowed for claims in which a discharge has been given.
                    For a man who has lost his suit in your court might perhaps say that you had
                    been deceived; but when a man has plainly decided against himself, by giving a
                    release and discharge, what complaint can he bring against himself that will
                    give him the right to bring suit again regarding the same matters? None
                    whatever, of course. Therefore the man who framed this law placed first among
                    cases in which suit may not be brought all those in which a man has given a
                    release or discharge. Both of these have been given by the plaintiff; for he has
                    released and discharged the defendant. That I am speaking the truth, men of
                    Athens, has been proved to you by the evidence presented. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>Take now, please, the statute of limitations.<quote n="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>The law, men of Athens, has thus clearly defined the time. But this man
                    Apollodorus, when more than twenty years have gone by, demands that you pay more
                    heed to his malicious charges than to the laws in accordance with which you have
                    sworn to give judgement. You should have regard to all the laws, but to this
                    one, men of Athens, above all others. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>For, in my judgement, Solon<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">It was the custom at
                        Athens to emphasize the sanctity of a given law by attributing its enactment
                        to the great lawgiver, Solon. So, in Sparta, laws were conventionally
                        assumed to have been enacted by Lycurgus.</note> framed it for no other
                    purpose than to prevent your having to be subjected to malicious and baseless
                    actions. For in the case of those who were wronged, he thought that a period of
                    five years was enough to enable them to recover what was their due; while the
                    lapse of time would best serve to convict those who advanced false claims. At
                    the same time, since he realized that neither the contracting parties nor the
                    witnesses would live forever, he put the law in their place, that it might be a
                    witness of truth for those who had no other defence. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>I, for my part, am wondering, men of the jury, what in the world the plaintiff,
                    Apollodorus, will try to say in reply to these arguments. For he can hardly have
                    made this assumption that you, although seeing that he has suffered no wrong
                    financially, will be indignant because Phormio has married his mother. For he is
                    not unaware of this—it is no secret to him or to many of you—that Socrates, the
                    well-known banker, having been set free by his masters just as the plaintiff's
                    father had been, gave his wife in marriage to Satyrus who had been his slave.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>Another, Socles, who had been in the banking business, gave his wife in marriage
                    to Timodemus, who is still in being and alive, who had been his slave. And it is
                    not here only, men of Athens, that those engaged in this line of business so
                    act; but in Aegina Strymodorus gave his wife in marriage to Hermaeus, his own
                    slave, and again, after her death, gave him his own daughter.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">It is probable that the word “gave” refers to provisions in
                        the will of Strymodorus. We must then assume that the wife died after the
                        will was made, but before the death of Strymodorus. So Sandys.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>And one could mention many other such cases; and no wonder. For although to you,
                    men of Athens, who are citizens by birth, it would be a disgrace to esteem any
                    conceivable amount of wealth above your honorable descent, yet those who obtain
                    citizenship as a gift either from you or from others, and who in the first
                    instance, thanks to this good fortune, were counted worthy of the same
                    privileges, because of their success in money-making, and their possession of
                    more wealth than others, must hold fast to these advantages. So your father
                    Pasio—and he was neither the first nor the last to do this—without bringing
                    disgrace upon himself or upon you, his sons, but seeing that the only protection
                    for his business was that he should bind the defendant to you by a family tie,
                    for this reason gave to him in marriage his own wife, your mother. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>If, then, you examine his conduct in the light of practical utility you will find
                    that he determined wisely; but if from family pride you scorn Phormio as
                    stepfather, see if it be not absurd for you to speak thus. For, if one were to
                    ask you what sort of a man you deem your father to have been, I am sure that you
                    would say, “an honorable man.” Now, then, which of you two do you think more
                    resembles Pasio in character and in manner of life, yourself or Phormio? I know
                    well that you think Phormio does. Then do you scorn this man who is more like
                    your father than you are yourself, just because he has married your mother? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>But that this arrangement was made by your father's grant and solemn injunction
                    may not only be seen from the will, men of Athens, but you yourself,
                    Apollodorus, are a witness to the fact. For when you claimed the right to
                    distribute your mother's estate share by share—and she had left children by the
                    defendant, Phormio—you then acknowledged that your father had given her with
                    full right, and that she had been married in accordance with the laws. For if
                    Phormio had taken her to wife wrongfully, and no one had given her—then the
                    children were not heirs, and if they were not heirs they had no right of sharing
                    in the property.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Illegitimate children could
                        not inherit; and the fact that Apollodorus recognized the children of
                        Phormio and Archippê as heirs, proves that he admitted the legality of the
                        marriage.</note><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To prove that I am speaking
                    the truth in this evidence has been submitted showing that he received a fourth
                        share<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There were four children: Apollodorus
                        and Pasicles, and the two born of Phormio and Archippê.</note> and gave a
                    release from all claims. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>Having, then, on no single point, men of Athens, any just claim to advance, he
                    had the audacity to make before the arbitrator the most shameless assertions
                    which it is best that you should hear in advance: first that no will was made at
                    all, but that this is a fiction and forgery from beginning to end; and,
                    secondly, that the reason why he had made all these concessions up to now, and
                    had abstained from going to law, was because Phormio was willing to pay him a
                    large rent, and promised that he would do so. But since he does not do this,
                    now, he says, I go to law. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>But that both of these statements, if he makes them, will be false and
                    inconsistent with his own conduct, pray observe from the following
                    considerations. When he denies the will, ask him this, how it came that he
                    received the lodging-house under the will as being the elder.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">A right not often recognized in Attic law. Compare <bibl
                            n="Dem. 39.29">Dem. 39.29</bibl>.</note> He surely will not claim that
                    all the clauses which his father wrote in the will in his favor are valid, and
                    the others invalid. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>And when he says that he was misled by the defendant's promises, remember that we
                    have brought before you as witnesses those who for a long time, after Phormio
                    had given it up, became lessees under the two brothers of the bank and the
                    shield-factory. And yet it was when he granted the lease to these men, that he
                    should at once have made his charges against the defendant if there were any
                    truth in the claims, for which he then gave a release, but for which he now
                    brings suit against him.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To prove that I am
                    speaking the truth that he took the lodging-house under the terms of the will as
                    being the elder, and that he not only thought it right to make no claims against
                    the defendant, but on the contrary praised his conduct, take the
                        deposition.<quote n="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>That you may know, men of Athens, what large sums he has received from the rents
                    and from the debts<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The debts, that is, due to
                        his father.</note>—he, who will presently wail as though he were destitute
                    and had lost everything—hear a brief account from me. This man has collected
                    twenty talents in all owing to debts he has recovered from the papers which his
                    father left, and of these sums more than half he keeps in his possession; for in
                    many instances he is defrauding his brother of his share. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>From the lessee, for the eight years during which Phormio had the bank, he
                    received eighty minae a year, half of the whole rent. These items make ten
                    talents and forty minae.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The rent of the
                        factory was a talent a year, and that of the bank a talent and forty minae,
                        making a total of one hundred and sixty minae annually, or eighty minae
                        apiece for each of the two brothers, or ten talents and forty minae for the
                        eight-year period.</note> For ten years after that, during which they
                    subsequently leased the bank to Xeno and Euphraeus and Euphro and Callistratus,
                    he received a talent every year.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The rents
                        under the new lease remained the same as before, but Apollodorus received
                        only that from the shield-factory, or a talent annually.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>Besides this he has had for about twenty years the income of the property
                    originally divided, of which he himself had charge, more than thirty minae. If
                    you add all these sums together,—what he got from the distribution, what he
                    recovered from the debts, and what he has collected as rent, it will be plain
                    that he has received more than forty talents, to say nothing of the present
                    Phormio made him, and his inheritance from his mother, and what he has had from
                    the bank and does not pay back—two and one-half talents and six hundred
                    drachmae. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>Ah, but, you will tell us, the state has received these sums, and you have been
                    outrageously treated, having used up your fortune in public services! No; what
                    you expended in public service out of the undivided funds, you and your brother
                    expended jointly; and what you gave after that does not amount to the interest,
                    I will not say on two talents, but even on twenty minae. Do not, then, accuse
                    the state, nor say that the state has received that portion of your patrimony
                    which you have shamefully and wickedly squandered. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>That you may know, men of Athens, the amount of property which he has received,
                    and the public services which he has assumed, the clerk shall read to you the
                    items one by one.Please take this list and this challenge and these
                        depositions.<quote n="List">
                        <title>List</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>All these monies he has received; he has debts due him to the value of many
                    talents, which he is collecting, some by voluntary payments, some by bringing
                    action. These debts were owing to Pasio—quite apart from the rent of the bank
                    and the other property which he left;—and these the two brothers have recovered.
                    He has expended upon public services merely what you have heard, the smallest
                    fraction of his income, not to say of his capital; and yet he will assume a
                    bragging air, and will talk about his expenditures for trierarchal and choregic
                        services.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">As a matter of fact Apollodorus
                        had served as trierarch with distinction, and had been most liberal in his
                        expenditures. See <bibl n="Dem. 50.11">Dem. 50.11 ff.</bibl>, and Oration
                            <bibl n="Dem. 45.78">Dem. 45.78</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>I have shown you that these assertions of his will be false; however, even if
                    they should all prove to be true, I think it more honorable and more just that
                    he should continue to render public service from his own funds, than that you
                    should give him the defendant's property, and while receiving yourselves but a
                    small portion of the whole, should see the defendant reduced to extreme poverty,
                    and the plaintiff in wanton insolence and spending his money in the manner that
                    has been his wont.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Contrast with this passage
                        the statements of Apollodorus himself regarding his manner of life in <bibl
                            n="Dem. 45.77">Dem. 45.77</bibl>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>With regard now to Phormio's wealth and his having got it from your father's
                    estate, and the questions you said you were going to ask as to how Phormio
                    acquired his fortune, you have the least right of any man in the world to speak
                    thus. For Pasio, your father, did not acquire his fortune, any more than Phormio
                    did, by good luck or by inheritance from his father, but he gave proof to the
                    bankers, Antisthenes and Archestratus, who were his masters, that he was a good
                    man and an honest, and so won their confidence. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>It is remarkable what a striking thing it is in the eyes of people who are active
                    in commercial life and in banking, when the same man is accounted industrious
                    and is honest.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The order of the words suggests
                        a slight contrast between <foreign xml:lang="grc">do/cai</foreign> and
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">ei)=nai</foreign>.</note> Well; this quality was
                    not imparted to Pasio by his masters; he was himself honest by nature; nor did
                    your father impart it to Phormio. It was yourself, rather than Phormio, whom he
                    would have made honest, if he had had the power. If you do not know that for
                    money-making the best capital of all is trustworthiness, you do not know
                    anything at all. But, apart from all this, Phormio has in many ways shown
                    himself useful to your father and to you, and in general to your affairs. But
                    your insatiate greed and your character, I take it, no one could adequately
                    express. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>I am surprised that you do not of yourself make this reflection, that
                    Archestratus, to whom your father formerly belonged, has a son here, Antimachus,
                    who fares not at all as he deserves, and who does not go to law with you and say
                    that he is outrageously treated, because you wear a soft mantle, and have
                    redeemed one mistress, and have given another in marriage (all this, while you
                    have a wife of your own), and take three attendant slaves about with you, and
                    live so licentiously that even those who meet you on the street perceive it,
                    while he himself is in great destitution. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>Nor does he fail to see Phormio's condition. And yet if on this ground you think
                    you have a claim on Phormio's property, because he once belonged to your father,
                    Antimachus has a stronger claim than you have. For your father in his turn
                    belonged to those men, so that both you and Phormio by this argument belong to
                    Antimachus. But you are so lost to all proper feeling, that you yourself compel
                    people to say things which you ought to hate anyone for saying. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>You disgrace yourself and your dead parents, and you cast reproach upon the
                    state, and instead of adorning and cherishing this good fortune<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">That is, of course, the right of citizenship.</note> which
                    your father, and afterward Phormio have come to enjoy through the kindness of
                    these men, so that it might have appeared as the highest of honors for those who
                    gave it and for you who obtained it, you drag it into public view, you point the
                    finger of scorn at it, you criticize it; you all but taunt the Athenians for
                    admitting to citizenship a person like yourself. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>Indeed you have come to such a pitch of insanity—what other name can one find for
                    it?—as not to see that at this moment we, who claim that, since Phormio has
                    received his freedom, it should not be remembered against him that he once
                    belonged to your father, are speaking in your interest; while you, in insisting
                    that he should never be on a footing of equality with yourself, are speaking
                    against yourself; for the same rule, which you lay down as just for yourself
                    against Phormio, will be advanced against you by those who at the first were the
                    masters of your father.To prove that Pasio also was somebody's slave, and that
                    he afterwards won his freedom in the same manner in which Phormio won his from
                    you, take, please, these depositions, which show that Pasio belonged to
                        Archestratus.<quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>The man, then, who at the first saved the family fortune, and rendered himself
                    useful in many ways to this man's father, the man who has conferred upon
                    Apollodorus himself all the benefits of which you have heard, he it is against
                    whom the plaintiff seeks a judgement with such heavy damages, and thinks proper
                    to cast out in ruin contrary to all right. For that, Apollodorus, is all that
                    you could possibly accomplish. For, if you look closely at the property, you
                    will see to whom it belongs, in case—which heaven forbid!—these jurymen are
                    misled by you.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The property of Phormio
                        consisted chiefly in the money of the depositors which he had invested in
                        diverse ways. If heavy damages were assessed against him, the depositors
                        would at once demand their money, and such a run on the bank would be
                        ruinous.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>Do you see Aristolochus, son of Charidemus? Once he possessed some land; now many
                    people own it; for he acquired it while he was in debt to many. And Sosinomus
                    and Timodemus and the other bankers, who, when they had to settle with their
                    creditors, had to give up all their property. But you think it unnecessary to
                    have regard even for the precautions which your father, a far better man than
                    you and a wiser, took to meet all contingencies. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>He—O Zeus and the gods—esteemed Phormio to be so much more valuable than you both
                    to yourself and to him and to your business, that, although you were a man
                    grown, it was to Phormio, not to you, that he left the control of the leases,
                    and gave him his wife in marriage and honored him as long as he lived. And
                    justly too, men of Athens. For other bankers, who had no rent to pay, but
                    carried on their business on their own account, have all come to ruin; while
                    Phormio, who paid a rent of two talents and forty minae, saved the bank for you.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>For this Pasio was grateful to him, but you make no account of it. Nay, in
                    defiance of the will and the imprecations written in it by your father, you
                    harass him, you prosecute him, you calumniate him. My good sir—you can be
                    addressed by this term—will you not desist, and know this—that to be honest
                    profits more than great wealth? In your own case, at any rate, although, if your
                    words are true, you received all this money, it has all been lost, as you say.
                    But, if you had been a man of character, you would not have squandered it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>For my own part, by Zeus and the gods, though I look at the matter from every
                    side, I can see no reason why the jury should be induced by you to give a
                    verdict against the defendant. Why should they? Because you make your charges so
                    soon after the offence? But you make them years and ages later. Ah, but you
                    avoided the trouble of lawsuits all this time? But who does not know of all the
                    cases in which you have been engaged without ceasing, not only prosecuting
                    private suits of no less importance than the present one, but maliciously
                    trumping up public charges, and bringing men to trial? Did you not accuse
                    Timomachus? Did you not accuse Callippus, who is now in Sicily? Or, again, Meno?
                    or Autocles? or Timotheus? or hosts of others?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Timomachus, Meno, and Autocles (see <bibl n="Dem. 50">Dem 50</bibl>.) were
                        successive commanders of the Athenian fleet in Thracian waters, where
                        Apollodorus served as trierarch. Callippus is all but certainly to be
                        identified with the trierarch of that name, who at the bidding of
                        Timomachus, and after Apollodorus's own refusal to do so, had transported
                        the exile Callistratus from Macedonia to Thasos. Timotheus was the
                        well-known Athenian general, against whom Apollodorus brought also a private
                        suit to recover funds (<bibl n="Dem. 49">Dem. 49</bibl>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>But is it reasonable to believe that you, who are Apollodorus, would deem it your
                    duty to seek satisfaction for public wrongs, which touched you only in part,
                    sooner than for the private wrongs, concerning which you now bring charges,
                    especially when they were as grave as you now claim? Why, then, did you accuse
                    those men, and leave Phormio alone? You were suffering no wrong, but methinks
                    the charges which you are now bringing are baseless and malicious. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>I think, then, men of Athens, that nothing could be more to the purpose than to
                    bring forward witnesses to these facts. For if one is continually making
                    baseless charges, what can one expect him to do now? In truth, men of Athens, I
                    think that whatever serves as an index of Phormio's character, and of his
                    uprightness and his generosity, I may rightly bring before you as something
                    quite to the purpose. For one who is dishonest in all matters might perhaps have
                    wronged the plaintiff among others; but a man who has never wronged anybody in
                    anything, but, on the contrary, has voluntarily done good to many, how could he
                    reasonably be thought to have wronged Apollodorus alone of all men?When you have
                    heard these depositions, you will know the character of either.<quote
                        n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>Now read those which bear upon the baseness of Apollodorus.<quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>Is this fellow of like stamp? Consider. Read on.<quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>Now read all the services which Phormio has rendered to the state.<quote
                        n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>Phormio, then, men of Athens, who has in so many ways proved himself of service
                    to the state and to many of you, and has never done harm to anyone either in
                    public or in private, and who is guilty of no wrong toward this man Apollodorus,
                    begs and implores and claims your protection, and we, his friends, join in the
                    same plea to you. Of another fact, too, you should be informed. Depositions have
                    been read to you, men of Athens, showing that the defendant has supplied you
                    with funds in excess of the whole amount that he or anybody else possesses; but
                    Phormio has credit with those who know him for so great an amount and for far
                    larger sums, and through this he is of service both to himself and to you.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">I follow Sandys in the interpretation of this
                        passage.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>Do not throw this away, nor suffer this abominable fellow to destroy it; do not
                    establish a shameful precedent, that it is permitted by you that rascals and
                    sycophants should take the property of those who are active in business and who
                    lead well-ordered lives. Far greater advantage accrues to you from this wealth
                    while it remains in the possession of the defendant. For you see for yourselves,
                    and you hear from the witnesses, what a friend he shows himself to be to those
                    in need. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>And not one of these acts has he done with a view to pecuniary advantage, but
                    from generosity and kindliness of disposition. So it is not right, men of
                    Athens, that you should give up such a man to be the prey of Apollodorus. Do not
                    show Phormio pity at a time when it will be of no profit to him, but now when it
                    is in your power to save him; for I see no time in which one could more
                    fittingly come to his aid than now. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>Most of what Apollodorus will say you must regard as mere talk and baseless
                    calumny. Bid him demonstrate to you, either that his father did not make this
                    will, or that there is another lease than the one which we produce; or that he
                    himself after going over the reckoning did not give Phormio a release from all
                    the claims regarding which his father-in-law made the award with the plaintiff's
                    own concurrence; or that the laws permit one to bring action regarding matters
                    thus decided. Or bid him try to show anything of that sort. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
                <p>But if, for want of proofs, he goes on uttering charges and calumnies and abuse,
                    do not heed him, nor let his noisy talk and shamelessness lead you astray. Nay,
                    keep in mind, and remember all that you have heard. If you do this you will be
                    faithful to your oaths, and will save the defendant, as justice bids. By Zeus
                    and all the gods he deserves it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
                <p>Take, and read them the law and these depositions.<quote n="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote><quote n="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>I do not know what reason there is why I should say more; for I believe
                    that nothing that I have said has escaped you. Pour out the water.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The speaker concludes without having exhausted
                        the time allowed him; there is, therefore, water left in the water-clock.
                        This he effectively bids the attendant to pour out. <bibl n="Dem. 38">Dem.
                            38</bibl> closes with these same words. In <bibl n="Dem. 54">Dem.
                            54</bibl>, while depositions are being read, the attendant is bidden to
                        check the flow of the water.</note></p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
