<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Demosthenes </title>
                <author>Dinarchus</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Dinarchus</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>April and May 1992</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>SGML markup</item>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This popular leader of yours, Athenians, who has
                    imposed on himself a sentence of death should he be proved to have taken even
                    the smallest sum from Harpalus, has been clearly convicted of taking bribes from
                    those very men whom he formerly professed to oppose. Much has already been said
                    by Stratocles<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Stratocles the orator, who
                        proposed that special honors should be paid to Lycurgus after his death
                            (<bibl n="Plut. Lyc. 852a">Plut. Vit. Lyc. 852 A</bibl>), may possibly
                        be the same man as the general of that name who served at <placeName
                            key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>.</note> and most of the charges
                    have now been made; as regards the report itself the Areopagus has expressed
                    opinions which are both just and true, while with events succeeding this
                    Stratocles has already dealt and read the decrees relating to them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>It remains for us, Athenians, especially when contesting a case never paralleled
                    in the experience of the city, to make a general exhortation to you all. May we
                    ask you first to pardon those of us who have still to speak if there are certain
                    points which we raise again; our aim is not to weary you by alluding twice to
                    the same matters but to arouse your anger all the more. Secondly, may we ask you
                    not to surrender the rights enjoyed by the whole city or to barter away our
                    common security in exchange for the arguments of the defendant. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>You are aware, Athenians, that whereas this man Demosthenes is here for judgement
                    before you, you are on trial before your fellows. For they are waiting to see
                    what kind of conclusion you will reach about your country's interests: are you
                    going to welcome into your midst the private venality and corruption of these
                    people, or will you make it universally known that you hate men who accept
                    bribes against their city and that, in ordering the Areopagus to make its
                    inquiry, your intention was not to acquit the culprits but rather, when the
                    councillors had made their report, to exact punishment in a manner appropriate
                    to the crimes? This decision then rests with you now. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>For when the people passed a lawful decree and every citizen wished to discover
                    which of the politicians had dared to accept money from Harpalus to the
                    discredit and danger of the city; when, moreover, you, Demosthenes, and many
                    others had proposed in a decree that the Areopagus, according to its traditional
                    right, should hold an inquiry to discover if any of them had received gold from
                    Harpalus, the Areopagus began its investigation. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>In reaching a just decision it paid no heed to your challenges, Demosthenes, nor
                    did it wish to pervert the truth or destroy its own reputation on your account.
                    On the contrary, gentlemen, although, as the Areopagites themselves said, the
                    council realized beforehand the strength of these men and their influence as
                    orators and statesmen, it did not consider that if incrimination or danger was
                    threatening its country it ought to be influenced by any misrepresentation
                    likely to be published about itself. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>Though this investigation has been conducted, in the people's opinion, both
                    fairly and profitably, accusations, challenges, and calumnies are proceeding
                    from Demosthenes, since he has been listed as the holder of twenty talents of
                    gold. Will that council then which, in cases of willful] murder, is trustworthy
                    enough to arrive at truth and justice and is empowered to pass judgement in
                    matters of life and death on each of the citizens, to take up the cause of those
                    who have met a violent end and banish or execute any in the city who have broken
                    the law,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">After the restoration of the democracy
                        in <date when="-0403">403</date> B.C. the Areopagus played a more important
                        part in public affairs than in the preceding half-century. It dealt with all
                        cases of voluntary homicide and sometimes with political cases also, when it
                        could act either on its own initiative (cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.63">Din.
                            1.63</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 18.133">Dem. 18.133</bibl>) or in response
                        to the people's request, as in the present instance. See <bibl n="Din. 1.50"
                            >Din. 1.50</bibl>.</note> be powerless now to administer justice over
                    the money credited to Demosthenes? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It will; for the council has told lies against
                    Demosthenes. This is the crowning argument in his case. It has told lies, has
                    it, against you and Demades: men against whom it is evidently not even safe to
                    speak the truth; though you previously instructed the Areopagus to investigate
                    many public matters and expressed approval of it for the inquiries which it had
                    held? Are the indictments which the council has made against these men false
                    when the whole city cannot compel them to do right? Great Heavens! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>Then why, Demosthenes, did you agree in the Assembly to a penalty of death for
                    yourself, if the report of the council should turn out against you? And why have
                    you yourself ruined many others by insisting on the findings of the council? To
                    what authority should the people now refer, or to whom should it entrust the
                    inquiry in the event of mysterious or momentous crimes, if it is to discover the
                    truth? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>For the council which formerly commanded confidence is being discredited by you,
                    who claim to be the people's man, though it is a body to which the people gave
                    in trust the protection of their lives, to whose charge they have often
                    committed their constitution and democracy, a council which, destined though you
                    were to malign it, has safeguarded your life, according to your own account so
                    often threatened, and which keeps the mystic deposits<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The exact nature of these mystic deposits, on which the
                        welfare of the community was thought to depend, is not known; they were
                        probably oracles.</note> whereby the safety of the city is preserved. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now in one respect—for I shall speak my mind—the
                    Areopagus fully deserves this treatment. It was faced with two alternatives. One
                    would have been, in accordance with the people's instructions, to conduct the
                    previous investigation over the three hundred talents which came from the
                    Persian king<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">After Alexander's accession Darius
                        subsidized several Greek states to oppose him. Three hundred talents offered
                        by him to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and officially
                        refused were said to have been accepted by Demosthenes to be used in the
                        king's interest. Cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.18">Din. 1.18</bibl>; <bibl
                            n="Aeschin. 3.239">Aeschin. 3.239</bibl> (who gives the sum which
                        Demosthenes appropriated as seventy talents); <bibl n="Diod. 17.4">Dio. Sic.
                            17.4</bibl>.</note>; in which case this monster would have been
                    convicted and the names of those who shared the money published; the betrayal of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, for which Demosthenes
                    was responsible,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In <date when="-0335"
                            >335</date> B.C., owing to a report that Alexander, who was fighting the
                        Triballi, had been killed, <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> revolted against Macedonian domination encouraged by
                        Demosthenes and others who assisted them to procure arms. When they applied
                        for assistance to the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>
                        and <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, the Peloponnesians
                        sent an army as far as the Isthmus, while <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> voted help but awaited the turn of events. Meanwhile
                            <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> was taken by
                        Alexander and destroyed. Dinarchus, who goes into greater detail later
                            (<bibl n="Din. 1.18">Din. 1.18-22</bibl>), maintains that for ten
                        talents of the Persian money Demosthenes could have secured the help of the
                        Peloponnesian army but was too miserly to do so. Cf. <bibl n="Diod. 17.8"
                            >Dio. Sic. 17.8</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.239">Aeschin.
                            3.239-240</bibl>.</note> would have been exposed, and we, exacting from
                    this demagogue the punishment he deserved, would have been rid of him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>Alternatively, if it was your wish to forgive Demosthenes for these offences and
                    to have in the city a large number of people who would take bribes against you,
                    the council ought, having tested your wishes in the previous cases, to have
                    refused to undertake an investigation over the payments of money recently
                    reported. For despite the excellence and the justice of this recent report,
                    which incriminates Demosthenes and the rest of them, and despite the fact that
                    the Areopagus has not deferred to the power of Demosthenes or Demades but has
                    regarded justice and truth as more important, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>Demosthenes goes round none the less maligning the council and telling the same
                    stories about himself with which he will probably try to mislead you presently.
                    “I made the Thebans your allies.”<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In making
                        this claim Demosthenes was referring to events just before the battle of
                            <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> when he won
                            <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> over to <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by offering her more liberal
                        terms than Philip. For his defence of this policy see <bibl n="Dem. 18.153"
                            >Dem. 18.153</bibl> sq.</note> No, Demosthenes, you impaired the common
                    interest of both our states. “I brought everyone into line at <placeName
                        key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>.” On the contrary you yourself were
                    the only one to leave the line at <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                        >Chaeronea</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The charge of
                        cowardice in battle is often brought against Demosthenes by Aeschines (e.g.
                            <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.175">Aeschin. 3.175</bibl>); it is mentioned by
                        Plutarch (<bibl n="Plut. Dem. 20.2">Plut. Dem. 855 A</bibl>) and in the
                            <title>Lives of the Ten Orators</title> (<bibl n="Plut. Dec. Orat. 845f"
                            >Plut. Vit. 845 F</bibl>).</note> “I served on many embassies on your
                    behalf.” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>One wonders what he would have done or what he would have said if the course that
                    he had recommended on these missions had proved successful, when, after touring
                    the whole Greek world to negotiate such disasters and mistakes, he still claims
                    to have been granted the greatest privileges, namely those of accepting bribes
                    against his country and saying and doing whatever he wishes against the public
                    interest. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>You made no allowance for Timotheus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        following passage is repeated almost word for word in the speech against
                        Philocles (<bibl n="Din. 3.17">Din. 3.17</bibl>). Timotheus, an Athenian
                        general and a friend of Isocrates, who recounts his exploits (<bibl
                            n="Isoc. 15.107">Isoc. 15.107-113</bibl>), sailed round the <placeName
                            key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> and gained a victory at
                            <placeName key="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName> in <date when="-0375"
                            >375</date> B.C. In 365 he took <placeName key="tgn,7002673"
                            >Samos</placeName>, which was occupied by a Persian garrison, after a
                        ten months' siege (<bibl n="Dem. 15.9">Dem. 15.9</bibl>). Thence he moved to
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> and mastered several
                        Chalcidian cities, of which Dinarchus here mentions three. In 356 he was
                        sent out with two others to reinforce the fleet of Chares who was trying to
                        crush an allied revolt; but in a sea battle near <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName> he failed to help Chares, owing to
                        stormy weather, and was therefore prosecuted by him for bribery. Timotheus
                        was not popular owing to his haughty behavior; and being fined the
                        unprecedented amount of a hundred talents, which he could not pay, he went
                        into exile in <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>. Cf.
                            <bibl n="Isoc. 15.131">Isoc. 15.131</bibl>.</note> Athenians, although
                    he sailed round the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> and
                    defeated the Lacedaemonians in a naval battle at <placeName key="tgn,7010886"
                        >Corcyra</placeName>, and was the son of <placeName key="tgn,1123029"
                        >Conon</placeName><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                                ><persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, a general in the
                        Peloponnesian war who fought at <placeName key="tgn,6000070"
                            >Aegospotami</placeName>, was later joint commander of the Persian
                        fleet. In this capacity he rendered a service to <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by defeating the Spartan
                        Pisander in a naval battle off <placeName key="tgn,5003757"
                            >Cnidus</placeName> in <date when="-0394">394</date> B.C.</note> too who
                    liberated <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. Though he captured
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="perseus,Methone">Methone</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Pydna"
                        >Pydna</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName>, and
                    twenty other cities besides, you did not permit such services to outweigh the
                    trial which you were then conducting or the oaths that governed your vote;
                    instead you fined him a hundred talents because Aristophon said that he had
                    accepted money from the Chians and Rhodians. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Will you then absolve this abominable wretch, this Scythian,—really I cannot
                    contain myself,—whom no mere individual but the whole Areopagus has shown, after
                    inquiry, to be in possession of money to your detriment, whose bribery and
                    corruption against the city have been revealed and established beyond doubt?
                    Will you not punish him and make him an example to others? He is known not only
                    to have taken gold from the royal treasuries<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >See note on <bibl n="Din. 1.10">Din. 1.10</bibl></note> but also to have
                    enriched himself at the city's own expense, since he did not even withhold his
                    hand from the money lately brought to her by Harpalus. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>Yet the embassies to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> which
                    Demosthenes undertook are equivalent to a mere fraction of Timotheus' services;
                    and which of you, contrasting with the exploits on which Demosthenes prides
                    himself those which Timotheus and <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>
                    performed on your behalf, would not laugh to scorn all who consented to listen
                    to this man? But then there should be no comparison made between this outcast
                    and the men who in your interests acted worthily of the city and your ancestors.
                    I will therefore cite the decree which was passed concerning Timotheus and then
                    return to my review of the defendant. Read.<quote type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This citizen, Demosthenes, of such a character,
                    who might well have gained the pardon and gratitude of his colleagues in the
                    public life of those days, since he had rendered great services to the city, not
                    in word only but in deed, and had always remained true to the same policy rather
                    than changing to and fro as you have done, met his death without begging the
                    people for such extensive favors as would set him above the laws or thinking
                    that men who had sworn to vote in accordance with the law should consider
                    anything more important than their word; he was ready even for condemnation, if
                    the jury decided upon it, and did not plead the inclemency of circumstance or
                    express in public opinions which he did not hold. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Will you not execute this accursed wretch,
                    Athenians, who, in addition to many other crucial blunders, stood by while the
                    Thebans' city was destroyed, though he had accepted three hundred talents from
                    the Persian King for their protection though the Arcadians,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">See note on <bibl n="Din. 1.10">Din. 1.10</bibl></note>
                    arriving at the Isthmus, had dismissed with a rebuff the envoys of Antipater and
                    welcomed those from the unhappy Thebans who had reached them with difficulty by
                    sea, bearing a suppliant's staff and heralds' wands, plaited, they said, from
                    olive shoots? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>They came to assure the Arcadians that no wish to break their friendship with the
                    Greeks had led the Thebans to a revolution, nor did they intend to do anything
                    to the detriment of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>; but they
                    were no longer able to countenance at home the behavior of the Macedonians in
                    the city, to endure slavery, or to witness the outrages perpetrated against the
                    persons of free men. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>The Arcadians were ready to help them and, sympathizing with their misfortunes,
                    explained that, though they were compelled through force of circumstance to
                    serve Alexander with their persons, in spirit they sided always with the Thebans
                    and the cause of Greek liberty. Since their leader, Astylus, was open to
                    bribery, as Stratocles said, and wanted ten talents as the price of helping the
                    Thebans, the envoys approached Demosthenes who, as they knew, held the King's
                    gold and earnestly begged him to spend the money to save their city. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>But this hard-hearted and impious miser could not bring himself to expend, from
                    his great resources, ten paltry talents, though he saw such high hopes dawning
                    for the salvation of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>.
                    Instead, as Stratocles said, he allowed others to provide this sum to induce
                    those of the Arcadians who had marched out to return home and deny their help to
                        <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>Do you consider that the evils for which Demosthenes and his avarice have been
                    responsible are trivial or of little import for the whole of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>? Do you think that he deserves any pity
                    at your hands after committing such offences? Should he not rather suffer the
                    extreme penalty to atone for his crimes, both past and present? The verdict
                    given by you today, Athenians, will be heard by all mankind, who will observe
                    how you, the judges, treat the man with such a record. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>You are the people who, for crimes far smaller than those Demosthenes has
                    committed, have inflicted on men severe and irrevocable penalties. It was you
                    who killed Menon the miller, because he kept a free boy from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Pellene">Pellene</placeName> in his mill. You punished with
                    death Themistius of <placeName key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName>,
                    because he assaulted the Rhodian lyre-player at the Eleusinian festival, and
                    Euthymachus, because he put the Olynthian girl in a brothel. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>But through this traitor children and women, the wives of the Thebans, were
                    distributed among the tents of the barbarians, a neighboring and allied city has
                    been torn up from the midst of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>
                    and the site of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> is being
                    ploughed and sown, the city of men who shared with you the war against Philip.
                    Yes, it is being ploughed and sown. And this unfeeling wretch showed no
                    compassion for a city thus lamentably destroyed, though he visited it as an
                    envoy representing you and has often shared the meat and drink of its citizens,
                    claiming himself that he made it our ally. But those to whom he often resorted
                    in their prosperity he has betrayed in their misfortune. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>The Thebans, so our elders tell us, when the democracy in our city had been
                    overthrown and Thrasybulus was assembling the exiles in <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> ready for the seizure of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Phyle">Phyle</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Thrasybulus and Anytus, exiled by the Thirty, were received in <placeName
                            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>. After seizing and holding the
                        fortress of <placeName key="perseus,Phyle">Phyle</placeName> in <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> in <date when="-0404">404</date>
                        B.C., they subsequently occupied the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus"
                            >Piraeus</placeName> and, with the intervention of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, brought about the restoration
                        of democracy in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note>
                    although the Spartans were strong and forbade them to admit or let out any
                    Athenian, helped the democrats to return and passed that decree which has so
                    often been read before you, stating that they would turn a blind eye if any
                    Athenian marched through their territory bearing arms. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>This man who fraternizes, as he will presently tell you, with our allies, behaved
                    very differently; he would not part with any of the money which he had received
                    for their protection. Remember these things, gentlemen; consider the disasters
                    caused by traitors in the downfall of <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                        >Olynthus</placeName> and of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName>; decide wisely now in your interest; destroy those who
                    are ready to take bribes against their country and so rest your hopes of safety
                    on yourselves and on the gods. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>For there is only one way, Athenians, in which you will reform the rest of
                    mankind, only one way: to expose those criminals who are notable men and punish
                    them as their crimes deserve. In the case of the average defendant no one knows
                    or troubles to inquire, when he is convicted, what has been his sentence. But
                    with men of note everyone hears the news and praises the jury, when they have
                    not sacrificed the interests of justice in deference to the reputation of the
                    defendants. Read the Theban decree. Cite the evidence. Read the letters.<quote
                        type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Evidence">
                        <title>Evidence</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Letters">
                        <title>Letters</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This man is a hireling, Athenians, a hireling of
                    long standing. It was he who summoned from <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName> the embassy coming to us from Philip and was responsible
                    for finishing the first war.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The first war with
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> (<date from="-0349"
                            to="-0346">349</date>-346 B.C.) was undertaken by <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and <placeName
                            key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> against Philip. Even before
                            <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> was taken the
                        king made overtures of peace, and it was Philocrates who proposed in
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> that these
                        negotiations should begin. However, after the fall of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> in 348, the Athenians tried
                        to unite other Greek states against Philip, and it was not until this
                        attempt had failed that Demosthenes acquiesced in peace proposals. In 347 he
                        defended Philocrates, who was accused of illegality in making his first
                        peace proposals, and himself served on an embassy to <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>. The final peace was signed in
                        346, when Antipater and Parmenio came to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> as Philip's envoys. Philocrates was prosecuted by
                        Hyperides in 343 for being bribed by Philip and went into exile. Cf. <bibl
                            n="Hyp. Fr. 16">Hyp. frag. 16</bibl></note> He helped to defend
                    Philocrates who proposed the peace with Philip and was exiled by you in
                    consequence, he hired a carriage for the envoys who came here with Antipater,
                    and by attaching them to himself, first introduced into the city the custom of
                    flattering <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>Do not acquit him, Athenians. Do not let go unpunished this man who has endorsed
                    the misfortunes of his country and the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                        >Greece</placeName>, when he has been caught with bribes against the city in
                    his very hands. Now that good fortune is improving your lot and, after expelling
                    from the city one of the two who have defiled their country, has surrendered
                    this other to you for execution, do not oppose all our interests yourselves but
                    rather bring happier omens to our state affairs and divert our misfortunes on to
                    the heads of these leaders. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>Against what occasion will you reserve Demosthenes in the belief that he will
                    prove useful to you? Could any one of you, or of the bystanders, say what public
                    or private affairs he has not ruined by his contact with them? After gaining
                    access to the home of Aristarchus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This story is
                        told more fully by Aeschines (<bibl n="Aeschin. 1.171">Aeschin.
                        1.171</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 2.148">Aeschin. 2.148</bibl> and <bibl
                            n="Aeschin. 2.166">Aeschin. 2.166</bibl>), who says that Aristarchus son
                        of Moschus was a wealthy orphan, half mad, from whom Demosthenes, pretending
                        to have taken a fancy to him personally, extracted three talents. He asserts
                        that together they contrived to murder, with great brutality, Nicodemus of
                        Aphidna who had once prosecuted Demosthenes for desertion; as the result of
                        which crime Aristarchus went into exile. Demosthenes himself mentions the
                        murder in his speech against Midias, where he claims that Midias went about
                        casting suspicion on him and persuaded the relatives of Nicodemus to do
                        likewise (<bibl n="Dem. 21.104">Dem. 21.104</bibl>). Cf. <bibl
                            n="Ath. 23.592">Athen. 23.592 f</bibl>.</note> and planning with him the
                    death of Nicodemus which they contrived, an affair of which you all know the
                    details, did he not banish Aristarchus on the most shameful charges? And did not
                    Aristarchus find in Demosthenes such a friend as to make him think that this was
                    some evil spirit which had visited him and the originator of all his
                    misfortunes? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>Is it not true that once this man began to advise the city, and would he had
                    never done so,—I shall pass over his private affairs, for time does not permit
                    me to speak at length,—absolutely no good has befallen it; indeed not only the
                    city but the whole of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> has been
                    involved in dangers, misfortunes, and dishonor? Is it not true that he has had
                    many opportunities while speaking to you and yet let slip every opportunity to
                    help you? On those occasions when a patriot with any regard for the city would
                    have chosen to make some move, this demagogue, who will presently say that he
                    has been of service to you, was so far from showing signs of action that he even
                    infected with his own ill-luck the men who were doing something to further your
                    interests. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>Charidemus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Charidemus of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Oreos">Oreos</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                            >Euboea</placeName> was made an Athenian citizen for his services as a
                        soldier (<bibl n="Dem. 23.151">Dem. 23.151</bibl>). He went to <placeName
                            key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> in <date when="-0335">335</date>
                        B.C., having been banished from <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> on the orders of Alexander (<bibl
                            n="Arr. An. 1.10.6">Arr. 1.10.6</bibl>), and after being well received
                        at first by Darius, fell under suspicion two years later and was executed
                            (<bibl n="Diod. 17.30">Dio. Sic. 17.30</bibl>).</note> set out to visit
                    the Persian King, wishing to do you some practical service apart from mere
                    talking, and anxious at his own peril to win safety for you and every Greek.
                    Demosthenes went round the market making speeches and associating himself with
                    the project. So completely did fortune wreck this plan that it turned out in
                    just the opposite way to what was expected. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>Ephialtes put to sea. Admittedly he hated Demosthenes but he was compelled to
                    have a partner in public affairs. Fortune robbed the city of this man too.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The facts are here distorted. Ephialtes, one of
                        the orators whose surrender was demanded by Alexander in <date when="-0335"
                            >335</date> B.C. (<bibl n="Arr. An. 1.104">Arr. 1.104</bibl>), was a
                        supporter of Demosthenes and, according to the Pseudo-Plutarch, brought back
                        money for the demagogues from the Persian court (<bibl n="Plut. Dem. 847f"
                            >Plut. Vit. Dem. 847 F</bibl> and 848 E). He was killed while helping
                        the Persians to defend <placeName key="tgn,7016142"
                            >Halicarnassus</placeName> against Alexander (<bibl n="Diod. 17.27">Dio.
                            Sic. 17.27</bibl>).</note> Euthydicus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >No details are known of Euthydicus. He seems to be mentioned as an Athenian
                        patriot together with Ephialtes and Lycurgus in the third letter of
                        Demosthenes (<bibl n="Dem. L. 3.31">Dem. L 3.31</bibl>), where however the
                        MSS. have <foreign xml:lang="grc">*eu)/dilkon</foreign>.</note> elected to
                    work for the people. Demosthenes claimed to be his friend. He too was lost. Do
                    not these facts, which you see and know better than I do, give you cause for
                    thought? Do they not make you weigh up your future prospects in the light of the
                    past and reflect in your own minds that this man is of no use except to our
                    enemies, against the interests of the city<gap/>? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p><gap/>to raise such another force as we had in the time of Agis,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">While Alexander was in the East, Agis the Third of
                            <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> rose against
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName> with the help of Darius
                        in <date when="-0333">333</date> B.C. In 331 he headed an army raised by
                        various Greek states but was refused the support of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, on the advice of Demosthenes.
                        Defeated near <placeName key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName>
                        by Antipater he was killed in battle (<bibl n="Diod. 17.48">Dio. Sic.
                            17.48</bibl> and <bibl n="Diod. 17.62">Dio. Sic. 17.62</bibl>).</note>
                    when the Spartans took the field together and Achaeans and men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName> were taking their part in the campaign
                    with ten thousand mercenaries also; when Alexander was in <placeName
                        key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Alexander was, in fact, in <placeName key="tgn,7000231"
                        >Persia</placeName>.</note> according to report, and the whole of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, owing to the traitors in every city,
                    was dissatisfied with the existing state of things and hoped for some release
                    from the misfortunes that beset her. In that hour,—for I need not dwell on other
                    crises,— </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>what was the behavior of this Demosthenes who had the power to give advice and
                    make proposals, who will shortly tell you that he hates our present
                    circumstances? On these matters, Demosthenes, did you offer any proposal, any
                    advice? Did you contribute money? Were you of the smallest value to the men
                    safeguarding us all? Not the least; you went round suborning speechwriters. He
                    wrote a letter at home, defiling the city's honor, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>and walked about dangling it from his finger ends, living in luxury during the
                    city's misfortunes, travelling down the road to the <placeName
                        key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> in a litter and reproaching the
                    needy for their poverty. Is this man then going to prove useful to you on future
                    occasions, when he has let slip every opportunity in the past? By our lady
                    Athena and Zeus the Savior, I could wish that the enemies of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> had lighted upon counsellors and
                    leaders like him and never better. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Let me remind you, gentlemen, of the conduct of
                    your forbears, who, at a time when many grave perils beset the city, faced
                    danger in the interests of the people, in a manner worthy of their country and
                    their well-earned reputation, as befitted free men. Time does not permit me to
                    deal with those figures of the past, Aristides and Themistocles: the men who
                    built the city's walls and carried up to the Acropolis the tribute paid by the
                    willing and even eager Greeks. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>But you will recall what was done, shortly before our own time, by Cephalus the
                    orator, Thrason of Herchia, Eleus and Phormisius and other fine men, some of
                    whom are still alive today.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cephalus assisted
                        in the overthrow of the Thirty in <date when="-0403">403</date> B.C. His
                        reputation as an orator is acknowledged by Demosthenes (<bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.219">Dem. 18.219</bibl>). Cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.76">Din.
                            1.76</bibl>. Of the other three men little is known. Thrason is
                        mentioned as a Theban proxenus by Aeschines (<bibl n="Aeschin. 3.139"
                            >Aeschin. 3.139</bibl>); Eleus is perhaps the trierarch (c. 323) whose
                        name appears in an inscription (I.G. 2.812, b. 14); Phormisius is a mere
                        name. Cf. <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 34.3">Aristot. Const. Ath.
                        34.3</bibl>.</note> Some of them, when the Cadmea was garrisoned by
                    Spartans, assisted the exiles who returned to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName> and at their own risk set free a neighboring city, long
                        enslaved.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In <date when="-0382">382</date>
                        B.C. Thebes was betrayed to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
                            >Sparta</placeName> and many leading men were exiled. These took refuge
                        at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, with whose help in
                        378 they soon overthrew the new government and ejected the Spartan garrison
                        from the city (<bibl n="Diod. 15.25">Dio. Sic. 15.25</bibl>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>Others lent aid when your ancestors were persuaded to take the field by Cephalus,
                    who proposed the decree and who, undaunted by the might of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and regardless of the risks either
                    of military or political action, moved that the Athenians should march out to
                    help the exiles who had taken Thebes. Your fathers did march out and in a few
                    days the commander of the Spartan garrison was expelled, the Thebans had been
                    freed and your city had acted worthily of your ancestors. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>They were counsellors, Athenians, they were leaders such as yourselves and the
                    state deserve. How different from rogues like this who neither have done nor
                    will do the city any service but watch over their own safety and treat
                    everything as a source of income. They have made the city more infamous than
                    themselves, and now, convicted of taking bribes against you, they deceive you
                    and presume, after conduct such as this, to talk to you about their own
                    aggrandizement. They ought, by the terms of their own decree, to have been put
                    to death long ago for doing such things. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Are you not ashamed, Athenians, that you should
                    think our speeches the only evidence you have on which to determine the
                    punishment of Demosthenes? Do you not know yourselves that this man is open to
                    bribes and is both a robber and a traitor to his friends that neither he nor the
                    fortune which has gone with him is fit for the city? Are there any decrees or
                    any laws which have not brought him money? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>Are there any people in the court who were among those included in the three
                    hundred when Demosthenes brought in his law concerning the trierarchs?<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For the trierarch law see note on <bibl
                            n="Hyp. Fr. 43">Hyp. frag. 43</bibl>.</note> Then tell your neighbors
                    that he accepted three talents and used to alter and re-draft the law for every
                    sitting of the Assembly, in some cases taking money over points for which he had
                    been paid already, in others failing to honor the sales which he had made. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>Really, gentlemen, tell me: do you think he got nothing for proposing that
                        Diphilus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Little is known of the various men
                        mentioned in this section. Diphilus was perhaps the son of Diopithes,
                        trierarch in 325/4 and <date from="-0323" to="-0322">323</date>/2 B.C. (CIA
                        2.809 d, 53 and 811 b, 104). For Chaerephilus, a dealer in salt fish,
                        compare <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 34">Hyp. frag. 34</bibl> and <bibl n="Hyp. Fr. 35"
                            >Hyp. frag. 35</bibl>. The three names following his are those of his
                        sons. All four were evidently put in the deme of Paeania, Pamphilus and
                        Phidippus being mentioned as members of it in inscriptions (CIA 2.172 and
                        CIA 2.811 d, 142). Cf. also <bibl n="Ath. 3.119">Athen. 3.119</bibl> sq. and
                            <bibl n="Ath. 8.339">Athen. 8.339 d</bibl>. Berisades is probably the
                        same man as Paerisades, a king of <placeName key="tgn,1115068"
                            >Bosporus</placeName> to whom Demosthenes refers (<bibl n="Dem. 34.8"
                            >Dem. 34.8</bibl>); Satyrus was his son.</note> should have meals at the
                    Prytaneum or for that statue to be put up in the market? Nothing for conferring
                    Athenian citizenship on Chaerephilus, Phidon, Pamphilus, and Phidippus, or again
                    on Epigenes and <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> the bankers?
                    Nothing for putting up in the market bronze statues of Berisades, Satyrus and
                    Gorgippus the tyrants from the <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Pontus</placeName>,
                    from whom he receives a thousand medimni of wheat a year—this man who will
                    presently tell you that there is nowhere for him to take refuge. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>Did he get nothing for proposing that Taurosthenes<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Dinarchus, like Aeschines, is distorting the facts. (Cf.
                            <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.85">Aeschin. 3 85</bibl> sq. and schol. ad loc.).
                        The cities of <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> had entered
                        the Athenian alliance in <date when="-0357">357</date> B.C., but in 348 they
                        revolted, probably owing to the intrigues of Philip with whom <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> was now at war over <placeName
                            key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>. Taurosthenes and Callias
                        commanded the army of <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis">Chalcis</placeName>
                        and the Athenians lost control of the island. In 343 however they
                        transferred the allegiance of <placeName key="perseus,Chalcis"
                            >Chalcis</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName>, and a few years later-the exact date is not
                        certain-were made Athenian citizens on the motion of Demosthenes (cf. <bibl
                            n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 col. 20</bibl>), whom Aeschines says they
                        bribed.</note> should become an Athenian, though he had enslaved his fellow
                    citizens and, with his brother Callias, betrayed the whole of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> to Philip? Taurosthenes whom the laws
                    forbid to set foot on Athenian soil, providing that if he does so he shall be
                    liable to the same penalties as an exile who returns after being sentenced by
                    the Areopagus. This was the man who Demosthenes the democrat proposed should be
                    your fellow citizen. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>Is there any need then for me to call up witnesses for you so far as these men
                    are concerned or any of the others whom he has proposed as proxeni or citizens?
                    I ask you in Athena's name: do you imagine that when he gladly accepts silver he
                    would refuse twenty talents of gold? Do you think that though he takes money in
                    dribblets, he would not accept as a lump sum so great a fee, or that the
                    Areopagus, which spent six months inquiring over Demosthenes, Demades, and
                        Cephisophon,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This is probably the same
                        Cephisophon, a politician of the time, as is mentioned by Demosthenes (<bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.21">Dem. 18.21</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 19.293">Dem.
                            19.293</bibl>).</note> has been unjust over the reports submitted to
                    you? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Gentlemen, you have very many witnesses, as I said
                    before, among citizens and other Greeks, watching to see how you will judge this
                    trial; are you, they wonder, going to bring within the scope of the courts the
                    venal actions of other men, or will there be complete freedom to accept bribes
                    against you? Will the things which so far have been held trustworthy and sure
                    now cease to be so on account of the trial of Demosthenes? On his past record he
                    ought to have been put to death, and he is liable to all the curses known to the
                    city, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>having broken the oaths he took on the Areopagus, in the names of the holy
                    goddesses and the other deities by whom it is customary to swear there, and
                    making himself accursed at every sitting of the Assembly. He has been proved to
                    have taken bribes against <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    has cheated the people and the council in defiance of the curse, professing
                    views he does not hold, and in private has recommended to Aristarchus a course
                    both cruel and unlawful.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cf. <bibl
                            n="Din. 1.30">Din. 1.30</bibl> and note.</note> For these misdeeds, if
                    there is any power to exact a just punishment from perjurers and criminals—as
                    there surely is—this man shall pay today. Gentlemen of the jury, listen to the
                        curse.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For the curse pronounced by the
                        herald before each sitting of the Council and Assembly on all who might be
                        acting treasonably against the state compare <bibl n="Lyc. 1.31">Lyc.
                            1.31</bibl>.</note><quote type="Curse">
                        <title>Curse</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Despite this, gentlemen of the jury, Demosthenes
                    is so ready with his lies and utterly unsound assertions, so oblivious of shame,
                    exposure, or curse, that he will dare to say of me, I gather, that I too was
                    previously condemned by the council. According to him I am behaving with the
                    utmost inconsistency, because in the past I opposed the council's report and
                    pleaded my own case, whereas I am now serving as its advocate and accusing him
                    over the report before us today. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>This is a story of his own invention, not based on fact, and he is impudent
                    enough to lie to you. So to make sure that, if he embarks upon this story, you
                    will pay no attention to him but will realize fully that the council did not
                    report me and was in no danger of doing so,—the truth being that I suffered at
                    the hands of a man of low character who has been convicted before you,—let me
                    explain briefly. Then I will come back to Demosthenes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The council of the Areopagus is bound, gentlemen,
                    to follow one of two methods in making all its reports. What are these methods?
                    Its inquiry is made either on its own initiative or in obedience to the people's
                        instructions.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note on <bibl
                            n="Din. 1.6">Din. 1.6</bibl>.</note> Apart from these two, there is no
                    other procedure it could follow. If then you tell us, you abominable brute, that
                    the council followed the people's instructions in making its inquiry and
                    publishing the report on me, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>show me the decree and tell me who were my accusers after the report was made.
                    Compare the present case, where you have both: a decree which authorized the
                    council's inquiry, and accusers, elected by the people, who are now giving the
                    jury an account of the crimes. If your story is true, I am prepared to die. But
                    if you claim that the council took the initiative in reporting me, produce the
                    Areopagites as witnesses, just as I myself shall produce them to show that I was
                    not reported, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>to show in fact that, after impeaching one rogue and traitor who, like you, had
                    maligned the council and myself, I proved before two thousand five hundred
                    citizens that he had hired himself to Pythocles<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Pythocles was an Athenian orator who, in company with Aeschines, attacked
                        Demosthenes unsuccessfully after <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                            >Chaeronea</placeName>. Cf. <bibl n="Dem. 18.285">Dem.
                        18.285</bibl>.</note> in making this attack upon me, and so avenged myself
                    with the help of those then serving on the jury. Clerk, please take the
                    deposition. I laid it before the jury previously as evidence and no one
                    questioned its veracity. So I will produce it now. Read the deposition.<quote
                        type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Is it not an anomaly, Athenians, that on that
                    occasion, because one man, Pistias an Areopagite,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Nothing else is known of Pistias except that Dinarchus
                        composed a speech against him, the title of which appears in the list of his
                        genuine public orations preserved by Dionysius.</note> told lies against the
                    council and myself and said that I was a criminal, falsehood would have
                    prevailed over truth, if through my weakness and isolation at the time the
                    trumped up lies against me had been believed; whereas now, when the fact is
                    admitted by the whole Areopagus that Demosthenes has taken twenty talents of
                    gold against your interests, and is therefore a criminal, and that your popular
                    leader, in whom some men place their hopes, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>has been caught in the act of taking bribes, the customs of the Areopagus and
                    truth and justice are going to prove weaker than Demosthenes' word? Truth will
                    be overridden by the slanderous statement he intends to make against the
                    council, namely that many of those reported by it as a menace to the people
                    have, on coming into court, been acquitted, in some cases the council failing to
                    secure a fifth part of the votes. There is an explanation for this which you
                    will easily follow. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>The council, gentlemen, has its own method of inquiring into the cases which you
                    assign to it and the crimes committed within its own body. Unlike
                    yourselves,—and you need not take offence at this,—who are sometimes apt when
                    judging to give more weight to mercy than to justice, it simply reports anyone
                    who is liable to the charges in question or has broken any traditional rule of
                    conduct believing that if a person is in the habit of committing small offences
                    he will more easily involve himself in serious crimes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>Consequently when one of its number robbed the ferryman of his fare it fined him
                    and reported him to you. Again, when someone claimed the five drachma
                        allowance<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">It appears from Hyperides (<bibl
                            n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 col. 26</bibl>), who seems to be referring to the same
                        case, that Dinarchus is here alluding to the dole made to Athenians to
                        enable them to attend the theater. The normal price of a seat was one-third
                        of a drachma only, but as the fund was apparently drawn upon for other
                        purposes also, it is perhaps not surprising that the sum mentioned here is
                        larger. Cf. <bibl n="Lib. Arg.D. 1">Libanius arg. ad Demosthenem 1</bibl>.
                        The portion mentioned in the following sentence was an allowance of
                        sacrificial meat made to members of the Areopagus.</note> in the name of an
                    absentee, it reported him also to you. Similarly it fined and expelled the man
                    who presumed to break the rule and sell the Areopagite portion. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>You tried these men and acquitted them. You were not thereby convicting the
                    Areopagus of error but you were more concerned with sympathy than justice, and
                    thought the punishment too severe for the offence which the defendants had
                    committed. Do you imagine then, Demosthenes, that the council made a false
                    report? Of course it did not. Nevertheless, gentlemen, you acquitted these men
                    and others like them, though the council reported that they were guilty of
                    breaking its rules. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>In the case of Polyeuctus of Cydantidae,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For
                        Polyeuctus of Cydantidae, the accuser of Euxenippus, cf. <bibl n="Hyp. 4.4"
                            >Hyp. 4.4</bibl>, Introduction.</note> when the people instructed the
                    council to inquire whether he was accompanying the exiles to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName> and to report back after the
                    investigation, it reported that he was doing so. You chose accusers as the law
                    prescribes: Polyeuctus came into court and you acquitted him, on his admitting
                    that he was going to <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName> to
                    Nicophanes who, he said, was married to his mother. So you did not consider that
                    he was doing anything strange or reprehensible in keeping in touch with his
                    mother's husband who was in difficulties, or in assisting him, so far as he
                    could, while he was banished from the country. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>The report of the council, Demosthenes, was not proved false; it was quite true,
                    but the jury decided to acquit Polyeuctus. The council was instructed to
                    discover the truth, yet, as I say, the court decided whether it was a case for
                    pardon. Is that any reason for distrusting the council over the present reports
                    in which it has stated that you and your confederates are in possession of the
                    gold? That would be disgraceful. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>Convince the jury now, Demosthenes, that any of those crimes ranks with yours and
                    that to take bribes against one's country is a pardonable act which would
                    justify these men in acquitting you. For other pecuniary offences the laws
                    prescribe damages twice as great as the sum involved,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">A misleading statement. Cf. <bibl n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 col.
                            24</bibl>, where the contrast made is between a simple and a tenfold
                        fine. A fine was doubled only if it had not been paid before a specific
                        date. Cf. <bibl n="Din. 2.17">Din. 2.17</bibl> and <bibl
                            n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 54">Aristot. Const. Ath. 54</bibl>.</note> but in
                    cases of bribery they have laid down two penalties only: either death, to ensure
                    that by meeting with this punishment the guilty man is an example to others, or
                    a fine for bribery ten times as great as the original bribe, so that men who
                    dare to commit this offence shall not gain by it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Perhaps you will not attempt to argue thus,
                    Demosthenes, but will say that of those whom the council has reported up till
                    now the rest have admitted that the penalty which it imposed was deserved,
                    whereas you alone have protested against it. But you alone, of all those ever
                    reported, asked these men of your own accord to be your judges and court of
                    inquiry. You proposed the decree against yourself and made the people witness of
                    the agreement, defining the penalty for yourself as death, if the council should
                    report that you had taken any of the money brought into the country by Harpalus.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
                <p>And yet in the past, Demosthenes, you proposed that the council of the Areopagus
                    should have power over all these men, and the rest of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> too, to enforce the laws of the land
                    and punish any who transgressed them. It was you who surrendered the whole city
                    into the hands of this council which you will presently tell us is oligarchic.
                    By the terms of your decree the death sentence has been inflicted on two
                    citizens, a father and a son, who were given over to the executioner. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
                <p>One of the descendants of Harmodius was imprisoned in pursuance of your order.
                    These gentlemen, acting on the council's report, tortured and killed
                        Antiphon.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Demosthenes (<bibl
                            n="Dem. 18.132">Dem. 18.132</bibl>) confirms this and says that Antiphon
                        promised Philip that he would burn the dockyards in the <placeName
                            key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>. Demosthenes caught him there
                        and brought him before the people, who at first acquitted him. But the
                        Areopagus intervened and he was later executed.</note> You expelled
                        Charinus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Charinus, a figure of little
                        importance, is mentioned as a traitor in the speech against Theocrines,
                        which was attributed by Dionysius to Dinarchus but has survived among the
                        works of Demosthenes (<bibl n="Dem. 58.38">Dem. 58.38</bibl>).</note> from
                    the city for treason on the strength of the council's reports and punishments.
                    After proposing this treatment for yourself also, are you now overriding the
                    decree of your own accord? Surely that is neither just nor lawful. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I summon as my witnesses, Athenians, the awful
                    goddesses and their abode, the heroes of the land, Athena Polias, and those
                    other gods who have obtained our city and countryside as their home, to show
                    that when the people has consigned to you for punishment one who, against his
                    country's interests, has accepted a part of the imported money,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The sense of this passage is clear, though the Greek wording
                        leaves room for doubt.</note> one who has defiled and ruined the city's
                    prosperity and betrayed that country which he claimed to have fortified by his
                        diplomacy,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">An allusion to some words of
                        Demosthenes in the speech on the Crown (<bibl n="Dem. 18.299">Dem.
                            18.299</bibl>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
                <p>enemies, and those who bear the city ill will, would wish him alive, counting
                    this a disaster for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; but all
                    who favor your concerns and hope that with a turn of fortune the city's
                    prospects may improve wish that this man may die and pay the penalty merited by
                    his conduct, and such is the burden of their prayers. I also join in praying the
                    gods to save our country, which I see to be in danger of forfeiting its safety,
                    its women and children, its honor, and every other thing of worth. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="section">
                <p>What shall we say to the bystanders, Athenians, when we come out of the court, if
                    you are deceived, as I pray you may not be, by the wizardry of this man? What
                    will be the feelings of you all, when, on your return, you presume to look upon
                    your fathers' hearths, after acquitting the traitor who first brought into his
                    own home the gold of bribery; after convicting as utterly false, in both its
                    inquiry and its conclusion, the body which all men hold in the greatest awe?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="section">
                <p>What hopes, Athenians,—picture for yourselves,—what hopes shall we have if some
                    danger overtakes the city, when we have made it a safe thing to take bribes
                    against one's country and have robbed of its status the body which kept watch
                    over the city in such times of crisis? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="section">
                <p>Or again,—let us suppose this to happen,—what if Alexander, in pursuance of
                    Demosthenes' decree,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Demosthenes had proposed
                        that the money should be kept on the Acropolis until Alexander sent for
                        it.</note> sends and asks us for the gold brought into the country by
                    Harpalus, and, over and above the fact that the council has made a report, sends
                    down here the slaves which have now been returned to him and asks us to find out
                    the truth from them; what in Heaven's name shall we say, gentlemen? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="section">
                <p>Will you propose, Demosthenes, that we go to war, in view of your success with
                    the previous wars? Suppose the rest of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> decides on this, which is fairer: for your gold to be
                    available for war along with other people's or for others to contribute from
                    their own property, melting down the personal ornaments of their wives, the cups
                    and all the country's store of offerings to the gods, as you said you would
                    suggest, though you yourself paid in fifty drachmas from your houses in
                        <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> and the city? That has
                    been your contribution under the last levy though now you have twenty talents.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="70" type="section">
                <p>Perhaps you will not advocate war but advise us to follow out the decree which
                    you proposed and give back to Alexander the gold brought to us? If so, it will
                    be for your sake that the people have to restore it. It is surely neither just
                    nor fair nor democratic that those who work should contribute, while you plunder
                    and steal; that some should make no secret of the property they hold and make
                    contributions proportionate to it, while you who have received more than a
                    hundred and fifty talents, either from the King's money<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">See note on <bibl n="Din. 1.10">Din. 1.10</bibl>.</note> or
                    from your association with Alexander, have no declared property in the city but
                    have fortified yourself against the people as though you had no confidence in
                    your own conduct of affairs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="71" type="section">
                <p>Is it right, when the laws demand that the orator or general who expects to get
                    the people's confidence shall observe the laws in begetting children, shall own
                    land within our boundaries, shall give all the lawful pledges and only thus lay
                    claim to be the people's leader, that you should have sold the land inherited
                    from your father or be claiming as yours children which are not your own, thus
                    breaking the laws which govern oaths in court,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >A reference to the oath whereby a man called down imprecations on his
                        children, swearing that he was not guilty of a certain action. Demosthenes
                        had lost his only child, a daughter, in 336 (<bibl n="Aeschin. 3.77"
                            >Aeschin. 3.77</bibl>); and if he had other children now, they were
                        adopted or by a hetaera. Cf. <bibl n="Ath. 13.592">Athen. 13.592
                        e</bibl>.</note> and be ordering others to fight when you deserted the
                    citizens' ranks yourself? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="72" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>What do you think it is, Athenians, that makes
                    cities vary between good and evil fortunes? You will find only one cause: the
                    counsellors and leaders. Take Thebes. It was a city; it became supreme. Under
                    what leaders and generals? All the older men, on whose authority I shall give
                    you the story, would admit that it was when Pelopidas,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Pelopidas and Epaminondas were the chief Theban generals
                        during their city's period of greatness (<date from="-0371" to="-0362"
                            >371</date>-<date when="-0362">362</date> B.C.). In 371 they defeated
                            <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> at Leuctra and, in
                        response to an appeal from the Arcadians who then rose against <placeName
                            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, entered the <placeName
                            key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> in 370. Here they refounded
                        the town of <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> which the
                        Spartans had destroyed at the end of the 8th century B.C. (<bibl
                            n="Diod. 15.56">Dio. Sic. 15.56</bibl> and <bibl n="Diod. 15.62">Dio.
                            Sic. 15.62-66</bibl>). Epaminondas conducted three further invasions of
                        the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>, penetrating
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002745">Laconia</placeName>, but never actually
                        taking <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. It was probably
                        during the second of these that he founded <placeName
                            key="perseus,Megalopolis">Megalopolis</placeName>, the new capital of
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>; in the third he was
                        killed at <placeName key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName> (362
                        B.C.).</note> so they have it, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="73" type="section">
                <p>led the Sacred Band<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Sacred Band was a
                        company of 300 picked soldiers maintained by the state. They first attracted
                        attention by defeating a Spartan force in <date when="-0375">375</date> B.C.
                        and played a large part in the victory of Leuctra. At <placeName
                            key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName> they fought to the last man and
                        were buried by the highway from <placeName key="tgn,4003963"
                            >Phocis</placeName> to Thebes with the figure of a lion over their
                        tomb.</note> and Epaminondas and their compeers were in command. It was then
                    that Thebes won the battle of Leuctra, then that they invaded the Spartans'
                    country which, it was thought, could not be ravaged. During that period they
                    accomplished many fine achievements: founded <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
                        >Messene</placeName> in the four hundredth<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            ><placeName key="tgn,7011369">Messenia</placeName> was first conquered
                        about the year <date when="-0700">700</date> B.C., so that the figure 400th
                        is a very rough estimate; 300th would be nearer. Cf. <bibl n="Lyc. 1.62"
                            >Lyc. 1.62</bibl> and note.</note> year after its fall, gave the
                    Arcadians self-government, and won a universal reputation. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="74" type="section">
                <p>On the other hand when was their achievement despicable and unworthy of their
                    spirit? When Timolaus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The three men mentioned
                        in this sentence were Theban generals at the battle of <placeName
                            key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>.</note> the friend of
                    Demosthenes, was corrupted and took bribes from Philip, when the traitor
                    Proxenus commanded the mercenaries enlisted at <placeName key="perseus,Amphissa"
                        >Amphissa</placeName> and Theagenes was placed in command of the phalanx, a
                    man of ill luck and, like the defendant here, open to bribes. Then, because of
                    the three men whom I have mentioned, the whole city was destroyed and blotted
                    from the face of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. Far from being
                    false it is only too true that leaders are responsible for all the citizens'
                    good fortunes and for the reverse. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="75" type="section">
                <p>Think again, this time of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    with the same points in mind. Our city was great, renowned in <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, and worthy of our forbears, apart from
                    the well-known exploits of the past, at the time when
                            <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> triumphed, as our elders
                    tell us, in the naval battle at <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>;
                    when Iphicrates destroyed the Spartan company, when Chabrias defeated the
                    Spartan triremes at sea off <placeName key="tgn,7003909">Naxos</placeName>, when
                    Timotheus won the sea battle off <placeName key="tgn,7010886"
                        >Corcyra</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For the exploits of
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> and Timotheus compare
                            <bibl n="Din. 1.14">Din. 1.14</bibl> and note. In <date when="-0391"
                            >391</date> B.C. the Athenian general Iphicrates, on going to the relief
                        of <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, surprised and
                        almost annihilated a Spartan company. The defeat of the Spartan fleet by
                        Chabrias took place in 376 and won supremacy in the <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002675">Aegean</placeName> for <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> for over fifty years (<bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.4.61"
                            >Xen. Hell. 5.4.61</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 20.77">Dem.
                        20.77</bibl>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="76" type="section">
                <p>That was the time, Athenians, when the Spartans, once famous through the leaders
                    in whose ways they had been schooled, came humbly to our city and begged our
                    ancestors to save them; and the democracy which they had overthrown was made by
                    the counsellors, whom we then had, the first power in <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> again: deservedly, in my belief; for
                    they had found generals of the type I have just mentioned and had as advisers
                    Archinus and Cephalus of Collytus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Like
                        Cephalus, who is mentioned above (<bibl n="Din. 1.38">Din. 1.38</bibl>),
                        Archinus took a leading part in the overthrow of the Thirty in 403.</note>
                    For the only salvation of a city or a nation is to find brave men to lead it and
                    wise counsellors. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="77" type="section">
                <p>It follows then, Athenians, that if you fully recognize this fact you should not
                    surely be parties in future to Demosthenes' corruption and ill-luck or rest your
                    hopes of security on him; you need not think that you will lack brave men or
                    wise advisers. Let the anger of your forefathers be yours. Put to death this
                    robber taken in the act, this traitor who does not withhold his hands from the
                    gold brought into <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> but has
                    cast the city into the direst misfortunes, this arch-criminal of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>. Have his body cast beyond the city's
                    borders, give her fortunes a chance to mend, and then, with this accomplished,
                    expect a happier lot. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="78" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I want you also, Athenians, to hear that other
                    decree moved by Demosthenes,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">One of the several
                        decrees relating to defence proposed by Demosthenes after <placeName
                            key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>; the oracle is mentioned in the
                        speech on the False Embassy (<bibl n="Dem. 19.297">Dem. 19.297</bibl>
                        sq.).</note> the decree which this democratic statesman proposed when the
                    city was in disorder after the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                        >Chaeronea</placeName>, and also the oracle sent from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Dodona">Dodona</placeName> from Dodonian Zeus; for it has long
                    been warning you clearly to beware of your leaders and advisers. Read the oracle
                        first.<quote type="Oracle">
                        <title>Oracle</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="79" type="section">
                <p>Read that splendid decree of his.<quote n="Part of the Decree">
                        <title>Part of the Decree</title>
                    </quote><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A fine democrat indeed who arranges for
                    himself, being a brave and courageous man, to remain in arms, while he orders
                    the citizens whom he rejects for service to go off to their work or to do
                    anything else he thinks is called for. Read the rest.<quote
                        n="Rest of the Decree">
                        <title>Rest of the Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="80" type="section">
                <p>Listen to that, gentlemen of the jury. The decree says that the chosen embassies
                    shall set out. When, after the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                        >Chaeronea</placeName>, he heard that Philip intended to invade our country
                    he appointed himself an envoy, so as to escape from the city, and went off,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Dinarchus is perhaps referring to the fact that
                        after Chaeronea Demosthenes was appointed a commissioner for corn (<foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">sitw/nhs</foreign>) and went abroad to procure it (cf.
                            <bibl n="Dem. 18.248">Dem. 18.248</bibl>). Alternatively when appeals
                        for help were made by <placeName key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName> to
                        some of the islands (cf. <bibl n="Lyc. 1.42">Lyc. 1.42</bibl>) Demosthenes
                        may have served as an envoy.</note> after scraping together eight talents
                    from the treasury, without a thought about the plight we were in, at a time when
                    everyone else was contributing from his own money to ensure your protection.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="81" type="section">
                <p>That is the character of your adviser. Demosthenes has made only these two
                    journeys abroad in his life<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This statement is
                        wholly incorrect and Dinarchus appears to be contradicting himself, since in
                            <bibl n="Din. 1.12">Din. 1.12</bibl> of this speech he does not attempt
                        to refute Demosthenes' claim to have served on many embassies. By excluding
                        the words “in his life” and placing a colon after “battle” Maetzner would
                        alter the sense to: “Demosthenes has made only these two journeys abroad
                        since the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731"
                        >Chaeronea</placeName>.”</note>: one after the battle when he ran away from
                    the city, and another just recently to <placeName key="tgn,7013967"
                        >Olympia</placeName> when he wanted to use the presidency of the sacred
                    embassy as a means of meeting <placeName key="tgn,2540820"
                        >Nicanor</placeName>.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Demosthenes was the
                        chief Athenian religious envoy at the Olympic games in <date when="-0324"
                            >324</date> B.C. when <persName><surname>Nicanor</surname></persName>
                        presented Alexander's decree demanding that exiles should be allowed to
                        return to all Greek cities except Thebes. Cf. <bibl>Dio. Sic. 18.8</bibl>;
                            <bibl n="Hyp. 5">Hyp. 5 col. 18</bibl>.</note> A right thing indeed to
                    entrust the city to this man's charge, when danger confronts us! When it was
                    time to fight against the enemy, side by side with his fellows, he left his post
                    and made for home; yet when he should have stayed at home to face danger with
                    them, he offered himself as an envoy and ran away and left the city. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="82" type="section">
                <p>When ambassadors were needed for the peace he said he would not move a foot to
                    leave the city; yet when it was reported that Alexander was restoring the exiles
                    and <persName><surname>Nicanor</surname></persName> came to <placeName
                        key="tgn,7013967">Olympia</placeName> he offered himself to the council as
                    president of the sacred embassy. These are the parts he plays: on the field of
                    battle he is a stay-at-home, when others stay at home he is an ambassador, among
                    ambassadors he is a runaway.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now read the<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That some words have dropped out of the text
                        here is evident from the fact that two decrees are to be read and compared;
                        moreover the executions mentioned in <bibl n="Din. 1.83">Din. 1.83</bibl>
                        could have no connection with the decree relating to the money of Harpalus,
                        since in this case Demosthenes himself was the first to be tried (<bibl
                            n="Din. 1.106">Din. 1.106</bibl>).</note> and the decree relating to the
                    inquiry over the money proposed by Demosthenes for the Areopagus and affecting
                    both himself and you. I want you by comparing them together to realize that he
                    is demented.<quote type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="83" type="section">
                <p>Did you propose this, Demosthenes? You did; you cannot deny it. Was the council
                    given authority on your motion? It was. Have some of the citizens been executed?
                    They have. Did your decree have power over them? You cannot deny that it
                        did.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Read the decree again which Demosthenes
                    proposed against Demosthenes. Let me have your attention, gentlemen.<quote
                        type="Decree">
                        <title>Decree</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="84" type="section">
                <p>The council has found Demosthenes guilty. Need we enlarge on this? It has made
                    its report on him, Athenians. Justice demanded that, having been self-condemned,
                    he should immediately be put to death. But now that he has fallen into the hands
                    of you who have been assembled by the people and have sworn to obey the laws and
                    the people's decrees, what will you do? Will you ignore the claims of piety
                    towards the gods and the justice recognized by the world? No, Athenians, do not
                    do so. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="85" type="section">
                <p>It would be an utter disgrace if, when others no worse, and even less guilty,
                    than Demosthenes have been destroyed by his decrees, he, with his contempt for
                    you and the laws, should be at large unpunished in the city, when by his own
                    motion and the decrees which he proposed he has been convicted. The same
                    council, Athenians, the same place, the same rights have been in question. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="86" type="section">
                <p>The same orator was responsible for the misfortunes which overtook them and those
                    which will soon overtake him. He himself in the Assembly instructed this council
                    to judge his case, after calling on you as his witnesses. He made an agreement
                    with the people and proposed the decree against himself, to be kept by the
                    mother of the gods,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Dinarchus is alluding to
                        the Metroon, in which the state archives were kept. Cf. <bibl n="Lyc. 1.66"
                            >Lyc. 1.66</bibl> and note.</note> who is the city's guardian of all
                    written contracts. It would thus be impious for you to invalidate this or, after
                    swearing by the gods in the present trial, to give a vote which did not conform
                    with the actions of the gods themselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="87" type="section">
                <p>When Poseidon lost his suit against Ares over Halirrothius he abode by the
                        decision.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">According to tradition,
                        Halirrothius, son of Poseidon, was killed by Ares for trying to seduce his
                        daughter Alcippe. Poseidon accused Ares before the Areopagus but failed to
                        secure his conviction. Cf. <bibl n="Apollod. 3.14.2">Apollod.
                        3.14.2</bibl>.</note> The awful goddesses too, in their case against
                        Orestes,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Orestes, pursued by the Furies,
                        was said to have been given protection by Athena, who allowed the Areopagus
                        to try his case and herself gave the casting vote which acquitted him. Cf.
                            <bibl n="Aesch. Eum. 443">Aesch. Eum. 443</bibl> sq.; <bibl
                            n="Paus. 1.28.5">Paus. 1.28.5</bibl>.</note> abode by the judgement of
                    this council, associating themselves for the future with its reputation for
                    truth. How will you act with your claim to unrivalled piety? Will you annul the
                    decision of the council and follow the bad example of Demosthenes? You will not,
                    Athenians, if you remain in your senses. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="88" type="section">
                <p>This is no small or incidental matter that you are deciding today; the question
                    at issue is the safety of the whole city and also bribery, an evil habit and a
                    practice which is harmful to you and has always brought men to ruin. If you do
                    everything in your power to rid the city of this vice and to suppress those who
                    gladly take bribes against you, we shall be saved, with Heaven's consent. But if
                    you allow the orators to sell you, you will stand by and see them wreck the
                    city. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="89" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Demosthenes himself proposed in the Assembly,
                    clearly implying that it was a just step to take, that we should keep for
                    Alexander the money brought into <placeName key="tgn,2022058">Attica</placeName>
                    with Harpalus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl n="Din. 1.68">Din.
                            1.68</bibl> and note.</note> Tell me, sir: are we going to keep it under
                    present conditions, when you have taken twenty talents for personal use, someone
                    else fifteen, Demades six thousand gold staters, and the others the various sums
                    that have been credited to them? For sixty-four talents have already been
                    traced, for which, you must conclude, gentlemen, that these men are to be held
                    responsible. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="90" type="section">
                <p>Which is the more honorable alternative, which the more just: that all the money
                    should be kept in the treasury until the people has reached some fair decision,
                    or that the orators and certain of the generals should seize and keep it?
                    Personally I think that to keep it in the treasury is the course which all would
                    admit to be just, while no one would consider it fair for these men to retain
                    it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="91" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The statements made by the defendant, gentlemen,
                    have been numerous and very varied but never consistent. For he realizes that
                    all along you have been cheated by him with empty hopes and lying assertions and
                    that you remember his promises only so long as they are being uttered. If then
                    the city must go on enjoying the fruits of Demosthenes' wickedness and
                    ill-fortune, that we may still be plagued by an evil genius,—I can find no other
                    word for it,—we should acquiesce in the present state of affairs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="92" type="section">
                <p>But if we have any regard for our country, if we hate wicked and corrupt men and
                    want our fortune to change for the better, you must not surrender yourselves,
                    Athenians, to the prayers of this accursed juggler or lend an ear to his laments
                    and quackeries. You have had enough experience of him, his speeches, his
                    actions, and his luck. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="93" type="section">
                <p>Which of you is so hopeful, Athenians, or so irrational, which of you is so
                    unversed in past or present history, as to expect that a man who reduced the
                    city, through whatever fault or fortune,—I am not concerned with that,—from such
                    great prosperity to such utter disgrace, will save us now by serving as a
                    counsellor and administrator? For besides the other difficulties and dangers
                    which beset us we have now corruption also, of men right in the city, and are
                    one and all striving to clear ourselves of a shameful charge, lest the people be
                    thought to hold in their own name the money which certain individuals are
                    keeping for themselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="94" type="section">
                <p>I am not citing other instances of his continual change of policy or of the
                    pernicious speeches which he has consistently made. At one time he made a
                    proposal forbidding anyone to believe in any but the accepted gods and at
                    another said that the people must not question the grant of divine honors to
                        Alexander<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Demosthenes had merely said: “Let
                        him be the son of Zeus and Poseidon too if he likes.” Cf. <bibl n="Hyp. 5"
                            >Hyp. 5 col. 31</bibl>.</note>; and again when he was on the point of
                    being tried before you, he impeached Callimedon for consorting with the
                        exiles<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName key="tgn,7001393"
                            >Athens</placeName>, unlike most Greek cities, refused to obey
                        Alexander's order for the restoration of exiles (cf. note on <bibl
                            n="Din. 1.81">Din. 1.81</bibl>). Callimedon, a politician with
                        pro-Macedonian sympathies, nicknamed the Crab, is mentioned several times by
                        Plutarch (e.g. <bibl n="Plut. Dem. 27">Plut. Dem. 27</bibl>).</note> in
                        <placeName key="tgn,7017133">Megara</placeName> with intent to overthrow the
                    democracy, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="95" type="section">
                <p>and directly after countermanded the impeachment and brought forward at the
                    recent sitting of the Assembly a false witness whom he had primed to say that
                    there was a plot afoot threatening the docks. In all this he offered no
                    proposals but simply furnished us with charges for the present trial, since on
                    all these points you are witnesses against him. This man is a juggler,
                    Athenians, and a blackguard, not entitled to be a citizen of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7001393">Athens</placeName>, either by virtue of his birth or of
                    his political record. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="96" type="section">
                <p>Where are the triremes which Demosthenes, like Eubulus<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">For the confidence inspired by Eubulus, son of Spintharus,
                        who controlled Athenian finances from 354 to <date when="-0350">350</date>
                        B.C., and perhaps for a further period also, compare <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.25"
                            >Aeschin. 3.25</bibl>.</note> in his time, has supplied to the city?
                    Where are the dockyards built under his administration? When did he improve the
                    cavalry either by decree or law? Despite such opportunities as were offered
                    after the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, did he
                    raise a single force either for land or sea? What ornament for the goddess has
                    he carried up to the Acropolis? What building has Demosthenes put up, either in
                    your exchange, or in the city, or anywhere else in the country? Not a man could
                    point to one anywhere. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="97" type="section">
                <p>Very well; if a person has proved untrustworthy in military matters and useless
                    in the business of the city, if he has idly watched his opponents accomplish
                    everything they wished, changing his own position and neglecting to pursue the
                    people's interests, will you wish to preserve him? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="98" type="section">
                <p>Not if you are prudent and make the right decision for yourselves and <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. No; you will welcome the good
                    fortune which gave up to you for punishment those orators who, through their own
                    bribery, have humiliated the city, and will beware, as the gods have often
                    cautioned you in oracles, against the leaders and counsellors of this type.
                    Listen to the oracle itself. Read the oracle.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Cf. <bibl n="Din. 1.78">Din. 1.78</bibl>.</note><quote type="Oracle">
                        <title>Oracle</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="99" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>How then shall we be of one mind, Athenians? How
                    shall we agree upon the interests of the state when our leaders and demagogues
                    take bribes and betray their country's interests, when you yourselves and the
                    whole people are in danger of losing the very foundations of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, together with your fathers' temples
                    and your wives and children, while they have conspired together, so that in the
                    assemblies they purposely abuse and lose their tempers with each other, though
                    in private they are united and thus deceive you, who are so ready to lend an ear
                    to what they say. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="100" type="section">
                <p>What is the duty of a democratic orator, hating those who menace the city by
                    speech or bill? What are we told, Demosthenes and Polyeuctus, about your
                    predecessors? What did they always do, even though no danger threatened the city
                    at the time? Did they not summon each other for trial; bring in impeachments?
                    Did they not indict each other for illegal proposals? Have you, who profess to
                    have the people at heart, and maintain that your safety rests upon this jury's
                    vote, done a single one of these things? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="101" type="section">
                <p>Have you denounced a decree, Demosthenes, despite the many outrageous and illegal
                    measures which Demades has proposed? Have you prevented any political step among
                    those which he has taken on his own initiative against the interests of the
                    state? Not a single one. Have you impeached this man who has often acted
                    contrary to the decrees of the people and the laws? Never. You allowed him to
                    have his statue set up in bronze in the market and to share entertainment in the
                    Prytaneum with the descendants of Harmodius and Aristogiton.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">These honors were paid to Demades about <date when="-0335"
                            >335</date> B.C. in recognition of his mission to Alexander after the
                        destruction of Thebes. Cf. Life of Demades</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="102" type="section">
                <p>In what way then did the people sample your goodwill, where did we see proof of
                    the orator's protecting power? Or will you all maintain that herein lie your
                    powers: to cheat these men by persisting that you cannot leave the country, that
                    you have no other refuge than our goodwill? You ought first to have made it
                    clear that in speech and action you opposed the decrees brought forward against
                    the people's interests and then sought to convince these men that your claim to
                    have no means of safety but the assistance offered by the people was true. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="103" type="section">
                <p>But you place your hopes abroad and compete in flattery with those who admit that
                    they are serving Alexander and have taken bribes from the same sources as those
                    from which you are reported by the council to have received them. And you,
                    Demosthenes, after conversing with Nicanor in front of all the Greeks and
                    settling everything you wanted, now make yourself out to be in need of pity,
                    traitor though you are and a receiver of bribes; as if these men will forget
                    your wickedness, as if you will not pay the penalty for the crimes at which you
                    have been caught. You are acting more boldly than Demades to this extent, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="104" type="section">
                <p>that though he has given warning in the Assembly of his desperate character and
                    admits that he accepts money and will continue to do so, still he has not dared
                    to show his face before these men and did not presume to dispute the council's
                    report; moreover he did not propose that the council should have authority over
                    him or lay down the death penalty if he should be proved to have taken bribes.
                    But you have such complete confidence in your own arguments and such a contempt
                    for these men's simplicity that you expect to persuade the jury that in your
                    case only has the council's statement been false and that you alone of those
                    whom it reported have not accepted the gold. Who could believe that? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="105" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Let me explain, Athenians, what you are going to
                    do. You have taken over the case from the people, who know the facts; and to
                    undergo the punishment, due to those whose names appear in the reports,
                    Demosthenes is brought in first. We have made our accusation and have allowed no
                    private interest on the part of any to stand in the way of common justice. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="106" type="section">
                <p>Will you disregard all that has passed and acquit the first man up before you?
                    Will you, with full power at your command, reject what seemed just both to the
                    people and the Areopagus, and indeed to everyone, and take upon yourselves these
                    men's depravity? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="107" type="section">
                <p>Or will you, for the city's sake, give a demonstration to all alike of the hatred
                    you bear towards traitors and those who, through love of gain, betray the
                    people's interests? All this now lies in your control, and the fifteen hundred
                    of you hold the city's safety in your hands. Your verdict of today will either
                    bring to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> great security, if
                    you are willing to make a just decision, or else, if you endorse such practices
                    as this, drive all men to despondency. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="108" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>You must not be cowed, Athenians, or by losing
                    your self-control give up the city's just defence, which touches all alike, in
                    deference to Demosthenes' entreaties. For none of you compelled this man to take
                    the money, to which he had no right, against your own interests, when he has
                    acquired, with your assistance, much more than enough besides, nor to defend
                    himself now when the crimes have been acknowledged and he has proposed the death
                    penalty for himself. But the avarice and wickedness, fostered in him by his
                    whole mode of life, have brought this on his head. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="109" type="section">
                <p>So do not be concerned when he weeps and laments. You might, with far more
                    justice, pity the country, which this man is exposing to danger by behaving as
                    he has, and which is begging you, who are its sons, in the names of your wives
                    and children, to take vengeance on the traitor and save it: the land which your
                    ancestors, after facing many noble combats for it, have handed on to you free in
                    which many noble examples have been left us of the courage of those who gave
                    their lives. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="110" type="section">
                <p>It is this land, Athenians, the sacrifices traditional in it, and its ancestral
                    sepulchres to which right-thinking men must turn their thoughts when they give
                    their vote. And when Demosthenes wishes to cheat you and cunningly turns
                    pathetic, shedding tears, you must think of the city's person, and the glory
                    which it once possessed, and judge between two alternatives: which has become
                    the more deserving of pity: the city because of Demosthenes or Demosthenes
                    because of the city? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="111" type="section">
                <p>You will find that this man has become famous since he entered politics; that
                    from being a speechwriter and a paid advocate, in the service of Ctesippus,
                    Phormio and many others,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Demosthenes was acting
                        in the interests of Ctesippus, son of Chabrias, when he attacked the Law of
                        Leptines in <date when="-0355">355</date> B.C. The Phormio referred to is
                        possibly the freedman of the banker Pasion whom he defended in 350. Cf.
                            <bibl n="Dem. 20">Dem. 20</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 36">Dem.
                        36</bibl>.</note> he has become the richest man in <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; that after being an unknown figure,
                    inheriting no family honor from his ancestors, he is now famous, while the city
                    has reached a pass unworthy of herself or the honor of our forbears. Therefore
                    ignore this man's entreaties and deceptions, bring in the verdict that is just
                    and right, having regard for your country's interest, as befits an honorable
                    jury, not the welfare of Demosthenes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="112" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And whenever anyone comes forward to speak for
                    him, bear in mind that he who does so, even if not involved in the reports we
                    are about to hear, is hostile to the constitution, unwilling to see punished
                    those who take bribes against the people and anxious that the general protection
                    of your persons, for which the Areopagus is responsible, should be abolished and
                    every right in the city overwhelmed; whereas, if it is some orator or general,
                    one of those participating in the defence because they wish to discredit the
                    report, which they expect will reflect against themselves, you must give their
                    arguments no credence, knowing as you do that all these men collaborated over
                    the landing of Harpalus and his release. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="113" type="section">
                <p>You must realize then, Athenians, that when these men come forward, they do so
                    against your interests, being enemies alike of the laws and the entire city. Do
                    not tolerate them; insist that their defence answers the charges. And do not
                    countenance his own fury either; for he prides himself on his powers as an
                    orator and, since he is known to have taken bribes against you, has been proved
                    an even greater fraud. No, punish him in a manner befitting yourselves and the
                    city. If you do not, by one verdict and at one trial you will release all who
                    have been reported, and all who ever will be, and will bring these men's
                    corruption upon yourselves and upon the people, even though, afterwards, you may
                    prosecute those who acquitted them, when it will avail you nothing. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="114" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I have now played my full part in assisting the
                    prosecution and have shown regard for nothing but justice and your interests. I
                    have not deserted the city or given more weight to personal favor than to the
                    people's vote. With an appeal to you to show the same spirit I now hand over the
                    water to the other prosecutors.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
