<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Apology</title>
                <author>Xenophon</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB Project</funder>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>


            <notesStmt>
                <note anchored="true">Text entered in Philipines 1990.</note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Xenophon</author>
                        <title>Xenophon in Seven Volumes, 4</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA; William Heinemann,
                                Ltd., London.</publisher>
                            <date>1979</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-11-09" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion work</change>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split speeches and converted to unicode</change>
            <change when="1992-10-30" who="DAS">added HEAD's and REFDECL's; glued minor works together</change>
            <change when="1992-08-11" who="DAS">changed chapters to div2's</change>
            <change when="1992-06-01" who="EM and WPM">tagged text to conform with prose.e dtd. Entered sections. Scanned and inserted text that had dropped out; sections 22-32.</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            
            <div type="edition" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg005.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It seems to me fitting to hand down to memory,
                    furthermore, how <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, on being
                    indicted, deliberated on his defence and on his end. It is true that others have
                    written about this, and that all of them have reproduced the loftiness of his
                    words,—a fact which proves that his utterance really was of the character
                    intimated;—but they have not shown clearly that he had now come to the
                    conclusion that for him death was more to be desired than life; and hence his
                    lofty utterance appears rather ill-considered. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
                <p>Hermogenes, the son of Hipponicus, however, was a companion of his and has given
                    us reports of such a nature as to show that the sublimity of his speech was
                    appropriate to the resolve he had made. For he stated that on seeing
                            <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> discussing any and
                    every subject rather than the trial, he had said: </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
                <p><said direct="true"><persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, ought you not to be giving
                    some thought to what defence you are going to make?</said> That
                            <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> had at first replied,
                    <said direct="true">Why, do I not seem to you to have spent my whole life in preparing to defend
                    myself?</said> Then when he asked, <said direct="true">How so?</said> he had said, <said direct="true">Because all my life I have
                    been guiltless of wrong-doing; and that I consider the finest preparation for a
                    defence.</said> Then when Hermogenes again asked, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
                <p><said direct="true">Do you not observe that the Athenian courts have often been carried away by an
                    eloquent speech and have condemned innocent men to death, and often on the other
                    hand the guilty have been acquitted either because their plea aroused compassion
                    or because their speech was witty?</said> <said direct="true">Yes, indeed!</said> he had answered; <said direct="true">and I have
                    tried twice already to meditate on my defence, but my divine sign interposes.</said>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
                <p>And when Hermogenes observed, <said direct="true">That is a surprising statement,</said> he had replied,
                    <said direct="true">Do you think it surprising that even God holds it better for me to die now? Do
                    you not know that I would refuse to concede that any man has lived a better life
                    than I have up to now? For I have realized that my whole life has been spent in
                    righteousness toward God and man,—a fact that affords the greatest satisfaction;
                    and so I have felt a deep self-respect and have discovered that my associates
                    hold corresponding sentiments toward me.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
                <p><said direct="true" rend="merge">But now, if my years are prolonged, I know that the frailties of old age will
                    inevitably be realized,—that my vision must be less perfect and my hearing less
                    keen, that I shall be slower to learn and more forgetful of what I have learned.
                    If I perceive my decay and take to complaining, how,</said> he had continued, <said direct="true">could I
                    any longer take pleasure in life?</said></p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
                <p><said direct="true" rend="merge">Perhaps,</said> he added, <said direct="true"
                            >God in his kindness is taking my part and securing me the opportunity
                            of ending my life not only in season but also in the way that is
                            easiest. For if I am condemned now, it will clearly be my privilege to
                            suffer a death that is adjudged by those who have superintended this
                            matter to be not only the easiest but also the least irksome to one’s
                            friends and one that implants in them the deepest feeling of loss for
                            the dead. For when a person leaves behind in the hearts of his
                            companions no remembrance to cause a blush or a pang, but dissolution
                            comes while he still possesses a sound body and a spirit capable of
                            showing kindliness, how could such a one fail to be sorely
                            missed?</said>
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
                <p><said direct="true" rend="merge">It was with good reason,</said> Socrates had continued, <said direct="true">that the gods opposed<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note on p. 494.</note> my studying up my
                    speech at the time when we held that by fair means or foul we must find some
                    plea that would effect my acquittal. For if I had achieved this end, it is clear
                    that instead of now passing out of life, I should merely have provided for dying
                    in the throes of illness or vexed by old age, the sink into which all distresses
                    flow, unrelieved by any joy.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
                <p><said direct="true" rend="merge">As Heaven is my witness, Hermogenes,</said> he had gone on, <said direct="true">I shall never court that
                    fate; but if I am going to offend the jury by declaring all the blessings that I
                    feel gods and men have bestowed on me, as well as my personal opinion of myself,
                    I shall prefer death to begging meanly for longer life and thus gaining a life
                    far less worthy in exchange for death.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hermogenes stated that with this resolve Socrates
                    came before the jury after his adversaries had charged him with not believing in
                    the gods worshipped by the state and with the introduction of new deities in
                    their stead and with corruption of the young, and replied: </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
                <p><said direct="true">One thing that I marvel at in Meletus, gentlemen, is what may be the basis of
                    his assertion that I do not believe in the gods worshipped by the state; for all
                    who have happened to be near at the time, as well as Meletus himself,—if he so
                    desired, — have seen me sacrificing at the communal festivals and on the public
                    altars.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
                <p><said direct="true">As for introducing <q type="soCalled">new divinities,</q> how
                            could I be guilty of that merely in asserting that a voice of God is
                            made manifest to me indicating my duty? Surely those who take their
                            omens from the cries of birds and the utterances of men form their
                            judgments on <q type="soCalled">voices.</q> Will any one dispute either
                            that thunder utters its <q type="soCalled">voice,</q> or that it is an
                            omen of the greatest moment? Does not the very priestess who sits on the
                            tripod at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName> divulge the
                            god’s will through a <q type="soCalled">voice</q>? </said></p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
                <p><said direct="true">But more than that, in regard to God’s foreknowledge of the
                            future and his forewarning thereof to whomsoever he will, these are the
                            same terms, I assert, that all men use, and this is their belief. The
                            only difference between them and me is that whereas they call the
                            sources of their forewarning <q type="emph">birds,</q>
                            <q type="emph">utterances,</q>
                            <q type="emph">chance meetings,</q>
                            <q type="emph">prophets,</q> I call mine a <q type="emph">divine</q>
                                thing;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Or <q type="emph">divine
                                    sign.</q> Here, as earlier, the mere adjective is used; but in
                                        <persName><surname>Plato</surname></persName>’s
                                    <title>Theages</title> (<bibl n="Plat. Theag. 128d">Plat. Theag.
                                    128 D</bibl> ff.) and <title>Apology</title> (<bibl
                                    n="Plat. Apol. 31d">Plat. Apol. 31 D</bibl>) this admonitory
                                something is described as a voice sent by heavenly dispensation, and
                                is called variously <q type="emph">the sign</q> (<bibl
                                    n="Plat. Apol. 41d">Plat. Apol. 41 D</bibl>), <q type="emph">the
                                    usual sign</q> (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 40c">Plat. Apol. 40
                                    C</bibl>), <q type="emph">the divine sign</q> (<bibl
                                    n="Plat. Rep. 496c">Plat. Rep. 496 C</bibl>), <q type="emph">the
                                    usual divine sign</q> (<bibl n="Plat. Euthyd. 272e">Plat.
                                    Euthyd. 272 E</bibl>, <bibl n="Plat. Phaedrus 242b">Plat.
                                    Phaedr. 242 B</bibl>, <bibl n="Plat. Theag. 129b">Plat. Theag.
                                    129 B</bibl>), <q type="emph">the sign from God</q> (<bibl
                                    n="Plat. Apol. 40b">Plat. Apol. 40 B</bibl>), <q type="emph"
                                    >something God-sent and divine</q> (<bibl n="Plat. Apol. 31d"
                                    >Plat. Apol. 31 D</bibl>). Plato reports
                                        <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>’
                                description of this as a voice not directing his actions but serving
                                only as a deterrent when he or his friends were contemplating doing
                                something inadvisable.</note> and I think that in using such a term
                            I am speaking with more truth and deeper religious feeling than do those
                            who ascribe the gods’ power to birds. Now that I do not lie against God
                            I have the following proof: I have revealed to many of my friends the
                            counsels which God has given me, and in no instance has the event shown
                            that I was mistaken.</said>
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hermogenes further reported that when the jurors
                    raised a clamour at hearing these words, some of them disbelieving his
                    statements, others showing jealousy at his receiving greater favours even from
                    the gods than they, <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> resumed:
                    <said direct="true">Hark ye; let me tell you something more, so that those of you who feel so
                    inclined may have still greater disbelief in my being honoured of Heaven. Once
                    on a time when Chaerephon<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A very enthusiastic
                        follower of <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>.</note> made
                    inquiry at the Delphic oracle concerning me, in the presence of many people
                    Apollo answered that no man was more free than I, or more just, or more
                    prudent.</said></p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When the jurors, naturally enough, made a still
                        greater tumult on hearing this statement, he said that
                                <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> again went on:
                            <said direct="true">And yet, gentlemen, the god uttered in oracles
                            greater things of Lycurgus, the Lacedaemonian law-giver, than he did of
                            me. For there is a legend that, as Lycurgus entered the temple, the god
                            thus addressed him: ‘I am pondering whether to call you god or man.’ Now
                            Apollo did not compare me to a god; he did, however, judge that I far
                            excelled the rest of mankind. However, do not believe the god even in
                            this without due grounds, but examine the god’s utterance in
                            detail.</said>
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
                <p>First, who is there in your knowledge that is less a slave to his bodily
                    appetites than I am? Who in the world more free,—for I accept neither gifts nor
                    pay from any one? Whom would you with reason regard as more just than the one so
                    reconciled to his present possessions as to want nothing beside that belongs to
                    another? And would not a person with good reason call me a wise man, who from
                    the time when I began to understand spoken words have never left off seeking
                    after and learning every good thing that I could? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
                <p>And that my labour has not been in vain do you not think is attested by this
                    fact, that many of my fellow-citizens who strive for virtue and many from abroad
                    choose to associate with me above all other men? And what shall we say is
                    accountable for this fact, that although everybody knows that it is quite
                    impossible for me to repay with money, many people are eager to make me some
                    gift? Or for this, that no demands are made on me by a single person for the
                    repayment of benefits, while many confess that they owe me a debt of gratitude?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
                <p>Or for this, that during the siege,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The blockade
                            of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> by the Spartans in
                            the last year of the Peloponnesian War.</note> while others were
                        commiserating their lot, I got along without feeling the pinch of poverty
                        any worse than when the city’s prosperity was at its height? Or for this,
                        that while other men get their delicacies in the markets and pay a high
                        price for them, I devise more pleasurable ones from the resources of my
                        soul, with no expenditure of money? And now, if no one can convict me of
                        misstatement in all that I have said of myself, do I not unquestionably
                        merit praise from both gods and men? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
                <p>But in spite of all, Meletus, do you maintain that I corrupt the young by such
                    practices? And yet surely we know what kinds of corruption affect the young; so
                    you tell us whether you know of any one who under my influence has fallen from
                    piety into impiety, or from sober into wanton conduct, or from moderation in
                    living into extravagance, or from temperate drinking into sottishness, or from
                    strenuousness into effeminacy, or has been overcome of any other base pleasure.”
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
                <p><said direct="true">But, by Heaven!</said> said Meletus: <said direct="true">there is one set of men I know,—those whom you
                    have persuaded to obey you rather than their parents.</said> <said direct="true">I admit it,</said> he reports
                            <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> as replying, <said direct="true">at least
                    so far as education is concerned; for people know that I have taken an interest
                    in that. But in a question of health, men take the advice of physicians rather
                    than that of their parents; and moreover, in the meetings of the legislative
                    assembly all the people of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    without question, follow the advice of those whose words are wisest rather than
                    that of their own relatives. Do you not also elect for your generals, in
                    preference to fathers and brothers,—yes, by Heaven! in preference to your very
                    selves,—those whom you regard as having the greatest wisdom in military
                    affairs?</said> <said direct="true">Yes,</said> Meletus had said; <said direct="true">for that is both expedient and
                    conventional.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
                <p><said direct="true">Well, then,</said>
                        <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> had rejoined, <said
                            direct="true">does it not seem to you an amazing thing that while in
                            other activities those who excel receive honours not merely on a parity
                            with their fellows but even more marked ones, yet I, because I am
                            adjudged by some people supreme in what is man’s greatest
                            blessing,—education,—am being prosecuted by you on a capital
                            charge?</said>
                    </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>More than this of course was said both by
                                <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> himself and by the
                        friends who joined in his defence. But I have not made it a point to report
                        the whole trial; rather I am satisfied to make it clear that while
                                <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>’ whole concern was
                        to keep free from any act of impiety toward the gods or any appearance of
                        wrong-doing toward man, he did not think it meet to beseech the jury to let
                        him escape death; instead, he believed that the time had now come for him to
                        die. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
                <p>This conviction of his became more evident than ever after the adverse issue of
                    the trial. For, first of all, when he was bidden to name his penalty, he refused
                    personally and forbade his friends to name one, but said that naming the penalty
                    in itself implied an acknowledgment of guilt. Then, when his companions wished
                    to remove him clandestinely from prison, he would not accompany them, but seemed
                    actually to banter them, asking them whether they knew of any spot outside of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> that was inaccessible to
                    death. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>When the trial was over,
                            <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName> (according to
                    Hermogenes) remarked: <said direct="true">Well, gentlemen, those who instructed the witnesses that
                    they must bear false witness against me, perjuring themselves to do so, and
                    those who were won over to do this must feel in their hearts a guilty
                    consciousness of great impiety and iniquity; but as for me, why should my spirit
                    be any less exalted now than before my condemnation, since I have not been
                    proved guilty of having done any of the acts mentioned in the indictment? For it
                    has not been shown that I have sacrificed to new deities in the stead of Zeus
                    and Hera and the gods of their company, or that I have invoked ill oaths or
                    mentioned other gods.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
                <p><said direct="true" rend="merge">And how could I be corrupting the young by habituating them to fortitude and
                    frugality? Now of all the acts for which the laws have prescribed the
                    death-penalty—temple robbery, burglary, enslavement, treason to the state—not
                    even my adversaries themselves charge me with having committed any of these. And
                    so it seems astonishing to me how you could ever have been convinced that I had
                    committed an act meriting death.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
                <p><said direct="true" rend="merge">But further, my spirit need not be less exalted because l am to be executed
                    unjustly; for the ignominy of that attaches not to me but to those who condemned
                    me. And I get comfort from the case of Palamedes<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">One of the Greek warriors at <placeName key="perseus,Troy"
                            >Troy</placeName>; put to death on a charge of treason trumped up by
                        Odysseus, or by Odysseus, Diomedes, and Agamemnon.</note> also, who died in
                    circumstances similar to mine; for even yet he affords us far more noble themes
                    for song than does Odysseus, the man who unjustly put him to death. And I know
                    that time to come as well as time past will attest that I, too, far from ever
                    doing any man a wrong or rendering him more wicked, have rather profited those
                    who conversed with me by teaching them, without reward, every good thing that
                    lay in my power.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>With these words he departed, blithe in glance, in
                    mien, in gait, as comported well indeed with the words he had just uttered. When
                    he noticed that those who accompanied him were in tears, <said direct="true">What is this?</said>
                    Hermogenes reports him as asking. <said direct="true">Are you just now beginning to weep? Have you
                    not known all along that from the moment of my birth nature had condemned me to
                    death? Verily, if I am being destroyed before my time while blessings are still
                    pouring in upon me, clearly that should bring grief to me and to my
                    well-wishers; but if I am ending my life when only troubles are in view, my own
                    opinion is that you ought all to feel cheered, in the assurance that my state is
                    happy.</said></p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>A man named Apollodorus, who was there with him, a
                        very ardent disciple of <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>,
                        but otherwise simple, exclaimed, <said direct="true">But,
                                    <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, what I find it
                            hardest to bear is that I see you being put to death unjustly!</said>
                        The other, stroking Apollodorus’ head, is said to have replied, <said
                            direct="true">My beloved Apollodorus, was it your preference to see me
                            put to death justly?</said> and smiled as he asked the question. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>It is said also that he remarked as he saw
                            Anytus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">One of the three plaintiffs in
                                    <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>’ trial.</note>
                        passing by: <said direct="true">There goes a man who is filled with pride at
                            the thought that he has accomplished some great and noble end in putting
                            me to death, because, seeing him honored by the state with the highest
                            offices, I said that he ought not to confine his son’s education to
                                hides<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The tanning trade had been in
                                the family from at least the time of the boy’s grandfather.</note>
                            What a vicious, fellow,</said> he continued, <said direct="true">not to
                            know, apparently, that whichever one of us has wrought the more
                            beneficial and noble deeds for all time, he is the real
                        victor.</said></p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
                <p><said direct="true" rend="merge">But,</said> he is reported to have added, <said direct="true">Homer has attributed to some of his heroes
                    at the moment of dissolution the power to foresee the future; and so I too wish
                    to utter a prophecy.At one time I had a brief association with the son of
                    Anytus, and I thought him not lacking in firmness of spirit; and so I predict
                    that he will not continue in the servile occupation that his father has provided
                    for him; but through want of a worthy adviser he will fall into some disgraceful
                    propensity and will surely go far in the career of vice.</said> </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
                <p>In saying this he was not mistaken; the young man, delighting in wine, never left
                        off drinking night or day, and at last turned out worth nothing to his city,
                        his friends, or himself. So Anytus, even though dead, still enjoys an evil
                        repute for his son’s mischievous education and for his own hard-heartedness. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
                <p>And as for <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, by exalting himself
                    before the court, he brought ill-will upon himself and made his conviction by
                    the jury more certain. Now to me he seems to have met a fate that the gods love;
                    for he escaped the hardest part of life and met the easiest sort of death. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
                <p>And he displayed the stalwart nature of his heart; for having once decided that
                    to die was better for him than to live longer, he did not weaken in the presence
                    of death (just as he had never set his face against any other thing, either,
                    that was for his good), but was cheerful not only in the expectation of death
                    but in meeting it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And so, in contemplating the man’s wisdom and
                        nobility of character, I find it beyond my power to forget him or, in
                        remembering him, to refrain from praising him. And if among those who make
                        virtue their aim any one has ever been brought into contact with a person
                        more helpful than <persName><surname>Socrates</surname></persName>, I count
                        that man worthy to be called most blessed.</p>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>

</TEI>
