<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>First Olynthiac</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <editor role="translator">J. H. Vince</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">1996</date>
            </publicationStmt> 			
            <notesStmt><note>Perseus 2.0</note></notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes. Vol. I. Olynthiacs, Philippics, Minor Public Speeches, Speech Against Leptines, I-XVII, XX. With an English translation by J. H. Vince</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date type="printing">1930</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.12682">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
            <change when="1992-06-02" who="David Smith">inserted quotedtext tag around verse</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>You would, I expect, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    accept it as the equivalent of a large amount of money, if it could be made
                    clear to you what will prove our best policy in the matters now under
                    discussion. This then being so, you are bound to give an eager hearing to all
                    who offer advice. For not only if someone comes forward with a well-considered
                    plan, could you hear and accept it, but also I count it part of your good
                    fortune that more than one speaker may be inspired with suitable suggestions on
                    the spur of the moment, so that out of the multitude of proposals the choice of
                    the best should not be difficult. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>The present crisis, Athenians, calls on you, almost with an audible voice, to
                    take into your own hands the control of your interests in the North, if you are
                    really anxious to safeguard them. But, I confess, our attitude puzzles me. My
                    own idea would be to vote an expedition at once, to make instant preparation for
                    its dispatch, thus avoiding our previous blunder, and to send ambassadors to
                    state our intentions and watch events. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>Our chief ground for alarm is that this man, so unscrupulous, so quick to seize
                    his opportunity, now yielding a point when it suits his purpose, now
                    threatening—and his threats may well carry conviction—now misrepresenting us and
                    our failure to intervene, may divert to his own purpose and wrest from us
                    something of vital importance. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>And yet, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, it is
                    reasonable to suggest that the very thing which makes Philip's position most
                    redoubtable is also most encouraging for you. For the swift and opportune
                    movements of war he has an immense advantage over us in the fact that he is the
                    sole director of his own policy, open or secret, that he unites the functions of
                    a general, a ruler and a treasurer, and that he is always at the head of his
                    army; but when it comes to a composition such as he would gladly make with
                        <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>, the tables are
                    turned. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>The eyes of the Olynthians are opened to the fact that they are now fighting not
                    for glory, not for a strip of territory, but to avert the overthrow and
                    enslavement of their fatherland. They know how he treated those Amphipolitans
                    who betrayed their city and those Pydnaeans who opened their gates to him. And a
                    despotism, I take it, is as a rule mistrusted by free constitutions, especially
                    when they are near neighbors. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>I bid you grasp these facts, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, and weigh well all the important considerations. Make
                    up your minds; rouse your spirits; put your heart into the war, now or never.
                    Pay your contributions cheerfully; serve in person; leave nothing to chance. You
                    have no longer the shadow of an excuse for shirking your duty. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>It was long the common talk that the Olynthians must be made to fight Philip; and
                    now it has come about in the natural course, and that too in a way that suits
                    you admirably. For if they had plunged into war in reliance on your advice, they
                    would perhaps have proved uncertain allies and only half-hearted in their
                    resolve; but now that their hatred of Philip is the outcome of their own
                    grievances, it is natural that their hostility should have a firm base in their
                    apprehensions and their experiences. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you must not let slip
                    the opportunity that offers, nor make the blunder you have so often made before.
                    When we returned from the Euboean expedition<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >The Athenians took <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> from the
                        Thebans in 357.</note> and Hierax and Stratocles, the envoys of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, mounted this platform and
                    bade you sail and take over their city, if we had shown the same earnestness in
                    our own cause as in defence of the safety of <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                        >Euboea</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
                        >Amphipolis</placeName> would have been yours at once and you would have
                    been relieved of all your subsequent difficulties. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>Once again, when news came of the siege of <placeName key="perseus,Pydna"
                        >Pydna</placeName>, of <placeName key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName>, of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Methone">Methone</placeName>, of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7012084">Pagasae</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In
                        357, 356, 354, and 352 respectively.</note> and of the rest of them—not to
                    weary you with a complete catalogue—if we had at that time shown the required
                    zeal in marching to the help of the first that appealed, we should have found
                    Philip today much more humble and accommodating. Unfortunately we always neglect
                    the present chance and imagine that the future will right itself, and so, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, Philip has us to thank
                    for his prosperity. We have raised him to a greater height than ever king of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> reached before. Today
                    this opportunity comes to us from the Olynthians unsought, a fairer opportunity
                    than we have ever had before. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, let anyone fairly
                    reckon up the blessings we have received of the gods, and though much is amiss,
                    none the less his gratitude will be great—and rightly so: for our many losses in
                    the war<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. the war about the possession of
                            <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>.</note> may
                    be justly imputed to our own supineness; that we did not suffer these losses
                    long ago and that this opportunity of alliance affords us some compensation, if
                    we choose to accept it, this I for my part should put down as a signal instance
                    of the favor of the gods. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>I suppose it is with national as with private wealth. If a man keeps what he
                    gains, he is duly grateful to fortune; if he loses it by his own imprudence, he
                    loses along with it the sense of gratitude. So in national affairs, those who
                    fail to use their opportunities aright, fail also to acknowledge the good that
                    the gods have given; for every advantage in the past is judged in the light of
                    the final issue. It is therefore our duty, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to keep a careful eye on the
                    future, that by restoring our prosperity we may efface the discredit of the
                    past.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>But if we leave these men too in the lurch, Athenians, and then <placeName
                        key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> is crushed by Philip, tell me
                    what is to prevent him from marching henceforward just where he pleases. I
                    wonder if any one of you in this audience watches and notes the steps by which
                    Philip, weak at first, has grown so powerful. First he seized <placeName
                        key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, next <placeName
                        key="perseus,Pydna">Pydna</placeName>, then <placeName key="tgn,6004814"
                        >Potidaea</placeName>, after that <placeName key="perseus,Methone"
                        >Methone</placeName>, lastly he invaded <placeName key="tgn,7001399"
                        >Thessaly</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>Then having settled Pherae, <placeName key="tgn,7012084">Pagasae</placeName>,
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002751">Magnesia</placeName>, and the rest of that
                    country to suit his purposes, off he went to <placeName key="tgn,7002756"
                        >Thrace</placeName>, and there, after evicting some of the chiefs and
                    installing others, he fell sick. On his recovery, he did not relapse into
                    inactivity, but instantly assailed <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                        >Olynthus</placeName>. His campaigns against Illyrians and Paeonians and
                    King Arybbas and any others that might be mentioned, I pass over in silence.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>“Well,” some of you may say, “why tell us this now?” Because, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I want you to know and realize two
                    things: first, what an expensive game it is to squander your interests one by
                    one; and secondly, the restless activity which is ingrained in Philip's nature,
                    and which makes it impossible for him ever to rest on his laurels. But if Philip
                    adopts the principle that he ought always to be improving his position, and you
                    the principle of never facing your difficulties resolutely, just reflect what is
                    likely to be the end of it all. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>Seriously, is anyone here so foolish as not to see that our negligence will
                    transfer the war from <placeName key="tgn,7002716">Chalcidice</placeName> to
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>? Yet if that comes to pass,
                    I am afraid, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that
                    just as men who borrow money recklessly at high interest enjoy a temporary
                    accommodation only to forfeit their estates in the end, so we may find that we
                    have paid a heavy price for our indolence, and because we consult our own
                    pleasure in everything, may hereafter come to be forced to do many of the
                    dfficult things for which we had no liking, and may finally endanger our
                    possessions here in <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> itself. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>Now someone may tell me that to find fault is easy and in any one's power, but
                    that it needs a statesman to expound the policy demanded by our circumstances.
                    But I am not unaware, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    that if anything goes wrong, you often vent your disappointment, not on the
                    responsible agents, but on those who happen to have addressed you last. I shall
                    not, however, consult my own safety by keeping back what I believe to be for
                    your true interests. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>I suggest then that the case calls for two distinct expeditions; one military
                    force must be dispatched to rescue their cities for the Olynthians, and a second
                    force, both naval and military, to ravage Philip's territory. If you neglect
                    either of them, I am afraid your campaign will prove abortive. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>For if you send a marauding expedition, he will stand on the defensive until he
                    has made himself master of <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus"
                        >Olynthus</placeName>, and then he will easily march to the relief of his
                    own territory; or if you confine yourselves to helping <placeName
                        key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>, he will know that his base is
                    secure and will give close and undivided attention to his operations, until at
                    last he overcomes the resistance of the besieged. Our expedition, you see, must
                    be on a large scale and twofold. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>Such are my views on the expeditionary force. With regard to the supply of money,
                    you have money, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; you
                    have more than any other nation has for military purposes. But you appropriate
                    it yourselves, to suit your own pleasure. Now if you will spend it on the
                    campaign, you have no need of a further supply; if not, you have—or rather, you
                    have no supply at all. “What!” someone will cry, “do you actually move to use
                    this money for military purposes?” Of course I do not. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>Only it is my opinion that we must provide soldiers and that there must be one
                    uniform system of pay in return for service. Your opinion, however, is that you
                    should, without any trouble, just appropriate the money for your festivals.<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Theoric Fund had been instituted by
                        Pericles, nominally to enable the poorer citizens to attend the public
                        festivals. It would seem that definite sums were alloted to the various
                        departments of State expenditure, and the surplus was at the disposal of the
                        democracy for special military or other objects. Somewhere about 354
                        Eubulus, who was one of the board which controlled the Theoric Fund, carried
                        a law appropriating to it the <emph>whole</emph> of the surplus revenue. He
                        does not seem to have starved the defensive services, but he left no
                        provision for a war, except by means of an extraordinary levy or <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">e)sfora/</foreign>. Either in 360, or perhaps in 349
                        before the delivery of the third Olynthiac, an attempt to revert to the
                        earlier arrangement was followed by the usual <foreign xml:lang="grc">grafh\
                            parano/mwn</foreign>, and Eubulus is alleged to have confirmed the bad
                        system by making it a capital offence even to propose a diversion of the
                        fund. Demosthenes approaches the subject with a studied show of
                        embarrassment.</note> Then the only alternative is a war-tax, heavy or
                    light, as circumstances demand. Only money we must have, and without money
                    nothing can be done that ought to be done. There are other proposals before you
                    for raising supplies; choose whichever of them you think expedient, and, while
                    there is yet time, grapple with the problem. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>It is worth while, however, to observe and consider how Philip stands today. His
                    present prospects are not so bright or satisfactory as they seem and as a
                    superficial observer might pronounce them; nor would he ever have provoked this
                    war had he thought that he would be bound to fight himself. He hoped that on his
                    first entry he would carry all before him, and he finds himself completely
                    mistaken. This unforeseen result confounds and discourages him; and besides
                    there is the question of <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>The Thessalians were always, of course, born traitors, and Philip finds them
                    today just what everyone has found them in the past. They have formally resolved
                    to demand the restitution of <placeName key="tgn,7012084">Pagasae</placeName>
                    and have hindered him from fortifying <placeName key="tgn,7002751"
                        >Magnesia</placeName>. I have also been informed that they will no longer
                    hand over to him the profits of their harbors and markets, on the ground that
                    this sum ought to be applied to the government of <placeName key="tgn,7001399"
                        >Thessaly</placeName> and not find its way into Philip's coffers. Now if he
                    is deprived of this source of revenue, he will be hard put to it to pay for the
                    maintenance of his mercenaries. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>But surely we must assume that your Paeonian or Illyrian or any other of these
                    tribes would prefer freedom and independence to slavery. They are not accustomed
                    to acknowledge a master, and Philip is by all accounts a particularly harsh one.
                    And indeed that is not surprising. Undeserved success engenders folly in
                    unbalanced minds, and therefore it often proves harder to keep than to win
                    prosperity. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>Look then, Athenians, upon his difficulties as your opportunity. Be prompt to
                    take up the challenge. Send embassies when necessary. Take the field in person.
                    Rouse all the other states. Reflect how eagerly Philip would march against you,
                    if he had such a chance as we have, and if the war were on our frontiers. Are
                    you not ashamed if, having the opportunity, you lack the courage to do to him
                    what he would certainly do to you if he could? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>One point more, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Do not
                    forget that you can today choose whether you must fight there or Philip must
                    fight here. If <placeName key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName> holds out,
                    you will fight there, to the detriment of his territory, while you enjoy in
                    security the land that is your home. But if Philip takes Olynthus, who is to
                    prevent his marching hither? The Thebans? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>It may be an unduly harsh thing to say, but they will join heartily in the
                    invasion. The Phocians then? What! the men who cannot protect their own country
                    without your help? Any others? “But, my friend,” cries someone, “he will not
                    wish to attack us.” Nay, it would be a crowning absurdity if, having the power,
                    he should lack the will to carry out the threat which today he utters at the
                    risk of his reputation for sanity. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>But indeed I think you want no speech to prove how vast is the difference between
                    a war here and a war yonder. Why, if you were obliged to take the field
                    yourselves for a bare month, drawing from <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
                        >Attica</placeName> the necessary supplies—I am assuming that there is no
                    enemy in this country—I suppose your farmers would lose more than the sum spent
                    upon the whole of the previous war.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The war
                        about <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>.
                        Demosthenes reckons its cost at <date when="1500">1500</date> talents (<bibl
                            n="Dem. 2.28">Dem. 2.28</bibl>).</note> But if war comes within our
                    borders, at what figure must we assess our losses? And you must add the
                    insolence of the enemy and the ignominy of our position, greater than any loss
                    in a wise man's estimation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>It is the duty of all of you to grasp the significance of these facts, and to
                    send out an expedition that shall thrust back the war into <placeName
                        key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>: it is the duty of the well-to-do,
                    that spending but a fraction of the wealth they so happily possess, they may
                    enjoy the residue in security; of our fighters, that gaining experience of war
                    on Philip's soil, they may prove the formidable guardians of an inviolate
                    fatherland; of the statesmen, that they may give a ready account of their
                    stewardship, for as is the issue of these events, so will be your judgement of
                    their policy. On every ground may that issue be prosperous!</p>
            </div>


        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
