<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Dream, or the Cock</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor>Austin Morris Harmon, 1878-1950</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>OCRd, tagged and added initial corrections to  the text</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg001.1st1K-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1915</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.b000604154">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<head>The Dream, or the Cock<note>A Cynic sermon in praise of poverty, cast in the form of a
dialogue between Micyllus the cobbler, who figures also in
The Downward Journey, and his cock, who is Pythagoras
reincarnated,
</note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Way, you scurvy cock, may Zeus himself annihilate
you for being so envious and shrill-voiced! I was
rolling in wealth and having a most delightful dream
and enjoying wonderful happiness when you uplifted your voice in a piercing, full-throated crow and
waked me up. Even at night you won't let me
escape my poverty, which is much more of a nuisance
than you are. And yet to judge from the fact that
the silence is still profound and the cold has not yet
stiffened me as it always does in the morning—which
_ is the surest indicator that I have of the approach
of day—it is not yet midnight, and this bird, who is
as sleepless as if he were guarding the golden fleece,
has started crowing directly after dark. He shall
suffer for it, though! I'll pay you back, never fear,
as soon as it is daylight, by whacking the life out of
you with my stick ; but if I tried it now, you would
bother me by hopping about in the dark.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Master Micyllus, I thought I should do you a
favour by cheating the night as much as I could, so
that you might make use of the morning hours and
fnish the greater part of your work early ; you see,
if you geta single sandal done before the sun rises,

<pb n="v.2.p.175"/>

you will be so much ahead toward earning your daily
bread. But if you had rather sleep, [ll keep quiet
for you and will be much more mute than a fish.
Take care, however, that you don’t dream you are
rich and then starve when you wake up.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Zeus, god of miracles, and Heracles, averter of
harm! what the devil does this mean? The cock
talked like a human being!
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Then do you think it a miracle if I talk the same
language as you men?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Why isn’t it a miracle? Gods, avert the evil
omen from us!
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
It appears to me, Micyllus, that you are utterly uneducated and haven’t even read Homer’s poems, for in
them Xanthus, the horse of Achilles, saying good-bye
to neighing forever, stood still and talked in the
thick of the fray, reciting whole verses, not prose as
I did ; indeed he even made prophecies and foretold
the future; yet he was not considered to be doing
anything out of the way, and the one who heard him
did not invoke the averter of harm as you did just now,
thinking the thing ominous.<note n="v.2.p.175.n.1">Iliad 19, 407 ff.</note> Moreover, what would
you have done if the stem of the Argo had spoken to
you as it spoke of old,<note n="v.2.p.175.n.2">Apoll. Rhod. 4, 580 ff.</note> or the oak at Dodona had
prophesied with a voice of its own; or if you had
seen hides crawling and the flesh of oxen bellowing
half-roasted on the spits?<note n="v.2.p.175.n.3">Od. 12, 325 ff.</note> I am the friend of

<pb n="v.2.p.177"/>

Hermes, the most talkative and eloquent of all the
gods, and besides I am the close comrade and messmate of men, so it was to be expected that I would
learn the human language without difficulty. But if
you promise me to keep your own counsel, I shall
not hesitate to.tell you the real reason for my having
the same tongue as you, and how it happens that
can talk like this.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Why, this is not a dream, is it? A cock talking
to me this way? Tell me, in the name of Hermes,
my good friend, what other reason you have for your
ability to speak. As to my keeping still and not
telling anybody, why should you have any fear, for
who would believe me if I told him anything asserting
that I had heard it from a cock ?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Listen, then, to an account which will be quite
incredible to you, I am very sure, Micyllus. I who
now appear to you in the guise of a cock was a man
not long ago.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
I heard something to that effect about you cocks a
good while ago. They say that a young fellow
named Alectryon (Cock) became friends with Ares
ind drank with the god and caroused with him and
shared his amorous adventures ; at all events, whenever Ares went to visit Aphrodite on poaching bent,
he took Alectryon along too ; and as he was especially
uspicious of Helius, for fear that he would look
down on them and tell Hephaestus, he always used
to leave the young fellow outside at the door to
warn him when Helius rose. Then, they say,
Alectryon fell asleep one time and unintentionally


<pb n="v.2.p.179"/>


betrayed his post, and Helius unexpectedly stole
upon Aphrodite with Ares, who was sleeping peacefully because he relied on Alectryon to tell him if
anyone came near. So Hephaestus found out from
Helius and caught them by enclosing and trapping
them in the snares that he had long before contrived
for them ; and Ares, on being let go in the plight in
which Hephaestus let him go,<note n="v.2.p.179.n.1">The story is told in the Odyssey 8, 300-366, and repeated by Lucian in Dialogues of the Gods, 21.</note> was angry at Alectryon
and changed him into this bird, weapons and all, so
that he still has the crest of his helmet on his head.
And for this reason, they say, you cocks try to put
yourselves right with Ares when it is no use, and
when you notice that the sun is about to come up,
you raise your voices far in advance and give warning
of his rising.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

<label>COCK</label>
That is what they say, Micyllus, I grant you; but
my own experience has been quite different, and it
is only just lately that I changed into a cock.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
How? That is what I want to know above all
else.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Have you ever heard of a man named Pythagoras,
the son of Mnesarchus, of Samos?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
You mean the sophist, the quack, who made laws
against tasting meat and eating beans, banishing
from the table the food that I for my part like best
of all, and then trying to persuade people that before he became Pythagoras he was Euphorbus (Well-

<pb n="v.2.p.181"/>

fed)? They say he was a conjurer and a miraclemonger, cock.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
I am that very Pythagoras, Micyllus, so stop
abusing me, my good friend, especially as you do not
know what sort of man I really was.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Now this is far more miraculous than the other
thing! A philosopher cock! Tell me, though, son
of Mnesarchus, how you became a cock instead of a
man and a Tanagriote instead of a Samian.<note n="v.2.p.181.n.1">Tanagra in Boeotia was famous for its game-cocks.</note> This
story is not plausible nor quite easy to believe, for
I think Ihave observed two things in you that are
quite foreign to Pythagoras.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
What are they?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
One thing is that you are very noisy and loudvoiced, whereas he recommended silence for five
whole years, I believe. The other is actually quite
illegal ; I came home yesterday, as you know, with
nothing but beans to throw you, and you picked
them up without even hesitating. So it must be
either that you have told a lie and are someone else,
or, if you are Pythagoras, you have broken the law
and committed as great an impiety in eating beans as
if you had eaten your father’s head.<note n="v.2.p.181.n.2">An allusion to the pseudo-Pythagorean verse ἶσόν τοι κυάμους τε φαγεῖν κεφαλάς τε τοκήων. (It is just as wrong for you to eat beans as to eat the heads of your parents).</note>

<pb n="v.2.p.183"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
<label>COCK</label>
Why, Micyllus, you don’t know what the reason
for these rules is, and what is good for particular
modes of existence. Formerly I did not eat beans
because I was a philosopher, but now I can eat them
because they are fit food for a bird and are not forbidden to us. But listen if you like, and I'll tell
you how from Pythagoras I became what I am, and
what existences I formerly led, and what I profited
by each change.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Do tell me, for I should be more than delighted
to hear it. Indeed, if anyone were to let me choose
whether I preferred to hear you tell a story like that
or to have once more that blissful dream I had a
little while ago, I don’t know which would be my
choice; for in my estimation what you say is close
akin to the most delightful of visions, and I hold
you both in equal esteem, you and my priceless
dream.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
What, are you still brooding on that vision, whatever it was that came to you, and are you still
cherishing idle delusions, hunting down in your
memory a vain and (as they say in poetry) disembodied happiness ?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Why, I shall never forget that vision, cock, you
may be sure. The dream left so much honied sweetness in my eyes when it went away that I can
hardly open my lids, for it drags them down in sleep
again. In fact, what I saw gave me as pleasant a
titillation as a feather twiddled in one’s ear.

<pb n="v.2.p.185"/>

<label>COCK</label>
Heracles! By what you say, Master Dream is an
adept indeed. Rumour says that he has wings and
can fly to the limit set by sleep, but now he “jumps
over the pit”<note n="v.2.p.185.n.1">The metaphor comes from the proverbial jump of Phayllus. Fifty feet of ground had been broken to form a pit for the jumpers to alight in, but Phayllus, they say, came down on the solid ground, five feet beyond the pit.</note> and lingers in eyes that are open,
presenting himself in a form so honey-sweet and
palpable. At all events I should be glad to hear
what he is like, since you hold him so very dear.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
I am ready to tell; in fact, it will be delightful
to think and talk about it. But when are you going
to tell me about your transmigrations, Pythagoras?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
When you stop dreaming, Micyllus, and rub the
honey out of your eyes. At present, you speak
first, so that I may find out whether it was through
the gates of ivory or the gates of horn that the
dream winged its way to you.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Not through either of them, Pythagoras.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Well, Homer mentions only those two.<note n="v.2.p.185.n.2">Od. 19, 562. The truthful dreams use the gates of horn, the deceitful the gates of ivory.</note>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Let that silly poet go hang! He knows nothing
about dreams. Perhaps the beggarly dreams go
out through those gates, dreams like those he used
to see; and he couldn’t see them very plainly
at that, for he was blind! But my darling dream

<pb n="v.2.p.187"/>

came through gates of gold, and it was gold itself
and all dressed in gold and brought heaps of gold
with it.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Stop babbling of gold, most noble Midas. Really
your dream was just like Midas’ prayer, and you
appear to me to have slept yourself into whole goldmines.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
I saw a lot of gold, Pythagoras, a lot; you can’t
think how beautiful it was, and with what brilliancy
it shone. What is it that Pindar says in praising it ?
Remind me, if you know. It is where he says water
is best and then extols gold (and well he may), right
in the beginning of the most beautiful of all his
odes.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Is this what you are after?
<cit><quote><l>Water is best, but gold</l>
<l>Like blazing fire at night</l>
<l>Stands out amid proud riches.</l></quote>
<bibl>Olymp. 1, 1.</bibl></cit>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
That is it, by Heaven! Pindar praises gold as
though he had seen my dream. But listen, so that
you may know what it was like, wisest of cocks. I
did not eat at home, yesterday, as you know; for
Eucrates, the rich man met me in the public square
and told me to take a bath<note>No reflection on the personal habits of Micyllus is intended. As the bath was the recognized preliminary to dining-out, to mention it amounts to little more than telling him to dress for dinner.</note> and then come to dinner
at the proper hour.



<pb n="v.2.p.189"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
<label>COCK</label>
I know that very well; I went hungry all day
until finally, late in the evening, you came back
rather tight, bringing me those five beans, not a
very bounteous repast for a cock who was once an
athlete and made a fair showing at the Olympic
games.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
When I came home after dinner, I went to sleep
as soon as I had thrown you the beans, and then
“through the ambrosial night,” as Homer puts it,<note n="v.2.p.189.n.1">Iliad 2, 56.</note> a
truly divine dream came to me and. . .
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
First tell me what happened at Eucrates’, Micyllus,
how the dinner was and all about the drinkingparty afterwards. For there is nothing to hinder
you from dining all over again by making up adream
so to speak, about that dinner and chewing the cud
of your food in fancy.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
I thought I should bore you by telling all that, but
since you want it, here goes. I never before dined
with a rich man in all my life, Pythagoras, but by
a stroke of luck I met Eucrates yesterday; after
giving him “Good-day, master,” as usual, I was for
going away again, so as not to shame him by joining
his company in my beggarly cloak. But: “Micyllus,”
said he, “I am giving a birthday party for my
daughter to-day, and have invited a great many of
my friends: but as one of them is ill, they say, and
can’t dine with us, you must take a bath and come in
his place, unless, to be sure, the man I invited says

<pb n="v.2.p.191"/>

that he will come himself, for just now his coming is
doubtful.” On hearing this I made obeisance to him
and went away, praying to all the gods to send an
attack of ague or pleurisy or gout to the invalid
whose substitute and diner-out and heir I had been
invited to become. I thought it an interminable
age until my bath, and kept looking all the while
to see how long the shadow was and when it would
at last be time to bathe.</p>
<p>When the time finally came, I scrubbed myself
with all speed and went off very well dressed, as I
had turned my cloak inside out so that the garment
might’ show the cleaner side.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>

I met at the door a
number of people, and among them, carried on the
shoulders of four bearers, the man whose place I was
to have filled, who they said was ill; and in fact he
was clearly ina bad way. At any rate he groaned
and coughed and hawked in a hollow and Giencive
way, and was all pale and flabby, a man of about
sixty. He was said to be one of those philosophers
who talk rubbish to the boys, and in fact. he had
a regular goat’s beard, excessively long. And when
Archibius, the doctor, took him to task for coming in
that condition, “Duty,” he said, “must not be
shirked, especially by a philosopher, though a
thousand illnesses stand in his way; Eucrates
would think he had been slighted by me.” “No
indeed,” ‘said I, “He will commend you if you
choose to die at home rather than to hawk and spit
your life away at his party!” But the man’s pride

<pb n="v.2.p.193"/>

was so great that he pretended not to have heard
the sally. In a moment Eucrates joined us after his
bath, and on seeing ‘Thesmopolis—for that was the
philosopher’s name—he said : “Professor, it was very
good of you to come to us, but you would not have
fared any the worse if you had stayed away, for
everything from first to last would have been sent
you.” With that he started to go in, conducting
Thesmopolis, who was supported by the servants too.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

I was getting ready to go away, but he turned my way
and hesitated a good while, and then, as he saw that
I was very: downeast, said: “You come in too,
Micyllus, and dine with us. Tl make my son eat
with his mother in the women’s quarters so that you
may have room.” I went in, therefore, after coming
within an ace of licking my lips for nothing, like
the wolf<note n="v.2.p.193.n.1">The proverb seems to be founded on the fable of the wolf and the old woman ; she threatened to throw a baby to the wolf if it did not stop crying, and the wolf waited all day for the baby, only to go home disappointed. (Aesop, 275 Halm.)</note>; I was ashamed, however, because I
seemed to have driven Eucrates’ boy out of the
dining-room.</p>
<p>When it was time to go to the table, first of all
they picked Thesmopolis up and put him in place,
not without some difficulty, though there were five
stout lads, I think, to do it; and they stuffed
eushions all round about him so that he could
maintain his position and hold out for a long time.
Then, as nobody else could endure to lie near him,
they took me and put me in the place below him,
making us neighbours at table. Then, Pythagoras,
we began eating a dinner of many courses and great
variety, served on gold and silver plate in profusion,


<pb n="v.2.p.195"/>

and there were goblets of gold and handsome
waiters and musicians and clowns withal. In short,
we were delightfully entertained, except for one
thing that annoyed me beyond measure: Thesmopolis
kept bothering me and talking to me about virtue,
whatever that may be, and teaching me that two
negatives make an affirmative, and that if it is day
it is not night ; and sometimes he actually said that I
had horns.<note n="v.2.p.195.n.1">For this and other Stoic fallacies, see Lucian I. p. 437 and note 2.</note> By philosophizing with me incessantly
after that fashion when I had no mind for it, he
spoiled and diminished my pleasure, not allowing me
to hear the performers who were playing and singing. Well, there you have your dinner, cock.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
It was not of the pleasantest, Micyllus, as your
lot was cast with that silly old man.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Now listen to my dream. I thought that Eucrates
himself had somehow become childless and lay dying,
and that, after sending for me and making a will in
which I was heir to everything, he lingered a while
and then died. On entering into possession of the
property, I dipped up the gold and the silver in
great bowlfuls, for there was an ever-flowing, copious
stream of it; and all the rest, too—the ‘clothing
and tables and cups and waiters—all was mine, ot
course. Then I drove out behind a pair of white
horses, holding my head high, the admiration and
the envy of all beholders; many ran before me and
rode beside me, and still more followed after me, and
I with his clothing on and my fingers covered with

<pb n="v.2.p.197"/>

heavy rings, fully sixteen of them, was giving orders
for a splendid feast to be prepared for the entertainment of my friends. In a moment they were there,
as is natural in a dream, and the dinner was being
served, and the drinking-bout was under way. While
I was thus engaged and was drinking healths with
each person there out of golden cups, just as the
dessert was being brought in you lifted up your
voice unseasonably, and disturbed our party, upset
the tables and caused that wealth of mine to be
scattered to the winds. Now do you think I was
unreasonable in getting angry at you, when I should
have been glad to see the dream last for three
nights ?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>

<label>COCK</label>
Are you such a lover of gold and of riches,
Micyllus, and is owning quantities of gold the only
thing in the world that you admire and consider
blissful ?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
I am not the only ‘one to do so, Pythagoras: you
yourself, when you were Euphorbus, sallied forth to
fight the Achaeans with your curls tricked out in
gold and silver, and even in war, where it would
have been better to wear iron, you thought fit to
face danger with your hair caught up with gold.<note n="v.2.p.197.n.1">Tliad 17, 52.</note>
No doubt Homer said that your hair was “like the
Graces” because “it was snooded with gold and with
silver” ; for it looked far finer and lovelier, of course,
when it was interwoven with gold and shone in
unison with it. And yet as far as you are concerned,
Goldenhair, it is of little moment that you, the son
of a Panthous, honoured gold, but what of the father

<pb n="v.2.p.199"/>

of gods and of men, the son of Cronus and Rhea?
When he was in love with that slip ofa girl in Argos,
not having anything more attractive to change
himself into nor any other means of corrupting the
sentries of Acrisius, he turned into gold, as you, of
course, have heard, and came down through the roof
to visit his beloved. Then what is the use of my
telling you the rest of it—how many uses gold has,
and how, when people have it, it renders them
handsome and wise and strong, lending them honour
and esteem, and not infrequently it makes inconspicuous and contemptible people admired and renowned in a short time?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>

For instance, you know
my neighbour, of the same trade, Simon, who dined
with me not long ago when I boiled the soup for
Cronus-day and put in two slices of sausage?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Yes, I know him; the snub-nosed, short fellow
who filched the earthen bowl and went away with it
under his arm after dinner, the only bowl we had—
I myself saw him, Micyllus.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
So it was he that stole it and then swore by so
many gods that he did not? But why didn’t you
cry out and tell on him then, cock, when you saw us
being plundered ?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
I crowed, and that was all that I could do at the
time. But what about Simon? You seemed to be
going to say something about him.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
He had a cousin who was enormously rich, named
Drimylus. This fellow while he was alive never gave

<pb n="v.2.p.201"/>

apenny to Simon—why should he, when he himself
did not touch his money? But since his death the
other day all his property is Simon’s by law, and now
he, the man with the dirty rags, the man that used
to lick the pot, takes the air pleasantly, dressed in
fine woollens and royal purple, the owner of servants
and carriages and golden cups and_ ivory-legged
tables, receiving homage from everybody and no
longer even giving a glance at me. Recently, for
example, I saw him coming toward me and said,
“Good-day, Simon’; but he replicd: “Tell that
pauper not to abbreviate my name; it is not Simon
but Simonides.”<note n="v.2.p.201.n.1">He adopts a name better suited to his new position in society ; ef. Timon 22.</note>1 What is more, the women are
actually in love with him now, and he flirts with
them and slights them, and when he receives some
and is gracious to them the others threaten to hang
themselves on account of his neglect. You see,
don’t you, what blessings gold is able to bestow,
when it transforms ugly people and renders them
lovely, like the girdle in poetry?<note n="v.2.p.201.n.2">The girdle of Aphrodite: /liad 14, 214 ff.</note> And you have
heard the poets say: “O gold, thou choicest
treasure,”<note n="v.2.p.201.n.3">Euripides, from the lost Danae: Nauck, Vrag. Graec. Frag. 324.</note> and

<cit><quote><l>Tis gold that over mortal men doth rule.</l></quote>
<bibl>Source unknown ; Nauck, ibid., adesp. 294.</bibl></cit>

But why did you interrupt me by laughing, cock ?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
<label>COCK</label>
Because in your ignorance, Micyllus, you have
gone just as far astray as most people in regard to
the rich. Take my word for it, they live a much

<pb n="v.2.p.203"/>

more wretched life than we. I who talk to you have
been both poor and rich repeatedly, and have tested
every kind of life : after a little you shall hear about
it all.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Yes, by Heaven, it is high time now for you to
talk and tell me how you got transformed and what
you know of each existence.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Listen ; but first let me tell you thus much, that I
have never seen anyone leading a happier life than
you.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Than I, cock? I wish you no better luck yourself! You force me to curse you, you know. But
begin with Euphorbus and tell me how you were
transformed to Pythagoras, and then the rest of it
till you get to the cock : for it is likely that you have
seen many sights and had many adventures in your
multifarious existences.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>

<label>COCK</label>
How my soul originally left Apollo, flew down to
earth and entered into a human body and what sin
it was condemned to expiate in that way would
make a long story; besides, it is impious either for
me to tell or for you to hear such things. But when
I became Euphorbus. . .
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
But I,—who was I formerly, wondrous creature ?
First tell me whether I too was ever transformed
like you.
Cock
Yes, certainly.

<pb n="v.2.p.205"/>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Then what was I ? ‘Tell me if you can, for I want
to know.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
You were an Indian ant, one of the gold-digging
kind.<note n="v.2.p.205.n.1">Herod. 3, 102.</note>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Confound the luck ! to think that I did not dare
to lay in even a small supply of gold-dust before
coming from that life to this! But what shall I be
next, tell me? You probably know. If it is anything good, [ll climb up this minute and hang
myself from the peg that you are standing on.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>

<label>COCK</label>
You can’t by any possibility find that out. But
when I became Euphorbus—for I am going back to
that subject—I fought at Troy and was killed by
Menelaus, and some time afterwards I entered into
Pythagoras. In the meanwhile I stood about and
waited without a house till Mnesarchus should build
me one.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Without food and drink, my friend ?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Yes, certainly ; for they turned out to be unnecessary, except for the body.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Well, then, tell me the story of Troy first. Was it
all as Homer says ?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Why, where did he get his information, Micyllus?
When all that was going on, he was a camel in

<pb n="v.2.p.207"/>

Bactria. Tl tell you thus much, though: nothing
was out of the common then, and Ajax was not as
tall and Helen herself not as fair as people think.
As I saw her, she had a white complexion and a long
neck, to be sure, so that you might know she was
the daughter of a swan ; but as for the rest of it, she
was decidedly old, about the saine age as Hecuba;
for Theseus eloped with her in the first place and
kept her at Aphidnae, and Theseus lived in the time
of Heracles, who took Troy the first time it was
taken, in the time of our fathers,—our then fathers,
Imean. Panthous told me all this, and said that
when he was quite small he had seen Heracles.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
But how about Achilles? Was he as Homer
describes him, supreme in everything, or is this only
a fable too ?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
I did not come into contact with him at all,
Micyllus, and I can’t tell you as accurately about
the Greek side. How could I, being one of the
enemy? His comrade Patroclus, however, I killed
without difficulty, running him through with my
spear.<note n="v.2.p.207.n.1">The cock is drawing the long-bow; Euphorbus only wounded Patroclus, Iliad 16, 806 ff.</note>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
And then Menelaus killed you with much greater
ease! But enough of this, and now tell me the
story of Pythagoras.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

<label>COCK</label>
In brief, Micyllus, I was a sophist, for I must tell
the truth, I suppose. However, I was not uneducated or unacquainted with the noblest sciences. I

<pb n="v.2.p.209"/>

even went to: Egypt to study with the prophets,
penetrated into their sanctuaries and learned the
books of Horus and Isis by heart, and then I sailed
away to Italy and worked upon the Greeks in that
quarter of the world to such an extent that they
thought me a god.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
So I have heard, and I have also heard that you
were thought to have come to life again after dying,
and that you once showed them that your thigh was of
gold. But, look here, tell me how it occurred to you
to make a law against eating either meat or beans?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Do not press that question, Micyllus.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Why, cock ?
Cock
Because I am ashamed to tell you the truth of it.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
But you oughtn’t to hesitate to tell a housemate
and a friend—for I cannot call myself your master
any longer.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
It was nothing sensible or wise, but I perceived
that if I made laws that were ordinary and just
like those of the run of legislators I should not
induce men to wonder at me, whereas the more I departed from precedent, the more of a figure I should
cut, I thought, in their eyes. Therefore I preferred
to introduce innovations, keeping the reason for
them secret so that one man might guess one thing


<pb n="v.2.p.211"/>

and one another, and all be perplexed, as they are in
the case of oracles that are obscure. Look here, you
are laughing at me, now.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Not so much at you as at the people of Croton
and Metapontum and Tarentum and all the rest who
followed you dumbly and worshipped the footprints
that you left in walking.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>

But after you put off the
part of Pythagoras what other did you assume ?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Aspasia, the courtesan from Miletus.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Whew, what a yarn! So Pythagoras became a
woman on top of everything else, and there was
once atime when you laid eggs, most distinguished
of cocks; when you lived with Pericles in the
capacity of Aspasia and had children by him and
carded wool and spun yarn and made the most of
your sex in courtesan style?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Yes, I did all that, and I am not the only one:
both Tiresias and Caeneus the son of Elatus preecded
me, so that all your jokes at my expense will be at
their expense too.<note n="v.2.p.211.n.1">Tiresias struck a pair of mating serpents with his staff, and turned into a woman ; seven years later he once more saw them and struck them, becoming a man again (Ovid, Melam. 3, 316 ff.). Poseidon turned Caenis into a man at her own request after he had wronged her (Metam. 12, 189 ff.).</note>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
How about it? Which life did you find the
pleasanter, when you were a man or when Pericles
dallied with you ?



<pb n="v.2.p.213"/>

<label>COCK</label>
Just see what a question you have asked there!
Even Tiresias paid dearly for answering it !<note n="v.2.p.213.n.1">Zeus had said that Hera’s sex enjoyed more pleasure than his own. Hera denied it; Tiresias was called in as umpire and held with Zeus, whereupon Hera struck him blind (Metam. l. c.).</note>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Whether you tell me or not, Euripides has settled
the business well enough, for he says that he would
sooner stand in line of battle thrice over than bear a
single child.<note n="v.2.p.213.n.2">Medea 251.</note>
<label>COCK</label>
I'll remind you of that before long, Micyllus, when
you are in child-bed; for you too will be a woman
again and again in your long cycle of existences.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Hang you, cock, do you think everybody hails from
Miletus or Samos? They say that while you were
Pythagoras and young and handsome you often
played Aspasia to the tyrant.</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"> <p>But what man or
woman did you become after Aspasia ?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
The Cynic Crates.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Twin brethren! what ups and downs! First a
courtesan, then a philosopher !
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Then a king, then a poor man, and soon a satrap ;
then a horse, a jackdaw, a frog, and a thousand things
besides ; it would take too long to enumerate them
all. But of late I have often been a cock, for I liked
that sort of life; and after belonging to many men,

<pb n="v.2.p.215"/>

both rich and poor, at length I am now living with
you, laughing at you every day for bewailing and
lamenting over your poverty and for admiring the
rich through ignorance of the troubles that are
theirs. Indeed, if you knew the cares they have,
you would laugh at yourself for thinking at_ first
that wealth was a source of extraordinary happiness.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Well then, Pythagoras—but tell me what you
like best to be called, so that I may not muddle up
our conversation by calling you different names.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
It will make no difference whether you call me
Euphorbus or Pythagoras, Aspasia or Crates; I am
all of them. But you had better call me what you
now see me to be, a cock, so as not to slight a bird
that, although held in low esteem, has in itself so
many souls.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Well then, cock, as you have tried almost every
existence and know everything, please tell me
clearly about the life of the rich and the life of the
poor, each by itself, so that I may learn if you are
telling the truth when you declare that I am happier
than the rich.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Well now, look at it this way, Micyllus. As for you,
you are little concerned about war if you hear that
the enemy is approaching, and you do not worry for
fear they may lay your farm waste in a raid or

<pb n="v.2.p.217"/>

trample down your garden or cut down your grapevines; when you hear the trumpet, at most you
simply consider yourself and where you are to turn in
order to save yourself and escape the danger. The
rich, however, not only fear for themselves but are
distressed when they look from the walls and see all
that they own in the country harried and plundered.
Moreover if it is necessary to pay a special tax, they
alone are summoned to do so, and if it is necessary
to take the field, they risk their lives in the van as
commanders of horse or foot, whereas you, with but
a wicker shield, have little to carry and nothing to
impede your flight, and are ready to celebrate the
victory when the general offers sacrifice after winning
the battle.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>

In time of peace, on the other hand, being one of
the voters, you go to the assembly and lord it over
the rich while they quake and cringe and seck your
good will with presents. Besides, it is they who
toil that you may have baths and shows and everything else to your heart’s content, while you investigate and scrutinize them harshly like a master,
sometimes without even letting them say a word for
themselves; and if you choose you shower them
generously with stones or confiscate their properties.
And_ you do not dread an informer, nor yet a robber
who might steal your gold by climbing over the
coping or digging through the wall; and you are
not bothered with casting up accounts or collecting
debts or squabbling with your confounded agents,
and thus dividing your attention among so many
worries. No, after you have finished a sandal and
received your pay of seven obols, you get up from
your bench toward evening, take a bath if you choose,

<pb n="v.2.p.219"/>

buy yourself a bloater or sprats or a bunch of onions,
and have a good time, singing a great deal and
philosophizing with that good soul, Poverty.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>

So in consequence of all this you are sound
and strong in body and can stand the cold, for
your hardships have trained you fine and made you
no mean fighter against adverse conditions that scem
to the rest of the world irresistible. No chance
that one of their severe illnesses will come near
you: on the contrary, if ever you get a light fever,
after humouring it a little while you jump out
of bed at once, shaking off your discomfort, and the
fever takes flight immediately on seeing that you
drink cold water and have no use for doctors’ visits.
But the rich, unhappy that they are—what ills are
they not subject to through intemperance? Gout
and consumption and pneumonia and dropsy are the
consequences of those splendid dinners.</p>

<p>In brief, some of them who like Icarus fly high
and draw near the sun without knowing that their
wings are fitted on with wax, now and then make
a great splash by falling head-first into the sea, while
of those who, copying Daedalus, have not let their
ambitions soar high in the air but have kept them
close to earth so that the wax is occasionally wet
with spray, the most part reach their journey’s end
in safety.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
You mean temperate and sensible people.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
But as for the others, Micyllus, you can see how
sadly they come to grief when a Croesus with his

<pb n="v.2.p.221"/>

wings clipped makes sport for the Persians by
mounting the pyre, or a Dionysius, expelled from
his tyrant’s throne, turns up in Corinth as a schoolmaster, teaching children their a, b—ab, after holding sway so widely.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Tell me, cock, when you were king—for you say
you were once on a time—how did you find that
life? You were completely happy, I suppose, as
you had what is surely the acme of all blessings.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Don’t even remind me of it, Micyllus, so utterly
wretched was I then; for although in all things
external I seemed to be completely happy, as you
say, I had a thousand vexations within.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
What were they? What you say is strange and
not quite credible.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
I ruled over a great country, Micyllus, one that
roduced everything and was among the most noteworthy for the number of its people and the beauty
of its cities, one that was traversed by navigable
rivers and had a sea-coast with good harbours ; and
I had a great army, trained cavalry, a large bodyguard, triremes, untold riches, a great quantity of
gold plate and all the rest of the paraphernalia of
rule enormously exaggerated, so that when I went
out the people made obeisance and thought they
beheld a god inthe flesh, and they ran up one after

<pb n="v.2.p.223"/>

another to look at me, while some even went up to
the house-tops, thinking it a great thing to have had
a good look at my horses, my mantle, my diadem,
and my attendants before and behind me. But I
myself, knowing how many vexations and torments
I had, pardoned them, to be sure, for their folly, but
pitied myself for being no better than the great
colossi that Phidias or Myron or Praxiteles made,
each of which outwardly is a beautiful Poseidon or
a Zeus, made of ivory and gold, with a thunderbolt
ora flash of lightning or a trident in his right hand ;
but if you stoop down and look inside, you will see
bars and props and nails driven clear through, and
beams and wedges and pitch and clay and a quantity
of such ugly stuff housing within, not to mention
numbers of mice and rats that keep their court in
them sometimes. That is what monarchy is like.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
You haven’t yet told me what the clay and the
props and bars are in monarchy, nor what that
“quantity of ugly stuff” is. [ll grant you, to drive
out as the ruler of so many people amid admiration
and homage is wonderfully like your comparison of
the colossus, for it savours of divinity. But tell me
about the inside of the colossus now.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
What shall I tell you first, Micyllus? The terrors,
the frights, the suspicions, the hatred of your

<pb n="v.2.p.225"/>

associates, the plots, and as a result of all this the
seanty sleep, and that not sound, the dreams full
of tumult, the intricate plans and the perpetual
expectations of something bad? Or shall I tell you
of the press of business, negotiations, lawsuits,
campaigns, orders, countersigns, and calculations ?
These things prevent a ruler from enjoying any
pleasure even in his sleep; he alone must think
about everything and have a thousand worries.
Even in the case of Agamemnon, son of Atreus,

<cit><quote><l>Sweet sleep came to him not as he weighed in his
mind many projects,</l></quote>
<bibl>Iliad10, 3-4</bibl></cit>

though all the Achaeans were snoring ! The king
of Lydia<note n="v.2.p.225.n.1">Croesus.</note> is worried because his son is mute, the
king of Persia<note n="v.2.p.225.n.2">Artaxerxes.</note> because Clearchus is enlisting troops
for Cyrus, another<note n="v.2.p.225.n.3">Dionysius the Younger. </note> because Dion is holding whispered conversations with a few Syracusans, another<note n="v.2.p.225.n.4">Alexander.</note>
because Parmenio is praised, Perdiccas because of
Ptolemy, and Ptolemy because of Seleucus. And
there are other grounds for worry too, when your
favourite will have nothing to do with you except by
constraint, when your mistress fancies someone else,
when one or another is said to be on the point of
revolting, and when two or three of your guardsmen
are whispering to one another. What is more, you
must be particularly suspicious of your dearest
friends and always be expecting some harm to come
from them. For example, I was poisoned by my son,
he himself by his favourite, and the latter no doubt
met some other death of a similar sort.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26">
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Tut, tut! What you say is dreadful, cock. For



<pb n="v.2.p.227"/>

me, at least, it is far safer to bend over and cobble
shoes than to drink out of a golden cup when
the health that is pledged you is qualified with
hemlock or aconite. The only risk I run is that
if my knife should slip sideways and fail to cut
straight, I might draw a little blood by cutting
my fingers; but they, as you say, do their feasting
at the peril of their lives and live amid a thousand
ills beside. Then when they fall they make no
better figure than the actors that you often see,
who for a time pretend to be a Cecrops or a Sisyphus
or a Telephus, with diadems and ivory-hilted swords
and waving hair and gold-embroidered tunics ; but if
(as often happens) one of them misses his footing
and falls down in the middle of the stage, it
naturally makes fun for the audience when the mask
gets broken to pieces, diadem and all, and the actor’s
own face is covered with blood, and his legs are
bared high, so as to show that his inner garments
are miserable rags and that the buskins with which
he is shod are shapeless and do not fit his foot. Do
you see how you have already taught me to make
comparisons, friend cock? Well, as for absolute
power, it proves to be something of that sort. But
when you became a horse or a dog or a fish or a frog,
how did you find that existence?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>


<label>COCK</label>
That is a long story you are starting, and we have
not time for it just now. But to give the upshot of
it, there is no existence that did not seem to me more
care-free than that of man, since the others are con-
‘ formed to natural desires and needs alone ; you will
not see among them a horse bailiff or a frog informer

<pb n="v.2.p.229"/>

or a jackdaw sophist or a mosquito chef or a libertine
cock or any of the other modes of life that you men
follow.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
No doubt that is true, cock. But as to myself, I
am not ashamed to tell you how I feel. I am not
yet able to unlearn the desire of becoming rich that
[have had since my boyhood. My dream, too, still
stands before my eyes displaying its gold; and
above all I am choking with envy of that confounded
Simon, who is revelling in so many blessings.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
I will cure you, Micyllus. As it is still night, get
up and follow me; I will take you to visit Simon
and to the house of the other rich men, so that you
may see what their establishments are like.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
How can you do it when their doors are locked?
You aren't going to make me be a burglar ?
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Not by any means. But Hermes, to whom IT am
consecrated, gave me this privilege, that if my
longest tail feather, the one that is so pliant that it
curls—
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
You have two like that.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
It is the one on the right, and if I permit any man
to pull it out and keep it, that man, as long as I
choose, can open every door and see everything
without being seen himself.

<pb n="v.2.p.231"/>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
I didn’t realize, cock, that you yourself were a
conjurer. Well, if you only let me have it, you shall
see all Simon’s possessions brought over here in a
jiffy: Pl slip in and bring them over, and he will
once more eat his leather as he stretches it.<note n="v.2.p.231.n.1">The ancient shoemaker held one side of the leather in his teeth in stretching it. Cf. <cit><quote><l>Dentibus antiquas solitus producere pelles</l> <l>et mordere luto putre vetusque solum—.</l></quote> <bibl>Martial 9, 73.</bibl></cit> </note>
<label>COCK</label>
That is impossible, for Hermes ordered me, if the
man who had the feather did anything of that sort,
to uplift my voice and expose him.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
It is hard to believe what you say, that Hermes,
himself a thief, begrudges others the same privilege.
But let’s be off just the same ; I'll keep my hands off
the gold if I can.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
First pluck the feather out, Micyllus . . . What's
this? You have pulled them both out !
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
It is safer to do so, cock, and it will spoil your
beauty less, preventing you from being crippled on
one side of your tail.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>
<label>COCK</label>
All right. Shall we visit Simon first, or one of
the other rich men?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
No: Simon, who wants to have a name of four
syllables instead of two, now that he is rich. Here
we are at the door already. What shall I do next?



<pb n="v.2.p.233"/>

<label>COCK</label>
Put the feather to the lock.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Look at that now! Heracles! The door has
opened just as it would toa key!
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Lead on. Do you see him sitting up and figuring ?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Yes, by Heaven, beside a dim and thirsty lamp ;
he is pale for some reason, cock, and all run down
and thin; from worrying, I suppose, for there was
no talk of his being ill in any other way.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Listen to what he is saying and you will find out
how he got this way.
</p>
<p><label>SIMON</label>
Well, then, that seventy talents is quite safely
buried under the bed and no one else knows of it;
but as for the sixteen, I think Sosylus the groom saw
me hiding them under the manger. At any rate he
is all for hanging about the stable, though he is not
particularly attentive to business otherwise or fond
of work. I have probably been robbed of much
more than that, or else where did Tibius get the
money for the big slice of salt fish they said he
treated himself to yesterday or the earring they said
he bought for his wife at a cost of five whole
drachmas ?_ It’s my money these fellows are squandering, worse luck! But my cups are not stored in a
safe place, either, and there are so many! I’m afraid
someone may burrow under the wall and steal them:
many envy me and plot against me, and above all my
neighbour Micyllus.

<pb n="v.2.p.235"/>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Yes, by Heaven, I’m just like you and go away
with the dishes under my arm!
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Hush, Micyllus, for fear he may find out that we
are here.
</p>
<p><label>SIMON</label>
At any rate it is best to stay awake myself and
keep watch. I'll get up from time to time and go
all about the whole house. Who is that? I see
you, burglar . . . oh! no, you are only a pillar, it is
allright. Ill dig up my gold and count it again, for
fear I made a mistake yesterday. There, now, somebody made a noise: he’s after me, of course. I am
beleaguered and plotted against by all the world.
Where is my sword? If I find anyone ... Let us
bury the gold again.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>

<label>COCK</label>
Well, Micyllus, that is the way Simon lives. Let’s
o and visit someone else while there is still a little
of the night left.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Unfortunate man, what a life he leads! I wish
my enemies wealth on those terms! Well, I want
to hit him over the head before I go.
</p>
<p><label>SIMON</label>
Who hit me? I’m being robbed, unlucky that I
am !
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Groan and lie awake and grow like your gold
in colour, cleaving fast to it! Let’s go and see
Gnipho the money-lender, if you don’t mind. He

<pb n="v.2.p.237"/>

too lives not far off. This door has opened to us
also.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p>

<label>COCK</label>
Do you see him awake with his worries like the
other, computing his interests and wearing his fingers
tothe bone? And yet he will soon have to leave all
this behind and become a beetle or a gnat or a dogfly.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
I see an unfortunate, senseless man who even now
lives little better than a beetle or a gnat. And how
completely run down he is from his computations !
Let’s go and see another.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="32"><p>

<label>COCK</label>
Your friend Eucrates, if you like. See, this door
has opened too, so let’s go in.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
All this belonged to me a little while ago.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Why, are you still dreaming of your wealth? Do
you see Eucrates and his servant, old man as he
is. . .?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Yes, by Heaven, I see lust and sensuality and
lewdness ill befitting a human being ; and in another
quarter I see his wife and the cook . . .
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg019.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="33">
<p><label>COCK</label>
How about it? Would you be willing to inherit
all this too, Micyllus, and have all that belongs to
Eucrates ?

<pb n="v.2.p.239"/>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Not on your life, cock! [I starve first! ‘To the
deuce with your gold and your dinners ; two obols is a
fortune to me in comparison with being an easy mark
for the servants.
</p>
<p><label>COCK</label>
Well, the day is just breaking, so let’s go
home now ; you shall see the rest of it some other
time.

<pb n="v.2.p.243"/>

</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>
