<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Theomnestus 2 from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>That he asserted that I had
        killed my father is in the knowledge of many of you, and they are my witnesses. But that I
        have not done it is evident; for I am thirty-two years old, and this is the twentieth year
        since your return to the city. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>You see, then, that I was
        twelve years old when my father was put to death by the Thirty, so that I did not even know
        what an oligarchy was, nor was I capable of defending my father. Nor, again, was his
        property a motive for my having designs upon him; for my elder brother got everything, and
        left us destitute. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Perhaps
        he will say that it is not among the forbidden things to say a man has killed his father,
        since the law does not prohibit this, but disallows the word “murderer.” But I think our
        dispute ought not to be over mere terms, but over the intention shown in acts, and that
        everyone knows that all who have killed others are murderers of those same persons, and
        those who are murderers of another have killed that man. <milestone n="4" unit="section"
        />For it would be too great a task for the lawgiver to write all the terms that have the
        same meaning: he preferred to mention one which should indicate all. I presume it cannot be
        that, if anyone who calls you a father-beater or a mother-beater is liable to a penalty, at
        the same time a person who says that you strike your male or female parent is to escape
        punishment. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>So, if someone calls a man a shield-caster, he
        is to be immune, since the law imposes a penalty for saying that a man has thrown away his
        shield, but not for saying he has cast it. Similarly, if you were one of the Eleven, you
        would not accept a prisoner arrested for stripping a man of his cloak or his shirt, unless
        he were given the name of clothes-stealer. <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>Nor, if someone
        abducted a child, would you accept him as a kidnapper. Now you have yourself taken
        proceedings for slander against the person who said you had cast your shield: yet it is not
        so written in the law, but the phrase is “saying a man has thrown it away.” How monstrous,
        then, that if such a thing is said about you, you should make play with the laws in the way
        I am doing now, and should be avenged on your enemies; but if you say such a thing yourself,
        you should claim to escape punishment! <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>I ask you,
        therefore, gentlemen, to protect me, reflecting that it is a greater injury to be accused of
        killing one's father than of having cast one's shield. I, for one, would rather admit to
        having thrown away any number than to entertaining such thoughts regarding my father. Yet I
        have seen this man acting in the way that you know, while I myself saved my shield. So on
        what ground should I fail to get redress from him? <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>What
        imputation stands against me? That I have been justly accused? No, not even yourselves can
        say so. That the defendant is a better man? No, not even himself can claim this. That having
        thrown away my arms I am suing a man who saved his? This is not the story that has been
        dispersed over the city. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>Do not, then, pity him for obloquy
        that he deserves, nor forgive him for outrages and expressions whereby he has broken the
        laws, especially in regard to a man<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The speaker's
          father.</note> who has held many generalships and shared many of your perils; who has
        neither fallen into the hands of the enemy nor been convicted by you at the audit of his
        service, and who at the age of seventy lost his life under the oligarchy for loyalty to you.
        There is good cause to feel anger on his account: <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>for what
        more distressing repute could he have than this,—after being slain by his enemies to bear
        the reproach of having been destroyed by his children? The memorials of his valor are
        hanging in your temples, while those of these people's baseness are seen in the temples of
        the enemy. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He will say that
        he has made the statement in a fit of anger. But your reflection on this must be that the
        lawgiver grants no indulgence to anger; he punishes the speaker, unless he proves the truth
        of his words. I have borne witness twice in regard to this man: for I was not aware that you
        punished the persons who had seen the deed, but pardoned those who had done the throwing
        away. I therefore request you to condemn him. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>For although
        at this moment I am prosecuting for slander, yet at the same casting of your vote I am
        prosecuted for murdering my father: no trial could be more serious for me than this; and I
        alone, when certified of age, indicted the Thirty before the Areopagus. Vindicate,
        therefore, both my father and me.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
