<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Boeotus 2 </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>Nothing is more painful, men of the jury, than when a man is addressed by name as
                    “brother” of certain persons, whom in fact he regards as enemies, and when he is
                    compelled, on account of the many cruel wrongs which he has suffered at their
                    hands, to come into court; as is my case now. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>For instance, I have not only had the misfortune in the beginning that Plangon,
                    the mother of these men, by deceit and manifest perjury, compelled my father to
                    bring himself to acknowledge them, and that consequently I was robbed of
                    two-thirds of my inheritance; but, in addition to this, I have been driven by
                    these men out of the house of my fathers, in which I was born and brought up,
                    and into which they were admitted, not by my father, but by myself after his
                    death; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>and I am being robbed of my mother's dowry, for which I am now bringing suit,
                    although I have myself given them satisfaction in all the matters in which they
                    made claims upon me, except some trifling cross-demands which they have
                    maliciously brought against me on account of this action, as will be perfectly
                    clear to you also; yet in the course of eleven years I have been unable to
                    obtain from them a reasonable settlement, and so at length I have had recourse
                    to you for help. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>I beg you all, men of the jury, to listen to me with goodwill, while I speak as
                    best I can; and if I seem to you to have suffered cruel wrongs, to pardon me for
                    seeking to recover what is my own, especially as it is for a marriage-portion
                    for my daughter. For it so happened that I married at my father's request when I
                    was only eighteen, and that I have a daughter who is already of marriageable
                    age. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>It is, therefore, just on many accounts that you should aid me who am being
                    wronged, and fitting that you should feel indignation against the men, who—O
                    Earth and the Gods—when they need not have come into court at all had they done
                    what is fair, are not ashamed to remind you of any improper acts of my father,
                    or of wrongs which they committed against him, but even force me to go to law
                    with them. To make you understand clearly that it is they, not I, who are to
                    blame for this, I will set forth to you the facts of the case from the beginning
                    with the utmost possible brevity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>My mother, men of the jury, was the daughter of Polyaratus, of Cholargus<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cholargus was a deme of the tribe
                        Acamantis.</note>, and sister of Menexenus, and Bathyllus and Periander. Her
                    father gave her in marriage to Cleomedon, son of Cleon,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The famous demagogue, known to us from Thucydides and
                        Aristophanes.</note> adding a talent as her marriage-portion; and at the
                    first she dwelt with him as his wife, and bore him three daughters and one son,
                    Cleon. After this her husband died, and she left his family, receiving back her
                    marriage-portion. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>Her brothers, Menexenus and.Bathyllus (for Periander was still a boy) then gave
                    her again in marriage with the talent for her dowry, and she dwelt with my
                    father as his wife. There were born to them myself and another brother, younger
                    than I, who died while still a child.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To prove
                    that I am speaking the truth, I will first bring forward witnesses to establish
                    these facts.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>My father, then, having thus married my mother, maintained her as his wife in his
                    own house; and he brought me up and showed me a father's affection such as you
                    also all show to your children. But with Plangon, the mother of these men, he
                    formed a connection of some sort or other (it is not for me to say what it was);
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>however, he was not so wholly the slave of his passion as to deem it right even
                    after my mother's death to receive the woman into his own house, or to admit
                    that the defendants were his children. No, for all the rest of the time they
                    lived as not being sons of my father, as most of you know; but after Boeotus had
                    grown up and had associated with himself a gang of blackmailers,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">On this whole passage compare the preceding
                        oration, <bibl n="Dem. 39.2">Dem. 39.2</bibl>.</note> whose leaders were
                    Mnesicles and that Menecles who secured the conviction of Ninus, in connection
                    with these men he brought suit against my father, claiming that he was his son.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>Many meetings took place about these matters, and my father declared that he
                    would never be convinced that these men were his children, and finally Plangon,
                    men of the jury (for the whole truth shall be told you), having in conjunction
                    with Menecles laid a snare for my father, and deceived him by an oath that among
                    all mankind is held to be the greatest and most awful,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">A quotation from <bibl n="Hom. Il. 15.37">Hom. Il.
                            15.37</bibl> f.</note> agreed that, if she were paid thirty minae, she
                    would get her brothers to adopt these men, and that, on her own part, if my
                    father should challenge her before the arbitrator to swear that the children
                    were in very truth his sons, she would decline the challenge. For if this were
                    done, she said, the defendants would not be deprived of their civic rights,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">These would be ensured to them by the fact of
                        their being enrolled in the clan register; but if they were enrolled as sons
                        of the brothers of Plangon, they could no longer “make trouble” for Mantias
                        by claiming to be sons of his.</note> but they would no longer be able to
                    make trouble for my father, seeing that their mother had refused the oath. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>When these terms had been accepted—for why should I make my story a long one?—he
                    went to meet her before the arbitrator, and Plangon, contrary to all that she
                    had agreed to do, accepted the challenge, and swore in the Delphinium<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The temple of Apollo Delphinius, situated
                        somewhere near the ancient entrance to the Acropolis.</note> an oath which
                    was the very opposite of her former one, as most of you know well; for the
                    transaction became a notorious one. Thus, my father was compelled on account of
                    his own challenge to abide by the arbitrator's award, but he was indignant at
                    what had been done, and took the matter heavily to heart, and did not even so
                    consent to admit these men into his house; but he was compelled to introduce
                    them to the clansmen. The defendant he enrolled as Boeotus, and the other as
                    Pamphilus. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>As for me, he forthwith persuaded me, for I was about eighteen years of age, to
                    marry the daughter of Euphemus, wishing to live to see children born to me. I,
                    men of the jury, as before, so especially then, when these men were beginning to
                    annoy him with lawsuits and were proving troublesome, thought that I, on the
                    contrary, ought to strive to gladden him by doing everything whereby I could
                    give him pleasure, and so obeyed him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>When I had married in this way, and he had lived to see my little daughter born,
                    not many years later he fell sick and died. Then, although during my father's
                    lifetime, men of the jury, I had thought it my duty to oppose him in nothing,
                    yet after his death I received these men into the house, and gave them a share
                    of all the property, not as being really my brothers (for most of you are well
                    aware of the manner in which they became such), but thinking that, as my father
                    had been beguiled, it was my duty to obey your laws. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>And when they had thus been received by me into the house, we proceeded to divide
                    the inheritance; and upon my demanding that my mother's marriage-portion be
                    repaid to me, these men put in a counter-claim, and alleged that a portion of
                    like amount was owing to their mother.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Below
                            (<bibl n="Dem. 40.20">Dem. 40.20</bibl>, end) the amount is set at more
                        than 100 minae, not a talent merely.</note> On the advice of friends who
                    were present we divided all the rest of the property but kept apart the house
                    and the domestic servants of my father, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>in order that whichever party of us might establish his claim to the dowry should
                    recover it from the value of the house; and from the slaves, who were common
                    property, the defendants, should they wish to search out<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The precise meaning of this phrase is open to question. It
                        may imply a claim that some property had been omitted from the inventory or
                        in some way concealed.</note> any of my father's effects, might make inquiry
                    by torturing them, or by prosecuting their search in any other way they might
                    please.That I am speaking the truth in this also you will know from these
                        depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>After this these men brought action against me to establish their claims, and I
                    sued them for the marriage-portion. At the first we had Solon, of Erchia,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Erchia was a deme of the tribe Aeantis.</note>
                    registered as arbitrator, and submitted to him for decision the claims we
                    advanced against each other. These men, however, did not appear, but avoided the
                    hearing; and thus considerable time was wasted, and it came about that Solon
                    died. These men then instituted their suit against me afresh, and I my suit
                    against the defendant, summoning him under the name of Boeotus, and inscribing
                    that name on the complaint; for that was the name my father gave him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>In the suit which these men brought against me, Boeotus appeared and fought the
                    case, but, since he was unable to establish any of their claims, the arbitrator
                    decided in my favor; and Boeotus, conscious that he was making charges without
                    any just basis, did not appeal to a jury, and has not now entered any suit
                    against me in regard to these matters, but in regard to some others, thinking to
                    break down this suit of mine by these counter-charges.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Boeotus evidently hoped that making claims on his own behalf
                        he could offset the claim of Mantitheus for the dowry of his mother.</note>
                    In the suit which at that time I was carrying on against Boeotus in regard to
                    the marriage-portion, since he was here in Athens and did not appear before the
                    arbitrator, the latter gave judgement against him by default. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>And Boeotus, men of the jury, though he was here at the time would not contest
                    the suit, but declared that I had not received the arbitrator's verdict against
                    him, for his name was not Boeotus, but Mantitheus; and thus, by quibbling about
                    a name, he is in fact depriving me of my mother's portion. As I was at a loss to
                    know how one should deal with a matter like this, I instituted the same suit
                    afresh against him as Mantitheus, and now in the eleventh year I have come to
                    you for help.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To prove that I am speaking the
                    truth in this also, the clerk will read the depositions dealing with these
                        matters.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>That my mother, therefore, men of the jury, bringing a talent as her dowry, and
                    given in marriage by her brothers, as the laws command, lived with my father as
                    his wife; the manner, too, in which I received these men into the house after my
                    father's death; and the fact that I obtained a verdict in the suits which they
                    brought against me;—all this has been established for you by proofs and by
                    testimony.Come now, take also this law concerning the marriage-portion.<quote
                        type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>Such being the law, I fancy that this man—call him Boeotus or Mantitheus, or any
                    other name by which he likes to be addressed—will have no valid or genuine
                    defence to offer, but, relying upon his own audaciousness and effrontery, will
                    endeavor to attach to me the misfortunes of his own family, as he is wont to do
                    also in private life; and will allege that when the property of Pamphilus, who
                    was the father of Plangon, was confiscated, my father took from out the
                        council-chamber<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Bouleuterion, the
                        meeting-place of the Council of 500, has been identified with a building
                        found on the east slope of the “Theseum” hill, overlooking the Agora. See
                        Vanderpool, <title>Hesperia</title>, 4. pp. 470 ff.</note> the surplus
                        proceeds<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The amount, that is, over and
                        above the debt to the treasury.</note> and he will thus try to show that his
                    own mother brought a dowry of more than one hundred minae, while my mother (he
                    will claim) brought my father no portion whatever. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>These things he will state at length to you, men of the jury, although he has not
                    put a single deposition in the box to substantiate them, and knows very well
                    that there is not a word of truth in what he says; for he is fully conscious
                    that in your court no man who confessed his guilt was ever acquitted, whereas by
                    lying and advancing arguments to lead you astray many a man ere now has avoided
                    paying the penalty for his deeds. In order, then, that you may not be deceived
                    by him, I think it is better to speak to you briefly about this matter also.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>For if he shall say that my mother did not bring with her a marriage-portion,
                    while their mother did, bear in mind that he is manifestly lying. To begin with,
                    Pamphilus, the father of this man's mother, died owing five talents to the
                    public treasury, and so far from there being any surplus proceeds for his
                    children after his property had been scheduled and confiscated, even his
                    indebtedness has not been paid in full, but to this day Pamphilus stands
                    inscribed as a debtor to the treasury. How, then, can it be that my father
                    received money from the estate of Pamphilus, which proved inadequate to pay in
                    full even the debt due to the city? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, men of the jury, bear this in mind, that were it never so true that
                    this surplus money did accrue as these men pretend, it was not my father who
                    would have received it, but the sons of Pamphilus, Boeotus and Hedylus and
                    Euthydemus; and, I fancy, they are not men who would go to all lengths to get
                    hold of the property of others, as you all know, and yet at the same time
                    quietly have allowed my father to take possession of what was theirs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>That the mother of these men did not bring with her a marriage-portion, but that
                    they are lying in regard to this, I think has been proved to you quite
                    adequately; but that my mother did bring one, I shall easily show. In the first
                    place, she was the daughter of Polyaratus, who was both honored by you citizens,
                    and had acquired a large estate. Secondly, it has been proved to you by
                    witnesses that her sister brought a dowry of the like amount when she married
                    Eryximachus, the brother-in-law of Chabrias.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >The famous Athenian general, whose victories over the Lacedaemonians made
                        him one of the most notable figures in Athenian military history during the
                        first half fo the fourth century B.C.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>Besides all this, my mother is shown to have been first given in marriage to
                    Cleomedon, whose father Cleon, we are told,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A
                        striking instance of the Greek preference for the spoken rather than the
                        written word.</note> commanded troops among whom were your ancestors, and
                    captured alive a large number of Lacedaemonians in Pylos,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">This was in <date when="-0425">425</date> B.C. The account
                        is given in <bibl n="Thuc. 4.3">Thuc. 4.3</bibl> ff.</note> and won greater
                    renown than any other man in the state; so it was not fitting that the son of
                    that famous man should wed my mother without a dowry, nor is it likely that
                    Menexenus and Bathyllus, who had large fortunes themselves, and who, after
                    Cleomedon's death, received back the dowry, defrauded their own sister; rather,
                    they would themselves have added to her portion, when they gave her in marriage
                    to my father, as they themselves and the others have testified before you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>And besides this, just consider why in the world, if my mother had not been a
                    lawfully espoused wife, and had brought no dowry, while the mother of these men
                    did, should my father have denied that they were his sons, and have acknowledged
                    me, and brought me up? Because, forsooth, as these men will claim, he dishonored
                    them in order to show favor to me and my mother. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>But my mother died, leaving me still a little boy, whereas the mother of these
                    men, Plangon, who was a handsome woman, maintained her connection with him both
                    before and after that; so that it was much more likely that for the sake of the
                    living woman, with whom he was in love all this time, he would dishonor the son
                    of her who was dead, than that for my sake and my dead mother's he would refuse
                    to acknowledge the children of her who was living and maintaining her connection
                    with him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>My opponent, however, has come to such a pitch of audacity as to declare that my
                    father made feast for him on the tenth day.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See
                        the Introduction to the preceding oration.</note> And in regard to this he
                    has put in depositions of Timocrates<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Perhaps to
                        be identified with the Timocrates against whom Demosthenes delivered Oration
                        24 (<bibl n="Dem. 24">Dem. 24</bibl>).</note> and Promachus alone, who are
                    in no way related to my father, and were not friends of his. The testimony they
                    have borne is so patently false, that, whereas you all know that Boeotus by
                    instituting proceedings forced my father against his will to acknowledge him
                    these men, like witnesses to a summons—and only two of them—depose that he made
                    a feast for this fellow on the tenth day! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>Is there anyone of you who can believe that? And assuredly it is not open to him
                    to say this, either—that when he was a little child my father acknowledged him,
                    but that when he was grown he scorned him because of some quarrel with the
                    mother of these men;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Compare the parallel
                        passage in the preceding oration, <bibl n="Dem. 39.23">Dem.
                        39.23</bibl>.</note> for surely man and wife are much more apt, in cases
                    where they are at variance with one another, to become reconciled for the sake
                    of their children than, because of their enmity toward each other, to hate their
                    common children as well. If, therefore, he attempts to say this, do not permit
                    him to brazen it out. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>And should he go on to talk about the actions brought by them, which the
                    arbitrator decided in my favor, and claim that he was caught by me unprepared,
                    remember, first, that it was not a short time that he had in which to prepare
                    himself, but a great many years, and secondly, that it was he who brought the
                    suit, so that it was much more likely that I should be taken unprepared by him
                    than he by me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>And further, all those who were present before the arbitrator have given
                    testimony that Boeotus was present when the arbitrator gave his decision in my
                    favor and that he did not appeal to the court, but acquiesced in the decision.
                    And yet it seems to me a strange thing that, whereas other men, who consider
                    that they are being wronged,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, by the
                        arbitrator's award.</note> bring before you on appeal cases even of the
                    slightest import, this fellow, who had brought suit against me to recover a
                    talent as the marriage-portion, and had this suit decided against him by the
                    arbitrator, unjustly, as he claims, should acquiesce in the decision. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>Ah, but it may be said that he is a man who loves peace and hates litigation. I
                    could indeed wish, men of the jury, that he were a man of that type. But here is
                    the truth: you are so generous and so kind toward your fellow-men that you did
                    not deem it right to banish from the city even the sons of the Thirty
                        Tyrants<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In <date when="-0403">403</date>
                        B.C.</note>; but Boeotus, plotting against me with Menecles, who is the
                    prime mover in all these schemes, having managed to get up a quarrel that from
                    disputes and revilings should come to blows, cut his own head, and summoned me
                    before the Areopagus on a charge of murderous assault, with the intention of
                    driving me into exile from the city. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>And if Euthydicus, the physician, to whom these men had gone in the first
                    instance, asking him to make a cut on the head of Boeotus—had not told to the
                    court of the Areopagus the whole truth, this man would have taken such vengeance
                    upon me, who was guilty of no wrong toward him, as you would not try to inflict
                    on those who were guilty of the greatest wrongs toward you.That I may not be
                    thought to be slandering him, read, please, the depositions.<quote
                        type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>This great and formidable contest, then, he got up against me, not as a
                    simple-minded fellow, but as a conspirator and a villain. But after this,
                    instead of the name, Boeotus, which my father had given him, as has been proved
                    to you by witnesses, after my father's death he had his name inscribed on the
                    list of the demesmen as Mantitheus, and being further addressed by the name of
                    the same father and the same deme as I myself, he not only forced a retrial of
                    the case in which I am now suing him,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">By
                        claiming that his name was Mantitheus, not Boeotus, he made of no effect the
                        judgement rendered against him under the latter name.</note> but when you
                    had elected me taxiarch, he came in person to the court to pass the probationary
                        test<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Every Athenian elected to public
                        office had to pass a scrutiny (<foreign xml:lang="grc">dokimasi/a</foreign>)
                        and prove his full citizenship.</note>; and when judgement had been given
                    against him in an ejectment suit, he declared that it was not against him but
                    against me that the judgement had been given. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>And to sum up the matter for you, he gave me so much trouble that he compelled me
                    to bring suit against him regarding the name, not in order to get money from
                    him, men of the jury, but that, if it should appear to you that I am being
                    outrageously treated and am suffering grievous wrongs, he may go on being called
                    Boeotus, as my father named him.To prove that I am speaking the truth in this
                    also, take, please, the depositions bearing on these matters.<quote
                        type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>In addition to all this, on the charge that, when I was on military service and
                    had collected mercenaries with Ameinias<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Apparently an otherwise unknown commander of mercenary troops, under whom
                        Mantitheus served as taxiarch.</note>(seeing that I was well-provided with
                    funds from other sources, and had collected from Mytilene from your
                        proxenus<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A state representative in a
                        foreign land, somewhat analogous to our consul.</note> Apollonides and the
                    friends of our city three hundred Phocaic staters,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The stater of Phocaea (a city on the coast of Ionia) was a
                        gold coin somewhat heavier than the stater of Cyzicus (<bibl n="Dem. 34.23"
                            >Dem. 34.23</bibl>).</note> and had spent that sum upon these troops, in
                    order that a matter might be prosecuted which was of advantage to you and to
                    them alike)— </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>for this he brings suit against me, alleging that I had collected a debt due to
                    my father from the city of the Mytileneans. In this he was seeking to serve
                        Cammys,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A tyrant of Mytilene, otherwise
                        unknown.</note> tyrant of Mytilene, who is an enemy of Athens and a private
                    enemy of mine.But to prove that my father at the time received in person the
                    reward which the people of Mytilene voted him, and that no debt was owing to him
                    in Mytilene, I will produce a deposition of your friends.<quote
                        type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>I could mention many other outrageous acts of which Boeotus has been guilty, men
                    of the jury, both against myself and against you; but I am compelled to pass
                    them by as but little water is left me in the clepsydra.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The water-clock.</note> I think, however, that, even as it
                    is, you have been shown conclusively that the same man who got up against me a
                    suit involving the risk of banishment, and sued me on charges which concerned me
                    not at all, is not one who would have come before the arbitrator unprepared; so
                    that if he tries to say anything about this, I imagine that you will not
                    tolerate it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>If, however, he declares that he offered to turn over all matters at issue
                    between us to Conon,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The grandson of the famous
                        Athenian general of this name.</note> son of Timotheus, for arbitration, and
                    that I refused to submit them, be sure that he will be trying to mislead you. I,
                    for my part, was ready to submit all matters upon which a decision had not yet
                    been rendered, either to Conon or to any other impartial arbitrator whom Boeotus
                    might choose; but matters regarding which the arbitrator had given a decision in
                    my favor, after Boeotus had thrice appeared before him and contested the case,—a
                    decision in which Boeotus acquiesced, as witnesses have testified to you,—these
                    matters, I thought, could not justly be reopened. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>For to what final settlement could we ever have come, if I had made invalid a
                    decision given by an arbitrator in accordance with the laws, and had referred
                    the same charge to the decision of another arbitrator?—especially as I knew full
                    well that, even though in relation to other men it is not proper to insist
                    overmuch on the decisions of arbitrators, yet it is peculiarly fair to deal thus
                    with Boeotus. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>For come, suppose someone should indict him for the usurpation of the rights of
                    citizenship, declaring that my father denied on oath that this man was his son;
                    could he rely on anything else to meet this charge than that, because of their
                    mother's oath and the decision of the arbitrators, my father was forced to abide
                    by the award? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>It would, then, be an outrageous thing, if this man, after having become a
                    citizen of your city through an arbitrator's decision, and having secured a
                    share of my inheritance, and obtained all that was fair, should be thought by
                    you to have any justice in his claim, when he demanded the reopening of the
                    suits in which I won my acquittal, when he was present and argued against it,
                    and acquiesced in the verdict; just as though, when it is to his interest,
                    awards ought to be valid, but, when it is not to his interest, his opinion
                    should have more weight than decisions rendered in accordance with your laws.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>He is such a crafty schemer that his purpose even in this proposal of arbitration
                    was not made that he might be rid of his disputes with me, but that, as he had
                    for eleven years previously carried on his knavery, so now, by rendering invalid
                    the decisions given in my favor by the arbitrator, he might afresh institute his
                    malicious proceedings against me, and elude the present suit. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>Here is a convincing proof of this. He would not accept the challenge which I
                    gave him according to the laws; and when I had previously referred the suit
                    about the name to Xenippus, whom he had proposed as arbitrator, he forbade him
                    to render any decision.That I am speaking the truth on these matters also you
                    will learn from the deposition and the challenge.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>This challenge, then, he did not accept, wishing rather to lay a snare for me and
                    to delay the suit as long as he possibly could; and now, as I learn, he will
                    accuse not only me, but my father as well, alleging that my father wronged him
                    in many ways in order to show favor to me. But I beg you, men of the jury, as
                    you would yourselves deem it an unseemly thing to be evil spoken of by your own
                    children, not to allow this man either to speak evil of his father. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>For it would indeed be an outrageous thing when you yourselves, after having come
                    to terms with those who in the time of the oligarchy put to death without trial
                    numbers of your countrymen, abide by your compact with them,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The allusion is to the amnesty declared after the expulsion
                        of the Thirty Tyrants. For this “gentleness” of the democracy see <bibl
                            n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 22.4">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 22.4</bibl>.</note> as
                    men of honor should do, that you should allow this man, who was reconciled with
                    my father while he lived, and won many advantages to which he had no right, now
                    to renew the quarrel and to speak evil of that father when he is no more. Do not
                    suffer this, men of the jury. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>If it be possible, prevent him from acting in this way; but if he persists in
                    defying you and in speaking evil of my father, remember that he is bearing
                    witness against himself that he is no son of his. For those who are true-born
                    children, even though they may quarrel with their fathers while they are alive
                    yet speak well of them when they are dead; whereas those who are accounted sons,
                    but are not in truth children of their supposed fathers, quarrel with them
                    without scruple while they are alive, and think nothing of slandering them when
                    they are dead. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>And, besides, think how absurd it is that this fellow should abuse my father for
                    his failings toward him, when it was thanks to this father's failings<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">“There is a play on the double sense of <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">a(marta/nein</foreign>, which is often used as a
                        euphemism for the frailties of love.”—Paley.</note> that he became a citizen
                    of your state. I, on my part, have, thanks to the mother of these men, been
                    deprived of two-thirds of my property, but for all that I have too much respect
                    for you to speak disparagingly of her. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>But Boeotus feels no shame in disparaging before you the man whom he compelled to
                    become his father, and has even come to such a pitch of vulgarity that, although
                    the laws forbid speaking ill even of other men's fathers after they are dead, he
                    will slander the man whose son he claims to be; whereas it would be proper for
                    him to show resentment if anyone else spoke evil of him. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>I fancy, men of the jury, that, when he is at a loss for anything else to say, he
                    will undertake to speak evil of me, and will try to bring me into disrepute,
                    rehearsing at length how I was reared and educated and married in my father's
                    house, while he had no share in any of these advantages. But I bid you bear in
                    mind that my mother died leaving me a child, so that the interest of her
                    marriage-portion was sufficient to rear and educate me; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>whereas Plangon, the mother of these men, maintained them and a host of female
                    servants in her own house, and herself lived lavishly, having my father ready,
                    because of his passion for her, to supply the funds for all this, and forcing
                    him to heavy expenditures. She therefore spent far more of his property than I
                    did, so that I might with far better reason bring charges against them than they
                    against me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>For, besides all the rest, in connection with my father I borrowed twenty minae
                    from Blepaeus the banker, for the purchase of some mining properties, and after
                    my father's death I shared the mines with these men, but had to pay the loan
                    myself. I also borrowed another thousand drachmae from Lysistratus of Thoricus
                    for my father's funeral, and have personally paid the debt.That I am speaking
                    the truth on these matters also you will learn from these depositions.<quote
                        type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>When I am thus so clearly at a disadvantage in so many respects, shall this man
                    now by making a great to-do and outcry about his wrongs, rob me also of my
                    mother's marriage-portion? But do not, men of the jury, I beg you by Zeus and
                    the Gods, do not be overwhelmed by the noise he makes. He is a violent fellow,
                    violent and ready to go to all lengths; and he is so unscrupulous that, if he
                    has no witnesses to prove a fact, he will say that it is well known to you, men
                    of the jury,—a trick to which all those have recourse who have no just argument
                    to advance. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>If he shall try any such trick, do not tolerate it; expose him. What anyone of
                    you does not know, let his deem that his neighbor does not know either. Let him
                    demand that Boeotus prove clearly whatever statements he may make, and not shirk
                    the truth by declaring that you know things about which he will have no just
                    argument to advance; since I, on my part, men of the jury, although you all know
                    the way in which my father was compelled to adopt these men, am none the less
                    suing them at law, and have brought forward witnesses responsible for their
                        testimony.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Liable, that is, to prosecution
                        for perjury, if their testimony be proved false.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>And yet the risk is not the same for both of us. On my part, if you are now led
                    astray by these men, it will not be open to me to bring suit again for the
                    marriage-portion; but they, if they claim that the arbitrator was wrong in
                    giving his decision in my favor, as at that time they had the right to appeal to
                    your court, so now again will be permitted, if they so wish, to recover their
                    rights from me in your court. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>I, if you leave me in the lurch, which I pray may not happen, shall have no means
                    of giving a dowry to my daughter, whose own father I am, although, if you see
                    her size, you would deem she was not my daughter but my sister<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">See above, <bibl n="Dem. 40.12">Dem. 40.12</bibl>.</note>;
                    but these men, if you come to my aid, will pay nothing out of their own
                    property, but will restore to me what is my own from the house which by common
                    agreement we reserved for the settlement of the marriage-portion, but in which
                    these men have been living by themselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>For it is not fitting that I, having a daughter of marriageable age, should dwell
                    with men of their sort, who are not only themselves living licentious lives, but
                    who also bring into the house a host of others of like stamp with themselves;
                    nay, by Zeus, I do not deem it safe to live in the same house with them myself.
                    When they have thus openly laid a plot, and got up a charge against me before
                    the Areopagus, do you suppose there is any poisoning or any other such villainy
                    from which they would abstain? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>Besides all the rest (for this has occurred to me just now), they have come to
                    such a pitch of audacity as to have put in a deposition of Crito, alleging that
                    he has purchased from me my one-third share in the house. Now that this is false
                    you will easily perceive; for in the first place Crito does not live so
                    economically as to be able to purchase a house from someone else, but so
                    extravagantly and licentiously that he spends the property of others as well as
                    his own. Again, he is not now this man's witness, but rather my adversary. For
                    who among you is ignorant that witnesses are those who have no interest in the
                    matter at issue in the suit; while adversaries are those who are involved in the
                    matters in regard to which one goes to law with them? The latter is the case
                    with Crito. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>And furthermore, out of all your number, men of the jury, out of all the host of
                    the rest of the Athenians, not a single other person has testified that he was
                    present at this sale; Timocrates alone, like a god from the machine,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The deus ex machina of the tragic stage.</note>
                    testified that my father gave a feast to Boeotus on the tenth day (and
                    Timocrates is of the same age as the present defendant!). Timocrates declares
                    that he has perfect knowledge of all that is for the advantage of these men; and
                    now on his own sole authority he testifies that he was present with Crito when
                    he bought the house from me. Who among you will believe this? Not one, of
                    course; especially since I am not now suing about the house to determine whether
                    Crito bought it or not, but about the marriage-portion which, seeing that my
                    mother brought it with her, the laws declare that I should recover. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>Therefore, as I have proved to you by an abundance of testimony and of
                    circumstantial evidence that my mother did bring a talent as her dowry; that I
                    have not recovered it from my father's estate; and that the house was set apart
                    by us to secure its payment; so do you demand of Boeotus that he prove to you,
                    either that I am not speaking the truth, or that it is not right that I should
                    recover the marriage-portion; for these are the questions regarding which you
                    are now going to cast your votes. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
                <p>But if, having no trustworthy witnesses, nor any other proofs regarding the
                    matters upon which he is being sued, he shall try unscrupulously to introduce
                    irrelevant arguments, and if he indulges in outcries and protestations which
                    have nothing to do with the matter, I adjure you by Zeus and the Gods, do not
                    tolerate it; nay, render me the help that is my due, remembering in the light of
                    all that I have urged that it is far more just that you should by your verdict
                    give my mother's portion to my daughter for her dowry, than that Plangon and
                    these men, in addition to all the rest that they have done, should, in utter
                    defiance of justice, rob me also of my house, which was set apart to secure the
                    payment of the marriage-portion.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
