<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader>
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>Preface</title>
				        <author>Appian</author>
				        <editor role="translator">Horace White</editor>
				        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				        <respStmt>
					          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					          <name>William Merrill</name>
					          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					          <name>David Smith</name>
				        </respStmt>
				        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			      </publicationStmt>

			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <author>Appian</author>
						            <title>The Roman History of Appian of Alexandria</title>
					          		<title type="sub">The Foreign Wars</title>
						            <editor role="translator">Horace White</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>The Macmillan Company</publisher>
							              <date>1899</date>
						            </imprint>
					          	<biblScope unit="volume">1
					          	</biblScope>
					          </monogr>
				        	<ref target="Open Content Alliance">https://archive.org/details/romanhistorytran01appiuoft</ref>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>

		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
         	<cRefPattern n="card" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
         		<p>This pointer pattern extracts card</p>
         	</cRefPattern>
              </refsDecl>
            </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="eng">English</language>
				        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
				        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>


		    <revisionDesc>
         <change who="gcrane"/>
		    	<change who="amahoney" when="2004-08-10">fix the XML files so they are valid, make the SGML obsolete so no one is confused</change>
		    	<change who="packel" when="2006-02-10">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
		    	<change who="rsingh04" when="2009-01-29">fixed chunking scheme</change>
		    	<change who="rsingh04" when="2009-02-27">fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags</change>
		    	<change who="student CEH" when="2009-07-06">edited entity tags CEH</change>
		    	<change who="lcerrato" when="2009-08-19">fixing Athenaeus refs</change>
		    	<change who="rsingh04" when="2009-10-07">began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files
		    	</change>
		    	<change who="Stella Dee" when="2014-07">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
		    	<change who="DMM" when="2013-11-02"/>
		    	<change who="TDBuck" when="2015-12-03">Updated for Epidoc and CTS Compliance</change>
      </revisionDesc>
	  </teiHeader>
	  <text>
		    <body>
         <div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0551.tlg001.perseus-eng2" type="translation" xml:lang="eng">
         	<div type="textpart" subtype="preface">
         	     <div n="1" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>
                  <figure>
						               <head>REDUCED FACSIMILE, VATICAN MS. GR. 141. XII CENTURY, FIRST PAGE OF
							AUTHOR'S PREFACE</head>
					             </figure> INTENDING to write the history of the Romans I have deemed it best to
					begin with the boundaries of the nations under their sway. They are as follows:
					In the ocean, the major part of those who inhabit the British Isles. Then
					entering the Mediterranean by the Pillars of Hercules and circumnavigating the
					same we find under their rule all the islands and the mainlands washed by that
					sea. The first of these on the right hand are the Mauritanians of the coast and
					various other African nations as far as Carthage. Farther inland are the nomad
					tribes whom the Romans call Numidians and their country Numidia; then other
					Africans who dwell around the Syrtes as far as Cyrene, and Cyrene itself; also
					the Marmaridæ, the Ammonii, and those who dwell by the lake Mareotis; then the
					great city founded by Alexander on the border of Egypt, and Egypt itself, as one
					sails up the Nile, as far as eastern Ethiopia; and as far as Pelusium by sea. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="2" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>Here turning our course we take in Palestine-Syria, and beyond it a part of
					Arabia. The Phœnicians hold the country next to Palestine on the sea, and beyond
					the Phœnician territory are Cœle-Syria, and the parts stretching from the sea as
					far inland as the river Euphrates, namely Palmyra and the sandy country round
					about, extending even to the Euphrates itself. The Cilicians come next to the
					Syrians, and their neighbors are the Cappadocians, and that part of the Armenian
					country called Lesser Armenia. Along the Euxine are other nations called by the
					common name Pontic, subject to the Roman rule. The Syrians and Cilicians border
					on the Mediterranean, the Armenians and Cappadocians extend to the Pontic
					nations and to the interior as far as Greater Armenia, which is not subject to
					the Romans in the way of tribute, but its people appoint their own kings.
					Descending from Cilicia and Cappadocia to Ionia we find the great peninsula
					bounded on the right by the Euxine, the Propontis, the Hellespont, and the
					Ægean, and on the left by the Pamphylian or Egyptian sea, for it is called by
					both names. Some of the countries embraced in it look toward the Egyptian sea,
					namely: Pamphylia and Lycia and after them Caria extending to Ionia. Others look
					toward the Euxine, the Propontis, and the Hellespont, namely: the Galatians,
					Bithynians, Mysians, and Phrygians. In the interior are the Pisidians and
					Lydians. So many nations inhabit this peninsula and all are under Roman rule. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="3" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>Crossing from these coasts they rule other nations around the Euixine, the
					Mysians of Europe and the Thracians who border that sea. Beyond Ionia are the
					Ægean sea, the Adriatic, the straits of Sicily, and the Tyrrhenian sea
					stretching to the Pillars of Hercules. This is the distance from Ionia to the
					ocean. Following the coast line we find the following countries subject to the
					Romans: all of Greece, Thessaly, and Macedonia, also the adjoining Thracians,
					the Illyrians, and Pannonians, and Italy itself, the longest of all, extending
					from the Adriatic and bordering the greater part of the Tyrrhenian sea as far as
					the country of the Celts (whom the Romans call Gauls), some of whom border the
					Mediterranean, others the Northern ocean, and still others dwell along the river
					Rhine; also all of Spain and Celtiberia on the Northern and Western oceans as
					far as the Pillars of Hercules. Of these I shall speak more particularly when I
					come to deal with each nation. But for the present let this suffice for the
					principal boundaries which define their empire along the sea. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="4" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>On the landward side the boundaries are a part of Mauritania lying against
					western Ethiopia and the remainder of Africa (having a very warm climate, or
					much infested with wild beasts) extending to eastern Ethiopia. These are the
					Roman boundaries in Africa. Those of Asia are the river Euphrates, Mount
					Caucasus, the kingdom of Greater Armenia, the Colchians who dwell along the
					Euxine sea, and the remainder of that coast. In Europe the two rivers, Rhine and
					Danube, for the most part bound the Roman empire. Of these the Rhine empties
					into the <figure>
						               <figDesc>The Roman Empire at the Time of Hadrian</figDesc>
					             </figure> Northern ocean and the Danube into the Euxine. On the other side of
					these rivers, however, some of the Celts beyond the Rhine are under Roman sway,
					and beyond the Danube some of the Getæ, who are called Dacians. These, with the
					nearest approach to accuracy, are the boundaries on the mainland. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="5" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>All the islands of the sea also, the Cyclades, Sporades, Ionian isles, Echinades,
					the Tuscan isles, the Balearic isles, and all the rest in Libyan, Ionian,
					Egyptian, Myrtoan, Sicilian, and Mediterranean waters, by whatever names called;
					also those which the Greeks by way of distinction call the great islands,
					Cyprus, Crete, Rhodes, Lesbos, Eubœa, Sicily, Sardinia, and Corsica, and
					whatever other isle there may be, large or small--all are under Roman rule.
					Crossing the Northern ocean to Britain, a continent in itself, they took
					possession of the better and larger part, not caring for the remainder. Indeed,
					the part they do hold is not of much use to them. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="6" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>Although holding the empire of so many and so great nations the Romans labored
					five hundred years with toil and difficulty to establish their power firmly in
					Italy itself. Half of this time they were under kings, but having expelled them
					and sworn to have kingly rule no longer, they adopted aristocracy, and chose
					their rulers yearly. In the two hundred years next succeeding the five hundred
					their dominion increased greatly, they acquired unexampled foreign power, and
					brought the greater part of the nations under their sway. Gaius [Julius] Cæsar
					having got the upper hand of his rivals possessed himself of the sovereignty,
					holding it in a firm grasp, and preserved the form and name of the republic but
					made himself the absolute ruler of all. In this way the government, from that
					time to this, has been a monarchy; but they do not call their rulers kings, out
					of respect, as I think, for the ancient oath. They call them imperators
					[emperors], that being the title also of those who formerly held the chief
					command of the armies for the time being. Yet they are very kings in fact. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="7" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>From the advent of the emperors to the present time is nearly two hundred years
					more, in the course of which the city has been greatly embellished, its revenue
					much increased, and in the long reign of peace and security everything has moved
					toward a lasting prosperity. Some nations have been added to the empire by these
					emperors, and the revolts of others have been suppressed. Possessing the best
					part of the earth and sea they have, on the whole, aimed to preserve their
					empire by the exercise of prudence, rather than to extend their sway
					indefinitely over poverty-stricken and profitless tribes of barbarians, some of
					whom I have seen at Rome offering themselves, by their ambassadors, as its
					subjects, but the chief of the state would not accept them because they would be
					of no use to it. They give kings to a great many other nations whom they do not
					wish to have under their own government. On some of these subject nations they
					spend more than they receive from them, deeming it dishonorable to give them up
					even though they are costly. They surround the empire with great armies and they
					garrison the whole stretch of land and sea like a single strong-hold. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="8" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>No government down to the present time ever attained to such size and duration.
					That of the Greeks, even if we count the mastery of Athens, Sparta, and Thebes
					successively from the invasion of Darius, which was the beginning of their
					glory, to the hegemony of Greece held by Philip the son of Amyntas, lasted
					comparatively but few years. Their wars were not for conquest abroad but rather
					for preëminence among themselves, and they were most distinguished for the
					defence of their freedom against foreign invaders. Those of them who invaded
					Sicily with the hope of extending their dominion made a failure, and whenever
					they marched into Asia they accomplished small results and speedily returned. In
					short the Greek power, although ardent in fighting for the Grecian hegemony,
					never advanced steadfastly beyond the boundaries of Greece, but took pride in
					holding itself unenslaved and seldom conquered, and from the time of Philip the
					son of Amyntas, and of Alexander the son of Philip, they seem to me to have done
					very badly and to have been unworthy of themselves. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="9" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>The mastery of Asia is not to be compared, as to labor and bravery, with that of
					the smallest of the countries of Europe, on account of the effeminacy and
					cowardice of the Asiatic peoples, as will be shown in the progress of this
					history. Such of the Asiatic nations as the Romans hold, they subdued in a few
					battles, though even the Macedonians joined in the defence, while the conquest
					of Africa and of Europe was in many cases very exhausting. Again, the duration
					of the Assyrians, Medes, and Persians taken together (the three greatest empires
					before Alexander), does not amount to nine hundred years, which that of Rome has
					already reached, and the size of their empire I think was not half that of the
					Romans, whose boundaries extend from the setting of the sun and the Western
					ocean to Mount Caucasus and the river Euphrates, and through Egypt to Ethiopia
					and through Arabia as far as the Eastern ocean, so that their boundary is the
					ocean both where the sun-god rises and where he sinks, while they control the
					entire Mediterranean, and all its islands as well as Britain in the ocean. The
					greatest sea-power of the Medes and Persians included either the gulf of
					Pamphylia and the single island of Cyprus or perhaps some other small islets
					belonging to Ionia in the Mediterranean. They controlled the Persian gulf also,
					but how much of a sea is that?<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">This
						is a conjectural rendering; the text is corrupt.</note>
				           </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="10" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>The history of Macedonia before Philip, the son of Amyntas, was of very small
					account; there was a time, indeed, when the Macedonians were a subject race. The
					reign of Philip himself was full of toil and struggles which were not
					contemptible, yet even his deeds concerned only Greece and the neighboring
					country. The empire of Alexander was splendid in its magnitude, in its armies,
					in the success and rapidity of his conquests, and it wanted little of being
					boundless and unexampled, yet in its shortness of duration it was like a
					brilliant flash of lightning. Although broken into several satrapies even the
					parts were splendid. The kings of my own country [Egypt] alone had an army
					consisting of 200,000 foot, 40,000 horse, 300 war elephants, and 2,000 armed
					chariots, and arms in reserve for 300,000 soldiers more. This was their force
					for land service. For naval service they had 2,000 barges propelled by poles,
					and other smaller craft, 1,500 galleys with from one and a half to five benches
					of oars each, and galley furniture for twice as many ships, 800 vessels provided
					with cabins, gilded on stem and stern for the pomp of war, with which the kings
					themselves were wont to go to naval combats; and money in their treasuries to
					the amount of 740,000 Egyptian talents. Such was the state of preparedness for
					war shown by the royal accounts as recorded and left by the king of Egypt second
					in succession after Alexander, who was the most formidable of these rulers in
					his preparations, the most lavish in expenditure, and the most magnificent in
					projects. It appears that many of the other satrapies were not much inferior in
					these respects. Yet all these resources were wasted under their successors by
					warring with each other. By means of such civil dissensions alone are great
					states destroyed. </p>
				           </div>
         					<div n="11" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>Through prudence and good fortune has the empire of the Romans attained to
					greatness and duration<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Literally:
						"The Roman power has excelled in greatness and good fortune by reason of
						prudence and long duration." This, as Schweighäuser points out, is an
						awkward expression and inharmonious with the author's argument, in which
						prudence and good fortune are grouped together as causes, and greatness and
						duration as consequences.</note> in gaining which they have excelled all
					others in bravery, patience, and hard labor. They were never elated by success
					until they had firmly secured their power, nor were they ever cast down by
					misfortune, although they sometimes lost 20,000 men in a single day, at another
					time 40,000, and once 50,000, and although the city itself was often in danger.
					Neither famine, nor frequently recurring plague, nor sedition, nor all these
					falling upon them at once could abate their ardor; until, through the doubtful
					struggles and dangers of seven hundred years, they achieved their present
					greatness, having enjoyed the favors of fortune through wisdom. </p>
				           </div>
			         	<div n="12" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>These things have been described by many writers, both Greek and Roman, and the
					history is even more copious than that of the Macedonian empire, which was the
					longest history of earlier times. Being interested in it, and desiring to
					compare the Roman prowess carefully with that of every other nation, my history
					has often led me from Carthage to Spain, from Spain to Sicily or to Macedonia,
					or to join some embassy to foreign countries, or some alliance formed with them;
					thence back to Carthage or Sicily, like a wanderer, and again elsewhere, while
					the work was still unfinished. At last I have brought the parts together,
					showing how often the Romans sent armies or embassies into Sicily and what they
					did there until they brought it into its present condition; also how often they
					made war and peace with the Carthaginians, or sent embassies to them or received
					the same from them, and what damage they inflicted upon or suffered from them
					until they demolished Carthage and made Africa a Roman province, and how they
					rebuilt Carthage and brought Africa into its present condition. I have made this
					research also in respect to each of the other provinces, desiring to learn the
					Romans' relations to each, in order to understand the weakness of these nations
					or their power of endurance, as well as the bravery or good fortune of their
					conquerors or any other circumstance contributing to the result. </p>
				           </div>
			         	<div n="13" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>Thinking that the public would like to learn the history of the Romans in this
					way, I am going to write the part relating to each nation separately, omitting
					what happened to the others in the meantime, and taking it up in its proper
					place. It seems superfluous to put down the dates of everything, but I shall
					mention those of the most important events now and then. The Roman citizens,
					like other people, formerly had only one name each; afterwards they took a
					second, and not much later, for easier recognition, there was given to some of
					them a third derived from some personal incident or as a distinction for
					bravery. In like manner surnames have been added to the names of certain Greeks.
					For purposes of distinction I shall sometimes mention all the names, especially
					of illustrious men, but for the most part I shall call these and others by the
					names that are deemed most characteristic. </p>
				           </div>
			         	<div n="14" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>As there are three books which treat of the numerous exploits of the Romans in
					Italy, these three must together be considered the Italian Roman history; but on
					account of the great number of events in them the division has been made. The
					first of these will show the events that took place in successive reigns while
					they had kings, of whom there were seven, and this I shall call the history of
					Rome under the kings. Next in order will be the history of the rest of Italy
					except the part along the Adriatic. This, by way of distinction from the former,
					will be called the second Italian book of Roman history. With the last nation,
					the Samnites, who dwelt on the Adriatic, the Romans struggled eighty years under
					the greatest difficulties, but finally they subjugated them and the neighbors
					who were allied with them, and also the Greeks who had settled in Italy. This,
					by way of distinction from the former, will be called the Samnite Roman history.
					The rest will be named according to its subject, the Celtic, Sicilian, Spanish,
					Hannibalic, Carthaginian, Macedonian, and so on. The order of these histories
					with respect to each other is according to the time when the Romans began to be
					embroiled in war with each nation, even though many other things intervened
					before that nation came to its end. The internal seditions and civil wars of the
					Romans--to them the most calamitous of all--will be designated under the names
					of their chief actors, as the wars of Marius and Sulla, those of Pompey and
					Caesar, those of Antony and the second Caesar, surnamed Augustus, against the
					murderers of the first Caesar, and those of Antony and Augustus against each
					other. At the end of this last of the civil wars Egypt passed under the Roman
					sway, and the Roman government itself became a monarchy. </p>
				           </div>
			         	<div n="15" type="textpart" subtype="card">
				           <p>Thus, the foreign wars will be divided into books according to the nations, and
					the civil wars according to the chief commanders. The last book will show the
					present military force of the Romans, the revenues they collect from each
					province, what they spend for the naval service, and other things of that kind.
					It is proper to begin with the origin of the people of whose prowess I am about
					to write. Who I am, who have written these things, many indeed know, and I have
					already indicated.<note resp="HW" place="foot" anchored="true">Schweighäuser
						considers this an allusion to the title page (now lost) which probably
						contained the name and nationality of the author.</note> To speak more
					plainly I am Appian of Alexandria, having reached the highest place in my native
					country, and having been, in Rome, a pleader of causes before the emperors,
					until they deemed me worthy of being made their procurator. And if any one has a
					great desire to learn more [about my affairs] there is a special treatise of
					mine on that subject. </p>
			         </div>
         </div>
         </div>
      </body>
	  </text>

</TEI>