<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>On the Peace</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <editor role="translator">J. H. Vince</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
                <date type="release">1996</date>
            </publicationStmt> 			
            <notesStmt><note>Perseus 2.0</note></notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes. Vol. I. Olynthiacs, Philippics, Minor Public Speeches, Speech Against Leptines, I-XVII, XX. With an English translation by J. H. Vince</title>
                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date type="printing">1930</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.12682">Internet Archive</ref>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split composite text and converted to unicode</change>
            <change when="1992-06-02" who="David Smith">inserted quotedtext tag around verse</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>I perceive, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that the
                    present outlook gives rise to much vexation and perplexity, because not only
                    have we suffered serious losses, which cannot be mended by fine speeches, but
                    there is also complete divergence of opinion about the preservation of what is
                    left of our empire, one favoring this policy, another that. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>While deliberation is naturally a vexatious and difficult task, you, Athenians,
                    have enhanced its difficulties; for all other people deliberate before the
                    event, but you after the event. And the result is that, as long as I can
                    remember, the man who attacks any mistakes you have made gains your applause as
                    an able speaker, but meanwhile the events and the real object of your
                    deliberation wholly escape you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>Nevertheless, although this is so, I have come forward in the belief and
                    confidence that, if you will consent to still the noise of faction and listen
                    with the attention that befits men who are debating the most important interests
                    of the state, I shall be able to offer you advice which will ameliorate our
                    present condition and redeem our past losses </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>While I am well aware, Athenians, that to talk in this assembly about oneself and
                    one's own speeches is a very profitable practice, if one has the necessary
                    effrontery, I feel that it is so vulgar and so offensive that, though I see the
                    necessity, I shrink from it. I believe, however, that you will form a better
                    judgement of what I am going to propose, if I remind you of a few things that I
                    have said on former occasions. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>For in the first place, Athenians, when it was proposed to take advantage of the
                    unrest in <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName><note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Through Philip's intrigues a Macedonian party had been
                        formed in the cities of <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>.
                        Plutarchus, the ruler of <placeName key="perseus,Eretria"
                            >Eretria</placeName>, applied to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> for help against a rising. The request was supported
                        by Eubulus and Midias, but opposed by Demosthenes. A force was sent under
                        the command of Phocion and won a battle, but Plutarchus proved himself a
                        traitor and was expelled from <placeName key="perseus,Eretria"
                            >Eretria</placeName>.</note> and side with Plutarchus in a war that
                    would bring us more expense than glory, I was the first and indeed the only
                    speaker to oppose it, and I narrowly escaped being torn to pieces by those who
                    induced you for trifling gains to commit many serious errors. It was not long
                    before you incurred disgrace and suffered indignities<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">According to the Scholiast, Plutarchus seized some of the
                        Athenian troops and compelled <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> to ransom them for 50 talents.</note> such as no men
                    have ever received from those whom they have helped, and so you realized the
                    baseness of those to whom you then gave ear and the wisdom of the advice you
                    received from me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>Again, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, when I saw that
                    Neoptolemus, the actor, enjoying safe conduct under cover of his profession, was
                    doing his best to injure our city and was Philip's agent and representative at
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, I once more came forward
                    and addressed you, not out of private animosity or love of informing, as indeed
                    my subsequent conduct has proved.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>And I shall not in this case, as in the former one, find fault with those who
                    spoke in defence of Neoptolemus, for not a man defended him, but with
                    yourselves. For if it had been a tragedy in the theater of Dionysus that you
                    were watching and not a debate on the very existence of your state, you could
                    not have shown more partiality to him and more ill-will against me.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>Yet I suppose that by this time you have all observed that after visiting the
                    enemy, in order, as he alleged, to collect sums owing to him there which he
                    might spend on public services here, and after making copious use of the
                    argument that it was too bad to arraign men who were transferring wealth from
                        <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, he secured a safe conduct owing to
                    the peace, converted into cash all the real property that he held here, and has
                    absconded to Philip.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>There, then, you have two of my warnings, bearing testimony to the value of my
                    earlier speeches, and uttered by me honestly and in strict conformity with the
                    facts. Thirdly, men of Athens—and when I have given just this one further
                    instance, I will at once pass on to some topics that I have omitted—when we
                    ambassadors returned from administering the oaths for the peace,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>at that time there were some who assured us that <placeName key="tgn,5004258"
                        >Thespiae</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Plataea"
                        >Plataea</placeName> would be rebuilt, that Philip, if he gained the
                    mastery, would protect the Phocians and break up <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                        >Thebes</placeName> into villages, and that you would retain Oropus and
                    receive <placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName> in exchange for
                        <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>. Led on by these
                    false hopes and cajoleries, you abandoned the Phocians against your own
                    interests and against justice and honor. But you will find that I neither took
                    part in this deception, nor passed it over in silence, but spoke out boldly, as
                    I am sure you remember, saying that I had neither knowledge nor expectation of
                    such results and that all such talk was nonsense.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>Now all these instances, where I appear to have had a clearer foresight than the
                    rest, I shall not refer to a single cause, men of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>—my real or pretended cleverness<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Greek here is difficult. Most edd. awkwardly
                        render <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)lazonei/a</foreign>“[;cause for];
                        boasting”: it is rather political quackery passing muster for real
                        statesmanship.</note>; nor will I claim that my knowledge and discernment
                    were due to anything else than two things, which I will mention. One, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, was good luck, which my
                    experience tells me is worth all the cleverness and wisdom in the world.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>The second is this: on public questions my estimates and decisions are
                    disinterested, and no one can show that my policy and my speeches have been in
                    any way bound up with my private gain. Hence I always see accurately the
                    advantageous course as suggested by actual circumstances. But the instant you
                    throw money into one scale, its weight bears down the judgement with it; and for
                    him that has once done this, accurate and sound calculation becomes utterly
                    impossible.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>Now there is one precaution which I think essential. If anyone proposes to
                    negotiate for our city an alliance or a joint contribution<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">A euphemism under the second Athenian confederacy for the
                        tribute (<foreign xml:lang="grc">fo/ros</foreign>) of the first.</note> or
                    anything of the sort, it must be done without detriment to the existing peace. I
                    do not mean that the peace is a glorious one or even creditable to you, but,
                    whatever we may think of it, it would better suit our purpose never to have made
                    it than to violate it when made, because we have now sacrificed many advantages
                    which would have made war safer and easier for us then than now.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>The second precaution, men of Athens, is to avoid giving the self-styled
                    Amphictyons now assembled any call or excuse for a crusade against us. For if we
                    should hereafter come to blows with Philip, about <placeName
                        key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName> or in any private quarrel
                    not shared by the Thessalians or the Argives or the Thebans, I do not believe
                    for a moment that any of the latter would be dragged into the war, least of
                    all—</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>hear me before you shout me down—least of all the Thebans. I do not mean that
                    they regard us with favor or that they would not readily oblige Philip, but they
                    do realize quite clearly, for all the stolidity that people attribute to them,
                    that if they ever fight you, they will have to take all the hard knocks
                    themselves, and someone else will sit quietly by, waiting for the spoils.
                    Therefore they would never make such a sacrifice unless the war had a common
                    cause and origin.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>If we went to war again with the Thebans about Oropus<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Oropus was in <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
                            >Attica</placeName>, close to the Boeotian frontier. A war for its
                        possession would therefore be confined to the Thebans and the Athenians, and
                        Demosthenes has no fear of the result.</note> or for some other private
                    reason, I do not think we should suffer, for both their allies and ours would,
                    of course, offer support, if their own territory were invaded, but would not
                    join either side in aggression. That is the way with every alliance worth
                    considering, and such is the natural result.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>No individual ally is so fond either of us or of the Thebans as to regard our
                    security and our supremacy in the same light. Secure they would all have us, for
                    their own sakes; that either nation should gain supremacy and be their master
                    would suit none of them. What, then, is the danger that I think we must guard
                    against? Lest the inevitable war should afford all states a common pretext and a
                    common ground of complaint.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>For if the Argives and Messenians and Megalopolitans, and other Peloponnesians
                    who side with them, quarrel with us because of our embassy to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and because they think that we have
                    some interest in Lacedaemonian policy; and if the Thebans are, as people admit,
                    hostile and likely to be even more so, because we offer an asylum to their
                    exiles and make no disguise of our hostility to them in every way; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>and if the Thessalians dislike us because we protect the Phocian fugitives, and
                    Philip because we are trying to exclude him from the Amphictyonic Council; then
                    I am afraid that these separate powers, having each a private grudge, may make
                    common cause against us on the strength of the Amphictyonic decrees, and may
                    then be tempted to go beyond what their several interests require, as they were
                    in the case of the Phocians.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>For of course you realize that in the present case the Thebans and Philip and the
                    Thessalians have acted in complete unison, though with widely different aims.
                    The Thebans, for instance, were powerless to prevent Philip from pressing on and
                    seizing the passes, or from coming in at the finish and usurping the credit of
                    their previous exertions.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>Hence today the Thebans have been partially successful in recovering territory,
                    but have failed lamentably to win honor and glory; for they would presumably
                    have gained nothing if Philip had not passed <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName>. That was not what they
                    wanted, but they put up with it all because they had the will, though not the
                    power, to grasp <placeName key="tgn,7011034">Orchomenus</placeName> and
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011235">Coronea</placeName>.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>Now some people actually go so far as to say that Philip was compelled, against
                    his real wishes, to hand over <placeName key="tgn,7011034"
                        >Orchomenus</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7011235">Coronea</placeName>
                    to the Thebans. For my part I wish them joy of their opinion. I only know this,
                    that Philip was less interested in those towns than desirous to secure the pass,
                    to win for himself the credit of finishing off the Sacred War, and to preside at
                    the Pythian games. That was the summit of his ambition.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>But the Thessalians aimed at the aggrandizement neither of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> nor of Philip, because they felt
                    that all that would tell against them; but they were anxious to control the
                    council at <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName> and the
                    Delphian temple<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Amphictyonic Council met in
                        autumn at the temple of Demeter near <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae"
                            >Thermopylae</placeName>, and at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi"
                            >Delphi</placeName> in spring.</note>—two clear gains for them; and it
                    was this ambition that led them to join in the war. So you will find that each
                    of these powers was induced for private reasons to do much that it did not wish.
                    That, however, is emphatically what we must avoid.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>“Must we then,” you ask, “do as we are told for fear of the consequences? Do you
                    of all men advise that?” Far from it. No, I think we ought so to act as to do
                    nothing unworthy of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and yet
                    avoid war; we ought to show to all men our good sense and the justice of our
                    claims. To those who think we ought boldly to risk everything, and who do not
                    foresee the inevitable hostilities, I suggest the following consideration. We
                    are allowing the Thebans to keep Oropus; and if anyone should ask us to tell him
                    candidly why we do so, we should have to answer, “In order to avoid war.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>In the same way by agreement with Philip we have waived our claim to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, and we are permitting
                        Cardia<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cardia, largely inhabited by
                        Athenian colonists, was included in the peace of 346 as an ally of
                        Philip.</note> to be excepted from the rest of the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017285">Chersonese</placeName>, the Carian<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Idrieus, satrap of <placeName key="tgn,7002358"
                            >Caria</placeName>, brother and successor of the famous Mausolus, who
                        had helped the islands in their revolt from <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                            >Athens</placeName> in the Social War of 357—355.</note> to occupy the
                    islands of <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>, Cos, and <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, and the Byzantines to detain our
                        ships<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Corn—ships from the Euxine forced to
                        pay toll at <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>.</note>
                    in harbor, obviously because we think that the respite which the peace affords
                    is more productive of advantages than wrangling and coming to blows over these
                    points. Therefore it is sheer folly and perversity, after dealing with the
                    powers one by one on matters of vital concern to ourselves, to challenge them
                    all together to fight about this phantom at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi"
                        >Delphi</placeName>.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
