<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Helen from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> There are some who are much pleased with themselves if, after setting up an absurd and
          self-contradictory subject, they succeed in discussing it in tolerable fashion; and men
          have grown old, some asserting that it is impossible to say, or to gainsay, what is
            false<note anchored="true" resp="ed">So Antisthenes and the Cynics; cf. <bibl
              n="Plat. Soph. 240c">Plat. Soph. 240c</bibl>.</note>, or to speak on both sides of the
          same questions, others maintaining that courage and wisdom and justice are identical<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">A reference to the views of Plato and the Academy.</note>, and
          that we possess none of these as natural qualities, but that there is one sort of
          knowledge concerned with them all.; and still others waste their time in captious
          disputations that are not only entirely useless, but are sure to make trouble for their
          disciples. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For my part, if I observed that this futile affectation had arisen only recently in
          rhetoric and that these men were priding themselves upon the novelty of their inventions,
          I should not be surprised at them to such degree; but as it is, who is so backward in
          learning as not to know that Protagoras and the sophists of his time have left to us
          compositions of similar character and even far more overwrought than these? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For how could one surpass Gorgias<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.268">Isoc. 15.268</bibl>. Gorgias of Leontini in <placeName
              key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, pupil of Teisias, came to Athens on an embassy
            in <date when="-0427">427 B.C.</date></note>, who dared to assert that nothing exists of
          the things that are, or Zeno<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This is Zeno of <placeName
              key="perseus,Elea">Elea</placeName>, in <placeName key="tgn,1000080"
            >Italy</placeName>, and not the founder of the Stoic School of philosophy. Zeno and
            Melissus were disciples of Parmenides.</note>, who ventured to prove the same things as
          possible and again as impossible, or Melissus who, although things in nature are infinite
          in number, made it his task to find proofs that the whole is one! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, although these men so clearly have shown that it is easy to contrive false
          statements on any subject that may be proposed, they still waste time on this commonplace.
          They ought to give up the use of this claptrap, which pretends to prove things by verbal
          quibbles, which in fact have long since been refuted, and to pursue the truth, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>to instruct their pupils in the practical affairs of our government and train to
          expertness therein, bearing in mind that likely conjecture about useful things is far
          preferable to exact knowledge of the useless, and that to be a little superior in
          important things is of greater worth than to be pre-eminent in petty things that are
          without value for living. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But the truth is that these men care for naught save enriching themselves at the expense
          of the youth. It is their “philosophy” applied to eristic disputations<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">eristics, “wordy wrangling” “mere disputation for its own
            sake”; cf. General Introd., Vol. I, p. xxi and <bibl n="Isoc. 13.1">Isoc.
            13.1</bibl>.</note> that effectively produces this result; for these rhetoricians, who
          care nothing at all for either private or public affairs, take most pleasure in those
          discourses which are of no practical service in any particular. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>These young men, to be sure, may well be pardoned for holding such views; for in all
          matters they are and always have been inclined toward what is extraordinary and
          astounding. But those who profess to give them training are deserving of censure because,
          while they condemn those who deceive in cases involving private contracts in business and
          those who are dishonest in what they say, yet they themselves are guilty of more
          reprehensible conduct; for the former wrong sundry other persons, but the latter inflict
          most injury upon their own pupils. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And they have caused mendacity to increase to such a degree that now certain men, seeing
          these persons prospering from such practices, have the effrontery to write that the life
          of beggars and exiles is more enviable than that of the rest of mankind, and they use this
          as a proof that, if they can speak ably on ignoble subjects, it follows that in dealing
          with subjects of real worth they would easily find abundance of arguments. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The most ridiculous thing of all, in my opinion, is this, that by these arguments they
          seek to convince us that they possess knowledge of the science of government, when they
          might be demonstrating it by actual work in their professed subject; for it is fitting
          that those who lay claim to learning and profess to be wise men should excel laymen and be
          better than they, not in fields neglected by everybody else, but where all are rivals.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But as it is, their conduct resembles that of an athlete who, although pretending to be
          the best of all athletes, enters a contest in which no one would condescend to meet him.
          For what sensible man would undertake to praise misfortunes? No, it is obvious that they
          take refuge in such topics because of weakness. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Such compositions follow one set road and this road is neither difficult to find, nor to
          learn, nor to imitate. On the other hand, discourses that are of general import, those
          that are trustworthy, and all of similar nature, are devised and expressed through the
          medium of a variety of forms and occasions of discourse whose opportune use is hard to
          learn, and their composition is more difficult as it is more arduous to practise dignity
          than buffoonery and seriousness than levity. The strongest proof is this: </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>no one who has chosen to praise bumble-bees and salt<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Plat. Sym. 177b">Plat. Sym. 177b</bibl>, where there is reference to an
              <title>Encomium of Salt</title> by an unknown writer. See <bibl n="Isoc. 12.135">Isoc.
              12.135</bibl>. Cf. Lucian's comic encomium, <title>Praise of the Fly</title>(see
            L.C.L. Lucian, Vol. I, pp. 81 ff.).</note> and kindred topics has never been at a loss
          for words, yet those who have essayed to speak on subjects recognized as good or noble, or
          of superior moral worth have all fallen far short of the possibilities which these
          subjects offer. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it does not belong to the same mentality to do justice to both kinds of subjects; on
          the contrary, while it is easy by eloquence to overdo the trivial themes, it is difficult
          to reach the heights of greatness of the others<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.36">Isoc. 12.36</bibl>.</note>; and while on famous subjects one rarely
          finds thoughts which no one has previously uttered, yet on trifling and insignificant
          topics whatever the speaker may chance to say is entirely original. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> This is the reason why, of those who have wished to discuss a subject with eloquence, I
          praise especially him who chose to write of Helen<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This
            statement certainly seems to refer to Gorgias, <bibl n="Isoc. 10.">Isoc. 10.</bibl>(see
            particularly the end of that composition which is translated by Van Hook, <title>Greek
              Life and Thought</title>, pp. 162 ff. See also the Introduction to this
            discourse).</note>, because he has recalled to memory so remarkable a woman, one who in
          birth, and in beauty, and in renown far surpassed all others. Nevertheless, even he
          committed a slight inadvertence—for although he asserts that he has written an encomium of
          Helen, it turns out that he has actually spoken a defense of her conduct! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the composition in defense does not draw upon the same topics as the encomium, nor
          indeed does it deal with actions of the same kind, but quite the contrary; for a plea in
          defense is appropriate only when the defendant is charged with a crime, whereas we praise
          those who excel in some good quality. But that I may not seem to be taking the easiest
          course, criticizing others without exhibiting any specimen of my own<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The same sentiment if found in <bibl n="Isoc. 11.9">Isoc. 11.9</bibl>.</note>,
          I will try to speak of this same woman, disregarding all that any others have said about
          her. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I will take as the beginning of my discourse the beginning of her family. For although
          Zeus begat very many of the demigods, of this woman alone he condescended to be called
          father. While he was devoted most of all to the son of Alcmena<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Heracles.</note> and to the sons of Leda<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Castor
            and Pollux.</note>, yet his preference for Helen, as compared with Heracles, was so
          great that, although he conferred upon his son strength of body, which is able to
          overpower all others by force, yet to her he gave the gift of beauty, which by its nature
          brings even strength itself into subjection to it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And knowing that all distinction and renown accrue, not from a life of ease, but from
          wars and perilous combats, and since he wished, not only to exalt their persons to the
          gods, but also to bequeath to them glory that would be immortal, he gave his son a life of
          labors and love of perils, and to Helen he granted the gift of nature which drew the
          admiration of all beholders and which in all men inspired contention<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Quoted and discussed by Demetrius, <title>On Style</title> 23.</note>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In the first place Theseus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For Isocrates' view of Theseus
            see <bibl n="Isoc. 12.126">Isoc. 12.126 ff.</bibl>, with his references to this
            discussion of the hero. For Theseus see <bibl n="Eur. Hipp. 887">Eur. Hipp. 887
              ff.</bibl> and <bibl n="Plut. Thes. 1">Plut. Thes.</bibl> Theseus, reputed son of
            Aegeus and of Aethra, daughter of Pittheus, king of <placeName key="tgn,5004287"
              >Troezen</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002739">Argolis</placeName>, was honored
            as the founder of the political institutions of Athens. Cf. p. 79 and note.</note>,
          reputedly the son of Aegeus, but in reality the progeny of Poseidon, seeing Helen not as
          yet in the full bloom of her beauty, but already surpassing other maidens, was so
          captivated by her loveliness that he, accustomed as he was to subdue others, and although
          the possessor of a fatherland most great and a kingdom most secure, thought life was not
          worth living amid the blessings he already had unless he could enjoy intimacy with her.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And when he was unable to obtain her from her guardians—for they were awaiting her
          maturity and the fulfilment of the oracle which the Pythian priestess had given—scorning
          the royal power of Tyndareus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Father of Helen.</note>,
          disdaining the might of Castor and Pollux<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Brothers of
            Helen.</note>, and belittling all the hazards in <placeName key="tgn,7011065"
            >Lacedaemon</placeName>, he seized her by force and established her at <placeName
            key="perseus,Aphidna">Aphidna</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
            >Attica</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So grateful was Theseus to Peirithos, his partner in the abduction, that when Peirithos
          wished to woo Persephon, the daughter of Zeus and Demeter, and summoned him to the descent
          into Hades to obtain her, when Theseus found that he could not by his warnings dissuade
          his friend, although the danger was manifest he nevertheless accompanied him, for he was
          of opinion that he owed this debt<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the figure of speech
            in <foreign xml:lang="greek">E)/RANOS</foreign> see <bibl n="Isoc. 11.1">Isoc.
              11.1</bibl> and <bibl n="Plat. Sym. 177c">Plat. Sym. 177c</bibl>.</note> of
          gratitude—to decline no task enjoined by Peirithos in return for his help in his own
          perilous enterprise. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If the achiever of these exploits had been an ordinary person and not one of the very
          distinguished, it would not yet be clear whether this discourse is an encomium of Helen or
          an accusation of Theseus; but as it is, while in the case of other men who have won renown
          we shall find that one is deficient in courage, another in wisdom, and another in some
          kindred virtue, yet this hero alone was lacking in naught, but had attained consummate
          virtue. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And it seems to me appropriate to speak of Theseus at still greater length; for I think
          this will be the strongest assurance for those who wish to praise Helen, if we can show
          that those who loved and admired her were themselves more deserving of admiration than
          other men. For contemporary events we should with good reason judge in accordance with our
          own opinions, but concerning events in times so remote it is fitting that we show our
          opinion to be in accord with the opinion of those men of wisdom who were at that time
          living. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The fairest praise that I can award to Theseus is this—that he, a contemporary of
          Heracles,won a fame which rivalled his. For they not only equipped themselves with similar
          armor, but followed the same pursuits, performing deeds that were worthy of their common
          origin. For being in birth the sons of brothers, the one of Zeus, the other of Poseidon,
          they cherished also kindred ambitions; for they alone of all who have lived before our
          time made themselves champions of human life. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It came to pass that Heracles undertook perilous labors more celebrated and more severe,
          Theseus those more useful, and to the Greeks of more vital importance. For example,
          Heracles was ordered by Eurystheus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Eurystheus, king of
              <placeName key="perseus,Mycenae">Mycenae</placeName>, imposed the twelve labors upon
            Heracles; see <bibl n="Isoc. 4.56">Isoc. 4.56</bibl> and note.</note> to bring the
          cattle from Erytheia<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An island near the coast of <placeName
              key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>.</note> and to obtain the apples of the Hesperides
          and to fetch Cerberus up from Hades and to perform other labors of that kind, labors which
          would bring no benefit to mankind, but only danger to himself; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Theseus, however, being his own master, gave preference to those struggles which would
          make him a benefactor of either the Greeks at large or of his native land. Thus, the bull
          let loose by Poseidon which was ravaging the land of <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
            >Attica</placeName>, a beast which all men lacked the courage to confront, Theseus
          singlehanded subdued, and set free the inhabitants of the city from great fear and
          anxiety. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And after this, allying himself with the Lapiths, he took the field against the Centaurs,
          those creatures of double nature, endowed with surpassing swiftness, strength, and daring,
          who were sacking, or about to sack, or were threatening, one city after another. These he
          conquered in battle and straightway put an end to their insolence, and not long thereafter
          he caused their race to disappear from the sight of men. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>At about the same time appeared the monster<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Minotaur,
            “the bull of Minos,” to whom seven boys and seven girls were annually sent as tribute by
            the Athenians; cf. <bibl n="Plat. Phaedo 58a">Plat. Phaedo 58a</bibl>.</note> reared in
            <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, the offspring of Pasipha, daughter of
          Helius, to whom our city was sending, in accordance with an oracle's command, tribute of
          twice seven children. When Theseus saw these being led away, and the entire populace
          escorting them, to a death savage and foreseen, and being mourned as dead while yet
          living, he was so incensed that he thought it better to die than to live as ruler of a
          city that was compelled to pay to the enemy a tribute so lamentable. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Having embarked with them for <placeName key="tgn,7012056">Crete</placeName>, he subdued
          this monster, half-man and half-bull, which possessed strength commensurate with its
          composite origin, and having rescued the children, he restored them to their parents, and
          thus freed the city from an obligation so savage, so terrible, and so ineluctable. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I am at a loss how to deal with what remains to be said; for, now that I have taken
          up the deeds of Theseus and begun to speak of them, I hesitate to stop midway and leave
          unmentioned the lawlessness of Sciron<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A mythical robber who
            haunted the rocks between <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> and <placeName
              key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>.</note> and of Cercyon and of other robbers
          like them whom he fought and vanquished and thereby delivered the Greeks from many great
          calamities. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But, on the other hand, I perceive that I am being carried beyond the proper limits of my
          theme and I fear that some may think that I am more concerned with Theseus than with the
          subject which I originally chose<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See the Introduction to
            this discourse.</note>. In this dilemma I prefer to omit the greater part of what might
          be said, out of regard for impatient hearers, and to give as concise an account as I can
          of the rest, that I may gratify both them and myself and not make a complete surrender to
          those whose habit it is out of jealousy to find fault with everything that is said. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> His courage Theseus displayed in these perilous exploits which he hazarded alone; his
          knowledge of war in the battles he fought in company with the whole city; his piety toward
          the gods in connexion with the supplications of Adrastus and the children of Heracles
          when, by defeating the Peloponnesians in battle, he saved the lives of the children<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Eur. Heraclid.">Eur. Heraclid.</bibl> for the
            story and also Isocrates, <bibl n="Isoc. 4.56">Isoc. 4.56</bibl>.</note>, and to
          Adrastus he restored for burial, despite the Thebans, the bodies of those who had died
          beneath the walls of the Cadmea<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Eur. Supp."
              >Eur. Supp.</bibl> The story of Adrastus is told in detail in <bibl n="Isoc. 12.168"
              >Isoc. 12.168 ff.</bibl> Adrastus, king of <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
              >Argos</placeName>, led the expedition of the “Seven against <placeName
              key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>” (cf. <bibl n="Aesch. Seven 1">Aesch.
              Seven</bibl>), which met with defeat.</note>; and finally, he revealed his other
          virtues and his prudence, not only in the deeds already recited, but especially in the
          manner in which he governed our city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For he saw that those who seek to rule their fellow-citizens by force are themselves the
          slaves of others, and that those who keep the lives of their fellow-citizens in peril
          themselves live in extreme fear, and are forced to make war, on the one hand, with the
          help of citizens against invaders from abroad, and, on the other hand, with the help of
          auxiliaries against their fellow citizens; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>further, he saw them despoiling the temples of the gods, putting to death the best of
          their fellow-citizens, distrusting those nearest to them, living lives no more free from
          care than do men who in prison await their death; he saw that, although they are envied
          for their external blessings, yet in their own hearts they are more miserable than all
          other men— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for what, pray, is more grievous than to live in constant fear lest some bystander kill
          you, dreading no less your own guards than those who plot against you? Theseus, then,
          despising all these and considering such men to be not rulers, but pests, of their states,
          demonstrated that it is easy to exercise the supreme power and at the same time to enjoy
          as good relations as those who live as citizens on terms of perfect equality. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In the first place, the scattered settlements and villages of which the state was
          composed he united, and made Athens into a city-state<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A
            reference to the <foreign xml:lang="greek">sunoikismo/s</foreign> attributed to Theseus,
            i.e., the uniting of the scattered villages in <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
              >Attica</placeName> into a polis or city-state. Cf. <bibl n="Thuc. 2.15">Thuc.
              2.15</bibl>.</note> so great that from then even to the present day it is the greatest
          state of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>: and after this, when he had
          established a common fatherland and had set free the minds of his fellow-citizens, he
          instituted for them on equal terms that rivalry of theirs for distinction based on merit,
          confident that he would stand out as their superior in any case, whether they practised
          that privilege or neglected it, and he also knew that honors bestowed by high-minded men
          are sweeter than those that are awarded by slaves<note anchored="true" resp="ed">With this
            passage (<bibl n="Isoc. 10.34">Isoc. 10.34-35</bibl>) <bibl n="Isoc. 4.38">Isoc.
              4.38-89</bibl>, with note, should be compared.</note>. And he was so far from doing
          anything contrary to the will of the citizens </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>that he made the people masters of the government, and they on their part thought it best
          that he should rule alone, believing that his sole rule was more to be trusted and more
          equitable than their democracy. For he did not, as the other rulers did habitually, impose
          the labors upon the citizens and himself alone enjoy the pleasures; but the dangers he
          made his own, and the benefits he bestowed upon the people in common. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In consequence, Theseus passed his life beloved of his people and not the object of their
          plots, not preserving his sovereignty by means of alien military force, but protected, as
          by a bodyguard, by the goodwill of the citizens<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 2.21">Isoc. 2.21</bibl>.</note>, by virtue of his authority ruling as a king,
          but by his benefactions as a popular leader; for so equitably and so well did he
          administer the city that even to this day traces of his clemency may be seen remaining in
          our institutions. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> As for Helen, daughter of Zeus, who established her power over such excellence and
          sobriety, should she not be praised and honored, and regarded as far superior to all the
          women who have ever lived? For surely we shall never have a more trustworthy witness or
          more competent judge of Helen's good attributes than the opinion of Theseus. But lest I
          seem through poverty of ideas to be dwelling unduly upon the same theme and by misusing
          the glory of one man to be praising Helen, I wish now to review the subsequent events
          also. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> After the descent of Theseus to Hades, when Helen returned to <placeName
            key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>, and was now of marriageable age, all the kings
          and potentates of that time formed of her the same opinion; for although it was possible
          for them in their own cities to wed women of the first rank, they disdained wedlock at
          home and went to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> to woo Helen. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And before it had yet been decided who was to be her husband and all her suitors still
          had an equal chance, it was so evident to all that Helen would be the object of armed
          contention that they met together and exchanged solemn pledges of assistance if anyone
          should attempt to take her away from him who had been adjudged worthy of winning her; for
          each thought he was providing this alliance for himself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In this their private hope all, it is true, save one man, were disappointed, yet in the
          general opinion which all had formed concerning her no one was mistaken. For not much
          later when strife arose among the goddesses for the prize of beauty, and Alexander<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e., <placeName key="tgn,7008038">Paris</placeName>.</note>,
          son of Priam, was appointed judge and when Hera offered him sovereignty over all Asia,
          Athena victory in war, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and Aphrodite Helen as his wife, finding himself unable to make a distinction regarding
          the charms of their persons, but overwhelmed by the sight of the goddesses, Alexander,
          compelled to make a choice of their proffered gifts, chose living with Helen before all
          else. In so doing he did not look to its pleasures—although even this is thought by the
          wise to be preferable to many things, but nevertheless it was not this he strove for— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but because he was eager to become a son of Zeus by marriage, considering this a much
          greater and more glorious honor than sovereignty over Asia, and thinking that while great
          dominions and sovereignties fall at times even to quite ordinary men, no man would ever in
          all time to come be considered worthy of such a woman; and furthermore, that he could
          leave no more glorious heritage to his children than by seeing to it that they should be
          descendants of Zeus, not only on their father's side, but also on their mother's. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For he knew that while other blessings bestowed by Fortune soon change hands, nobility of
          birth abides forever with the same possessors; therefore he foresaw that this choice would
          be to the advantage of all his race, whereas the other gifts would be enjoyed for the
          duration of his own life only. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> No sensible person surely could find fault with this reasoning, but some, who have not
          taken into consideration the antecedent events but look at the sequel alone, have before
          now reviled Alexander; but the folly of these accusers is easily discerned by all from the
          calumnies they have uttered. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Are they not in a ridiculous state of mind if they think their own judgement is more
          competent than that which the gods chose as best<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e.,
            Alexander's.</note>? For surely they did not select any ordinary arbiter to decide a
          dispute about an issue that had got them into so fierce a quarrel, but obviously they were
          as anxious to select the most competent judge as they were concerned about the matter
          itself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>There is need, moreover, to consider his real worth and to judge him, not by the
          resentment of those who were defeated for the prize, but by the reasons which caused the
          goddesses unanimously to choose his judgement. For nothing prevents even innocent persons
          from being ill-treated by the stronger, but only a mortal man of greatly superior
          intelligence could have received such honor as to become a judge of immortals. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I am astonished that anyone should think that Alexander was ill-advised in choosing to
          live with Helen, for whom many demigods were willing to die. Would he not have been a fool
          if, knowing that the deities themselves were contending for the prize of beauty, he had
          himself scorned beauty, and had failed to regard as the greatest of gifts that for the
          possession of which he saw even those goddesses most earnestly striving? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> What man would have rejected marriage with Helen, at whose abduction the Greeks were as
          incensed as if all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> had been laid waste,
          while the barbarians were as filled with pride as if they had conquered us all? It is
          clear how each party felt about the matter; for although there had been many causes of
          contention between them before, none of these disturbed their peace, whereas for her they
          waged so great a war, not only the greatest of all wars in the violence of its passions,
          but also in the duration of the struggle and in the extent of the preparations the
          greatest of all time. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And although the Trojans might have rid themselves of the misfortunes which encompassed
          them by surrendering Helen, and the Greeks might have lived in peace for all time by being
          indifferent to her fate, neither so wished; on the contrary, the Trojans allowed their
          cities to be laid waste and their land to be ravaged, so as to avoid yielding Helen to the
          Greeks, and the Greeks chose rather, remaining in a foreign land to grow old there and
          never to see their own again, than, leaving her behind, to return to their fatherland.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And they were not acting in this way as eager champions of Alexander or of Menelaus; nay,
          the Trojans were upholding the cause of Asia, the Greeks of <placeName key="tgn,1000003"
            >Europe</placeName>, in the belief that the land in which Helen in person resided would
          be the more favored of Fortune. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> So great a passion for the hardships of that expedition and for participation in it took
          possession not only of the Greeks and the barbarians, but also of the gods, that they did
          not dissuade even their own children from joining in the struggles around <placeName
            key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.81">Isoc. 12.81</bibl>.</note>; Zeus, though foreseeing the fate of
            Sarpedon<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Sarpedon, son of Zeus and Laodameia, prominent
            in the <title>Iliad</title>, was killed by Patroclus; Memnon and Cycnus were slain by
            Achilles.</note>,and Eos that of Memnon, and Poseidon that of Cycnus, and Thetis that of
          Achilles, nevertheless they all urged them on and sent them forth, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>thinking it more honorable for them to die fighting for the daughter of Zeus than to live
          without having taken part in the perils undergone on her account. And why should we be
          astonished that the gods felt thus concerning their children? For they themselves engaged
          in a far greater and more terrible struggle than when they fought the Giants; for against
          those enemies they had fought a battle in concert, but for Helen they fought a war against
          one another. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> With good reason in truth they came to this decision, and I, for my part, am justified
          in employing extravagant language in speaking of Helen; for beauty she possessed in the
          highest degree, and beauty is of all things the most venerated, the most precious, and the
          most divine. And it is easy to determine its power; for while many things which do not
          have any attributes of courage, wisdom, or justice will be seen to be more highly valued
          than any one of these attributes, yet of those things which lack beauty we shall find not
          one that is beloved; on the contrary, all are despised, except in so far as they possess
          in some degree this outward form, beauty, and it is for this reason that virtue is most
          highly esteemed, because it is the most beautiful of ways of living. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And we may learn how superior beauty is to all other things by observing how we ourselves
          are affected by each of them severally. For in regard to the other things which we need,
          we only wish to possess them and our heart's desire is set on nothing further than this;
          for beautiful things, however, we have an inborn passion whose strength of desire
          corresponds to the superiority of the thing sought. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And while we are jealous of those who excel us in intelligence or in anything else,
          unless they win us over by daily benefactions and compel us to be fond of them, yet at
          first sight we become well-disposed toward those who possess beauty, and to these alone as
          to the gods we do not fail in our homage; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>on the contrary, we submit more willingly to be the slaves of such than to rule all
          others, and we are more grateful to them when they impose many tasks upon us than to those
          who demand nothing at all. We revile those who fall under the power of anything other than
          beauty and call them flatterers, but those who are subservient to beauty we regard as
          lovers of beauty and lovers of service. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So strong are our feelings of reverence and solicitude for such a quality, that we hold
          in greater dishonour those of its possessors who have trafficked in it and ill-used their
          own youth than those who do violence to the persons of others; whereas those who guard
          their youthful beauty as a holy shrine, inaccessible to the base, are honored by us for
          all time equally with those who have benefited the city as a whole. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But why need I waste time in citing the opinions of men? Nay, Zeus, lord of all, reveals
          his power in all else, but deigns to approach beauty in humble guise. For in the likeness
          of Amphitryon he came to Alcmena, and as a shower of gold he united with Danae, and in the
          guise of a swan he took refuge in the bosom of Nemesis, and again in this form he espoused
          Leda; ever with artifice manifestly, and not with violence, does he pursue beauty in
          women. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And so much greater honor is paid to beauty among the gods than among us that they pardon
          their own wives when they are vanquished by it; and one could cite many instances of
          goddesses who succumbed to mortal beauty, and no one of these sought to keep the fact
          concealed as if it involved disgrace; on the contrary, they desired their adventures to be
          celebrated in song as glorious deeds rather than to be hushed in silence. The greatest
          proof of my statements is this: we shall find that more mortals have been made immortal
          because of their beauty than for all other excellences. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> All these personages Helen surpassed in proportion as she excelled them in the beauty of
          her person. For not only did she attain immortality but, having won power equalling that
          of a god, she first raised to divine station her brothers<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Castor and Pollux; cf. § 19.</note>, who were already in the grip of Fate, and wishing
          to make their transformation believed by men, she gave to them honors<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">A reference to “St. Elmo's fire”; cf. Pliny ii. 37.</note> so manifest that
          they have power to save when they are seen by sailors in peril on the sea, if they but
          piously invoke them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>After this she so amply recompensed Menelaus for the toils and perils which he had
          undergone because of her, that when all the race of the Pelopidae had perished and were
          the victims of irremediable disasters, not only did she free him from these misfortunes
          but, having made him god instead of mortal, she established him as partner of her house
          and sharer of her throne forever. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And I can produce the city of the Spartans, which preserves with especial care its
          ancient traditions, as witness for the fact; for even to the present day at Therapne<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Just outside <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName> were the tombs of Menelaus and Helen (see Pausanias iii. 19.9) and
            their sanctuary (Herodotus vi. 61).</note> in <placeName key="tgn,7002745"
            >Laconia</placeName> the people offer holy and traditional sacrifices to them both, not
          as to heroes, but as to gods. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And she displayed her own power to the poet Stesichorus<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The famous lyric poet of Himera, in <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
            >Sicily</placeName>.</note> also; for when, at the beginning of his ode, he spoke in
          disparagement of her, he arose deprived of his sight; but when he recognized the cause of
          his misfortune and composed the <title>Recantation</title>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The well-known <title>Palinode</title>; for this legend and the fragment of the poem
            see <bibl n="Plat. Phaedrus 242a">Plat. Phaedrus 242a</bibl>.</note> as it is called,
          she restored to him his normal sight. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And some of the Homeridae also relate that Helen appeared to Homer by night and commanded
          him to compose a poem on those who went on the expedition to <placeName key="perseus,Troy"
            >Troy</placeName>, since she wished to make their death more to be envied than the life
          of the rest of mankind; and they say that while it is partly because of Homer's art, yet
          it is chiefly through her that this poem has such charm and has become so famous among all
          men. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Since, then, Helen has power to punish as well as to reward, it is the duty of those who
          have great wealth to propitiate and to honor her with thank-offerings, sacrifices, and
          processions, and philosophers should endeavour to speak of her in a manner worthy of her
          merits; for such are the first-fruits it is fitting that men of cultivation should offer.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Far more has been passed over than has been said. Apart from the arts and philosophic
          studies and all the other benefits which one might attribute to her and to the Trojan War,
          we should be justified in considering that it is owing to Helen that we are not the slaves
          of the barbarians. For we shall find that it was because of her that the Greeks became
          united in harmonious accord and organized a common expedition against the barbarians, and
          that it was then for the first time that <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName>
          set up a trophy of victory over Asia; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and in consequence, we experienced a change so great that, although in former times any
          barbarians who were in misfortune presumed to be rulers over the Greek cities (for
          example, Danaus, an exile from <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, occupied
            <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, Cadmus of <placeName key="tgn,7002861"
            >Sidon</placeName> became king of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>,
          the Carians colonized the islands<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Thuc. 1.4"
              >Thuc. 1.4</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 12.43">Isoc. 12.43</bibl>.</note>, and Pelops,
          son of Tantalus, became master of all the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnese</placeName>), yet after that war our race expanded so greatly that it took
          from the barbarians great cities and much territory. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="69" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If, therefore, any orators wish to dilate upon these matters and dwell upon them, they
          will not be at a loss for material apart from what I have said, wherewith to praise Helen;
          on the contrary, they will discover many new arguments that relate to her.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
