<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Slander: on not Being Quick to Put Faith in it</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
    <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
    <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
</monogr>
  <series>Loeb Classical Library</series>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianha01luciuoft/page/360/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.b000604153?urlappend=%3Bseq=372">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.1.p.361"/>
<head>Slander: on not Being Quick to Put Faith in it<note xml:lang="eng">This essay is rhetoric pure and simple, and was probably
written early in Lucian’s career. It is famous because it
contains a vivid description of a picture by Apelles, which
was again translated into paint by Botticelli in “La
Calunnia.”</note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>


It is really a terrible thing, is ignorance, a cause
of many woes to humanity; for it envelops things
in a fog, so to speak, and obscures the truth and
overshadows each man’s life. Truly, we all resemble
people lost in the dark—nay, we are even like blind
men. Now we stumble inexcusably, now we lift our
feet when there is no need of it; and we do not see
what is near and right before us, but fear what is far
away and extremely remote as if it blocked our path.
In short, in everything we do we are always making
plenty of missteps. For this redson the writers of
tragedy have found in this universal truth many and
many a motive for their dramas—take for example,
the house of Labdacus,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">King of Thebes, father of Laius.</note> the house of Pelops and their
like. Indeed, most of the troubles that.are put on
the stage are supplied to the poets, you will find, by
ignorance, as though it were a sort of tragic divinity.
What I have in mind more than anything else is
slanderous lying about acquaintances and friends,
through which families have been rooted out, cities
have utterly perished, fathers have been driven mad



<pb n="v.1.p.363"/>

against their children, brothers against own brothers,
children against their parents and lovers against
those they love. Many a friendship, too, has. been
parted and many an oath broken through belief in
slander.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

In order, then, that we may as far as
possible avoid being involved in it, I wish to show in
words, as if in a painting, what sort of thing slander
is, how it begins and what it does.</p>

<p>I should say, however, that Apelles of Ephesus
long ago preempted this subject for a picture ; and
with good reason, for he himself had been slandered
to Ptolemy on the ground that he had taken part
with Theodotas in the conspiracy in Tyre, although
Apelles had never set eyes on Tyre and did not
know who Theodotas was, beyond having heard that
he was one of Ptolemy’s governors, in charge of affairs
in Phoenicia.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The story is apocryphal, as Apelles must have been in
his grave nearly a hundred years when Theodotus (not
Theodotas) betrayed Ptolemy Philopator (219 3.c.).</note>
Nevertheless, one of his rivals named
Antiphilus, through envy of his favour at court
and professional jealousy, maligned him by telling
Ptolemy that he had taken part in the whole enterprise, and that someone had seen him dining with
Theodotas in Phoenicia and whispering into his ear
all through the meal; and in the end he declared
that the revolt of Tyre and the capture of Pelusium
had taken place on the advice of Apelles.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>

Ptolemy, who in general was not particularly sound
of judgment, but had been brought up in the midst
of courtly flattery, was so inflamed and upset by this



<pb n="v.1.p.365"/>

surprising charge that he did not take into account
any of the probabilities, not considering either that
the accuser was a rival or that a painter was too
insignificant a person for so great a piece of treason—
a painter, too, who had been well treated by him
and honoured above any of his fellow-craftsmen.
Indeed, he did not even enquire whether Apelles
had gone to Tyre at all. On the contrary, he at
once began to rave and filled the palace with noise,
shouting “The ingrate,” “The plotter,’ and “The
conspirator.”’ And if one of his fellow-prisoners,
who was indignant at the impudence of-Antiphilus
and felt sorry for poor Apelles, had not said that the
man had not taken any part whatever in the affair,
he would have had his head cut off, and so would
have shared the consequences of the troubles in Tyre
without being himself to blame for them in any way.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

Ptolemy is said to have been so ashamed of the
affair that he presented Apelles with a hundred
talents and gave him Antiphilus for his slave.
Apelles, for his part, mindful of the risk that he had
run, hit back at slander in a painting.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>

On the right
of it sits a man with very large ears, almost like
those of Midas, extending his hand to Slander while
she is still at some distance from him. Near him,
on one side, stand two women—Ignorance, I think,
and Suspicion. On the other side, Slander is coming
up, a woman beautiful beyond measure, but full of
passion and excitement, evincing as she does fury
and wrath by carrying in her left hand a blazing
torch and with the other dragging by the hair a
young man who stretches out his hands to heaven


<pb n="v.1.p.367"/>

and calls the gods to witness his innocence, She is ©
conducted by a pale ugly man who has a piercing
eye and looks as if he had wasted away in long illness; he may be supposed to be Envy. Besides,
there are two women in attendance on Slander,
egging her on, tiring her and tricking her out.
According to the interpretation of them given me
by the guide to the picture, one was Treachery and
the other Deceit. They were followed by a woman
dressed in deep mourning, with black clothes all in
tatters—Repentance, I think, her name was. At all
events, she was turning back with tears in her eyes
and casting a stealthy glance, full of shame, at
Truth, who was approaching.</p>
<p>That is the way in which Apelles represented in
the painting his own hairbreadth escape.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

Come,
suppose we too, if you like, following the lead of the
Ephesian artist, portray the characteristics of slander,
after first sketching it in outline: for in that way
our picture will perhaps come out more clearly.
Slander, then, is a clandestine accusation, made without the cognizance of the accused and _ sustained
by the uncontradicted assertion of one side. This is
the subject of my lecture, and since there are three
leading characters in slander as in comedy—the
slanderér, the slandered person, and the hearer of
the slander,—let us consider what is ukely to happen
in the case of each of them.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">This partition, derived from Herodotus (7, 10), is not at
all strictly followed by Lucian in developing his theme.</note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
In the first place, if you like, let us bring on the
star of the play, I mean the author of the slander.
That he is not a good man admits of no doubt, I am



<pb n="v.1.p.369"/>

sure, because no good man would make trouble for
his neighbour. On the contrary, it is characteristic
of good men to win renown and gain a reputation
for kind-heartedness by doing good to their friends,
not by accusing others wrongfully and getting them
hated.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>

Furthermore, that such a man is unjust, lawless,
impious and harmful to his associates is easy to see.
Who will not admit that fairness in everything and
unselfishness are due to justice, unfairness and:
selfishness to injustice? But when a man plies
slander in secret against people who are absent, is
he not selfish, inasmuch as he completely appropriates
his hearer by getting his ear first, stopping it up
and making it altogether impervious to the defence
because it has been previously filled with slander?
Such conduct is indeed the height of injustice, and
the best of the lawgivers, Solon and Draco, for
example, would say so, too; for they put the jurors
on oath to hear both sides alike and to divide
their goodwill equally between the litigants until
such time as the plea of the defendant, after
comparison with the other, shall disclose itself to be
better or worse. To pass judgment betore weighing
the defence against the complaint would, they
thought, be altogether impious and irreligious. In
truth, we may say that the very gods would be angry
if we should permit the plaintiff to say his say
unhampered, but should stop our ears to the defendant or silence him,<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The Greek is here corrupt. The translation merely
gives the probable sense of the passage.</note>

and then condemn him,



<pb n="v.1.p.371"/>

conquered by the'first plea. It may be said, then, that
slander does not accord with what is just and legal,
and what the jurors swear to do. But. if anybody
thinks that the lawgivers, who regommend that verdicts be so just and impartial, are not good authority,
I shall cite the best of poets in support of my contention. He makes a very admirable pronouncement
— indeed, lays down a law—on this point, saying :
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Though this verse was frequently quoted in antiquity,
its authorship was unknown even then, and it was variously,
attributed to Phocylides, Hesiod, and Pittheus. See Bergk,
Poet. Lyr. Graec. ii, p. 93.</note>

<quote>
<l>Nor give your verdict ere both sides you hear.</l></quote>

He knew, I suppose, like everyone else, that though
there are many unjust things in the world, nothing
worse or more unjust can be found than for men to
have been condemned untried and unheard. But
this is just what the slanderer tries his best to
accomplish, exposing the slandered person untried
to the anger of the hearer and precluding defence by
the secrecy of his accusation.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

Of course, all such men are also disingenuous and
cowardly ; they do nothing in the open, but shoot
from some hiding-place or, other, like soldiers in
ambush, so that it is impossible either to face them or
to fight them, but a man must let himself be slain in
helplessness and in ignorance of the character of the
war. And this is the surest proof that there is no
truth in the stories of slanderers; for if a man is
conscious that he is making a true charge, that man,
I take it, accuses the other in public, brings him to
book and pits himself against him in argument. No
soldier who can win in fair fight makes use of
ambushes and tricks against the enemy.



<pb n="v.1.p.373"/>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
For the most part, such men may be seen enjoying
high favour in the courts of kings and among the
friends of governors and princes, where envy is great,
suspicions are countless, and occasions for flattery and
slander are frequent. For where hope runs ever high,
there envy is more bitter, hate more dangerous, and
rivalry more cunning. All eye one another sharply
and keep watch like gladiators to detect some part
of the body exposed. Everyone, wishing to be first
himself, shoves or elbows his neighbour out of his
way and, if he can, slyly pulls down or trips up the
man ahead. In this way a good man is simply
upset and thrown at the start, and finally thrust off
the course in disgrace, while one who is better
versed in flattery and cleverer at such unfair
practices wins. In a word, it is “devil take the
hindmost !” ; for they quite confirm Homer’s saying:
<cit>
<quote>
<l>Impartial war adds slayer to the slain.</l></quote>
<bibl>Iliad 18, 309.</bibl></cit>

So, as their conflict is for no small stake, they think
out all sorts of ways to get at each other, of which
the quickest, though most perilous, road is slander,
which has a hopeful beginning in envy or hatred,
but leads to a sorry, tragic ending, beset with many
accidents.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
Yet this is not an insignificant or a simple thing,
as one might suppose; it requires much skill, no
little shrewdness, and some degree of close study.

<pb n="v.1.p.375"/>

For slander would not do so much harm if it were
not set afoot in a plausible way, and it would not
prevail over truth, that is stronger than all else, if it
did not assume a high degree of attractiveness and
plausibility and a thousand things beside to disarm
its hearers.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>


Generally speaking, slander is most often directed
against a man who is in favour and on this account is
viewed with envy by those he has put behind him.
They all direct their shafts at him, regarding him as
a hindrance and a stumbling-block, and each one
expects to be first himself when he has routed his
chief and ousted him from favour. Something of
the same sort happens in the athletic games, in footraces. A good runner fram the moment that the
barrier falls
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Races were started in antiquity by the dropping of a
rope or bar.</note>
thinks only of getting forward, sets
his mind on the finish and counts on his legs to
win for him; he therefore does not molest the man
next to him in any way or trouble himself at ail
about the contestants. But an inferior, unsportsmanlike competitor, abandoning all hope based on
his speed, resorts to crooked work, and the only
thing in the world he thinks of is cutting off the
runner by holding or tripping him, with the idea
that if he should fail in this he would never be able
to win. So it is with the friendships of the mighty.
The man in the lead is forthwith the object of plots,
and if caught off.his guard in the midst of his foes,
he is made away with, while-they are cherished and
are thought friendly because of the harm they
appeared to be doing to others.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>

As for the verisimilitude of their slander, calum-



<pb n="v.1.p.377"/>

niators are not careless in thinking out that point;
all their work centres on it, for they are afraid to
put in anything discordant or even irrelevant. For
example, they generally make their charges credible
by distorting the real attributes of the man they are
slandering. Thus they insinuate that a doctor is a
poisoner, that a rich man is a would-be monarch, or
that a courtier is a traitor.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>


Sometimes, however, the hearer himself suggests
the starting-point for slander, and the knaves attain
their end by adapting themselves to his disposition.
If they see that he is jealous, they say: “He signed
to your wife during dinner and gazed at her and
sighed, and Stratonice was not very displeased withhim.” In short, the charges they make to him are .
based on passion and illicit love. If he has a bent
for poetry and prides himself on it, they say : “No,
indeed! Philoxenus made fun of your verses, pulled
them to pieces and said that they wouldn’t scan and
were wretchedly composed.” Toa pious, godly man
the charge is made that his friend is godless and
impious, that he rejects God and denies Providence.
Thereupon the man, stung in the ear, so to speak,
by a gadfly, gets thoroughly angry, as is natural, and
turns his back on his friend without awaiting definite
proof.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>

In short, they think out and say the sort of
thing that they know to be best adapted to provoke
the hearer to anger, and as they know the place
where each can be wounded, they shoot their arrows
and throw their spears at it, so that their hearer,
thrown off his balance by sudden anger, will not
thereafter be free to get at the truth; indeed, however much a slandered man may want to defend
himself, he will not let him do so, because he is


<pb n="v.1.p.379"/>

prejudiced by the surprising nature of what he has’
heard, just as if that made it true.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>


A very effective form of slander is the one that is
based on opposition to the hearer’s tastes. For instance, in the court of the Ptolemy who was called
Dionysus<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Probably Ptolemy Auletes, father of Cleopatra, who
styled himself "the new Dionysus.”</note> there was once a man who accused Demetrius, the Platonic philosopher, of drinking nothing
but water and of being the only person who did not
wear women’s clothes during the feast of Dionysus.
If Demetrius, on being sent for early the next morning, had ‘not drunk wine in view of everybody and
had not put on a thin gown and played the cymbals
and danced, he would have been put to death for not
liking the king’ s mode of life, and being a critic and
an opponent of Ptolemy’s luxury.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>

In the court of Alexander it was once the greatest
of all slanderous charges to say that a man did not
worship Hephaestion or even make obeisance to him
—for after the death of Hephaestion, Alexander for
the love he bore him determined to add to his other
great feats that of appointing the dead man a god.
So the cities at once erected temples; plots of ground -
were consecrated ; altars, sacrifices and feasts were
established in honour of this new god, and everybody’s strongest oath was “By Hephaestion.” If
anyone smiled at what went on or failed to'seem
quite reverent, the penalty prescribed was death.
The flatterers, taking hold of this childish passion
of Alexander’s, at once began to feed it and fan it
into flame by telling about dreams of Hephaestion,
in that way ascribing to him visitations and cures
and accrediting him with prophecies; and at last



<pb n="v.1.p.381"/>

they began to sacrifice to him as “‘ Coadjutor” and
"Saviour.”<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">In this way they made him out the associate of Apollo.</note>
Alexander liked to hear all this, and
at length believed it, and was very proud of himself for being, as he thought, not only the son of
a god but also able to make gods. Well, how many
of Alexander's friends, do you suppose, reaped the
results of Hephaestion’s divinity during that period,
through being accused of not honouring the universal god, and consequently being banished and
deprived of the king’s favour?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

It was then that
Agathocles of Samos, one of Alexander’s captains
whom he esteemed highly, came near being shut up
in a lion’s den because he was charged with having
wept as he went by the tomb of Hephaestion. But
Perdiccas is said to have come to his rescue, swearing
by all the gods and by Hephaestion to boot that
while he was hunting the god had appeared to him
in the flesh and had bidden him tell Alexander to
spare Agathocles, saying that he had not wept from
want of faith or because he thought Hephaestion
dead, but only because he had been put in mind
of their old-time friendship.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>


As you see, flattery and slander were most likely
to find an opening when they were framed with
reference to Alexander's weak point. In a siege
the enemy do not attack the high, sheer and secure
parts of the wall, but wherever they notice that any
portion is unguarded, unsound or low, they move all
their forces against that place because they can very
easily get in there and take the city. Just so with
slanderers: they assail whatever part of the soul
they perceive to be weak, unsound and easy of
access, bringing their siege-engines to bear on it



<pb n="v.1.p.383"/>

and finally capturing it, as no one opposes them or
notices their assault. Then, when they are once
within the walls, they fire everything and smite and
slay and banish ; for all these things are likely to
happen when the soul is captured and put in
bondage.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
The engines that they use against the hearer
are deceit, lying, perjury, insistence, impudence, and
a thousand other unprincipled means; but the most
important of all is flattery, a bosom friend, yes, an
own sister to slander. Nobody is so high-minded
and has a soul so well protected by walls of adamant
that he cannot succumb to the assaults of flattery,
especially when he is being undermined and his
foundations sapped by slander.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>

All this is on the
outside, while on the inside there are many traitors
who help the enemy, holding out their hands to him,
opening the gates, and in every way furthering
the capture of the hearer. First there is fondness
for novelty, which is by nature common to all
mankind, and ennui also; and secondly, a tendency
to be attracted by startling rumours. Somehow or
other we all like to hear stories that are slyly
whispered in our ear, and are packed with innuendo:
indeed, I know men who get as much pleasure from
having their ears titillated with slander as some do
from being tickled with feathers.


<pb n="v.1.p.385"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
Therefore, when the enemy falls on with all these
forces in league with him, he takes the fort by storm,
I suppose, and his victory cannot even prove difficult,
since nobody mans the walls or tries to repel
his attacks. No, the hearer surrenders of his own
accord, and the slandered person is not aware of the
design upon him: slandered men are murdered
in their sleep, just as when a city is captured in
the night.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
The saddest thing of all is that the slandered
man, unaware of all that has taken place, meets his
friend cheerfully, not being conscious of any misdeed,
and speaks and acts in his usual manner, when he
is beset on every side, poor fellow, with lurking foes.
The other, if he is noble, gentlemanly, and outspoken, at once lets his anger burst out and vents
his wrath, and then at last, on permitting a defence
to be made, finds out that he was incensed at_ his
friend for nothing.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

But if he is ignoble and mean
he welcomes him and smiles at him out of the
corner of his mouth, while all the time he hates
him and secretly grinds his teeth and broods, as the
poet says<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Homer; the word is frequent in the Odyssey (e.g. 9, 316 ; 17, 66).</note> on his anger. Yet nothing, I think, is
more unjust or more contemptible than to bite
your lips and nurse your bitterness, to lock your
hatred up within yourself and nourish it, thinking
one thing in the depths of your heart and saying
another, and acting a very eventful tragedy, full of
lamentation, with a jovial comedy face.</p>

<p>
Men are more liable to act in this way when
the slanderer has long seemed to be a friend of
the person slandered, and yet does what he does.



<pb n="v.1.p.387"/>

In that case they are no longer willing even
to hear the voice of the men slandered or of those
who speak in their behalf, for they assume in
advance that the accusation can be relied on
because of the apparent friendship of long standing,
without even reflecting that many reasons for hatred .
often arise between the closest friends, of which
the rest of the world knows nothing. Now and
then, too, a man makes haste to accuse his neighbour of something that he is himself to blame for,
trying in this way to escape accusation himself.
And in general, nobody would venture to slander
an enemy, for in that case his accusation would not
inspire belief, as its motive would be patent. No,
they attack those men who seem to be their best
friends, aiming to show their good will toward their
hearers by sacrificing even their nearest and dearest
to help them.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>

There are people who, even if they afterwards
learn that their friends have been unjustly accused
to them, nevertheless, because they are ashamed of
their own credulity, no longer can endure to receive
them or look at them, as though they themselves
had been wronged merely by finding out that the
others were doing no wrong at all!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>

It follows, then, that life has been filled with
troubles in abundance through the slanderous stories
that have been believed so readily and so unquestioningly. Anteia says:

<cit>
<quote>
<l>Die, Proetus, or despatch Bellerophon,</l>
<l>Who offered me his love, by me unsought,</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Homer, Iliad 6, 164.</bibl></cit>
when she herself had made the first move and had

<pb n="v.1.p.389"/>

been scorned. So the young man came near getting
killed in the encounter with the Chimaera, and was
rewarded for his continence and his respect for his
host by being plotted against by a wanton. As for
Phaedra, she too made a similar charge against her
stepson and so brought it about that Hippolytus was
cursed by his father
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Theseus: the story is told in the Hippolytus of Euripides.</note>
when he had done nothing
impious—good Heavens, nothing !
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>

“Yes,” somebody will say, “but now and then
the man who brings a personal charge deserves
credence, because he seems to be just in all other
matters and sensible also, and one would have to
heed him, as he would never do such a scoundrelly
thing as that.” Well, is there anyone more just than
Aristides? But even he conspired against Themistocles and had a hand in stirring up the people
against him, because, they say, he was secretly
pricked by the same political ambition as Themistocles. Aristides was indeed just, in comparison with
the rest of the world; but he was a man like anyone
else and had spleen and not only loved but hated on
occasion.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>

And if the story of Palamedes is true, the
most sensible of the Greeks and the best of them in
other ways stands convicted of having, through envy,
framed a plot and an ambush to trap a kinsman and
a friend, who had sailed away from home to front
the same peril as he<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">Odysseus trapped Palamedes by getting a forged letter
from Priam hidden in his tent and then pretending to
discover it.</note>; so true is it that to err in this
direction is inborn in all mankind.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>

Why should I
mention Socrates, who was unjustly slandered to the
Athenians as an irreligious man and a traitor? or




<pb n="v.1.p.391"/>

Themistocles and Miltiades, both of whom, after
all their victories, came to be suspected of treason
against Greece? The instances are countless, and
are already for the most part well known.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>

“Then what should a man do, if he has sense
and lays claim to probity or truthfulness?.” In my
opinion he should do what Homer suggested in his
parable of the Sirens. He bids us to sail past these
deadly allurements and to stop our ears ; not to hold
them wide open to men prejudiced by passion, but,
setting Reason as a strict doorkeeper over all that is
said, to welcome and admit what deserves it, but
shut out and drive off what is bad. For surely,
it would be ridiculous to have doorkeepers to guard
your house, but to leave your ears and your mind
wide open.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg013.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p>

Therefore, when a man comes and tells
you a thing of this sort, you must investigate the
matter on its own merits, without regarding the years
of the speaker or his standing, or his carefulness in
what he says; for the more plausible a man is, the
closer your investigation should be. You should not,
then, put faith in another's judgment, or rather
(as you would be doing), in the accuser’s want of
judgment,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Literally, "in the accuser’s hatred.” To secure something like the word-play in the Greek, the sense had to
suffer slightly.</note>
but should reserve to yourself the province
of investigating the truth, accrediting the slanderer
with his envy and conducting an open examination
into the sentiments of both men; and you should
only hate or love a man after you have put him to
the proof. To do so before that time, influenced
by the first breath of slander—Heavens! how


<pb n="v.1.p.393"/>

childish, how base and, beyond everything, how unjust! But the cause of this and all the rest of it, as
I said in the beginning, is ignorance, and the fact
that the real character of each of us is shrouded in
darkness. Hence, if some oné of the gods would
only unveil our lives, Slander would vanish away
to limbo, having no place left, since everything would
be illumined by Truth.


</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>

