<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Fragments </title>
        <author>Epictetus</author>
        <editor role="editor" n="transl">Thomas Wentworth Higginson</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>



      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <title>The Works of Epictetus: His Discourses, in Four Books, the Enchiridion, and
              Fragments</title>
            <author>Epictetus</author>
            <respStmt>
              <name>Thomas Wentworth Higginson</name>
              <resp>translator</resp>
            </respStmt>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
              <publisher>Thomas Nelson and Sons</publisher>
              <date>1890</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <editorialDecl>
        <correction method="silent" status="high">
          <!--&Perseus.OCR;-->
          <p>Perseus OCR</p>
        </correction>
      </editorialDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="text"/>
        <refState unit="book"/>
        <refState n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="text"/>
        <refState n="chunk" unit="chapter"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English</language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
        <language ident="la">Latin</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>03-Dec-03</date>
<respStmt><name>AEM</name><resp>markup</resp></respStmt>
<item>initial markup
</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
      <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>

  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <head>Fragments of Epictetus from Stobaeus, Antonius, and Maximus.<note anchored="true"
          >Stobaeus lived early in the fifth century, Maximus in the seventh, and Antonius, surnamed
            <placeName key="tgn,2119179">Melissa</placeName>, or the Bee, in the eighth. Their
          collections are. printed together. Many of these sayings are merely traditional. -
          H.</note></head>
      <div type="book" n="0">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p>A life at odds with Fortune resembles a wintry torrent; for it is turbulent and muddy
            and difficult to pass, and violent and noisy and brief.</p>
          <p>A soul conversant with virtue resembles a perpetual fountain; for it is clear and
            gentle and agreeable and sweet and serviceable and rich and harmless and innocent.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p>If you would be good, first believe that you are bad.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p>It is better sometimes frankly to offend, and act often wisely, than to say we seldom
            err and offend frequently. <pb n="p.2248"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p>Chastise your passions, that they may not chastise you.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p>Be not so much ashamed of what is inglorious, as studious to shun what is
            untruthful.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p>If you would be well spoken of, learn to speak well of others. And when you have
            learned to speak well, endeavor likewise to do well; and thus you will reap the fruit of
            being well spoken of.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p>Freedom and slavery are merely names of virtue and of vice; and both these are matters
            of will. But neither of them belongs to things in which will has no share. But Fortune
            is accustomed to dispose at her pleasure of the body, and those things relating to the
            body in which will has no share. For no one is a slave whose will is free.</p>
          <p>Fortune is an evil chain to the body, and vice to the soul. For he whose body is
            unbound, and whose soul is chained, is a slave. On the contrary, he whose body is
            chained, and his soul unbound, is free. The chain of the body, Nature unbinds by death,
            or baseness for money; the chain of the soul, virtue unbinds by wisdom and experience
            and philosophic training. <pb n="p.2249"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p>If you would live tranquil and contented, endeavor that all who live with you may be
            good. And you can have them good by instructing the willing and dismissing the
            unwilling. For sin and bondage will fly with those who leave you, and with those who
            remain with you will virtue and liberty be left.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p>It is scandalous that he who sweetens his drink by the gift of the bees, should by vice
            embitter reason, the gift of the gods.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p>No one who is a lover of money, a lover of pleasure, or a lover of glory, is likewise a
            lover of mankind; but only he who is a lover of virtue.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p>As you would not wish to sail in a large and elegant and gilded ship, and sink; so
            neither is it desirable to inhabit a grand and sumptuous house, and be in a tumult.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p>When we are invited to an entertainment we take what we find; and if any one should bid
            the master of the house set fish or tarts before him, he would be thought absurd. Yet in
            the world we ask the gods <pb n="p.2250"/> for what they do not give us; and that,
            though there are so many things which they have given us.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p>They are pretty fellows indeed, said he, who value themselves on things not in our own
            power. I am a better man than you, says one; for I have many estates, and you are pining
            with hunger. I have been consul, says another; I am a ruler, says a third; and I have a
            fine head of hair, says a fourth. Yet one horse does not say to another, "I am better
            than you, for I have a great deal of hay and a great deal of oats, and I have a gold
            bridle and embroidered trappings;" but only, " I am swifter than you." And every
            creature is better or worse from its own good or bad qualities. Is man, then, the only
            creature which has no natural good quality? And must we take account of hair and clothes
            and ancestors?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p>Patients are displeased with a physician who does not prescribe to them; and think he
            gives them over. And why are none so affected towards a philosopher as to conclude that
            he despairs of their recovery to a right way of thinking, if he tells them nothing for
            their good?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p>They who have a good constitution of body can bear heat and cold; and so they who have
            a right <pb n="p.2251"/> constitution of soul can meet anger and grief and immoderate
            joy and the other passions.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p>Examine yourself, whether you had rather be rich or happy. And if rich, be assured that
            this is neither a good, nor altogether in your own power; but if happy, that this is
            both a good, and in your own power; since the one is a temporary loan of Fortune, and
            the other depends on will.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p>As when you see a viper, or an asp, or a scorpion in a box of ivory or gold, you do not
            love it or think it happy because of the magnificence of the material in which it is
            enclosed, but you shun and detest it, because it is of a pernicious nature; so,
            likewise, when you see vice lodged in the midst of wealth, and the swelling pride of
            fortune, be not struck by the splendor of the material with which it is surrounded; but
            despise the base alloy of its manners.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p>Riches are not among the number of things which are good; prodigality is of the number
            of those which are evil; modesty of those which are good. Now modesty invites to
            frugality and the acquisition of things that are good; but riches invite to prodigality
            and seduce from modesty. It is difficult, therefore, <pb n="p.2252"/> for a rich person
            to be modest, or a modest person rich.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p>If you had been born and bred in a ship, you would not be impatient to become the
            pilot. For you are not necessarily identified with the ship there, nor with riches here;
            but with reason everywhere. That therefore which is natural and congenial to you,
            reason, think likewise to be peculiarly your own, and take care of it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p>If you were born in <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>, you would not
            endeavor to live in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, but to be happy in
            the place where you were. Why, then, if you are born in poverty, do you yearn to be
            rich, and not rather to be happy in the condition where you are?</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p>As it is better to lie straitened for room upon a little couch in health, than to toss
            upon a wide bed in sickness, so it is better to contract yourself within the compass of
            a small fortune, and be happy, than to have a great one and be wretched.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p>It is not poverty that causes sorrow, but covetous desires; nor do riches deliver from
            fear, but only reasoning. If therefore you acquire a habit of reasoning, you will
            neither desire riches, nor complain of poverty. <pb n="p.2253"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p>A horse is not elated, and does not value himself on his fine stable or trappings or
            saddle-cloths, nor a bird on the warm materials of its nest; but the former on the
            swiftness of his feet, and the latter of its wings. Do not you, therefore, glory in your
            food or dress, or in short any external advantage, but in integrity and beneficence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p>There is a difference between living well and living profusely. The one arises from
            contentment and order and propriety and frugality; the other from dissoluteness and
            luxury and disorder and indecency. In short, to the one belongs true praise; to the
            other, censure. If therefore you would live well, do not seek to be praised for
            profuseness.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p>Let the first satisfaction of appetite be always the measure to you of eating and
            drinking; and appetite itself the sauce and the pleasure. Thus you will never take more
            than is necessary, nor will you want cooks; and you will be contented with whatever
            drink falls in your way.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p>Consider that you do not thrive merely by the food in your stomach; but by the
            elevation of your soul. <pb n="p.2254"/> For the former, as you see, is evacuated and
            carried off altogether; but the latter, though the soul be parted, remains uncorrupted
            through all things.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p>In every feast remember that there are two guests to be entertained, the body and the
            soul; and that what you give the body you presently lose, but what you give the soul
            remains forever.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p>Do not mingle anger with profusion, and set them before your guests. Profusion, when it
            has made its way through the body, is quickly gone; but anger, when it has penetrated
            the soul, abides for a long time. Take care not to pay a great price merely to be
            transported with anger, and affront your guests; but rather delight them at a cheap rate
            by gentle behavior.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p>Take care at your meals that the attendants be not more in number than those whom they
            are to attend. For it is absurd that many persons should wait on a few chairs.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p>It would be best if, both while you are personally making your preparations and while
            you are feasting at table, you could give among the servants part of what is before you.
            But if such a thing be difficult <pb n="p.2255"/> at that time, remember that you, who
            are not weary, are attended by those who are; you who are eating and drinking, by those
            who are not; you who are talking, by those who are silent; you who are at ease, by those
            who are under constraint; and thus you will never be heated into any unreasonable
            passion yourself, nor do any mischief by provoking another.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p>Strife and contention are always absurd, but particularly unbecoming at table
            conversations. For a person warmed with wine will never either teach, or be convinced
            by, one who is sober. And wherever sobriety is wanting, the end will show that you have
            exerted yourself to no purpose.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p>Grasshoppers are musical; but snails are dumb. The latter rejoice in being wet; and the
            former in being warm. Then the dew calls out the one race, and for this they come forth;
            but, on the contrary, the noonday sun awakens the others, and in this they sing. If
            therefore you.would be a musical and harmonious person, whenever the soul is bedewed
            with wine at drinking-parties, suffer her not to go forth and defile herself. But when
            in rational society she glows by the beams of reason, then command her to speak from
            inspiration, and utter the oracles of justice. <pb n="p.2256"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="33">
          <p>Consider him with whom you converse in one of these three ways: either as your
            superior, or inferior, or equal. If superior, you ought to hear him and be convinced; if
            inferior, to convince him; if equal, to agree with him; and thus you will never be led
            into the love of strife.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="34">
          <p/>
          <p rend="right">It is better, by yielding to truth, to conquer prejudice, than by yielding
            to principle to be defeated by truth.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="35">
          <p>If you seek truth, you will not seek merely victory at all hazards; and when you have
            found truth, you will have a security against being conquered.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="36">
          <p>Truth conquers by itself; prejudice, by appealing to externals.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="37">
          <p>It is better, through living with one free person, to be fearless and free, than to be
            a slave in company with many.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="38">
          <p/>
          <p rend="right">What you avoid suffering yourself, seek not to impose on others. You avoid
            slavery, for instance; take care not to enslave. For if you can bear to <pb n="p.2257"/>
            exact slavery from others, you appear to have been yourself a slave. For vice has
            nothing in common with virtue, nor freedom with slavery. As a person in health would not
            wish to be attended by the sick, nor to have those who live with him in a state of
            sickness; so neither would a person who is free bear to be served by slaves, nor to have
            those who live with him in a state of slavery.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="39">
          <p>Whoever you are that would live apart from slaves, deliver yourself from slavery. And
            you will be free if you deliver yourself from appetite. For neither was Aristides called
            just, nor Epaminondas divine, nor Lycurgus a preserver, because they were rich and
            slave-holders; but because, being poor, they delivered <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
              >Greece</placeName> from slavery.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="40">
          <p>If you would have your house securely inhabited, imitate the Spartan Lycurgus. And as
            he did not enclose his city with walls, but fortified the inhabitants with virtue, and
            preserved the city always free; so do you, likewise, not surround yourself with a great
            court-yard, nor raise high towers, but strengthen those who live with you by benevolence
            and fidelity and friendship. And thus nothing hurtful will enter, even if the whole band
            of wickedness be set in array against it. <pb n="p.2258"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="41">
          <p>Do not hang your house round with tablets and pictures, but adorn it with virtue. For
            those are merely foreign and a fading deception of the eyes; but this, a congenial and
            indelible and perpetual ornament to the house.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="42">
          <p>Instead of herds of oxen, endeavor to assemble flocks of friends about your house.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="43">
          <p/>
          <p rend="right">As a wolf resembles a dog, so much does a flatterer, an adulterer, a
            parasite, resemble a friend. Take heed, therefore, that instead of guardian dogs, you do
            not inadvertently admit ravening wolves.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="44">
          <p>To seek admiration by adorning one's house with stucco belongs to a tasteless man; but
            to adorn our characters by the charm of an amiable nature shows at once a lover of
            beauty and a lover of man.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="45">
          <p>If you chiefly admire little things, you will never be held worthy of great ones; but
            if you are above little things, you will be held greatly worthy. <pb n="p.2259"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="46">
          <p>Nothing is meaner than the love of pleasure, the love of gain, and insolence. Nothing
            is nobler than magnanimity, meekness, and philanthropy.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="47">
          <p>[We represent] those intractable philosophers who do not think pleasure to be in itself
            the natural state of man, but merely an incident of those things in which his natural
            state consists, -justice, moderation, and freedom. Why, then, should the soul rejoice
            and be glad in the minor blessings of the body, as Epicurus says, and not be pleased
            with its own good, which is the very greatest? And yet Nature has given me likewise a
            sense of shame; and I am covered with blushes, when I think I have uttered any indecent
            expression. This emotion will not suffer me to recognize pleasure as a good and the end
            of life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="48">
          <p>The ladies at <placeName key="perseus,Rome">Rome</placeName> have Plato's Republic in
            their hands, because he allows a community of wives; for they attend merely to the words
            of the author, and not to his sense. For he does not first order one man and one woman
            to marry and live together, and then allow a community of wives; but he abolishes that
            system of marriage, and introduces one of another kind. And, in general, men are pleased
            in <pb n="p.2260"/> ending out excuses for their own faults. Yet philosophy says it is
            not fit even to move a finger without 30me reason.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="49">
          <p>It is the rarest pleasures which especially delight us.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="50">
          <p>Once exceed moderation, and the most delightful things may become the most
            undelightful.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="51">
          <p>Agrippinus was justly entitled to praise on this account, that, though he was a man of
            the highest worth, he never praised himself, but blushed even if another praised him.
            And he was a man of such a character as to commend every untoward event that befell him:
            if he was feverish, the fever; if disgraced, the disgrace; if banished, the banishment.
            And, when once, as he was going to dine, a messenger brought him word that Nero ordered
            him to banishment, Well, then, said Agrippinus, let us dine at <placeName
              key="perseus,Aricia">Aricia</placeName>.<note anchored="true">The first stage on his
              journey into banishment. See note, <emph>ante</emph>. - H.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="52">
          <p>Diogenes affirmed -no labor to be good, unless the end were a due state and tone of the
            soul, and not of the body. <pb n="p.2261"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="53">
          <p>As a true balance is neither set right by a true one, nor judged by a false one; so
            likewise a just person has neither to be set right by just persons, nor to be judged by
            unjust ones.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="54">
          <p>As what is straight needs no straightness, so what is just needs [to borrow] no
            justice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="55">
          <p>Give no judgment from another tribunal before you have yourself been judged at the
            tribunal of absolute justice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="56">
          <p>If you would give a just decision, heed neither parties nor pleaders, but the cause
            itself.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="57">
          <p>You will commit the fewest faults in judging, if you are faultless in your own
            life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="58">
          <p>It is better, by giving a just judgment, to be blamed by him who is deservedly
            condemned, than, by giving an unjust judgment, to be justly censured by Nature. <pb
              n="p.2262"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="59">
          <p>As the touchstone which tries gold, but is not itself tried by the gold, such is he who
            has the standard of judgment.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="60">
          <p>It is scandalous for a judge to have to be judged by others.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="61">
          <p>As nothing is straighter than absolute straightness, so nothing is juster than absolute
            justice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="62">
          <p>Who among you does not admire the action of Lycurgus the Lacedemonian? For when he had
            been deprived of one of his eyes by one of the citizens, and the people had delivered
            the young man to him, to be punished in whatever manner he should think proper, Lycurgus
            forbore to give him any punishment; but having instructed him, and rendered him a good
            man, he brought him into the theatre, and while the Lacedemonians were struck with
            admiration, "I received," said he, "this person from you, dangerous and violent, and I
            restore him to you gentle and a good citizen."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="63">
          <p>When Pittacus had been unjustly treated by some person, and had the power of chastising
            him, he let <pb n="p.2263"/> him go, saying, "Forgiveness is better than punishment; for
            the one is the proof of a gentle, the other of a savage, nature."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="64">
          <p>This, above all, is the business of nature, to connect and apply the active powers to
            what appears fit and beneficial.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="65">
          <p>It is the character of the most mean-spirited and foolish men, to suppose that they
            shall be despised by others, unless they somehow strike the first blow at their
            enemies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="66">
          <p>When you are going to attack any one with vehemence and threatening, remember to say
            first to yourself that you are constituted gentle, and that by doing nothing violent,
            you will live without the need of repentance, and irreproachable.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="67">
          <p>We ought to know that it is not easy for a man to form his principles of action, unless
            he daily reiterates and hears the same things, and at the same time applies them in
            action.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="68">
          <p>Nicias was so intent on business, that he often asked his domestics whether he had
            bathed and whether he h.ad dined. <pb n="p.2264"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="69">
          <p>While Archimedes was intent on his diagrams, his servants drew him away by violence,
            and anointed<note anchored="true">The ancients anointed the body every day. - C.</note>
            him; and after his body was anointed, he traced his figures upon that.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="70">
          <p>When Lampis, the naval commander, was asked how he acquired wealth, he answered, that
            great wealth cost but little trouble, but that a little wealth [at the beginning] cost a
            great deal.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="71">
          <p>When Solon was silent at an entertainment, and was asked by Periander whether he was
            silent for want of words or from folly, "No fool," answered he, " can be silent at a
            feast."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="72">
          <p>Consult nothing so much, upon every occasion, as discretion. Now, it is more discreet
            to be silent than to speak, and to omit speaking whatever is not accompanied with sense
            and reason.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="73">
          <p>As light-houses in harbors, by kindling a great flame from a few fagots, afford a
            considerable assistance to ships wandering on the sea; so an illus- <pb n="p.2265"/>
            trious person, in a state harassed by storms, confers great benefits on his
            fellow-citizens, when himself contented with little.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="74">
          <p>You would certainly, if you undertook to steer a ship, learn the steersman's art. And
            as in that case you can steer the whole ship, so, in another case, the whole state.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="75">
          <p>If you have a mind to adorn your city by consecrated monuments, first consecrate in
            yourself the most beautiful monument, - of gentleness and justice and benevolence.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="76">
          <p>You will confer the greatest benefits on.your city, not by raising its roofs, but by
            exalting its souls. For it is better that great souls should live in small habitations,
            than that abject slaves should burrow in great houses.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="77">
          <p>Do not variegate the structure of your walls with Euboean and Spartan stone, but adorn
            both the minds of the citizens and of those who govern them by the Greek culture. For
            cities are made good habitations by the sentiments of those who live in them, not by
            wood or stone. <pb n="p.2266"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="78">
          <p>As, if you were to breed lions, you would not be solicitous about the magnificence of
            their dens, but about the qualities of the animals; so, if you undertake to preside over
            your fellow-citizens, be not so solicitous about the magnificence of the buildings as
            careful of the nobleness of those who inhabit them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="79">
          <p>As a skilful manager of horses does not feed the good colts, and suffer the unruly ones
            to starve, but feeds them both alike, chastising the one more, to make him draw equally
            with his fellow; so a man of foresight and administrative skill endeavors to do good to
            the well-disposed citizens, but not at once to destroy those that are otherwise. He by
            no means denies subsistence to either of them; only he disciplines and urges on, with
            the greater vehemence, him who resists reason and the laws.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="80">
          <p>As a goose is not alarmed by hissing, nor a sheep by bleating, so neither be you
            terrified by the voice of a senseless multitude.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="81">
          <p>As you do not comply with a multitude, when it unreasonably asks of you any part of
            your own <pb n="p.2267"/> property; so/neither be disconcerted before a mob, demanding
            of you any unjust compliance.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="82">
          <p>Pay in advance your dues to the public, and you will never be asked for what is not
            due.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="83">
          <p>As the sun waits not for prayers and incantations to be prevailed on to rise, but
            immediately shines forth, and is received with universal salutation; so neither do you
            wait for applauses and shouts and praises in order to do good, but be a voluntary
            benefactor, and you will be beloved like the sun.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="84">
          <p>A ship ought not to be held by one anchor, nor life by a single hope.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="85">
          <p>We ought not to stretch either our legs or our hopes for a point they cannot reach.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="86">
          <p>Thales, being asked what was the most universal possession, answered, "Hope; for they
            have it who have nothing else."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="87">
          <p>It is more necessary for the soul to be healed than the body; for it is better to die
            than to live ill. <pb n="p.2268"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="88">
          <p>Pyrrho used to say, "There is no difference between living and dying." A person asked
            him, Why then do you not die? "Because." answered Pyrrho, "there is no difference."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="89">
          <p>Nature is admirable and, as Xenophon says, avaricious of life. Hence we love and tend
            the body, which is of all things the most unpleasant and squalid. For if we were
            obliged, for only five days, to take care of our neighbor's body, we would not endure
            it. For only consider what it would be, when we rise in the morning, to clean the teeth
            of others, and do all requisite offices besides. In reality, it is wonderful that we
            should love a thing which every day demands so much attendance. I stuff this sack, and
            then I empty it again. What is more troublesome? But I must obey God. Therefore I
            remain, and endure to wash and feed and clothe this poor body. When I was younger, he
            demanded of me still more, and I bore it. And when Nature, which gave the body, takes it
            away, will you not bear that? " I love it," say you. This is what I have just been
            observing; and this very love has Nature given you, but she also says, "Now let it go,
            and have no further trouble." <pb n="p.2269"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="90">
          <p>When a young man dies, some one blames the gods that, at the time when he himself ought
            to be at rest, he is still encumbered with the troubles of life. Yet when death
            approaches he wishes to live, and sends for the physician, and entreats him to omit no
            care or pains. It is marvellous that men should not be willing either to live or
            die.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="91">
          <p>To a longer and worse life, a shorter and better is by all means to be preferred by
            every one.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="92">
          <p>When we are children, our parents deliver us to the care of a tutor, who is continually
            to watch over us that we get no hurt. When we are become men, God delivers us to the
            guardianship of an implanted conscience. We ought by no means, then, to despise this
            guardian; for it will both displease God, and we shall be enemies to our own
            conscience.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="93">
          <p>Riches ought to be used as the means to some end, and not lavished on every
            occasion.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="94">
          <p>All men should wish rather for virtue than for wealth, which is dangerous to the
            foolish, since vice <pb n="p.2270"/> is increased by riches. And in proportion as any
            one is foolish, he becomes the more profuse, through having the means of gratifying his
            passion for pleasure.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="95">
          <p>What ought not to be done, do not even think of doing.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="96">
          <p>Deliberate much before you speak or act; for what is once said or done you cannot
            recall.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="97">
          <p>Every place is safe to him who dwells with justice.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="98">
          <p>Crows pick out the eyes of the dead, when they are no longer of any use. But flatterers
            destroy the souls of the living by blinding their eyes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="99">
          <p>The anger of a monkey and the threats of a flatterer deserve equal regard.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="100">
          <p>Kindly receive those who are willing to give good advice, but not those who upon every
            occasion are eager to flatter. For the former truly see what is advantageous; but the
            latter consider only the opinions of their superiors, and imitate the shadows of bodies,
            nodding assent to what they say. <pb n="p.2271"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="101">
          <p>An adviser ought, in the first place, to have a regard to the delicacy and sense of
            shame of the person admonished. For they who are beyond blushing are incorrigible.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="102">
          <p>It is better to advise than reproach; for the one is mild and friendly, the other stern
            and severe; the one corrects the erring, the other only convicts them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="103">
          <p>Impart to strangers and persons in need according to your ability. For he who gives
            nothing to the needy shall receive nothing in his own need.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="104">
          <p>A person once brought clothes to a pirate, who had been cast ashore, and almost killed
            by the severity of the weather; then carried him to his house, and furnished him with
            all necessaries. Being reproached by some one for doing good to the evil, "I have paid
            this regard," answered he, "not to the man, but to humanity."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="105">
          <p>We ought not to choose every pleasure, but that whose end is good. <pb n="p.2272"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="106">
          <p>It belongs to a wise man to resist pleasure, and to a fool to be enslaved by it.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="107">
          <p>In all vice, pleasure, being presented like a bait, draws sensual minds to the hook of
            perdition.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="108">
          <p>Choose rather to punish your appetites than to be punished by them.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="109">
          <p>No one is free who commands not himself.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="110">
          <p>The vine bears three clusters: the first of pleasure, the second of intoxication, the
            third of outrage.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="111">
          <p>Do not talk much over wine to show your learning, for your discourse will be
            unpleasing.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="111">
          <p>He is a drunkard who takes more than three glasses; and though he be not drunk, he has
            exceeded moderation.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="112">
          <p>Let discourse of God be renewed every day more surely than our food. <pb n="p.2273"
            /></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="114">
          <p>Think of God oftener than you breathe.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="115">
          <p>If you always remember that God stands by as a witness of whatever you do, either in
            soul or body, you will never err, either in your prayers or actions, and you will have
            God abiding with you.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="116">
          <p>As it is pleasant to view the sea from the shore, so it is pleasant to one who has
            escaped, to remember his past labors.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="117">
          <p>Law aims to benefit human life; but it cannot, when men themselves choose to suffer,
            for it manifests its proper virtue on condition of obedience.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="118">
          <p>As physicians are the preservers of the sick, so are the laws, of the injured.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="119">
          <p>The justest laws are the truest.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="120">
          <p>It is decent to yield to a law, to a ruler, and to a wiser man. <pb n="p.2274"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="121">
          <p>Things done contrary to law are to be regarded as undone.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="122">
          <p>In prosperity it is very easy to find a friend; in adversity, nothing is so
            difficult.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="123">
          <p>Time delivers fools from grief; and reason, wise men.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="124">
          <p>He is a man of sense who does not grieve for what he has not, but rejoices in what he
            has.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="125">
          <p>Epictetus being asked how a person might grieve his enemy, answered, "By doing as well
            as possible himself."</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="126">
          <p>Let no wise man estrange himself from the government of the state; for it is both
            wicked to withdraw from being useful to the needy, and cowardly to give way to the
            worthless. For it is foolish to choose rather to be governed ill than to govern
            well.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="127">
          <p>Nothing is more becoming a ruler than to despise no one, nor be insolent, but to
            preside over all impartially. <pb n="p.2275"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="128">
          <p>Any person may live happy in poverty, but few in wealth and power. So great is the
            advantage of poverty, that no wise man would exchange it for disreputable wealth; unless
            indeed Themistocles, the son of Neocles, the most wealthy of the Athenians, but poor in
            virtue, was better than Aristides and Socrates. But both himself and his wealth are
            perished, and without a name. For a bad man loses all in death; but virtue is
            eternal.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="129">
          <p>[Remember] that such is and was and will be the nature of the world, nor is it possible
            that things should be otherwise than they now are; and that not only men and other
            creatures upon earth partake of this change and transformation, but diviner things also.
            For indeed even the four elements are transformed and metamorphosed; and earth becomes
            water, and water air, and this again is transformed into other things. And the same
            manner of transformation happens from things above to those below. Whoever endeavors to
            turn his mind towards these points, and persuade himself to receive with willingness
            what cannot be avoided, will pass his life in moderation and harmony. <pb n="p.2276"
            /></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="130">
          <p>He who is discontented with things present and allotted is unskilled in life. But he
            who bears them, and the consequences arising from them, nobly and rationally, is worthy
            to be esteemed a good man.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="131">
          <p>All things serve and obey the [laws of the] universe: the earth, the sea, the sun, the
            stars, and the plants and animals of the earth. Our body likewise obeys the same, in
            being sick and well, young and old, and passing through the other changes decreed. It is
            therefore reasonable that what depends on ourselves, that is, our own understanding,
            should not be the only rebel. For the universe is powerful and superior, and consults
            the best for us by governing us in conjunction with the whole. And further, opposition,
            besides that it is unreasonable, and produces nothing except a vain struggle, throws us
            into pain and sorrows. <pb n="p.2277"/></p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Other fragments.</head>
        <p><emph>The following Fragments are ascribed jointly to Epictetus and other
          authors</emph>.</p>
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p>Moderation, as it is a short and agreeable way, brings much delight and little
            trouble.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p>Fortify yourself with moderation; for this is an impregnable fortress.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p>Prefer nothing to truth, not even the choicest friendship, since this borders on those
            passions by which justice is both confounded and darkened.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p>Truth is an immortal and an eternal thing. It bestows not a beauty which time will
            wither, nor a courage which may quail before a human tribunal; but only things just and
            lawful, from which it divides and destroys all that is unjust.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p>We should have neither a blunt sword nor a pointless speech.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p>Nature has given man one tongue, but two ears, that we may hear twice as much as we
            speak. <pb n="p.2278"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="7">
          <p>Nothing is in reality either pleasant or unpleasant by nature; but all things become
            such through habit.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="8">
          <p>Choose the best life; for habit will make it pleasant.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="9">
          <p>Choose rather to leave your children well instructed than rich. For the hopes of the
            wise are better than the riches of the ignorant.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="10">
          <p>A daughter is to a father a possession which is not his own.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="11">
          <p>The same person advised to bequeath modesty to children, rather than gold.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="12">
          <p>The reproof of a father is an agreeable medicine; for the profit is greater than the
            pain.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="13">
          <p>He who is fortunate in a son-in-law finds a son; he who is unfortunate in one loses
            likewise a daughter. <pb n="p.2279"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="14">
          <p>The worth of instruction, like that of gold, passes current in every place.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="15">
          <p>He who cultivates-wisdom cultivates the knowledge of God.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="16">
          <p>There is no creature so beautiful as a man adorned by instruction.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="17">
          <p>We ought to flee the friendship of the wicked, and the enmity of the good.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="18">
          <p>Misfortunes test friends, and detect enemies.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="19">
          <p>We ought to do well by our friends when they are present, and speak well of them when
            they are absent.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="20">
          <p>Let him not think himself loved by any, who loves none.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="21">
          <p>We ought to choose, both for a physician and for a friend, not the most agreeable, but
            the most useful. <pb n="p.2280"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="22">
          <p>If you would lead a life without sorrow, regard things which will happen, as if they
            had already happened.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="23">
          <p>Be exempt from grief; not like irrational creatures, from insensibility, nor from
            inconsiderateness, like fools; but like a man of virtue, making reason the remedy for
            grief.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="24">
          <p>They whose minds are the least grieved by calamities, and who best meet them in action,
            are the greatest both in public and in private life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="25">
          <p>They who are well instructed, like those who are exercised in the palaestra, if they
            happen to fall quickly and dexterously rise again from misfortunes.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="26">
          <p>We ought to call in reason, like a good physician, to our assistance in misfortune.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="27">
          <p>Too much intoxication from good fortune, as from drinking, makes a fool more
            senseless.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="28">
          <p>Envy is the adversary of the fortunate. <pb n="p.2281"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="29">
          <p>He who remembers what man is, can be discontented at nothing which happens.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="30">
          <p>A pilot and a fair wind are necessary to a happy voyage; reason and art, to a happy
            life.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="31">
          <p>Of good fortune, as of ripe fruit, we must make the most while it lasts.</p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="32">
          <p>He is unreasonable who quarrels with events which happen from natural necessity. <pb
              n="p.2282"/></p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Doubtful fragments.</head>
        <p>The following Fragments are omitted by Mr. Upton, but as they stand under the name of
          Arrian, and seem to be in the spirit of Epictetus, they are added here. - [C.]</p>
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <p>What does it signify to me, said he, whether the universe is composed of atoms or
            uncompounded substances, or of fire and earth? Is it not sufficient to know the essence
            of good and evil, and the proper bounds of the desires and aversions, and of the active
            powers; and by making use of these as so many certain rules, to order the conduct of
            life, and let go these things which are above us; which, perhaps, are incomprehensible
            to human understanding, but if one should suppose them ever so comprehensible, are still
            of doubtful benefit when comprehended. And must it not be said that he gives himself
            trouble to no purpose who attributes these things as essential to the character of a
            philosopher? "What, then; is the Delphic admonition, <emph>Know thyself</emph>,
            superflous?" "No, surely," said he. "What, then, does it mean?" If any one should
            admonish a performer in a chorus to know himself, would he not take it as a hint to
            improve his motions?<note anchored="true">Stobaeus <emph>de Diis. <placeName
                  key="tgn,1005589">Serm</placeName></emph>. 211, p. 714, ed. Francof. <date
                when="1581">1581</date>. - C.</note>
            <pb n="p.2283"/></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="2">
          <p>The same person being asked, "Wherein do the diligent have the advantage of the
            slothful?" answered, " Wherein the pious have the advantage of the impious, - in good
              hopes."<note anchored="true">Maximus, <foreign xml:lang="grc">peri\
                filoponi/as</foreign>
              <placeName key="tgn,1005589">Serm</placeName>. 118, p. 374. -C.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="3">
          <p>Walls give to cities, and education to minds, ornament and security.<note
              anchored="true">Ant. and Max. <title xml:lang="la">de Disciplina</title>
              <emph><placeName key="tgn,1005589">Serm</placeName></emph>. 210, p. 704. C.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="4">
          <p>When a young man was giving himself airs in a public place, and saying that he had
            grown wise by conversing with many wise men; " I have conversed too," answered somebody,
            "with many rich men, but I have not grown rich.".<note anchored="true">Ant. and Max.
                <title xml:lang="la">de Disciplina</title>
              <emph><placeName key="tgn,1005589">Serm</placeName></emph>. 210, p. 704. C.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="5">
          <p>Socrates, being sent for by Archelaus, as designing to make him a rich man, returned
            him this answer: "Four quarts of meal are sold at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> for five denarii, and the fountains run with water. If what I have
            is not sufficient for me, yet I am sufficiently able to make a shift with that; and thus
            it becomes sufficient for me. Do you not perceive that it makes no difference in the
            goodness of Polus's voice, whether he performs the part of Oedipus in <pb n="p.2284"/>
            his regal state, or whether he is a wanderer and a beggar at <placeName
              key="perseus,Colonus">Colonus</placeName>? And shall a brave man appear worse than
            Polus, and not perform well in whatever part is imposed upon him by the Deity? Shall he
            not imitate Odysseus, who made no worse figure in rags than in a fine purple robe?
              "<note anchored="true">Stobaeus, Compar. Paupertatis et Divitiarum. <placeName
                key="tgn,1005589">Serm</placeName>. 237, 778.-C.</note></p>
        </div>
        <div type="chapter" n="6">
          <p>There are some persons who are calmly of a high spirit, and do all the same things
            quietly, and as it were without anger, which those do who are hurried with strong
            passion. We are to guard, therefore, against the faults of such persons, as being much
            worse than those of violent anger. For people of the latter character are quickly
            satiated with vengeance; whereas the others, like persons in a slow lever, extend the
            excitement over a longer time.<note anchored="true">Stobaeus, <emph>Quod Eventus,
              </emph>etc., pp. 324, 329. - C.</note>
            <pb n="p.2285"/></p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>

</TEI>
