<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Defense Against a Charge of Subverting the Democracy</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="Intro, Narr, Proof" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I can find full excuse for
        you, gentlemen of the jury, if on hearing such statements and remembering past events you
        are equally incensed against all those who remained in the city. But I am surprised at my
        accusers: they neglect their own concerns to attend to those of others, and now, though they
        know for certain who are guilty of nothing and who have committed many offences, they seek
        to persuade you into holding this same opinion about us all. <milestone n="2" unit="section"
        />Now, if they conceive that they have charged me with everything that the city has suffered
        at the hands of the Thirty, I consider them to be speakers of no ability; for they have not
        mentioned so much as a small fraction of what has been perpetrated by those men. But if
        their statements imply that I had any connection with those things, I shall prove that their
        words are nothing but lies, and that on my part I behaved as the best citizen in the
        Peiraeus would have done, if he had remained in the city. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>I
        beg you, gentlemen, not to share the views of the slander-mongers. Their business is to
        inculpate even those who have committed no offence, —for it is out of them especially that
        they would make money,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">An inoffensive, peaceable man would
          usually prefer paying an informer blackmail to undergoing the trouble and risk of a legal
          action. Cf. <bibl n="Xen. Mem. 2.9.1">Xen. Mem. 2.9.1</bibl>.</note>—while yours is to
        allow an equal enjoyment of civic rights to those who have done no wrong; for in this way
        you will secure to the established constitution the greatest number of allies. <milestone
          n="4" unit="section"/>And I claim, gentlemen, if I am found to have been the cause of none
        of our disasters, but rather to have performed many services to the State with both my
        person and my purse, that at any rate I should have that support from you which is the just
        desert, not merely of those who have served you well, but also of those who have done you no
        wrong. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Now, I consider that I have a strong justification
        in the fact that, if my accusers were able to convict me of wrongdoing in private life, they
        would not charge me with the misdeeds of the Thirty: they would not see occasion to traduce
        others on the score of what those persons have perpetrated, but only to requite the actual
        wrongdoers. But in fact they conceive that your resentment against those men is sufficient
        to involve in their ruin those who have done no harm at all. <milestone n="6" unit="section"
        />I, however, hold that, just as it would be unfair, when some men have been the source of
        many benefits to the city, to let others carry off the reward of your honors or your thanks,
        so it is unreasonable, when some have continually done you harm, that their acts should
        bring reproach and slander upon those who have done no wrong. The city has enough enemies
        already existing, who count it a great gain to have people brought up on slanderous charges.
          <milestone n="7" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I will now try to explain
        to you who of the citizens are inclined, in my view, to court oligarchy, and who democracy.
        This will serve as a basis both for your decision and for the defence that I shall offer for
        myself; for I shall make it evident that neither under the democracy nor under the oligarchy
        has my conduct suggested any inclination to be disloyal to your people. <milestone n="8"
          unit="section"/>Now, first of all, you should reflect that no human being is naturally
        either an oligarch or a democrat: whatever constitution a man finds advantageous to himself,
        he is eager to see that one established; so it largely depends on you whether the present
        system finds an abundance of supporters. That this is the truth, you will have no difficulty
        in deducing from the events of the past. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>For consider,
        gentlemen of the jury, how many times the leaders of both governments<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">The oligarchy of the Four Hundred and the despotism of the Thirty.</note>
        changed sides. Did not Phrynichus, Peisander and their fellow demagogues, when they had
        committed many offences against you, proceed, in fear of the requital that they deserved, to
        establish the first oligarchy? And did not many of the Four Hundred, again, join in the
        return of the Peiraeus party, while some, on the other hand, who had helped in the expulsion
        of the Four Hundred, actually appeared among the Thirty? Some, too, of those who had
        enlisted for <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName> marched out with you to
        besiege their own comrades! <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>There is thus no difficulty in
        concluding, gentlemen, that the questions dividing men are concerned, not with politics, but
        with their personal advantage. You should therefore apply this test in the probation of your
        citizens: examine their use of the citizenship under the democracy, and inquire whether they
        stood to benefit by a change in the government. In this way you will most justly form your
        decision upon them. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>Now, in my opinion, all those who had
        been disfranchised under the democracy, or deprived of their property, or subjected to any
        other misfortune of the sort, were bound to desire a different system, in the hope that the
        change would be some benefit to themselves. But in the case of those who have done the
        people many good services, and never a single hurt, and who deserve your grateful favors
        instead of punishment for what they have achieved, it is not fair to harbor the slanders
        aimed at them, not even if all who have charge of public affairs allege that they favor
        oligarchy. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now I, gentlemen
        of the jury, never suffered any misfortune during that time,<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">The six years between the restoration of the democracy in <date when="-0410"
            >410</date> B.C. and the tyranny of the Thirty in <date when="-0404">404</date>
          B.C.</note> either private or public, which could lead me, through eagerness to be
        relieved of present ills, to court a change in our system. I have equipped a warship five
        times, fought in four sea-battles, contributed to many war levies, and performed my other
        public services as amply as any citizen. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>But my purpose in
        spending more than was enjoined upon me by the city was to raise myself the higher in your
        opinion, so that if any misfortune should chance to befall me I might defend myself on
        better terms. Of all this credit I was deprived under the oligarchy; for instead of
        regarding those who had bestowed some benefit on the people as worthy recipients of their
        favors, they placed in positions of honor the men who had done you most harm, as though this
        were a pledge by which they held us bound. You ought all to reflect on those facts and
        refuse to believe the statements of these men: you should rather judge each person by the
        record of his actions. <milestone n="14" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>For
        I, gentlemen, was not one of the Four Hundred: I challenge anyone who wishes amongst my
        accusers to come forward and convict me of this. Neither, again, will anyone prove that,
        when the Thirty were established, I sat on the Council or held any office. Surely, if I
        chose not to hold office when I could have done so, I deserve to be honored by you today.
        If, on their part, the men who were in power at that time preferred not to give me a place
        in the government, could I find a more signal proof than this of the falsehood of my
        accusers? <milestone n="15" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Furthermore,
        gentlemen of the jury, you ought also to take account of the rest of my conduct. For amid
        the misfortunes of the city my behavior was such that, if everyone had been of one mind with
        me, not one of you would have experience of a single misfortune. I had no hand during the
        oligarchy, you will find, either in the arrest of anybody, or in taking vengeance upon any
        of my enemies, or in conferring a favor on any of my friends, <milestone n="16"
          unit="section"/>—and in that there is nothing to wonder at, for at that time it was
        difficult to confer favors, though an act of mischief was easy for anyone who wished. Again,
        you will find that I did not place the name of a single Athenian on the black list,<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The Thirty drew up a list of citizens, other than the
          privileged 3000, who were suspected of opposing or disapproving the violent measures of
          the cabal.</note> or obtain a decree of arbitration against anyone, or enrich myself by
        means of your misfortunes. Yet surely, if you are incensed against the authors of your past
        troubles, it is reasonable that those who have done no mischief should stand the higher in
        your opinion. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>And indeed, gentlemen of the jury, I
        consider that I have given the democracy the strongest pledge of my attachment. For if I did
        no mischief at that time, when ample licence for it was allowed, surely I shall now make
        every effort to be a good citizen in the full knowledge that, if I am guilty of wrong, I
        shall incur immediate punishment. But in fact I have continually held to this resolve,
        —under an oligarchy, not to covet the property of others, and under a democracy, to spend my
        own upon you with zeal. <milestone n="18" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I
        consider, gentlemen, that you would not be justified in hating those who have suffered
        nothing under the oligarchy, when you can indulge your wrath against those who have done
        your people mischief; or in regarding as enemies those who did not go into exile instead of
        those who expelled you, or those who were anxious to save their own property instead of
        those who stripped others of theirs, or those who stayed in the city with a view to their
        own safety instead of those who took part in the government for the purpose of destroying
        others. If you think it your duty to destroy the men whom they passed over, not one of the
        citizens will be left to us. <milestone n="19" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"
        />You ought also to take account of this further point, gentlemen of the jury: you are all
        aware that under the previous democracy there were many in the ministry who robbed the
        Treasury; while some accepted bribes at your expense, and others by malicious informations
        estranged your allies.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">For this kind of mischief-making cf.
            <bibl n="Isoc. 15.318">Isoc. 15.318</bibl>.</note> Now, if the Thirty had kept their
        punishments for these cases, you would have held them yourselves to be honest men: but when
        in fact you found them deliberately oppressing the people because of the offences of those
        persons, you were indignant; for you considered it monstrous that the crimes of the few
        should be spread over the whole city. <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>It is not right,
        therefore, that you should resort to those offences which you saw them committing, or regard
        those deeds, which you deemed unjust when done to you, as just when you do them to others.
        No: let your feeling towards us after your restoration be the same as you had towards
        yourselves in your exile; for by this means you will produce the utmost harmony amongst us,
        the power of the city will be at its highest, and you will vote for what will be most
        distressing to your enemies. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"
        />And you should reflect, gentlemen, on the events that have occurred under the Thirty, in
        order that the errors of your enemies may lead you to take better counsel on your own
        affairs. For as often as you heard that the people in the city were all of one mind, you had
        but slight hopes of your return, judging that our concord was the worst of signs for your
        exile: <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>but as soon as you had tidings that the Three
        Thousand were divided by faction, that the rest of the citizens had been publicly banned
        from the city, that the Thirty were not all of one mind, and that those who had fears for
        you outnumbered those who were making war on you, you immediately began to look forward to
        your return and the punishment of your enemies. For it was your prayer to the gods that
        those men should do the things that you saw them doing, since you believed that the villainy
        of the Thirty would be far more useful for your salvation than the resources of the exiles
        for your return. <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>You ought therefore, gentlemen, to take
        the events of the past as your example in resolving on the future course of things, and to
        account those men the best democrats who, desiring your concord, abide by their oaths and
        covenants, because they hold this to be the most effective safeguard of the city and the
        severest punishment of her enemies. For nothing could be more vexatious to them than to
        learn that we are taking part in the government and to perceive at the same time that the
        citizens are behaving as though they had never had any fault to find with each other.
          <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>And you should know, gentlemen, that the exiles desire
        to see the greatest possible number of their fellow citizens not merely slandered but
        disfranchised; since they hope that the men who are wronged by you will be their allies, and
        they would gladly have the venal informers standing high in your esteem and influential in
        the city. For they judge the villainy of those creatures to be their own safeguard.
          <milestone n="25" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>You will do well to
        remember also the events that followed the rule of the Four Hundred<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">June-September, <date when="-0411">411</date> B.C.</note>; for you will fully
        realize that the measures advised by these men have never brought you any advantage, while
        those that I recommend have always profited both parties in the State. You know that
        Epigenes, Demophanes and Cleisthenes, while reaping their personal gains from the city’s
        misfortunes, have inflicted the heaviest losses on the public weal. <milestone n="26"
          unit="section"/>For they prevailed on you to condemn several men to death without trial,
        to confiscate unjustly the property of many more, and to banish and disfranchise other
        citizens; since they were capable of taking money for the release of offenders, and of
        appearing before you to effect the ruin of the innocent. They did not stop until they had
        involved the city in seditions and the gravest disasters, while raising themselves from
        poverty to wealth. <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>But your temper moved you to welcome
        back the exiles, to reinstate the disfranchised in their rights, and to bind yourselves by
        oaths to concord with the rest. At the end of it all, you would have been more pleased to
        punish those who traded in slander under the democracy than those who held office under the
        oligarchy. And with good reason, gentlemen: for it is manifest now to all that the unjust
        acts of rulers in an oligarchy produce democracy, whereas the trade of slanderers in the
        democracy has twice led to the establishment of oligarchy. It is not right, therefore, to
        hearken many times to the counsels of men whose advice has not even once resulted in your
        profit. <milestone n="28" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>And you should
        consider that, in the Peiraeus party, those who are in highest repute, who have run the
        greatest risk, and who have rendered you the most services, had often before exhorted your
        people to abide by their oaths and covenants, since they held this to be the bulwark of
        democracy: for they felt that it would give the party of the town immunity from the
        consequences of the past,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Those who had remained in
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> under the Thirty were for long held
          in suspicion by the restored democrats.</note> and the party of the Peiraeus an assurance
        of the most lasting permanence of the constitution. <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>For
        these are the men whom you would be far more justified in trusting than those who, as
        exiles, owed their deliverance to others and, now that they have returned, are taking up the
        slanderer’s trade. In my opinion, gentlemen of the jury, those among our people remaining in
        the city who shared my views have clearly proved, both under oligarchy and under democracy,
        what manner of citizens they are. <milestone n="30" unit="section"/>But the men who give us
        good cause to wonder what they would have done if they had been allowed to join the Thirty
        are the men who now, in a democracy, imitate those rulers; who have made a rapid advance
        from poverty to wealth, and who hold a number of offices without rendering an account of
        any; who instead of concord have created mutual suspicion, and who have declared war instead
        of peace; and who have caused us to be distrusted by the Greeks. <milestone n="31"
          unit="section"/>Authors of all these troubles and of many more besides, and differing no
        whit from the Thirty, —save that the latter pursued the same ends as theirs during an
        oligarchy, while these men follow their example in a democracy, —they yet make it their
        business to maltreat in this light fashion any person they may wish, as though everyone else
        were guilty, and they had proved themselves men of the highest virtue. <milestone n="32"
          unit="section"/>(Nay, it is not so much they who give cause for wonder as you, who suppose
        that there is a democracy, whereas things are done just as they please, and punishment
        falls, not on those who have injured your people, but on those who refuse to yield their own
        possessions.) And they would sooner have the city diminished than raised to greatness and
        freedom by others: <milestone n="33" unit="section"/>they consider that their perils in the
        Peiraeus give them licence now to do just as they please, while, if later on you obtain
        deliverance through others, they themselves will be swept away, and those others will be
        advanced in power. So they combine to obstruct any efforts that others may make for your
        benefit. <milestone n="34" unit="section"/>But their purpose is readily detected by any
        observer: for they are not anxious to hide themselves, but are rather ashamed not to be
        reputed villains; while you partly see the mischief for yourselves, and partly hear it from
        many other persons. As for us, gentlemen, we consider that you are bound by your duty
        towards all the citizens to abide by your covenants and your oaths: <milestone n="35"
          unit="section"/></p>
      <p>nevertheless, when we see justice done upon the authors of your troubles, we remember your
        former experiences, and condone you; but when you show yourselves openly chastising the
        innocent along with the guilty, by the same vote you will be involving us all in
          suspicion.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">The speaker seems to be accusing the
          democratic leaders of persecuting citizens who had shown oligarchic sympathies and who
          ought now to be protected by the oaths of concord that had been sworn by the two
          parties.</note><gap reason="lost"/><milestone n="Concl" unit="part"/></p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
