<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Second Tetralogy: Prosecution for Accidental Homicide from Speeches</title>
        
        <author>Antiphon</author>
        <editor role="translator">K. J. Maidment</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><idno type="OCLC">5331826</idno><idno type="ISBN">0674993403</idno></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=2">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=3">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=4">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.tetralogy">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Tetralogy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd
      </item></change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Checkmark
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/7/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed tetralogy names and div2s again, prior to importing
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>made some corrections to the SGML
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>also fixed quoted text which had no content, just the attribute.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>15 October 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: antiph_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-10-07 21:00:37  rsingh04
began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

Revision 1.6  2009/06/22 19:41:56  student
edited entity tags CEH

Revision 1.5  2008/11/21 21:38:13  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.4  2008/02/13 19:32:23  lcerrato
fixed incorrect bibl tags

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 21:10:04  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 15:48:40  packel
removed stray item tags

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:27:36  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:14:27  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2000/03/04 20:33:52  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.6  2000/01/28 23:23:50  dasmith
Made ID numbers be the tag content.

Revision 1.5  1999/10/15 23:08:23  dasmith
Make sure we get three sections at a time.

Revision 1.4  1999/10/15 21:20:01  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.


</item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="tetralogy" n="1">
        <head>First speech for the Prosecution</head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p> Cases in which the facts are agreed upon are settled in advance either by the law or
            by the statutes of the Assembly, which between them control every branch of civic life.
            But should matter for dispute occur, it is your task, gentlemen, to give a decision.
            However, I do not imagine that any dispute will in fact arise between the defendant and
            myself. My son was struck in the side by a javelin thrown by yonder lad in the
            gymnasium, and died instantly. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <p>I accuse him not of killing my son deliberately, but of killing him by accident—though
            the loss which I have suffered is not thereby lessened. But if he has not caused the
            dead boy himself disquiet, he has caused disquiet to the living<note anchored="true"
              resp="ed">For <foreign xml:lang="greek">E)NQU/MIOS</foreign> see General
              Introduction.</note>; and I ask you to pity that dead boy's childless parents: to show
            your sorrow for his own untimely end: to forbid his slayer to set foot where he is
            forbidden to set foot by the law<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
                n="Antiph. 6.34">Antiph. 6.34</bibl> ff., <title>On the Choreutes</title>, for the
              meaning of <foreign xml:lang="greek">EI)/RGESQAI TW=N NOMI/MWN</foreign>.</note>: and
            to refuse to allow him to defile the whole city.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="tetralogy" n="2">
        <head>Reply to a Charge of Accidental Homicide</head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p> I now see that sheer misfortune and necessity can force those who hate litigation to
            appear in court and those who love peace to show boldness<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
              >For <foreign xml:lang="greek">TOLMA=N</foreign> used absolutely in this sense cf.
                <bibl n="Antiph. 3.3.2">Antiph. 3.3.2</bibl>.</note> and generally belie their
            nature in word and deed; for I myself, who, unless I am sorely mistaken, am very far
            from finding or wanting to find such a task congenial, have today been forced by sheer
            misfortune to depart from my habits and appear as defendant in a case in which I found
            it hard enough to arrive at the exact truth, but which leaves me still more perplexed
            when I consider how I should present it to you. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <p>I am driven by pitiless necessity: and I, like my opponents, gentlemen of the jury,
            seek refuge in your sympathy. I beg of you: if my arguments appear more subtle than
            those generally presented to you, do not allow the circumstances already mentioned<note
              anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e. the fact that he was not accustomed to appearing in
              courts of law, which should make it a priori probable that he is a simple and
              straightforward man who would not resort to subtleties of argument if his case were a
              sound one.</note> so to prejudice you against my defence as to make you base your
            verdict upon apparent fact instead of upon the truth; apparent fact puts the advantage
            with the clever speaker, but truth with the man who lives in justice and righteousness.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>In training my son in those pursuits from which the state derives most benefit I
            imagined that both of us would be rewarded; but the result has sadly belied my hopes.
            For the lad—not from insolence or wantonness, but while at javelin-practice in the
            gymnasium with his fellows—made a hit, it is true, but killed no one, if one considers
            his true part in the matter<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Two interpretations of the
              text as it stands in the manuscripts are possible: (1) “He threw (his spear), it is
              true, but killed no one”; (2) “He struck (someone), it is true, but did not kill him.”
              (1) gives good sense; but elsewhere in the tetralogy <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >BA/LLEIN</foreign> means “to hit,” not “to throw.” (2) avoids this difficulty; but
              it has been urged (e.g. by Blass, who favors emendation) that the words <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">TO\N ME\N BALO/NTA KAI\ A)POKTEI/NANTA OU)/TE TRW=SAI OU)/TE
                A)POKTEI/NAI/ FHSI</foreign> in <bibl n="Antiph. 3.3.5">Antiph. 3.3.5</bibl> (cf.
              also <bibl n="Antiph. 3.3.6">Antiph. 3.3.6</bibl> sub fin.) prove that the speaker in
              the present passage had not admitted that X struck Y. The contradiction, however, is
              only apparent. The speaker here is saying in effect that the responsibility for the
              blow must rest with Y, although X dealt it; in <bibl n="Antiph. 3.3.5">Antiph.
                3.3.5-6</bibl> his opponents argue that the responsibility must rest with X, because
              X dealt it.</note>: he accidentally<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">A)KOUSI/WS</foreign> cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 2.3.1">Antiph.
                2.3.1</bibl>, note 2.</note> incurred the blame for the error of another which
            affected that other's own person. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="section">
          <p>Had the boy been wounded because the javelin had traveled in his direction outside the
            area appointed for its flight, we should be left unable to show that we had not caused
            his death. But he ran into the path of the javelin and placed his person in its way.
            Hence my son was prevented from hitting the target: while the boy, who moved into the
            javelin's path, was struck, thereby causing us to be blamed for what we did not do. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="section">
          <p>It was because he ran in front of the javelin that the boy was struck. The lad is
            therefore accused without just cause, as he did not strike anyone standing clear of the
            target. At the same time, since it is plain to you that the boy was not struck while
            standing still, but was struck only after deliberately moving into the path of the
            javelin, you have still clearer proof that his death was due to an error on his own
            part. Had he stood still and not run across, he would not have been struck. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Both sides are agreed, as you see, that the boy's death was accidental; so by
            discovering which of the two was guilty of error, we should prove still more
            conclusively who killed him. For it is those guilty of error in carrying out an intended
            act who are responsible for accidents<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The argument is:
              (1) It is agreed that death was accidental. (2) But accidents are always due to
                <foreign xml:lang="greek">A(MARTI/A</foreign> on the part of someone. (3) Therefore
              if the person guilty of <foreign xml:lang="greek">A(MARTI/A</foreign> is discovered,
              we have eo ipso discovered the person responsible for the boy's death.</note>: just as
            it is those who voluntarily do a thing or allow it to be done to them who are
            responsible for the effects suffered. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Now the lad, on his side, was not guilty of error in respect of anyone: in practising
            he was not doing what he was forbidden but what he had been told to do, and he was not
            standing among those engaged in gymnastics when he threw the javelin, but in his place
            among the other throwers: nor did he hit the boy because he missed the target and sent
            his javelin instead at those standing clear. He did everything correctly, as he
            intended; and thus he was not the cause of any accident, but the victim of one, in that
            he was prevented from hitting the target. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>The boy, on the other hand, who wished to run forward, missed the moment at which he
            could have crossed without being hit, with results which he by no means desired. He was
            accidentally guilty of an error which affected his own person, and has thus met with a
            disaster for which he had himself alone to thank. He has punished himself for his error,
            and is therefore duly requited; not that we rejoice at or approve of it—far from it: we
            feel both sympathy and sorrow.</p>
          <p>It is thus the dead boy who proves to have been guilty of error; so the act which
            caused his death is to be attributed not to us, but to him, the party guilty of error:
            just as the recoiling of its effects upon the agent not only absolves us from blame, but
            has caused the agent to be punished as he deserved directly his error was committed.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Furthermore, our innocence is attested by the law upon which my accuser relies in
            charging me with the boy's death, the law which forbids the taking of life whether
            wrongfully or otherwise. For the fact that the victim himself was guilty of error clears
            the defendant here of having killed him by accident: while his accuser does not even
            suggest that he killed him deliberately. Thus he is cleared of both charges, of killing
            the boy by accident and of killing him deliberately. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="10" type="section">
          <p>Not only do the true facts of the case and the law under which he is being prosecuted
            attest my son's innocence; but our manner of life is equally far from justifying such
            harsh treatment of us. Not only will it be an outrage, if my son is to bear the blame
            for errors which he did not commit; but I myself, who am equally innocent, though
            assuredly not more so, will be visited with woes many times more bitter. Once my son is
            lost, I shall pass the rest of my days longing for death: once I am left childless, mine
            will be a life within the tomb. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="11" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Have pity, then, on this child, the victim of calamity, though guilty of no error: and
            have pity on me, an old man in distress, stricken thus suddenly with sorrow. Do not
            bring a miserable fate upon us by condemning us: but show that you fear God by
            acquitting us. The dead boy is not unavenged for the calamity which befell him: nor
            ought we ourselves to share the responsibility for errors due to our accusers. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="12" type="section">
          <p>So respect the righteousness which the facts before you have revealed: respect justice:
            and acquit us as godly and just men should. Do not bring upon a father and a son, two of
            the most wretched of beings, sorrows which the years of neither can well bear.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="tetralogy" n="3">
        <head>Second Speech for the Prosecution</head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p> That sheer necessity can force all men to belie their nature in both word and deed is
            a fact of which the defendant seems to me to be giving very real proof. Whereas in the
            past he was the last to show impudence or audacity, his very misfortune has today forced
            him to say things which I for one would never have expected of him. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <p>I, in my great folly, imagined that he would not reply; otherwise I would not have
            deprived myself of half of my opportunities as prosecutor by making only one speech
            instead of two; and he, but for his audacity, would not have had the twofold advantage
            over me of using one speech to answer the one speech for the prosecution and making his
            accusations when they could not be answered.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">I take the
              speaker to mean: “The case seemed so simple that instead of developing any argument in
              my first speech for the prosecution, I merely stated the bare facts. The defendant,
              however, has made an elaborate reply, and will doubtless do the same again in his
              second speech; this is equivalent to his making two speeches to my one. Further, he
              will be able to use his second speech to answer my one serious speech for the
              prosecution (<foreign xml:lang="greek">E(/NA PRO\S E(/NA LO/GON
                A)POLOGHQEI/S</foreign>); while I cannot effectively answer the attack which he made
              upon me in his first speech (<foreign xml:lang="greek">A(\ KATHGO/RHSEN A)NAPOKRI/TWS
                EI)PW/N</foreign>), because, as prosecutor, I must now devote myself to attacking
              him.”</note>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>With his great advantage over us in the matter of the speeches, and with the far
            greater one which his methods have given him in addition,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
              >Referring apparently to the artifices employed by the defence for working upon the
              feelings of the court (cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 3.2.1">Antiph. 3.2.1</bibl> ff.).</note>
            it is outrageous that the accused should entreat you to listen kindly to his defence. I
            myself, on the other hand, far from causing any harm, have been the victim of cruel
            affliction, and am today being treated still more cruelly. It is as one who seeks more
            than a pretended refuge in your sympathy that I make my own request of you. You who take
            vengeance for unrighteous deeds and determine wherein is righteousness, do not, I beg of
            you, let worthless subtleties of speech induce you to disregard plain facts and treat
            the truth as false; </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="section">
          <p>for such subtleties result in a tale more plausible than true, whereas the truth, when
            told, will be less guileful and therefore less convincing.</p>
          <p>My faith in justice, then, enables me to despise his defence. Yet my distrust of the
            pitiless will of fate makes me fear that I may not only lose the benefit of my child,
            but that I may see him convicted by you of taking his own life in addition. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="section">
          <p>For the defendant has had the audacity and shamelessness to say that he who struck and
            killed neither wounded nor killed, whereas he who neither touched the javelin nor had
            any intention of throwing it missed every other point on earth and every other person,
            and pierced his own side with the javelin. Why, I should myself sound more convincing, I
            think, were I accusing the lad of willful murder, than does the defendant in claiming
            that the lad neither struck nor killed. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>My son was bidden at that moment by the master in charge, who was taking the javelins
            of the throwers into his keeping, to pick them up; but thanks to the wantonness of him
            who cast it, he was greeted by yonder lad's cruel weapon; though guilty of error in
            respect of no single person, he died a piteous death. The lad, on the other hand, who
            mistook the moment at which the javelins were being picked up, was not prevented from
            making a hit. To my bitter sorrow, he struck a target; and although he did not kill my
            son deliberately, there are better grounds for maintaining that he did than for
            asserting that he neither struck nor killed. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Although it was by accident that they killed my son, the effects were the same as those
            of willful murder. Yet they deny that they killed him at all, and even maintain that
            they are not amenable to the law which forbids the taking of life whether wrongfully or
            otherwise. Then who did throw the javelin? To whom is the boy's death in fact to be
            attributed? To the spectators or the masters in charge—whom no one accuses at all? The
            circumstances of my son's death are no mystery: to me, for one, they are only too clear;
            and I maintain that the law is right when it orders the punishment of those who have
            taken life; not only is it just that he who killed without meaning to kill should suffer
            punishment which he did not mean to incur; but it would also be an injustice to the
            victim, whose injury is not lessened by being accidental, were he deprived of vengeance.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Nor does he deserve acquittal because of his misfortune in committing the error which
            he did. If, on the one hand, the misfortune is not due to any dispensation of heaven,
            then, as an error pure and simple, it is right that it should prove disastrous to him
            who was guilty of it; and if, on the other hand, a defilement from heaven has fallen
            upon the slayer by reason of some act of sin, then it is wrong for us to impede the
            visitation of God.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">i.e. it might be argued that the lad
              was <foreign xml:lang="greek">A)TUXH/S</foreign> in committing the <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">A(MARTI/A</foreign> which he did, and therefore deserves acquittal.
              But the prosecution produces a dilemma: (a) If the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >A)TUXI/A</foreign> was a piece of divine retribution for some past offence, he
              deserves punishment all the more, as it is God's will that he should be punished. (b)
              If it is not due to God, then to say that the lad was the victim of <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">A)TUXI/A</foreign> is only a more polite way of saying that he was
              guilty of <foreign xml:lang="greek">A(MARTI/A</foreign>(<foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >A(MA/RTHMA OU)=SA</foreign>), and we are back where we started.</note>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>They also maintained that it is wrong for those who have lived as honorably as they to
            be treated with severity. But what of us? Should we be treated aright, if we are
            punished with death when our life has been as praiseworthy as theirs?</p>
          <p>When he argues that he is not guilty of error and claims that the consequences must be
            borne by those who are, instead of being diverted to the innocent, he is pleading our
            case for us. Not only would it be an injustice to my son, who was killed by yonder lad,
            though guilty of error in respect of no one, were he deprived of vengeance; but it will
            be an outrage, if I myself, who am even more guiltless than he, fail to obtain from you
            the recompense which the law assigns me. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="10" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Further, the defence's own statements show that the accused cannot be acquitted either
            of error or of accidentally taking life, but that he and my son are equally guilty of
            both; I will prove this.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">An attempt to show the two-edged
              character of the arguments used by the defence. “If,” say the prosecution, “the dead
              boy has been proved guilty by the defence, then eo ipso the lad has been proved guilty
              too.”</note> Assume that because my son moved into the path of the javelin instead of
            standing still, he deserves to be treated as his own slayer. Then the lad is not free
            from blame either; he is only innocent if he was standing still and not throwing his
            javelin when the boy was killed. The boy's death was therefore due to both of them. Now
            the boy, whose error affected his own person, has punished himself even more harshly
            than that error warranted: for he has lost his life. So what right has his accomplice,
            who joined him in committing his unfortunate error, to escape unpunished? </p>
        </div>
        <div n="11" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>The accused have themselves proved by their defence that the lad had a share in the
            slaying. So, as just and god-fearing men, you cannot acquit him. If we, who have lost
            our life through the defendants' error, were found guilty of having taken it ourselves,
            it would be an act not of righteousness but of wickedness on your part: and if those
            responsible for our death were not prohibited from setting foot where they should not,
            [;it would be an outrage against heaven:];<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The passive of
                <foreign xml:lang="greek">EU)SEBEI=N</foreign>, while exceedingly rare (it occurs
              otherwise only at [;Plato,]; <title>Axiochus</title> 4, as far as I know), might be
              supported here by the parallel use of the passive of <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >A)SEBEI=N</foreign> in the phrase <foreign xml:lang="greek">TOU\S A)/NW QEOU\S
                A)SEBEI=SQAI</foreign>, <bibl n="Lys. 2.7">Lys. 2.7</bibl>. But <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">EU)SEBOI=NT' A)/N</foreign> could only mean “would be reverenced”;
              and that clearly gives an impossible sense to the passage, which requires something
              like “would be rendered <foreign xml:lang="greek">EU)SEBEI=S</foreign>,” or “would be
              treated as <foreign xml:lang="greek">EU)SE/BEIA</foreign> requires,” if it is to be
              intelligible. Conceivably there is a lacuna before <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >EU)SEBOI=NT' A)/N</foreign>, which might be filled by <foreign xml:lang="greek">TA\
                A)/CIA A)\N FE/ROINTO TH=S AU(TW=N A(MARTI/AS: OU)DE\ AU)= AU)TOI\ OI(
                QEOI\</foreign> or something similar, giving <foreign xml:lang="greek">EU)SEBOI=NT'
                A)/N</foreign> the subject it requires. But this would destroy the balance of the
              two halves of the sentence as they stand in the manuscripts; and it is more probable
              that the words <foreign xml:lang="greek">EU)SEBOI=NT' A)/N</foreign> are themselves
              corrupt.</note> you would have acquitted persons stained with guilt.</p>
          <p>As the whole of the defilement, upon whomsoever it rests, is extended to you, you must
            take the greatest care. If you find him guilty and prohibit him from setting foot where
            the law forbids him to set foot, you will be free of the charges brought today; but if
            you acquit him, you become liable to them. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="12" type="section">
          <p>So satisfy the claims of heaven and the laws by taking him and punishing him. Do not
            share his blood-guilt yourselves: but let me, the parent whom he has sent to a living
            death, at least appear to have had my sorrow lightened.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="tetralogy" n="4">
        <head>Second Speech for the Defense</head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p>While it is only to be expected that the preoccupation of my opponent with his speech
            for the prosecution should prevent his understanding my defence, the same is not true of
            yourselves. You should bear in mind that while we, the interested parties, take a
            biassed view of the case, each naturally thinking that his own version of it is fair,
            your duty is to consider the facts conscientiously; and so you must give your attention
            to me as much as you did to him<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The addition of this
              sentence is necessary for a proper understanding of the connection of thought. The
                <foreign xml:lang="greek">GA/R</foreign> is explanatory of the words <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">U(MA=S DE\ XRH/</foreign> in section 1.</note>: </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <p>as it is in what is said that the true facts are to be sought. For my part, if I have
            told any falsehoods, I am content that you should treat the truth which I have spoken as
            itself a piece of equally dishonest pleading. On the other hand, if my arguments have
            been honest, but close and subtle, it is not I who used them, but he whose conduct made
            them necessary, upon whom the displeasure which they have caused should properly fall.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>I would have you understand to begin with that it requires not mere assertion, but
            proof, to show that someone has killed someone else. Now our accuser agrees with us as
            to how the accident happened, but disagrees as to the person responsible; yet it is only
            from what happened that that person can be determined. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="section">
          <p>He complains bitterly, because, according to him, it is a slur upon his son's memory
            that he should have been proved a slayer when he neither threw the javelin nor had any
            intention of doing so. That complaint is not an answer to my arguments. I am not
            maintaining that his son threw the javelin or struck himself. I am maintaining that
            since he moved within range of the javelin, his death was due not to the lad, but to
            himself; for he was not killed standing in his place. As this running across was his
            undoing, it follows that if it was at his master's summons that he ran across, the
            master would be the person responsible for his death<note anchored="true" resp="ed">It
              is at first sight odd that so little is made of the part played by the <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">PAIDOTRI/BHS</foreign>, who would be a vitally important witness,
              were the case being tried in a modern court of law. But it should not be forgotten
              that the writer is throughout endeavoring to exhibit the possibilities of the <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">PI/STIS E)/NTEXNOS</foreign> as such. See General
              Introduction.</note>; but if he moved into the way of his own accord, his death was
            due to himself. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Before proceeding to any further argument, I wish to show still more clearly which of
            the two was responsible for the accident. The lad no more missed the target than any of
            those practising with him<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A highly artificial piece of
              sophistry. (1) The lad did exactly the same as the other throwers: so, as they did not
              miss the target, neither can he have done. (2) On the other hand, the boy did not do
              the same as the other spectators; and so he is not blameless, as they are.</note>: nor
            has he rendered himself guilty of any of the acts with which he is charged owing to
            error on his own part. On the other hand, the boy did not do the same as the other
            onlookers; he moved into the javelin's path. And this is clear proof that it was through
            his own error that he met with a disaster which those who stood still did not. The
            thrower would not have been guilty of an error in any respect,<note anchored="true"
              resp="ed">A curious admission that the <foreign xml:lang="greek">MEIRA/KION</foreign>
              was guilty of <foreign xml:lang="greek">A(MARTI/A</foreign> to at least some
              extent.</note> had no one moved into the path of his spear: while the boy would not
            have been hit, had he remained in his place among the onlookers. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Further, my son was not more concerned in the boy's death than any one of those
            throwing javelins with him, as I will show. If it was owing to the fact that my son was
            throwing a javelin that the boy was killed, then all those practising with him must
            share in the guilt of the deed, as it was not owing to their failure to throw that they
            did not strike him, but owing to the fact that he did not move into the path of the
            javelin of any one of them. Similarly the young man, who was no more guilty of error
            than they, would not have hit the boy any more than they did, had the boy stood still
            with the onlookers. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>Again, not only was the boy guilty of the error committed; he was also to blame for the
            failure to take due precautions. My son saw no one running across, so how could he have
            taken precautions against striking anyone? The boy, on the other hand, upon seeing the
            throwers, might easily have guarded against running across, as he was quite at liberty
            to remain standing still. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>The law which they quote is a praiseworthy one; it is right and fair that it should
            visit those who have killed without meaning to do so with chastisement which they did
            not mean to incur. But the lad is not guilty of error; and it would therefore be unjust
            that he should suffer for him who is. It is enough that he should bear the consequences
            of his own errors. On the other hand, the boy, who perished through his own error,
            punished himself as soon as he had committed that error. And as the slayer has been
            punished, the slaying has not gone unavenged. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="section">
          <p/>
          <p>The slayer has paid the penalty; so it is not by acquitting us, but by condemning us
            that you will leave a burden upon your consciences. The boy, who is bearing the
            consequence of his own error, will leave behind him nothing that calls for atonement
            from anyone; but if my son, who is innocent, is put to death, the conscience of those
            who have condemned him will be more heavily burdened than ever.</p>
          <p>If the arguments put forward prove the dead boy his own slayer, it is not we who have
            stated them whom he has to thank, but the fact that the accident happened as it did.
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="10" type="section">
          <p>Since examination proves beyond doubt that the boy was his own slayer, the law absolves
            us from blame, and condemns him who was guilty. See, then, that we are not plunged into
            woes which we do not deserve, and that you yourselves do not defy the powers above by a
            verdict succoring my opponents in their misfortunes. Remember, as righteousness and
            justice require you to do, that the accident was caused by him who moved into the
            javelin's path. Remember, and acquit us; for we are not guilty of his death.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
