<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Odes (English). Machine readable text - I.</title>
                <author>Pindar</author>
                <editor role="translator">Diane Arnson Svarlien</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>


            <notesStmt>
                <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"> Diane Arnson Svarlien typed in her
                    translation. Basic SGML tagging by EM </note>
            </notesStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <bibl default="false">
                    <title>Odes</title>
                    <author>Pindar</author>
                    <editor role="translator">Diane Arnson Svarlien</editor>
                    <date>1990</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <editorialDecl default="false">
                <correction default="false" status="high" method="silent">
                    <p> professional data entry</p>
                </correction>
            </editorialDecl>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="book"/>
                <refState unit="poem"/>
                <refState unit="line"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
                <language ident="latin">Latin</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>8/9</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Ted Armstrong</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Proofread for typos.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>1990</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EM and SFSH</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Make sure that the file matches new DTDs.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>8/91</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>EM</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Revise DTDs and recheck texts.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>9/91</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>WPM</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Entered Hubbard's revisions.</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>11/91</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>WPM</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Entered Svarlien's responses to Hubbard.</item>
            </change>
        -->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="book" n="I.">
                <head>Isthmian Odes</head>
                <p/>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="poem" n="1">
                    <head>
                        <title>Isthmian 1</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Herodotus of Thebes</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Chariot Race</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0458">458</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> My mother, Thebe of the golden shield, I shall place your interests
                        above my lack of leisure. May rocky <placeName key="perseus,Delos"
                            >Delos</placeName> , in whose praises I have poured myself out, not be
                        indignant at me. </l>
                    <l n="5"> What is dearer to good men than their noble parents? Yield, island of
                        Apollo; indeed, with the help of the gods I shall accomplish the end of both
                        graceful songs, <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="7"> honoring in the dance both Phoebus with the unshorn hair, in
                        wave-washed <placeName key="tgn,7010867">Ceos</placeName> with its mariners,
                        and the sea-dividing reef of the Isthmus.</l>
                    <l n="10"> Since the Isthmus gave to the people of Cadmus six garlands from her
                        games, the glory of triumph for my fatherland, where Alcmena bore her
                        fearless <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="13"> son, before whom the bold hounds of Geryon once trembled. But I,
                        while I frame for Herodotus a prize of honor for his four-horse chariot, </l>
                    <l n="15"> and for managing the reins with his own hands and not another's, want
                        to join him to the song of Castor or of Iolaus, for of all heroes they were
                        the strongest charioteers, the one born in <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
                            >Sparta</placeName> and the other in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> . <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="18"> And in the games they attempted the greatest number of contests, and
                        adorned their homes with tripods</l>
                    <l n="20"> and caldrons and goblets of gold, tasting victorious garlands. Their
                        excellence shines clearly, in the naked footraces and in the shield-clashing
                        hoplite races, <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="24"> and in all the deeds of their hands, in flinging the spear </l>
                    <l n="25"> and whenever they hurled the stone discus. For there was no
                        pentathlon, but for each feat a separate prize was set up. Often crowning
                        their hair with wreaths from these contests they appeared beside the streams
                        of Dirce or near the Eurotas, <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="30"> </l>
                    <l n="30"> the son of Iphicles, who was of the same city as the race of the Sown
                        Men, and the son of Tyndareus, dwelling among the Achaeans in his highland
                        home of Therapne. Farewell. But I, arraying with song Poseidon and the
                        sacred Isthmus and the shores of Onchestus, shall tell, along with the
                        honors of this man, the very famous fortune of his father Asopodorus
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="35"> </l>
                    <l n="35"> and of his ancestral land of Orchomenus, which received him from the
                        boundless sea when he was hard-pressed by shipwreck, in chilly misfortune.
                        But now once more his hereditary fortune has embarked him on </l>
                    <l n="40"> the fair weather of the old days. And he who has suffered toils gains
                        foresight in his mind. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="41"> If a man has devoted his whole spirit to excellence, sparing neither
                        expense nor toils, it is right to grant the boast of manliness to those who
                        achieve excellence, with an ungrudging </l>
                    <l n="45"> mind. For it is an easy gift for a skilled man to speak words of
                        praise in recompense for labors of all kinds and thus to promote the common
                        good. <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="47"> Different wages for different deeds are sweet to men, to the shepherd
                        and the ploughman and the bird-trapper, and the man whom the sea nourishes.
                        Every man is intent upon keeping persistent famine from his belly. </l>
                    <l n="50"> But he who wins rich renown in the games or in war receives the
                        highest gain: to be well spoken of by his fellow-citizens and by strangers,
                        the choicest bloom of speech. <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="52"> For us it is right to celebrate the earth-shaking son of Cronus,
                        returning a good deed to our beneficent neighbor, the lord of horse-racing
                        and chariots; </l>
                    <l n="55"> and to invoke your sons, Amphitryon, and the secluded valley of
                        Minyas, and <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName> , the
                        famous precinct of Demeter, and <placeName key="tgn,7002677"
                            >Euboea</placeName> , when we speak of curving race-courses. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="58"> Protesilas, I add besides your sacred ground in <placeName
                            key="perseus,Phylace">Phylace</placeName> , the home of Achaean men. </l>
                    <l n="60"> But the brief limits of my song prevent me from telling of all the
                        victories that Hermes, lord of games, granted to Herodotus and his horses.
                        Truly, often that which is hushed in silence actually brings greater
                        pleasure. <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="64"> May he, raised up on the splendid wings of the Pierian Muses with
                        their lovely voices, </l>
                    <l n="65"> also arm his hand with wreaths from <placeName key="tgn,7010770"
                            >Pytho</placeName> , with exquisite wreaths from the Alpheus and the
                        Olympian games, thus winning glory for seven-gated Thebes. But if someone
                        hoards hidden wealth at home, and attacks others with mockery, he fails to
                        consider that he is giving up his soul to Hades without glory. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="poem" n="2">
                    <head>
                        <title>Isthmian 2</title>
                        <persName type="winner">In memory of the victories of Xenocrates of
                            Acragas</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Chariot Race</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0470">470</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> The men of old, Thrasybulus, who mounted the chariot of the Muses with
                        their golden headbands, joining the glorious lyre, lightly shot forth their
                        honey-voiced songs for young men, if one was handsome and had </l>
                    <l n="5"> the sweetest ripeness that brings to mind Aphrodite on her lovely
                        throne. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="6"> For in those days the Muse was not yet a lover of gain, nor did she
                        work for hire. And sweet gentle-voiced odes did not go for sale, with
                        silvered faces, from honey-voiced Terpsichore. But as things are now, she
                        bids us heed </l>
                    <l n="10"> the saying of the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName>
                        man, which comes closest to actual truth: <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="11"> “Money, money makes the man,” he said, when he lost his wealth and
                        his friends at the same time. But enough, for you are wise. I sing the
                        Isthmian victory with horses, not unrecognized, which Poseidon granted to
                        Xenocrates, </l>
                    <l n="15"> and sent him a garland of Dorian wild celery for his hair, to have
                        himself crowned, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="17"> thus honoring the man of the fine chariot, the light of the people of
                        Acragas. And in <placeName key="tgn,7018211">Crisa</placeName> widely
                        powerful Apollo looked graciously on him, and gave him glory there as well.
                        And joined with the renowned favors of the sons of Erechtheus </l>
                    <l n="20"> in splendid Athens, he found no fault with the chariot-preserving
                        hand of the man who drove his horses, <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="22"> the hand with which Nicomachus gave the horses full rein at the right
                        moment—that driver whom the heralds of the seasons, the Elean truce-bearers
                        of Zeus son of Cronus recognized, since they had no doubt experienced some
                        hospitable act of friendship from him. </l>
                    <l n="25"> And with sweet-breathing voice they greeted him when he fell into the
                        lap of golden Victory <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="27"> in their own land, which they call the precinct of Olympian Zeus,
                        where the sons of Aenesidamus were linked with immortal honors. </l>
                    <l n="30"> Truly, Thrasybulus, the homes of your family are not unfamiliar with
                        lovely victory-processions, nor with the sweet boasting of songs. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="33"> For it is no hill to climb, nor is the road steep, if one brings the
                        honors of the Heliconian Muses to the homes of famous men. </l>
                    <l n="35"> Having hurled the discus far, may I fling my javelin as far beyond
                        all others, as Xenocrates obtained a sweet temper surpassing all men. He was
                        honored in his townsmen's company, <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="38"> and he upheld the raising of horses according to the customs of all
                        Greeks. He also welcomed all the banquets for the gods, </l>
                    <l n="40"> and the force of the blowing wind never made him furl his sail around
                        his hospitable table; he journeyed as far as <placeName key="tgn,7012263"
                            >Phasis</placeName> in the summer, and in the winter sailed to the banks
                        of the <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName> . <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="43"> Now, although envious hopes beset the minds of mortals, let him never
                        hush in silence either his father's excellence </l>
                    <l n="45"> or these songs. For I did not fashion them to stand idle. Give this
                        message, Nicasippus, when you come across my trusty friend. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="poem" n="3">
                    <head>
                        <title>Isthmian 3</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Melissus of Thebes</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race"> Chariot Race at <placeName key="perseus,Nemea"
                                >Nemea</placeName>
                        </seg>
                        <date>?474/3</date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> If any man has good fortune, either in famous contests or by the
                        strength of his wealth, yet restrains troublesome ambition in his mind, he
                        is worthy to be joined with his townsmen's praises. Zeus, great excellence
                        attends on mortals </l>
                    <l n="5"> from you. Greater prosperity lives with those who revere you; but it
                        does not keep company with crooked minds, flourishing equally for all time.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="7"> As a recompense for glorious deeds, it is right to celebrate a noble
                        man, and it is right to exalt him in victory-songs with the gentle Graces.
                        Yes, in two contests Melissus </l>
                    <l n="10"> has had a share of good fortune, to turn his heart to sweet
                        joyfulness; he received garlands in the glens of the Isthmus, and in the
                        valley of the deep-chested lion he had <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                            >Thebes</placeName> announced <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="13"> when he was victorious in horse-racing. He does not dishonor the
                        inborn excellence he has from his ancestors. </l>
                    <l n="15"> Surely you know of the ancient glory of Cleonymus in the
                        chariot-races. And, being related to the Labdacids on their mother's side,
                        they followed a path of wealth with the toil of their four-horse teams. But
                        the whirling days of a man's lifetime change many things. Only the children
                        of the gods are unwounded. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="poem" n="4">
                    <head>
                        <title>Isthmian 4</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Melissus of Thebes</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Pancratium</seg>
                        <date>?474/3</date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Thanks to the gods, I have countless paths opening on every side;
                        Melissus, at the Isthmian games you revealed abundant resources for
                        celebrating in song the excellence of your family, in which the sons of
                        Cleonymus flourish perpetually, </l>
                    <l n="5"> with a god's favor, as they progress towards the mortal end of life.
                        But a changeable wind sweeps down and drives all men at different times.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="7"> These men truly are spoken of as honored in Thebes from the beginning;
                        they have good relations with the neighboring towns, and are bereft of loud
                        arrogance. And as for the memorials that fly through all the world, </l>
                    <l n="10"> memorials of boundless fame for living and dead men, they have
                        attained all of these in full. Through their manly deeds they reached from
                        home to touch the farthest limit, the pillars of Heracles— <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="13"> do not pursue excellence any farther than that! And they became
                        breeders of horses </l>
                    <l n="15"> and were pleasing to bronze-clad Ares. But on a single day the rough
                        storm of war robbed their blessed hearth of four men. Now, after the wintry
                        gloom of the changing months, the ground has blossomed as if with crimson
                        roses <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="19"> by the will of the gods. The shaker of the earth who dwells at
                        Onchestus </l>
                    <l n="20"> and at the sea-bridge before the walls of Corinth, by offering to
                        that family this marvellous song, wakes from her bed their ancient fame for
                        glorious deeds. For she had fallen asleep, but now she has awakened and her
                        body shines, marvellous to see, like the morning-star among other stars.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="25"> </l>
                    <l n="25"> She proclaimed their chariot victorious on the high ground of Athens
                        and also in <placeName key="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName> at the games of
                        Adrastus, and thus gave them leaves of song, like these, from the singers of
                        their time. Nor did they keep their curved chariot from competing in the
                        general contests; striving against all of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
                            >Greece</placeName> , they rejoiced in spending their wealth on their
                        horses.</l>
                    <l n="30"> Those who attempt nothing face silence and obscurity, <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="31"> and fortune remains hidden even to those who contend, until they
                        reach the final goal. For she dispenses from this side and from that, and
                        the skill of weaker men </l>
                    <l n="35"> can overtake and trip up a stronger man. Indeed, you know of the
                        bloodstained might of Aias, which late at night he pierced by falling on his
                        own sword, thus bringing blame on all the sons of the Greeks who went to
                            <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> . <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="37"> But he is honored throughout the world by Homer, who set the record
                        right concerning all his excellence and told it with the staff of his divine
                        words, for posterity to play.</l>
                    <l n="40"> For if one says something well, that saying goes forth speaking with
                        an immortal voice. And the radiance of fine deeds, forever unquenchable, has
                        crossed the fruitful earth and the sea. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"
                        />
                    </l>
                    <l n="43"> May we win the favor of the Muses and kindle that torch of song, a
                        worthy garland from the pancratium</l>
                    <l n="45"> for Melissus, too, the scion of the race of Telesias. For in the toil
                        of conflict he resembles the spirit of loud-roaring lions in boldness, while
                        in wisdom he is like the fox, who forestalls the swoop of the eagle by
                        falling on her back. And it is right to do anything to blot out one's enemy.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="49"> For Melissus was not allotted the nature of Orion; </l>
                    <l n="50"> he is negligible to look at, though heavy to grapple with in his
                        strength. And yet once there went from Thebes, Cadmus' city, a hero short in
                        stature but unflinching in spirit. This hero went to the house of Antaeus in
                        grain-bearing <placeName key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName> , to keep him
                        from roofing Poseidon's temple with the skulls of strangers, <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="55"> </l>
                    <l n="55"> Alcmena's son. He went to <placeName key="tgn,7011019"
                            >Olympus</placeName> , after he had explored all lands and the
                        high-cliffed hollow of the gray sea, and had tamed the straits for sailors.
                        Now he dwells beside aegis-bearing Zeus, and has the most beautiful
                        prosperity. He is honored as a friend by the immortals and is married to
                        Hebe; </l>
                    <l n="60"> he is lord of a golden house, and son-in-law to Hera. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="61"> For him, above the Electran gates, we Thebans, busily preparing the
                        feast and the circle of newly-built altars, pile up burnt offerings in honor
                        of the eight bronze-clad men, now dead, the sons whom <placeName
                            key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName> , Creon's daughter, bore him. </l>
                    <l n="65"> For them the flame rises in the rays of the setting sun and blazes
                        all night long, prodding the air with fragrant smoke. <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="67"> And on the second day is that struggle of strength, the final event
                        of the annual games. And there, his head wreathed with white </l>
                    <l n="70"> myrtle, this man showed forth a double victory, having won before in
                        the boy's contest by heeding the wise advice of his helmsman and trainer,
                        Orseas. I will honor him together with Orseas in my victory-song, pouring
                        delightful grace on both. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="poem" n="5">
                    <head>
                        <title>Isthmian 5</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Phylacidas of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Pancratium</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0478">478</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Mother of the Sun, Theia of many names, for your sake men honor gold
                        as more powerful than anything else;</l>
                    <l n="5"> and through the value you bestow on them, o queen, ships contending on
                        the sea and yoked teams of horses in swift-whirling contests become marvels.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="7"> And in athletic contests, someone who has wreathed his hair with many
                        garlands has achieved longed-for fame, when he has been victorious with his
                        hands </l>
                    <l n="10"> or with the swiftness of his feet. But the valor of men is judged by
                        gods, and there are only two things that cultivate the sweetest flower of
                        life in blossoming prosperity: <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="13"> to have good fortune and a noble reputation. Do not seek to become
                        Zeus; you have everything, </l>
                    <l n="15"> if a share of these fine things comes to you. Mortal aims befit
                        mortal men. But for you, Phylacidas, flourishing twofold excellence is
                        recorded at the Isthmus, and at <placeName key="perseus,Nemea"
                            >Nemea</placeName> for both you and Pytheas in the pancratium. But my
                        heart </l>
                    <l n="20"> cannot taste songs without telling of the race of Aeacus. I have come
                        with the Graces for the sons of Lampon <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"
                        />
                    </l>
                    <l n="22"> to this well-governed city. If Aegina turns her steps to the clear
                        road of god-given deeds, then do not grudge </l>
                    <l n="25"> to mix for her in song a boast that is fitting recompense for toils.
                        In heroic times, too, fine warriors gained fame, and they are celebrated
                        with lyres and flutes in full-voiced harmonies <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="28"> for time beyond reckoning. Heroes who are honored by the grace of
                        Zeus provide a theme for skilled poets:</l>
                    <l n="30"> among the Aetolians the brave sons of Oeneus are worshipped with
                        shining sacrifices; in <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>
                        the horseman Iolaus has his honor, and Perseus in <placeName
                            key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> , and the spearman Castor together
                        with Polydeuces by the streams of Eurotas. <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="34"> But in Oenone the honors belong to the great-hearted spirits </l>
                    <l n="35"> of Aeacus and his sons. Twice in battles they sacked the city of the
                        Trojans: the first time following Heracles, the second time the sons of
                        Atreus. Now, drive me into the air! Tell me, who killed Cycnus, and who
                        Hector,</l>
                    <l n="40"> and the fearless commander of the Ethiopians, bronze-armed Memnon?
                        Who wounded noble Telephus with his spear by the banks of Caïcus? <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="43"> Men whose voices name the outstanding island of Aegina as their
                        fatherland, built long ago </l>
                    <l n="45"> as a tower for lofty excellence to ascend. My swift tongue has many
                        arrows, to shout the praises of these heroes. And now the city of Aias,
                        Salamis, could testify that she was saved by her sailors in Ares'
                        confrontation <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="49"> in the destructive storm sent by Zeus, </l>
                    <l n="50"> when slaughter poured like hail on countless men. Nevertheless,
                        quench this boast in silence. Zeus dispenses both good and bad, Zeus the
                        master of all. But such honors as these also welcome the joy of triumph,
                        covered with the delicious honey of song. Let a man strive and contend
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="55"> </l>
                    <l n="55"> in the games when he has learned from the race of Cleonicus. The long
                        toil of their men is not hidden in blind darkness, nor has thought of the
                        expense fretted away their devotion to their hopes. I praise Pytheas also
                        among limb-subduing pancratiasts, </l>
                    <l n="60"> skillful with his hands in guiding straight the course of Phylacidas'
                        blows, and with a mind to match. Take a garland for him, and bring him a
                        fillet of fine wool, and send along this winged new song. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="poem" n="6">
                    <head>
                        <title>Isthmian 6</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Phylacidas of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Pancratium</seg>
                        <date> ?484 or <date when="-0480">480</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Just as we mix the second bowl of wine when the men's symposium is
                        flourishing, here is the second song of the Muses for Lampon's children and
                        their athletic victories: first in Nemea, Zeus, in your honor they received
                        the choicest of garlands, </l>
                    <l n="5"> and now in honor of the lord of the Isthmus and the fifty Nereids, for
                        the victory of the youngest son, Phylacidas. May there be a third libation
                        of honey-voiced songs to pour over Aegina in honor of Zeus Soter of Olympia.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="10"> </l>
                    <l n="10"> For if a man, rejoicing in expense and toil, achieves godly
                        excellence, and a divinity sows the seed of lovely fame in him, then he
                        already casts his anchor on the farthest shore of prosperity, since he is
                        honored by the gods. The son of Cleonicus prays that with such feelings </l>
                    <l n="15"> he will meet death and welcome gray old age. And I entreat Clotho,
                        throned on high, and her sister Fates, to hear my friend's prayers for fame.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="19"> And as for you, sons of Aeacus with your golden chariots, </l>
                    <l n="20"> I say that it is my clearest law to sprinkle you with praises
                        whenever I set foot on this island. Countless continuous roads have been cut
                        a hundred feet wide for your fine deeds, both beyond the springs of the Nile
                        and through the land of the Hyperboreans. There is no city so barbarous or
                        so strange in its speech </l>
                    <l n="25"> that it does not know the fame of the hero Peleus, the fortunate
                        in-law of gods, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="26"> or of Aias and his father Telamon. The son of Alcmena led him in
                        ships to Troy, the toil of heroes, for war that delights in bronze, as an
                        eager ally along with the men of Tiryns because of Laomedon's wrongdoing. </l>
                    <l n="30"> He took Pergamos, and with Telamon's help he slew the tribes of
                        Meropes, and the herdsman Alcyoneus, huge as a mountain, whom he found at
                        Phlegrae, and he did not keep his hands off the deep-voiced bow-string, not
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="35"> </l>
                    <l n="35"> Heracles. But when he came to summon the son of Aeacus to that
                        expedition, he found them feasting. Standing in a lion's skin, the strong
                        warrior, son of Amphitryon, was asked to pour the first libation of nectar
                        by incomparable Telamon, who lifted up to him </l>
                    <l n="40"> the wine-bearing goblet bristling with gold. And Heracles stretched
                        his invincible hands up to heaven and said, “Father Zeus, if you have ever
                        heard my prayers with a willing heart, <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 2"
                        />
                    </l>
                    <l n="44"> now, now with divine prayers</l>
                    <l n="45"> I entreat you to grant this man a brave son from Eriboea, a son fated
                        to be my guest-friend. May he have a body as invulnerable as this skin that
                        is now wrapped around me, from the beast whom I killed that day in Nemea as
                        the very first of my labors. And may he have spirit to match.” When he had
                        spoken, the god sent to him</l>
                    <l n="50"> the king of birds, a great eagle. He felt thrilled inside with sweet
                        joy, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="51"> and he spoke like a prophet: “Telamon, you will have the son that you
                        ask for. Name him after the bird that appeared: wide-ruling Aias, awesome in
                        the war-toils of the people.” <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                            resp="Svarlien"> Compare <hi rend="Italic">Aias</hi> with Greek <foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">ai)eto/s</foreign> , <hi rend="Italic">eagle</hi>
                        </note>
                    </l>
                    <l n="55"> He spoke, and immediately sat down. But for me it would take a long
                        time to tell the story of all their excellence. For I came, Muse, a steward
                        of victory-songs to Phylacidas and Pytheas and Euthymenes. The story will be
                        told in the Argive manner, very briefly. <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="60"> </l>
                    <l n="60"> For those splendid boys and their uncle won three victories in the
                        pancratium—at the Isthmus, and others at Nemea with its fine trees, and they
                        brought to light a great share of praises. With the lovely dew of the Graces
                        they refresh the family of the Psalychids; </l>
                    <l n="65"> they have kept upright the house of Themistius, and they live in a
                        city which the gods love. Lampon, “taking care with his work,” honors these
                        words of Hesiod, and he advises his sons with them too, <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="69"> thus bringing a shared adornment to his city. </l>
                    <l n="70"> He is loved for his kindness to his guest-friends; he pursues with
                        moderation in his thoughts and restrains with moderation. He does not say
                        one thing and think another. You might say that for athletes he is like the
                        bronze-mastering Naxian whetstone among other stones. I shall give him to
                        drink the pure water of Dirce, which the deep-waisted daughters of </l>
                    <l n="75"> golden-robed Mnemosyne <note place="unspecified" anchored="true"
                            resp="Svarlien">Memory</note> brought forth beside the fine-walled gates
                        of Cadmus. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="poem" n="7">
                    <head>
                        <title>Isthmian 7</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Strepsiades of Thebes</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Pancratium</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0454">454</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> In which of the local glories of the past, divinely blessed Thebe, did
                        you most delight your spirit? Was it when you raised to eminence the one
                        seated beside Demeter of the clashing bronze cymbals, flowing-haired </l>
                    <l n="5"> Dionysus? Or when you received, as a snow-shower of gold in the middle
                        of the night, the greatest of the gods, <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 1"
                        />
                    </l>
                    <l n="6"> when he stood in the doorway of Amphitryon, and then went in to the
                        wife to beget Heracles? Or did you delight most in the shrewd counsels of
                        Teiresias? Or in the wise horseman Iolaus?</l>
                    <l n="10"> Or in the Sown Men, untiring with the spear? Or when you sent
                        Adrastus back from the mighty war-shout, bereft <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="epode 1"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="11"> of countless companions, to Argos, home of horses? Or because you
                        stood upright on its feet the Dorian colony of the men of Lacedaemon, and
                        your descendants, </l>
                    <l n="15"> the Aegeids, captured Amyclae according to the Pythian oracles? But
                        since ancient grace sleeps, and mortals are forgetful <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="18"> of whatever does not reach the highest bloom of skillful song, joined
                        to glorious streams of words,</l>
                    <l n="20"> then begin the victory procession with a sweet-singing hymn for
                        Strepsiades; for he is the victor in the pancratium at the Isthmus, both
                        awesome in his strength and handsome to look at; and he treats excellence as
                        no worse a possession than beauty. <milestone unit="strophe" n="ant. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="23"> He is made radiant by the violet-haired Muses, and he has given a
                        share in his flowering garland to his uncle and namesake, </l>
                    <l n="25"> for whom Ares of the bronze shield mixed the cup of destiny; but
                        honor is laid up as recompense for good men. For let him know clearly,
                        whoever, in this cloud of war, wards off the hailstorm of blood in defense
                        of his dear fatherland <milestone unit="strophe" n="epode 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="28"> by bringing destruction to the enemy host, that he is causing the
                        greatest glory to grow for the race of his fellow-citizens, </l>
                    <l n="30"> in both his life and his death. And you, son of Diodotus, emulating
                        the warrior Meleager, emulating Hector and Amphiaraus, breathed out your
                        blossoming youth <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="35"> </l>
                    <l n="35"> in the front ranks, where the best men sustained the strife of war at
                        the limit of their hopes. They endured unspeakable sorrow; but now the
                        holder of the earth has sent me calm after the storm. I shall sing entwining
                        my hair with garlands. May the envy of the immortals not disturb <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="ant. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="40"> </l>
                    <l n="40"> whatever delight I pursue from day to day as I peacefully make my way
                        towards old age and the allotted span of my life. For we die all alike, but
                        our fates are diverse. If a man looks to things far away, he is too short to
                        reach the bronze-floored home of the gods; winged Pegasus threw <milestone
                            unit="strophe" n="epode 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="45"> his master Bellerophon, who wanted to go to the dwelling-places of
                        heaven and the company of Zeus. A thing that is sweet beyond measure is
                        awaited by a most bitter end. But grant to us, Loxias, luxuriant with your
                        golden hair, </l>
                    <l n="50"> a blossoming garland also from your contests at Pytho. </l>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" type="poem" n="8">
                    <head>
                        <title>Isthmian 8</title>
                        <persName type="winner">For Cleandros of Aegina</persName>
                        <seg part="N" type="race">Pancratium</seg>
                        <date> ? <date when="-0478">478</date> B. C. </date>
                    </head>

                    <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 1"/>
                    <l n="1"> Young men! One of you go, in honor of Cleandros and his youth, to the
                        splendid doorway of his father Telesarchus, and awake the victory-song,
                        glorious recompense for his troubles, as a reward for his victory at the
                        Isthmus, and </l>
                    <l n="5"> because he found strength in the Nemean games. Therefore I too, though
                        grieving in my heart, am asked to invoke the golden Muse. Released from
                        great sorrows, let us not fall into bereavement of garlands; do not nurse
                        your pain. Having ceased from insurmountable troubles, we will sing
                        something sweet for the people, even after toil. Since</l>
                    <l n="10"> one of the gods has turned aside for us the stone of Tantalus above
                        our heads, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 2"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="11"> an unbearable hardship for Greece. But as for me, the passing away of
                        terror has stopped my mighty worry. It is always better to look at what lies
                        before one's foot, in every case. For a treacherous lifetime hangs over
                        men's heads, </l>
                    <l n="15"> twisting around the path of life. Yet even this may be healed for
                        mortals, if only they have freedom. It is right for a man to take to heart
                        good hope; and it is right for a man raised in seven-gated Thebes to offer
                        the choicest bloom of the Graces to Aegina. For as twin daughters they were
                        born to the same father, the youngest of Asopus' children, and they were
                        pleasing to Zeus the king. He caused one of them to dwell beside the
                        beautiful stream </l>
                    <l n="20"> of Dirce, to lead a chariot-loving city; <milestone unit="strophe"
                            n="str. 3"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="21"> but he carried you to the island Oenopia and slept with you there,
                        where you bore Aeacus, the dearest of all men on earth to the
                        loud-thundering father. Aeacus settled disputes even for the gods. His
                        god-like </l>
                    <l n="25"> sons and their sons, devoted to war, were the best in manliness,
                        engaged in the brazen battle-throng that causes groans, and they were wise
                        and prudent in spirit. All this was remembered even by the assembly of the
                        blessed gods, when Zeus and splendid Poseidon contended for marriage with
                        Thetis, each of them wanting her to be his lovely bride; for desire
                        possessed them.</l>
                    <l n="30"> But the immortal minds of the gods did not accomplish that marriage
                        for them, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 4"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="31"> when they heard the divine prophecies. Wise Themis spoke in their
                        midst and said that it was fated that the sea-goddess should bear a princely
                        son, stronger than his father, who would wield another weapon in his hand
                        more powerful than the thunderbolt</l>
                    <l n="35"> or the irresistible trident, if she lay with Zeus or one of his
                        brothers. “No, cease from this. Let her accept a mortal's bed, and see her
                        son die in battle, a son who is like Ares in the strength of his hands and
                        like lightning in the swift prime of his feet. My counsel is to bestow this
                        god-granted honor of marriage on Peleus son of Aeacus, </l>
                    <l n="40"> who is said to be the most pious man living on the plain of Iolcus.
                            <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 5"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="41"> Let the message be sent at once to Cheiron's immortal cave, right
                        away, and let the daughter of Nereus never again place the leaves of strife
                        in our hands. On the evening of the full moon </l>
                    <l n="45"> let her loosen the lovely bridle of her virginity for that hero.” So
                        the goddess spoke, addressing the sons of Cronus, and they nodded assent
                        with their immortal brows. The fruit of her words did not perish, for they
                        say that Zeus shared the common concern even for the marriage of Thetis. And
                        the voices of poets made known the youthful excellence of Achilles to those
                        who had been unaware of it—Achilles, who </l>
                    <l n="50"> stained the vine-covered plain of Mysia, spattering it with the dark
                        blood of Telephus, <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 6"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="51"> and bridged a homecoming for the Atreids, and freed Helen, cutting
                        with his spear the sinews of Troy, which had once tried to keep him from
                        marshalling on the plain the work of man-slaying war—he cut down </l>
                    <l n="55"> the high-spirited strength of Memnon, and Hector, and other excellent
                        heroes. Achilles, champion of the sons of Aeacus, showed them the way to the
                        house of Persephone, and thus brought fame to Aegina and to his race. Even
                        when he was dead songs did not forsake him; beside his pyre and tomb the
                        Muses of Helicon stood, and poured over him the many-voiced dirge. It proved
                        to be the will of the immortals </l>
                    <l n="60"> to make a noble man, even when dead, a theme for the hymns of
                        goddesses; <milestone unit="strophe" n="str. 7"/>
                    </l>
                    <l n="61"> and even now this brings up a subject for words, and the Muses'
                        chariot rushes forward to shout praises in memory of Nicocles the boxer.
                        Honor him, who won the garland of wild Dorian celery in the Isthmian valley;
                        since </l>
                    <l n="65"> he too was once victorious over all that lived around him, battering
                        them with his inescapable hands. He is not dishonored by the offspring of
                        his father's distinguished brother. Therefore let another young man weave
                        for Cleandros a garland of tender myrtle in honor of the pancratium, since
                        the contest of Alcathous and the young men of Epidaurus welcomed him before
                        in his success. A good man may praise him, </l>
                    <l n="70"> for he did not restrain his youth, keeping it hidden in his pocket
                            <note place="unspecified" anchored="true" resp="Svarlien"> Reading
                                <foreign xml:lang="grc">ko/lpw|</foreign> (Theiler, Slater) or
                                <foreign xml:lang="grc">ko/lpou</foreign> (Young) rather than
                                <foreign xml:lang="grc">keia=|</foreign> . </note> and ignorant of
                        fine deeds. </l>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
