<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>AIRS WATERS PLACES </title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 1, 2005</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>Hippocrates Collected Works I</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">W. H. S. Jones</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
							              <date>1923</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="eng">English</language>
				        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-29" who="Thibault Clérice">Bumped URN</change>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng"
              type="translation"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg002.perseus-eng4">
			         <pb n="p.71"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 1</head>
				           <p>W<hi rend="sc">HOEVER</hi> wishes to pursue properly the science of medicine must
					proceed thus. First he ought to consider what effects each season of the year
					can produce ; for the seasons are not at all alike, but differ widely both in
					themselves and at their changes. The next point is the hot winds and the cold,
					especially those that are universal, but also those that are peculiar to each
					particular region. He must also consider the properties of the waters ; for as
					these differ in taste and in weight, so the property of each is far different
					from that of any other. Therefore, on arrival at a town with which he is
					unfamiliar, a physician should examine its position with respect to the winds
					and to the risings of the sun. For a northern, a southern, an eastern, and a
					western aspect has each its own individual property. He must consider with the
					greatest care both these things and how the natives are off for water, whether
					they use marshy, soft waters, or such as are hard and come from rocky heights,
					or brackish and harsh. The soil too, whether bare and dry or wooded and watered,
					hollow and hot or high and cold. The mode of life also of the inhabitants that
					is pleasing to them, whether they</p>
				           <pb n="p.73"/>
				           <p>are heavy drinkers, taking lunch,<note>That is, taking more than one full meal
						every day.</note> and inactive, or athletic, industrious, eating much and
					drinking little.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 2</head>
				           <p>II. Using this evidence he must examine the several problems that arise. For if a
					physician know these things well, by preference all of them, but at any rate
					most, he will not, on arrival at a town with which he is unfamiliar, be ignorant
					of the local diseases, or of the nature of those that commonly prevail ; so that
					he will not be at a loss in the treatment of diseases, or make blunders, as is
					likely to be the case if he have not this knowledge before he consider his
					several problems. As time and the year passes he will be able to tell what
					epidemic diseases will attack the city either in summer or in winter, as well as
					those peculiar to the individual which are likely to occur through change in
					mode of life. For knowing the changes of the seasons, and the risings and
					settings of the stars, with the circumstances of each of these phenomena, he
					will know beforehand the nature of the year that is coming. Through these
					considerations and by learning the times beforehand, he will have full knowledge
					of each particular case, will succeed best in securing health, and will achieve
					the greatest triumphs in the practice of his art. If it be thought that all this
					belongs to meteorology, he will find out, on second thoughts, that the
					contribution of astronomy to medicine is not a very small one but a very great
					one indeed. For with the seasons men's diseases, like their digestive organs,
					suffer change.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 3</head>
				           <p>III. I will now set forth clearly how each of the foregoing questions ought to be
					investigated, and</p>
				           <pb n="p.75"/>
				           <p>the tests to be applied. A city that lies exposed to the hot winds--these are
					those between the winter rising of the sun and its winter setting--when subject
					to these and sheltered from the north winds, the waters here are plentiful and
					brackish, and must be near the surface,<note>
                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">METE/WROS2</foreign> "elevated," both here and in Chapter XXIV, seems,
						when applied to springs, to mean the opposite of "Deep," <hi rend="ital">i.
							e.</hi> rising from a point near the surface of the soil. Contrast
						Chapter VII, where water <foreign xml:lang="grc">E)K BAQUTA/TWN
							PHGE/WN</foreign> is said to be warm in winter and cool in
						summer.</note> hot in summer and cold in winter. The heads of the
					inhabitants are moist and full of phlegm, and their digestive organs are
					frequently deranged from the phlegm that runs down into them from the head. Most
					of them have a rather flabby physique, and they are poor eaters and poor
					drinkers. For men with weak heads will be poor drinkers, as the after-effects
					are more distressing to them. The endemic diseases are these. In the first
					place, the women are unhealthy and subject to excessive fluxes. Then many are
					barren through disease and not by nature, while abortions are frequent. Children
					are liable to convulsions and asthma, and to what they think causes the disease
					of childhood, and to be a sacred disease.<note>That is, epilepsy. Coray's
						reading means, "that affection which they think is caused by Heaven, and to
						be sacred."</note> Men suffer from dysentery, diarrhoea, ague, chronic
					fevers in winter, many attacks<note>Or "forms."</note> of eczema, and from
					hemorrhoids. Cases of pleurisy, pneumonia, ardent fever, and of diseases
					considered acute, rarely occur. These diseases cannot prevail where the bowels
					are loose. Inflammations of the eyes occur with running, but are not</p>
				           <pb n="p.77"/>
				           <p>serious ; they are of short duration, unless a general epidemic take place after
					a violent change. When they are more than fifty years old, they are paralyzed by
					catarrhs supervening from the brain, when the sun suddenly strikes their head or
					they are chilled. These are their endemic diseases, but besides, they are liable
					to any epidemic disease that prevails through the change of the seasons.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 4</head>
				           <p>IV. But the following is the condition of cities with the opposite situation,
					facing the cold winds that blow from between the summer setting and the summer
					rising of the sun, being habitually exposed to these winds, but sheltered from
					the hot winds and from the south. First, the waters of the region are generally
					hard and cold. The natives must be sinewy and spare, and in most cases their
					digestive organs are costive and hard in their lower parts, but more relaxed in
					the upper. They must be bilious rather than phlegmatic. Their heads are healthy
					and hard, but they have in most cases a tendency to internal lacerations. Their
					endemic diseases are as follow. Pleurisies are common, likewise those diseases
					which are accounted acute. It must be so, since their digestive organs are hard,
					and the slightest cause inevitably produces in many patients abscesses, the
					result of a stiff body and hard digestive organs. For their dryness, combined
					with the coldness of the water, makes them liable to internal lacerations.
					Such</p>
				           <pb n="p.79"/>
				           <p>constitutions necessarily make men eat much and drink little ; for one cannot be
					both a great eater and a great drinker. Inflammations of the eyes occur at last
					; they are hard and violent, and rapidly cause rupture of the eyes. Men under
					thirty suffer from violent bleedings at the nose in summer. Instances of the
					disease called "sacred" are rare but violent. These men are more likely to be
					long-lived than are others. Their sores become neither phlegmatic<hi rend="sup">1</hi> nor malignant, but their characters incline to fierceness, not to
					mildness. For men these diseases are endemic, besides there are epidemic
					diseases which may prevail through the change of the seasons. As to the women,
					firstly many become barren through the waters being hard, indigestible and cold.
					Their menstrual discharges are not healthy, but are scanty and bad. Then
					childbirth is difficult, although abortion is rare. After bearing children they
					cannot rear them, for their milk is dried up through the hardness and
					indigestibility of the waters, while cases of phthisis are frequent after
					parturition, for the violence of it causes ruptures and strains. Children suffer
					from dropsies in the testicles while they are little, which disappear as they
					grow older. In such a city puberty is late.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 5</head>
				           <p>V. The effects of hot winds and of cold winds on these cities are such as I have
					described ; the following are the effects of winds on cities lying</p>
				           <p>"Suppurating."</p>
				           <pb n="p.81"/>
				           <p>exposed to those between the summer and winter risings of the sun, and to those
					opposite to these. Those that lie towards the risings of the sun are likely to
					be healthier than those facing the north and those exposed to the hot winds,
					even though they be but a furlong apart. In the first place, the heat and the
					cold are more moderate. Then the waters that face the risings of the sun must be
					clear, sweet-smelling, soft and delightful, in such a city. For the sun, shining
					down upon them when it rises, purifies them. The persons of the inhabitants are
					of better complexion and more blooming than elsewhere, unless some disease
					prevents this. They are clear-voiced, and with better temper and intelligence
					than those who are exposed to the north, just as all things growing there are
					better. A city so situated is just like spring, because the heat and the cold
					are tempered ; the diseases, while resembling those which we said occur in
					cities facing the hot winds, are both fewer and less severe. The women there
					very readily conceive and have easy deliveries.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 6</head>
				           <p>VI. Such are the conditions in these cities. Those that lie towards the settings
					of the sun, and are</p>
				           <pb n="p.83"/>
				           <p>sheltered from the east winds, while the hot winds and the cold north winds blow
					past them--these cities must have a most unhealthy situation. In the first
					place, the waters are not clear, the reason being that in the morning mist is
					generally prevalent, which dissolves in the water and destroys its clearness, as
					the sun does not shine upon it before it is high on the horizon. In the summer
					cold breezes blow in the morning and there are heavy dews ; for the rest of the
					day the sun as it advances towards the west thoroughly scorches the inhabitants,
					so that they are likely to be pale and sickly, subject to all the diseases
					aforesaid, for none are peculiar to them.<note>
                     <foreign xml:lang="grc">AU)TOI=S2</foreign> may be either a dative of advantage or one of
						disadvantage. There can thus be two meanings :-- <p>(1) "for none are
							isolated to their advantage," <hi rend="ital">i. e.</hi> they are exempt
							from none ;</p>
						               <p>(2) "for none are isolated to their disadvantage," <hi rend="ital">i.
								e.</hi> they have no disease peculiar to themselves. I have taken
							the latter meaning, with Littré, but a good case could be made out for
							the former.</p>
                  </note> They are likely to have deep, hoarse voices,
					because of the atmosphere, since it is usually impure and unhealthy in such
					places. For while it is not clarified much by the north winds, which are not
					prevalent there, the winds that do prevail insistently are very rainy, such
					being the nature of westerly winds. Such a situation for a city is precisely
					like autumn in respect of the changes of the day, seeing that the difference
					between sunrise and afternoon is great.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 7</head>
				           <p>VII. So much for winds, healthy and unhealthy. I wish now to treat of waters,
					those that bring disease or very good health, and of the ill or good that is
					likely to arise from water. For the influence</p>
				           <pb n="p.85"/>
				           <p>of water upon health is very great. Such as are marshy, standing and stagnant
					must in summer be hot, thick and stinking, because there is no outflow ; and as
					fresh rain-water is always flowing in and the sun heats them, they must be of
					bad colour, unhealthy and bilious. In winter they must be frosty, cold and
					turbid through the snow and frosts, so as to be very conducive to phlegm and
					sore throats. Those who drink it have always large, stiff spleens, and hard,
					thin, hot stomachs, while their shoulders, collar-bones and faces are emaciated
					; the fact is that their flesh dissolves to feed the spleen, so that they are
					lean. With such a constitution they eat and drink heavily. Their digestive
					organs, upper and lower, are very dry and very hot, so that they need more
					powerful drugs. This malady is endemic both in summer and in winter. In addition
					the dropsies that occur are very numerous and very fatal. For in the summer
					there are epidemics of dysentery, diarrhoea and long quartan fever, which
					diseases when prolonged cause constitutions such as I have described to develop
					dropsies that result in death. These are their maladies in summer. In winter
					young people suffer from pneumonia and illnesses attended by delirium, the
					older, through the hardness of their digestive organs, from ardent fever. Among
					the women occur swellings and leucophlegmasia ; they conceive hardly and are
					delivered with difficulty. The babies are big and swollen, and</p>
				           <pb n="p.87"/>
				           <p>then, as they are nursed, they oecome emaciated<note>Or "consumptive."</note> and
					miserable. The discharge after childbirth is bad. Children are very subject to
					hernia and men to enlarged veins and to ulcers on the legs, so that such
					constitutions cannot be long-lived but must grow prematurely old. Moreover, the
					women appear to be with child, yet, when the time of delivery comes, the
					fullness of the womb disappears, this being caused by dropsy in that organ. Such
					waters I hold to be absolutely bad. The next worst will be those whose springs
					are from rocks--for they must be hard--or from earth where there are hot waters,
					or iron is to be found, or copper, or silver, or gold, or sulphur, or alum, or
					bitumen, or soda. For all these result from the violence of the heat. So from
					such earth good waters cannot come, but hard, heating waters, difficult to pass
					and causing constipation. The best are those that flow from high places and
					earthy hills. By themselves they are sweet and clear, and the wine they can
					stand is but little. In winter they are warm, in summer cold. They would
					naturally be so, coming from very deep springs. I commend especially those whose
					flow breaks forth towards the rising--by preference the summer rising--of the
					sun. For they must be brighter, sweet-smelling and light ; while all that are
					salt, harsh and hard are not good to drink, though there are some constitutions
					and some diseases which are benefited by drinking such waters, concerning which
					I will speak</p>
				           <pb n="p.89"/>
				           <p>presently. Aspect affects spring waters thus. Those whose sources face the
					risings of the sun are the very best. Second in excellence come those between
					the summer risings and the summer settings, by preference in the direction of
					the risings. Third best are those between the summer and winter settings. The
					worst are those that face the south, and those between the winter rising and
					setting. These are very bad indeed when the winds are in the south, less bad
					when they are in the north. Spring waters should be used thus. A man in health
					and strength can drink any water that is at hand without distinction, but he who
					because of disease wishes to drink the most suitable can best attain health in
					the following way. Those whose digestive organs are hard and easily heated will
					gain benefit from the sweetest, lightest and most sparkling waters. But those
					whose bellies are soft, moist, and phlegmatic, benefit from the hardest, most
					harsh and saltish waters, for these are the best to dry them up. For waters that
					are best for cooking and most solvent naturally loosen the digestive organs the
					most and relax them ; but harsh waters, hard and very bad for cooking, contract
					most these organs and dry them up. In fact the public are mistaken about saline
					waters through inexperience, in that they are generally considered to be
					laxative. The truth is that they are just the reverse ; they are harsh and bad
					for cooking, so that the digestive organs too are stiffened by them rather than
					loosened.</p>
				           <pb n="p.91"/>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 8</head>
				           <p>VIII. Such are the facts about spring waters. I will now proceed to speak of rain
					water and snow water. Rain waters are the lightest, sweetest, finest and
					clearest. To begin with, the sun raises and draws up the finest and lightest
					part of water, as is proved by the formation of salt. The brine, owing to its
					coarseness and weight, is left behind and becomes salt ; the finest part, owing
					to its lightness, is drawn up by the sun. Not only from pools does the sun raise
					this part, but also from the sea and from whatever has moisture in it--and there
					is moisture in everything. Even from men it raises the finest and lightest part
					of their juices. The plainest evidence thereof is that when a man walks or sits
					in the sun wearing a cloak, the parts of his skin reached by the sun will not
					sweat, for it draws up each layer of sweat as it appears. But those parts sweat
					which are covered by his cloak or by anything else. For the sweat drawn forcibly
					out by the sun is prevented by the covering from disappearing through the sun's
					power. But when the man has come into a shady place, his whole body sweats
					alike, as the sun no longer shines upon it. For this reason too rain-water grows
					foul quicker than any other, and has a bad smell ; being a mixture gathered from
					very many sources it grows foul very quickly. Furthermore, when it has been
					carried away aloft, and has combined with the atmosphere as it circles round,
					the turbid, dark part of it separates out, changes and becomes mist and fog,
					while the clearest and</p>
				           <pb n="p.93"/>
				           <p>lightest part of it remains, and is sweetened as the heat of the sun produces
					coction, just as all other things always become sweeter through coction. Now as
					long as it is scattered and uncondensed, it travels about aloft, but as soon as
					it collects anywhere and is compressed into one place owing to sudden, contrary
					winds, then it bursts wherever the most compression happens to take place. For
					this is more likely to occur when the clouds, set in motion and carried along by
					a wind that allows them no rest, are suddenly encountered by a contrary blast
					and by other clouds.<note>The reading of Kéhlewein means, "condensed, set in
						motion and carried along by a wind, are suddenly," etc.</note> In such cases
					the front is compressed, the rear comes on and is thus thickened, darkened and
					compressed into one place, so that the weight bursts it and causes rain. Such
					waters are naturally the best. But they need to be boiled and purified<note>Or,
						with the reading of Coray, "filtered."</note> from foulness if they are not
					to have a bad smell, and give sore throat, coughs and hoarseness to those who
					drink them.</p>
				           <p>Waters from snow and ice are all bad. For, once frozen, water never recovers its
					original nature, but the clear, light, sweet part is separated out and
					disappears, while the muddiest and heaviest part remains. The following
					experiment will prove it. Pour by measure, in winter, water into a vessel and
					set it in the open, where it will freeze best ; then on the next day bring it
					under cover, where the ice will</p>
				           <pb n="p.95"/>
				           <p>melt best ; if, when it is dissolved, you measure it again you will find it much
					diminished. This shows that freezing dries up and causes to disappear the
					lightest and finest part, not the heaviest and coarsest, to do which it has no
					power. In this way, therefore, I am of opinion that such waters, derived from
					snow or ice, and waters similar to these, are the worst for all purposes.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 9</head>
				           <p>IX. Such are the properties of rain waters, and of those from snow and ice.
					Stone, kidney disease, strangury and sciatica are very apt to attack people, and
					ruptures occur, when they drink water of very many different kinds, or from
					large rivers, into which other rivers flow, or from a lake fed by many streams
					of various sorts, and whenever they use foreign waters coming from a great, not
					a short, distance. For one water cannot be like another ; some are sweet, others
					are impregnated with salt and alum, others flow from hot springs. These when
					mixed up together disagree, and the strongest always prevails. But the strongest
					is not always the same ; sometimes it is one, sometimes another, according to
					the winds. One has its strength from a north wind, another from the south wind,
					and similarly with the others. Such waters then must leave a sediment of mud and
					sand in the vessels, and drinking them causes the diseases mentioned before.
					That there are exceptions I will proceed to set forth.</p>
				           <p>Those whose bowels are loose and healthy, whose bladder is not feverish, and the
					mouth of whose bladder is not over narrow, pass water easily, and no</p>
				           <pb n="p.97"/>
				           <p>solid matter forms in their bladder. But feverishness of the bowels must be
					accompanied by feverishness of the bladder. For when it is abnormally heated its
					mouth is inflamed. In this condition it does not expel the urine, but concocts
					and heats it within itself. The finest part is separated off, and the clearest
					passes out as urine, while the thickest and muddiest part forms solid matter,
					which, though at first small, grows in course of time. For as it rolls about in
					the urine it coalesces with whatever solid matter forms, and so it grows and
					hardens. When the patient makes water, it is forced by the urine to fall against
					the mouth of the bladder, and staying the flow of the urine causes violent pain.
					So that boys that suffer from stone rub and pull at their privy parts, under the
					impression that there lies the cause of their making water.<note>Coray's
						emendation would mean, "the cause of the stoppage," an attractive
						alteration.</note> That my account is correct is shown by the fact that
					sufferers from stone emit urine that is very clear, as the thickest and muddiest
					part of it remains and solidifies. This in most cases is the cause of stone.
					Children get stone also from the milk, if it be unhealthy, too hot and bilious.
					For it heats the bowels and the bladder, so that the urine is heated and
					affected as I have described. And my opinion is that we should give to young
					children only very diluted wine, which heats and parches the veins less. Females
					suffer less from stone. For their urethra is short and broad, so that the urine
					is easily expelled. Nor do they rub the privy parts as do males, nor handle
					the</p>
				           <pb n="p.99"/>
				           <p>urethra. For it opens directly into the privy parts, which is not so with males,
					nor is their urethra wide. And they drink more than boys do.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 10</head>
				           <p>X. This, or something very like this, is the truth concerning these matters. As
					to the seasons, a consideration of the following points will make it possible to
					decide whether the year will prove unhealthy or healthy. If the signs prove
					normal when the stars set and rise ; if there be rains in autumn, if the winter
					be moderate, neither too mild nor unseasonably cold, and if the rains be
					seasonable in spring and in summer, the year is likely to be very healthy. If,
					on the other hand, the winter prove dry and northerly, the spring rainy and
					southerly, the summer cannot fail to be feverladen, causing ophthalmia and
					dysenteries. For whenever the great heat comes on suddenly while the earth is
					soaked by reason of the spring rains and the south wind, the heat cannot fail to
					be doubled, coming from the hot, sodden earth and the burning sun ; men's bowels
					not being braced nor their brain dried--for when spring is such the body and its
					flesh must necessarily be flabby--the fevers that attack are of the acutest type
					in all cases, especially among the phlegmatic. Dysenteries are also likely to
					come upon women and the most humid constitutions. If at the rising of the Dog
					Star stormy rain occurs and the Etesian winds blow, there is hope that the
					distempers will cease and that the autumn will be healthy. Otherwise there is
					danger lest deaths</p>
				           <pb n="p.101"/>
				           <p>occur among the women and children, and least of all among the old men ; and lest
					those that get better lapse into quartans, and from quartans into dropsies. But
					if the winter be southerly, rainy and mild, and the spring be northerly, dry and
					wintry, in the first place women with child whose delivery is due by spring
					suffer abortion ; and if they do bring forth, their children are weak and
					sickly, so that either they die at once, or live puny, weak and sickly. Such is
					the fate of the women. The others have dysenteries and dry ophthalmia, and in
					some cases catarrhs descend from the head to the lungs. Phlegmatics are liable
					to dysenteries, and women also, phlegm running down from the brain because of
					the humidity of their constitution. The bilious have dry ophthalmia because of
					the warm dryness of their flesh. Old men have catarrhs because of their
					flabbiness and the wasting of their veins, so that some die suddenly, while
					others become paralyzed on the right side or the left. For whenever, owing to
					the winter being southerly and the body warm, neither brain nor veins are
					hardened, a northerly, dry, cold spring supervening, the brain, just at the time
					when it ought to have been relaxed along with spring and purged by cold in the
					head and hoarseness, congeals and hardens, so that the heat of summer having
					suddenly supervened and the change supervening, these diseases befall. Such</p>
				           <pb n="p.103"/>
				           <p>cities as are well situated with regard to sun and winds, and use good waters,
					are less affected by such changes ; but if they use marshy or standing waters,
					and are not well situated with regard to winds and sun, they are more affected.
					If the summer prove dry, the diseases cease more quickly ; if it be rainy, they
					are protracted. Sores are apt to fester from the slightest cause. Lienteries and
					dropsies supervene on the conclusion of the diseases, as the bowels do not
					readily dry up. If the summer and the autumn be rainy and southerly, the winter
					must be unhealthy ; phlegmatics and men over forty are likely to suffer from
					ardent fevers, bilious people from pleurisy and pneumonia. If the summer prove
					dry and northerly, and the autumn rainy and southerly, it is likely that in
					winter headaches occur and mortifications of the brain,<note>See Littré V. 581
						foll.</note> and in addition hoarseness, colds in the head, coughs, and in
					some cases consumption as well. But if the weather be northerly and dry, with no
					rain either during the Dog Star or at Arcturus, it is very beneficial to those
					who have a phlegmatic or humid constitution, and to women, but it is very
					harmful to the bilious. For these dry up overmuch, and are attacked by dry
					ophthalmia and by acute, protracted fevers, in some cases too by melancholies.
					For the most humid and watery part of the bile is dried up and is spent, while
					the</p>
				           <pb n="p.105"/>
				           <p>thickest and most acrid part is left, and similarly with the blood. Consequently
					these diseases come upon them. But all these conditions are helpful to the
					phlegmatic, for they dry up and reach winter dried up and not flabby.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 11</head>
				           <p>XI. By studying and observing after this fashion one may foresee most of the
					consequences of the changes. One should be especially on one's guard against the
					most violent changes of the seasons, and unless compelled one should neither
					purge, nor apply cautery or knife to the bowels, before at least ten days are
					past. The following are the four most violent changes and the most dangerous
					:--both solstices, especially the summer solstice, both the equinoxes, so
					reckoned, especially the autumnal. One must also guard against the risings of
					the stars, especially of the Dog Star, then of Arcturus, and also of the setting
					of the Pleiades. For it is especially at these times that diseases come to a
					crisis. Some prove fatal, some come to an end, all others change to another form
					and another constitution.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 12</head>
				           <p>XII. So much for the changes of the seasons. Now I intend to compare
						Asia<note>That is, Asia Minor.</note> and Europe, and to show how they
					differ in every respect, and how the nations of the one differ entirely in
					physique from those of the other. It would take too long to describe them all,
					so I will set forth my views about the most important and the greatest
					differences. I hold that Asia differs very widely from Europe in the</p>
				           <pb n="p.107"/>
				           <p>nature of all its inhabitants and of all its vegetation. For everything in Asia
					grows to far greater beauty and size ; the one region is less wild than the
					other, the character of the inhabitants is milder and more gentle. The cause of
					this is the temperate climate, because it lies towards the east midway between
					the risings<note>That is, the winter rising and the summer rising.</note> of the
					sun, and farther away than is Europe from the cold. Growth and freedom from
					wildness are most fostered when nothing is forcibly predominant, but equality in
					every respect prevails. Asia, however, is not everywhere uniform ; the region,
					however, situated midway between the heat and the cold is very fruitful, very
					wooded and very mild ; it has splendid water, whether from rain or from springs.
					While it is not burnt up with the heat nor dried up by drought and want of
					water, it is not oppressed with cold, nor yet damp and wet with excessive rains
					and snow. Here the harvests are likely to be plentiful, both those from seed and
					those which the earth bestows of her own accord, the fruit of which men use,
					turning wild to cultivated and transplanting them to a suitable soil. The cattle
					too reared there are likely to flourish, and especially to bring forth the
					sturdiest young and rear them to be very fine creatures.<note>Or, if <foreign xml:lang="grc">PUKN/OTATA</foreign> and <foreign xml:lang="grc">K/ALLIDTA</foreign> be adverbs, "they are very prolifio and the best of
						mothers."</note> The men will be well nourished, of very fine physique and
					very tall, differing from one another but little either in physique or stature.
					This region, both in character and in the mildness of its seasons, might fairly
					be said to bear a close resemblance to spring</p>
				           <pb n="p.109"/>
				           <p>Courage, endurance, industry and high spirit could not arise in such conditions
					either among the natives or among immigrants,<note>The writer is thinking of
						Asiatic natives and the Greek colonists on the coast of Asia Minor.</note>
					but pleasure must be supreme . . .<note>There is a gap in the text here dealing
						with the Egyptians and Libyans.</note> wherefore in the beasts they are of
					many shapes.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 13</head>
				           <p>XIII. Such in my opinion is the condition of the Egyptians and Libyans. As to the
					dwellers on the right of the summer risings of the sun up to Lake Maeotis, which
					is the boundary between Europe and Asia, their condition is as follows. These
					nations are less homogeneous than those I have described, because of the changes
					of the seasons and the character of the region. The land is affected by them
					exactly as human beings in general are affected. For where the seasons
					experience the most violent and the most frequent changes,<note>Or, more
						idiomatically, "the variations of climate are most violent and most
						frequent." The four changes at the end of the four seasons were only the
						most important of many <foreign xml:lang="grc">METABOLAI</foreign>. See
						Chapter XI, and pp. 68, 69.</note> the land too is very wild and very uneven
					; you will find there many wooded mountains, plains and meadows. But where the
					seasons do not alter much, the land is very even. So it is too with the
					inhabitants, if you will examine the matter. Some physiques resemble wooded,
					well-watered mountains, others light, dry land, others marshy meadows, others a
					plain of bare, parched earth. For the seasons which modify a physical frame
					differ ; if the</p>
				           <pb n="p.111"/>
				           <p>differences be great, the more too are the differences in the shapes.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 14</head>
				           <p>XIV. The races that differ but little from one another I will omit, and describe
					the condition only of those which differ greatly, whether it be through nature
					or through custom. I will begin with the Longheads.<note>Practically nothing
						more is told us about this race by our other authorities, Pliny,
						Harpocration and Suidas. But see Littré IV., xi. and xii.</note> There is no
					other race at all with heads like theirs. Originally custom was chiefly
					responsible for the length of the head, but now custom is reinforced by nature.
					Those that have the longest heads they consider the noblest, and their custom is
					as follows. As soon as a child is born they remodel its head with their hands,
					while it is still soft and the body tender, and force it to increase in length
					by applying bandages and suitable appliances, which spoil the roundness of the
					head and increase its length. Custom originally so acted that through force such
					a nature came into being ; but as time went on the process became natural, so
					that custom no longer exercised compulsion. For the seed comes from all parts of
					the body, healthy seed from healthy parts, diseased seed from diseased parts.
					If, therefore, bald parents have for the most part bald children, grey-eyed
					parents grey-eyed children, squinting parents squinting children, and so on with
					other physical peculiarities, what prevents a long-headed parent having a
					long-headed child?<note>Modern biologists hold that acquired characteristics are
						not inherited.</note> At the present time long-headedness is less common
					than it was, for owing to intercourse with other men the custom is less
					prevalent.</p>
				           <pb n="p.113"/>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 15</head>
				           <p>XV. These are my opinions about the Longheads. Now let me turn to the dwellers on
					the Phasis. Their land is marshy, hot, wet, and wooded ; copious violent rains
					fall there during every season. The inhabitants live in the marshes, and their
					dwellings are of wood and reeds, built in the water. They make little use of
					walking in the city and the harbour, but sail up and down in dug-outs made from
					a single log, for canals are numerous. The waters which they drink are hot and
					stagnant, putrefied by the sun and swollen by the rains. The Phasis itself is
					the most stagnant and most sluggish of all rivers. The fruits that grow in this
					country are all stunted, flabby and imperfect, owing to the excess of water, and
					for this reason they do not ripen. Much fog from the waters envelops the land.
					For these causes, therefore, the physique of the Phasians is different from that
					of other folk. They are tall in stature, and of a gross habit of body, while
					neither joint nor vein is visible. Their complexion is yellowish, as though they
					suffered from jaundice. Of all men they have the deepest voice, because the air
					they breathe is not clear, but moist and turbid. They are by nature disinclined
					for physical fatigue. There are but slight changes of the seasons, either in
					respect of heat or of cold. The winds are mostly moist, except one breeze
					peculiar to the country, called <hi rend="ital">cenchron</hi>, which sometimes
					blows strong, violent</p>
				           <pb n="p.115"/>
				           <p>and hot. The north wind rarely blows, and when it does it is weak and gentle.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 16</head>
				           <p>XVI. So much for the difference, in nature and in shape, between the inhabitants
					of Asia and the inhabitants of Europe. With regard to the lack of spirit and of
					courage among the inhabitants, the chief reason why Asiatics are less warlike
					and more gentle in character than Europeans is the uniformity of the seasons,
					which show no violent changes either towards heat or towards cold, but are
					equable. For there occur no mental shocks nor violent physical change, which are
					more likely to steel the temper and impart to it a fierce passion than is a
					monotonous sameness. For it is changes of all things that rouse the temper of
					man and prevent its stagnation. For these reasons, I think, Asiatics are feeble.
					Their institutions are a contributory cause, the greater part of Asia being
					governed by kings. Now where men are not their own masters and independent, but
					are ruled by despots, they are not keen on military efficiency but on not
					appearing warlike. For the risks they run are not similar. Subjects are likely
					to be forced to undergo military service, fatigue and death, in order to benefit
					their masters, and to be parted from their wives, their children and their
					friends. All their worthy, brave deeds merely serve to aggrandize and raise up
					their lords, while the harvest they themselves reap is danger and death.
					Moreover, the land of men like these</p>
				           <pb n="p.117"/>
				           <p>must be desert, owing to their enemies and to their laziness,<note>Or, reading
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">H(MEROU=S1QAI TH\N O)RGH\N U(PO/ TE A)POLEMI/WN
							K.T.L.</foreign>, "the temper of men like these must be gentle, because
						they are unwarlike and inactive."</note> so that even if a naturally brave
					and spirited man is born his temper is changed by their institutions. Whereof I
					can give a clear proof. All the inhabitants of Asia, whether Greek or non-Greek,
					who are not ruled by despots, but are independent, toiling for their own
					advantage, are the most warlike of all men. For it is for their own sakes that
					they run their risks, and in their own persons do they receive the prizes of
					their valour as likewise the penalty of their cowardice. You will find that
					Asiatics also differ from one another, some being superior, others inferior. The
					reason for this, as I have said above, is the changes of the seasons.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 17</head>
				           <p>XVII. Such is the condition of the inhabitants of Asia. And in Europe is a
					Scythian race, dwelling round Lake Maeotis, which differs from the other races.
					Their name is Sauromatae. Their women, so long as they are virgins, ride, shoot,
					throw the javelin while mounted, and fight with their enemies. They do not lay
					aside their virginity until they have killed three of their enemies, and they do
					not marry before they have performed the traditional sacred rites. A woman who
					takes to herself a husband no longer rides, unless she is compelled to do so by
					a general expedition. They have no right breast ; for while they are yet babies
					their mothers make</p>
				           <pb n="p.119"/>
				           <p>red-hot a bronze instrument constructed for this very purpose and apply it to the
					right breast and cauterise it, so that its growth is arrested, and all its
					strength and bulk are diverted to the right shoulder and right arm.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 18</head>
				           <p>XVIII. As to the physique of the other Scythians, in that they are like one
					another and not at all like others, the same remark applies to them as to the
					Egyptians, only the latter are distressed by the heat, the former by the
						cold.<note>Both people are of peculiar physique, and the cause of the
						peculiarity is in the one case extreme heat, and in the other extreme
						cold.</note> What is called the Scythian desert is level grassland, without
						trees,<note>Or, reading <foreign xml:lang="grc">U(YHLH/</foreign>, "a
						plateau."</note> and fairly well-watered. For there are large rivers which
					drain the water from the plains. There too live the Scythians who are called
					Nomads because they have no houses but live in wagons. The smallest have four
					wheels, others six wheels. They are covered over with felt and are constructed,
					like houses, sometimes in two compartments and sometimes in three, which are
					proof against rain, snow and wind. The wagons are drawn by two or by three yoke
					of hornless oxen. They have no horns because of the cold. Now in these wagons
					live the women, while the men ride alone on horseback, followed by the sheep
					they have, their cattle and their horses. They remain in the same place just as
					long as there is sufficient fodder for their animals ; when it gives out they
					migrate. They themselves eat boiled</p>
				           <pb n="p.121"/>
				           <p>meats and drink mares' milk. They have a sweetmeat called <hi rend="ital">hippace</hi>, which is a cheese from the milk of mares (<hi rend="ital">hippoi</hi>).</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 19</head>
				           <p>XIX. So much for their mode of living and their customs. As to their seasons and
					their physique, the Scythians are very different from all other men, and, like
					the Egyptians, are homogeneous ; they are the reverse of prolific, and Scythia
					breeds the smallest and the fewest wild animals. For it lies right close to the
					north and the Rhipaean mountains, from which blows the north wind. The sun comes
					nearest to them only at the end of its course, when it reaches the summer
					solstice, and then it warms them but slightly and for a short time. The winds
					blowing from hot regions do not reach them, save rarely, and with little force ;
					but from the north there are constantly blowing winds that are chilled by snow,
					ice, and many waters,<note>Or, "heavy rains."</note> which, never leaving the
					mountains, render them uninhabitable. A thick fog envelops by day the plains
					upon which they live, so that winter is perennial, while summer, which is but
					feeble, lasts only a few days. For the plains are high and bare, and are not
					encircled with mountains, though they slope from the north. The wild animals too
					that are found there are not large, but such as can find shelter under ground.
					They are stunted owing to the severe climate and the bareness of the land, where
					there is neither warmth<note>Strangely enough, both Littré and Adams translate
						as though they took <foreign xml:lang="grc">A)LE/H</foreign> to be the Epic
						word meaning "means of escape."</note> nor shelter. And the changes of the
					seasons are</p>
				           <pb n="p.123"/>
				           <p>neither great nor violent, the seasons being uniform and altering but little.
					Wherefore the men also are like one another in physique, since summer and winter
					they always use similar food and the same clothing, breathing a moist, thick
					atmosphere, drinking water from ice and snow, and abstaining from fatigue. For
					neither bodily nor mental endurance is possible where the changes are not
					violent. For these causes their physiques are gross, fleshy, showing no joints,
					moist and flabby, and the lower bowels are as moist as bowels can be. For the
					belly cannot possibly dry up in a land like this, with such a nature and such a
					climate, but because of their fat and the smoothness of their flesh their
					physiques are similar, men's to men's and women's to women's. For as the seasons
					are alike there takes place no corruption or deterioration in the coagulation of
					the seed,<note>As a modern physiologist might put it, "abnormal variations in
						the formation of the embryo."</note> except through the blow of some violent
					cause or of some disease.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 20</head>
				           <p>XX. I will give clear testimony to their moistness. The majority of the
					Scythians, all that are Nomads, you will find have their shoulders cauterized,
					as well as their arms, wrists, breast, hips and loins, simply because of the
					moistness and softness of their constitution. For owing to their moistness and
					flabbiness they have not the strength either to draw a bow or to throw a javelin
					from the shoulder. But when they have been cauterized the excess of moisture</p>
				           <pb n="p.125"/>
				           <p>dries up from their joints, and their bodies become more braced, more nourished
					and better articulated. Their bodies grow relaxed and squat, firstly because,
					unlike the Egyptians, they do not use swaddling clothes, of which they have not
					the habit,<note>This is a literal translation of the text, but see the footnote
						on the opposite page.</note> for the sake of their riding, that they may sit
					a horse well ; secondly, through their sedentary lives. For the boys, until they
					can ride, sit the greater part of the time in the wagon, and because of the
					migrations and wanderings rarely walk on foot ; while the girls are wonderfully
					flabby and torpid in physique. The Scythians are a ruddy race because of the
					cold, not through any fierceness in the sun's heat. It is the cold that burns
					their white skin and turns it ruddy.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 21</head>
				           <p>XXI. A constitution of this kind prevents fertility. The men have no great desire
					for intercourse because of the moistness of their constitution and the softness
					and chill of their abdomen, which are the greatest checks on venery. Moreover,
					the constant jolting on their horses unfits them for intercourse. Such are the
					causes of barrenness in the men ; in the women they are the fatness and
					moistness of their flesh, which are such that the womb cannot absorb the seed.
					For neither is their monthly purging as it should be, but scanty and late, while
					the mouth of the womb is closed by fat and does not admit the seed. They are
					personally fat and lazy, and their</p>
				           <pb n="p.127"/>
				           <p>abdomen is cold and soft. These are the causes which make the Scythian race
					unfertile. A clear proof is afforded by their slave-girls. These, because of
					their activity and leanness of body, no sooner go to a man than they are with
					child.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 22</head>
				           <p>XXII. Moreover, the great majority among the Scythians become impotent, do
					women's work, live like women and converse accordingly. Such men they call
					Anaries. Now the natives put the blame on to Heaven, and respect and worship
					these creatures, each fearing for himself. I too think that these diseases are
					divine, and so are all others, no one being more divine or more human than any
					other ; all are alike, and all divine. Each of them has a nature of its own, and
					none arises without its natural cause. How, in my opinion, this disease arises I
					will explain. The habit of riding causes swellings at the joints,<note>For this
						difficult word see Littré V. 320 and VIII. xxxix foll.</note> because they
					are always astride their horses ; in severe cases follow lameness and sores on
					the hips. They cure themselves in the following way. At the beginning of the
					disease they cut the vein behind each ear. When the blood has ceased to flow
					faintness comes over them and they sleep. Afterwards they get up, some cured and
					some not. Now, in my opinion, by this treatment the seed is destroyed. For by
					the side of the ear are veins, to</p>
				           <pb n="p.129"/>
				           <p>cut which causes impotence, and I believe that these are the veins which they
					cut. After this treatment, when the Scythians approach a woman but cannot have
					intercourse, at first they take no notice and think no more about it. But when
					two, three or even more attempts are attended with no better success, thinking
					that they have sinned against Heaven they attribute thereto the cause, and put
					on women's clothes, holding that they have lost their manhood. So they play the
					woman, and with the women do the same work as women do.</p>
				           <p>This affliction affects the rich Scythians because of their riding, not the lower
					classes but the upper, who possess the most strength ; the poor, who do not
					ride, suffer less. But, if we suppose this disease to be more divine than any
					other, it ought to have attacked, not the highest and richest classes only of
					the Scythians, but all classes equally--or rather the poor especially, if indeed
					the gods are pleased to receive from men respect and worship, and repay these
					with favours. For naturally the rich, having great wealth, make many sacrifices
					to the gods, and offer many votive offerings, and honour them, all of which
					things the poor, owing to their poverty, are less able to do ; besides, they
					blame the gods for not giving them wealth, so that the penalties for such sins
					are likely to be paid by the poor rather than by the rich. But the truth is, as
					I said above, these affections are neither more nor less divine than any others,
					and all and each are natural. Such a disease arises</p>
				           <pb n="p.131"/>
				           <p>among the Scythians for such a reason as I have stated, and other men too are
					equally liable to it, for wherever men ride very much and very frequently, there
					the majority are attacked by swellings at the joints, sciatica and gout, and are
					sexually very weak. These complaints come upon the Scythians, and they are the
					most impotent of men, for the reasons I have given, and also because they always
					wear trousers and spend most of their time on their horses, so that they do not
					handle the parts, but owing to cold and fatigue forget about sexual passion,
					losing their virility before any impulse is felt.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 23</head>
				           <p>XXIII. Such is the condition of the Scythians. The other people of Europe differ
					from one another both in stature and in shape, because of the changes of the
					seasons, which are violent and frequent, while there are severe heat waves,
					severe winters, copious rains and then long droughts, and winds, causing many
					changes of various kinds. Wherefore it is natural to realize that generation too
					varies in the coagulation of the seed,<note>
                     <hi rend="ital">I. e.</hi> "in the
						formation of the foetus."</note> and is not the same for the same seed in
					summer as in winter nor in rain as in drought. It is for this reason, I think,
					that the physique of Europeans varies more than that of Asiatics, and that their
					stature differs very widely in each city. For there arise more corruptions in
					the coagulation of the seed when the changes of the seasons</p>
				           <pb n="p.133"/>
				           <p>are frequent than when they are similar or alike. The same reasoning applies also
					to character. In such a climate arise wildness, unsociability and spirit. For
					the frequent shocks to the mind impart wildness, destroying tameness and
					gentleness. For this reason, I think, Europeans are also more courageous than
					Asiatics. For uniformity engenders slackness, while variation fosters endurance
					in both body and soul ; rest and slackness are food for cowardice, endurance and
					exertion for bravery. Wherefore Europeans are more warlike, and also because of
					their institutions, not being under kings as are Asiatics. For, as I said above,
					where there are kings, there must be the greatest cowards. For men's souls are
					enslaved, and refuse to run risks readily and recklessly to increase the power
					of somebody else. But independent people, taking risks on their own behalf and
					not on behalf of others, are willing and eager to go into danger, for they
					themselves enjoy the prize of victory. So institutions contribute a great deal
					to the formation of courageousness.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 24</head>
				           <p>XXIV. Such, in outline and in general, is the character of Europe and of Asia. In
					Europe too there are tribes differing one from another in stature, in shape and
					in courage. The differences are due to the same causes as I mentioned above,
					which I will now describe more clearly. Inhabitants of a region which is
					mountainous, rugged, high, and watered,</p>
				           <pb n="p.135"/>
				           <p>where the changes of the seasons exhibit sharp contrasts, are likely to be of big
					physique, with a nature well adapted for endurance and courage, and such possess
					not a little wildness and ferocity. The inhabitants of hollow regions, that are
					meadowy, stifling, with more hot than cool winds, and where the water used is
					hot, will be neither tall nor well-made, but inclined to be broad, fleshy, and
					dark-haired ; they themselves are dark rather than fair, less subject to phlegm
					than to bile. Similar bravery and endurance are not by nature part of their
					character, but the imposition of law can produce them artificially. Should there
					be rivers in the land, which drain off from the ground the stagnant water and
					the rain water, these<note>The people or the rivers ? Probably the former, in
						which case "bright" will mean "of bright (clear) complexion."</note> will be
					healthy and bright. But if there be no rivers, and the water that the people
					drink be marshy, stagnant, and fenny, the physique of the people must show
					protruding bellies and enlarged spleens. Such as dwell in a high land that is
					level, windy, and watered, will be tall in physique and similar to one another,
					but rather unmanly and tame in character. As to those that dwell on thin, dry,
					and bare soil, and where the changes of the seasons exhibit sharp contrasts, it
					is likely that in such country the people will be hard in physique and
					well-braced, fair rather than dark, stubborn and independent in character and in
					temper. For where the changes of the seasons are most frequent and most sharply
					contrasted, there you will find the greatest diversity in physique, in
					character, and in constitution.</p>
				           <pb n="p.137"/>
				           <p>These are the most important factors that create differences in men's
					constitutions ; next come the land in which a man is reared, and the water. For
					in general you will find assimilated to the nature of the land both the physique
					and the characteristics of the inhabitants. For where the land is rich, soft,
					and well-watered, and the water is very near the surface, so as to be hot in
					summer and cold in winter, and if the situation be favourable as regards the
					seasons, there the inhabitants are fleshy, ill-articulated, moist, lazy, and
					generally cowardly in character. Slackness and sleepiness can be observed in
					them, and as far as the arts are concerned they are thick-witted, and neither
					subtle nor sharp. But where the land is bare, waterless, rough, oppressed by
					winter's storms and burnt by the sun, there you will see men who are hard, lean,
					well-articulated, well-braced, and hairy ; such natures will be found energetic,
					vigilant, stubborn and independent in character and in temper, wild rather than
					tame, of more than average sharpness and intelligence in the arts, and in war of
					more than average courage. The things also that grow in the earth all assimilate
					themselves to the earth. Such are the most sharply contrasted natures and
					physiques. Take these observations as a standard when drawing all other
					conclusions, and you will make no mistake.</p>
			         </div>

			         <pb n="p.139"/>
		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
