<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>On Airs, Waters, and Places</title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 20, 2003</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							              <date>1886</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="eng">English</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-29" who="Thibault Clérice">Bumped URN</change>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng"
              type="translation"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg002.perseus-eng3">
			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 1 </head>
				           <p>Whoever wishes to investigate medicine properly, should proceed thus: in the
					first place to consider the seasons of the year, and what effects each of them
					produces (for they are not at all alike, but differ much from themselves in
					regard to their changes).<note>The part in parenthesis is rather obscure. In the
						old French translation it is rendered thus: "Elles sont tres differentes
						entre elles par leur nature, et il arrive d'ailleurs une infinite de
						changemens qui sont tous divers." On these changes, see Aphor. iii.,
						2-15.</note> Then the winds, the hot and the cold, especially such as are
					common to all countries, and then such as are peculiar to each locality. We must
					also consider the qualities of the waters, for as they differ from one another
					in taste and weight, so also do they differ much in their qualities. In the same
					manner, when one comes into a city to which he is a stranger, he ought to
					consider its situation, how it lies as to the winds and the rising of the sun;
					for its influence is not the same whether it lies to the north or the south, to
					the rising or to the setting sun. These things one ought to consider most
					attentively, and concerning the waters which the inhabitants use, whether they
					be marshy and soft, or hard, and running from elevated and rocky situations, and
					then if saltish and unfit for cooking; and the ground, whether it be naked and
					deficient in water, or wooded and well watered, and whether it lies in a hollow,
					confined situation, or is elevated and cold; and the mode in which the
					inhabitants live, and what are their pursuits, whether they are fond of drinking
					and eating to excess, and given to indolence, or are fond of exercise and labor,
					and not given to excess in eating and drinking.<pb n="p.20"/>
				           </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 2 </head>
				           <p> From these things he must proceed to investigate everything else. For if one
					knows all these things well, or at least the greater part of them, he cannot
					miss knowing, when he comes into a strange city, either the diseases peculiar to
					the place, or the particular nature of common diseases, so that he will not be
					in doubt as to the treatment of the diseases, or commit mistakes, as is likely
					to be the case provided one had not previously considered these matters. And in
					particular, as the season and the year advances, he can tell what epidemic
					diseases will attack the city, either in summer or in winter, and what each
					individual will be in danger of experiencing from the change of regimen. For
					knowing the changes of the seasons, the risings and settings of the stars, how
					each of them takes place, he will be able to know beforehand what sort of a year
					is going to ensue. Having made these investigations, and knowing beforehand the
					seasons, such a one must be acquainted with each particular, and must succeed in
					the preservation of health, and be by no means unsuccessful in the practice of
					his art. And if it shall be thought that these things belong rather to
					meteorology, it will be admitted, on second thoughts, that astronomy contributes
					not a little, but a very great deal, indeed, to medicine. For with the seasons
					the digestive organs of men undergo a change.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 3 </head>
				           <p> But how of the aforementioned things should be investigated and explained, I
					will now declare in a clear manner. A city that is exposed to hot winds (these
					are between the wintry rising, and the wintry setting of the sun), and to which
					these are peculiar, but which is sheltered from the north winds; in such a city
					the waters will be plenteous and saltish, and as they run from an elevated
					source, they are necessarily hot in summer, and cold in winter; the heads of the
					inhabitants are of a humid and pituitous constitution, and their bellies subject
					to frequent disorders, owing to the phlegm running down from the head; the forms
					of their bodies, for the most part, are rather flabby; they do not eat nor drink
					much; drinking wine in particular, and more especially if carried to
					intoxication, is oppressive to them; and the following diseases are peculiar to
					the district: in the first place, the women are sickly and subject to excessive
					menstrua- <pb n="p.21"/>tion; then many are unfruitful from disease, and not
					from nature, and they have frequent miscarriages; infants are subject to attacks
					of convulsions and asthma, which they consider to be connected with infancy, and
					hold to be a sacred disease (epilepsy). The men are subject to attacks of
					dysentery, diarrhea, hepialus,<note>The Hepialus is a species of intermittent
						fever, very common in warm climates. It would appear to be a variety of the
						quotidian. See PAULUS AEGINETA, Vol. I., 252, Syd. Soc. edition.</note>
					chronic fevers in winter, of epinyctis,<note>Frequent mention of this disease of
						the skin occurs in the works of the ancient writers on medicine.</note>
					frequently, and of hemorrhoids about the anus. Pleurisies, peripneumonies,
					ardent fevers, and whatever diseases are reckoned acute, do not often occur, for
					such diseases are not apt to prevail where the bowels are loose. Ophthalmies
					occur of a humid character, but not of a serious nature, and of short duration,
					unless they attack epidemically from the change of the seasons. And when they
					pass their fiftieth year, defluxions supervening from the brain, render them
					paralytic when exposed suddenly to strokes of the sun, or to cold. These
					diseases are endemic to them, and, moreover, if any epidemic disease connected
					with the change of the seasons, prevail, they are also liable to it. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 4 </head>
				           <p> But the following is the condition of cities which have the opposite exposure,
					namely, to cold winds, between the summer settings and the summer risings of the
					sun, and to which these winds are peculiar, and which are sheltered from the
					south and the hot breezes. In the first place the waters are, for the most part,
					hard cold. The men must necessarily be well braced and slender, and they must
					have the discharges downwards of the alimentary canal hard, and of difficult
					evacuation, while those upwards are more fluid, and rather bilious than
					pituitous. Their heads are sound and hard, and they are liable to burstings (of
					vessels?) for the most part. The diseases which prevail epidemically with them,
					are pleurisies, and those which are called acute diseases. This must be the case
					when the bowels are bound; and from any causes, many become affected with
					suppurations in the lungs, the cause of which is the tension of the body, and
					hardness of the bowels; for their dryness and the <pb n="p.22"/>coldness of the
					water dispose them to ruptures (of vessels?). Such constitutions must be given
					to excess of eating, but not of drinking; for it is not possible to be gourmands
					and drunkards at the same time. Ophthalmies, too, at length supervene; these
					being of a hard and violent nature, and soon ending in rupture of the eyes;
					persons under thirty years of age are liable to severe bleedings at the nose in
					summer; attacks of epilepsy are rare but severe. Such people are likely to be
					rather long-lived; their ulcers are not attended with serious discharges, nor of
					a malignant character; in disposition they are rather ferocious than gentle. The
					diseases I have mentioned are peculiar to the men, and besides they are liable
					to any common complaint which may be prevailing from the changes of the seasons.
					But the women, in the first place, are of a hard constitution, from the waters
					being hard, indigestible, and cold; and their menstrual discharges are not
					regular, but in small quantity, and painful. Then they have difficult
					parturition, but are not very subject to abortions. And when they do bring forth
					children, they are unable to nurse them; for the hardness and indigestable
					nature of the water puts away their milk. Phthisis frequently supervenes after
					childbirth, for the efforts of it frequently bring on ruptures and strains.
					Children while still little are subject to dropsies in the testicle, which
					disappear as they grow older; in such a town they are late in attaining manhood.
					It is, as I have now stated, with regard to hot and cold winds and cities thus
					exposed. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 5 </head>
				           <p> Cities that are exposed to winds between the summer and the winter risings of
					the sun, and those the opposite to them, have the following characters:- Those
					which lie to the rising of the sun are all likely to be more healthy than such
					as are turned to the North, or those exposed to the hot winds, even if there
					should not be a furlong between them. In the first place, both the heat and cold
					are more moderate. Then such waters as flow to the rising sun, must necessarily
					be clear, fragrant, soft, and delightful to drink, in such a city. For the sun
					in rising and shining upon them purifies them, by dispelling the vapors which
					generally prevail in the morning. The persons of the inhabitants are, for the
					most part, well colored and blooming, unless some <pb n="p.23"/>disease
					counteract. The inhabitants have clear voices, and in temper and intellect are
					superior to those which are exposed to the north, and all the productions of the
					country in like manner are better. A city so situated resembles the spring as to
					moderation between heat and cold, and the diseases are few in number, and of a
					feeble kind, and bear a resemblance to the diseases which prevail in regions
					exposed to hot winds. The women there are very prolific, and have easy
					deliveries. Thus it is with regard to them. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 6 </head>
				           <p> But such cities as lie to the west, and which are sheltered from winds blowing
					from the east, and which the hot winds and the cold winds of the north scarcely
					touch, must necessarily be in a very unhealthy situation: in the first place the
					waters are not clear, the cause of which is, because the mist prevails commonly
					in the morning, and it is mixed up with the water and destroys its clearness,
					for the sun does not shine upon the water until he be considerably raised above
					the horizon. And in summer, cold breezes from the east blow and dews fall; and
					in the latter part of the day the setting sun particularly scorches the
					inhabitants, and therefore they are pale and enfeebled, and are partly subject
					to all the aforesaid diseases, but no one is peculiar to them. Their voices are
					rough and hoarse owing to the state of the air, which in such a situation is
					generally impure and unwholesome, for they have not the northern winds to purify
					it; and these winds they have are of a very humid character, such being the
					nature of the evening breezes. Such a situation of a city bears a great
					resemblance to autumn as regards the changes of the day, inasmuch as the
					difference between morning and evening is great. So it is with regard to the
					winds that are conducive to health, or the contrary. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 7 </head>
				           <p> And I wish to give an account of the other kinds of waters, namely, of such as
					are wholesome and such as are unwholesome, and what bad and what good effects
					may be derived from water; for water contributes much towards health. Such
					waters then as are marshy, stagnant, and belong to lakes, are necessarily hot in
					summer, thick, and have a strong smell, since they have no current; but being
					constantly supplied by rain-water, and the <pb n="p.24"/>sun heating them, they
					necessarily want their proper color, are unwholesome and form bile; in winter,
					they become congealed, cold, and muddy with the snow and ice, so that they are
					most apt to engender phlegm, and bring on hoarseness; those who drink them have
					large and obstructed spleens, their bellies are hard, emaciated, and hot; and
					their shoulders, collar-bones, and faces are emaciated; for their flesh is
					melted down and taken up by the spleen, and hence they are slender; such persons
					then are voracious and thirsty; their bellies are very dry both above and below,
					so that they require the strongest medicines.<note>It can scarcely admit of a
						doubt that our author here alludes to scurvy.</note> This disease is
					habitual to them both in summer and in winter, and in addition they are very
					subject to dropsies of a most fatal character; and in summer dysenteries,
					diarrheas, and protracted quartan fevers frequently seize them, and these
					diseases when prolonged dispose such constitutions to dropsies, and thus prove
					fatal. These are the diseases which attack them in summer; but in winter younger
					persons are liable to pneumonia, and maniacal affections; and older persons to
					ardent fevers, from hardness of the belly. Women are subject to oedema and
						leucophlegmasiae;<note>The leucophlegmasia is treated of in different parts
						of the Hippocratic treatises, as Aphor. vii., 29; de Morb. ii. By it he
						evidently meant a species of dropsy.</note> when pregnant they have
					difficult deliveries; their infants are large and swelled, and then during
					nursing they become wasted and sickly, and the lochial discharge after
					parturition does not proceed properly with the women. The children are
					particularly subject to hernia, and adults to varices and ulcers on their legs,
					so that persons with such constitutions cannot be long-lived, but before the
					usual period they fall into a state of premature old age. And further, the women
					appear to be with child, and when the time of parturition arrives, the fulness
					of the belly disappears, and this happens from dropsy of the uterus. Such waters
					then I reckon bad for every purpose. The next to them in badness are those which
					have their fountains in rocks, so that they must necessarily be hard, or come
					from a soil which produces thermal waters, such as those having iron, <pb n="p.25"/> copper, silver, gold, sulphur, alum, bitumen, or nitre (soda) in
					them; for all these are formed by the force of heat. Good waters cannot proceed
					from such a soil, but those that are hard and of a heating nature, difficult to
					pass by urine, and of difficult evacuation by the bowels. The best are those
					which flow from elevated grounds, and hills of earth; these are sweet, clear,
					and can bear a little wine; they are hot in summer and cold in winter, for such
					necessarily must be the waters from deep wells. But those are most to be
					commended which run to the rising of the sun, and especially to the summer sun;
					for such are necessarily more clear, fragrant, and light. But all such as are
					salty, crude, and harsh, are not good for drink. But there are certain
					constitutions and diseases with which such waters agree when drunk, as I will
					explain presently. Their characters are as follows: the best are such as have
					their fountains to the east; the next, those between the summer risings and
					settings of the sun, and especially those to the risings; and third, those
					between the summer and winter settings; but the worst are those to the south,
					and the parts between the winter rising and setting, and those to the south are
					very bad, but those to the north are better. They are to be used as follows:
					whoever is in good health and strength need not mind, but may always drink
					whatever is at hand. But whoever wishes to drink the most suitable for any
					disease, may accomplish his purpose by attending to the following directions: To
					persons whose bellies are hard and easily burnt up, the sweetest, the lightest,
					and the most limpid waters will be proper; but those persons whose bellies are
					soft, loose, and pituitous, should choose the hardest, those kinds that are most
					crude, and the saltiest, for thus will they be most readily dried up; for such
					waters as are adapted for boiling, and are of a very solvent nature, naturally
					loosen readily and melt down the bowels; but such as are intractable, hard, and
					by no means proper for boiling, these rather bind and dry up the bowels. People
					have deceived themselves with regard to salt waters, from inexperience, for they
					think these waters purgative, whereas they are the very reverse; for such waters
					are crude, and ill adapted <pb n="p.26"/> for boiling, so that the belly is more
					likely to be bound up than loosened by them. And thus it is with regard to the
					waters of springs.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 8 </head>
				           <p> I will now tell how it is with respect to rain-water, and water from snow. Rain
					waters, then, are the lightest, the sweetest, the thinnest, and the clearest;
					for originally the sun raises and attracts the thinnest and lightest part of the
					water, as is obvious from the nature of salts; for the saltish part is left
					behind owing to its thickness and weight, and forms salts; but the sun attracts
					the thinnest part, owing to its lightness, and he abstracts this not only from
					the lakes, but also from the sea, and from all things which contain humidity,
					and there is humidity in everything; and from man himself the sun draws off the
					thinnest and lightest part of the juices. As a strong proof of this, when a man
					walks in the sun, or sits down having a garment on, whatever parts of the body
					the sun shines upon do not sweat, for the sun carries off whatever sweat makes
					its appearance; but those parts which are covered by the garment, or anything
					else, sweat, for the particles of sweat are drawn and forced out by the sun, and
					are preserved by the cover so as not to be dissipated by the sun; but when the
					person comes into the shade the whole body equally perspires, because the sun no
					longer shines upon it. Wherefore, of all kinds of water, these spoil the
					soonest; and rain water has a bad spot smell, because its particles are
					collected and mixed together from most objects, so as to spoil the soonest. And
					in addition to this, when attracted and raised up, being carried about and mixed
					with the air, whatever part of it is turbid and darkish is separated and removed
					from the other, and becomes cloud and mist, but the most attenuated and lightest
					part is left, and becomes sweet, being heated and concocted by the sun, for all
					other things when concocted become sweet. While dissipated then and not in a
					state of consistence it is carried aloft. But when collected and condensed by
					contrary winds, it falls down wherever it happens to be most condensed. For this
					is likely to happen when the clouds being carried along and moving with a wind
					which does not allow them to rest, suddenly encounters another wind and <pb n="p.27"/>other clouds from the opposite direction: there it is first
					condensed, and what is behind is carried up to the spot, and thus it thickens,
					blackens, and is conglomerated, and by its weight it falls down and becomes
					rain. Such, to all appearance, are the best of waters, but they require to be
					boiled and strained; for otherwise they have a bad smell, and occasion
					hoarseness and thickness of the voice to those who drink them. Those from snow
					and ice are all bad, for when once congealed, they never again recover their
					former nature; for whatever is clear, light, and sweet in them, is separated and
					disappears; but the most turbid and weightiest part is left behind. You may
					ascertain this in the following manner: If in winter you will pour water by
					measure into a vessel and expose it to the open air until it is all frozen, and
					then on the following day bring it into a warm situation where the ice will
					thaw, if you will measure the water again when dissolved you will find it much
					less in quantity. This is a proof that the lightest and thinnest part is
					dissipated and dried up by the congelation, and not the heaviest and thickest,
					for that is impossible: wherefore I hold that waters from snow and ice, and
					those allied to them, are the worst of any for all purposes whatever. Such are
					the characters of rain-water, and those from ice and snow. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 9 </head>
				           <p> Men<note>This is a most interesting chapter, as containing the most ancient
						observations which we possess on the important subject of urinary calculi.
						The ancients never improved the theory, nor added much to the facts which
						are here stated by our author. We have given the summary of their opinions
						in the Commentary on PAULUS AEGINETA, B. III., 45. I would beg leave to
						remark that, notwithstanding the number of curious facts which modern
						chemistry has evolved regarding the composition of urinary calculi, the
						etiology of the disease is nearly as obscure now as it was in the days of
						Hippocrates.</note> become affected with the stone, and are seized with
					diseases of the kidneys, strangury, sciatica, and become ruptured, when they
					drink all sorts of waters, and those from great rivers into which other rivulets
					run, or from a lake into which many streams of all sorts flow, and such as are
					brought from a considerable distance. For it is impossible that such waters can
					resemble one another, but one kind is sweet, another saltish and aluminous, and
					some flow from thermal springs; and these being all mixed up together disagree,
					and the strongest part always <pb n="p.28"/>prevails; but the same kind is not
					always the strongest, but sometimes one and sometimes another, according to the
					winds, for the north wind imparts strength to this water, and the south to that,
					and so also with regard to the others. There must be deposits of mud and sand in
					the vessels from such waters, and the aforesaid diseases must be engendered by
					them when drunk, but why not to all I will now explain. When the bowels are
					loose and in a healthy state,<note>Coray remarks that Prosper Martian, in his
						commentary on this passage, confirms the truth of the observation here made,
						that persons affected with calculus have the bowels consipated.</note> and
					when the bladder is not hot, nor the neck of the bladder very contracted, all
					such persons pass water freely, and no concretion forms in the bladder; but
					those in whom the belly is hot, the bladder must be in the same condition; and
					when preternaturally heated, its neck becomes inflamed; and when these things
					happen, the bladder does not expel the urine, but raises its heat excessively.
					And the thinnest part of it is secreted, and the purest part is passed off in
					the form of urine, but the thickest and most turbid part is condensed and
					concreted, at first in small quantity, but afterwards in greater; for being
					rolled about in the urine, whatever is of a thick consistence it assimilates to
					itself, and thus it increases and becomes indurated. And when such persons make
					water, the stone forced down by the urine falls into the neck of the bladder and
					stops the urine, and occasions intense pain; so that calculous children rub
					their privy parts and tear at them, as supposing that the obstruction to the
					urine is situated there. As a proof that it is as I say, persons affected with
					calculus have very limpid urine, because the thickest and foulest part remains
					and is concreted. Thus it generally is in cases of calculus. It forms also in
					children from milk, when it is not wholesome, but very hot and bilious, for it
					heats the bowels and bladder, so that the urine being also heated undergoes the
					same change. And I hold that it is better to give children only the most diluted
					wine, for such will least burn up and dry the veins. Calculi do not form so
					readily in women, for in them the urethra is short and wide, so that in them the
					urine is easily expelled; neither do they rub the pudendum with their hands, nor
					handle <pb n="p.29"/> the passage like males; for the urethra in women opens
					direct into the pudendum, which is not the case with men, neither in them is the
					urethra so wide, and they drink more than children do. Thus, or nearly so, is it
					with regard to them. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 10 </head>
				           <p> And respecting the seasons, one may judge whether the year will prove sickly or
					healthy from the following observations:<note>Coray makes the following remarks
						on the natural characters of the seasons in Greece. The natural temperature
						of the winter in Greece was cold and humid; thus a dry and northerly winter
						was reckoned an unnatural season. Spring was reckoned unnatural when the
						heat and rain were excessive.</note>- If the appearances connected with the
					rising and setting stars be as they should be; if there be rains in autumn; if
					the winter be mild, neither very tepid nor unseasonably cold, and if in spring
					the rains be seasonable, and so also in summer, the year is likely to prove
					healthy. But if the winter be dry and northerly, and the spring showery and
					southerly, the summer will necessarily be of a febrile character, and give rise
					to ophthalmies and dysenteries. For when suffocating heat sets in all of a
					sudden, while the earth is moistened by the vernal showers, and by the south
					wind, the heat is necessarily doubled from the earth, which is thus soaked by
					rain and heated by a burning sun, while, at the same time, men's bellies are not
					in an orderly state, nor the brain properly dried; for it is impossible, after
					such a spring, but that the body and its flesh must be loaded with humors, so
					that very acute fevers will attack all, but especially those of a phlegmatic
					constitution. Dysenteries are also likely to occur to women and those of a very
					humid temperament. And if at the rising of the Dogstar rain and wintery storms
					supervene, and if the etesian winds blow, there is reason to hope that these
					diseases will cease, and that the autumn will be healthy; but if not, it is
					likely to be a fatal season to children and women, but least of all to old men;
					and that convalescents will pass into quartans, and from quartans into dropsies;
					but if the winter be southerly, showery and mild, but the spring northerly, dry,
					and of a wintry character, in the first place women who happen to be with child,
					and whose accouchement should take place in spring, are apt to miscarry; and
					such as bring forth, have feeble and sickly children, so that they either die
					presently or are <pb n="p.30"/>tender, feeble, and sickly, if they live. Such is
					the case with the women. The others are subject to dysenteries and dry
					ophthalmies, and some have catarrhs beginning in the head and descending to the
					lungs. Men of a phlegmatic temperament are likely to have dysenteries; and
					women, also, from the humidity of their nature, the phlegm descending downwards
					from the brain; those who are bilious, too, have dry ophthalmies from the heat
					and dryness of their flesh; the aged, too, have catarrhs from their flabbiness
					and melting of the veins, so that some of them die suddenly and some become
					paralytic on the right side or the left. For when, the winter being southerly
					and the body hot, the blood and veins are not properly constringed; a spring
					that is northerly, dry, and cold, having come on, the brain when it should have
					been expanded and purged, by the coryza and hoarseness is then constringed and
					contracted, so that the summer and the heat occurring suddenly, and a change
					supervening, these diseases fall out. And such cities as lie well to the sun and
					winds, and use good waters, feel these changes less, but such as use marshy and
					pooly waters, and lie well both as regards the winds and the sun, these all feel
					it more. And if the summer be dry, those diseases soon cease, but if rainy, they
					are protracted; and there is danger of any sore that there is becoming
					phagedenic from any cause; and lienteries and dropsies supervene at the
					conclusion of diseases; for the bowels are not readily dried up. And if the
					summer be rainy and southerly, and next the autumn, the winter must, of
					necessity, be sickly, and ardent fevers are likely to attack those that are
					phlegmatic, and more elderly than forty years, and pleurisies and peripneumonies
					those that are bilious. But if the summer is parched and northerly, but the
					autumn rainy and southerly, headache and sphacelus of the brain are likely to
					occur; and in addition hoarseness, coryza, coughs, and in some cases,
					consumption. But if the season is northerly and without water, there being no
					rain, neither after the Dogstar nor Arcturus; this state agrees best with those
					who are naturally phlegmatic, with those who are of a humid temperament, and
					with women; but it is most inimical to the bilious; for they become much parched
					up, and ophthalmies of a dry nature supervene, fevers both acute and chronic,
						<pb n="p.31"/> and in some cases melancholy; for the most humid and watery
					part of the bile being consumed, the thickest and most acrid portion is left,
					and of the blood likewise, when these diseases came upon them. But all these are
					beneficial to the phlegmatic, for they are thereby dried up, and reach winter
					not oppressed with humors, but with them dried up. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 11 </head>
				           <p> Whoever studies and observes these things may be able to foresee most of the
					effects which will result from the changes of the seasons; and one ought to be
					particularly guarded during the greatest changes of the seasons, and neither
					willingly give medicines, nor apply the cautery to the belly, nor make incisions
					there until ten or more days be past. Now, the greatest and most dangerous are
					the two solstices, and especially the summer, and also the two equinoxes, but
					especially the autumnal. One ought also to be guarded about the rising of the
					stars, especially of the Dogstar, then of Arcturus, and then the setting of the
					Pleiades; for diseases are especially apt to prove critical in those days, and
					some prove fatal, some pass off, and all others change to another form and
					another constitution. So it is with regard to them.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 12 </head>
				           <p> I wish to show, respecting Asia and Europe, how, in all respects, they differ
					from one another, and concerning the figure of the inhabitants, for they are
					different, and do not at all resemble one another. To treat of all would be a
					long story, but I will tell you how I think it is with regard to the greatest
					and most marked differences. I say, then, that Asia differs very much from
					Europe as to the nature of all things, both with regard to the productions of
					the earth and the inhabitants, for everything is produced much more beautiful
					and large in Asia; the country is milder, and the dispositions of the
					inhabitants also are more gentle and affectionate. The cause of this is the
					temperature of the seasons, because it lies in the middle of the risings of the
					sun towards the east, and removed from the cold (and heat), for nothing tends to
					growth and mildness so much as when the climate has no predominant quality, but
					a general equality of temperature prevails. It is not everywhere the same with
					regard to Asia, but such parts of the country as lie intermediate between the
					heat and the cold, are the best supplied with <pb n="p.32"/>fruits and trees,
					and have the most genial climate, and enjoy the purest waters, both celestial
					and terrestrial. For neither are they much burnt up by the heat, nor dried up by
					the drought and want of rain, nor do they suffer from the cold; since they are
					well watered from abundant showers and snow, and the fruits of the season, as
					might be supposed, grow in abundance, both such as are raised from seed that has
					been sown, and such plants as the earth produces of its own accord, the fruits
					of which the inhabitants make use of, training them from their wild state and
					transplanting them to a suitable soil; the cattle also which are reared there
					are vigorous, particularly prolific, and bring up young of the fairest
					description; the inhabitants too, are well fed, most beautiful in shape, of
					large stature, and differ little from one another either as to figure or size;
					and the country itself, both as regards its constitution and mildness of the
					seasons, may be said to bear a close resemblance to the spring. Manly courage,
					endurance of suffering, laborious enterprise, and high spirit, could not be
					produced in such a state of things either among the native inhabitants or those
					of a different country, for there pleasure necessarily reigns. For this reason,
					also, the forms of wild beasts there are much varied. Thus it is, as I think,
					with the Egyptians and Libyans.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 13 </head>
				           <p> But concerning those on the right hand of the summer risings of the sun as far
					as the Palus Maeotis (for this is the boundary of Europe and Asia), it is with
					them as follows: the inhabitants there differ far more from one another than
					those I have treated of above, owing to the differences of the seasons and the
					nature of the soil. But with regard to the country itself, matters are the same
					there as among all other men; for where the seasons undergo the greatest and
					most rapid changes, there the country is the wildest and most unequal; and you
					will find the greatest variety of mountains, forests, plains, and meadows; but
					where the seasons do not change much there the country is the most even; and, if
					one will consider it, so is it also with regard to the inhabitants; for the
					nature of some is like to a country covered with trees and well watered; of
					some, to a thin soil deficient in water; of others, to fenny and marshy places;
					and of <pb n="p.33"/>some again, to a plain of bare and parched land. For the
					seasons which modify their natural frame of body are varied, and the greater the
					varieties of them the greater also will be the differences of their shapes.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 14 </head>
				           <p> I will pass over the smaller differences among the nations, but will now treat
					of such as are great either from nature, or custom; and, first, concerning the
					Macrocephali. There is no other race of men which have heads in the least
					resembling theirs. At first, usage was the principal cause of the length of
					their head, but now nature cooperates with usage. They think those the most
					noble who have the longest heads. It is thus with regard to the usage:
					immediately after the child is born, and while its head is still tender, they
					fashion it with their hands, and constrain it to assume a lengthened shape by
					applying bandages and other suitable contrivances whereby the spherical form of
					the head is destroyed, and it is made to increase in length. Thus, at first,
					usage operated, so that this constitution was the result of force: but, in the
					course of time, it was formed naturally; so that usage had nothing to do with
					it; for the semen comes from all parts of the body, sound from the sound parts,
					and unhealthy from the unhealthy parts. If, then, children with bald heads are
					born to parents with bald heads; and children with blue eves to parents who have
					blue eyes; and if the children of parents having distorted eyes squint also for
					the most part; and if the same may be said of other forms of the body, what is
					to prevent it from happening that a child with a long head should be produced by
					a parent having a long head? But now these things do not happen as they did
					formerly, for the custom no longer prevails owing to their intercourse with
					other men. Thus it appears to me to be with regard to them.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 15 </head>
				           <p> As to the inhabitants of Phasis, their country is fenny, warm, humid, and
					wooded; copious and severe rains occur there at all seasons; and the life of the
					inhabitants is spent among the fens; for their dwellings are constructed of wood
					and reeds, and are erected amidst the waters; they seldom practice walking
					either to the city or the market, but sail about, up and down, in canoes
					constructed out of single trees, for there are many canals <pb n="p.34"/>there.
					They drink the hot and stagnant waters, both when rendered putrid by the sun,
					and when swollen with rains. The Phasis itself is the most stagnant of all
					rivers, and runs the smoothest; all the fruits which spring there are
					unwholesome, feeble and imperfect growth, owing to the redundance of water, and
					on this account they do not ripen, for much vapor from the waters overspreads
					the country. For these reasons the Phasians have shapes different from those of
					all other men; for they are large in stature, and of a very gross habit of body,
					so that not a joint nor vein is visible; in color they are sallow, as if
					affected with jaundice. Of all men they have the roughest voices, from their
					breathing an atmosphere which is not clear, but misty and humid; they are
					naturally rather languid in supporting bodily fatigue. The seasons undergo but
					little change either as to heat or cold; their winds for the most part are
					southerly, with the exception of one peculiar to the country, which sometimes
					blows strong, is violent and hot, and is called by them the wind cenchron. The
					north wind scarcely reaches them, and when it does blow it is weak and gentle.
					Thus it is with regard to the different nature and shape of the inhabitants of
					Asia and Europe.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 16 </head>
				           <p> And with regard to the pusillanimity and cowardice of the inhabitants, the
					principal reason the Asiatics are more unwarlike and of gentler disposition than
					the Europeans is, the nature of the seasons, which do not undergo any great
					changes either to heat or cold, or the like; for there is neither excitement of
					the understanding nor any strong change of the body whereby the temper might be
					ruffled and they be roused to inconsiderate emotion and passion, rather than
					living as they do always in the state. It is changes of all kinds which arouse
					understanding of mankind, and do not allow them to get into a torpid condition.
					For these reasons, it appears to me, the Asiatic race is feeble, and further,
					owing to their laws; for monarchy prevails in the greater part of Asia, and
					where men are not their own masters nor independent, but are the slaves of
					others, it is not a matter of consideration with them how they may acquire
					military discipline, but how they may seem not to be warlike, for the dangers
					are not equally shared, since they must serve as soldiers,<pb n="p.35"/> perhaps
					endure fatigue, and die for their masters, far from their children, their wives,
					and other friends; and whatever noble and manly actions they may perform lead
					only to the aggrandizement of their masters, whilst the fruits which they reap
					are dangers and death; and, in addition to all this, the lands of such persons
					must be laid waste by the enemy and want of culture. Thus, then, if any one be
					naturally warlike and courageous, his disposition will be changed by the
					institutions. As a strong proof of all this, such Greeks or barbarians in Asia
					as are not under a despotic form of government, but are independent, and enjoy
					the fruits of their own labors, are of all others the most warlike; for these
					encounter dangers on their own account, bear the prizes of their own valor, and
					in like manner endure the punishment of their own cowardice. And you will find
					the Asiatics differing from one another, for some are better and others more
					dastardly; of these differences, as I stated before, the changes of the seasons
					are the cause. Thus it is with Asia. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 17 </head>
				           <p> In Europe there is a Scythian race, called Sauromatae, which inhabits the
					confines of the Palus Maeotis, and is different from all other races. Their
					women mount on horseback, use the bow, and throw the javelin from their horses,
					and fight with their enemies as long as they are virgins; and they do not lay
					aside their virginity until they kill three of their enemies, nor have any
					connection with men until they perform the sacrifices according to law. Whoever
					takes to herself a husband, gives up riding on horseback unless the necessity of
					a general expedition obliges her. They have no right breast; for while still of
					a tender age their mothers heat strongly a copper instrument constructed for
					this very purpose, and apply it to the right breast, which is burnt up, and its
					development being arrested, all the strength and fullness are determined to the
					right shoulder and arm.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 18 </head>
				           <p> As the other Scythians have a peculiarity of shape, and do not resemble any
					other, the same observation applies to the Egyptians, only that the latter are
					oppressed by heat and the former by cold. What is called the Scythian desert is
					a prairie, rich in meadows, high-lying, and well watered; for the rivers which
					carry off the water from the plains are large. There live <pb n="p.36"/>those
					Scythians which are called Nomades, because they have no houses, but live in
					wagons. The smallest of these wagons have four wheels, but some have six; they
					are covered in with felt, and they are constructed in the manner of houses, some
					having but a single apartment, and some three; they are proof against rain,
					snow, and winds. The wagons are drawn by yokes of oxen, some of two and others
					of three, and all without horns, for they have no horns, owing to the cold. In
					these wagons the women live, but the men are carried about on horses, and the
					sheep, oxen, and horses accompany them; and they remain on any spot as long as
					there is provender for their cattle, and when that fails they migrate to some
					other place. They eat boiled meat, and drink the milk of mares, and also eat
					hippace, which is cheese prepared from the milk of the mare. Such is their mode
					of life and their customs. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 19 </head>
				           <p> In respect of the seasons and figure of body, the Scythian race, like the
					Egyptian, have a uniformity of resemblance, different from all other nations;
					they are by no means prolific, and the wild beasts which are indigenous there
					are small in size and few in number, for the country lies under the Northern
					Bears, and the Rhiphaean mountains, whence the north wind blows; the sun comes
					very near to them only when in the summer solstice, and warms them but for a
					short period, and not strongly; and the winds blowing from the hot regions of
					the earth do not reach them, or but seldom, and with little force; but the winds
					from the north always blow, congealed, as they are, by the snow, ice, and much
					water, for these never leave the mountains, which are thereby rendered
					uninhabitable. A thick fog covers the plains during the day, and amidst it they
					live, so that winter may be said to be always present with them; or, if they
					have summer, it is only for a few days, and the heat is not very strong. Their
					plains are high-lying and naked, not crowned with mountains, but extending
					upwards under the Northern Bears. The wild beasts there are not large, but such
					as can be sheltered underground; for the cold of winter and the barrenness of
					the country prevent their growth, and because they have no covert nor shelter.
					The changes of the seasons, too, are not great nor violent, for, in <pb n="p.37"/> fact, they change gradually; and therefore their figures resemble one
					another, as they all equally use the same food, and the same clothing summer and
					winter, respiring a humid and dense atmosphere, and drinking water from snow and
					ice; neither do they make any laborious exertions, for neither body nor mind is
					capable of enduring fatigue when the changes of the seasons are not great. For
					these reasons their shapes are gross and fleshy, with ill-marked joints, of a
					humid temperament, and deficient in tone: the internal cavities, and especially
					those of the intestines, are full of humors; for the belly cannot possibly be
					dry in such a country, with such a constitution and in such a climate; but owing
					to their fat, and the absence of hairs from their bodies, their shapes resemble
					one another, the males being all alike, and so also with the women; for the
					seasons being of a uniform temperature, no corruption or deterioration takes
					place in the concretion of the semen, unless from some violent cause, or from
					disease. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 20 </head>
				           <p> I Will give you a strong proof of the humidity (laxity?) of their constitutions.
					You will find the greater part of the Scythians, and all the Nomades, with marks
					of the cautery on their shoulders, arms, wrists, breasts, hip-joints, and loins,
					and that for no other reason but the humidity and flabbiness of their
					constitution, for they can neither strain with their bows, nor launch the
					javelin from their shoulder owing to their humidity and atony: but when they are
					burnt, much of the humidity in their joints is dried up, and they become better
					braced, better fed, and their joints get into a more suitable condition. They
					are flabby and squat at first, because, as in Egypt, they are not swathed (?);
					and then they pay no attention to horsemanship, so that they may be adepts at
					it; and because of their sedentary mode of life; for the males, when they cannot
					be carried about on horseback, sit the most of their time in the wagon, and
					rarely practise walking, because of their frequent migrations and shiftings of
					situation; and as to the women, it is amazing how flabby and sluggish they are.
					The Scythian race are tawny from the cold, and not from the intense heat of the
					sun, for the whiteness of the skin is parched by the cold, and becomes
					tawny.</p>
			         </div>
			         <pb n="p.38"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 21 </head>
				           <p> It is impossible that persons of such a constitution could be prolific, for,
					with the man, the sexual desires are not strong, owing to the laxity of his
					constitution, the softness and coldness of his belly, from all which causes it
					is little likely that a man should be given to venery; and besides, from being
					jaded by exercise on horseback, the men become weak in their desires. On the
					part of the men these are the causes; but on that of the women, they are
					embonpoint and humidity; for the womb cannot take in the semen, nor is the
					menstrual discharge such as it should be, but scanty and at too long intervals;
					and the mouth of the womb is shut up by fat and does not admit the semen; and,
					moreover, they themselves are indolent and fat, and their bellies cold and soft.
					From these causes the Scythian race is not prolific. Their female servants
					furnish a strong proof of this; for they no sooner have connection with a man
					than they prove with child, owing to their active course of life and the
					slenderness of body.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 22 </head>
				           <p> And, in addition to these, there are many eunuchs among the Scythians, who
					perform female work, and speak like women. Such persons are called effeminates.
					The inhabitants of the country attribute the cause of their impotence to a god,
					and venerate and worship such persons, every one dreading that the like might
					befall himself; but to me it appears that such affections are just as much
					divine as all others are, and that no one disease is either more divine or more
					human than another, but that all are alike divine, for that each has its own
					nature, and that no one arises without a natural cause. But I will explain how I
					think that the affection takes its rise. From continued exercise on horseback
					they are seized with chronic defluxions in their joints owing to their legs
					always hanging down below their horses; they afterwards become lame and stiff at
					the hip-joint, such of them, at least, as are severely attacked with it. They
					treat themselves in this way: when the disease is commencing, they open the vein
					behind either ear, and when the blood flows, sleep, from feebleness, seizes
					them, and afterwards they awaken, some in good health and others not. To me it
					appears that the semen is altered by this treatment, for there are veins behind
					the ears which, if cut, induce impotence; now, these veins would appear <pb n="p.39"/>to me to be cut.<note>This opinion of our author was no doubt
						founded on the erroneous notion regarding the distribution of the veins
						which prevailed in his time, and which we find advocated in the tract "on
						the Nature of Man," and elsewhere. (See Aristot., H. N., iii., 3.) Coray
						strives hard, in his annotations on this passage, to make out that the fact
						may be as he stated by his ancient countryman, although the hypothesis by
						which he explained it be false. It is singular, however, that, after the
						lapse of more than two thousand years, Phrenology should have come to the
						assistance of Hippocrates in this case. I need scarcely remark that Gall and
						his followers hold that the cerebellum is the seat o the animal appetites,
						so that, if this be really the fact, a close sympathy between the back of
						the head and the genital organs may be very legitimately inferred. At all
						events, this coincidence between ancient observation and modern hypothesis
						must be admitted to be very remarkable. </note> Such persons afterwards,
					when they go in to women and cannot have connection with them, at first do not
					think much about it, but remain quiet; but when, after making the attempt two,
					three, or more times, they succeed no better, fancying they have committed some
					offence against the god whom they blame for the affection, they put on female
					attire, reproach themselves for effeminacy, play the part of women, and perform
					the same work as women do. This the rich among the Scythians endure, not the
					basest, but the most noble and powerful, owing to their riding on horseback; for
					the poor are less affected, as they do not ride on horses. And yet, if this
					disease had been more divine than the others, it ought not to have befallen the
					most noble and the richest of the Scythians alone, but all alike, or rather
					those who have little, as not being able to pay honors to the gods, if, indeed,
					they delight in being thus rewarded by men, and grant favors in return; for it
					is likely that the rich sacrifice more to the gods, and dedicate more votive
					offerings, inasmuch as they have wealth, and worship the gods; whereas the poor,
					from want, do less in this way, and, moreover, upbraid the gods for not giving
					them wealth, so that those who have few possessions were more likely to bear the
					punishments of these offences than the rich. But, as I formerly said, these
					affections are divine just as much as others, for each springs from a natural
					cause, and this disease arises among the Scythians from such a cause as I have
					stated. But it attacks other men in like manner, for whenever men ride much and
					very frequently on horseback, then many are affected with rheums in the joints,
					sciatica, and gout, <pb n="p.40"/>and they are inept at venery. But these
					complaints befall the Scythians, and they are the most impotent of men for the
					aforesaid causes, and because they always wear breeches, and spend the most of
					their time on horseback, so as not to touch their privy parts with the hands,
					and from the cold and fatigue they forget the sexual desire, and do not make the
					attempt until after they have lost their virility. Thus it is with the race of
					the Scythians.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 23 </head>
				           <p> The other races in Europe differ from one another, both as to stature and shape,
					owing to the changes of the seasons, which are very great and frequent, and
					because the heat is strong, the winters severe, and there are frequent rains,
					and again protracted droughts, and winds, from which many and diversified
					changes are induced. These changes are likely to have an effect upon generation
					in the coagulation of the semen, as this process cannot be the same in summer as
					in winter, nor in rainy as in dry weather; wherefore, I think, that the figures
					of Europeans differ more than those of Asiatics; and they differ very much from
					one another as to stature in the same city; for vitiations of the semen occur in
					its coagulation more frequently during frequent changes of the seasons, than
					where they are alike and equable. And the same may be said of their
					dispositions, for the wild, and unsociable, and the passionate occur in such a
					constitution; for frequent excitement of the mind induces wildness, and
					extinguishes sociableness and mildness of disposition, and therefore I think the
					inhabitants of Europe more courageous than those of Asia; for a climate which is
					always the same induces indolence, but a changeable climate, laborious exertions
					both of body and mind; and from rest and indolence cowardice is engendered, and
					from laborious exertions and pains, courage. On this account the inhabitants of
					Europe are than the Asiatics, and also owing to their institutions, because they
					are not governed by kings like the latter, for where men are governed by kings
					there they must be very cowardly, as I have stated before; for their souls are
					enslaved, and they will not willingly, or readily undergo dangers in order to
					promote the power of another; but those that are free undertake dangers on their
					own account, <pb n="p.41"/>and not for the sake of others; they court hazard and
					go out to meet it, for they themselves bear off the rewards of victory, and thus
					their institutions contribute not a little to their courage. Such is the general
					character of Europe and Asia.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 24 </head>
				           <p> And there are in Europe other tribes, differing from one another in stature,
					shape, and courage: the differences are those I formerly mentioned, and will now
					explain more clearly. Such as inhabit a country which is mountainous, rugged,
					elevated, and well watered, and where the changes of the seasons are very great,
					are likely to have great variety of shapes among them, and to be naturally of an
					enterprising and warlike disposition; and such persons are apt to have no little
					of the savage and ferocious in their nature; but such as dwell in places which
					are low-lying, abounding in meadows and ill ventilated, and who have a larger
					proportion of hot than of cold winds, and who make use of warm waters- these are
					not likely to be of large stature nor well proportioned, but are of a broad
					make, fleshy, and have black hair; and they are rather of a dark than of a light
					complexion, and are less likely to be phlegmatic than bilious; courage and
					laborious enterprise are not naturally in them, but may be engendered in them by
					means of their institutions. And if there be rivers in the country which carry
					off the stagnant and rain water from it, these may be wholesome and clear; but
					if there be no rivers, but the inhabitants drink the waters of fountains, and
					such as are stagnant and marshy, they must necessarily have prominent bellies
					and enlarged spleens. But such as inhabit a high country, and one that is level,
					windy, and well-watered, will be large of stature, and like to one another; but
					their minds will be rather unmanly and gentle. Those who live on thin,
					ill-watered, and bare soils, and not well attempered in the changes of the
					seasons, in such a country they are likely to be in their persons rather hard
					and well braced, rather of a blond than a dark complexion, and in disposition
					and passions haughty and self-willed. For, where the changes of the seasons are
					most frequent, and where they differ most from one another, there you will find
					their forms, dispositions, and nature the most varied. These are the strongest
					of the natural causes of difference, and next the country in which<pb n="p.42"/>
					one lives, and the waters; for, in general, you will find the forms and
					dispositions of mankind to correspond with the nature of the country; for where
					the land is fertile, soft, and well-watered, and supplied with waters from very
					elevated situations, so as to be hot in summer and cold in winter, and where the
					seasons are fine, there the men are fleshy, have ill-formed joints, and are of a
					humid temperament; they are not disposed to endure labor, and, for the most
					part, are base in spirit; indolence and sluggishness are visible in them, and to
					the arts they are dull, and not clever nor acute. When the country is bare, not
					fenced, and rugged, blasted by the winter and scorched by the sun, there you may
					see the men hardy, slender, with well-shaped joints, well-braced, and shaggy;
					sharp industry and vigilance accompany such a constitution; in morals and
					passions they are haughty and opinionative, inclining rather to the fierce than
					to the mild; and you will find them acute and ingenious as regards the arts, and
					excelling in military affairs; and likewise all the other productions of the
					earth corresponding to the earth itself. Thus it is with regard to the most
					opposite natures and shapes; drawing conclusions from them, you may judge of the
					rest without any risk of error.</p>
			         </div>


		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
