<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Antigone</title>      
                <title type="sub">Modernized by Perseus</title>
                <author>Sophocles</author>
                <editor role="translator">Richard Jebb</editor>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>About 90Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Sophocles</author>
                        <title>Sophocles The Plays and Fragments</title>
                        <title type="sub">The Antigone</title>
                        <editor role="translator">Richard Jebb</editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>Cambridge</pubPlace>
                            <publisher>Cambridge University Press</publisher>
                            <date>1891</date>
                        </imprint>
                        <biblScope unit="volume">3</biblScope>
                    </monogr>
                    <ref target="https://archive.org/details/sophocles03soph/page/8/mode/2up">Open Content Alliance</ref>
                </biblStruct>
                
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="line"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div//tei:l[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts lines</p>
                </cRefPattern>  
            </refsDecl>
            <!--<refsDecl n="CTS">
                
                <cRefPattern n="card" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts cards</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                
            </refsDecl>-->
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2017-02-02" who="Lisa Cerrato">fixing change log, adding line numbers, structural revisions to lines</change>
            <change when="2016-01-15" who="TDBuck">CTS RefsDecl added</change>
            <change when="2015" who="Stella Dee">converted to EpiDoc</change>
            <change when="2013-09-13" who="balmas01">moving Greg's work-in-progress on CTS-izing
                greco-roman collection texts to a Work directory</change>
            <change when="2013-06-30" who="gcrane">the card divs had had a line range but there was a problem with this, so we just have the start line in the n attribute.</change>
            <change when="2009-12-08" who="rsingh04">moved more xml files around based on copyright status</change>
            <change when="2006-02-10" who="packel">places/dates now actually tagged</change>
            <change when="2005-08-01" who="packel">removed stray item tags</change>
            <change when="2005-07-25" who="packel">Converted to XML</change>
            <change when="2004-04-21" who="mimno">added card 1s</change>
            <change when="2003-07-01" who="yorkc">Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)</change>
            <change when="2000-03-04" who="dasmith">Added separate funder entity to TEI header.</change>
            <change when="2000-02-15" who="amahoney">use n attribute on sp element to carry over the speaker name when the speech is interrupted by a card break; this also requires that the card break at the end come after the close of the sp, not within</change>
            <change when="2000-02-08" who="amahoney">bring up to P</change>
            <change when="2000-02-08" who="Anne Mahoney"></change>
            <change when="1995-06-01" who="Lisa Cerrato">Added missing speaker tags for cards which had none.</change>
            <change when="1991-08-01" who="EM">Put in Gibert's revisions, and revise DTDs and
                recheck texts.</change>
            <change when="1991-08-01" who="John Gilbert">Review and comment on modernization of translation.</change>
            <change when="1990-09-19" who="EM">Final check of cardbreaks, tags, and linenumbers.</change>
            <change when="1990-07-01" who="Jane Chaplin">ed. Proofread text</change>
            <change when="1988" who="Pierre Habel, John Gilbert">This text was modernized by Pierre Habel, so as to remove archaisms. It was reviewed by John Gibert, and revisions were made accordingly.</change>
            <change when="1987" who="EM, Scott Ettinger and Roger Travis">Text scanned at U. Chicago in 1987. Basic SGML tagging by EM, Scott Ettinger and Roger Travis.</change>
</revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>

    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0011.tlg002.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                <milestone unit="card" n="1"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="1" resp="p">Ismene, my sister, true child of my own mother, do you know any evil out
                            of all the evils bequeathed by Oedipus that Zeus will not fulfil for the
                            two of us in our lifetime? There is nothing—no pain, no ruin,</l>
                        <l n="5" resp="p">no shame, nor dishonor—that I have not
                            seen in your sufferings and mine. And now what is this new edict that
                            they say the general has just decreed to all the city? Do you know
                            anything? Have you heard? Or does it escape you that </l>
                        <l n="10" resp="p">evils from our enemies are on the march against
                            our friends?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="11" resp="p">To me no word of our friends, Antigone, either bringing joy or bringing
                            pain has come since we two were robbed of our two brothers who died in
                            one day by a double blow. </l>
                           <l n="15" resp="p">And since
                            the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> army has fled during
                            this night, I have learned nothing further, whether better fortune is
                            mine, or further ruin.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="18" resp="p">I knew it well, so I was trying to bring you outside the courtyard gates
                            to this end, that you alone might hear.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="20" resp="p">Hear what? It is clear that you are
                            brooding on some dark news.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="21" resp="p">Why not? Has not Creon destined our brothers, the one to honored burial,
                            the other to unburied shame? Eteocles, they say, with due observance of
                            right and custom, he has laid in the earth </l>
                        <l n="25" resp="p">for his honor among the dead below. As for the poor
                            corpse of Polyneices, however, they say that an edict has been published
                            to the townsmen that no one shall bury him or mourn him, but instead
                            leave him unwept, unentombed, for the birds a pleasing store</l>
                        <l n="30" resp="p">as they look to satisfy their hunger.
                            Such, it is said, is the edict that the good Creon has laid down for you
                            and for me—yes, for me—and it is said that he is coming here to proclaim
                            it for the certain knowledge of those who do not already know. They say
                            that he does not conduct this business lightly, </l>
                        <l n="35" resp="p">but whoever performs any of these rites, for him the
                            fate appointed is death by public stoning among the entire city. This is
                            how things stand for you, and so you will soon show your nature, whether
                            you are noble-minded, or the corrupt daughter of a noble line.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="39"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="39" resp="p">Poor sister, if things have come to this, what would I </l>
                        <l n="40" resp="p">profit by loosening or tightening this knot?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="41" resp="p">Consider whether you will share the toil and the task.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="42" resp="p">What are you hazarding? What do you intend?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="43" resp="p">Will you join your hand to mine in order to lift his corpse?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="44" resp="p">You plan to bury him—when it is forbidden to the city?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="45" resp="p">Yes, he is my brother, and yours
                            too, even if you wish it otherwise. I will never be convicted of
                            betraying him.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="47" resp="p">Hard girl! Even when Creon has forbidden it?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="48" resp="p">No, he has no right to keep me from my own.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="49" resp="p">Ah, no! Think, sister, how our father </l>
                        <l n="50" resp="p">perished in hatred and infamy, when, because of the crimes that he
                            himself detected, he smashed both his eyes with self-blinding hand; then
                            his mother-wife, two names in one, with a twisted noose destroyed her
                                life; </l>
                        <l n="55" resp="p">lastly, our two brothers
                            in a single day, both unhappy murderers of their own flesh and blood,
                            worked with mutual hands their common doom. And now we, in turn—we two
                            who have been left all alone—consider how much more miserably we will be
                            destroyed, if in defiance of the law </l>
                        <l n="60" resp="p">we transgress against an autocrat’s decree or his powers.
                            No, we must remember, first, that ours is a woman’s nature, and
                            accordingly not suited to battles against men; and next, that we are
                            ruled by the more powerful, so that we must obey in these things and in
                            things even more stinging. </l>
                        <l n="65" resp="p">I, therefore, will
                            ask those below for pardon, since I am forced to this, and will obey
                            those who have come to authority. It is foolish to do what is
                            fruitless.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="69"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="69" resp="p">I would not encourage you—no, nor, even if you were willing
                                later, </l>
                        <l n="70" resp="p">would I welcome you as
                            my partner in this action. No, be the sort that pleases you. I will bury
                            him—it would honor me to die while doing that. I shall rest with him,
                            loved one with loved one, a pious criminal. For the time is
                                greater </l>
                        <l n="75" resp="p">that I must serve the
                            dead than the living, since in that world I will rest forever. But if
                            you so choose, continue to dishonor what the gods in honor have
                            established.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="78" resp="p">I do them no dishonor. But to act in violation of the
                            citizens’ will—of that I am by nature incapable.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="80" resp="p">You can make that your pretext!
                            Regardless, I will go now to heap a tomb over the brother I love.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="82" resp="p">Oh no, unhappy sister! I fear for you!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="83" resp="p">Do not tremble for me. Straighten out your own destiny.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="84" resp="p">Then at least disclose the deed to no one before you do it.</l>
                        <l n="85" resp="p">Conceal it, instead, in secrecy—and so,
                            too, will I.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="86" resp="p">Go on! Denounce it! You will be far more hated for your silence, if you
                            fail to proclaim these things to everyone.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="88" resp="p">You have a hot heart for chilling deeds.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="89" resp="p">I know that I please those whom I am most bound to please.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="90" resp="p">Yes, if you will also have the
                            power. But you crave the impossible.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="91" resp="p">Why then, when my strength fails, I will have finished.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="92" resp="p">An impossible hunt should not be tried in the first place.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="93" resp="p">If you mean that, you will have my hatred, and you will be subject to
                            punishment as the enemy of the dead. </l>
                        <l n="95" resp="p">But leave me and the foolish plan I have authored to suffer this
                            terrible thing, for I will not suffer anything so terrible that my death
                            will lack honor.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="98" resp="p">Go, then, if you so decide. And of this be sure: though
                            your path is foolish, to your loved ones your love is straight and
                                true.<stage>Exit Antigone on the spectators’ left. Ismene exits into
                                the palace.</stage></l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="100"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="choral">
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="1">
                    <stage>Enter the Chorus on the right.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="100" resp="p">Shaft of the sun, fairest light of all that have dawned
                                on <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> of the seven
                                gates, you have shone forth at last, eye of golden day, advancing
                                over Dirce’s streams!</l>
                        <l n="105" resp="p">You have goaded with a sharper bit the
                            warrior of the white shield, who came from <placeName
                                key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> in full armor, driving him to
                            headlong retreat.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="110"/>
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="110" resp="p">He set out against our land
                            because of the strife-filled claims of Polyneices, and like a screaming
                            eagle he flew over into our land, covered by his snow-white
                                wing, </l>
                        <l n="115" resp="p">with a mass of weapons
                            and crested helmets.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="117"/>
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="117" resp="p">He paused above our dwellings; he
                            gaped around our sevenfold portals with spears thirsting for blood; but
                            he left </l>
                        <l n="120" resp="p">before his jaws were ever glutted with our gore, or
                                before the Fire-god’s pine-fed flame had seized our crown of towers. </l>
                        <l n="125" resp="p">So
                            fierce was the crash of battle swelling about his back, a match too hard
                            to win for the rival of the dragon.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="127"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="127" resp="p">For Zeus detests above all the
                            boasts of a proud tongue. And when he saw them advancing in a swollen
                                flood, </l>
                        <l n="130" resp="p">arrogant their clanging
                            gold, he dashed with brandished fire one who was already starting to
                            shout victory when he had reached our ramparts.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="134"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="134" resp="p">Staggered, he fell to the earth
                            with a crash, </l>
                        <l n="135" resp="p">torch in hand, a man
                            possessed by the frenzy of the mad attack, who just now was raging
                            against us with the blasts of his tempestuous hate. But his threats did
                            not fare as he had hoped, and to the other enemies mighty Ares dispensed
                            each their own dooms with hard blows, </l>
                        <l n="140" resp="p">Ares, our mighty ally at the turning-point.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="141"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="141" resp="p">For the seven captains, stationed
                            against an equal number at the seven gates, left behind their brazen
                            arms in tribute to Zeus the turner of battle—all but the accursed pair
                            who, born of one father and one </l>
                        <l n="145" resp="p">mother, set against each other their spears, both victorious, and who
                            now share in a common death.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="148"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="148" resp="p">But since Victory whose name is
                            glory has come to us, smiling in joy equal to the joy of chariot-rich
                                <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, </l>
                        <l n="150" resp="p">let us make for ourselves forgetfulness after
                            the recent wars, and visit all the temples of the gods with night-long
                            dance and song. And may Bacchus, who shakes the earth of <placeName
                                key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, rule our dancing!</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="155"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="155" resp="p">But look, the king of the land is
                            coming here, Creon, the son of Menoeceus, our new ruler in accordance
                            with the new circumstances fated by the gods. What policy is he setting
                            in motion, </l>
                        <l n="160" resp="p">that he has proposed
                            this special conference of elders, and summoned it by a general
                            mandate?</l>

                    </sp></div></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="162"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                    <stage>Enter Creon, with two attendants.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="162" resp="p">My fellow citizens! First, the
                            gods, after tossing the fate of our city on wild waves, have once more
                            righted it. Second, I have ordered you through my messengers to come
                                here </l>
                        <l n="165" resp="p">apart from all the rest,
                            because I knew, first of all, how constant was your reverence for the
                            power of the throne of Laius; how, again, you were reverent, when
                            Oedipus was guiding our city; and lastly, how, when he was dead, you
                            still maintained loyal thoughts towards his children. </l>
                        <l n="170" resp="p">Since, then, these latter have fallen in one day by a
                            twofold doom—each striking, each struck, both with the stain of a
                            brother’s murder—I now possess all the power and the throne according to
                            my kinship with the dead. </l>
                        <l n="175" resp="p">Now, it is impossible to know fully any man’s character,
                            will, or judgment, until he has been proved by the test of rule and
                            law-giving. For if anyone who directs the entire city does not cling to
                            the best and wisest plans, </l>
                        <l n="180" resp="p">but because of some
                            fear keeps his lips locked, then, in my judgment, he is and has long
                            been the most cowardly traitor. And if any man thinks a friend more
                            important than his fatherland, that man, I say, is of no account. Zeus,
                            god who sees all things always, be my witness— </l>
                        <l n="185" resp="p">I would not be silent if I saw ruin, instead of safety,
                            marching upon the citizens. Nor would I ever make a man who is hostile
                            to my country a friend to myself, because I know this, that our country
                            is the ship that bears us safe, and that only when </l>
                        <l n="190" resp="p">we sail her on a straight course can we make
                            true friends. Such are the rules by which I strengthen this city. Akin
                            to these is the edict which I have now published to the citizenry
                            concerning the sons of Oedipus: Eteocles, who fell fighting</l>
                        <l n="195" resp="p">in behalf of our city and who excelled
                            all in battle, they shall entomb and heap up every sacred offering that
                            descends to the noblest of the dead below. But as for his brother,
                            Polyneices, I mean, who on his return from exile wanted to burn to the
                                ground </l>
                        <l n="200" resp="p">the city of his fathers and his race’s gods, and wanted
                            to feed on kindred blood and lead the remnant into slavery—it has been
                            proclaimed to the city that no one shall give him funeral honors or
                            lamentation, </l>
                        <l n="205" resp="p">but all must leave him unburied and a sight of shame,
                            with his body there for birds and dogs to eat. This is my will, and
                            never will I allow the traitor to stand in honor before the just. But
                            whoever has good will to <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                                >Thebes</placeName>, </l>
                        <l n="210" resp="p">he shall
                            be honored by me in death as in life.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="211"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="211" resp="p">That is your will, Creon, towards this city’s enemy and
                            its friend. And the power is yours, I believe, to make use of every law
                            whatsoever, both concerning the dead and all us who live.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="215" resp="p">See, then, that you be guardians
                            of my commands.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="216" resp="p">Lay the weight of this task on some younger man.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="217" resp="p">That is not what I meant—the guards for the corpse are already in
                            place.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="218" resp="p">Then what is this other command that you would give?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="219" resp="p">That you not give way to the breakers of my commands.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="220" resp="p">There is no one so foolish as to
                            crave death.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="221" resp="p">I assure you, that is the wage for disobedience. Yet by just the hope of
                            it, money has many times corrupted men.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <stage>Enter Guard.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="223" resp="p">My king, I will not say that I arrive breathless because of speed, or
                            from the action of a swift foot. </l>
                        <l n="225" resp="p">For often I brought myself to a stop because of my thoughts, and
                            wheeled round in my path to return. My mind was telling me many things:
                            <q type="thought">Fool, why do you go to where your arrival will mean your punishment?</q>
                            <q type="thought">Idiot, are you dallying again? If Creon learns it from another, must
                            you not suffer for it?</q> </l>
                        <l n="230" resp="p">So
                            debating, I made my way unhurriedly, slow, and thus a short road was
                            made long. At last, however, the view prevailed that I should come
                            here—to you. Even if my report brings no good, still will I tell
                                you, </l>
                        <l n="235" resp="p">since I come with a good
                            grip on one hope, that I can suffer nothing except what is my fate.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="237"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="237" resp="p">And what is it that so disheartens you?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="238" resp="p">I want to tell you first about myself—I did not do the deed, nor did I
                            see the doer, </l>
                        <l n="240" resp="p">so it would be wrong
                            that I should come to any harm.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="241" resp="p">Like a bowman you aim well at your target from a distance, and all around
                            you hedge yourself off well from the deed. It is clear that you have
                            some unheard-of thing to tell.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="243" resp="p">That I do, for terrible news imposes great hesitation.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="244" resp="p">Then tell it, will you, and so unburdened go away?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="245" resp="p">Well, here it is. The corpse—some
                            one has just given it burial and disappeared after sprinkling thirsty
                            dust on the flesh and performing the other rites that piety demands.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="248" resp="p">What are you saying? What man dared do this?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="249" resp="p">I do not know. For there was no scar of a pickax to be seen
                                there, </l>
                        <l n="250" resp="p">no earth thrown up by a
                            mattock. The ground was hard and dry, unbroken, not rolled over by
                            wheels. The doer was someone who left no trace. When the first
                            day-watchman showed it to us, a discomforting amazement fell on us
                                all. </l>
                        <l n="255" resp="p">The dead man was veiled
                            from us—not shut within a tomb, but a light cover of dust was on him, as
                            if put there by the hand of one who shunned a curse. And no sign was
                            visible that any beast of prey or any dog had approached or torn him.
                            Then evil words flew thick and loud among us, </l>
                        <l n="260" resp="p">guard accusing guard. It would even have come to blows
                            in the end, nor was there anyone there to prevent it: every man was the
                            culprit, and no one was plainly guilty, while all disclaimed knowledge
                            of the act. We were ready to take red-hot iron in our hands,</l>
                        <l n="265" resp="p">to walk through fire and to swear oaths
                            by the gods that we had neither done the deed, nor shared knowledge of
                            the planning or the doing. At last, when our investigating got us
                            nowhere, someone spoke up and made us all bend our faces</l>
                        <l n="270" resp="p">in fear towards the earth. For we did
                            not know how we could argue with him, nor yet prosper, if we did what he
                            said. His argument was that the deed must be reported to you and not
                            hidden. This view prevailed, and so it was that </l>
                        <l n="275" resp="p">the lot doomed miserable me to win this prize. So here
                            I stand, as unwelcome to you as I am unwilling, I well know. For no man
                            delights in the bearer of bad news.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="278"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="278" resp="p">My king, my thoughts have long been deliberating whether this deed is
                            somehow the work of gods?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="280" resp="p">Quiet, before your words truly
                            fill me with rage, so that you not be found at the same time foolish as
                            well as old. You say what is intolerable when you claim that the gods
                            have concern for that corpse. Was it in high esteem for his
                                benefactions </l>
                        <l n="285" resp="p">that they sought
                            to hide him, when he had come to burn their columned shrines, their
                            sacred treasures and their land, and scatter its laws to the winds? Or
                            do you see the gods honoring the wicked? It cannot be. No! From the very
                                first </l>
                        <l n="290" resp="p">certain men of the city
                            were chafing at this edict and muttering against me, tossing their heads
                            in secret, and they did not keep their necks duly under the yoke in
                            submission to me. By those men, I am certain, they were led astray and
                            bribed to do this deed. </l>
                        <l n="295" resp="p">Nothing so
                            evil as money ever grew to be current among men. This destroys cities,
                            this drives men from their homes, this trains and warps honest minds to
                            set themselves to works of shame, </l>
                        <l n="300" resp="p">this teaches people to practise villainies, and to know every act of
                            unholiness. But all the men who did this job for hire have made sure
                            that, sooner or later, they shall suffer the punishment. Now, as Zeus
                            still has my reverence, know this well— </l>
                        <l n="305" resp="p">I tell you on my oath. If you do not find the very hand
                            that made this burial, and reveal him before my eyes, mere death shall
                            not suffice for you, not before, hung up alive, you have made this
                            outrage plain, </l>
                        <l n="310" resp="p">so that hereafter
                            you may thieve with better knowledge of where your money should be
                            received from, and learn that it is best not to be fond of money-making
                            from any and every source. For you will find that ill-gotten gains bring
                            more men to ruin than to safety.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="315"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="315" resp="p">Will you allow me to speak? Or
                            shall I just turn and go?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="316" resp="p">Do you not know even now how much your voice sickens me?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="317" resp="p">Is the pain in your ears, or in your soul?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="318" resp="p">And why would you define the seat of my pain?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="319" resp="p">He who did it hurts your heart, but I, your ears.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="320" resp="p">God! How plain it is that you are
                            a born babbler.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="321" resp="p">Perhaps, but never the author of this action.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="322" resp="p">Yes, and what is more, you sold your life for silver.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="323" resp="p">Ah! It is truly sad when the judge judges wrong .</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="324" resp="p">Expound on <q type="soCalled">judgment</q> as you will. But, if you fail to </l>
                        <l n="325" resp="p">show me the perpetrators of these crimes, you
                            will avow that money basely earned wreaks sorrows.<stage>Exit
                                Creon.</stage></l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="327" resp="p">Well, may the man be found! That would be best. But, whether he be caught
                            or not—for fortune must decide that—I assure you that you will not see
                            me come here again. </l>
                        <l n="330" resp="p">Saved just now
                            beyond hope and belief, I owe the gods great thanks.<stage>Exit the
                                Guard.</stage></l>

                    </sp>
                </div>

                <milestone unit="card" n="332"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="choral">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="332" resp="p">Wonders are many, and none is more
                            wonderful than man. </l>
                        <l n="335" resp="p">This power
                            spans the sea, even when it surges white before the gales of the
                            south-wind, and makes a path under swells that threaten to engulf him.
                            Earth, too, the eldest of the gods, the immortal, the
                                unwearied, </l>
                        <l n="340" resp="p">he wears away to
                            his own ends, turning the soil with the offspring of horses as the plows
                            weave to and fro year after year.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="343"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="343" resp="p">The light-hearted tribe of
                                birds </l>
                        <l n="345" resp="p">and the clans of wild
                            beasts and the sea-brood of the deep he snares in the meshes of his
                            twisted nets, and he leads them captive, very-skilled man. He masters by
                            his arts </l>
                        <l n="350" resp="p">the beast who dwells in
                            the wilds and roams the hills. He tames the shaggy-maned horse, putting
                            the yoke upon its neck, and tames the tireless mountain bull.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="354"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="354" resp="p">Speech and thought fast as
                                the </l>
                        <l n="355" resp="p">wind and the moods that
                            give order to a city he has taught himself, and how to flee the arrows
                            of the inhospitable frost under clear skies and the arrows of the
                            storming rain. </l>
                        <l n="360" resp="p">He has resource for
                            everything. Lacking resource in nothing he strides towards what must
                            come. From Death alone he shall procure no escape, but from baffling
                            diseases he has devised flights.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="365"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="365" resp="p">Possessing resourceful skill, a
                            subtlety beyond expectation he moves now to evil, now to good. When he
                            honors the laws of the land and the justice of the gods to which he is
                            bound by oath, </l>
                        <l n="370" resp="p">his city prospers.
                            But banned from his city is he who, thanks to his rashness, couples with
                            disgrace. Never may he share my home,  </l>
                        <l n="375" resp="p">never think my thoughts, who does these things!</l>

                    </sp>
                </div>

                <milestone unit="card" n="376"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                        <stage>Enter the Guard, on the spectators’ left, leading in
                            Antigone.</stage>
                        <sp>
                            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                            <l n="376" resp="p">What marvel sent by the gods is this?—I am
                                bewildered! I know her. How can I deny that this girl is Antigone? O
                                unhappy child </l>
                            <l n="380" resp="p">of your unhappy father, of Oedipus! What can this
                                mean? What! Surely they are not bringing you captive for disobeying
                                the King’s laws and being caught in lunacy?</l>
                        </sp>
                    </div>
                </div>

                <milestone unit="card" n="384"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="384" resp="p">Here is she, the one who did the deed. </l>
                        <l n="385" resp="p">We caught this one burying him. Where is Creon?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <stage>Enter Creon from the palace.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="386" resp="p">There, he is coming from the house again at our need.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="387" resp="p">What is it? What has happened that makes my coming timely?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="388" resp="p">My king, there is nothing that a man can rightly swear he
                            will not do. For second thought belies one’s first intent. </l>
                        <l n="390" resp="p">I could have vowed that I would not ever come here
                            again, because of your threats by which I had just been storm-tossed.
                            But since this joy that exceeds and oversteps my hopes can be compared
                            in fulness to no other pleasure, I am back—though it is contrary to my
                            sworn oath— </l>
                        <l n="395" resp="p">bringing this girl who
                            was caught giving burial honors to the dead. This time there was no
                            casting of lots. No, this piece of luck has fallen to me, and me alone.
                            And now, my king, as it pleases you, take her yourself, question her and
                            convict her. But justice would see me </l>
                        <l n="400" resp="p">released free and clear from this trouble.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="401" resp="p">Your prisoner here—how and where did you take her?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="402" resp="p">She was burying the man. You know all there is to tell.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="403" resp="p">Are you clear and sure about what you are saying?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="404" resp="p">I am. I saw her burying the corpse that you </l>
                        <l n="405" resp="p">had forbidden to bury. Is that plain and
                            sufficient?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="406" resp="p">And how was she observed? How taken in the act?</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="407"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Guard</speaker>
                        <l n="407" resp="p">It happened like this. When we had come to the place with those fierce
                            threats of yours still in our ears, we swept away all the dust that
                                covered </l>
                        <l n="410" resp="p">the corpse and bared
                            the damp body well. We then sat down on the brow of the hill to
                            windward, fleeing the smell from him, lest it strike us. Each man was
                            wide awake and kept his neighbor alert with torrents of threats, if any
                            one should be careless of this task. </l>
                        <l n="415" resp="p">So time passed, until the disk of the sun stood bright
                            in mid-sky and the heat began to burn. And then suddenly a whirlwind
                            lifted from the earth a storm of dust, a trouble in the sky, and it
                            filled the plain, marring all the foliage of its woods. </l>
                        <l n="420" resp="p">Soon the wide air was choked with it. We closed
                            our eyes, and endured the plague from the gods. When, after a long
                            while, this storm had passed, the girl was seen, and she wailed aloud
                            with the sharp cry of a grieving bird, as when inside her
                                empty </l>
                        <l n="425" resp="p">nest she sees the bed
                            stripped of its nestlings. So she, too, when she saw the corpse bare,
                            broke into a cry of lamentation and cursed with harsh curses those who
                            had done it. Immediately she took thirsty dust in her hands,</l>
                        <l n="430" resp="p">and from a pitcher of beaten bronze held
                            high she crowned the dead with thrice-poured libations. We rushed
                            forward when we saw it, and at once closed upon our quarry, who was not
                            at all dismayed. We then charged her with her past and present
                                doings, </l>
                        <l n="435" resp="p">but she made no denial of anything—at once to my joy and
                            to my pain. For to have escaped from trouble one’s self gives the
                            greatest joy, but it stings to lead friends to evil. Naturally, though,
                            all such things are </l>
                        <l n="440" resp="p">of less account to me than my own safety.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="441"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="441" resp="p">You, you with your face bent to the ground, do you admit, or deny that
                            you did this?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="443" resp="p">I declare it and make no denial.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <stage>To the Guard.</stage>
                        <l n="444" resp="p">You can take yourself wherever you please, </l>
                        <l n="445" resp="p">free and clear of a heavy charge.<stage>Exit
                                Guard.</stage></l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <stage>To Antigone.</stage>
                        <l n="446" resp="p">You, however, tell me—not at length, but briefly—did you know that an
                            edict had forbidden this?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="448" resp="p">I knew it. How could I not? It was public.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="449" resp="p">And even so you dared overstep that law?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="450" resp="p">Yes, since it was not Zeus that
                            published me that edict, and since not of that kind are the laws which
                            Justice who dwells with the gods below established among men. Nor did I
                            think that your decrees were of such force, that a mortal could override
                            the unwritten </l>
                        <l n="455" resp="p">and unfailing statutes given us by the gods. For their
                            life is not of today or yesterday, but for all time, and no man knows
                            when they were first put forth. Not for fear of any man’s pride was I
                            about to owe a penalty to the gods for breaking these. </l>
                        <l n="460" resp="p">Die I
                            must, that I knew well (how could I not?). That is true even without
                            your edicts. But if I am to die before my time, I count that a gain.
                            When anyone lives as I do, surrounded by evils, how can he not carry off
                            gain by dying? </l>
                        <l n="465" resp="p">So for me to meet this doom is a grief of no account.
                            But if I had endured that my mother’s son should in death lie an
                            unburied corpse, that would have grieved me. Yet for this, I am not
                            grieved. And if my present actions are foolish in your sight, </l>
                        <l n="470" resp="p">it may
                            be that it is a fool who accuses me of folly.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="471"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="471" resp="p">She shows herself the wild offspring of a wild father, and does not know
                            how to bend before troubles.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="473" resp="p">Yet remember that over-hard spirits most often collapse. It is the
                            stiffest iron, baked to </l>
                        <l n="475" resp="p">utter hardness in the fire, that you most often see
                            snapped and shivered. And I have witnessed horses with great spirit
                            disciplined by a small bit. For there is no place for pride, when one is
                            his neighbors’ slave. </l>
                        <l n="480" resp="p">This girl was already
                            practiced in outrage when she overstepped the published laws. And, that
                            done, this now is a second outrage, that she glories in it and exults in
                            her deed. In truth, then, I am no man, but she is, </l>
                        <l n="485" resp="p">if this victory rests with her and brings no penalty.
                            No! Whether she is my sister’s child, or nearer to me in blood than any
                            of my kin that worship Zeus at the altar of our house, she and her
                            sister will not escape a doom most harsh. For in truth</l>
                        <l n="490" resp="p">I charge that other with an equal share
                            in the plotting of this burial. Call her out! I saw her inside just now,
                            raving, and not in control of her wits. Before the deed, the mind
                            frequently is convicted of stealthy crimes when conspirators are
                            plotting depravity in the dark. </l>
                        <l n="495" resp="p">But, truly, I detest it, too, when one who has been caught in
                            treachery then seeks to make the crime a glory.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="497" resp="p">What more do you want than to capture and kill me?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="498" resp="p">I want nothing else. Having that, I have everything.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="499"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="499" resp="p">Why then do you wait? In none of your maxims </l>
                        <l n="500" resp="p">is there anything that pleases me—and may there never
                            be! Similarly to you as well my views must be displeasing. And yet, how
                            could I have won a nobler glory than by giving burial to my own brother?
                            All here would admit that they approve, </l>
                        <l n="505" resp="p">if fear did not grip their tongues. But tyranny, blest
                            with so much else, has the power to do and say whatever it pleases.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="508" resp="p">You alone out of all these Thebans see it that way.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="509" resp="p">They do, too, but for you they hold their tongues.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="510" resp="p">Are you not ashamed that your
                            beliefs differ from theirs?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="511" resp="p">No, there is nothing shameful in respecting your own flesh and blood.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="512" resp="p">Was not he your brother too, who died in the opposite cause?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="513" resp="p">A brother by the same mother and the same father.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="514" resp="p">Why, then, do you pay a service that is disrespectful to him?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="515" resp="p">The dead man will not support you
                            in that.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="516" resp="p">Yes, he will, if you honor him equally with the wicked one.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="517" resp="p">It was his brother, not his slave, who died.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="518" resp="p">But he died ravaging this land, while he fell in its defense.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="519" resp="p">Hades craves these rites, nevertheless.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="520" resp="p">But the good man craves a portion not equal to the
                            evil’s.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="521" resp="p">Who knows but that these actions are pure to those below?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="522" resp="p">You do not love someone you have hated, not even after death.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="523" resp="p">It is not my nature to join in hate, but in love.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="524" resp="p">Then, go down to hell and love them </l>
                        <l n="525" resp="p">if you must. While I live, no woman will rule me.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="526"/>
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <stage>Enter Ismene from the house, led in by two attendants.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="526" resp="p">Look, here comes Ismene from the palace, shedding the tears of a loving
                            sister. A cloud over her eyes mars her red-flushed face,</l>
                        <l n="530" resp="p">and it breaks into rain on her comely
                            cheek.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="531"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="531" resp="p">You who were lurking like a viper in my own house and
                                secretly gulping up my life’s blood, while I was oblivious that I
                                was nurturing two plagues, two revolutions against my throne—tell me
                                now, will you also affirm </l>
                        <l n="535" resp="p">your share in this
                            burial, or will you forswear all knowledge of it?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="536" resp="p">I performed the deed—as long as she concurs—and I share and carry the
                            burden of guilt.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="538" resp="p">No, justice will not permit you to do this, since you were not willing to
                            help with the deed, nor did I give you a part in it.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="540" resp="p">But now with this sea of troubles
                            around you, I am not ashamed to sail in a sea of suffering at your
                            side.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="542" resp="p">As to whose deed it is, Hades and the dead are witnesses. A friend in
                            words is not the type of friend I love.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="544" resp="p">No, sister, do not strip me of death’s honor, </l>
                        <l n="545" resp="p">but let me die with you and make due consecration to
                            the dead.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="546" resp="p">Do not share my death. Do not claim deeds to which you did not put your
                            hand. My death will suffice.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="548" resp="p">And how can I cherish life, once I am deprived of you?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="549" resp="p">Ask Creon. Your concern is for him.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="550" resp="p">Why do you torture me like this,
                            when it does not help you?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="551" resp="p">No, if I mock you, it is to my own pain that I do so.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="552" resp="p">Tell me, how can I help you, even now?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="553" resp="p">Save yourself. I do not grudge your escape.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="554" resp="p">Ah, misery! Will I fall short of sharing your fate?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="555" resp="p">Your choice was to live, it was
                            mine to die.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="556"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="556" resp="p">At least your choice was not made without my protests.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="557" resp="p">One world approved your wisdom, another approved mine.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="558" resp="p">Nevertheless, the offense is identical for both of us.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="559" resp="p">Take heart! You live. But my life has long been </l>
                        <l n="560" resp="p">in Death’s hands so that I might serve the dead.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="561" resp="p">One of these maidens, I declare, has just revealed her foolishness; the
                            other has displayed it from the moment of her birth.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="563" resp="p">Yes, Creon. Whatever amount of reason nature may have given them does not
                            remain with those in dire straits, but goes astray.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="565" resp="p">Yours did, I know, when you chose
                            dire actions with dire allies.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="566" resp="p">What life would there be for me alone, without her presence?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="567" resp="p">Do not speak of her <q type="mentioned">presence</q>. She lives no longer.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="568" resp="p">What? You will kill your own son’s bride?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="569" resp="p">Why not? There are other fields for him to plough.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Ismene</speaker>
                        <l n="570" resp="p">But not fitted to him as she
                            was.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="571" resp="p">I abhor an evil wife for my son.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="572" resp="p">Haemon, dearest! How your father wrongs you!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="573" resp="p">Enough! Enough of you and of your marriage!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="574" resp="p">Will you really cheat your son of this girl?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="575" resp="p">Death it is who will end these
                            bridals for me.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="576" resp="p">Then it seems that it is resolved that she will die.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="577" resp="p">Resolved, yes, for you and by me.<stage>To the two Attendants.</stage>No
                            more delay! Servants, take them inside! Hereafter they must be women,
                            and not left at large. </l>
                        <l n="580" resp="p">For it is
                            known that even the brave seek to flee, when they see Death now closing
                            on their life.<stage>Exeunt Attendants, guarding Antigone and Ismene.
                                Creon remains.</stage></l>

                    </sp></div>
                </div>

                <milestone unit="card" n="583"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="choral">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="583" resp="p">Blest are those whose days have
                            not tasted of evil. For when a house has once been shaken by the
                                gods, </l>
                        <l n="585" resp="p">no form of ruin is
                            lacking, but it spreads over the bulk of the race, just as, when the
                            surge is driven over the darkness of the deep by the fierce breath of
                            Thracian sea-winds, </l>
                        <l n="590" resp="p">it rolls up
                            the black sand from the depths, and the wind-beaten headlands that front
                            the blows of the storm give out a mournful roar.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="593"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="593" resp="p">I see that the ancient sorrows of
                            the house of the Labdacids </l>
                        <l n="595" resp="p">are
                            heaped upon the sorrows of the dead. Each generation does not set its
                            race free, but some god hurls it down and the race has no release. For
                            now that dazzling ray of hope that had been spread </l>
                        <l n="600" resp="p">over the last roots in the house of
                            Oedipus—that hope, in its turn, the blood-stained dust of the gods
                            infernal and mindlessness in speech and frenzy at the mind cuts
                            down.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="605"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="605" resp="p">Your power, great Zeus—what human
                            overstepping can check it? Yours is power that neither Sleep, the
                            all-ensnaring, nor the untiring months of the gods can defeat. Unaged
                            through time, </l>
                        <l n="610" resp="p">you rule by your
                            power and dwell thereby in the brilliant splendor of <placeName
                                key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>. And through the future, both
                            near and distant, as through the past, shall this law prevail: nothing
                            that is vast comes to the life of mortals without ruin.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="615"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="615" resp="p">See how that hope whose wanderings
                            are so wide truly is a benefit to many men, but to an equal number it is
                            a false lure of light-headed desires. The deception comes to one who is
                            wholly unawares until he burns his foot on a hot fire. </l>
                        <l n="620" resp="p">For with wisdom did someone once reveal the
                            maxim, now famous, that evil at one time or another seems good, to him
                            whose mind a god leads to ruin. </l>
                        <l n="625" resp="p">But for the briefest moment such a man fares free of destruction.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="626"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <stage>Enter Haemon.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="626" resp="p">But here is Haemon, the last of
                            your offspring. Does he come grieving for the doom of Antigone, his
                            promised bride, </l>
                        <l n="630" resp="p">and bitter for the
                            deceived hope of their marriage?</l>

                    </sp>
                </div></div>

                <milestone unit="card" n="631"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="631" resp="p">We will soon know better than seers could tell us.—My son, can it be that
                            after hearing the final judgment concerning your betrothed, you have
                            come in rage against your father? Or do I have your loyalty, act how I
                            may?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="635" resp="p">Father, I am yours, and you keep
                            me upright with precepts good for me—precepts I shall follow. No
                            marriage will be deemed by me more important than your good
                            guidance.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="640" resp="p">Yes, my son, this is the spirit you should maintain in
                            your heart—to stand behind your father’s will in all things. It is for
                            this that men pray: to sire and raise in their homes children who are
                            obedient, that they may requite their father’s enemy with evil and honor
                            his friend, just as their father does. </l>
                        <l n="645" resp="p">But the man who begets
                            unhelpful children—what would you say that he has sown except miseries
                            for himself and abundant exultation for his enemies? Never, then, my
                            son, banish your reason for pleasure on account of a woman,</l>
                        <l n="650" resp="p">knowing that this embrace soon becomes
                            cold and brittle—an evil woman to share your bed and home. For what
                            wound could strike deeper than a false friend? No, spit her out as if
                            she were an enemy, let her go find a husband in Hades. </l>
                        <l n="655" resp="p">For since I caught her alone of all the city in
                            open defiance, I will not make myself a liar to my city. I will kill
                            her. So let her call on Zeus who protects kindred blood. If I am to
                            foster my own kin to spurn order, </l>
                        <l n="660" resp="p">surely I will do the same for outsiders. For whoever shows his
                            excellence in the case of his own household will be found righteous in
                            his city as well. But if anyone oversteps and does violence to the laws,
                            or thinks to dictate to those in power, </l>
                        <l n="665" resp="p">such a one will never win praise from me. No, whomever
                            the city may appoint, that man must be obeyed in matters small and great
                            and in matters just and unjust. And I would feel confident that such a
                            man would be a fine ruler no less than a good and willing
                                subject, </l>
                        <l n="670" resp="p">and that beneath a
                            hail of spears he would stand his ground where posted, a loyal and brave
                            comrade in the battle line. But there is no evil worse than
                            disobedience. This destroys cities; this overturns homes; this
                                breaks </l>
                        <l n="675" resp="p">the ranks of allied spears into headlong rout. But the
                            lives of men who prosper upright, of these obedience has saved the
                            greatest part. Therefore we must defend those who respect order, and in
                            no way can we let a woman defeat us. It is better to fall from power, if
                            it is fated, by a man’s hand,</l>
                        <l n="680" resp="p">than that we be called weaker than
                            women.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="681"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="681" resp="p">To us, unless our years have stolen our wit, you seem to say what you say
                            wisely.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="683" resp="p">Father, the gods implant reason in men, the highest of all things that we
                            call our own. </l>
                        <l n="685" resp="p">For my part, to
                            state how you are wrong to say those things is beyond my power and my
                            desire, although another man, too, might have a useful thought. In any
                            case, it is my natural duty to watch on your behalf all that men say, or
                            do, or find to blame. </l>
                        <l n="690" resp="p">For dread of
                            your glance forbids the ordinary citizen to speak such words as would
                            offend your ear. But I can hear these murmurs in the dark, how the city
                            moans for this girl, saying: <q type="spoken">No woman ever merited death
                                less—</q> </l>
                        <l n="695" resp="p"><q type="spoken" rend="emph">none ever died so
                            shamefully for deeds so glorious as hers, who, when her own brother had
                            fallen in bloody battle, would not leave him unburied to be devoured by
                            savage dogs, or by any bird. Does she not deserve to receive golden
                                honor?</q> </l>
                        <l n="700" resp="p">Such is the rumor
                            shrouded in darkness that silently spreads. For me, father, no treasure
                            is more precious than your prosperity. What, indeed, is a nobler
                            ornament for children than the fair fame of a thriving father, or for a
                            father than that of his children? </l>
                        <l n="705" resp="p">Do not, then, bear one mood only in yourself: do not think that your
                            word and no other, must be right. For if any man thinks that he alone is
                            wise—that in speech or in mind he has no peer—such a soul, when laid
                            open, is always found empty. </l>
                        <l n="710" resp="p">No,
                            even when a man is wise, it brings him no shame to learn many things,
                            and not to be too rigid. You see how the trees that stand beside the
                            torrential streams created by a winter storm yield to it and save their
                            branches, while the stiff and rigid perish root and all?</l>
                        <l n="715" resp="p">And in the same way the pilot who keeps
                            the sheet of his sail taut and never slackens it, upsets his boat, and
                            voyages thereafter with his decking underwater. Father, give way and
                            allow a change from your rage. For if even from me, a younger man, a
                            worthy thought may be supplied, </l>
                        <l n="720" resp="p">by
                            far the best thing, I believe, would be for men to be all-wise by
                            nature. Otherwise—since most often it does not turn out that way—it is
                            good to learn in addition from those who advise you well.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="724"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="724" resp="p">My king, it is right, if he speaks something appropriate, that you should
                            learn from him </l>
                        <l n="725" resp="p">and that you, in
                            turn, Haemon, should learn from your father. On both sides there have
                            been wise words.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="726" resp="p">Men of my age—are we, then, to be schooled in wisdom by men of his?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="728" resp="p">Not in anything that is not right. But if I am young, you should look to
                            my conduct, not to my years.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="730" resp="p">Is it worthy conduct to honor
                            disrupters?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="731" resp="p">I could not urge anyone to show respect for the wicked.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="732" resp="p">And is she not in the grasp of that disease?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="733" resp="p">All the people of this city of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                                >Thebes</placeName> deny it.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="734" resp="p">Shall <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> prescribe to me
                            how I must rule?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="735" resp="p">See, there, how you have spoken so
                            much like a child.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="736" resp="p">Am I to rule this land by the will of another than myself?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="737" resp="p">That is no city, which belongs to one man.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="738" resp="p">Does not the city by tradition belong to the man in power?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="739" resp="p">You would make a fine monarch in a desert.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="740" resp="p">This boy seems to be fighting on
                            the side of the woman.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="741" resp="p">If you are a woman, for, to be sure, my concern is for you.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="742" resp="p">You traitor, attacking your father, accusing him!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="743" resp="p">Because I see you making a mistake and committing injustice.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="744" resp="p">Am I making a mistake when I respect my own prerogatives?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="745" resp="p">Yes. You do not respect them, when you trample on the
                            gods’ honors.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="746" resp="p">Polluted creature, submitting to a woman!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="747" resp="p">You will never catch me submitting to shamelessness.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="748" resp="p">You do. Your every word, after all, pleads her case.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="749" resp="p">And yours, and mine, and that of gods below.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="750" resp="p">You can never marry her, not while
                            she is still alive.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="751" resp="p">Then she will die, and in death destroy another.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="752" resp="p">What! Does your audacity run to open threats?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="753" resp="p">How is it a threat to speak against empty plans?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="754" resp="p">You will regret your unwise instructions in wisdom.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="755" resp="p">If you were not my father, I would
                            have called you insane.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="756" resp="p">You woman’s slave, do not try to cajole me.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="757" resp="p">Do you want to have your say and then have done without a reply?</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="758"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="758" resp="p">Is that so? By Olympus above—know this well—you will have no joy for
                            taunting me over and above your censures. </l>
                        <l n="760" resp="p">Bring out that hated thing, so that with him looking on
                            she may die right now in her bridegroom’s presence and at his side!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Haemon</speaker>
                        <l n="762" resp="p">No, not at my side will she die—do not ever imagine it. Nor shall you
                            ever look at me and set eyes on my face again. </l>
                        <l n="765" resp="p">Indulge in your madness now with whomever of your
                            friends can endure it.<stage>Exit Haemon.</stage></l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="766" resp="p">The man is gone, King Creon, in anger and haste. A young mind is fierce
                            when stung.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="768" resp="p">Let him do—no!—let him plan something more immense than befits a man.
                            Farewell to him! Still he will not save these two girls from death.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="770" resp="p">Then the pair of them, you really
                            intend to kill them both?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="771" resp="p">Not the one who did not put her hands to the burial. You are right.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="772" resp="p">And by what mode of death do you mean to kill the other?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="773" resp="p">I will take her where the path is deserted, unvisited by men, and entomb
                            her alive in a rocky vault, </l>
                        <l n="775" resp="p">setting out a ration of food, but only as much as piety requires so
                            that all the city may escape defilement. And praying there to Hades, the
                            only god she worships, perhaps she will obtain immunity from death, or
                            else will learn, at last, even this late, </l>
                        <l n="780" resp="p">that it is fruitless labor to revere the
                                dead.<stage>Exit Creon.</stage></l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="781"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="choral">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="781" resp="p">Love, the unconquered in battle, Love, you who descend
                                upon riches, and watch the night through on a girl’s soft cheek, </l>
                        <l n="785" resp="p">you roam over
                            the sea and among the homes of men in the wilds. Neither can any
                            immortal escape you, </l>
                        <l n="790" resp="p">nor any man
                            whose life lasts for a day. He who has known you is driven to
                            madness.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="791"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="791" resp="p">You seize the minds of just men
                            and drag them to injustice, to their ruin. You it is who have incited
                            this conflict of men whose flesh and blood are one. </l>
                        <l n="795" resp="p">But victory belongs to radiant Desire swelling
                            from the eyes of the sweet-bedded bride. Desire sits enthroned in power
                            beside the mighty laws. </l>
                        <l n="800" resp="p">For in all
                            this divine Aphrodite plays her irresistible game.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="801"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <stage>Enter Antigone under guard from the palace.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="801" resp="p">But now, witnessing this, I too am
                            carried beyond the bounds of loyalty. The power fails me to keep back my
                            streaming tears any longer, when I see Antigone making her way to the
                            chamber where all are laid to rest, </l>
                        <l n="805" resp="p">now her bridal chamber.</l>

                    </sp></div></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="806"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="choral">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="806" resp="p">Citizens of my fatherland, see me
                            setting out on my last journey, looking at my last sunlight,</l>
                        <l n="810" resp="p">and never again. No, Hades who lays all to rest leads me
                                living to <placeName key="tgn,1120946">Acheron</placeName>’s shore,
                                though I have not had my due portion of the chant that brings the
                                bride, nor has any hymn been mine</l>
                        <l n="815" resp="p">for the crowning of marriage. Instead
                            the lord of <placeName key="tgn,1120946">Acheron</placeName> will be my
                            groom.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="817"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="817" resp="p">Then in glory and with praise you
                            depart to that deep place of the dead, neither struck by wasting
                                sickness, </l>
                        <l n="820" resp="p">nor having won the
                            wages of the sword. No, guided by your own laws and still alive, unlike
                            any mortal before, you will descend to Hades.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="823"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="823" resp="p">I have heard with my own ears how
                            our Phrygian guest, the daughter of Tantalus, perished </l>
                        <l n="825" resp="p">in so much suffering on steep Sipylus—how, like
                            clinging ivy, the sprouting stone subdued her. And the rains, as men
                            tell, do not leave her melting form, nor does the snow, </l>
                        <l n="830" resp="p">but beneath her weeping lids she dampens her
                            collar. Most like hers is the god-sent fate that leads me to my
                            rest.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="834"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="834" resp="p">Yet she was a goddess, as you
                            know, and the offspring of gods, </l>
                        <l n="835" resp="p">while we are mortals and mortal-born. Still it is a great thing for a
                            woman who has died to have it said of her that she shared the lot of the
                            godlike in her life, and afterwards, in death.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="839"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="839" resp="p">Ah, you mock me! In the name of our fathers’ gods, </l>
                        <l n="840" resp="p">why do you not
                            wait to abuse me until after I have gone, and not to my face, O my city,
                            and you, her wealthy citizens? Ah, spring of Dirce, and you holy ground
                            of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> whose chariots are
                                many, </l>
                        <l n="845" resp="p">you, at least, will bear
                            me witness how unwept by loved ones, and by what laws I go to the
                            rock-closed prison of my unheard-of tomb! Ah, misery! </l>
                        <l n="850" resp="p">I have no home among men or with the shades, no
                            home with the living or with the dead.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="853"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="3">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="853" resp="p">You have rushed headlong to the
                            far limits of daring, and against the high throne of Justice</l>
                        <l n="855" resp="p">you have fallen, my daughter, fallen
                            heavily. But in this ordeal you are paying for some paternal crime.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="858"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="858" resp="p">You have touched on my most bitter
                                thought </l>
                        <l n="860" resp="p">and moved my ever-renewed pity for my father and for the
                                entire doom ordained for us, the famed house of Labdacus. Oh, the
                                horrors of our mother’s bed! Oh, the slumbers of the wretched mother
                                at the side </l>
                        <l n="865" resp="p">of her own son, my own father! What manner of parents
                            gave me my miserable being! It is to them that I go like this, accursed
                            and unwed, to share their home. </l>
                        <l n="870" resp="p">Ah, my brother, the marriage you made was doomed, and by dying you
                            killed me still alive!</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="872"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="3">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="872" resp="p">Your pious action shows a certain
                            reverence, but an offence against power can no way be tolerated by him
                            who has power in his keeping. </l>
                        <l n="875" resp="p">Your
                            self-willed disposition is what has destroyed you.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="876"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="876" resp="p">Unwept, unfriended, without
                            marriage-song, I am led in misery on this journey that cannot be put
                            off. No longer is it permitted me, unhappy girl, </l>
                        <l n="880" resp="p">to look up at this sacred eye of the burning
                            sun. But for my fate no tear is shed, no friend moans in sorrow.</l>

                    </sp></div></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="883"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                    <stage>Enter Creon.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="883" resp="p">Do you not know that dirges and
                            wailing before death would never be given up, if it were allowed to make
                            them freely? </l>
                        <l n="885" resp="p">Take her away—now!
                            And when you have enshrouded her, as I proclaimed, in her covered tomb,
                            leave her alone, deserted—let her decide whether she wishes to die or to
                            live entombed in such a home. It makes no difference, since our hands
                            are clean so far as regards this girl. </l>
                        <l n="890" resp="p">But no matter what, she will be stripped of her home
                            here above.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="891" resp="p">Tomb, bridal-chamber, deep-dug eternal prison where I go to find my own,
                            whom in the greatest numbers destruction has seized and Persephone has
                            welcomed among the dead! </l>
                        <l n="895" resp="p">Last of
                            them all and in by far the most shameful circumstances, I will descend,
                            even before the fated term of my life is spent. But I cherish strong
                            hopes that I will arrive welcome to my father, and pleasant to you,
                            Mother, and welcome, dear brother, to you. </l>
                        <l n="900" resp="p">For, when each of you died, with my own hands I washed
                            and dressed you and poured drink-offerings at your graves. But now,
                            Polyneices, it is for tending your corpse that I win such reward as
                            this. <del>And yet I honored you rightly, as the wise understand.</del></l>
                        <l n="905" resp="p"><del>Never, if I had been a mother of children, or if a
                            husband had been rotting after death, would I have taken that burden
                            upon myself in violation of the citizens’ will. For the sake of what
                            law, you ask, do I say that? A husband lost, another might have been
                            found, </del></l>
                        <l n="910" resp="p"><del>and if
                            bereft of a child, there could be a second from some other man. But when
                            father and mother are hidden in Hades, no brother could ever bloom for
                            me again. Such was the law whereby I held you first in honor, but for
                            that Creon judged me guilty of wrongdoing</del> </l>
                        <l n="915" resp="p"><del>and of dreadful outrage, dear brother! And now he leads
                            me thus in his hands’ strong grasp, when I have enjoyed no marriage bed
                            or bridal song and have not received any portion of marriage or the
                            nurture of children. But deserted by friends, </del></l>
                        <l n="920" resp="p"><del>in misery I go living to the hollow graves of the
                            dead.</del> What law of the gods have I transgressed? Why should I look to
                            the gods anymore? What ally should I call out to, when by my reverence I
                            have earned a name for irreverence? </l>
                        <l n="925" resp="p">Well, then, if these events please the gods, once I have suffered my
                            doom I will come to know my guilt. But if the guilt lies with my judges,
                            I could wish for them no greater evils than they inflict unjustly on
                            me.</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="929"/>
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="929" resp="p">Still the same tempest of the soul </l>
                        <l n="930" resp="p">grips this girl with the same fierce gusts.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="931" resp="p">Then because of this her guards will have reason to lament their
                            slowness.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="933" resp="p">Ah, no! That command verges close on death.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="935" resp="p">I cannot console you with any hope
                            that your doom is not to be fulfilled in that way.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Antigone</speaker>
                        <l n="937" resp="p">O city of my fathers, land of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                                >Thebes</placeName>, and you gods, our ancestors! I am led away now;
                            there is no more delay! </l>
                        <l n="940" resp="p">Look at me, you who are <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                                    >Thebes</placeName>’ lords—look at the only remaining daughter
                                of the house of your kings. See what I suffer, and at whose hands,
                                because I revered reverence!<stage>Antigone is led away by the
                                    guards.</stage></l>

                    </sp></div></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="944"/>

                    <div type="textpart" subtype="choral">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="944" resp="p">So too endured Danae in her beauty
                            to change </l>
                        <l n="945" resp="p">the light of the sky for
                            brass-bound walls, and in that chamber, both burial and bridal, she was
                            held in strict confinement. And yet was she of esteemed lineage, my
                                daughter, </l>
                        <l n="950" resp="p">and guarded a
                            deposit of the seed of Zeus that had fallen in a golden rain. But
                            dreadful is the mysterious power of fate—there is no deliverance from it
                            by wealth or by war, by towered city, or dark, sea-beaten ships.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="955"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="955" resp="p">And Dryas’s son, the Edonian king swift to rage, was
                                tamed in recompense for his frenzied insults, when, by the will of
                                Dionysus, he was shut in a rocky prison. There the fierce and
                                swelling force of his madness trickled away. </l>
                        <l n="960" resp="p">That man came to know the god whom in his
                            frenzy he had provoked with mockeries. For he had sought to quell the
                            god-inspired women and the Bacchanalian fire, </l>
                        <l n="965" resp="p">and he angered the Muses who love the flute.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="966"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="966" resp="p">And by the waters of the Dark
                            Rocks, the waters of the twofold sea, are the shores of <placeName
                                key="tgn,1115068">Bosporus</placeName> and the Thracian city
                                Salmydessus, </l>
                        <l n="970" resp="p">where Ares,
                            neighbor of that city, saw the accursed, blinding wound inflicted on the
                            two sons of Phineus by his savage wife. It was a wound that brought
                            darkness to the hollows, making them crave vengeance </l>
                        <l n="975" resp="p">for the eyes she crushed with her bloody hands
                            and with her shuttle for a dagger.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="977"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="977" resp="p">Wasting away in their misery, they
                            bewailed their miserable suffering </l>
                        <l n="980" resp="p">and their birth from their mother stripped of her
                                marriage. But she traced her descent from the ancient line of the
                                Erechtheids, and in far-distant caves she was raised amidst her
                                father’s gusts. She was the child of Boreas, </l>
                        <l n="985" resp="p">running swift as
                            horses over the steep hills, a daughter of gods. Yet she, too, was
                            assailed by the long-lived Fates, my child.</l>

                    </sp></div></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="988"/>

     <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                    <stage>Enter Teiresias, led by a boy, on the spectators’ right.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="988" resp="p">Princes of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                                >Thebes</placeName>, we have come on a shared journey, two scouting
                            the way by the eyes of one. </l>
                        <l n="990" resp="p">For this is the method of travel for the blind, using a
                            guide.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="991" resp="p">What is it, old Teiresias? What is your news?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="992" resp="p">I will tell you. You, obey the seer.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="993" resp="p">It was not my habit before, at any rate, to stand apart
                            from your will.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="994" resp="p">Therefore you captained this city on an upright course.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="995" resp="p">I have felt and can attest your benefits.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="996" resp="p">Realize that once more now you are poised on fortune’s
                            razor-edge.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="997" resp="p">What do you mean? I shudder to hear you!</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="998" resp="p">You will understand, when you hear the signs revealed by my
                            art. As I took my place on my old seat of augury </l>
                        <l n="1000" resp="p">where all birds regularly gather for me, I heard an
                            unintelligible voice among them: they were screaming in dire frenzy that
                            made their language foreign to me. I realized that they were ripping
                            each other with their talons, murderously—the rush of their wings did
                            not lack meaning. </l>
                        <l n="1005" resp="p">Quickly, in fear, I tried burnt-sacrifice on a
                            duly-kindled altar, but from my offerings Hephaestus did not blaze.
                            Instead juice that had sweated from the thigh-flesh trickled out onto
                            the embers and smoked and sputtered; </l>
                        <l n="1010" resp="p">the gall was scattered high up in the air; and the
                            streaming thighs lay bared of the fat that had been wrapped around them.
                            Such was the failure of the rites that yielded no sign, as I learned
                            from this boy. For he is my guide, as I am guide to others. </l>
                        <l n="1015" resp="p">And it is your will that is the source of the sickness
                            now afflicting the city. For the altars of our city and our hearths have
                            one and all been tainted by the birds and dogs with the carrion taken
                            from the sadly fallen son of Oedipus. And so the gods no more accept
                            prayer and sacrifice at our hands, </l>
                        <l n="1020" resp="p">or the burning of thigh-meat, nor does any bird sound
                            out clear signs in its shrill cries, for they have tasted the fatness of
                            a slain man’s blood. Think, therefore, on these things, my son. All men
                            are liable to err.</l>
                        <l n="1025" resp="p">But when an error is made, that man is no longer unwise
                            or unblessed who heals the evil into which he has fallen and does not
                            remain stubborn. Self-will, we know, invites the charge of foolishness.
                            Concede the claim of the dead. Do not kick at the fallen. </l>
                        <l n="1030" resp="p">What prowess is it to kill the dead all over again? I
                            have considered for your good, and what I advise is good. The sweetest
                            thing is to learn from a good advisor when his advice is to your
                            profit.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="card" n="1033"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1033" resp="p">Old man, you all shoot your arrows at me, like archers at
                            their mark, and I am not safe </l>
                        <l n="1035" resp="p">even from the plottings of the seer’s divine art, but
                            by their tribe I have long been bought and sold and made their
                            merchandise. Turn your profits, make your deals for the white gold of
                                <placeName key="perseus,Sardis">Sardis</placeName> and the gold of
                                <placeName key="tgn,7000198">India</placeName>, if it pleases you,
                            but you shall not cover that man with a grave, </l>
                        <l n="1040" resp="p">not even if the eagles of Zeus wish to snatch and carry
                            him to be devoured at the god’s throne. No, not even then, for fear of
                            that defilement will I permit his burial, since I know with certainty
                            that no mortal has the power to defile the gods. </l>
                        <l n="1045" resp="p">But even the exceedingly clever, old Teiresias, falls
                            with a shameful fall, when they couch shameful thoughts in fine phrasing
                            for profit’s sake.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1048" resp="p">Alas! Does any man know, does any consider—</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1049" resp="p">What is this? What universal truth are you announcing?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1050" resp="p">—by how much the most precious of our possessions is
                            the power to reason wisely?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1051" resp="p">By as much, I think, as senselessness is the greatest
                            affliction.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1052" resp="p">Yet you came into being full of that disease.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1053" resp="p">I have no desire to trade insults with the seer.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1054" resp="p">Yet that is what you do in saying that I prophesy
                            falsely.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1055" resp="p">Yes, for the prophet-clan was ever fond of money.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1056" resp="p">And the race sprung from tyrants loves shameful gain.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1057" resp="p">Do you know that you ramble so about your king?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1058" resp="p">I am aware, since through me you have saved this city.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1059" resp="p">You are a wise seer, but fond of doing injustice.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1060" resp="p">You will stir me to utter the dire secret in my
                            soul.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1061" resp="p">Out with it! But only if it is not for gain that you speak
                            it.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1062" resp="p">Indeed, I think I speak without mention of gain—where you
                            are concerned.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1063" resp="p">Be certain that you will not trade in my will.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="card" n="1064"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Teiresias</speaker>
                        <l n="1064" resp="p">Then know, yes, know it well! You will not live through
                            many more </l>
                        <l n="1065" resp="p">courses of the sun’s swift chariot, before you will
                            give in return one sprung from your own loins, a corpse in requital for
                            corpses. For you have thrust below one of those of the upper air and
                            irreverently lodged a living soul in the grave, </l>
                        <l n="1070" resp="p">while you detain in this world that which belongs to
                            the infernal gods, a corpse unburied, unmourned, unholy. In the dead you
                            have no part, nor do the gods above, but in this you do them violence.
                            For these crimes the avenging destroyers, </l>
                        <l n="1075" resp="p">the Furies of Hades and of the gods, lie in ambush for
                            you, waiting to seize you in these same sufferings. And look closely if
                            I tell you this with a silvered palm. A time not long to be delayed will
                            reveal in your house wailing over men and over women. </l>
                        <l n="1080" resp="p">All the cities are stirred up in hostility, whose
                            mangled corpses the dogs, or the wild beasts or some winged bird buried,
                            carrying an unholy stench to the city that held each man’s hearth.
                            There, now, are arrows for your heart, since you provoke me, </l>
                        <l n="1085" resp="p">launched at you, archer-like, in my anger. They fly
                            true—you cannot run from their burning sting. Boy, lead me home, so that
                            he may launch his rage against younger men, and learn to keep a quieter
                            tongue </l>
                        <l n="1090" resp="p">and a better mind within his breast than he now
                                bears.<stage>Exit Teiresias.</stage></l>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="card" n="1091"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1091" resp="p">The man is gone, my king, leaving dire prophecies behind.
                            And for all the time that I have had this hair on my head, now white,
                            once dark, I know that he has never been a false prophet to our
                            city.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1095" resp="p">I, too, know it well, and my mind is troubled. To yield
                            is terrible, but, to resist, to strike my pride with ruin—this, too,
                            inspires terror.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1098" resp="p">The moment, Creon, requires that you reason wisely.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1099" resp="p">What should I do, then? Speak, and I will obey.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1100" resp="p">Go and free the girl from her hollowed chamber. Then
                            raise a tomb for the unburied dead.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1102" resp="p">And you recommend this? You think that I should yield?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1103" resp="p">Yes, my king, and with all possible speed. For harms sent
                            from the gods swiftly cut short the follies of men.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1105" resp="p">Ah, it is a struggle, but I depart from my heart’s
                            resolve and obey. We must not wage vain wars with necessity.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1107" resp="p">Go, do these things and do not leave their performance to
                            others.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1108" resp="p">Right away I will go. Go, go, my servants, each and all of
                            you! Take axes in your hands, </l>
                        <l n="1110" resp="p">and hurry to that place there in view! But since my
                            judgment has taken this turn, I will be there to set her free, as I
                            myself confined her. I am held by the fear that it is best to keep the
                            established laws to life’s very end.</l>
                    </sp>
                </div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1115"/>

                        <div type="textpart" subtype="choral">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1115" resp="p">God of many names, glory of the
                            Cadmeian bride and offspring of loud-thundering Zeus, you who watch over
                            far-famed <placeName key="tgn,1000080">Italy</placeName> and
                                reign </l>
                        <l n="1120" resp="p">in the valleys of
                            Eleusinian Deo where all find welcome! O Bacchus, denizen of <placeName
                                key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, the mother-city of your
                            Bacchants, dweller by the wet stream of Ismenus on the soil</l>
                        <l n="1125" resp="p">of the sowing of the savage dragon’s teeth!</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1126"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1126" resp="p">The smoky glare of torches sees
                            you above the cliffs of the twin peaks, where the Corycian nymphs move
                            inspired by your godhead, </l>
                        <l n="1130" resp="p">and Castalia’s stream sees you, too. The ivy-mantled
                                slopes of <placeName key="perseus,Nysa">Nysa</placeName>’s hills and
                                the shore green with many-clustered vines send you, when accompanied
                                by the cries of your divine words, </l>
                        <l n="1135" resp="p">you visit the
                            avenues of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1137"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1137" resp="p"><placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
                                >Thebes</placeName> of all cities you hold foremost in honor,
                            together with your lightning-struck mother. </l>
                        <l n="1140" resp="p">And now when the whole city is held subject to a
                            violent plague, come, we ask, with purifying feet over steep <placeName
                                key="tgn,7011022">Parnassus</placeName>, </l>
                        <l n="1145" resp="p">or over the groaning straits!</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1146"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1146" resp="p">O Leader of the chorus of the
                            stars whose breath is fire, overseer of the chants in the night, son
                            begotten of Zeus, </l>
                        <l n="1150" resp="p">appear, my
                            king, with your attendant Thyiads, who in night-long frenzy dance and
                            sing you as Iacchus the Giver!</l>

                    </sp></div>
                </div>

                <milestone unit="card" n="1155"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                    <stage>Enter Messenger, on the spectators’ left.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1155" resp="p">Neighbors of the house of Cadmus and of Amphion, there
                            is no station of human life that I would ever praise or blame as being
                            settled. Fortune sets upright and Fortune sinks the lucky and unlucky
                            from day to day, </l>
                        <l n="1160" resp="p">and no one can prophesy to men concerning the order
                            that has just been established. For Creon, as I saw it, was once blest:
                            he had saved this land of Cadmus from its enemies; and having won sole
                            and total dominion in the land, he guided it on a straight course and
                            flourished in his noble crop of children. </l>
                        <l n="1165" resp="p">And now all this has been lost. When a man has
                            forfeited his pleasures, I do not reckon his existence as life, but
                            consider him just a breathing corpse. Heap up riches in your house, if
                            you wish! Live with a tyrant’s pomp! But if there is no joy</l>
                        <l n="1170" resp="p">along with all of that, I would not pay even the shadow
                            of smoke for all the rest, compared with joy.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1172" resp="p">What is this new grief for our princes that you have come
                            to report?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1173" resp="p">They are dead, and the living are guilty of the deaths.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1174" resp="p">Who is the murderer? Who the murdered? Tell us.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1175" resp="p">Haemon is dead—his blood was shed by no strange
                            hand.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1176" resp="p">Was it his father’s, or his own ?</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1177" resp="p">He did it by his own, enraged with his father for the
                            murder.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1178" resp="p">Ah, prophet, how true, then, you have proved your word!</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1179" resp="p">Knowing that these things are so, you must consider the
                            rest.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1180" resp="p">Wait, I see the unhappy Eurydice, Creon’s wife, nearby.
                            She comes from the house either knowing of her son, or merely by
                            chance.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="card" n="1183"/>
                    <stage>Enter Eurydice.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Eurydice</speaker>
                        <l n="1183" resp="p">People of <placeName key="tgn,7011071">Thebes</placeName>,
                            I heard your words as I was on my way to the gates to address divine
                            Pallas with my prayers. </l>
                        <l n="1185" resp="p">At one and the same time I was loosening the bolts of
                            the gate to open it, and the sound of a blow to our house struck my ear.
                            In terror I sank back into the arms of my handmaids, and my senses fled. </l>
                        <l n="1190" resp="p">But repeat what your news was, for I shall hear it with
                            ears that are no strangers to sorrow.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp n="Messenger">
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1192" resp="p">Dear mistress, I will tell what I witnessed and leave no
                            word of the truth unspoken. For what good would it do that should I
                            soothe you with words in which I must later be found false? </l>
                        <l n="1195" resp="p">The truth is always best. I attended your husband as
                            his guide to the furthest part of the plain, where unpitied the body of
                            Polyneices, torn by dogs, still lay. After we had prayed to the goddess
                            of the roads </l>
                        <l n="1200" resp="p">and to Pluto to restrain their anger in mercy, we
                            washed him with pure washing, and with freshly-plucked boughs we burned
                            what remains there were. Lastly we heaped a high-mounded tomb of his
                            native earth. Afterwards we turned away to enter the maiden’s
                            stoney-bedded </l>
                        <l n="1205" resp="p">bridal chamber, the caverned mansion of Hades’ bride.
                            From a distance, one of us servants heard a voice of loud wailing near
                            that bride’s unwept bed and came to tell our master Creon. And as the
                            King moved closer and closer, obscure signs rising from a bitter cry
                            surrounded him— </l>
                        <l n="1210" resp="p">he groaned and said in bitter lament, <q type="spoken"
                                >Ah, misery, am I now the prophet of evil? Am I going on the path
                                most lined with grief of all that I have walked before? My son’s
                                voice greets me. Go, my servants,</q>
                        </l>
                        <l n="1215" resp="p"><q type="spoken" rend="merge">hurry closer, and when
                                you have reached the tomb, enter the opening where the stones of the
                                mound have been torn away, up to the cell’s very mouth. See if it is
                                Haemon’s voice that I recognize, or if I am cheated by the
                            gods.</q></l>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="card" n="1219"/>
                    <sp>
                        <l n="1219" resp="p">This search, at our desperate master’s word, </l>
                        <l n="1220" resp="p">we went to make, and in the furthest part of the tomb
                            we saw her hanging by the neck, fastened by a halter of fine linen
                            threads, while he was embracing her with arms thrown around her waist,
                            bewailing the loss of his bride to the spirits below, as well as his
                            father’s deeds, and his grief-filled marriage. </l>
                        <l n="1225" resp="p">But his father, when he saw him, cried aloud with a
                            dreadful cry and went in and called to him with a voice of wailing: <q
                                type="spoken">Ah, unhappy boy, what have you done! What plan have
                                you seized on? By what misfortune have you lost your reason?</q>
                        </l>
                        <l n="1230" resp="p"><q type="spoken" rend="merge">Come out, my son, I pray
                                you, I beg you!</q> But the boy glared at him with savage eyes, spat
                            in his face, and without a word in response drew his twin-edged sword.
                            As his father rushed out in flight, he missed his aim. Then the
                            ill-fated boy was enraged with himself </l>
                        <l n="1235" resp="p">and straightway stretched himself over his sword and
                            drove it, half its length, into his side. Still conscious, he clasped
                            the maiden in his faint embrace, and, as he gasped, he shot onto her
                            pale cheek a swift stream of oozing blood. </l>
                        <l n="1240" resp="p">Corpse enfolding corpse he lay, having won his marriage
                            rites, poor boy, not here, but in Hades’ palace, and having shown to
                            mankind by how much the failure to reason wisely is the most severe of
                            all afflictions assigned to man.<stage>Eurydice departs into the
                                house.</stage>
                        </l>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="card" n="1244"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1244" resp="p">What would you infer from this? The lady </l>
                        <l n="1245" resp="p">has turned back and gone without a word, either for
                            good or for evil.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1246" resp="p">I, too, am startled. Still I am nourished by the hope that
                            at the grave news of her son she thinks it unworthy to make her laments
                            before the city, but in the shelter of her home will set her handmaids
                            to mourn the house’s grief. </l>
                        <l n="1250" resp="p">For she is not unhabituated to discretion, that she
                            should err.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1251" resp="p">I do not know. But to me, in any case, a silence too strict
                            seems to promise trouble just as much as a fruitless abundance of
                            weeping.</l>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1253" resp="p">I will find out whether she is not, in fact, hiding some
                            repressed plan in the darkness of her passionate heart. </l>
                        <l n="1255" resp="p">I will go in, since you are right—in an excess of
                            silence, too, there may be trouble.<stage>Exit Messenger.</stage></l>
                    </sp>
                    <milestone unit="card" n="1257"/>
                    <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                        <stage>Enter Creon, attended and carrying the shrouded body of Haemon, on
                            the spectators’ left.</stage>
                        <sp>
                            <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                            <l n="1257" resp="p">Look, here is the King himself approaching, his hands
                                grasping a monument plainly signing that his—if we may say it—and no
                                one else’s,</l>
                            <l n="1260" resp="p">was the madness of this error.</l>
                        </sp>
                    </div>
                </div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1261"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="choral">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1261" resp="p">Ah, the blunders of an unthinking
                            mind, blunders of rigidity, yielding death! Oh, you witnesses of the
                            killers and the killed, both of one family! </l>
                        <l n="1265" resp="p">What misery arises from my reasonings! Haemon, you have
                            died after a young life, youngest and last of my sons! O God! You have
                            departed not by your foolishness, but by my own!</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1270"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1270" resp="p">Ah, how late you seem to see the
                            right!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1271" resp="p">God, I have mastered the bitter lesson! But then, then, I think, some god
                            struck me on my head with a crushing weight, and drove me into savage
                                paths, </l>
                        <l n="1275" resp="p">—ah!—and overthrew my
                            joy to be trampled on! Ah, the labors men must toil through!</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1278"/>
                    <sp>
                        <stage>Enter the Messenger from the house.</stage>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1278" resp="p">My master, you have come, I
                            think, like one whose hands are not empty, but who has a ready store:
                            first, you carry that burden visible in your arms; </l>
                        <l n="1280" resp="p">second, you will soon look upon further
                            sufferings inside your house.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1281"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1281" resp="p">What worse suffering is still to follow upon these sufferings?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1282" resp="p">Your wife is dead, true mother of that corpse, poor lady, by wounds newly
                            cut.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1284"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="1">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1284" resp="p">O harbor of Hades, hard to
                                purify! </l>
                        <l n="1285" resp="p">Why, why do you ruin
                            me? Herald of evil, of grief, what word do you say? Ah, you have done in
                            a dead man anew! What are you saying, boy? What is this you report to
                                me </l>
                        <l n="1290" resp="p">God no!—what new slaughter, my wife’s doom, is heaped
                                upon this ruin?</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1293"/>
                    <sp>
                        <stage>The doors of the palace are opened, and the corpse of Eurydice is
                            disclosed.</stage>
                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1293" resp="p">The sight is at hand. It is no longer hidden inside.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1294"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="2">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1294" resp="p">Ah, misery! </l>
                        <l n="1295" resp="p">There I see a new, a
                            second evil! What destiny, ah, what, can still await me? I have just now
                            taken my son in my arms, and now I see another corpse before
                                me! </l>
                        <l n="1300" resp="p">Oh, tormented mother! Oh,
                            my son!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1301" resp="p">By the altar, with a
                            sharp-whetted sword, she struck until her eyes went slack and dark.
                            Before that she bewailed the noble fate of Megareus who died earlier,
                            and then the fate of this boy, and also, with her last breath,</l>
                        <l n="1305" resp="p">she called down evil fortune upon you,
                            the slayer of her sons.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1306"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="3">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1306" resp="p">Ah, no! I tremble with fear. Why
                            does no one strike me full on my chest with a two-edged sword?</l>
                        <l n="1310" resp="p">I am miserable—ah—and bathed in
                            miserable anguish!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1312" resp="p">Yes, because you were accused of responsibility for both
                                this son’s death, and the other’s, by her whose corpse you see.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1314" resp="p">What was the manner of the violent deed by which she departed?</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Messenger</speaker>
                        <l n="1315" resp="p">Her own hand struck her to the heart upon learning her
                                son’s sharply-lamented fate.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1317"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="strophe" n="4">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1317" resp="p">Ah this guilt can never be
                            fastened onto any other mortal so as to remove my own! It was I, yes, I,
                            who killed you, I the wretch. </l>
                        <l n="1320" resp="p">I
                            admit the truth. Lead me away, my servants, lead me from here with all
                            haste, who am no more than a dead man!</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1325" resp="p">The course you recommend is to
                            your gain, if there can be gain amidst evil. What is briefest is best,
                            when trouble lies at your feet.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1328"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="3">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1328" resp="p">Let it come, let it appear, that
                            fairest of fates for me, that brings my final day, </l>
                        <l n="1330" resp="p">the fate supreme! Oh, let it come, so that I may never
                                see tomorrow’s light!</l>

                    </sp>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1334"/>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1334" resp="p">These things are in the future.
                            We must see to present affairs. </l>
                        <l n="1335" resp="p">Fulfillment of these things rests in the hands where it should
                            rest.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                        <l n="1336" resp="p">All that I crave was summed in that prayer.</l>

                    </sp>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1337" resp="p">Then pray no more; for mortals have no release from destined
                            misfortune.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                

                <milestone unit="card" n="1339"/>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="antistrophe" n="4">
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Creon</speaker>
                         <l n="1339" resp="p">Lead me away, I beg you, a rash,
                            useless man. </l>
                        <l n="1340" resp="p">I have murdered you,
                            son, unwittingly, and you, too, my wife—the misery! I do not know which
                            way I should look, or where I should seek support. All is </l>
                        <l n="1345" resp="p">amiss that is in my hands, and, again,
                            a crushing fate has leapt upon my head.</l>

                    </sp></div>
                </div>

                <milestone unit="card" n="1347"/>

                <div type="textpart" subtype="episode">
                <div type="textpart" subtype="anapests">
                    <stage>As Creon is being conducted into the house, the Chorus Leader speaks the
                        closing verses.</stage>
                    <sp>
                        <speaker>Chorus</speaker>
                        <l n="1347" resp="p">Wisdom is provided as the chief
                            part of happiness, and our dealings with the gods must be in no way
                            unholy. The great words of arrogant men have to make repayment with
                            great blows, and in old age teach wisdom.</l>

                    </sp></div></div>

                
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
