<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Answer to Philip's Letter </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by C. A. Vince, M. A. and J.
                            H. Vince, M.A.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1926</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>6/2/92</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>inserted quotedtext tags around verse</item>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>It must now be clear to all of you, Athenians, that Philip never concluded a
                    peace with you, but only postponed the war; for ever since he handed Halus<note
                        anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A town in the south of <placeName
                            key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> on the Pagasaean Gulf; not to be
                        confused with Halonnesus.</note> over to the Pharsalians, settled the
                    Phocian question, and subdued the whole of <placeName key="tgn,7002756"
                        >Thrace</placeName>, coining false excuses and inventing hollow pretexts, he
                    has been all the time practically at war with <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, though it is only now that he confesses it openly in
                    the letter which he has sent. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>I shall, however, try to prove to you that you must not quail before his power
                    nor offer a half-hearted resistance, but must enter the war with an unsparing
                    provision of men, money, and ships—in a word, with all your resources. For
                    first, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you may
                    reasonably expect that your mightiest allies and supporters will be those gods
                    whose sanction he has flouted and whose name he has taken in vain through his
                    unjust violation of the peace. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>Then again, he has at last come to the end of his policy of deception and his
                    lavish promises of future benefit, which before helped him to power. The
                    Perinthians and Byzantines with their allies realize that his aim is to deal
                    with them even as he dealt with the Olynthians before. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>The Thessalians recognize that he is determined to be their despot and not the
                    president of a confederacy. The Thebans suspect him, because he keeps a garrison
                    at <placeName key="perseus,Nicaea">Nicaea</placeName> and has stolen into the
                    Amphictyonic Council, and because he attracts to his court the embassies of the
                    Peloponnesian powers and secures their allies for himself. Thus of his old
                    friends some are even now his irreconcilable foes, others are no longer his
                    hearty supporters, while all regard him with suspicion and dislike. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>Then too—nor is this a matter of small importance—quite recently the satraps of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName> sent a force of
                    mercenaries and compelled Philip to raise the siege of Perinthus; but today
                    their hostility is confirmed, the danger, if he reduces <placeName
                        key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>, is at their very doors, and
                    not only will they eagerly join the war against him, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>but they will prompt the king of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>
                    to become our paymaster and he is richer than all the rest together, and his
                    power to interfere in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> is such
                    that in our former wars with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>,
                    whichever side he joined, he ensured their victory, and so, if he sides with us
                    now, he will easily crush the power of Philip. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>Now, admitting these great advantages, I cannot deny that Philip has used the
                    peace to forestall us in occupying many fortresses, harbors, and other points of
                    vantage; only I observe that when a league is knit together by goodwill, and
                    when all the allied states have the same interests, then the coalition stands
                    firm; but when, like Philip's, it is based on treachery and greed and maintained
                    by fraud and violence, then on some slight pretext or by some trifling slip it
                    is instantly shattered and dissolved. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>Moreover, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, frequent
                    reflection has taught me that not only do Philip's alliances end in suspicion
                    and hostility, but also the various parts of his own kingdom are not united by
                    such satisfactory and intimate ties as people imagine. For although in a general
                    way the Macedonian power carries some weight and value as an auxiliary, yet by
                    itself it is weak and, in face of such a stupendous task, even negligible; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>and Philip, by his wars and his campaigns and by all those activities to which
                    his greatness might be attributed, has really made it a less trusty weapon to
                    his own hand. For you must not imagine, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, that his subjects share his tastes; you must rather
                    reflect that he wants glory, but they security. He cannot gain his end without
                    danger; they, thinking of children, parents, and wives left at home, are not so
                    eager to court ruin and danger every day to oblige him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>From this you can gauge the feelings of the great body of the Macedonians towards
                    Philip; while as regards his courtiers and captains of his mercenaries you will
                    find that, though they have some repute for valor, they live in greater fear
                    than those who have none; for these have only the enemy to fear, but those dread
                    the sycophants and slanderers of the court more than a pitched battle. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>These, again, have the whole army to support them when they face the hostile
                    ranks, but those both have to bear the chief burden of the war, and, apart from
                    that, it is their peculiar misfortune to fear the temper of their king.
                    Moreover, if a common soldier is at fault, his punishment is proportioned to his
                    deserts, but it is just when the officers are most successful that they are most
                    exposed to unmerited curses and gibes. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>And all this no one in his senses would refuse to believe; for those who have
                    resided at his court agree that Philip is so jealous that he wants to take to
                    himself all the credit of the chief successes, and is more annoyed with a
                    general or an officer who achieves something praiseworthy than with those who
                    fail ignominiously. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>This being so, how is it that they have so long remained loyal to him? Because,
                    men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, at present his
                    prosperity overshadows all such shortcomings, for success has a strange power of
                    obscuring and covering men's failings; but if he trips, all his weakness will be
                    clearly revealed. For it is with the political as with the bodily constitution.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>As long as a man is in good health, he is conscious of no unsoundness here or
                    here, but when his health breaks down, every part is set a-working, be it a
                    rupture or a sprain or any organ that is not perfectly healthy. So with all
                    monarchies and oligarchies; as long as their arms prosper, few detect their
                    weaknesses, but when they stumble, even as Philip must stumble beneath a burden
                    that is greater than he can bear, then all their disadvantages are plain for all
                    men to see. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>Now if any of you, Athenians, seeing Philip's good fortune, considers him a
                    formidable and dangerous opponent, he is exercising a prudent forethought. For
                    fortune is indeed a great weight in the scale; I might almost say it is
                    everything in human affairs. And yet in many respects our good fortune is to be
                    preferred to Philip's. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>For our prosperity is inherited from our ancestors, and is of an earlier date
                    than the prosperity not only of Philip, but, roughly speaking, of all the kings
                    that have ever reigned in <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>.
                    Those kings actually paid tribute to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, but <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
                    never paid tribute to any power in the world. Moreover, we have a more secure
                    claim than Philip upon the favour of heaven, in so far as our conduct has always
                    been guided by greater regard for religion and for justice. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>Why, then, was he more successful than we in the late war? I will be frank with
                    you, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. It is because he
                    always takes a personal share in the hardships and dangers of the campaign,
                    never neglects a chance, never wastes any season of the year; while we—for the
                    truth must out—sit here idle; we are always hanging back and passing resolutions
                    and haunting the market-place to learn the latest news. Yet what more startling
                    news could there be than that a Macedonian should insult Athenians, daring to
                    send us such a letter as you have heard read a moment ago? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>Philip's resources include mercenary soldiers, and also, observe! certain
                    mercenary orators here among us, men who are not ashamed to devote their lives
                    to his service, thinking that they are carrying home his bribes, but blind to
                    the fact that they are bartering all the interests of the State, and their own
                    as well, for a paltry profit. We, on the other hand, make no attempt to foment a
                    revolution in his kingdom, we decline to hire mercenaries, we shrink from taking
                    the field. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>It is not a strange thing, then, that he has gained ground at our expense in the
                    late war, but rather that we, performing no single duty of a nation at war,
                    think that we are going to defeat one who does everything that a grasping
                    ambition demands. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>Bearing this in mind, Athenians, and reflecting that it is not even in our power
                    to pretend that we are at peace, for Philip has already issued a declaration of
                    war and followed it up by active hostilities, it is necessary to spare no
                    expense, public or private, to take the field eagerly and in full force,
                    wherever the opportunity occurs, and to employ abler generals than before. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>For none of you must assume that the same policy that weakened the power of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> will suffice to restore
                    and advance it, nor suppose that, if you are as half-hearted as before, others
                    will be zealous in defence of your interests. Reflect, rather, what a disgrace
                    it would be if your fathers faced many hardships and great dangers in fighting
                    the Lacedaemonians, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>but you should refuse to defend with vigor those advantages which they justly won
                    and bequeathed to you; what a disgrace if one, with only the tradition of
                        <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> behind him, so cheerfully
                    courts danger that, in the task of extending his sway, he has been wounded in
                    every limb on the battle-field, but Athenians, whose ancestral boast it is in
                    war to yield to none and conquer all, should renounce, through indolence or
                    cowardice, alike the deeds of their ancestors and the interests of their
                    fatherland. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>Not to detain you longer, I say that we must be prepared for war, and must urge
                    the Greek states, by our action rather than by our appeals, to join our
                    alliance; for all words divorced from action are futile, especially words from
                    Athenian lips, in proportion as we are reputed to be more ready of speech than
                    all other Greeks.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
