<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Aphobus 1 </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>If Aphobus, men of the jury, had been willing to do what is fair, or to submit
                    the matters in dispute between us to the arbitration of friends, there would be
                    no occasion for a troublesome lawsuit; for I should have been satisfied to abide
                    by their decision, and we should have had no controversy with him. Since,
                    however, he has refused to let those well acquainted with our affairs give a
                    decision, and has come before you, who have no accurate knowledge of them, it
                    must be in your court that I try to win from him what is my due. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>I know well, men of the jury, that it is a hard task to enter into a contest in
                    which all my fortune is at stake with men who are able speakers and clever in
                    preparing their case, while I because of my youth am wholly without experience
                    in affairs. Yet nevertheless, although they have every advantage over me, I have
                    strong hopes that I shall obtain justice in your court, and that, as far at
                    least as relating the facts, I shall myself speak well enough to ensure that not
                    a single detail shall escape you, and that you will not be in the dark regarding
                    the matters concerning which you are to cast your vote. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>I beg of you, men of the jury, to give me a favorable hearing, and, if you judge
                    that I have been wronged, to render me the aid which is my due. I shall make my
                    speech as brief as possible, and shall begin by endeavoring to inform you of the
                    facts from which you will most readily understand the case. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Demosthenes, my father, men of the jury, left at
                    his death an estate of nearly fourteen talents, a son, myself, aged seven, and
                    my sister, aged five, and his widow, our mother, who had brought him a fortune
                    of fifty minae. He had taken thought for our welfare, and, when he was about to
                    die, put all this property in the hands of the defendant, Aphobus, and Demophon,
                    son of Demo, nephews of his, one by his brother, the other by his sister, and of
                    Therippides of Paeania,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Paeania was a deme of
                        the tribe Pandionis.</note> who was not a relative, but had been his friend
                    from boyhood. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>To Therippides he gave the interest on seventy minae of my property, to be
                    enjoyed by him until I should come of age,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">At
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> a youth, on reaching
                        the age of eighteen, was, after an official examination (<foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">dokimasi/a</foreign>), duly entered on the list of the
                        members of his tribe, and assumed the status and the duties of a
                        citizen.</note> in order that avarice might not tempt him to mismanage my
                    affairs. To Demophon he gave my sister with a dowry of two talents, to be paid
                    at once, and to the defendant himself he gave our mother with a dowry of eighty
                    minae, and the right to use my house and furniture. His thought was that, if he
                    should unite these men to me by still closer ties, they would look after my
                    interests the better because of this added bond of kinship. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>But these men, who took at once their own legacies from the estate, and as my
                    guardians administered all the remainder for ten years, have robbed me of my
                    entire fortune except the house, and fourteen slaves and thirty silver minae,
                    which they have handed over to me—amounting in all to about seventy minae. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>This, men of the jury, to put it as briefly as possible, is a summing up of the
                    wrongs they have done me. But of the fact that the amount of property left by my
                    father was as much as I have stated these men themselves have proved the most
                    convincing witnesses, for in the tax-company<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Each of the ten Athenian tribes selected one hundred and twenty men as
                        their richest members. These twelve hundred men were divided into twenty
                        groups of sixty each (called <foreign xml:lang="grc">summori/ai</foreign>),
                        and from them certain men were designated to bear the burdens of public
                        service (the treirarchy, choregia, etc.) and of the special property-tax
                        imposed in time of need.</note> they agreed on my behalf to a tax of five
                    hundred drachmae on every twenty-five minae<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >This was a tax of 20 percent of the man's entire property, and was the
                        maximum.</note>—a tax equal to that paid by Timotheus, son of <placeName
                        key="tgn,1123029">Conon</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Timotheus was one of the leading citizens of <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. His father, <placeName
                            key="tgn,1123029">Conon</placeName>, was the famous general who in 395
                        had destroyed the Lacedemonian fleet at <placeName key="tgn,5003757"
                            >Cnidos</placeName>.</note> and those possessing the largest fortunes.
                    However, I had better inform you in detail what portions of the property were
                    producing a profit and what were unproductive, and what were their respective
                    values; for when you have accurate information regarding these matters, you will
                    know that of all who have ever acted as trustees none have so shamelessly and so
                    openly plundered an estate as these men have plundered ours. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>I shall produce witnesses to prove, first, that in the tax-company they agreed on
                    my behalf to be taxed to the amount which I have stated, and, next, that my
                    father did not leave me a poor man, nor one possessing an estate of merely
                    seventy minae. On the contrary, my estate was so considerable that these men
                    were themselves unable to hide its value from the state.<milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/>Take,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">These words were
                        addressed to the clerk of the court.</note> please, and read this
                        deposition.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>From this evidence it is clear what the value of the property was. Three talents
                    is the tax on an estate of fifteen, and this tax they saw fit to pay. But you
                    will see this more clearly if you hear what the property was. My father, men of
                    the jury, left two factories, both doing a large business. One was a
                    sword-manufactory, employing thirty-two or thirty-three slaves, most of them
                    worth five or six minae each and none worth less than three minae. From these my
                    father received a clear income of thirty minae each year. The other was a
                    sofa-manufactory, employing twenty slaves, given to my father as security for a
                    debt of forty minae. These brought him in a clear income of twelve minae. In
                    money he left as much as a talent, loaned at the rate of a drachma a month,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A drachma, that is, on each mina. This (12
                        percent) was the normal rate of interest on well-secured loans.</note> the
                    interest of which amounted to more than seven minae a year. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>This was the amount of productive capital which my father left, as these men will
                    themselves admit, the principal amounting to four talents and five thousand
                        drachmae,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In mercantile affairs the Greeks
                        often preferred to reckon in thousands of drachmae instead of tens of
                        minae.</note> and the proceeds to fifty minae each year. Besides this, he
                    left ivory and iron, used in the factory, and wood for sofas, worth about eighty
                    minae; and gall<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was obtained from the
                        oak-apple and was used for staining wood or ivory.</note> and copper, which
                    he had bought for seventy minae; furthermore, a house worth three thousand
                    drachmae, and furniture and plate, and my mother's jewelry and apparel and
                    ornaments, worth in all ten thousand drachmae, and in the house eighty minae in
                    silver. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>To these sums left by him at home we must add seventy minae, a maritime loan to
                    Xuthus; twenty-four hundred drachmae in the bank of Pasion, six hundred in that
                    of Pylades, sixteen hundred in the hands of Demomeles, son of Demon, and about a
                    talent loaned without interest in sums of two hundred or three hundred drachmae.
                    The total of these last sums amounts to more than eight talents and fifty minae,
                    and the whole taken together you will find on examination to come to about
                    fourteen talents.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Strictly, thirteen talents
                        and forty-six minae; see the Introduction.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>This, then, men of the jury, was the amount of property left by my father. How
                    much of it has been squandered, how much they have severally taken, and of how
                    much they have jointly robbed me, it is impossible to tell in the time<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Literally, “water,” the time allotted to each
                        speaker being measured by a water-clock.</note> allotted to one plea. I must
                    discuss each one of these questions separately. I pass over the question as to
                    what property of mine Demophon or Therippides are holding. It will be time
                    enough to discuss this when I bring in my accusations against them. I shall
                    speak to you now of the defendant and shall state what his colleagues prove that
                    he has in his hands, and what I know he has taken. In the first place I shall
                    show that he has the marriage-portion, the eighty minae, and after that shall
                    take up the other matters and discuss them with the utmost brevity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Immediately after my father's death the defendant
                    came and dwelt in the house according to the terms of the will, and took
                    possession of my mother's jewels and the plate. In these he received the
                    equivalent of about fifty minae. Furthermore, he received from Therippides and
                    Demophon the proceeds of the sale of the slaves until he had made up the full
                    amount of the marriage-portion, eighty minae; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>and after getting this, when he was about to set sail for <placeName
                        key="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName> as trierarch,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">That is, in command of a trireme which he had himself
                        equipped for service.</note> he sent Therippides a written acknowledgement
                    that he had these sums in his possession, and admitted that he had received the
                    marriage-portion. Of these matters Demophon and Therippides, his co-trustees,
                    are witnesses, and, besides this, his own acknowledgement of having received
                    these moneys is attested by Demochares, of Leuconion,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Leuconion, or Leuconoe, was a deme of the tribe
                        Loentis.</note> who is the husband of my aunt, and by many other witnesses.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>For when it proved that Aphobus, though he had her fortune, would not maintain my
                    mother, and refused to let the property, choosing rather to administer it
                    himself in conjunction with the other guardians, Demochares remonstrated with
                    him about the matter; and Aphobus, when he had heard him, neither denied that he
                    had the money nor waxed indignant as one who had received nothing, but admitted
                    the fact, and said that he was having a little dispute with my mother about her
                    jewels, and that, when he had settled this matter, he would act regarding the
                    maintenance and all else in such a way that I should have no ground for
                    complaint. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>Yet, if it be shown that he made these admissions before Demochares and the
                    others who were present; that he received from Demophon and Therippides the
                    money accruing from the sale of the slaves in part settlement of the marriage
                    portion; that he gave to his co-trustees a written acknowledgement that he had
                    received the portion; and that he occupied the house immediately after the death
                    of my father; will it not be clear—the matter being admitted by everybody—that
                    he has received the portion, the eighty minae, and that his denial of having
                    received it is a piece of shameless impudence? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>To prove that what I say is true, take and read
                    the depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>The dowry, then, he got in this way, and kept. But in the event of his
                    not marrying my mother the law declares that he owes me the amount of the dowry
                    with interest at nine obols a month.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is,
                        at 18 percent.</note> However, I set it down at a drachma a month only. This
                    comes, if one adds the principle and the interest for ten years, to about three
                    talents. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>This money I have thus shown you that he received and that he confessed in the
                    presence of a host of witnesses that he had it. Then he has also in his
                    possession thirty minae besides, which he received as the revenue from the
                    factory, and of which he has tried to defraud me in the most shameless manner
                    possible. My father left me a revenue of thirty minae accruing from the factory;
                    and after the sale by these men of one-half of the slaves, I should receive the
                    proportionate sum of fifteen minae. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>Therippides, however, who had charge of the slaves for seven years, has submitted
                    an account of eleven minae a year, four minae a year less than it should have
                    been; and the defendant who had charge of the business at the first for two
                    years shows no profit whatever, but says sometimes that the factory was idle,
                    and sometimes that he was not himself the manager, but that the foreman,
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName>, a freedman of ours, had
                    charge of it, and that I should look for an accounting from him. If he persists
                    even now in making any of these statements he will easily be convicted of
                    falsehood. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>If he declares that the factory was idle, yet he has himself rendered an account
                    of money expended, not on provisions for the men, but for their work—ivory for
                    the trade, swordhandles, and other supplies—indicating that the workmen were
                    busy. Furthermore, he charges me with money which he has paid to Therippides for
                    the hire of three slaves of his who were in my factory. Yet if no work was being
                    done, Therippides should have received no pay, nor should these expenditures
                    have been charged to me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Again, if he alleges that the work was done, but that there was no market for
                    goods manufactured, he ought at any rate to show that he has delivered to me
                    these goods, and to produce witnesses in whose presence he delivered them.
                    Seeing that he has done neither of these things, how can you doubt that he is
                    keeping thirty minae, the two years' income from the factory, since the business
                    has so manifestly been carried on? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>If, however, he shall make none of these statements, but shall assert that
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> had charge of everything,
                    how can you believe him, when he alleges that he himself made the disbursements
                    amounting to more than five hundred drachmae, but that any profits which accrued
                    are in the hands of <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName>? For my part,
                    I think it likely that the very opposite is the case, supposing that
                            <persName><surname>Milyas</surname></persName> actually did have charge
                    of the work,—that he made the disbursements, and that Aphobus received the
                    profits, if we may draw any conclusion from the general character and the
                    shamelessness of the man.Take now and read these depositions to the jury.<quote
                        type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>These thirty minae, then, he has received from the factory, and the interest on
                    them for eight years; and if one sets this down at the rate of a drachma
                        only,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, at 12 percent, instead of 18
                        percent, which was normal in the case of marriage-portions.</note> it will
                    make thirty minae more. These sums he has himself embezzled, and, if they be
                    added to the marriage-portion, the total is about four talents, principal and
                    interest combined. Now I shall go on to show you what sums he has embezzled in
                    conjunction with his co-trustees, and what sums he asserts were never left by my
                    father at all. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>First, regarding the twenty sofa-makers, given to my father as security for a
                    debt of forty minae, whom my father certainly left behind him at his death, but
                    of whom these men show not a trace—let me prove to you with what utter
                    shamelessness and how openly they are seeking to cheat me of these. That these
                    slaves were left by my father in the house they all admit, and that they brought
                    him in an income of twelve minae every year. Yet these men report no receipts as
                    having come in to my credit from them in ten years, and Aphobus reckons up a
                    total expenditure on them of nearly a thousand drachmae. To such a pitch of
                    effrontery has he come! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>And these slaves themselves, upon whom he alleges that he has expended the money,
                    they have never handed over to me. On the contrary, they tell the idlest tale
                    imaginable, to the effect that the man who pledged the slaves to my father is
                    the vilest sort of a fellow, who has left many friendly loans<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)/ranos</foreign>, originally a
                        meal to which each contributed his due portion, came not unnaturally to mean
                        a “club” to which each member contributed, and from which he could claim
                        help, if need arose. Then it was also used, as here, of the “contribution”
                        or better, the “loan,” made to such members.</note> unpaid, and who is
                    overwhelmed with debt; and to prove this against him they have called a large
                    number of witnesses. But as for the slaves—who got them; how they went out of
                    the house; who took them away; or in what suit they lost them by judgement, they
                    are unable to say. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>Yet, if there were any truth in what they allege they would not be bringing
                    forward witnesses to prove this man's vile character (with which I have no
                    concern), but would be holding on to the slaves, or would show who took them,
                    and would have left not one of them out of sight. But as it is, though they
                    admit that the slaves were left by my father, and though they took possession of
                    them and enjoyed the profits from them for ten years, they have in the most
                    ruthless manner possible done away with the whole factory.To prove that I am
                    speaking the truth in this, take, please, and read the depositions.<quote
                        type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>That, moreover, Moeriades was not without resources and that my father did not
                    act foolishly in making the contract with him about the slaves, I will show you
                    by the clearest proof. For after Aphobus took into his own hands the factory as
                    you have yourselves heard from the witnesses, when it was his duty as my
                    guardian to prevent anyone else from advancing money on the same security, he
                    himself loaned to Moeriades on the security of these same slaves the sum of five
                    hundred drachmae, which he admits he has duly recovered from him in full. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>And yet is it not outrageous that we who made the prior loan should, besides
                    having received no profit from the slaves, have lost our security, while this
                    fellow, who loaned money on security belonging to us, and whose loan was so long
                    subsequent to ours, should from funds that were ours have recovered both
                    principal and interest, and have suffered no loss whatever? To prove that what I
                    say is true, take the deposition and read it.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>Consider now of how large a sum they are defrauding me in the matter of these
                    sofa-makers: the principal alone, forty minae, and interest upon it for ten
                    years, two talents; for they obtained from the slaves a profit of twelve minae
                    each year. Is this a trifling sum drawn from some obscure source, which might
                    easily have been miscalculated, or have they not manifestly robbed me of nearly
                    three talents<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Strictly, two talents and forty
                        minae. See the table on p. 11.</note>? Of this sum which they have jointly
                    scattered to the winds, it is surely right that I should recover a third from
                    the defendant. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, men of the jury, they have dealt in much the same way with the ivory
                    and iron which were left me. They do not produce them. Yet it is impossible that
                    one who possessed so many sofa-makers and so many sword-makers should not also
                    have left iron and ivory. These things must have been available, for what could
                    the slaves have produced without these materials? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>Well then, though my father possessed more than fifty slaves and conducted two
                    factories, one of which easily consumed two minae worth of ivory per month for
                    the sofas, while the sword-factory consumed as much more, and iron besides,
                    these men declare that he left no ivory and no iron; to such a pitch of
                    shamelessness have they come! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>From these facts alone it is easy to see that no credence is to be given to their
                    statements; but that my father actually did leave such an amount of these
                    materials as not only to suffice for his own workmen to use in their trade, but
                    also for sale to anyone else who wished to buy, is made clear by the fact that
                    he himself during his lifetime used to sell these materials, and that after his
                    death Demophon and the defendant continued to sell them from out my house to
                    those wishing to buy. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>And yet how large must one suppose the quantity left by my father to have been,
                    when it is shown to have sufficed for such extensive factories, and to have been
                    sold by the guardians besides? Was it a small amount, or not rather much more
                    than I have charged?<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Take now these depositions
                    and read them to the jury.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>Of this ivory, you see, there is more than a talent's worth of which
                    they make no report—neither of the raw material nor of the finished product. No;
                    this also they have utterly and absolutely made away with. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, men of the jury, I shall prove to you from the account which they
                    render, and from the receipts admitted by themselves, that these three men have
                    in their possession more than eight talents of my money, and that of this amount
                    Aphobus has separately taken three talents and one thousand drachmae. I shall
                    set down separately at a higher figure than they do themselves the moneys they
                    have expended, and shall deduct all the sums they have paid me, that you may see
                    the utter shamelessness of their attempts. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>They confess to have received from my estate, Aphobus one hundred and eight minae
                    (besides what I shall now show to be in his hands); Therippides two talents; and
                    Demophon eighty-seven minae. This makes altogether five talents and fifteen
                    minae. Of this sum there are nearly seventy-seven minae, the income from the
                    slaves, which were not received all at once, and a little less than four talents
                    of which they got possession immediately. Now, if you add to this last sum the
                    interest for ten years, reckoned at a drachma only<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">That is, at 12 percent, as above. Demosthenes is liberal
                        indeed in his allowances. The entire sum of seventy-seven minae is crossed
                        off as balanced by expenditures; the interest on four talents for ten years
                        is set down as four talents forty minae, instead of four talents forty-eight
                        minae, so that the total amount becomes eight talents and forty minae. From
                        this there are deducted the moneys paid to him (thirty-one minae) and those
                        paid in taxes (set down as thirty minae, instead of eighteen) and the
                        balance (roughly, eight talents less one talent), is reckoned as seven
                        talents.</note> you will find that the whole, principal and interest,
                    amounts to eight talents and four thousand drachmae. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>From the seventy-seven minae, the profits of the factory, the cost of maintenance
                    of the men must be deducted, for Therippides expended for this seven minae a
                    year, and I admit having received thus much. Thus they expended on our behalf in
                    the ten years seventy minae for maintenance; to this I add the balance, seven
                    hundred drachmae, and thus credit them with a larger expenditure than they do
                    themselves. There must also be deducted from the eight talents and more the sum
                    they handed over to me when I came of age, and the taxes which they have paid to
                    the state. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>The defendant and Therippides paid me thirty-one minae, and they compute that
                    they have paid eighteen minae in taxes. I will go beyond them and will make this
                    sum thirty minae, that they may have not a word to say in protest. Well, then,
                    if you take away one talent from the eight, seven are left, which, according to
                    their own admissions of receipts, they must necessarily have in their
                    possession. This sum, then, even if they rob me of everything else and deny that
                    they have it, they ought at least to have paid me, seeing that they admit having
                    received it from my estate. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>But what is it that they do? They report no return in interest for this money,
                    and tell me that they have expended the entire principal together with the
                    seventy-seven minae; and Demophon has, moreover, actually set me down as
                    indebted to him. Is not this absolute and barefaced effrontery? Is it not the
                    very excess of outrageous rapacity? What is the meaning of outrageous, if
                    matters pushed to this extreme are not to be so called? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>The defendant, then, for his own part, since he admits having received one
                    hundred and eight minae, has in his possession these and the interest on them
                    for ten years, in all about three talents and one thousand drachmae.In proof
                    that what I say is true—that each one of them in the account of his guardianship
                    admits that he has received the money, but claims to have spent it all—take the
                    depositions and read them.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>I think, men of the jury, that you have now been fully informed regarding the
                    theft and wrongdoings of each of these men. You would, however, have had more
                    exact knowledge of the matter, if they had been willing to give up to me the
                    will which my father left; for it contained (so my mother tells me) a statement
                    of all the property that my father left, along with instructions regarding the
                    funds from which these men were to take what had been given them, and regarding
                    the letting of the property.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>But as it is, on my demanding it, they admit that there was a will, but they do
                    not produce it; and they take this course because they do not want to make known
                    the amount of the property which was left, and which they have embezzled, and to
                    the end that they may not appear to have received their legacies—as though they
                    would not easily be convicted by the facts themselves.Take now, and read them
                    the evidence of those in whose presence they made their answers.<quote
                        type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>This man<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">“This man” appears to refer to
                        Therippides.</note> declares that a will was made and testifies that in it
                    the two talents were given to Demophon, and the eighty minae to Aphobus; but he
                    declares there was no additional clause regarding the seventy minae which
                    Therippides received, or regarding the amount of the property bequeathed, or
                    instructions as to the letting of it; for it was not to his interest to make
                    these further admissions.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now take the answer of
                    the defendant.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>He also declares that the will was made, and that the money accruing from the
                    copper and the gall was duly paid to Therippides, which Therippides denies; and
                    that the two talents were paid to Demophon; but in regard to the money given to
                    himself, while he admits that the clause was written in the will, he declares
                    that he did not assent to it, in order that he may not appear to have received
                    it. But as to the amount of the estate he, too, reveals absolutely nothing, nor
                    as to letting the property. For it was not to his interest either to make these
                    further admissions. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>The amount of the property that was left is, however, none the less clear (though
                    these men seek to conceal it) from the terms of the will, in accordance with
                    which they state that such large sums were given to them severally. When a man
                    out of four talents and three thousand drachmae has given to two of these men
                    three talents and two thousand drachmae as marriage-portions, and to the third
                    the interest on seventy minae, it is clear, I fancy, that he took these sums,
                    not from a small estate, but from one bequeathed to me of more than double this
                    amount. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>For, I take it, he would not wish to leave me, his son, in poverty, and be eager
                    further to enrich these men, who were already wealthy. No; it was because of the
                    size of the estate left to me that he gave to Therippides the interest on a sum
                    so considerable, and to Demophon that on the two talents—though he was not yet
                    to marry my sister—in order to accomplish one or the other of two ends: either
                    he would by his gifts encourage them to act the more honorably in the
                    guardianship, or, if they should prove dishonest, they would meet with no
                    leniency at your hands, seeing that, after being so liberally treated, they
                    sinned so grievously against us. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>Well now, the defendant, who in addition to my mother's marriage-portion has
                    taken the female servants, and has lived in the house, when it becomes necessary
                    to render an account of these matters, says he is busy with his own affairs; and
                    he has come to such a pitch of rapaciousness, that he has even cheated my
                    instructors of their fees, and has left unpaid some of the taxes, although he
                    charges me with the amounts.Take these depositions too, and read them to the
                        jury.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>How could one show more clearly that he has made havoc of the whole estate,
                    sparing nothing, however small, than by proving, as I have done by so many
                    witnesses and proofs, that he admitted having received the marriage-portion, and
                    that he acknowledged in writing to the guardians that he had it; that he enjoyed
                    the profits of the factory, but makes report of none; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>that of our other effects he has sold some without paying to us the proceeds,
                    while others he has taken to himself and hidden; that according to the account
                    which he has himself rendered, he has embezzled large sums; that in addition to
                    all this he has made away with the will, sold the slaves, and in all other
                    respects has administered the estate as not even the bitterest enemies would
                    have done? I do not see how anyone could prove the matter more clearly. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>He had the audacity to say before the
                        arbitrator<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The public arbitrators at
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> were chosen from a
                        body of citizens of advanced age. To one or another of these men (selected
                        by lot) the magistrate would refer civil cases before trial in hopes of
                        bringing about a settlement of the points at issue out of court.</note> that
                    he had paid many debts for me out of the estate to Demophon and Therippides, his
                    fellow-guardians, and that they received a large part of my property, yet
                    neither of these facts was he able to prove. He did not show by the books that
                    my father left me in debt, nor has he brought forward as witnesses the men whom
                    he says he paid; nor, again, is the amount of money which he charged against his
                    fellow-guardians equal to the amount which he is shown to have received himself.
                    On the contrary, it is much less. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>When the arbitrator questioned him about each of these matters, and asked him
                    whether he had managed his own estate from the interest or had spent the
                    principal, and whether,if he had been under guardianship, he would have accepted
                    an account of this sort from his guardians or would have demanded that the money
                    be duly paid to him with the accrued interest, he made no answer to these
                    questions, but tendered me a challenge<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        challenge was often used in Athenian lawsuits. Here Aphobus virtually offers
                        Demosthenes a compromise, fixing the value of the estate at ten talents
                        instead of thirty. Sometimes the challenger “dares” his opponent to give an
                        oath, or to offer a slave for torture.</note> to the effect that he was
                    ready to show that my property was worth ten talents, and said that, if it fell
                    short of this amount, he would himself make up the difference. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>When I bade him prove this to the arbitrator, he did not do so, nor did he show
                    that his fellow-guardians had paid me (for if he had, the arbitrator would not
                    have given judgement against him); but he put in a piece of evidence<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The speaker would have the jury think that the
                        bit of evidence in question is unworthy of further notice.</note> of a sort
                    regarding which he will try to find something to say.<milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/>If even now he still tries to assert that I am in possession of
                    property, ask him who handed it over to me, and demand that he produce witnesses
                    to prove each statement. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>If he declares that it is my possession in this sense, that he reckons up what is
                    in the hands of either of the trustees, it will be clear that he accounts for
                    only a third part, and still does not prove that I have possession of it. For as
                    I have convicted the defendant of having in his possession the large amount I
                    have stated, I shall also prove that each of them has not less than he. This
                    statement, therefore, will not help him. No; he must show that either he or his
                    fellow-trustees really handed the money over to me. If he fails to prove this,
                    why should you pay any attention to his challenge? He still does not prove that
                    I have the money. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>Being sorely at a loss to explain any of these matters before the arbitrator, and
                    being convicted on each point, just as he is now before you, he had the audacity
                    to make an outrageously false statement, to the effect that my father left me
                    four talents buried in the ground, and that he had put my mother in charge of
                    them. He made this statement in order that, if I should assume that he would
                    repeat it here, I might waste my time in refuting it, when I ought to be
                    preferring the rest of my charges against him; or if I should pass it over, not
                    expecting him to repeat it, then he himself might now bring it up, in the hope
                    that I, by seeming to be rich, might meet with less compassion from you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>Yet he who dared to make such a statement put in no evidence to prove it, but
                    relied on his bare word, as though you would lightly give him credence. When one
                    asks him upon what he has spent so much of my money, he says he has paid debts
                    for me, and so represents me as poor; yet, when it pleases him, he makes me
                    rich, as it seems, seeing that my father left such a sum of money in the house.
                    It is easy to see, however, from many considerations that he is lying, and that
                    there is no basis of fact in this story. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>For if my father had no confidence in these men, it is plain that he would
                    neither have entrusted to them the rest of his property, nor, if he had left
                    this money in the way alleged, would he have told them of it. It would have been
                    the height of madness to tell them of hidden treasure, when he was not going to
                    make them trustees even of his visible property. But if he had confidence in
                    them, he would not, I take it, have given into their hands the bulk of his
                    property, and not have put them in control of this. Nor would he have entrusted
                    this remainder to my mother to keep, and then have given her herself in marriage
                    to this man who was one of the guardians. For it is not reasonable that he
                    should seek to secure the money through my mother, and yet to put one of the men
                    whom he distrusted in control both of her and of it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, if there were any truth in all this, do you suppose Aphobus would
                    not have taken my mother to wife, bequeathed to him as she was by my father? He
                    had already taken her marriage-portion—the eighty minae—as though he were going
                    to marry her; but he subsequently married the daughter of Philonides of
                        Melite<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Melite was a deme of the tribe
                        Cecropis.</note> But if there had been four talents in the house and in her
                    custody, as he alleges, don't you imagine he would have raced to get possession
                    both of her and of them? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="section">
                <p>Would he have joined with his co-trustees in so shamefully plundering my visible
                    property, which many of you knew had been left me, and have refrained, when he
                    had the chance, from seizing a fund to the evidence of which you would not be
                    able to testify? Who can believe this? It is impossible, men of the jury; it is
                    impossible. No; my father entrusted to these men all the property which he left,
                    and the defendant will tell this story, that I may meet with less compassion
                    from you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="section">
                <p>I have many other charges to make against him, but summing them all up in one, I
                    will break down every defence of his. He could have avoided all this trouble,
                    had he let the estate in accordance with these laws.Take the laws and read
                        them.<quote type="Laws">
                        <title>Laws</title>
                    </quote>In the case of Antidorus, as a result of his property having been let in
                    accordance with these laws, there was given over to him, at the end of six
                    years, an estate of six talents and more from an original amount of three
                    talents and three thousand drachmae; and this some of you have seen with your
                    own eyes; for Theogenes of Probalinthus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Probalinthus was a deme of the tribe Pandionis.</note> who leased the
                    estate, counted out that sum in the market-place. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="section">
                <p>But in my case, fourteen talents in ten years, when consideration is given to the
                    time and the terms of his lease, ought to have been more than trebled. Ask him
                    why he did not do this. If he declares that it was better not to let the estate,
                    let him show, not that it has been doubled or trebled, but that the mere
                    principal has been paid back to me in full. But if out of fourteen talents they
                    have handed over to me not even seventy minae, and one of them has actually
                    recorded me as in his debt, how can it be right to accept any word they say? It
                    is surely impossible. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="section">
                <p>Seeing that the fortune left me was of so great value, as you heard at the
                    beginning, the third part of it bringing in an income of fifty minae, these men,
                    albeit insatiate in their greed, even if they refused to let the property, might
                    out of this income and leaving the principal untouched, have maintained us, paid
                    the taxes to the state, and saved the residue. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="61" type="section">
                <p>The rest of the estate—an amount twice as large—they might have invested
                    profitably, and, if greedy for money, have taken a reasonable amount for
                    themselves, and have increased my estate from the income, besides keeping the
                    principal intact. Yet they did nothing of the sort. Instead, by selling to one
                    another the most valuable of the slaves and by absolutely doing away with the
                    rest, they destroyed the existing source of my income and secured a considerable
                    one for themselves at my cost. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="62" type="section">
                <p>Having taken all the rest thus shamefully, they unite in maintaining that more
                    than half of my property was never left to me at all. They have rendered an
                    account as though the estate were one of five talents only; they do not produce
                    the principal, though reporting no income from it, but have the impudence to
                    tell me that the capital itself has been expended. And for this audacity they
                    feel no shame! </p>
            </div>
            <div n="63" type="section">
                <p>What, pray, would have been my plight, if I had continued longer as their ward?
                    They would have hard work to tell. For when, after the lapse of ten years, I
                    have recovered so little from two of these men, and by the third am even set
                    down as a debtor, have I not good ground for indignation? Nay, it is wholly
                    clear. If I had been left an orphan of a year old, and had been six years longer
                    under their guardianship, I should never have recovered even the pitiful amounts
                    I now have. For, if the expenditures they have made were justifiable, the sums
                    they have handed over to me would not have lasted six years, but they would
                    either have had to support me themselves or to have let me perish from hunger.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="64" type="section">
                <p>Yet is it not an outrage, if estates left to others of a value of one or two
                    talents have as a result of letting been doubled or trebled, so that the owners
                    have been called upon for state services,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That
                        is, they have been classed among the wealthy citizens. See note
                            <emph>a</emph> on <bibl n="Dem. 27.7">Dem. 27.7</bibl>, above.</note>
                    while mine, which has been wont to equip triremes and to make large
                    contributions in taxes, will be unable to contribute even small sums thanks to
                    the shameless acts of these men? What words are gross enough to describe their
                    conduct? They have done away with the will, thinking to avoid discovery, their
                    own estates they have administered from the income, and have greatly increased
                    their capital by drawing upon my funds, while, as for my own estate, they have
                    destroyed my entire capital, as if in requital for some grievous wrong we had
                    done them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="65" type="section">
                <p>You, on your part, do not act thus even toward those who sin against you: when
                    you give judgement against any of them, you do not take away all that they have,
                    but in pity for their wives and children you leave something even to these. But
                    these men are so different from you that, although they had received legacies
                    from us to make them administer their trust faithfully, they have done us these
                    outrageous wrongs. They felt no touch of shame for their ruthlessness toward my
                    sister, who, though my father left two talents as the dowry due her, will now
                    get no fitting portion. Nay, they have recked nothing of kinship, as though they
                    had been left to us, not as friends and kinsfolk, but as bitterest enemies. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="66" type="section">
                <p>For myself, I am the most wretched of men. I am helpless both to give my sister a
                    portion and to maintain myself. Besides this, the state is pressing me hard,
                    demanding taxes, and with right, for my father left me an estate large enough to
                    pay them; but these men have taken all the money left me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="67" type="section">
                <p>And now, in seeking to recover what is mine, I have come into the greatest peril;
                    for if the defendant is acquitted (which heaven forbid!) I shall have to pay
                    one-sixth of the damages,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The plaintiff in a
                        private suit who was so far from being able to prove his case that he did
                        not receive a fifth part of the votes, was subject to a fine of one-sixth of
                        the damages claimed (an obol for each drachma). Failure to pay entailed the
                        loss of civic rights. Compare <bibl n="Dem. 28.18">Dem. 28.18</bibl>, end.
                        In the case of Aphobus, the amount for which he would be held liable, if he
                        lost suit, would be fixed by the court.</note> one hundred minae. The
                    defendant, if you give judgement against him, will be liable for a sum to be
                    determined, and will make payment, not out of his own funds, but out of mine;
                    while in my case the sum is fixed, so that I shall not only have been robbed of
                    my inheritance, but shall also lose my civic rights, unless you now take pity on
                    me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="68" type="section">
                <p>I beg you, therefore, men of the jury, I entreat, I implore you, to remember the
                    laws and the oaths which you took as jurors, to render me the aid that is my
                    due, and not to count the pleas of this man of higher worth than mine. It is
                    your duty to show pity, not toward the guilty, but toward those in unmerited
                    misfortune; not upon those who so cruelly rob another of his goods, but upon me,
                    who have for so long a time been deprived of my inheritance and treated with
                    outrage by these men, and who am now in danger of losing my civic rights. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="69" type="section">
                <p>Loudly methinks, would my father groan, should he learn that I, his son, am in
                    danger of being forced to pay the sixth part of the marriage-portions and
                    legacies given by himself to these men; and that, while others of our countrymen
                    out of their own funds have dowered the daughters of impoverished kinsfolk and
                    even friends, Aphobus refuses to pay back even the marriage-portion which he
                    took, and that too in the tenth year.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
