<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Ergocles</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>The counts of the accusation
        are so many and so grave, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that
        not even were he put to death a number of times for each one of his acts would Ergocles be
        able, in my opinion, to give your people due satisfaction. For it is evident that he has
        betrayed cities, wronged your representatives and your citizens, and advanced himself from
        poverty to wealth at your expense. <milestone n="2" unit="section"/>Now tell me, how can you
        forgive these persons, when you see the fleet that they commanded breaking up for want of
        money and dwindling in numbers,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Diodorus Siculus ( <bibl
            n="Diod. 14.94">Dio. Sic. 14.94</bibl>) mentions a storm in which Thrasybulus lost 23
          warships.</note> while these men, who were poor and needy on sailing out, have so quickly
        acquired the largest fortune in the city? It is your duty, therefore, men of <placeName
          key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to show indignation at such conduct. <milestone
          n="3" unit="section"/>And indeed it would be strange if now, when you are yourselves thus
        oppressed by the special levies, you should forgive men who embezzle and take bribes; and
        yet heretofore, when your estates were ample and the public revenue was ample too, those who
        coveted your property you punished with death. <milestone n="4" unit="section"/>I think you
        will all agree that, if Thrasybulus had proposed to you that he should sail out with
        warships which he was to deliver up worn out instead of new; that the dangers were to be
        yours, while the benefits would accrue to his own friends; and that he would reduce you to
        worse poverty owing to the levies, but would make Ergocles and his other adulators the
        wealthiest men in the city,—not one of you would have given the man permission to sail out
        with your ships. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>And to make matters worse, as soon as you
        had decreed that an inventory be made of the sums obtained from the cities, and that his
        fellow-commanders should sail home to undergo their audit, Ergocles said that there you were
        at your slander-mongering and hankering after the ancient laws,<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">Which regulated the collection of tribute from the states subject to
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> down to the time of the Peloponnesian
          War.</note> and he advised Thrasybulus to occupy <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium"
          >Byzantium</placeName>, keep the ships, and marry Seuthes’<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">A prince of <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> friendly to
          Thrasybulus.</note> daughter: <milestone n="6" unit="section"/>“by this means,” he told
        him, “you will cut short their slander-mongering; for you will make them sit still,
        contriving no harm against you and your friends, but full of fear for themselves.” So far
        did they go, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,—as soon as they had
        gorged themselves and were regaled with your possessions,—in regarding themselves as alien
        to the city. <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>No sooner are they rich than they hate you;
        they plan thenceforth, not to be your subjects, but to be your rulers, and, apprehensive for
        the fruits of their depredations, they are ready to occupy strongholds, establish an
        oligarchy, and seek every means of exposing you, day after day, to the most awful dangers.
        The result will be, they expect, that you will cease paying attention to their particular
        offences and, in terror for yourselves and for the city, will leave them in peace.
          <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>Now, as for Thrasybulus, men of <placeName
          key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,—for there is no need to say more about him,—he
        did well to end his life as he did<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">He was killed in a riot
          at <placeName key="tgn,7002374">Aspendus</placeName>, <dateRange from="-389" to="-388"
            >389</dateRange>-388 B.C.</note>: for it was not right for him either to live in the
        prosecution of such schemes or to suffer death at your hands with his repute of having
        served you well in the past, but rather to settle his account with the city in that sort of
        way. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>But the others, I see, in consequence of the Assembly
        that was held two days ago,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">When Ergocles had been voted
          guilty.</note> are no longer sparing their money, but are purchasing their lives from the
        speakers, from their enemies, and from the Committee,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">See
            <bibl n="Lys. 22.2">Lys. 22.2</bibl> and note.</note> and are corrupting numerous
        Athenians with hard cash. It is your duty to clear yourselves of that suspicion by punishing
        this man today, and to make it plain to all people that there is no sum large enough to
        overcome you in your purpose of exacting requital from the guilty. <milestone n="10"
          unit="section"/>For you must reflect, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
          >Athens</placeName>, that it is not Ergocles alone, but the whole city as well, that is on
        trial. Today you are to demonstrate to your officers whether they ought to be upright or,
        after abstracting as much of your property as they can, to compass their salvation by the
        same means as these men are now applying. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/>Well, of one
        thing you may be assured, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>: whoever
        in this serious stringency of your affairs either betrays your cities or decides to steal
        your money or receive bribes, is the very man to surrender your walls and your ships to the
        enemy, and to establish oligarchy in place of democracy. It is not right, then, that you
        should be mastered by their devices: you should rather make an example for all men to see,
        and regard neither profit nor pity nor aught else as more important than the punishment of
        these men. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>I do not
        suppose, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, that in regard to
          <placeName key="tgn,7016142">Halicarnassus</placeName> and his command and his own
        proceedings Ergocles will attempt any justification, but that he will state that he returned
        from Phyle,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">With the democrats in <date value="-403"
            >403</date> B.C.</note> that he is a democrat, and that he bore his share in your
        dangers. But I, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, do not view the
        position in that sort of way. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>Those who, longing for
        liberty and justice, desiring the maintenance of the laws and hating wrongdoers, shared in
        your dangers, I do not regard as bad citizens, nor would it be unfair, I say, that the exile
        of that party should be reckoned into their account. But those who, after their return, do
        injury to your people under a democracy, and enlarge their private properties at your
        expense, deserve to feel your wrath far more than the Thirty. <milestone n="14"
          unit="section"/>The latter were elected for the very purpose of doing you harm by any
        available means, whereas you have entrusted yourselves to these men in order that they may
        promote the greatness and freedom of the city. Nothing of the sort have you secured: so far
        as they could, they have involved you in the most awful dangers; and hence you would be far
        more justified in pitying yourselves, your children and your wives than these men, when you
        think of the ravages that you suffer at such hands as theirs. <milestone n="15"
          unit="section"/>For, just when we are convinced that we have salvation in our grasp, we
        meet with more terrible treatment from our officers than from the enemy. Of course you all
        understand that you have no hope of salvation if you undergo a reverse.<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">The reference is to the depletion of the Treasury.</note> You ought therefore
        to exhort yourselves to impose on these men today the extreme penalty, and to make it
        evident to the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> that you punish the
        guilty and mean to reform your officers. <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>This, at least,
        is my own exhortation to you; and you should know that, if you take my advice, you will
        decide wisely for yourselves, but if not, you will find the rest of the citizens more
        unruly. Besides, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, if you acquit
        them, they will not be thankful to you, but to their expenditure and to the funds that they
        have embezzled; so that, while you endow yourselves with their enmity, they will thank those
        means for their salvation. <milestone n="17" unit="section"/>Furthermore, men of <placeName
          key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, both the people of <placeName key="tgn,7016142"
          >Halicarnassus</placeName> and the other victims of these men, if you inflict the extreme
        penalty upon them, will feel that, although they have been ruined by these persons, they
        have been vindicated by you; but if you save their lives, they will suppose that you have
        put yourselves in accord with their betrayers. So, bearing all these points in mind, you
        ought by the same act to show your gratitude to your friends and to do justice upon the
        guilty.</p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
