<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Apaturius </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>The law, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, ordains that
                    actions for merchants and shipowners shall be before the Thesmothetae<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Thesmothetae were the six archons (other
                        than the Eponymus, the Basileus, and the Polemarch), and were empowered to
                        administer justice in cases not specifically within the province of any
                        other magistrate.</note> if they have been in any way wronged in the market
                    either in connection with a voyage from <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> to any point, or from some other port to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; and it fixes imprisonment as the
                    penalty for wrongdoers until such time as they shall have paid the amount
                    adjudged against them, so that no one may lightly do wrong to any merchant. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>To those, however, who are brought into court in cases where no contract has been
                    made, the law gives the right to have recourse to a special plea, that no one
                    may bring a baseless or malicious suit, but that actions may be confined to
                    those among the merchants and shipowners who are really wronged. Many defendants
                    in mercantile suits have before now entered special pleas in accordance with
                    this law, and have come before you and proved that their adversaries were making
                    unjust charges and bringing baseless suits under pretence of being engaged in
                    commerce. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>Who it is that has conspired with this fellow against me and who has concocted
                    this suit, will become clear to you as my speech goes on. Since, however,
                    Apaturius has made a false charge against me, and is suing me contrary to law,
                    seeing that there had been a release and discharge from all contracts made
                    between him and me, and there exists no other contract made with him by me
                    whether for business by sea or on land, I have entered the special plea that the
                    action is not maintainable, according to the following laws.<quote type="Laws">
                        <title>Laws</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>That Apaturius, then, has instituted suit against me contrary to these laws and
                    that his charges are false, I shall show you by many proofs. I, men of the jury,
                    have by now been for a long time engaged in foreign trade, and up to a certain
                    time risked the sea in my own person; it is not quite seven years since I gave
                    up voyaging, and, having a moderate capital, I try to put it to work by making
                    loans on adventures overseas. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>As I have visited many places and spend my time in your exchange, I know most of
                    those who are seafarers, and with these men from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName> I am on intimate terms through
                    having myself spent much time there. My position, then, was such as I have
                    described, when this fellow put into our port with a fellow-countryman of his,
                    named Parmeno, a Byzantine by birth, who was an exile from his country. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>The plaintiff and Parmeno came up to me on the exchange and spoke about money. It
                    happened that the plaintiff owed forty minae on his ship, and his creditors were
                    pressing him hard with demands for their money, and were about to board the ship
                    and take possession of it, as his note was overdue. While he was in this
                    embarrassment, Parmeno agreed to give him ten minae, and the plaintiff asked me
                    to contribute thirty minae, charging that the creditors in their eagerness to
                    secure the ship had slandered him on the exchange, that they might seize the
                    ship by putting him in a position where he could not pay.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>I happened to have no ready money in hand, but being acquainted with Heracleides,
                    the banker, I persuaded him to lend the money, and to take me as surety. But
                    when now the thirty minae had been procured, Parmeno happened to fall out with
                    the plaintiff. However, seeing that he had agreed to furnish him with ten minae
                    and had already given him three of them, he was compelled on account of the
                    money he had given to pay the remainder as well. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>Not wishing, however, for the reason given, to make the loan in his own name, he
                    bade me to arrange it so that things should be as safe as possible for him. So I
                    took over the seven minae from Parmeno, and having had transferred to myself the
                    obligation for the three, which the plaintiff had already received from him,
                    caused a bill of sale to be executed on the ship and the slaves until such time
                    as he should repay me the ten minae, which he had received through me, and also
                    the thirty for which he had made me his surety with the banker. In proof that my
                    words are true, hear the depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>In this way, then, Apaturius here got rid of his creditors. Not long after this,
                    the bank having failed, and Heracleides for a time having gone into hiding, the
                    plaintiff schemed to send the slaves from <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, and to remove the ship from the harbor. This was the
                    cause of my first quarrel with him. For Parmeno, learning of the fact, laid
                    hands on the slaves as they were being taken away, and prevented the sailing of
                    the ship; then he sent for me, and told me of the affair. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>When I heard him, thinking this fellow a most impious wretch because of his
                    attempt, I set about considering how I might myself get free from my guaranty to
                    the bank, and how the foreigner<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The foreigner
                        is, of course, Parmeno.</note> might avoid the loss of the money he had lent
                    this fellow through me. After stationing men to guard the ship I told the whole
                    story to the sureties of the bank and turned the security over to them, telling
                    them that the foreigner had a lien of ten minae on the ship. Having arranged
                    this, I attached the slaves, in order that, if any shortage occurred, the
                    deficiency might be made up by the proceeds of their sale. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>In this way, when I found that Apaturius was a rascal, I set matters right in my
                    own interest and in the interest of the foreigner. But Apaturius, as though the
                    wrong was on my side, and not on his, made complaint to me, and asked if it were
                    not enough for me to be released from my guaranty to the bank, without also
                    attaching the ship and the slaves to secure his money for Parmeno, and thus
                    making an enemy of himself in the interest of one who was an exile. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>I replied that, when a man had put his trust in me, I was all the less inclined
                    to leave him in the lurch, because, while he was an exile and in misfortune, he
                    was being wronged by the plaintiff; and after I had done everything possible,
                    and had incurred the utmost enmity on the part of this fellow, I with difficulty
                    secured the money, the ship being sold for forty minae, the precise amount for
                    which she was mortgaged. The thirty minae then having been paid back to the
                    bank, and the ten minae to Parmeno, in the presence of many witnesses, we
                    cancelled the bond in accordance with which the money had been lent, and
                    mutually released and discharged one another from our engagements so that the
                    plaintiff had nothing more to do with me, nor I with him. In proof that my words
                    are true, hear the depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>Since then I have had no business transaction with the fellow, whether great or
                    small, but Parmeno sued him for damages for the blows which he received from him
                    when he laid hands on the slaves as they were being carried off, and because he
                    had been prevented by him from making the voyage to <placeName key="tgn,7003122"
                        >Sicily</placeName>. When the action had been instituted, Parmeno tendered
                    an oath to Apaturius regarding some of his charges, and he accepted it, and
                    furthermore made a deposit to be forfeited if he did not swear the oath.In proof
                    that my words are true, take the deposition.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Having accepted the oath, since he was aware that many would know that he had
                    perjured himself, he did not present himself for the swearing, but, as though he
                    could get free of the oath by an action, he summoned Parmeno into court. When
                    both actions had been instituted, on the advice of persons present they
                    proceeded to an arbitration, and after drawing up an agreement they submitted
                    the matter to one common arbitrator, Phocritus, a fellow-country-man of theirs;
                    and each one appointed one man to sit with Phocritus, Apaturius choosing
                    Aristocles of Oea,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A deme of the tribe
                        Oeneïs.</note> and Parmeno choosing me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>They agreed in the articles that, if we three were of one mind, our decision
                    should be binding on them, but, if not, then they should be bound to abide by
                    what the two should determine. Having made this agreement, they appointed
                    sureties for one another to guarantee its fulfillment. Apaturius appointed
                    Aristocles, and Parmeno Archippus of Myrrhinus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >A deme of the tribe Pandionis.</note> At the outset they deposited their
                    agreement with Phocritus, but upon his bidding them to deposit it with someone
                    else, they deposited it with Aristocles.In proof that my words are true, hear
                    the depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>That the agreements were deposited with Aristocles, and that the arbitration was
                    left with Phocritus, Aristocles and myself, has been testified to you by
                    witnesses who know the facts. And now, men of the jury, I beg of you to hear
                    from me what happened after this; for from this it will be clear to you that
                    this man Apaturius is making a claim upon me which is baseless and malicious.
                    For when he saw that Phocritus and I were of one mind, and realized that we
                    should give judgement against him, wishing to break down the arbitration, he
                    sought, in collusion with the man who held them, to destroy the articles of
                    agreement, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>and he proceeded to contend that Aristocles was his arbitrator, and declared that
                    Phocritus and I were empowered to do nothing else than seek to bring about a
                    reconciliation. Angered at this statement, Parmeno demanded of Aristocles that
                    he produce the agreement, adding that if there had been any criminal meddling
                    with the papers, proof of the fact would not be far to seek, for his own slave
                    had written them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>Aristocles promised that he would produce the articles, but up to this day has
                    not brought them to light. He did meet us on the appointed day at the
                        Hephaesteum,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The temple of Hephaestus;
                        perhaps the well-preserved Doric structure commonly called the
                        Theseum.</note> but made the excuse that his slave while waiting for him had
                    fallen asleep and lost the document. The man who concocted this plot was
                    Eryxias, the physician from Peiraeus, an intimate friend of Aristocles, the same
                    man who out of enmity toward me has also got up this action against me.Now in
                    proof that Aristocles pretended that he had lost the document, hear the
                        depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>After this the arbitration was done away with, the articles of agreement having
                    disappeared and the authority of the arbitrators being questioned. They did
                    endeavor to draw up new articles about these matters, but could come to no
                    agreement, as the plaintiff insisted on having Aristocles, and Parmeno the three
                    to whom in the first instance the arbitration had been referred. Nevertheless,
                    although no new articles had been drawn, and those originally drawn had been
                    made away with, the man who had made away with them came to such a pitch of
                    shamelessness that he declared he would in his own single person pronounce the
                    award. Parmeno called witnesses to be present, and forbade Aristocles to
                    pronounce an award against him, without his co-arbitrators, in defiance of the
                    articles of agreement.Hear the deposition of those in whose presence he thus
                    forbade him.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>After this there befell Parmeno, men of the jury, a dire misfortune. He was
                    dwelling in Ophrynium<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A city in the <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002331">Troad</placeName>.</note> because of his being an
                    exile from home, when the earthquake in the <placeName key="tgn,7010345"
                        >Chersonese</placeName> occurred; and in the collapse of his house his wife
                    and children perished. Immediately on hearing of the disaster he departed by
                    ship from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Aristocles,
                    although the man had adjured him in the presence of witnesses not to pronounce
                    judgement against him without his co-arbitrators, when Parmeno had left the
                    country because of the disaster, pronounced an award against him by default.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Phocritus and I, who were named in the same articles, refused to participate in
                    the award, because the plaintiff denied that in his view we were arbitrators;
                    but Aristocles, whose authority was not only disputed, but who had expressly
                    been forbidden to act, nevertheless made the declaration—a thing which not one
                    of you and not one of all the other Athenians could have been induced to do.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>For all that Apaturius and the arbitrator did in connection with the
                    disappearance of the articles and the pronouncing of the award, the man wronged,
                    if ever he comes safely back to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, will obtain satisfaction from them. But since Apaturius
                    has come to such a pitch of shamelessness as to bring suit against me also,
                    charging that I undertook to pay any sum that might be awarded against Parmeno,
                    and since he declares that my name was entered in the articles as surety, I
                    shall free myself from such a charge in the proper way; I shall first bring
                    forward witnesses to prove that it was not I who became surety for Parmeno, but
                    Archippus of Myrrhinus; and I shall then undertake, men of the jury, to make my
                    defence by circumstantial proofs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>In the first place, I hold that the time is a witness for me to prove that the
                    charge is groundless. For the agreement to arbitrate made by this fellow and
                    Parmeno and the award of Aristocles took place two years ago; but merchants may
                    bring action every month from Boëdromion to Munichion,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Roughly, from September to April, the period when the seas
                        were closed, and the ships laid up in port.</note> in order that they may
                    obtain their rights without delay and put to sea. So, if I was in truth a surety
                    for Parmeno, why did not Apaturius immediately after the award proceed to
                    collect the sum guaranteed? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>It is not open to him to say that because of his friendship for me he was loth to
                    incur my enmity, for he had himself in utter unfriendliness been forced by me to
                    pay the one thousand drachmae due to Parmeno; and when he was trying to get his
                    ship out of the port in his plot to sneak away and to defraud the bank of what
                    was due, it was I who prevented him. So, if I had become a surety for Parmeno,
                    he would not have waited until two years afterward to exact the sum guaranteed,
                    but would have proceeded to do so at once. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>Ah, but he was well provided with funds, so that it was open to him to proceed
                    against me later on, and at the moment he had no time, as he was about to put to
                    sea! On the contrary, he was in such straits that he had lost all his effects,
                    and had sold his ship. And, if there really had been anything to prevent his
                    immediately bringing suit against me, why, when he was in town last year, did he
                    not dare, I will not say to bring suit, but even to make a demand? It was surely
                    the proper course for him, if judgement had been given against Parmeno in his
                    favour, and if I was the latter's surety, to come to me himself accompanied by
                    witnesses, and to demand the amount guaranteed, if not the year before last, at
                    any rate in the year just past; and then, if I proffered payment, to take his
                    money, and, if I did not, to bring suit. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>For in claims of this sort everyone makes demand before he brings suit. Well,
                    there isn't a person living who will testify that he was present either last
                    year or the year before, when this man either instituted proceedings against me
                    or made any mention to me whatever of the claims for which he is now suing me.To
                    prove that he was in town last year when the courts were open, please take the
                        deposition.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>Now, please take the law which declares that guaranties shall be for a year
                        only.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, they become invalid, if not
                        renewed at the end of a year.</note> I do not lay stress on the law to show
                    that I should not pay what is due, if I actually became a surety, but I declare
                    that the law is a witness that I did not become one, and so is the fellow
                    himself; for otherwise he would have brought suit against me within the time
                    specified by the law.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>Let this, then, be another proof to you that Apaturius is lying. If I had become
                    surety to him for Parmeno, it is inconceivable that I should have made the
                    plaintiff my enemy for Parmeno's sake, taking every care that the latter should
                    not lose what he had lent the plaintiff through me, and yet have allowed myself
                    to be left in the lurch by him as his surety to the plaintiff. For what ground
                    had I to hope that leniency would be shown me by the man whom I had compelled to
                    do justice to Parmeno? And when I had made him my enemy by exacting from him
                    what was guaranteed to the bank, what treatment could I myself have expected to
                    receive at his hands? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>It is worth while also for you to bear this in mind, men of the jury, that, if I
                    had been surety, I should never have denied it. For my argument was much
                    stronger, if I admitted the guaranty and appealed to the agreement in accordance
                    with which the arbitration was to be held. That the matter was referred to three
                    arbitrators has been shown by testimony. When, then, there had been no decision
                    by the three, why in the world should I have denied the guaranty? For, if
                    judgement had not been given in accordance with the agreement, neither should I
                    have been open to action for my guaranty. Therefore, men of the jury, if I had
                    really become a surety, I should not have given up a defence which was at hand,
                    and have proceeded to deny the fact. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>Again, the following fact has been testified to you by witnesses, that, after the
                    articles of agreement had been made away with by these men, the plaintiff and
                    Parmeno sought to have new articles drawn up, thus admitting that their former
                    agreement was without force. Yet, when they sought to have other articles drawn
                    in regard to the judgement that was to be given, since the existing ones had
                    been lost, how was it possible that, if other articles were not drawn, there
                    could be either arbitration or guaranty? It was the fact that they disagreed
                    upon this very point that prevented their writing new articles, Apaturius
                    demanding that there should be one arbitrator, and Parmeno that there should be
                    three. But, since the original articles were made away with, in accordance with
                    which he alleges that I became a surety, and other articles were not written,
                    what right has he to bring suit against me, against whom he is able to produce
                    no agreement? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>Further, it has been testified to you by witnesses that Parmeno forbade
                    Aristocles to give judgement against him without the concurrence of his
                    co-arbitrators. When, therefore, it is shown that the same person has made away
                    with the document in accordance with the terms of which the arbitration was to
                    be made, and declares that he has made the decision without his co-arbitrators,
                    and in defiance of the notice forbidding him to do so, how can you with any
                    fairness credit the fellow and condemn me? Consider this, men of the jury: </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>suppose it was not against me, but against Parmeno, that this man Apaturius were
                    now taking action, seeking to recover the twenty minae in reliance upon the
                    judgement of Aristocles; and that Parmeno was present and making his defence,
                    calling witnesses to prove that he had turned the matter over to Aristocles, not
                    as a single arbitrator, but as one of three; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>that he had forbidden him to announce a decision against him without his
                    co-arbitrators; and that, after his wife and children had perished in the
                    earthquake, and he in the face of a disaster so appalling had sailed for home,
                    the man who had made away with the articles of agreement announced a judgement
                    against him by default in his absence, is there a single one of you who, when
                    Parmeno had brought out these facts in his defence, would have considered an
                    award so unjustly made to be valid? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>More than this; suppose that not every point was under dispute; that there were
                    in existence articles of agreement; that Aristocles was admittedly an arbitrator
                    having sole authority; that Parmeno had not forbidden him to make the award; but
                    that the calamity had befallen the man before the announcement of the award;
                    what adversary or what arbitrator would have been so cruel as not to postpone
                    the case until the man returned to the country? Then, if Parmeno, coming to
                    plead before you, should be judged in every point to speak with more justice
                    than the plaintiff, how can you justly give judgement against me, who have
                    absolutely no contract with this man? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>That I, on my part, have made my special plea with good right, and that Apaturius
                    has lodged against me a claim that is .baseless, and instituted a suit contrary
                    to law, has, I think, been shown to you, men of the jury, by many proofs. The
                    main point is this: Apaturius will not even attempt to say that he has any
                    articles showing an agreement between us. When he falsely states that my name
                    was written in as surety in the agreement made with Parmeno, demand of him the
                    articles. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>Meet him on this ground: that all men, when they make agreements with one
                    another, seal the articles and deposit them with persons whom they can trust,
                    for this very purpose, that, if a dispute arises between them, they may refer to
                    the document and so settle the point at issue. But when a man, after doing away
                    with the source of accurate knowledge, undertakes to deceive you with words, how
                    can you with justice put any confidence in him? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>But perhaps some witness (for this is the easiest course for those who have
                    chosen to do wrong and to bring baseless charges) will testify for him against
                    me. If then, I take action against the witness, how will he prove that his
                    testimony is true? By the articles of agreement? Well, then, let there be no
                    delay about this; let the one who has them bring forward the articles at once.
                    But if he says they have been lost, how, then, shall I find means of refuting
                    the false testimony brought against me? If the document had been deposited with
                    me, it would have been open to Apaturius to charge that I had made away with it
                    because of my guaranty; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>but, if it was deposited with Aristocles, why is it, if the agreement has been
                    lost without the plaintiff's knowledge, that instead of bringing suit against
                    the man who received the agreement but does not produce it, he makes charges
                    against me, bringing forward as a witness against me the man who made away with
                    the agreement, against whom he ought to feel resentment, if it were not that
                    they are leagued together in their evil scheming?I have made a just plea to the
                    best of my ability. Do you now give a just decision in accordance with the
                    laws.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
