<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Estate of Hagnias from Speeches (ENGLISH). Machine readable
					text</title>
				<author>Isaeus</author>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>


			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Isaeus</author>
						<title>Isaeus with an English translation by Edward Seymour Forster,
							M.A.</title>

						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
								Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1962</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="speech"/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English </language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek </language>
				<language ident="latin">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--
<change><date>March 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>September 1992</date><respStmt><name>D. Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed notes and regularized citations</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
			<change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>

			<div n="hypothesis" type="section">
				<p>A certain Hagnias had several cousins, namely, Theopompus, his brother
					Stratocles, Stratius, and Eubulides. When he was at the point of death he
					adopted a daughter, stipulating in his will that, if anything should happen to
					her, the estate should pass to Glaucon, who was his half-brother, his mother's
					son. After making these arrangements he died; and the daughter received the
					inheritance and then herself died. Eubulides having also died, his daughter
					brought an action against Glaucon and was awarded the estate. After this,
					Stratocles and Stratius having died, Theopompus, acting alone, brought a suit
					against her and was awarded the estate. It is against him that the son of his
					brother Stratocles brings an action through a guardian, alleged that the
					inheritance belongs in equal shares to Theopompus and to his brother's son. The
					discussion turns on a point of fact. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="1" type="section">
				<p><quote type="Laws"><title>Laws</title></quote><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I
					have read you the laws because my opponent bases on the first of them the claim
					of the child to half the estate—a claim which is false. Hagnias, it is true, was
					not our brother; but in the matter of a brother's property the law<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The text of the law is given in <bibl
							n="Dem. 43.51">Dem. 43.51</bibl> (<foreign xml:lang="greek">*pro\s
							*maka/ptaton</foreign>).</note> has given the right of inheritance first
					to brothers and nephews provided they are on the father's side; for they are
					related to the deceased in the nearest degree. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="2" type="section">
				<p>In default of these, the law next names sisters by the same father and their
					issue. If these fail, it gives the right of succession as next-of-kin to the
					third degree, namely, first cousins on the father's side including their
					children. If this degree is also lacking, the law goes back and gives the
					succession to the relatives of the deceased on his mother's side on the same
					principles as originally regulated the rights of inheritance by the relatives on
					the father's side. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="3" type="section">
				<p>These are the only rights of next-of-kin which the framer of the law recognizes;
					the wording which he employs is briefer than my paraphrase, but he shows his
					intention quite clearly in the text of the law. This child does not possess a
					single one of these titles as next-of-kin to Hagnias, but is outside all
					relationship. In order that you may know exactly upon what points you are going
					to give your verdict, I challenge my opponent to state, without superfluous
					words, in which of the above-mentioned degrees of relationship this child stands
					to the former tenant of the estate. If he can be shown to be in any way related,
					I willingly concede that half the estate is his. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="4" type="section">
				<p>If, on the other hand, he cannot prove the existence of any such relationship,
					surely he will be clearly convicted of bringing a vexatious suit against me and
					of trying to deceive you in contravention of the laws. I intend, therefore, to
					make him stand up before you and to interrogate him, reading out the text of the
					law. You will thus learn whether, or no, the child has any right to the fortune
					of Hagnias. (To the Clerk) Please take these laws; and (to his opponent) you,
					come up here, since you are so clever at misrepresentation and at distorting the
					laws. Read on.<quote type="Laws"><title>Laws</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="5" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Stop. I wish to question you. Is the child a
					brother of Hagnias, or a nephew, the son of a brother or sister, or a first
					cousin, or the child of a first cousin on his mother's or his father's side?
					Which of these titles, which are regarded by the law as constituting kinship,
					does he possess? And beware of saying that he is my nephew; for it is not a
					question now of my estate, for I am still alive. If I had died without issue and
					he were claiming my property, it would be quite fitting that he should give this
					reply to one who interrogated him. On the present occasion, however, it is the
					half of Hagnias's estate that you say belongs to the child; you must, therefore,
					define the degree of relationship which unites him to Hagnias. Tell these
					gentlemen, therefore, what it is. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="6" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You observe that he cannot define the
					relationship, but gives any sort of answer rather than the information which you
					require. Yet one who is acting in good faith ought not to be embarrassed, but
					ought to be able to answer immediately, and not only so but also swear an oath
					and produce witnesses about the degree of relationship, so that you might have
					attached greater credence to what he said. As it is, regarding matters about
					which he has given no answer, produced no witnesses, sworn no oath and quoted no
					law, he thinks that you, who have sworn to give your verdict according to the
					laws, ought to believe him and illegally condemn me in this criminal suit. This
					is the wicked and shameless sort of scoundrel that he is. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="7" type="section">
				<p>I have no intention of following his example; instead, I shall state my degree of
					relationship and the basis of my claim to the estate, and I shall prove, in such
					a manner as to win your assent, that the child and the former claimants against
					me for the estate are all outside the limits of kinship. I must state the facts
					from the beginning; for you will thus recognize my claim as next-of-kin and see
					that my opponent has no title to the succession. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="8" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Hagnias, Eubulides, Stratocles, Stratius, the
					brother of Hagnias's mother, and I, gentlemen, are all the children of cousins,
					our fathers having been cousins, the children of brothers by the same father.
					When Hagnias was preparing to set out as ambassador on that mission<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See Introduction.</note> which had such
					favorable results for the city, he did not leave his possessions, in case
					anything happened to him, to us, his nearest relatives, but adopted a niece; and
					if anything happened to her, he devised his property to Glaucon, his half-
					brother on his mother's side. These dispositions he embodied in a will. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="9" type="section">
				<p>After some interval of time Eubulides died. The daughter whom Hagnias had adopted
					also died, and Glaucon received the estate in accordance with the will. We never
					for a moment thought of contesting Hagnias's will, but considered that his
					intentions regarding his own property ought to be carried into effect, and by
					these we abode. But the daughter of Eubulides, with the assistance of her
					confederates, laid claim to the estate and obtained it, having gained an action
					against those who based their rights on the will. She was outside the prescribed
					degree of kinship, but hoped, it seems, that we should not bring an action
					against her, because we had not contested the will either. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="10" type="section">
				<p>But we—that is to say, Stratius, Stratocles, and myself—since the estate had now
					become adjudicable to the next-of-kin,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The will
						having been set aside, the next-of-kin would have to prove his title to the
						intestate estate.</note> all prepared to bring a suit. However, before the
					hearing of the case, Stratius and Stratocles both died; and thus I am the only
					surviving relative on the father's side, being the son of a cousin and the only
					person to whom, according to the law, the estate could pass, all the other
					relatives having died who possessed the same degree of kinship as myself.</p>
			</div>
			<div n="11" type="section">
				<p>But, it may be asked, how are you to know that I possess the rights of a
					next-of-kin, while the children of the other cousins, including this child, did
					not possess them? The law itself will make this clear. It is universally
					admitted that the rights as next-of-kin belong to cousins on the father's side,
					including their children, but the point which we have now to examine whether the
					law grants these rights to our children also. Take, therefore, the law and read
					it to the court.<quote type="Law"><title>Law</title>[;If there is no relative on
						the father's side as far as the degree of the children of cousins, then the
						right of inheritance passes to the mother's side in the same order of
						succession.];</quote><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This is the only law
						which is quoted in the manuscripts of Isaeus; it has probably been invented
						on the basis of the following section.</note>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="12" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Mark you, gentlemen, the legislator did not say
					that, in default of heirs on the father's side up to the degree of cousin's
					children, the rights descend to the latter's children; no, in default of us<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., on the failure of the children of cousins
						on the male side.</note>, he gives the inheritance to the relatives of the
					deceased on his mother's side, namely, to brothers and sisters and their
					children, and so on, in the same order as was laid down before. But he has
					placed our children outside the right of succession. How, then, can those to
					whom, even if I were dead, the law does not award Hagnias's estate, imagine
					that, while I am alive and have a legal right to the property, they themselves
					can have any title as next-of-kin? Their claim is quite preposterous. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="13" type="section">
				<p>Indeed, if the right of succession is not possessed by those whose fathers stood
					in the same degree of relationship as myself, neither is it possessed by this
					child; for his father stood in the same degree as they. Is it not, therefore,
					outrageous, that, whereas the laws have thus explicitly given me the right of
					inheritance and have placed my opponents outside the requisite degree of
					kinship, this fellow should dare to play these pettifogging tricks and, at the
					moment when I was laying claim to the estate, should think fit, not to bring an
					action against me and pay the necessary deposit—this being the proper moment to
					have the question settled, if his claims were well-founded—but to annoy me in
					the name of this child and make me run the most serious risks? </p>
			</div>
			<div n="14" type="section">
				<p>His charge is not concerned<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Grammatically the
						whole of this sentence depends on <foreign xml:lang="greek">ou)/koun
							deino/n</foreign> (<bibl n="Isaeus 13.4">Isaeus 13.4</bibl>).</note>
					with money which admittedly belongs to the child, nor can he say that I have
					received any such money—if I had administered any property in the manner in
					which he has done, I should deserve to be prosecuted; no, in bringing this kind
					of suit he has designs upon property which you, after permitting anyone who
					wished to dispute my claim to it, assigned by your verdict to me. Such is the
					extent of his impudence. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="15" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>From what I have already said I think that you
					fully recognize that I am doing no wrong to the child and that I am not in the
					least degree guilty of these charges; but you will, I think, understand this
					still more exactly from the rest of my story, and, in particular, when you have
					heard how the adjudication to me of the inheritance took place. When I brought
					the action claiming the inheritance, neither did my opponent, who is now
					bringing an impeachment against me, think fit to make the necessary deposit on
					behalf of the child, nor did the sons of Stratius, who stand in the same
					relationship as the child, &lt;either for this&gt;<note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true">There is a lacuna in the text at this point.</note> or for
					any other reason think that they had any right to the money; </p>
			</div>
			<div n="16" type="section">
				<p>for my opponent would not be troubling me now, if I had allowed him to dissipate
					the child's property and had not opposed him. These men, then, as I have said,
					knowing that they were outside the requisite degree of relationship, kept quiet;
					but those who were acting on behalf of the daughter of Eubulides, who stands in
					the same degree of relationship as the child and the sons of Stratius, and the
					legal representatives of Hagnias's mother, were disposed to contest my claim.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="17" type="section">
				<p>They found it so difficult to know what to say in their written counter-claim
					about the degree of relationship, that the woman who was in possession of the
					estate and those who were seeking to explain her kinship, when they lied, were
					easily convicted by me of daring to put in writing what was not true; and those
					who were supporting Hagnias's mother, who stands in the same degree of
					relationship as I do (being sister of Stratius) but who is excluded by the law
					which ordains that the males shall have the preference, omitted all reference to
					this point, and, thinking to gain an advantage over me, described her as the
					mother of the deceased—the nearest possible relationship by blood, but
					admittedly conferring no rights as next-of-kin. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="18" type="section">
				<p>Having thus described myself as the son of a cousin and having proved that these
					women were not within the requisite degree of kinship, I thus had the estate
					adjudicated to me by you; and her former success against those who claimed on
					the basis of the will was of no avail to the woman who was in possession of the
					inheritance, nor did it avail the other woman that she was mother of the
					deceased who left the estate, but those who were trying the case attached so
					much importance to justice and their oaths that they gave their verdict in favor
					of me, whose claim was in conformity with the law. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="19" type="section">
				<p>Yet since I thus triumphed over these women by proving that they were not within
					the requisite degree of kinship to Hagnias; and since my present opponent did
					not venture to go to law with me, claiming half the estate for the child; and
					since the sons of Stratius, who stand in the same degree of kinship as this
					child, do not even now think of bringing a suit against me for the estate; and
					since I am in possession of the estate by your adjudication; and since I can
					prove that my opponent even at the present time cannot state what relationship
					the child possesses which confers rights as next-of-kin to Hagnias—what further
					information do you require, and what more do you wish to hear on the subject?
					Since I regard you as men of good sense, I think that what I have said is
					sufficient. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="20" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>My opponent, thinking nothing of telling any lie
					whatever and considering that his own rascality does him no harm, dares to utter
					many calumnies against me, with which I will deal presently. In particular, he
					now alleges that Stratocles and I made a compact, when we were about to engage
					in the suit about the inheritance, though of those who had prepared to put in a
					claim we were the only persons for whom such a mutual agreement was impossible.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="21" type="section">
				<p>The daughter of Eubulides and the mother of Hagnias, in an action against me,
					since they were not claiming on the same grounds, might have made an agreement,
					that if one of them were successful, she should give a share to the defeated
					claimant; for the votes accorded to each of them would be placed in different
					urns. But with us it was quite otherwise; we stood in the same relationship and
					were making two separate claims, each to have half the estate; and when two
					claimants found their claims on the same grounds, only one voting urn is
					employed, so that it would be impossible for one to be unsuccessful and the
					other successful, but we both ran the same risk, so we could not possibly have
					made any compact or agreement about the inheritance. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="22" type="section">
				<p>But when Stratocles died before the actions claiming half the estate, which we
					were each bringing, could come on, and so there was no further question of his
					participating in the estate, nor had this child of his any title owing to the
					law, but the whole inheritance devolved upon me as next-of-kin, if I could
					defeat those who are now in possession, then and not till then does my opponent
					devise and invent these fictions, expecting easily to mislead you by these
					stories. That no such compact was possible but that all the details of procedure
					are already provided for, can easily be seen from the law. Please take and read
					it to the court.<quote type="Law"><title>Law</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="23" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Does it appear to you that the law gives any
					liberty for a concerted arrangement? Or are not its provisions in an exactly
					contrary sense, since, even if a previous arrangement existed, it expressly
					ordains that each party shall bring an action for his own share, and prescribes
					a single voting-urn, when the two parties base their claims on the same ground,
					and makes this the system of adjudication? But my opponent, in spite of these
					legal provisions and the impossibility of a preconcerted arrangement, has had
					the impudence to invent this lie against all common sense. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="24" type="section">
				<p>But he has not stopped there; he has also invented the most inconsistent story
					possible, to which, gentlemen, please give your close attention. He declares
					that I agreed, if I won my case against the present possessors of the estate, to
					give the child a half-share of the inheritance. Yet if the child had any right
					to a share in virtue of his relationship, as my opponent declares, what need was
					there for this agreement between me and them? For the half of the estate was
					adjudicable to them just as much as to me, if what they say is true. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="25" type="section">
				<p>If, on the other hand, they had no claim by right of kinship, why should I have
					agreed to give them a share, when the laws have given me the right of succession
					to the whole estate? Was it then impossible for me to make my claim without
					their consent? But the law gives full liberty to anyone who likes to make a
					claim, so that they could not possibly make this allegation. Did I then require
					some evidence from them material to my case, in default of which I was unlikely
					to secure the adjudication of the estate? No, I was claiming by right of
					kinship, not of testamentary disposition, so that I had no need of witnesses.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="26" type="section">
				<p>And indeed, if it was impossible for me to have made an arrangement with
					Stratocles in his lifetime; if his father did not bequeath the estate to him,
					since he never had any of it adjudicated to him; if it was unlikely that I
					should have agreed to give the child half the inheritance; and since you awarded
					me the estate by your adjudication and my opponents brought no action at the
					time and have never yet thought of disputing the estate—how can you believe
					their allegations to be true? In my opinion you cannot possibly do so. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="27" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Seeing that you might reasonably be astonished
					that they did not at the time bring a suit claiming half the estate, my opponent
					pretends that I was the cause of their not bringing a suit against the other
					parties, because I had agreed to give them a share and so they did not make the
					necessary deposit, while they allege that the laws forbade them to bring a suit
					against me on the ground that orphans may not bring actions against their
					guardians. Both these statements are untrue. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="28" type="section">
				<p>For my opponent could not point to any law which forbids him to bring a private
					action against me on behalf of the child; for no law exists which is opposed to
					such a proceeding, but, just as the law has granted the right to bring a public
					indictment against me, so it has created the opportunity either for me or the
					child to bring a private suit. Again, it was not because I agreed to give them a
					share that they failed to bring an action against the other parties who were in
					possession of the estate, but because they had absolutely no right to this
					money. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="29" type="section">
				<p>I am convinced that even had I agreed to let the child receive from me by the
					adjudication of the court a half of the inheritance, they would never have
					carried out this bargain or attempted to do so; they know perfectly well, that
					if, being outside the requisite degree of kinship, they had been in possession
					of anything which did not belong to them, they would have been easily deprived
					of it by the next-of-kin. For, as I said before, the law does not give any
					rights at all as next-of-kin to our children after us, but transfers them to the
					relatives of the deceased on his mother's side. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="30" type="section">
				<p>In the first place, then, Glaucon, the brother of Hagnias, would have come
					forward, against whom they could not urge a claim of closer relationship; on the
					contrary, they would have been clearly shown to be outside the requisite degree
					of kinship. Next, if Glaucon had been unwilling to come forward, the mother of
					Hagnias and Glaucon would have done so, since she possessed a claim of kinship
					to her son,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Not as his mother but as her son's
						cousin.</note> and so, if she had engaged in a suit against those who
					possessed no title as next-of-kin, she would clearly have been awarded half the
					estate by you, since justice and the laws have given her a right to it. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="31" type="section">
				<p>These, then, are the reasons why he did not bring an action, and it was not
					because he was prevented from doing so by me or by the laws; and these are the
					pretexts which he has invented for resorting to these vexatious proceedings
					against me, and it is upon the basis of them, that having brought a public
					indictment against me and slandering me, he hopes to obtain money and to deprive
					me of my guardianship. He thinks that he is managing very cleverly in employing
					these devices, because, if he is unsuccessful, he will lose nothing of his own,
					whereas, if he can carry out his wishes, he will henceforward be able to
					squander the child's property as well with impunity. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="32" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You must, therefore, not listen to his arguments
					nor tolerate his utterance of them, nor allow the custom to grow up of bringing
					public actions about matters for which the laws have prescribed private suits.
					For the rights of the case are perfectly simple and easy to understand. After
					dealing briefly with them and leaving them stored in your memory, I will then
					turn to the rest of my defence against the charges brought against me. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="33" type="section">
				<p>What then are the rights of the case and how do I define them? If my opponent
					declares that part of Hagnias's estate belongs to the child by right of kinship,
					let him bring an action before the archon claiming the half, and, if you decide
					in his favor, let him take it; for thus the laws ordain. But if he does not
					claim on these grounds but alleges that I agreed to give the child a
					share—though I declare that there is not a word of truth in his allegation—let
					him bring an action, and, if he can prove that I made such an agreement, let him
					secure the execution of it; for that is only right. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="34" type="section">
				<p>But if he declares that the child cannot either claim a share from me at law or
					sue me for breach of contract,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">An action
						claiming property was described as <foreign xml:lang="greek">pro/s
							tina</foreign>, an action for breach of contract as <foreign
							xml:lang="greek">kata/ tinos</foreign>.</note> let him name the law
					which prohibits this, and, if he can indicate it, let the child in these
					circumstances, too, receive the share of the estate. If, again, he contends that
					there is no need to have the half-share adjudicated or to go to law with me at
					all, but that this share already belongs to the child, let him make an
					application to the archon for its inclusion in the lease of the orphan's estate
					and let the lessee exact from me this portion as belonging to the child. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="35" type="section">
				<p>Such are the essential rights of the case, and such the provisions of the laws,
					which do not, thank heaven, oblige me to submit to criminal trials in matters
					about which they have instituted private suits nor to run any personal risk
					because I refuse to share with the child this estate, which I received by your
					verdict when I won my case against those who were in possession. If I were
					holding any property which admittedly belonged to the child and had
					maladministered it to his detriment, then he would be justified in bringing this
					criminal charge against me, but not, by heaven, when it is a question of my own
					property. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="36" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>That my adversary has in this matter acted
					entirely unjustly, and that otherwise he has never spoken a word of truth, but
					has cleverly devised the whole plot from motives of self-interest, uttering
					calumnies, misinterpreting the laws and seeking to get the better both of you
					and of me contrary to justice—of all this, by heaven, you are, I think, well
					aware and all alike understand; and so I do not know what more I need say. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="37" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I notice, gentlemen, that most of his speech is
					taken up with a discussion of my fortune and of that of the child; he represents
					the circumstances of the child as embarrassed, while he attributes to me a
					position of wealth and accuses me of baseness on the ground that I cannot bring
					myself to provide any of the four daughters of Stratocles with a dowry,
					although, according to his account, I am in possession of the child's property.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="38" type="section">
				<p>I should like to deal with this point; for he hopes by his arguments to arouse in
					your minds a prejudice against me regarding the fortune which has accrued to me,
					and a feeling of pity in favor of the children, if they can be represented to
					you as reduced to poverty. You must not, therefore, be left in any ignorance on
					these points but must have an exact idea of them, so that you may understand
					that here, too, my opponent is lying, as he has lied about everything else. For,
					gentlemen, I would admit myself to be the basest of all men, if it could be
					shown that the affairs of Stratocles were left in a state of embarrassment at
					his death and that I, being myself in easy circumstances, gave not a thought to
					his children. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="39" type="section">
				<p>But if he left them a fortune more considerable and better secured than my own
					and sufficient to endow his daughters fittingly without sensibly diminishing his
					son's wealth, and if I am so managing the property as greatly to increase it,
					surely I cannot reasonably be blamed for not giving them my own money as well; I
					rather deserve to be praised for preserving and increasing their fortune. That
					these statements are true, I shall easily prove to you. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="40" type="section">
				<p>First, therefore, I will give you details about the property, and after that
					state the principles on which I think fit to administer the children's
						affairs.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This part of the speech is
						lost.</note><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Stratocles and I had a patrimony
					sufficient to supply our needs but not large enough to defray the cost of public
					services. An indication of this is that each of us received a dowry of only 20
					minae with his wife, and so small a dowry would not be given to a husband with a
					large fortune. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="41" type="section">
				<p>Stratocles, however, happened to receive an addition of more than two and a half
					talents to his fortune; for Theophon, his wife's brother, at his death adopted
					one of his daughters and left her his property, consisting of land at <placeName
						key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName> worth two talents, 60 sheep, 100
					goats, furniture, a fine horse which he rode when he was a cavalry commander,
					and all the rest of his goods and chattels. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="42" type="section">
				<p>Having had complete control of this property for nine whole years, he left a
					fortune of 5 talents 3000 drachmae, including his patrimony but excluding the
					fortune left to his daughter by Theophon. His property comprised land at
						<placeName key="perseus,Thria">Thria</placeName><note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true"><placeName key="tgn,1001774">North-west</placeName> of
							<placeName key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>.</note> worth two
					and a half talents, a house at Melite<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A quarter
						of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> west of the
						Areopagus.</note> which cost 3000 drachmae, and another at <placeName
						key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName> which cost 500 drachmae. These
					made up his real property, the land being let at 12 minae and the houses at 3, a
					total of 15 minae; but he had also about 4000 drachmae lent out at interest, the
					yearly income of which, at a monthly rate of 9 obols, amounts to 720 drachmae.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="43" type="section">
				<p>He thus had a total income of rather more than 20 minae. Besides this he left
					furniture, sheep, barley, wine, and fruits, the sale of which brought in 4900
					drachmae; also 900 drachmae were found in the house. In addition his—that is the
					child's—mother included in the inventory made in the presence of witnesses sums
					lent without interest, which were recovered, amounting to nearly 1000 drachmae.
					I make no mention now of the other property which was left, but which my
					opponents refuse to disclose; I only include what was declared and admitted by
					them. Please call the witnesses in support of the above statements.<quote
						type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="44" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Stratocles' fortune amounts to even more than
					this; but I will deal later with my opponents embezzlements. Now to what does my
					fortune amount? I have a property at Oenoe worth 5000 drachmae and another at
					Prospalta worth 3000 drachmae and a house in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
						>Athens</placeName> worth 2000 drachmae; to this must be added the estate
					left by Hagnias, worth about two talents; for I am sure that it would not fetch
					more than this. This gives a total of only three talents 4000 drachmae—110 minae
					less than the fortune of the child. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="45" type="section">
				<p>I include in the reckoning the fortune of my son, who was adopted into another
					family, while I excluded from the child's fortune the property of Theophon, two
					and a half talents, which he left to his sister when he adopted her; for their
					family property could be easily reckoned at eight talents, but the money which
					came from Theophon has been reckoned separately. On my side, the estate left by
					Hagnias is not yet secured to me; for trials for perjury are still pending, </p>
			</div>
			<div n="46" type="section">
				<p>and the law ordains that, if there is any conviction for perjury, the action
					claiming an estate must be heard over again. On the other hand, the child's
					fortune bequeathed to him by Stratocles is admitted and not contested. To prove
					that this is the amount of my property, including that of my son who has been
					adopted into another family, and that suits for perjury in connection with
					Hagnias's estate are still pending, take and read the depositions.<quote
						type="Depositions"><title>Depositions</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="47" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Is the difference, then, trifling between our
					respective fortunes? Or rather, is it not so great that mine is nothing in
					comparison with that of the children of Stratocles? No credence must therefore
					be attached to the statements of my opponent, who, though so large a fortune has
					been left to the children, has dared to utter such lies with the object of
					discrediting me. According to his reckoning I have received three inheritances
					and am in enjoyment of a large fortune, but I hide my wealth in order that you
					may derive as little advantage from it as possible.<note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true">i.e. in order to avoid the performance of public
						services.</note> Those who have no just claims to urge on the facts are
					obliged to bring forward such arguments as will give them an advantage over
					their adversaries by calumniating them. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="48" type="section">
				<p>But you all are my witnesses that my wife's brothers, Chaereleos and Macartatus,
					were not among those who supported public burdens but among those who possessed
					only slender fortunes. You know that Macartatus sold his land and bought a
					trireme which he manned and sailed away in it to <placeName key="tgn,7012056"
						>Crete</placeName>. The affair was no secret but even gave rise to a
					discussion in the Assembly,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See
						Introduction.</note> since it was feared that he might bring about a state
					of war instead of peace between us and the Lacedaemonians. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="49" type="section">
				<p>Chaereleos left the estate at Prospalta, which would not fetch more than 30
					minae. The brother who left this estate happened to die before Macartatus, who
					in his turn perished with all the property which he took with him when he sailed
					away; for he lost the trireme and everything else in the war as well as his own
					life. The estate at Prospalta was left and passed to their sister, who is my
					wife, and I was persuaded by her to allow one of our two sons to be adopted into
					the family of Macartatus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This child is the
						Macartatus attacked in the pseudo-Demosthenic speech, <bibl n="Dem. 43">Dem.
							43</bibl>.</note> My object was not to avoid the performance of public
					services which the addition of this estate would involve; </p>
			</div>
			<div n="50" type="section">
				<p>for my having allowed my son to be adopted made no difference, for indeed I
					performed public services<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Theopompus has
						already stated that his fortune did not render him liable to perform any
							<foreign xml:lang="greek">leitourgi/a</foreign> (e.g., the <foreign
							xml:lang="greek">trihraxi/a</foreign> or <foreign xml:lang="greek"
							>xwrhgi/a</foreign>): he is, therefore, here using the term in the wider
						sense of the duties of a citizen (e.g., the payment of the war-tax and
						service in the army).</note> no less than before, but was among those who
					paid war contributions and carried out all the duties imposed by the state. My
					opponent, however, in representing me as a wealthy but unprofitable citizen is
					using these terms to calumniate me.<milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>As the
					strongest argument of all, I will sum the matter up in a single proposal, which,
					I am sure, will appear to you to be just. I am willing to bring my whole estate
					into hotchpotch with that of the child, and let us each take half of the
					aggregate amount, whether it be large or small, so that neither party may have
					more than is fitting; but my opponent will never consent to this.<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The rest of the speech is lacking.</note></p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
