<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Dionysodorus </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by Norman W. DeWitt, Ph.D.,
                            and Norman J. DeWitt, Ph.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1949</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>I am a sharer in this loan, men of the jury. We, who have engaged in the business
                    of overseas trade and put our money in the hands of others, have come to know
                    one thing very clearly: that in all respects the borrower has the best of us. He
                    received the money in cash which was duly acknowledged, and has left us on a
                    scrap of paper<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, of course,
                        papyrus.</note> which he bought for a couple of coppers, his agreement to do
                    the right thing. We on our part do not promise to give the money, we give it
                    outright to the borrower. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>What, then, do we rely upon, and what security do we get when we risk our money?
                    We rely upon you, men of the jury, and upon your laws, which ordain that all
                    agreements into which a man voluntarily enters with another shall be valid. But
                    in my opinion there is no use in your laws or in any contract, if the one who
                    receives the money is not thoroughly upright in character, and does not either
                    fear you<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, the jury in the
                        law-courts.</note> or regard the rights of the one making the loan.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>Now Dionysodorus here does neither the one nor the other, but has come to such a
                    pitch of audacity, that although he borrowed from us three thousand drachmae
                    upon his ship on the condition that it should sail back to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and although we ought to have got
                    back our money in the harvest-season of last year, he took his ship to
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> and there unladed his cargo
                    and sold it in defiance of the contract and of your laws<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Athenian dealers were allowed to ship grain only to
                            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, not to foreign
                        ports; cf. <bibl n="Dem. 56.10">Dem. 56.10 infra</bibl>.</note>; and from
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> again he despatched his ship
                    to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and from thence back to
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, and to us who lent our
                    money at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> he has up to this
                    day neither paid back our money nor produced to us our security. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>Nay, for two years now he has been using our money for his profit, keeping the
                    loan and the trade and the ship that was mortgaged to us, and notwithstanding
                    this he has come into your court, intending plainly to get us fined with the
                    sixth part of the damages,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">For this fine, the
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)pwbeli/a</foreign>, imposed upon the
                        plaintiff, he failed to obtain a fifth of the votes, see note on p. 50 of
                        vol. 1.</note> and to put us in prison,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >Properly the “lodging.” The same euphemism occurs in <bibl n="Dem. 32.29"
                            >Dem. 32.29</bibl>.</note> besides robbing us of our money. We
                    therefore, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, beg and
                    implore you one and all to come to our aid, if you find that we are being
                    wronged. But first I want to explain to you how the loan was contracted; for
                    thus it will be easiest for you also to follow the case. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>This Dionysodorus, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and
                    his partner Parmeniscus came to us last year in the month Metageitnion,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The month Metageitnion corresponds to the latter
                        half of August and the prior half of September.</note> and said that they
                    desired to borrow money on their ship on the terms that she should sail to
                        <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and from <placeName
                        key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName> or <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    and they agreed to pay the interest for the voyage to either one of these ports.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>We answered, men of the jury, that we would not lend money for a voyage to any
                    other port than <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and so they
                    agreed to return here, and with this understanding they borrowed from us three
                    thousand drachmae on the security of their ship for the voyage out and home; and
                    they entered into a written agreement to these terms. In the contract Pamphilus
                    here was named the lender; but I, although not mentioned, was a sharer in the
                    loan.</p>
                <p>And first the clerk shall read to you the agreement.<quote type="Agreement">
                        <title>Agreement</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>In accordance with this agreement, men of the jury, Dionysodorus here and his
                    partner Parmeniscus, when they had got the money from us, despatched their ship
                    from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>. Parmeniscus sailed in charge of the
                    ship; Dionysodorus remained at <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>. All these men, I would have you know, men of the jury,
                    were underlings and confederates of Cleomenes, the former ruler of <placeName
                        key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">After
                        his conquest of <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> in <date
                            when="-0331">331</date> B.C. Alexander had made Cleomenes collector of
                        revenues for that province.</note> who from the time he received the
                    government did no small harm to your state, or rather to the rest of the Greeks
                    as well, by buying up grain for resale and fixing its price, and in this he had
                    these men as his confederates. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>Some of them would despatch the stuff from <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                        >Egypt</placeName>, others would sail in charge of the shipments, while
                    still others would remain here in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> and dispose of the consignments. Then those who remained
                    here would send letters to those abroad advising them of the prevailing prices,
                    so that if grain were dear in your market, they might bring it here, and if the
                    price should fall, they might put in to some other port. This was the chief
                    reason, men of the jury, why the price of grain advanced; it was due to such
                    letters and conspiracies. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>Well then, when these men despatched their ship from <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, they left the price of grain here
                    pretty high, and for this reason they submitted to have the clause written in
                    the agreement binding them to sail to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName> and to no other port. Afterwards, however, men of the
                    jury, when the ships from <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> had
                    arrived, and the prices of grain here were falling, and their ship had reached
                        <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, the defendant straightway
                    sent a man to <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> to inform his
                    partner Parmeniscus of the state of things here, well knowing that his ship
                    would be forced to touch at <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>The outcome was that Parmeniscus, the defendant's partner, when he had received
                    the letter sent by him and had learned the price of grain prevailing here,
                    discharged his cargo of grain at <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>
                    and sold it there in defiance of the agreement, men of the jury, and of the
                    penalties to which they had of their own will bound themselves, in case they
                    should commit any breach of the agreement, and in contempt also of your laws
                    which ordain that shipowners and supercargoes shall sail to the port to which
                    they have agreed to sail or else be liable to the severest penalties. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>We on our part, as soon as we learned what had taken place, were greatly dismayed
                    at his action, and went to this man, who was the prime mover in the whole plot,
                    complaining angrily, as was natural, that although we had expressedly stipulated
                    in the agreement that the ship should sail to no other port than to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, and had lent our money on this
                    condition, he had left us open to suspicion with people who might wish to accuse
                    and say that we also had been partners to the conveyance of the grain to
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>; and complaining also that
                    he and his partner, despite their agreement to do so, had not brought the ship
                    back to your port. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>When, however, we made no headway in talking about the agreement and our rights,
                    we demanded that he at any rate pay us back the amount loaned with the interest
                    as originally agreed upon. But the fellow treated us with such insolence as to
                    declare that he would not pay the interest stipulated in the agreement. “If,
                    however,” he said, “you are willing to accept the interest calculated in
                    proportion to the voyage completed, I will give you,” said he, “the interest as
                    far as <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>; but more I will not
                    give.” Thus he made a law for himself and refused to comply with the just terms
                    of the agreement. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When we said that we could not acquiesce in
                    anything like this, considering that, were we to do so, it would be an admission
                    that we too had been engaged in conveying grain to <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName>, he became even more insistent, and came up to us,
                    bringing a host of witnesses, asserting that he was ready to pay us the
                    principal with interest as far as <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName>; not that he had any more intention to pay, men of the
                    jury, but suspecting that we should be unwilling to accept the money on account
                    of the charges to which our action might give rise. The result made this clear.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>For when some of your citizens, men of Athens, who chanced to be present advised
                    to accept what was offered and to sue for the amount under dispute, but not to
                    admit the reckoning of the interest to <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName> until the case should be settled we agreed to this. We
                    were not unaware, men of the jury, of our rights under the agreement, but we
                    thought it better to suffer some loss and to make a concession, so as not to
                    appear litigious. But when the fellow saw that we were on the point of accepting
                    his offer, he said, “Well, then, cancel the agreement.” “We cancel the
                    agreement? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>Indeed we will not. However, as far as concerns any money you may pay we will in
                    the presence of the banker agree to annul the agreement; but cancel it in its
                    entirety we will not, until we get a verdict on the matters under dispute. For
                    what just plea shall we have, or on what can we rely when we come to a contest
                    at law, whether we have to appear before an arbitrator or before a court, if we
                    have cancelled the agreement on which we rely for the recovery of our rights?”
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>Such was our answer to him, men of the jury, and we demanded of this fellow
                    Dionysodorus that he should not disturb or annul the agreement which these men
                    themselves admitted to be binding, but that in regard to the amount he should
                    pay us what he himself acknowledged to be due and to leave the settlement of the
                    sum under dispute (with the understanding that the money was available) to the
                    decision of one or more arbitrators, as he might prefer, to be chosen from among
                    the merchants of this port. Dionysodorus, however, would not listen to anything
                    of this sort, but because we refused to accept what he agreed to pay and cancel
                    the agreement altogether, he has for two years kept and made use of our capital;
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>and what is the most outrageous thing of all, men of the jury, the fellow himself
                    gets maritime interest<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Maritime loans appear to
                        have commanded a higher rate of interest than those secured by real property
                        because of the greater risk involved. In <bibl n="Dem. 50.17">Dem.
                            50.17</bibl> we are told of a maritime loan contracted at 12 1/2%, but
                        the rate of interest varied.</note> from other people from our money,
                    lending it, not at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> or for a
                    voyage to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, but for voyages to
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> and <placeName
                        key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, while to us who lent him money for a
                    voyage to your port he thinks he need do nothing that justice demands</p>
                <p>To prove that I am speaking the truth, the clerk shall read you the challenge
                    which I gave Dionysodorus concerning these matters.<quote type="Challenge">
                        <title>Challenge</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>This challenge, then, we tendered to this Dionysodorus again and again, and we
                    exposed the challenge to public view over a period of many days. He, however,
                    declared that we must be absolute simpletons, if we supposed him to be senseless
                    enough to go before an arbitrator—who would most certainly condemn him to pay
                    the debt—when he might come into court bringing the money with him, and then, if
                    he could hoodwink you he would go back keeping possession of what was another's,
                    and if he could not, he would then pay the money. Thus he showed that he had no
                    confidence in the justice of his case, but that he wished to make trial of you.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>You have heard, then, men of the jury, what Dionysodorus has done; and as you
                    have heard I fancy you have long been amazed at his audacity, and have wondered
                    upon what in the world he relies in coming into court. For is it not the height
                    of audacity, when a man who has borrowed money from the port of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>and has expressly agreed in writing that his ship shall return to your port, or
                    that, if she does not, he shall pay double the amount, has not brought the ship
                    to the Peiraeus and does not pay his debt to the lenders; and as for the grain,
                    has unladed that and sold it at <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>,
                    and then despite all this dares to look into your faces? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>But hear what he says in reply to this. He alleges that the ship was disabled on
                    the voyage from <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and that for
                    this reason he was obliged to touch at <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName> and unlade the grain there. And as a proof of this he
                    states that he chartered ships from <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName> and shipped some of his goods to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. This is one part of his defence,
                    and here is another. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>He claims that some other creditors of his have agreed to accept from him
                    interest as far as <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, and that it
                    would be hard indeed if we should not make the same concession that they have
                    made. And thirdly, besides all this, he declares that the agreement requires him
                    to pay the money if the ship arrives safely, but that the ship has not arrived
                    safely in the Peiraeus. To each of these arguments, men of the jury, hear the
                    just answer that we make. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>In the first place, when he says that the ship was disabled, I think it is plain
                    to you all that he is lying. For if his ship had met with this mishap, she would
                    neither have got safely to <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> nor
                    have been fit for sailing afterwards. But in fact it is plain that she did get
                    safe to <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> and was sent back from
                    thence to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>, and that at the
                    present time she is still sailing everywhere except to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. And yet is it not outrageous that,
                    when he has to bring his ship back to the port of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, he says she was disabled, but when
                    he wants to unlade his grain at <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>,
                    then that same ship is seen to be seaworthy? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>Why, then, he says, did I charter other ships and tranship my cargo and despatch
                    it here to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>? Because, men of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, neither the defendant
                    nor his partner was owner of the entire cargo, but, I fancy, the supercargoes
                    who were on board despatched their own goods hither, in other bottoms
                    necessarily, seeing that these men had cut short the voyage before the ship
                    reached her destination. As for the goods, however, which were their own, they
                    did not ship these in their entirety to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, but sought out what ones had advanced in price. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>For why, pray, was it that, when you had hired other bottoms, as you say, you did
                    not tranship the entire cargo of your vessel, but left the grain there in
                        <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>? Because, men of the jury,
                    it was to their interest to sell the grain in <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName>; for they heard that the price had fallen here in
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, but they shipped to you
                    the other goods, from which they hoped to make a profit. When, then,
                    Dionysodorus, you talk about the chartering of the vessels, you give proof, not
                    that your ship was disabled, but that it was to your advantage to do so. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>Concerning these matters, then, what I have said is sufficient, but in regard to
                    the creditors, who, they say, consented to accept from them the interest as far
                    as <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, this has nothing to do with
                    us. If any man has remitted to you any part of what was due him, no wrong is
                    suffered by either party to the arrangement. But we have not remitted anything
                    to you, nor have we consented to your voyage to <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName>, nor in our judgement is anything more binding than the
                    agreement. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>Now what does the agreement say, and to what port does it require you to sail?
                    From Athens to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and from
                        <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; and in default of your so doing, it
                    requires you to pay double the amount. If you have done this, you have committed
                    no wrong; but if you have not done it, and have not brought your ship back to
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, it is proper that you
                    should suffer the penalty provided by the agreement; for this requirement was
                    imposed upon you, not by some other person, but by yourself. Show, then, to the
                    jury one or the other of two things—that our agreement is not valid, or that you
                    are not required to do everything in accordance with it. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>If certain people have remitted anything in your favor, and have been induced on
                    one ground or another to accept interest only as far as <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, does it follow that you are doing no
                    wrong to us, your agreement with whom you have broken in having your ship put
                    into <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>? I do not think so. For
                    this jury is not now deciding upon concessions made to you by others, but upon
                    an agreement entered into by you yourself with us. For that the remission of the
                    interest, supposing that it actually took place, as these men allege, was to the
                    advantage of the creditors, is plain to every one of you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>For those who lent their money to these men for the outward voyage from
                        <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, when they reached <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> and this man put into that port,
                    suffered no loss, I take it, by remitting the interest and receiving the amount
                    of their loan at <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, and then
                    putting the money to work again for a voyage to <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                        >Egypt</placeName>. No; this was more to their advantage than to continue
                    the voyage to this port. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>For voyaging from <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> is uninterrupted, and they could put the
                    same money to work two or three times, whereas here they would have had to pass
                    the winter and to await the season for sailing. These creditors therefore have
                    reaped an additional profit, and have not remitted anything to these men. With
                    us, however, it is not a question of the interest merely, but we are unable to
                    recover even our principal. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>Do not, then, listen to him, when he seeks to hoodwink you, and brings before you
                    his transactions with other creditors, but refer him to the agreement and to the
                    rights growing out of it. It remains for me to interpret this matter for you,
                    and the defendant insists upon this very thing, stating that the agreement
                    requires him to repay the loan only if the ship arrives safe. We also maintain
                    that this should be so. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>But I should be glad to ask you yourself, Dionysodorus, whether you are speaking
                    of the ship as having been lost, or as having arrived safe. For if the ship has
                    been wrecked and is lost, why do you keep on disputing about the interest and
                    demanding that we accept interest as far as <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
                        >Rhodes</placeName>? For in that case we have not the right to recover
                    either interest or principal. But if the ship is safe and has not been wrecked,
                    why do you not pay us the money which you agreed to pay? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>In what way, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, can you
                    be most convincingly assured that the ship has reached port safe? In the first
                    instance by the mere fact that she is now at sea, and less clearly by the
                    statements made by these men themselves. For they ask us to accept payment of
                    the principal and a certain portion of the interest, thus implying that the ship
                    has reached port safe, but has not completed her entire voyage. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p>Now consider, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, whether
                    it is we who are abiding by the requirements of the contract, or whether it is
                    these men, who have sailed, not to the port agreed upon, but to <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                        >Egypt</placeName>, and who, when the ship has reached port safe and has not
                    been lost, claim to be entitled to an abatement of the interest, although they
                    have broken the agreement, and have themselves made a large profit by the
                    carrying of grain to <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, and by
                    keeping and making use of our money for two years. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>What they are doing is indeed an unheard-of thing. They offer to pay us the
                    principal of our loan, thus implying that the ship has reached port safe, but
                    they claim the right to rob us of our interest on the ground that she has been
                    wrecked. The agreement, however, does not say one thing about the interest and
                    another about the principal of the loan, but our rights are the same for both
                    and our means of recovery the same. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>Please read the agreement again.<quote type="Agreement"
                            ><title>Agreement</title><p>From <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                >Athens</placeName> to <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                                >Egypt</placeName> and from <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                                >Egypt</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                                >Athens</placeName>.</p></quote></p>
                <p>You hear, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. It says
                    “From Athens to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and from
                        <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.”</p>
                <p>Read the rest.<quote type="Agreement"><title>Agreement</title><p>And if the ship
                            arrives safe at Peiraeus . . .</p></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>Men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, it is a very simple
                    thing for you to reach a decision in this suit, and there is no need of many
                    words. That the ship has reached port safe, and is safe, is admitted by these
                    men themselves; for otherwise they would not be offering to pay the principal of
                    the loan and a portion of the interest. She has not, however, been brought back
                    to the Peiraeus. It is for this reason that we, the creditors, claim that we
                    have been wronged, and regarding this we are bringing suit, that, namely she did
                    not make the return voyage to the port agreed upon. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>Dionysodorus, however, claims that he is doing no wrong because of this very
                    fact, since he is not bound to pay the interest in its entirety inasmuch as the
                    ship did not complete her voyage to Peiraeus. But what does the agreement say?
                    By Zeus it is not at all what you say, Dionysodorus. No; it declares that if you
                    do not pay both the principal and interest, or if you fail to present the
                    security, plain to see and unimpaired, or if in any other respect you violate
                    the agreement, you are required to pay double the amount.</p>
                <p>Read, please, that clause of the agreement.<quote type="Statement"
                            ><title>Statement</title><p>And if they shall not produce the security,
                            plain to see and unimpaired, or if in any respect they shall violate the
                            agreement, they shall pay double the amount.</p></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>Have you, then, at any place whatever produced the ship plain to see since the
                    time you received the money from us? And yet you yourself admit that she is
                    safe. Or have you ever since that time brought her back to the port of
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, though the agreement
                    expressly stipulates that you shall bring your ship back to the Peiraeus, and
                    produce her plain to see before the lenders? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>This is an important point, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>. Just observe the extravagance of his statement. The
                    ship was disabled, so he says, and for this reason he brought her into the port
                    of <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>. Well, then, after that she
                    was repaired and became fit for sea. Why, then, my good fellow, did you send her
                    off to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and to other ports, but
                    have never up to this day sent her back to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, to us your creditors, to whom the agreement requires
                    you to produce the ship, plain to see and unimpaired, and that too although we
                    made demand upon you again and again and challenged you to do so? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>No; you are so bold or rather so impudent, that, while under the agreement you
                    owe us double the amount of our loan, you do not see fit to pay us even the
                    accrued interest, but bid us accept interest as far as <placeName
                        key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>, as if your command ought to prove of
                    more force than the agreement; and you have the insolence to declare that the
                    vessel did not arrive safe at the Peiraeus; for which you might with justice be
                    condemned to death by the jurors. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>For who other than this fellow is to blame, men of the jury, if the ship did not
                    arrive safe at the Peiraeus? Are we to blame, who lent our money expressly for a
                    voyage to <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, or is it the fault of this fellow
                    and his partner, who after borrowing money on these terms, that the vessel
                    should return to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, then took
                    her to <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>? And that they did this
                    of their own will and not of necessity is clear on many grounds. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>For if what occurred took place against their will, and the ship was really
                    disabled, afterwards, when they had repaired the ship, they would surely not
                    have let her for a voyage to other ports, but would have despatched her to
                        <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to make amends for the
                    involuntary accident. As it is, however, they have not only made no amends, but
                    to their original wrongdoings they have added others greater far, and have come
                    here to contest the suit as it were in a spirit of mockery, assuming that it
                    will rest with them, if you give judgement against them, merely to pay the
                    principal and interest. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>Do not you, then, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,
                    suffer men of this stamp to have their own way, nor allow them to ride on two
                    anchors, with the hope that, if they are successful, they will retain what
                    belongs to others, and if they are not able to hoodwink you, they will merely
                    pay the bare amount which they owe; but inflict upon them the penalties provided
                    in the agreement. For it would be an outrageous thing, when these men have
                    themselves in writing imposed upon themselves a penalty of double the amount, if
                    they commit any breach of the agreement, that you should be more lenient toward
                    them; especially when you have yourselves been wronged no less than we. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>Our claims in the matter, therefore, are few and easy to be remembered. We lent
                    this fellow Dionysodorus and his partner three thousand drachmae for a voyage
                    from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to <placeName
                        key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> and from <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
                        >Egypt</placeName> to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; we
                    have not received either principal or interest, but they have kept our money and
                    had the use of it for two years; they have not even to this day brought the ship
                    back to your port, nor produced it plain to see. The agreement, however,
                    declares, that if they fail to deliver up the ship plain to see they shall pay
                    double the amount, and that the money may be recovered from either one or both
                    of them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>These are the just claims with which we have come before you demanding to recover
                    our money through your help, since we cannot get it from these men themselves.
                    Such is the statement of our case. These men, however, while they admit that
                    they borrowed the money and have not paid it back, contend that they are not
                    bound to pay the interest stipulated in the agreement, but the interest as far
                    as <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> only, which they made no part
                    of their contract, and to which we have not consented. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>Perhaps, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, if we were
                    trying the case in a Rhodian court, these men might get the better of us, seeing
                    that they have taken grain to <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName>
                    and sailed in their ship into that port; as it is, however, since we have come
                    before Athenians and our contract called for a voyage to your port, we hold it
                    right that you should give no advantage to men who have wronged you as well as
                    ourselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>Besides this, men of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, you must
                    not forget that, while you are today deciding one case alone you are fixing a
                    law for the whole port, and that many of those engaged in overseas trade are
                    standing here and watching you to see how you decide this question. For if you
                    hold that contracts and agreements made between man and man are to be binding,
                    and show no leniency towards those who transgress them, lenders will be more
                    ready to risk their money, and the business of your port will be increased. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>But if shipowners, after engaging in written contracts to sail to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, are to be permitted to put their
                    ships into other ports, giving out that they have been disabled, or advancing
                    other pretexts such as these of which Dionysodorus has availed himself, and to
                    reduce the interest in proportion to the length of the voyage which they say
                    they have made instead of paying it according to the agreement, there will be
                    nothing to prevent the voiding of all contracts. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>For who is going to be willing to risk his money, when he sees that written
                    agreements are of no force, but that arguments such as these prevail and that
                    the claims of wrongdoers take precedence over what is right? Do not permit this,
                    men of the jury, for it is not to the interest of the mass of your people any
                    more than of those engaged in trade, who are a body of men most useful to your
                    public at large and to the individuals who have dealings with them. For this
                    reason you should be careful of their interests.</p>
                <p>I, for my part, have said all that I could; but I desire also to have one of my
                    friends speak in my behalf.<milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Come forward,
                    Demosthenes.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
