<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - Lamentations</title>
                
                <editor>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor>
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                  <!-- <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>-->
             <refState unit="chapter"/><refState unit="verse"/></refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>14-Oct-99</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <resp>markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial markup from flat ASCII text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>5/27/09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>RS</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: world.english.xml,v $
			Revision 1.2  2010-06-29 22:00:29  student
			fixing place tags - AD

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:10:56  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.3  2009/05/27 16:11:31  rsingh04
			added/fixed cvs log keyword
                </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="Lamentations" type="book">
                <head>Lamentations</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        How does the city sit solitary, that was full of people!
She has become as a widow, who was great among the nations!
She who was a princess among the provinces is become tributary!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        She weeps sore in the night, and her tears are on her cheeks;
Among all her lovers she has none to comfort her:
All her friends have dealt treacherously with her; they are become her
      enemies.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Judah is gone into captivity because of affliction, and because
      of great servitude;
She dwells among the nations, she finds no rest:
All her persecutors overtook her within the straits.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        The ways of Zion do mourn, because none come to the solemn
      assembly;
All her gates are desolate, her priests do sigh:
Her virgins are afflicted, and she herself is in bitterness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Her adversaries are become the head, her enemies prosper;
For Yahweh has afflicted her for the multitude of her transgressions:
Her young children are gone into captivity before the adversary.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        From the daughter of Zion all her majesty is departed:
Her princes are become like harts that find no pasture,
They are gone without strength before the pursuer.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Jerusalem remembers in the days of her affliction and of her
      miseries all her pleasant things that were from the days of old:
When her people fell into the hand of the adversary, and none did help
      her,
The adversaries saw her, they did mock at her desolations.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Jerusalem has grievously sinned; therefore she is become as an
      unclean thing;
All who honored her despise her, because they have seen her nakedness:
Yes, she sighs, and turns backward.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Her filthiness was in her skirts; she didn't remember her latter
      end;
Therefore is she come down wonderfully; she has no comforter:
See, Yahweh, my affliction; for the enemy has magnified himself.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        The adversary has spread out his hand on all her pleasant things:
For she has seen that the nations are entered into her sanctuary,
Concerning whom you did command that they should not enter into your
      assembly.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        All her people sigh, they seek bread;
They have given their pleasant things for food to refresh the soul:
Look, Yahweh, and see; for I am become abject.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Is it nothing to you, all you who pass by?
Look, and see if there be any sorrow like my sorrow, which is brought
      on me,
With which Yahweh has afflicted [me] in the day of his fierce anger.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        From on high has he sent fire into my bones, and it prevails
      against them;
He has spread a net for my feet, he has turned me back:
He has made me desolate and faint all the day.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        The yoke of my transgressions is bound by his hand;
They are knit together, they are come up on my neck; he has made my
      strength to fail:
The Lord has delivered me into their hands, against whom I am not able
      to stand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        The Lord has set at nothing all my mighty men in the midst of me;
He has called a solemn assembly against me to crush my young men:
The Lord has trodden as in a winepress the virgin daughter of Judah.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        For these things I weep; my eye, my eye runs down with water;
Because the comforter who should refresh my soul is far from me:
My children are desolate, because the enemy has prevailed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Zion spreads forth her hands; there is none to comfort her;
Yahweh has commanded concerning Jacob, that those who are round about
      him should be his adversaries:
Jerusalem is among them as an unclean thing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Yahweh is righteous; for I have rebelled against his commandment:
Please hear all you peoples, and see my sorrow:
My virgins and my young men are gone into captivity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        I called for my lovers, [but] they deceived me:
My priests and my elders gave up the spirit in the city,
While they sought them food to refresh their souls.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        See, Yahweh; for I am in distress; my heart is troubled;
My heart is turned within me; for I have grievously rebelled:
Abroad the sword bereaves, at home there is as death.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        They have heard that I sigh; there is none to comfort me;
All my enemies have heard of my trouble; they are glad that you have
      done it:
You will bring the day that you have proclaimed, and they shall be like
      me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Let all their wickedness come before you;
Do to them, as you have done to me for all my transgressions:
For my sighs are many, and my heart is faint.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        How has the Lord covered the daughter of Zion with a cloud in
      his anger!
He has cast down from heaven to the earth the beauty of Israel,
And hasn't remembered his footstool in the day of his anger.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        The Lord has swallowed up all the habitations of Jacob, and has
      not pitied:
He has thrown down in his wrath the strongholds of the daughter of
      Judah;
He has brought them down to the ground; he has profaned the kingdom and
      the princes of it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        He has cut off in fierce anger all the horn of Israel;
He has drawn back his right hand from before the enemy:
He has burned up Jacob like a flaming fire, which devours round about.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        He has bent his bow like an enemy, he has stood with his right
      hand as an adversary,
Has killed all that were pleasant to the eye:
In the tent of the daughter of Zion he has poured out his wrath like
      fire.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        The Lord is become as an enemy, he has swallowed up Israel;
He has swallowed up all her palaces, he has destroyed his strongholds;
He has multiplied in the daughter of Judah mourning and lamentation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        He has violently taken away his tent, as if it were of a garden;
      he has destroyed his place of assembly:
Yahweh has caused solemn assembly and Sabbath to be forgotten in Zion,
Has despised in the indignation of his anger the king and the priest.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        The Lord has cast off his altar, he has abhorred his sanctuary;
He has given up into the hand of the enemy the walls of her palaces:
They have made a noise in the house of Yahweh, as in the day of a
      solemn assembly.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Yahweh has purposed to destroy the wall of the daughter of Zion;
He has stretched out the line, he has not withdrawn his hand from
      destroying;
He has made the rampart and wall to lament; they languish together.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Her gates are sunk into the ground; he has destroyed and broken
      her bars:
Her king and her princes are among the nations where the law is not;
Yes, her prophets find no vision from Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        The elders of the daughter of Zion sit on the ground, they keep
      silence;
They have cast up dust on their heads; they have girded themselves with
      sackcloth:
The virgins of Jerusalem hang down their heads to the ground.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        My eyes do fail with tears, my heart is troubled;
My liver is poured on the earth, because of the destruction of the
      daughter of my people,
Because the young children and the infants swoon in the streets of the
      city.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        They tell their mothers, Where is grain and wine?
When they swoon as the wounded in the streets of the city,
When their soul is poured out into their mothers' bosom.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        What shall I testify to you? what shall I liken to you, daughter
      of Jerusalem?
What shall I compare to you, that I may comfort you, virgin daughter of
      Zion?
For your breach is great like the sea: who can heal you?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Your prophets have seen for you false and foolish visions;
They have not uncovered your iniquity, to bring back your captivity,
But have seen for you false oracles and causes of banishment.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        All that pass by clap their hands at you;
They hiss and wag their head at the daughter of Jerusalem, [saying],
Is this the city that men called The perfection of beauty, The joy of
      the whole earth?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        All your enemies have opened their mouth wide against you;
They hiss and gnash the teeth; they say, We have swallowed her up;
Certainly this is the day that we looked for; we have found, we have
      seen it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Yahweh has done that which he purposed; he has fulfilled his
      word that he commanded in the days of old;
He has thrown down, and has not pitied:
He has caused the enemy to rejoice over you; he has exalted the horn of
      your adversaries.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Their heart cried to the Lord:
wall of the daughter of Zion, let tears run down like a river day and
      night;
Give yourself no respite; don't let the apple of your eye cease.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Arise, cry out in the night, at the beginning of the watches;
Pour out your heart like water before the face of the Lord:
Lift up your hands toward him for the life of your young children, that
      faint for hunger at the head of every street.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Look, Yahweh, and see to whom you have done thus!
Shall the women eat their fruit, the children that are dandled in the
      hands?
Shall the priest and the prophet be killed in the sanctuary of the Lord?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        The youth and the old man lie on the ground in the streets;
My virgins and my young men are fallen by the sword:
You have killed them in the day of your anger; you have slaughtered,
      [and] not pitied.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        You have called, as in the day of a solemn assembly, my terrors
      on every side;
There was none that escaped or remained in the day of Yahweh's anger:
Those that I have dandled and brought up has my enemy consumed.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        I am the man that has seen affliction by the rod of his wrath.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        He has led me and caused me to walk in darkness, and not in light.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Surely against me he turns his hand again and again all the day.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        My flesh and my skin has he made old; he has broken my bones.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        He has built against me, and compassed me with gall and travail.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        He has made me to dwell in dark places, as those that have been
      long dead.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        He has walled me about, that I can't go forth; he has made my
      chain heavy.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Yes, when I cry, and call for help, he shuts out my prayer.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        He has walled up my ways with hewn stone; he has made my paths
      crooked.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        He is to me as a bear lying in wait, as a lion in secret places.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        He has turned aside my ways, and pulled me in pieces; he has
      made me desolate.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        He has bent his bow, and set me as a mark for the arrow.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        He has caused the shafts of his quiver to enter into my reins.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        I am become a derision to all my people, and their song all the
      day.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        He has filled me with bitterness, he has sated me with wormwood.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        He has also broken my teeth with gravel stones; he has covered
      me with ashes.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        You have removed my soul far off from peace; I forgot prosperity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        I said, My strength is perished, and my expectation from Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Remember my affliction and my misery, the wormwood and the gall.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        My soul still remembers them, and is bowed down within me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        This I recall to my mind; therefore have I hope.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        [It is of] Yahweh's lovingkindnesses that we are not consumed,
      because his compassion doesn't fail.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        They are new every morning; great is your faithfulness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        Yahweh is my portion, says my soul; therefore will I hope in him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        Yahweh is good to those who wait for him, to the soul that seeks
      him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        It is good that a man should hope and quietly wait for the
      salvation of Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        It is good for a man that he bear the yoke in his youth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        Let him sit alone and keep silence, because he has laid it on
      him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        Let him put his mouth in the dust, if so be there may be hope.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        Let him give his cheek to him who strikes him; let him be filled
      full with reproach.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        For the Lord will not cast off forever.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="32"/>
                        For though he cause grief, yet will he have compassion according
      to the multitude of his lovingkindnesses.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="33"/>
                        For he does not afflict willingly, nor grieve the children of
      men.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="34"/>
                        To crush under foot all the prisoners of the earth,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="35"/>
                        To turn aside the right of a man before the face of the Most
      High,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="36"/>
                        To subvert a man in his cause, the Lord doesn't approve.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="37"/>
                        Who is he who says, and it comes to pass, when the Lord doesn't
      command it?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="38"/>
                        Doesn't evil and good come out of the mouth of the Most High?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="39"/>
                        Why does a living man complain, a man for the punishment of his
      sins?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="40"/>
                        Let us search and try our ways, and turn again to Yahweh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="41"/>
                        Let us lift up our heart with our hands to God in the heavens.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="42"/>
                        We have transgressed and have rebelled; you have not pardoned.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="43"/>
                        You have covered with anger and pursued us; you have killed, you
      have not pitied.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="44"/>
                        You have covered yourself with a cloud, so that no prayer can
      pass through.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="45"/>
                        You have made us an off-scouring and refuse in the midst of the
      peoples.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="46"/>
                        All our enemies have opened their mouth wide against us.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="47"/>
                        Fear and the pit are come on us, devastation and destruction.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="48"/>
                        My eye runs down with streams of water, for the destruction of
      the daughter of my people.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="49"/>
                        My eye pours down, and doesn't cease, without any intermission,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="50"/>
                        Until Yahweh look down, and see from heaven.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="51"/>
                        My eye affects my soul, because of all the daughters of my city.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="52"/>
                        They have chased me sore like a bird, those who are my enemies
      without cause.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="53"/>
                        They have cut off my life in the dungeon, and have cast a stone
      on me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="54"/>
                        Waters flowed over my head; I said, I am cut off.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="55"/>
                        I called on your name, Yahweh, out of the lowest dungeon.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="56"/>
                        You heard my voice; don't hide your ear at my breathing, at my
      cry.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="57"/>
                        You drew near in the day that I called on you; you said, Don't
      be afraid.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="58"/>
                        Lord, you have pleaded the causes of my soul; you have redeemed
      my life.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="59"/>
                        Yahweh, you have seen my wrong; judge you my cause.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="60"/>
                        You have seen all their vengeance and all their devices against
      me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="61"/>
                        You have heard their reproach, Yahweh, and all their devices
      against me,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="62"/>
                        The lips of those that rose up against me, and their device
      against me all the day.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="63"/>
                        See you their sitting down, and their rising up; I am their song.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="64"/>
                        You will render to them a recompense, Yahweh, according to the
      work of their hands.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="65"/>
                        You will give them hardness of heart, your curse to them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="66"/>
                        You will pursue them in anger, and destroy them from under the
      heavens of Yahweh.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        How is the gold become dim! [how] is the most pure gold changed!
The stones of the sanctuary are poured out at the head of every street.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        The precious sons of Zion, comparable to fine gold,
How are they esteemed as earthen pitchers, the work of the hands of the
      potter!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Even the jackals draw out the breast, they give suck to their
      young ones:
The daughter of my people is become cruel, like the ostriches in the
      wilderness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        The tongue of the sucking child cleaves to the roof of his mouth
      for thirst:
The young children ask bread, and no man breaks it to them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Those who did feed delicately are desolate in the streets:
Those who were brought up in scarlet embrace dunghills.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        For the iniquity of the daughter of my people is greater than the
      sin of Sodom,
That was overthrown as in a moment, and no hands were laid on her.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Her nobles were purer than snow, they were whiter than milk;
They were more ruddy in body than rubies, their polishing was as of
      sapphire.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Their visage is blacker than a coal; they are not known in the
      streets:
Their skin cleaves to their bones; it is withered, it is become like a
      stick.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Those who are killed with the sword are better than those who are
      killed with hunger;
For these pine away, stricken through, for want of the fruits of the
      field.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        The hands of the pitiful women have boiled their own children;
They were their food in the destruction of the daughter of my people.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Yahweh has accomplished his wrath, he has poured out his fierce
      anger;
He has kindled a fire in Zion, which has devoured the foundations of it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        The kings of the earth didn't believe, neither all the
      inhabitants of the world,
That the adversary and the enemy would enter into the gates of
      Jerusalem.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        [It is] because of the sins of her prophets, [and] the
      iniquities of her priests,
That have shed the blood of the just in the midst of her.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        They wander as blind men in the streets, they are polluted with
      blood,
So that men can't touch their garments.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Depart you, they cried to them, Unclean! depart, depart, don't
      touch!
When they fled away and wandered, men said among the nations, They
      shall no more sojourn [here].
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        The anger of Yahweh has scattered them; he will no more regard
      them:
They didn't respect the persons of the priests, they didn't favor the
      elders.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Our eyes do yet fail [in looking] for our vain help:
In our watching we have watched for a nation that could not save.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        They hunt our steps, so that we can't go in our streets:
Our end is near, our days are fulfilled; for our end is come.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Our pursuers were swifter than the eagles of the sky:
They chased us on the mountains, they laid wait for us in the
      wilderness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        The breath of our nostrils, the anointed of Yahweh, was taken in
      their pits;
Of whom we said, Under his shadow we shall live among the nations.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Rejoice and be glad, daughter of Edom, that dwell in the land of
      Uz:
The cup shall pass through to you also; you shall be drunken, and shall
      make yourself naked.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        The punishment of your iniquity is accomplished, daughter of
      Zion; he will no more carry you away into captivity:
He will visit your iniquity, daughter of Edom; he will uncover your
      sins.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Remember, Yahweh, what has come on us:
Look, and see our reproach.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Our inheritance is turned to strangers,
Our houses to aliens.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        We are orphans and fatherless;
Our mothers are as widows.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        We have drunken our water for money;
Our wood is sold to us.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Our pursuers are on our necks:
We are weary, and have no rest.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        We have given the hand to the Egyptians,
To the Assyrians, to be satisfied with bread.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Our fathers sinned, and are no more;
We have borne their iniquities.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Servants rule over us:
There is none to deliver us out of their hand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        We get our bread at the peril of our lives,
Because of the sword of the wilderness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Our skin is black like an oven,
Because of the burning heat of famine.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        They ravished the women in Zion,
The virgins in the cities of Judah.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Princes were hanged up by their hand:
The faces of elders were not honored.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        The young men bare the mill;
The children stumbled under the wood.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        The elders have ceased from the gate,
The young men from their music.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        The joy of our heart is ceased;
Our dance is turned into mourning.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        The crown is fallen from our head:
Woe to us! for we have sinned.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        For this our heart is faint;
For these things our eyes are dim;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        For the mountain of Zion, which is desolate:
The foxes walk on it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        You, Yahweh, abide forever;
Your throne is from generation to generation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Why do you forget us forever,
[And] forsake us so long time?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Turn you us to you, Yahweh, and we shall be turned;
Renew our days as of old.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        But you have utterly rejected us;
You are very angry against us.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
