<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>
               </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by Norman W. DeWitt, Ph.D.,
                            and Norman J. DeWitt, Ph.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1949</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div n="Intro" type="part">
                <div n="1" type="section">
                    <p>With gross outrage I have met, men of the jury, at the hands of the
                        defendant, <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, and have suffered
                        such bodily injury that for a very long time neither my relatives nor any of
                        the attending physicians thought that I should survive. Contrary to
                        expectation, however, I did recover and regain my strength, and I then
                        brought against him this action for the assault. All my friends and
                        relatives, whose advice I asked, declared that for what he had done the
                        defendant was liable to summary seizure as a highwayman, or to public
                        indictments for criminal outrage<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">As guilty
                            of highway robbery the defendant had made himself liable to summary
                            arrest (<foreign xml:lang="grc">a)pagwgh/</foreign>), and the gravity of
                            his assault would have justified a public indictment for criminal
                            outrage (<foreign xml:lang="grc">u(/brews grafh/</foreign>), for either
                            of which crimes he would, if convicted, have suffered a heavy penalty.
                            The private suit for assault and battery (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
                                >ai)kei/as di/kh</foreign>) entailed merely a fine to be paid to the
                            plaintiff.</note>; but they urged and advised me not to take upon myself
                        matters which I should not be able to carry, or to appear to be bringing
                        suit for the maltreatment I had received in a manner too ambitious for one
                        so young. I took this course, therefore, and, in deference to their advice,
                        have instituted a private suit, although I should have been very glad, men
                        of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, to prosecute the
                        defendant on a capital charge. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="2" type="section">
                    <p>And for this you will all pardon me, I am sure, when you hear what I have
                        suffered. For, grievous as was the injury which at that time fell to my lot,
                        it was no more so than the subsequent insults of the defendant. I ask as my
                        right, therefore, and implore you all without distinction, to listen with
                        goodwill, while I tell you what I have suffered, and then, if you think that
                        I have been the victim of wrongful and lawless acts, to render me the aid
                        which is my due. I shall state to you from the beginning each incident as it
                        occurred in the fewest words I can. </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Narr" type="part">
                <div n="3" type="section">
                    <p>Two years ago I went out to Panactum,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >Panactum was an Athenian fort on the borders of <placeName
                                key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>. An expedition to this point
                            in <date when="-0343">343</date> B.C . is mentioned by Demosthenes in
                                <bibl n="Dem. 19.326">Dem. 19.326</bibl>. However, as we are told by
                                <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 42.4">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 42.4</bibl>,
                            that the <foreign xml:lang="grc">e)/fhboi</foreign> (young men of
                            military age), in the second year of their training, patrolled the
                            country and spent their spare time in the forts, it may be that no
                            formal military expedition is meant. In that case the loose discipline
                            is more understandable.</note> where we had been ordered to do garrison
                        duty. The sons of the defendant,
                            <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, encamped near us, as I
                        would to heaven they had not done; for our original enmity and our quarrels
                        began in fact just there. How these came about, you shall hear. These men
                        used always to spend the entire day after luncheon in drinking, and they
                        kept this up continually as long as we were in the garrison. We, on our
                        part, conducted ourselves while in the country just as we were wont to do
                        here. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="4" type="section">
                    <p>Well, at whatever time the others might be having their dinner, these men
                        were already drunk and abusive, at first toward our body-slaves, but in the
                        end toward ourselves. For, alleging that the slaves annoyed them with smoke
                        while getting dinner, or were impudent toward them, or whatever else they
                        pleased, they used to beat them and empty their chamber-pots over them, or
                        befoul them with urine; there was nothing in the way of brutality and
                        outrage in which they did not indulge. When we saw this, we were annoyed and
                        at first expostulated with them, but they mocked at us, and would not
                        desist, and so our whole mess in a body—not I alone apart from the rest—went
                        to the general and told him what was going on. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="5" type="section">
                    <p>He rebuked them with stern words, not only for their brutal treatment of us,
                        but for their whole behavior in camp; yet so far from desisting, or being
                        ashamed of their acts, they burst in upon us that very evening as soon as it
                        grew dark, and, beginning with abusive language, they proceeded to beat me,
                        and they made such a clamor and tumult about the tent, that both the general
                        and the taxiarchs<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The taxiarchs were the
                            commanders of the infantry detachments of the several tribes.</note>
                        came and some of the other soldiers, by whose coming we were prevented from
                        suffering, or ourselves doing, some damage that could not be repaired, being
                        victims as we were of their drunken violence. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="6" type="section">
                    <p>When matters had gone thus far, it was natural that after our return home
                        there should exist between us feelings of anger and hatred. However, on my
                        own part I swear by the gods I never saw fit to bring an action against
                        them, or to pay any attention to what had happened. I simply made this
                        resolve—in future to be on my guard, and to take care to have nothing to do
                        with people of that sort.</p>
                    <p>I wish in the first place to bring before you depositions proving these
                        statements, and then to show what I have suffered at the hands of the
                        defendant himself, in order that you may see that Conon, who should have
                        dealt rigorously with the first offences, has himself added to these far
                        more outrageous acts of his own doing.<quote type="Depositions">
                            <title>Depositions</title>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="7" type="section">
                    <p>These, then, are the acts of which I thought proper to take no account. Not
                        long after this, however, one evening, when I was taking a walk, as my
                        custom was, in the agora with Phanostratus of Cephisia,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">Cephisia, a deme of the tribe Erectheïs.</note> a man of
                        my own age,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This suggests that they were in
                            the same military age-class, and may have been together in camp at
                            Panactum.</note> Ctesias, the son of the defendant, passed by me in a
                        drunken state opposite the Leocorion,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This
                            was a monument erected in honor of the three daughters of Leos, whom, in
                            obedience to an oracle, their father had sacrificed for the safety of
                            their country.</note> near the house of Pythodorus. At sight of us he
                        uttered a yell, and, saying something to himself, as a drunken man does, in
                        an unintelligible fashion, passed on up, toward Melitê.<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">Melitê was a hilly district in the western part of
                                <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, its entrance
                            from the agora being through the hollow between the extremity of the
                            Areopagus and the <foreign xml:lang="grc">*kolwno\s
                                *)agorai=os</foreign>.</note> Gathered together there for a drinking
                        bout, as we afterwards learned, at the house of Pamphilus the fuller, were
                        the defendant <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, a certain
                        Theotimus, Archeblades, Spintharus, son of Eubulus, Theogenes, son of
                        Andromenes, and a number of others. Ctesias made them all get up, and
                        proceeded to the agora. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="8" type="section">
                    <p>It happened that we were turning back from the temple of Persephonê,<note
                            resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The site of this temple, as that of the
                            Leocorion, remains uncertain.</note> and on our walk were again about
                        opposite the Leocorion when we met them. When we got close to them one of
                        them, I don't know which, fell upon Phanostratus and pinned him, while the
                        defendant <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> together with his
                        son and the son of Andromenes threw themselves upon me. They first stripped
                        me of my cloak, and then, tripping me up they thrust me into the mud and
                        leapt upon me and beat me with such violence that my lip was split open and
                        my eyes closed; and they left me in such a state that I could neither get up
                        nor utter a sound. As I lay there I heard them utter much outrageous
                        language, </p>
                </div>
                <div n="9" type="section">
                    <p>a great deal of which was such foul abuse that I should shrink from repeating
                        some of it in your presence. One thing, however, which is an indication of
                        the fellow's insolence and a proof that the whole affair has been of his
                        doing, I will tell you. He began to crow, mimicking fighting cocks that have
                        won a battle and his fellows bade him flap his elbows against his sides like
                        wings. After this some people who happened to pass took me home stripped as
                        I was, for these men had gone off taking my cloak with them. When my bearers
                        got to my door, my mother and the women servants began shrieking and
                        wailing, and it was with difficulty that I was at length carried to a bath.
                        There I was thoroughly bathed, and shown to the surgeons.</p>
                    <p>To prove that these statements of mine are true, I shall call before you the
                        witnesses who attest them.<quote type="Witnesses">
                            <title>Witnesses</title>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="10" type="section">
                    <p>It happened, men of the jury, that Euxitheus of Cholleidae,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">Cholleidae, a deme of the tribe Leontis.</note> who is
                        here in court and is a relative of mine, and with him Meidias, on their way
                        back from a dinner somewhere, came up to me, when I was now near my home,
                        followed after me as I was borne to the bath, and were present when men
                        brought the surgeon. I was so weak, that, as it was far for me to be carried
                        from the bath to my home, those who were with me decided to carry me to the
                        house of Meidias for that night; and so they did.</p>
                    <p>Now let the clerk take the depositions establishing these facts, that you may
                        understand that a host of people know what outrage I suffered at the hands
                        of these men.<quote type="Depositions">
                            <title>Depositions</title>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>Take now the deposition of the surgeon also.<quote type="Deposition">
                            <title>Deposition</title>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="11" type="section">
                    <p>At that time, then, as the immediate result of the blows and the maltreatment
                        I received, I was brought into this condition, as you hear from my own lips,
                        and as all the witnesses who saw me at the time have testified. Afterwards,
                        although the swellings on my face and the bruises, my physician said, did
                        not give him great concern, continuous attacks of fever ensued and violent
                        and acute pains throughout all my body, but especially in my sides and the
                        pit of my stomach, and I was unable to take my food. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="12" type="section">
                    <p>Indeed, the surgeon said that, if a copious hemorrhage had not spontaneously
                        occurred, while my agony was extreme and my attendants were at their wits'
                        end, I should have died of internal suppuration; but as it was, this loss of
                        blood saved me.</p>
                    <p>To prove now that these statements of mine are true, and that from the blows
                        which these men dealt me there resulted an illness so severe that it brought
                        me to the point of death. Read the depositions of the surgeon and of those
                        who came to see me.<quote type="Depositions">
                            <title>Depositions</title>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Proof" type="part">
                <div n="13" type="section">
                    <p>That the wounds I received, then, were not slight or trifling, but that I was
                        brought near to death by the outrage and brutality of these men, and that
                        the action which I have entered is far more lenient than the case deserves,
                        has been made clear to you, I think, on many grounds. I fancy, however, that
                        some of you are wondering what in the world there can be that
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> will have the audacity
                        to say in reply to these charges. I wish, therefore, to tell you in advance
                        the defence which I hear he is prepared to make. He will try to divert your
                        attention from the outrage and the actual facts, and will seek to turn the
                        whole matter into mere jest and ridicule. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="14" type="section">
                    <p>He will tell you that there are many people in the city, sons of respectable
                        persons, who in sport, after the manner of young men, have given themselves
                        nicknames, such as Ithyphalli or Autolecythi,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">These words are best left untranslated
                                    (<persName><surname>Kennedy</surname></persName>, following
                            Auger, renders them “Priapi and Sileni”). The former suggests gross
                            licentiousness, and the latter, for which various meanings have been
                            proposed, has been plausibly interpreted by Sandys as indicating one who
                            carried his own oil-flask (<foreign xml:lang="grc">lh/kuqos</foreign>).
                            He would thus dispense with the customary slave, and be freed from
                            having even such an one as witness to his wanton doings.</note> and that
                        some of them are infatuated with mistresses; that his own son is one of
                        these and has often given and received blows on account of some girl; and
                        that things of this sort are natural for young men. As for me and all my
                        brothers, he will make out that we are not only drunken and insolent
                        fellows, but also unfeeling and vindictive.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                                    ><persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, the speaker
                            says, will represent us as being as much addicted to drunkenness and
                            violence as himself and his sons, but surly and vindictive in going to
                            law over such trifling matters!</note>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="15" type="section">
                    <p>For myself, men of the jury, deeply indignant though I am at what I have
                        suffered, I should feel no less indignation at this, and should count myself
                        the victim of a fresh outrage, if you will pardon the strong expression, if
                        this fellow <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> shall be deemed by
                        you to be speaking the truth about us, and you are to be so misguided as to
                        assume that a man bears the character which he claims for himself or which
                        someone else accuses him of possessing, and respectable people are to derive
                        no benefit from their daily life and conduct. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="16" type="section">
                    <p>No man in the world has ever seen us drunken or committing outrages, and I
                        hold that I am doing nothing unfeeling in demanding to receive satisfaction
                        according to the law for the wrongs I have suffered. This man's sons are
                        welcome, so far as I am concerned, to be Ithyphalli and Autolecythi; I only
                        pray the gods that these things and all things like them may recoil upon
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> and his sons; </p>
                </div>
                <div n="17" type="section">
                    <p>for they are those who initiate one another with the rites of Ithyphallus,
                        and indulge in acts which decent people cannot even speak of without deep
                        disgrace, to say nothing of performing them.</p>
                    <p>But what has all this to do with me? Why, for my part, I am amazed if they
                        have discovered any excuse or pretext which will make it possible in your
                        court for any man, if convicted of assault and battery, to escape
                        punishment. The laws take a far different view, and have provided that even
                        pleas of necessity shall not be pressed too far. For example (you see I have
                        had to inquire into these matters and inform myself about them because of
                        the defendant), </p>
                </div>
                <div n="18" type="section">
                    <p>there are actions for evil-speaking; and I am told that these are instituted
                        for this purpose—that men may not be led on, by using abusive language back
                        and forth, to deal blows to one another. Again, there are actions for
                        battery; and these, I hear, exist for this reason—that a man, finding
                        himself the weaker party, may not defend himself with a stone or anything of
                        that sort, but may await legal redress. Again, there are public prosecutions
                        for wounding, to the end that wounds may not lead to murder. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="19" type="section">
                    <p>The least of these evils, namely abusive language, has, I think, been
                        provided for to prevent the last and most grievous, that murder may not
                        ensue, and that men be not led on step by step from vilification to blows,
                        from blows to wounds, and from wounds to murder, but that in the laws its
                        own penalty should be provided for each of these acts, and that the decision
                        should not be left to the passion or the will of the person concerned. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="20" type="section">
                    <p>This, then, is what is ordained in the laws; but if
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> says, “We belong to a
                        club of Ithyphalli, and in our love-affairs we strike and throttle whom we
                        please,” are you, then, going to let him off with a laugh? I think not. No
                        one of you would have been seized with a fit of laughter, if he had happened
                        to be present when I was dragged and stripped and maltreated, when I was
                        borne home on a litter to the house which I had left strong and well, and my
                        mother rushed out, and the women set up such a wailing and screaming (as if
                        someone had died in the house) that some of the neighbors sent to inquire
                        what it was that had happened. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="21" type="section">
                    <p>Speaking broadly, men of the jury, I hold it right that no man should have
                        any excuse or immunity to rely on, when he is brought before you, so valid
                        that he is to be permitted to commit outrage; but if allowance is to be made
                        for anyone, it should be for those only who commit an act of this sort in
                        the folly of youth,—it is for these, I say, that such indulgence should be
                        reserved, and even in their case it should not extend to the remission of
                        the penalty, but to its mitigation. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="22" type="section">
                    <p>But when a man over fifty years of age in the company of younger men, and
                        these his own sons, not only did not discourage or prevent their wantonness,
                        but has proved himself the leader and the foremost and the vilest of all,
                        what punishment could he suffer that would be commensurate with his deeds?
                        For my part, I think that even death would be too mild. Why, if
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> had committed none of
                        the acts himself, but had merely stood by while his son Ctesias did what he
                        is himself proved to have done, you would regard him with loathing, and
                        rightly. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="23" type="section">
                    <p>For if he has trained up his sons in such fashion that they feel no fear or
                        shame while committing in his presence crimes for some of which the
                        punishment of death is ordained, what punishment do you think too severe for
                        him? I think these actions are a proof that he has no reverence for his own
                        father; for if he had honored and feared him, he would have exacted honor
                        and fear from his own children. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="24" type="section">
                    <p>Now take the statutes, that concerning assault and that concerning highway
                        robbers. You will see that the defendant is amenable to them both.
                            Read.<quote type="Laws">
                            <title>Laws</title>
                        </quote></p>
                    <p>By both these statutes, then, the defendant
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> is amenable for what
                        he has done; for he committed both assault and highway robbery. If I on my
                        part have not chosen to proceed against him under these statutes, that
                        should fairly prove that I am a peaceful and inoffensive person, not that he
                        is any the less a villain. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="25" type="section">
                    <p>And, assuredly, if anything had happened to me,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">A frequent euphemism for, “if my death had
                            ensued.”</note> he would have been liable to a charge of murder and the
                        severest of penalties. At any rate the father of the priestess at <placeName
                            key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true"><placeName key="perseus,Brauron">Brauron</placeName> was
                            a district on the eastern coast of <placeName key="tgn,7002681"
                                >Attica</placeName>, where there was a famous shrine of Artemis. It
                            was to this point that Orestes and Iphigeneia were said to have brought
                            the statue of Artemis from the land of the Taurians. The facts regarding
                            the case alluded to are unknown.</note> although it was admitted that he
                        had not laid a finger on the deceased, but had merely urged the one who
                        dealt the blow to keep on striking, was banished by the court of the
                        Areopagus. And justly; for, if the bystanders, instead of preventing those
                        who through the influence of drink or anger or any other cause are
                        undertaking to act lawlessly, are themselves to urge them on, there is no
                        hope of safety for one who falls in with lawless rascals; he may be sure
                        that he will be maltreated until they grow weary as was the case with me.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="26" type="section">
                    <p>I wish now to tell you what they sought to do at the arbitration; for from
                        this you will perceive their utter insolence. They spun out the time till
                        past midnight, refusing to read the depositions or to put in copies; leading
                        to the altar one at a time our witnesses who were present and putting them
                        on oath; writing depositions which had nothing to do with the case (for
                        instance “that Ctesias was the son of
                            <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> by a mistress, and that he
                        had been treated thus and so”<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If Ctesias
                            were illegitimate, <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> could
                            not be held responsible for his misdoings, and previous mistreatment by
                            the plaintiff is alleged as justification of the assault made upon the
                            latter by Ctesias.</note>)—a course of action, men of the jury, which I
                        assure you by the gods roused resentment and disgust in the mind of every
                        one present; and finally they were disgusted at themselves. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="27" type="section">
                    <p>Be that as it may, when they had had their fill and were tired of acting
                        thus, they put in a challenge with a view to gaining time and preventing the
                        boxes from being sealed, offering to deliver up certain slaves, whose names
                        they wrote down, to be examined as to the assault. And I fancy that their
                        defence will hinge chiefly upon this point. I think, however, that you
                        should all note one thing—that if these men tendered the challenge in order
                        that the inquiry by the torture should take place, and had confidence in
                        this method of proof, they would not have tendered it when the award was now
                        just being announced, when night had fallen and no further pretext was left
                        them; no, </p>
                </div>
                <div n="28" type="section">
                    <p>before the action had been brought, while I was lying ill and not knowing
                        whether I should recover, and was denouncing the defendant to all who came
                        to see me as the one who dealt the first blow and was the perpetrator of
                        most of the maltreatment I received,—it was then, I say, that he would have
                        come to my house without delay, bringing with him a number of witnesses; it
                        was then that he would have offered to deliver up his slaves for the
                        torture, and would have invited some members of the Areopagus to attend; for
                        if I had died, the case would have come before them. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="29" type="section">
                    <p>But if he was unaware of this situation, and having this proof, as he will
                        now say, made no preparation against so serious a danger, surely when I had
                        left my sick bed and summoned him, he would at our first meeting before the
                        arbitrator have shown himself ready to deliver up the slaves. But he did
                        nothing of the kind.</p>
                    <p>To prove that I am speaking the truth, and that the challenge was tendered
                        merely for the sake of gaining time, read this deposition. It will be clear
                        from this.<quote type="Deposition">
                            <title>Deposition</title>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="30" type="section">
                    <p>With regard to the examination by the torture, then, bear these facts in
                        mind: the time when the challenge was tendered, his evasive purpose in doing
                        this, and the first occasions, in the course of which he showed that he did
                        not wish this test to be accorded him, and neither proposed it nor demanded
                        it. Since, however, he was convicted on all these points before the
                        arbitrator, just as he is now, and proved manifestly guilty of all the
                        charges against him, he puts into the box a false deposition, </p>
                </div>
                <div n="31" type="section">
                    <p>and writes at the head of it as witnesses the names of people whom I think
                        you will know well when you hear them— “Diotimus, son of Diotimus, of
                            <placeName key="tgn,7010824">Icaria</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true"><placeName key="tgn,7010824">Icaria</placeName>, a deme
                            of the tribe Aegeïs.</note> Archebiades, son of Demoteles, of <placeName
                            key="tgn,5004271">Halae</placeName>,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >There were two demes of this name, one on the east coast of <placeName
                                key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> and the other on the Saronic
                            Gulf. The former belonged to the tribe Aegeis, the latter to the tribe
                            Cecropis.</note> Chaeretimus, son of Chaerimenes, of Pithus,<note
                            resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Pithus, a deme of the tribe Cecropis.</note>
                        depose that they were returning from a dinner with <placeName
                            key="tgn,1123029">Conon</placeName>, and came upon Ariston and the son
                        of <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> fighting in the agora, and
                        that <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> did not strike Ariston,”
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="32" type="section">
                    <p>—as though you would believe them off-hand, and would have no regard to the
                        truth of the matter that, to begin with, Lysistratus and Paseas and
                        Niceratus and Diodorus, who have expressly testified that they saw me being
                        beaten by <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, stripped of my
                        cloak, and suffering all the other forms of brutal outrage I
                        experienced—men, remember, who were unacquainted with me and who happened on
                        the affair by chance—that these men, I say, would never in the world have
                        consented to give testimony which they would have known to be false, if they
                        had not seen the maltreatment which I received; and, secondly, that I
                        myself, if I had not been thus treated by the defendant, should never have
                        let off men who are admitted by my opponents themselves to have struck me,
                        and have chosen to proceed first against the one who never laid a finger on
                        me. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="33" type="section">
                    <p>Why should I? No; the man who was first to strike me and from whom I suffered
                        the greatest indignity, he it is whom I am suing, whom I abhor, and whom I
                        am now prosecuting. My words, then, are all true and are proved to be so,
                        whereas the defendant, if he had not brought forward these witnesses, had, I
                        take it, not an argument to advance, but would have had silently to undergo
                        an immediate conviction. But it stands to reason, that these men, who have
                        been partners in his drinking bouts and have shared in many deeds of this
                        sort, have given false testimony. If matters are to come to this pass, if
                        once certain people shall prove shameless enough to give manifestly false
                        testimony, and there shall be no advantage in the truth, it will be a
                        terrible state of things. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="34" type="section">
                    <p>Ah but, they will say, they are not people of that sort. I am inclined to
                        think, however, that many of you know Diotimus and Archebiades and
                        Chaeretimus, the grey-headed man yonder, men who by day put on sour looks
                        and pretend to play the Spartan<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Many men in
                                <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in the days of
                            Plato and Demosthenes, as an indication of their contempt for democracy
                            and a protest against the decay of morals, sought to imitate the Spartan
                            severity in dress and manners. Men such as those whom the writer is here
                            depicting would not unnaturally seek by this means to build up a
                            spurious reputation for austerity.</note> and wear short cloaks and
                        single-soled shoes, but when they get together and are by themselves leave
                        no form of wickedness or indecency untried. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="35" type="section">
                    <p>And these are their brilliant and vigorous pleas, “What! Are we not to give
                        testimony for one another? Isn't that the way of comrades and friends? What
                        is there that you really fear in the charges he will bring against you? Do
                        some people say they saw him being beaten? We will testify that he wasn't
                        even touched by you. That his cloak was stripped off? We will testify that
                        they had done this first to you. That his lip has been sewn up? We will say
                        that your head or something else has been broken.” </p>
                </div>
                <div n="36" type="section">
                    <p>But I bring forward surgeons also as witnesses. This, men of the jury, is not
                        the case with them, but except what is deposed by themselves they will have
                        not a single witness against me. But Heaven knows I could not tell you how
                        great and how reckless a readiness you may expect on their part to
                        perpetrate anything whatever.</p>
                    <p>Now that you may know what sort of things they do as they go about—read them
                        these depositions, and do you check the flow of the water.<quote
                            type="Depositions">
                            <title>Depositions</title>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div n="37" type="section">
                    <p>Well then, if people break into houses and beat those who come in their way,
                        do you suppose they would scruple to swear falsely on a scrap of paper in
                        the interest of one another—these men who are partners in such great and
                        such reckless malignity and villainy and impudence and outrage? For I
                        certainly think that all these terms fit the deeds they are in the habit of
                        doing. And yet there are other deeds of theirs more dreadful even than
                        these, though I should be unable to find out all who have suffered from
                        them. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="38" type="section">
                    <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The thing, however, which is the most impudent
                        of all that he is going to do, as I hear, I think it better to warn you of
                        in advance. For they say that he will bring his children, and, placing them
                        by his side, will swear by them, imprecating some dread and awful curses of
                        such a nature that a person who heard them and reported them to me was
                        amazed. Now, men of the jury, there is no way of withstanding such audacity;
                        for, I take it, the most honorable men and those who would be the last to
                        tell a falsehood themselves, are most apt to be deceived by such people—not
                        but that they ought to look at their lives and characters before believing
                        them. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="39" type="section">
                    <p>The contempt, however, which this fellow feels for all sacred things I must
                        tell you about; for I have been forced to make inquiry. For I hear, then,
                        men of the jury, that a certain Bacchius, who was condemned to death in your
                        court, and Aristocrates, the man with the bad eyes, and certain others of
                        the same stamp, and with them this man
                            <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, were intimates when they
                        were youths, and bore the nickname Triballi<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >The Triballi were a wild Thracian people. Many parallels for the use of
                            the name to denote a club of lawless youths at <placeName
                                key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> might be cited. Sandys
                            refers to the Mohock club of eighteenth century <placeName
                                key="tgn,7011781">London</placeName>.</note>; and that these men
                        used to devour the food set out for Hecatê<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >The witch-goddess worshipped at cross roads. Portions of victims which
                            had served for purification were set out for her. To take and eat this
                            food might connote extreme poverty, but suggested also an utter
                            disregard for sacred things.</note> and to gather up on each occasion
                        for their dinner with one another the testicles of the pigs which are
                        offered for purification when the assembly convenes,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">Young pigs were sacrificed in a ceremonial purification
                            of the place of meeting before the people entered the <foreign
                                xml:lang="grc">e)kklhsi/a</foreign>(the popular assembly).</note>
                        and that they thought less of swearing and perjuring themselves than of
                        anything else in the world. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="40" type="section">
                    <p>Surely <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, a man of that sort, is
                        not to be believed on oath; far from it indeed. No; the man who would not
                        swear by any object which your custom does not recognize even an oath which
                        he intended to observe, and would not even think of doing so by the lives of
                        his children, but would suffer anything rather than that; and who, if forced
                        to swear, will take only a customary oath, imprecating destruction upon
                        himself, his race, and his house, is more to be believed than one who swears
                        by his children or is ready to pass through fire.<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">The speaker is plainly contrasting his own caution in
                            taking an oath with the recklessness shown by the defendant, but the
                            difficulty of the passage is only partially removed by the transposition
                            mentioned in the critical note. As to the concluding phrase, it is
                            doubtful if an ordeal by fire is alluded to, although suggestive
                            parallels are found in <bibl n="Soph. Ant. 264">Soph. Ant. 264</bibl>
                            and <bibl n="Aristoph. Lys. 133">Aristoph. Lys.133</bibl></note> I,
                        then, who on every account am more worthy to be believed than you,
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, offered to take the
                        oath here cited,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Cited, that is, in the
                            following challenge.</note> not that through readiness to do anything
                        whatsoever I might avoid paying the penalty for crimes which I had
                        committed, as is the case with you, but in the interest of truth, and in
                        order that I might not be subjected to further outrage, and as one who will
                        not allow his case to be lost through your perjury.</p>
                    <p>Read the challenge.<quote type="Challenge">
                            <title>Challenge</title>
                        </quote>
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div n="Concl" type="part">
                <div n="41" type="section">
                    <p>This oath I was at that time ready to take, and now, to convince you and
                        those who stand gathered about, I swear by all the gods and goddesses that I
                        have in very truth suffered at the hands of
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> this wrong for which I
                        am suing him; that I was beaten by him, and that my lip was cut open so that
                        it had to be sewn up, and that it is because of gross maltreatment that I am
                        prosecuting him. If I swear truly, may many blessings be mine, and may I
                        never again suffer such an outrage; but, if I am forsworn, may I perish
                        utterly, I and all I possess or ever may possess. But I am not forsworn; no,
                        not though <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> should say so till
                        he bursts. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="42" type="section">
                    <p>Therefore, men of the jury, since I have shown you all the just arguments
                        which I have to present, and have furthermore added an oath, it is but right
                        that you should feel toward <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> on
                        my behalf the same resentment which each one of you, had he been the victim,
                        would have felt toward the one who did the wrong, and not to regard an act
                        of this sort as a private matter which might fall to the lot of any man. No;
                        whoever may be the victim, bear him aid and give him the redress that is his
                        due, and loathe those who in the face of their crimes are bold and reckless,
                        but when they are brought to trial are impudent villains, caring nothing for
                        reputation or character or anything else, provided only they can escape
                        punishment. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="43" type="section">
                    <p>Of course <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName> will entreat you and
                        wail aloud. But consider, which of us is more deserving of pity, a man who
                        has suffered such treatment as I have at the hands of the defendant, if I am
                        to go forth having met with the further disgrace of losing my suit, or
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, if he is to be
                        punished? Is it to the advantage of each one of you that a man be permitted
                        to indulge in battery and outrage, or that he be not permitted? I certainly
                        think he should not be. Well then, if you let him off, there will be many
                        such; if you punish him, fewer. </p>
                </div>
                <div n="44" type="section">
                    <p>I might have much to say, men of the jury, about the services we have
                        rendered you, I, and my father while he lived, both as trierarchs and in the
                        army, and in performing whatever duty was laid upon us, and I could show
                        that neither the defendant nor any of his sons have rendered any service;
                        but the allowance of water is not sufficient nor is it at this time a
                        question of such services. For, if it were indeed our lot to be by common
                        consent regarded as more useless and more base than
                                <persName><surname>Conon</surname></persName>, we are not, I
                        suppose, to be beaten or maltreated.</p>
                    <p>I do not know what reason there is why I should say more; for I believe that
                        nothing which I have said has escaped you.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >Compare the concluding paragraph in <bibl n="Dem. 36">Dem. 36</bibl>
                            and <bibl n="Dem. 28">Dem. 28</bibl>.</note></p>
                </div>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
