<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Diogeiton from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="Intro" unit="part"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>If the matters in dispute were not important, gentlemen of the jury, I should
        never have allowed these persons to appear before you; for I regard a dispute with one’s
        relations as most disgraceful, and I know that you reprobate not merely those who are guilty
        of wrong, but also anyone who is unable to tolerate the sharp practice of a kinsman. But,
        gentlemen, since they have been robbed of a great sum of money and, after suffering numerous
        outrages from those who should have been the last to act in such a way, have sought refuge
        in me, their brother-in-law, I find it incumbent on me to speak for them. <milestone n="2"
          unit="section"/>I am married to their sister, a child of Diogeiton’s daughter; and after
        many appeals I at first prevailed on both parties to submit the case to the arbitration of
        their friends, as I held it most desirable that their affairs should not be known to anyone
        else. But since Diogeiton would not allow himself to be advised by any of his own friends
        regarding the property which he was plainly convicted of holding, but preferred to be
        prosecuted, to sue against the validity of judgements, and to encounter the utmost risks,
        rather than do the just thing which would relieve him of all their complaints, I entreat
        you, <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>if I prove that the guardianship of their grandfather
        has been conducted more disgracefully than any heretofore held in the city by persons who
        had no bond of relationship, to give them the support of justice: otherwise, believe this
        man entirely, and reprobate us henceforward. I will now try to inform you on the matter from
        the beginning. <milestone n="Narr" unit="part"/><milestone n="4" unit="section"/><milestone
          ed="P" unit="para"/>Diodotus and Diogeiton, gentlemen of the jury, were brothers born of
        the same father and mother, and they had divided between them the personal estate, but held
        the real property in partnership. When Diodotus had made a large fortune in shipping
        business, Diogeiton induced him to marry the one daughter that he had, and two sons and a
        daughter were born to him. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>Some time later, when Diodotus
        was enrolled for infantry service, he summoned his wife, who was his niece, and her father,
        who was also his father-in-law and his brother, and grandfather and uncle of the little
        ones, as he felt that owing to these connections there was nobody more bound to act justly
        by his children: he then gave him a will and five talents of silver in deposit; <milestone
          n="6" unit="section"/>and he also produced an account of his loans on bottomry, amounting
        to seven talents and forty minae<gap reason="lost"/>and two thousand drachmae invested in the <placeName
          key="tgn,7017285">Chersonese</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In <placeName
            key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>. This sentence is evidently defective.</note> He
        charged him, in case anything should happen to himself, to dower his wife and his daughter
        with a talent each, and to give his wife the contents of the room; he also bequeathed to his
        wife twenty minae and thirty staters of <placeName key="perseus,Cyzicus"
          >Cyzicus</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">See <bibl n="Lys. 12.11">Lys.
            12.11</bibl>, note.</note>
        <milestone n="7" unit="section"/>Having made these arrangements and left duplicate deeds in
        his house, he went to serve abroad with Thrasyllus. He was killed at <placeName
          key="tgn,7002499">Ephesus</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="Loeb"><date value="-409"
            >409</date> B.C. Thrasyllus was one of the commanders who were executed after Arginusae,
            <date value="-406">406</date> B.C.</note>: for a time Diogeiton concealed from his
        daughter the death of her husband, and took possession of the deeds which he had left under
        seal, alleging that these documents were needed for recovering the sums lent on bottomry.
          <milestone n="8" unit="section"/>When at length he informed them of the death, and they
        had done what is customary,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">This comprised the lying in
          state, the burial or cremation, the funeral feast, sacrifices offered on the third and
          ninth days, and mourning with black garments and shaven heads for thirty days.</note> they
        lived for the first year in the Peiraeus, as all their provisions had been left there. But
        when these began to give out, he sent up the children to the city, and gave their mother in
        marriage with a dowry of five thousand drachmae,—a thousand less than her husband had given
        her. <milestone n="9" unit="section"/>Seven years later the elder of the boys was certified
        to be of age<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">In his eighteenth year: cf. <bibl
            n="Lys. 10.31">Lys. 10.31</bibl>.</note>; when Diogeiton summoned them, and said that
        their father had left them twenty minae of silver and thirty staters, adding,—“Now I have
        spent a great deal of my own money on your support: so long as I had the means, I did not
        mind; but at this moment I too am in difficulties myself. You, therefore, since you have
        been certified and have attained manhood, must henceforth contrive to provide for yourself.”
          <milestone n="10" unit="section"/>On hearing these words they went away, aghast and
        weeping, to their mother, and brought her along with them to me. It was pitiful to see how
        they suffered from the blow: the poor wretches, turned out of doors, wept aloud and besought
        me not to allow them to be deprived of their patrimony and reduced to beggary by the last
        persons who ought to have committed this outrage upon them, but to give my best aid, for
        their sister’s sake as well as their own. <milestone n="11" unit="section"/><milestone
          ed="P" unit="para"/>Of the mourning that filled my house at that time it would take long
        to tell. In the end, their mother implored and entreated me to assemble her father and
        friends together, saying that even though she had not before been accustomed to speak in the
        presence of men, the severity of their misfortunes would compel her to give us a full
        account of their hardships. <milestone n="12" unit="section"/>I went first and expressed my
        indignation to Hegemon, the husband of this man’s daughter; I then discussed the matter with
        the other relations; and I called upon this man to allow his handling of the money to be
        investigated. Diogeiton at first refused, but finally he was compelled by his friends. When
        we held our meeting, the mother asked him what heart he could have, that he thought fit to
        take such measures with the children, “when you are their father’s brother,” she said, “and
        my father, and their uncle and grandfather. <milestone n="13" unit="section"/>Even if you
        felt no shame before any man, you ought to have feared the gods. For you received from him,
        when he went on the expedition, five talents in deposit. I offer to swear to the truth of
        this on the lives of my children, both these and those since born to me, in any place<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">i.e., in some temple.</note> that you yourself may name. Yet I
        am not so abject, or so fond of money, as to take leave of life after perjuring myself on
        the lives of my own children, and to appropriate unjustly my father’s estate.” <milestone
          n="14" unit="section"/>And she convicted him further of having recovered seven talents and
        four thousand drachmae of bottomry loans, and she produced the record of these; for she
        showed that in the course of his removal from Collytus<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">A
          district to the north of the Acropolis.</note> to the house of Phaedrus the children had
        happened upon the register, which had been mislaid, and had brought it to her. <milestone
          n="15" unit="section"/>She also proved that he had recovered a hundred minae which had
        been lent at interest on land mortgages, besides two thousand drachmae and some furniture of
        great value; and that corn came in to them every year from the <placeName key="tgn,7010345"
          >Chersonese</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Where evidently the 2000
          drachmae invested by Diodotus (see <bibl n="Lys. 32.6">Lys. 32.6</bibl>) brought in an
          annual supply of corn as interest.</note>“After that,” she said, “you had the audacity to
        state, when you had so much money in your possession, that their father bequeathed them two
        thousand drachmae and thirty staters,—just the amount that was bequeathed to me, and that I
        gave you after his decease! <milestone n="16" unit="section"/>And you thought fit to turn
        these, the children of your daughter, out of their own house, in worn-out clothes, without
        shoes or attendant or bedding or cloaks; without the furniture which their father bequeathed
        to them, and without the money which he had deposited with you. <milestone n="17"
          unit="section"/>And now you are bringing up the children you have had by my step-mother in
        all the comforts of affluence; and you are quite right in that: but you are wronging mine,
        whom you ejected from the house in dishonor, and whom you are intent on turning from persons
        of ample means into beggars. And over proceedings of this sort you feel neither fear of the
        gods nor shame before me who am cognizant of the facts, nor are you mindful of your brother,
        but you put money before us all.” <milestone n="18" unit="section"/>Thereupon, gentlemen of
        the jury, after hearing all the severe things spoken by the mother, the whole company of us
        there were so affected by this man’s conduct and by her statements,—when we saw how the
        children had been treated, and recalled the dead man to mind and how unworthy was the
        guardian he had left in charge of his estate, and reflected how hard it is to find a person
        who can be trusted with one’s affairs,—that nobody, gentlemen, among us there was able to
        utter a word: we could only weep as sadly as the sufferers, and go our ways in
          silence.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, first, will you come forward, witnesses, to
        support what I say.<label>Witnesses</label>
        <milestone n="Proof" unit="part"/><milestone n="19" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>Well, gentlemen of the jury, I ask that due attention be given to this
        reckoning, in order that you may take pity on the young people for the depth of their
        misfortune, and may consider that this man deserves the anger of everyone in the city. For
        Diogeiton is reducing all men to such a state of suspicion towards their fellows that
        neither living nor dying can they place any more confidence in their nearest relations than
        in their bitterest enemies; <milestone n="20" unit="section"/>since he has had the face to
        deny one part of his debt and, after finally confessing to the rest, to make out a sum of
        seven talents of silver and seven thousand drachmae as receipts and expenses on account of
        two boys and their sister during eight years. So gross is his impudence that, not knowing
        how he should enter the sums spent, he reckoned for the viands of the two young boys and
        their sister five obols a day<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">At this period the daily cost
          of food for an adult could be reckoned at one obol: in the present case, for the food
          (other than cereal) of three children, the charge of five obols is at least twice what it
          should be. A more reasonable scale is suggested by the speaker at <bibl n="Lys. 32.28"
            >Lys. 32.28</bibl> below.</note>; for shoes, laundry and hairdressing he kept no monthly
        or yearly account, but he shows it inclusively, for the whole period, as more than a talent
        of silver. <milestone n="21" unit="section"/>For the father’s tomb, though he did not spend
        twenty-five minae of the five thousand drachmae shown, he charges half this sum to himself,
        and has entered half against them.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Having stated that the
          tomb cost 50 minae (5000 drachmae), he undertook to pay half of this himself, and charge
          the other half to the children’s estate: but this latter half covered the actual
          cost.</note> Then for the Dionysia,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Orphans’ estates were
          not required to contribute to the offerings at the State festivals.</note> gentlemen of
        the jury,—I do not think it irrelevant to mention this also,—he showed sixteen drachmae as
        the price of a lamb, and charged eight of these drachmae to the children: this entry
        especially roused our anger.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Here again the actual cost was
          probably no more than the half-share charged to the children. Here again the actual cost
          was probably no more than the half-share charged to the children.</note> And so it is,
        gentlemen: in the midst of heavy losses the sufferers of wrong are sometimes wounded as much
        by little things; for these expose in so very clear a light the wickedness of the wrongdoer.
          <milestone n="22" unit="section"/>Then for the other festivals and sacrifices he charged
        to their account an expenditure of more than four thousand drachmae; and he added a
        multitude of things which he counted in to make up his total, as though he had been named in
        the will as guardian of the children merely in order that he might show them accounts
        instead of money, and reduce them from wealth to utter poverty, and that they might forget
        whatever ancestral enemy they might have to wage war on their guardian for stripping them of
        their patrimony! <milestone n="23" unit="section"/>But yet, had he wished to act justly by
        the children, he was free to act in accordance with the laws which deal with orphans for the
        guidance of incapable as well as capable guardians: he might have farmed out the estate and
        so got rid of a load of cares, or have purchased land and used the income for the children’s
        support; whichever course he had taken, they would have been as rich as anyone in <placeName
          key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. But the fact is, in my opinion, that at no time
        has he had any notion of turning their fortune into real estate, but has meant to keep their
        property for himself, assuming that his own wickedness ought to be heir of the wealth of the
        deceased. <milestone n="24" unit="section"/>Most monstrous of all, gentlemen of the jury, he
        asserts that in sharing with Alexis, son of Aristodicus, the service of equipping a warship,
        he paid a contribution of forty-eight minae, and has entered half of this against these
        orphan children, whom the State has not only exempted during their childhood, but has freed
        from all public services for a year after they have been certified to be of age. Yet he,
        their grandfather, illegally exacts from his daughter’s children one half of his expenses in
        equipping a warship! <milestone n="25" unit="section"/>Again, he dispatched to the Adriatic
        a cargo of two talents’ value, and told their mother, at the moment of its sailing, that it
        was at the risk of the children<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">It was unlawful for a
          guardian to venture a ward’s money in bottomry, and the Adriatic was notoriously perilous
          for navigation.</note>; but when it went safely through and the value was doubled,<note
          anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Hume (Essay on the Populousness of Ancient Nations) has
          remarked on the fact that a profit of 100 per cent on such a venture does not seem to have
          been thought extraordinary.</note> He declared that the venture was his. But if he is to
        lay the losses to their charge, and keep the successful gains for himself, he will have no
        difficulty in making the account show on what the money has been spent, while he will find
        it easy to enrich himself from the money of others. <milestone n="26" unit="section"/>To set
        the reckoning before you in detail, gentlemen of the jury, would be a lengthy affair; but
        when with some trouble I had got him to hand over the balance-sheet, in the presence of
        witnesses I asked Aristodicus, brother of Alexis,—the latter being now dead—whether he had
        the account for the equipment of a warship. He told me that he had, and we went to his house
        and found that Diogeiton had paid Alexis a contribution of twenty-four minae towards
        equipping the warship. <milestone n="27" unit="section"/>But the expenditure that he showed
        was forty-eight minae, so that the children have been charged exactly the total of what he
        has spent.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Again the whole of his actual contribution (24
          minae) has been charged to the children’s estate, as a half-share of an exaggerated
          total.</note> Now, what do you suppose he has done in cases of which nobody else has had
        cognizance, and where he managed the business alone, when in those which were conducted
        through others and of which information could easily be obtained he did not shrink from
        falsehood in mulcting his own daughter’s children to an amount of twenty-four minae? Please
        come forward, witnesses, in support of this.<label>Witnesses</label>
        <milestone n="28" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>You have heard the
        witnesses, gentlemen of the jury. I will now base my reckoning against him on the sum which
        he did eventually confess to holding,—seven talents and forty minae: not counting in any
        income, I will put down, as spent out of capital, a larger amount than anyone in the city
        has ever spent,—for two boys and their sister, an attendant and a maid, a thousand drachmae
        a year, a little less than three drachmae a day.<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Cf. a
          similar estate in <bibl n="Dem. 27.36">Dem. 27.36</bibl>.</note>
        <milestone n="29" unit="section"/>For eight years, that amounts to eight thousand drachmae;
        and we are left with a balance of six talents and twenty minae. For he will not be able to
        show that he has either had losses by pirates, or met with failure or paid off debts.<gap reason="lost"/>
        <milestone n="Concl" unit="part"/></p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
