<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Nausimachus and Xenopeithes</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>Inasmuch as the laws, men of the jury, have granted that a special plea may be
                    entered in cases where a man, after giving a release and discharge,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The opening sentences of this speech repeat
                        almost verbatim those of the preceding oration.</note> nevertheless brings
                    suit, and as both of these have been given to our father by Nausimachus and
                    Xenopeithes who have commenced suit against us, we have pleaded, as you have
                    just now heard, that their suit is not admissible. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>I shall make of you all a just and reasonable request: first, that you listen to
                    my words with goodwill, and, secondly, that if you think that I am being wronged
                    and made defendant in a suit which has no valid basis, you render me the succor
                    which is my due. The damages claimed in the action are, as you have heard,
                    thirty minae; but the sum for which we are really being sued is four talents.
                    For there are two of them, and they have entered four suits against us, all for
                    a like amount, each for three thousand drachmae damages;<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">From this it is plain that each of the two claimants brought
                        suit against each of the four sons of Aristaechmus. This makes eight suits
                        for thirty minae each, so that the total amount is four talents.</note> and
                    now on a complaint for thirty minae we are brought to trial for so large a sum.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>The malicious actions of these men, and the guile with which they have proceeded
                    against us, you will come to know from the facts themselves. But first the clerk
                    shall read to you the depositions which show that they released our father from
                    the charges which they made on the matter of his guardianship; for it is on this
                    ground that we entered our plea that the action is not maintainable.Please read
                    these depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>That they entered suit, men of the jury, regarding the guardianship; that they
                    dropped those actions; and that they have in their possession the sums of money
                    agreed upon, you hear from the witnesses. That the laws do not allow suit to be
                    entered afresh regarding matters which have been thus settled, I presume you
                    know, even if I say nothing about the matter; nevertheless I want to read you
                    the law itself.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Read the law.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>You hear the law, men of the jury, expressly stating the several cases in which
                    there shall be no actions. One of them (and it is as binding as any of the
                    others) is that suit may not be brought in matters for which anyone has given a
                    release and discharge. Yet, although the release was thus given in the presence
                    of numerous witnesses, and although the law manifestly absolves us, these men
                    have come to such a pitch of shamelessness and audacity, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>that, when fourteen years have elapsed from the time when they gave my father a
                    release, and twenty-two years after they had first indicted him,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This passage offers difficulties. The best
                        established text can be rendered only as above; but the question at once
                        arises: why the long lapse of time between the filing of the suit and the
                        settlement? Again, the use of <foreign xml:lang="grc">gegramme/noi</foreign>
                        of a civil suit is suprising, although this difficulty might be met by
                        assuming (with Kennedy) that a public prosecution is meant; but even so the
                        eight year period remains unexplained. If with MS. A we read <foreign
                            xml:lang="grc">e)ggegramme/noi</foreign> and render, “after they had
                        been enrolled as citizens,” we still have to ask why they should have waited
                        eight years after attaining their majority before seeking an accounting from
                        their guardians.</note> when my father was now dead, with whom the
                    settlement had been made and also the guardians who after his death had charge
                    of our property, when their own mother, too, was dead, who was well-informed
                    regarding all these matters, and the arbitrators, the witnesses, and almost
                    everybody else, if I may so say, counting our inexperience and necessary
                    ignorance a boon to themselves, they have instituted these suits against us, and
                    have the audacity to make statements which are neither just nor reasonable. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>They declare that they did not sell their father's estate for the money which
                    they received, nor did they give up the property, but that all that was left
                    them—credits, furniture, and even money—still belongs to them. I, for my part,
                    know by hearsay that Xenopeithes and Nausicrates<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The former was the uncle, the latter the father of the
                        plaintiff.</note> left their entire property in outstanding debts, and
                    possessed very little tangible property; and that when the debts had been
                    collected and some furniture and slaves had been sold, their guardians purchased
                    the farms and lodging-houses, which our opponents received from them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>If there had been no dispute about these matters before, and no suit had been
                    entered charging maladministration of the property, it would have been another
                    story; but since these men brought suit against our father in the matter of his
                    general conduct as guardian and recovered damages, all these matters were at
                    that time released. For our opponents, I take it, did not bring suit for the
                    mere name “mal-administration in guardianship,” but for the money; nor did the
                    guardians buy off this name with the money which they paid, but they bought off
                    the claims. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>That, therefore, these men have no right of action
                    against us for the debts which our father collected before the settlement, or,
                    in general, for monies which he received by virtue of his guardianship, seeing
                    that they have given a release for their claims, I think you have all adequately
                    learned from the laws themselves and from the release. Moreover, that it is
                    impossible that the collection of these funds should have been made subsequently
                    (this is the story they are making up to lead you astray), I wish to prove. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>As for my father, they cannot charge that he received them; for he died three or
                    four months after the settlement was made with them; and that Demaretus, whom
                    our father left as our guardian, could not have received them either (for they
                    have written his name also in their complaint), this, too, I shall show. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>These men are themselves our strongest witnesses; for they will be shown never to
                    have brought suit against Demaretus in his lifetime; but, more than that, anyone
                    who examines and studies the case itself will see, not only that he did not
                    receive the money, but that it was impossible that he should have received it.
                    For the debt was in Bosporus, a place which Demaretus never visited; how, then,
                    could he have collected it? Ah, but, they will say, he sent someone to get the
                    money. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>But look at the matter in this way. Hermonax owed these men one hundred
                        staters,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Athenian stater was a gold
                        coin worth twenty drachmae.</note> which he had received from Nausicrates.
                    Aristaechmus was for sixteen years the guardian and caretaker of these men.
                    Therefore, the money which Hermonax paid in his own person after these men had
                    come of age, he had not paid when they were minors; for he certainly did not pay
                    the same debt twice. Now is there any man so silly as voluntarily to pay money
                    to one not entitled to it, who demanded it by letter, when he had for so long a
                    time evaded payment to the rightful owners? For my part, I think there is not.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>However, to prove that I am speaking the truth,—that our father died immediately
                    after the settlement, that these men never brought suit against Demaretus for
                    this money, and that he absolutely never went to sea, nor visited Bosporus, take
                    the depositions.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Well then, that our father did not collect the money after the release; that no
                    one would voluntarily have paid the money, if Demaretus had sent someone to get
                    it; and that he himself neither put out to sea nor visited Bosporus, has been
                    made clear to you from the dates and the depositions. I wish, then, to show you
                    that their whole statement too of the case is absolute falsehood. They have
                    written in the complaint which they are now prosecuting, that we owe the money,
                    inasmuch as our father received it in payment, and passed it over to them as a
                    debt due and payable in his account of his guardianship.Take, and read me,
                    please, the complaint itself.<quote type="Complaint">
                        <title>Complaint</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>You hear it stated in the complaint, “inasmuch as Aristaechmus passed the debt
                    over to me in his account of his guardianship.” But, when they brought suit
                    against my father in the matter of his guardianship, they wrote the very
                    opposite of this; for they plainly charged him with not rendering an
                    account.Read, please, the complaint itself, which they then brought against my
                        father.<quote type="Complaint">
                        <title>Complaint</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>In what account, pray, Xenopeithes and Nausimachus, do you now charge that he
                    passed the debt over to you? For at one time you brought suit and demanded money
                    on the ground that he rendered no account. But if it is to be permitted you to
                    bring your malicious charge on both grounds, and at one time you collected money
                    because he did not hand something over to you, and at another are suing him on
                    the ground that he did hand it over, there is nothing to prevent your looking
                    for some third ground after this, so as to commence proceedings afresh. But that
                    is not what the laws state: they declare that suit may be brought once only
                    against the same person for the same acts. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>Now, men of the jury, that you may know that they not only have suffered no wrong
                    in the present case, but that they are bringing suit in defiance of all your
                    laws, I wish to cite to you this statute also, which expressly states that, if
                    five years have elapsed and they have brought no suit, it is no longer permitted
                    to orphans to bring suit regarding claims connected with guardianship.The clerk
                    will read you this law.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>You hear the law, men of the jury, flatly stating that if they do not bring suit
                    within five years, they have no longer the right to sue. But we did bring suit,
                    they may say. Yes, and you made a settlement, too; so you have no right to bring
                    a fresh suit. Else it would be an outrageous thing, if for original wrongdoings
                    the law does not allow suit to be brought by orphans after five years against
                    guardians who have not been released, but now in the twentieth year you are to
                    maintain an action against us, the children of your guardians, for matters
                    concerning which you did give them a release. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>But I hear that they are going to shun arguments based upon the facts of the case
                    and upon the laws, and are prepared to assert that a large estate was left them
                    and that they were defrauded of it; and that they will advance as a proof of
                    this the large sum asked as damages in their original suit, and they will wail
                    over their orphanhood, and will go through the guardianship accounts. These and
                    such-like points are the ones upon which they have fixed their trust, and by
                    which they hope to beguile you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>For my own part, I think that the large sum asked as damages in the suits then
                    brought is a stronger proof for us, that our father was the victim of a
                    malicious action, than for them, that they were being defrauded of a large
                    estate. For if he could prove his claims for eighty talents, no man in the world
                    would have accepted three talents in settlement; whereas anyone, being defendant
                    in a guardianship suit involving such large sums, would have paid three talents
                    to buy off the risk and the advantages with which at that time nature supplied
                    these men. They were orphans and young, and you were ignorant of their real
                    characters; and everyone says that in your courts these things have more weight
                    than strong arguments. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Moreover, I think I can also prove that you might
                    with good reason refuse to hear a word from them in regard to the
                        guardianship.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The following passage is
                        repeated almost verbatim from the preceding oration, <bibl n="Dem. 37.58"
                            >Dem. 37.58</bibl> ff.</note> For suppose one should grant that they
                    have suffered the greatest possible wrongs, and that everything which they will
                    now allege about these matters is true, this, at least, I presume you would all
                    admit: that it has happened to others ere now to have suffered many wrongs more
                    serious than pecuniary wrongs. For involuntary homicides, outrages on what is
                    sacred, and many other such crimes are committed; yet in all these cases the
                    fact they have yielded to persuasion and given a release is appointed for the
                    parties wronged as a limit and settlement of the dispute. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>And this just principle is so binding among all men, that, if one, having
                    convicted another of involuntary homicide, and clearly shown him to be polluted,
                    subsequently takes pity upon him, and releases him, he has no longer the right
                    to have the same person driven into exile. If, then, when life and all that is
                    most precious are at stake, a release has this power and validity, shall it be
                    without effect, when money is at stake, or claims of lesser importance? Surely
                    not. For the thing most to be feared is, not that I should fail to obtain
                    justice in your court, but that a just practice, established from the beginning
                    of time, should now be done away with. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>“They did not let our property,” they will perhaps say. No; for your uncle
                    Xenopeithes did not want it let, but, after Nicidas had denounced him for
                        this,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If a guardian did not fulfil the
                        duties imposed by his position, any citizen might charge him before the
                        archon with breach of trust.</note> induced the jurors to allow him to
                    administer it; and this everybody knows. “They robbed us of huge sums.” Well,
                    for this you have received from them the damages upon which you agreed; and, I
                    take it, you are not entitled to recover it again from me. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>But, that you may not think there is anything in all this—it is of course not
                    fair (how could it be?) after having come to a settlement with the guilty
                    parties, to accuse persons who know nothing about the case—none the less,
                    Xenopeithes and Nausimachus, if you have the idea that your claims are so
                    marvellously valid, pay back three talents, and go on with your suit. After
                    having exacted so large a sum for not pressing your charges, you are bound to
                    keep silent until you have paid this back—not to make the charges and keep the
                    money; that is the very extreme of unfair dealing. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>Now it is likely that they will talk about their trierarchies, and say that they
                    have expended their property upon you. That their statements will be false; that
                    they have squandered much of their property upon themselves, while the state has
                    received but a small share; and that they will deem it right to reap from you a
                    gratitude that is not deserved nor due—all this I shall pass over. I myself, men
                    of the jury, deem it right that somewhat of gratitude should be accorded by you
                    to all who bear the public burdens. But to whom should you accord most
                    gratitude? To those who, while in their actions doing what is of service to the
                    state, do not bring to pass what all would call a shame and a reproach. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>But those who while performing public services have squandered their own
                    property, bring the state into disrepute instead of rendering her service. For
                    no man ever yet blamed himself; on the contrary, he declares that the state has
                    taken away his property. But those who with ready hearts perform all the duties
                    you lay upon them, and who by the soberness of their lives in other matters
                    preserve their property, rightly have the better of the others in this respect,
                    that they both have been and will be of service, and also because this service
                    accrues to you from them without reproach. We shall be found to be men of this
                    type in our relations to you; as for them, I shall pass them by, that they may
                    not charge that I am speaking evil of them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>I should not be surprised if they try to shed tears and make themselves seem
                    worthy of pity. But I deem that, in view of this, you should all remember that
                    it is the part of shameless men, or rather of men with no sense of right, after
                    having squandered their fortune in gluttony and wine-bibbing along with
                    Aristocrates and Diognetus and others of that stamp in shameful and evil
                    fashion, to weep and wail now in the hope of getting what belongs to others. You
                    would have good cause to weep over your former doings. Yet it is not now a time
                    to weep, but to prove that you did not give a release, or that action may be had
                    afresh for the matters released, or that it is legal to bring an action after
                    the lapse of twenty years, when the law has fixed five years as the limit. These
                    are the questions which these gentlemen are to decide. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>If they are unable to prove these things, as they will be unable, we beg of you
                    all, men of the jury, not to deliver us up as prey to these men, nor to give yet
                    a fourth fortune to those who have mismanaged three others—that which they
                    received from their guardians without compulsion, that which they exacted by
                    compromising their suits, and that which the other day they took from Aesius by
                    a judgement—but to allow us, as is right, to retain what is our own. It is of
                    greater service to you in our hands than in theirs. And surely it is more just
                    that we should have what is our own than that they should have it.I do not know
                    what reason there is why I should say more<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        speaker closes with a brief paragraph which occurs also at the end of <bibl
                            n="Dem. 36">Dem. 36</bibl>.</note>; for I believe that nothing that I
                    have said has escaped you. Pour out the water.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
