<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - Galatians</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <editor role="editor">Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="NO">
                <biblStruct default="NO">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor role="editor">
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="NO">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>14-Oct-99</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <resp>markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial markup from flat ASCII text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>5/27/09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>RS</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: world.english.xml,v $
			Revision 1.2  2010-06-29 22:00:29  student
			fixing place tags - AD

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:10:56  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.3  2009/05/27 16:11:31  rsingh04
			added/fixed cvs log keyword
                </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="Galatians" type="book">
                <head>Paul's Letter to the Galatians</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Paul, an apostle (not from men, neither through man, but
through Jesus Christ, and God the Father, who raised him from the
dead),
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        and all the brothers who are with me, to the assemblies of
Galatia:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Grace to you and peace from God the Father, and our Lord
Jesus Christ,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        who gave himself for our sins, that he might
deliver us out of this present evil age, according to the will of our
God and Father --
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        to whom be the glory forever and ever. Amen.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        I marvel that you are so quickly deserting him who called you
in the grace of Christ to a different gospel;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        and there isn't
another gospel. Only there are some who trouble you, and want to
pervert the gospel of Christ.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        But even though we, or an angel
from heaven, should preach to you any gospel other than that which we
preached to you, let him be cursed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        As we have said before, so I
now say again: if any man preaches to you any gospel other than that
which you received, let him be cursed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        For am I now seeking the
favor of men, or of God? Or am I striving to please men? For if I were
still pleasing men, I wouldn't be a servant of Christ.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        But I
make known to you, brothers, concerning the gospel which was preached
by me, that it is not according to man.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        For neither did I
receive it from man, nor was I taught it, but it came to me through
revelation of Jesus Christ.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        For you have heard of my way of
living in time past in the Jews' religion, how that beyond measure I
persecuted the assembly of God, and ravaged it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        I advanced in
the Jews' religion beyond many of my own age among my countrymen, being
more exceedingly zealous for the traditions of my fathers.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        But
when it was the good pleasure of God, who separated me from my mother's
womb, and called me through his grace,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        to reveal his Son in me,
that I might preach him among the Gentiles, I didn't immediately confer
with flesh and blood,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        nor did I go up to Jerusalem to those who
were apostles before me, but I went away into Arabia. Then I returned
to Damascus.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Then after three years I went up to Jerusalem to
visit Peter, and stayed with him fifteen days.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        But of the other
apostles I saw no one, except James, the Lord's brother.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Now
about the things which I write to you, behold, before God, I'm not
lying.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Then I came to the regions of Syria and Cilicia.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        I
was still unknown by face to the assemblies of Judea which were in
Christ,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        but they only heard: "He who once persecuted us now
preaches the faith that he once tried to destroy."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        And they
glorified God in me.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then after a period of fourteen years I went up again to
Jerusalem with Barnabas, taking Titus also with me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        I went up by
revelation, and I laid before them the gospel which I preach among the
Gentiles, but privately before those who were respected, for fear that
I might be running, or had run, in vain.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        But not even Titus, who
was with me, being a Greek, was compelled to be circumcised.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        This
was because of the false brothers secretly brought in, who stole in to
spy out our liberty which we have in Christ Jesus, that they might
bring us into bondage;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        to whom we gave no place in the way of
subjection, not for an hour, that the truth of the gospel might
continue with you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        But from those who were reputed to be
important (whatever they were, it makes no difference to me; God
doesn't show partiality to man) -- they, I say, who were respected
imparted nothing to me,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        but to the contrary, when they saw that I
had been entrusted with the gospel for the uncircumcision, even as
Peter with the gospel for the circumcision
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        (for he who appointed
Peter to the apostleship of the circumcision appointed me also to the
Gentiles);
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        and when they perceived the grace that was given to
me, James and Cephas and John, they who were reputed to be pillars,
gave to me and Barnabas the right hand of fellowship, that we should go
to the Gentiles, and they to the circumcision.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        They only asked
us to remember the poor -- which very thing I was also zealous to do.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        But when Peter came to Antioch, I resisted him to the face,
because he stood condemned.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        For before some people came from
James, he ate with the Gentiles. But when they came, he drew back and
separated himself, fearing those who were of the circumcision.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        And the rest of the Jews joined him in his hypocrisy; so that even
Barnabas was carried away with their hypocrisy.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        But when I saw
that they didn't walk uprightly according to the truth of the gospel, I
said to Peter before them all, "If you, being a Jew, live as the
Gentiles do, and not as the Jews do, why do you compel the Gentiles to
live as the Jews do?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        "We, being Jews by nature, and not Gentile sinners,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        yet knowing that a man is not justified by the works of the law but
through the faith of Jesus Christ, even we believed in Christ Jesus,
that we might be justified by faith in Christ, and not by the works of
the law, because no flesh will be justified by the works of the law.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        But if, while we sought to be justified in Christ, we ourselves
also were found sinners, is Christ a servant of sin? Certainly not!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        For if I build up again those things which I destroyed, I prove
myself a law-breaker.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        For I, through the law, died to the law,
that I might live to God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        I have been crucified with Christ, and
it is no longer I that live, but Christ living in me. That life which I
now live in the flesh, I live by faith in the Son of God, who loved me,
and gave himself up for me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        I don't make void the grace of God.
For if righteousness is through the law, then Christ died for nothing!"
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Foolish Galatians, who has bewitched you not to obey the
truth, before whose eyes Jesus Christ was openly set forth among you as
crucified?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        I just want to learn this from you. Did you receive
the Spirit by the works of the law, or by hearing of faith?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Are
you so foolish? Having begun in the Spirit, are you now completed in
the flesh?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Did you suffer so many things in vain, if it is indeed
in vain?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        He therefore who supplies the Spirit to you, and works
miracles among you, does he do it by the works of the law, or by
hearing of faith?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Even as Abraham "believed God, and it was
counted to him for righteousness."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Know therefore that those who
are of faith, the same are sons of Abraham.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        The Scripture,
foreseeing that God would justify the Gentiles by faith, preached the
gospel beforehand to Abraham, saying, "In you all the nations will be
blessed."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        So then, those who are of faith are blessed with the
faithful Abraham.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        For as many as are of the works of the law are
under a curse. For it is written, "Cursed is everyone who doesn't
continue in all things that are written in the book of the law, to do
them."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Now that no man is justified by the law before God is
evident, for, "The righteous will live by faith."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        The law is not
of faith, but, "The man who does them will live by them."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Christ redeemed us from the curse of the law, having become a
curse for us. For it is written, "Cursed is everyone who hangs on a
tree,"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        that the blessing of Abraham might come on the Gentiles
through Christ Jesus; that we might receive the promise of the Spirit
through faith.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Brothers, I speak like men. Though it is only a
man's covenant, yet when it has been confirmed, no one makes it void,
or adds to it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Now the promises were spoken to Abraham and to
his seed. He doesn't say, "To seeds," as of many, but as of one, "To
your seed," which is Christ.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Now I say this. A covenant
confirmed beforehand by God in Christ, the law, which came four hundred
and thirty years after, does not annul, so as to make the promise of no
effect.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        For if the inheritance is of the law, it is no more of
promise; but God has granted it to Abraham by promise.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        What then is the law? It was added because of transgressions,
until the seed should come to whom the promise has been made. It was
ordained through angels by the hand of a mediator.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Now a
mediator is not between one, but God is one.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Is the law then
against the promises of God? Certainly not! For if there had been a law
given which could make alive, most assuredly righteousness would have
been of the law.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        But the Scriptures shut up all things under
sin, that the promise by faith in Jesus Christ might be given to those
who believe.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        But before faith came, we were kept in custody
under the law, shut up to the faith which should afterwards be
revealed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        So that the law has become our tutor to bring us to
Christ, that we might be justified by faith.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        But now that faith
is come, we are no longer under a tutor.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        For you are all sons of
God, through faith in Christ Jesus.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        For as many of you as were
baptized into Christ have put on Christ.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        There is neither Jew
nor Greek, there is neither slave nor free man, there is neither male
nor female; for you are all one in Christ Jesus.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        If you are
Christ's, then you are Abraham's seed and heirs according to promise.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        But I say that so long as the heir is a child, he is no
different from a bondservant, though he is lord of all;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        but is
under guardians and stewards until the day appointed by the father.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        So we also, when we were children, were held in bondage under the
elements of the world.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        But when the fullness of the time came,
God sent out his Son, born to a woman, born under the law,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        that
he might redeem those who were under the law, that we might receive the
adoption of sons.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        And because you are sons, God sent out the
Spirit of his Son into your hearts, crying, "Abba, Father!"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        So
you are no longer a bondservant, but a son; and if a son, then an heir
of God through Christ.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        However at that time, not knowing God, you
were in bondage to those who by nature are not gods.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        But now that
you have come to know God, or rather to be known by God, why do you
turn back again to the weak and miserable elements, to which you desire
to be in bondage all over again?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        You observe days, months,
seasons, and years.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        I am afraid for you, that I might have
wasted my labor for you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        I beg you, brothers, become as I am,
for I also have become as you are. You did me no wrong,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        but you
know that because of weakness of the flesh I preached the gospel to you
the first time.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        That which was a temptation to you in my flesh,
you didn't despise nor reject; but you received me as an angel of God,
even as Christ Jesus.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        What was the blessing you enjoyed? For I testify to you that,
if possible, you would have plucked out your eyes and given them to me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        So then, have I become your enemy by telling you the truth?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        They zealously seek you in no good way. No, they desire to
alienate you, that you may seek them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        But it is always good to
be zealous in a good cause, and not only when I am present with you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        My little children, of whom I am again in travail until
Christ is formed in you--
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        but I could wish to be present with
you now, and to change my tone, for I am perplexed about you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Tell me, you that desire to be under the law, don't you listen to the
law?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        For it is written that Abraham had two sons, one by the
handmaid, and one by the free woman.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        However, the son by the
handmaid was born according to the flesh, but the son by the free woman
was born through promise.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        These things contain an allegory, for
these are two covenants. One is from Mount Sinai, bearing children to
bondage, which is Hagar.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        For this Hagar is Mount Sinai in
Arabia, and answers to the Jerusalem that exists now, for she is in
bondage with her children.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        But the Jerusalem that is above is
free, which is the mother of us all.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        For it is written,
"Rejoice, you barren who don't bear.
   Break forth and shout, you that don't travail.
   For more are the children of the desolate than of her who has a
      husband."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        Now we, brothers, as Isaac was, are children of promise.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        But as then, he who was born according to the flesh persecuted
him who was born according to the Spirit, so also it is now.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="30"/>
                        However what does the Scripture say? "Throw out the handmaid and her
son, for the son of the handmaid will not inherit with the son of the
free woman."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="31"/>
                        So then, brothers, we are not children of a
handmaid, but of the free woman.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Stand firm therefore in the liberty by which Christ has made
us free, and don't be entangled again with a yoke of bondage.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Behold, I, Paul, tell you that if you receive circumcision, Christ will
profit you nothing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Yes, I testify again to every man who
receives circumcision, that he is a debtor to do the whole law.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        You are alienated from Christ, you who desire to be justified by the
law. You have fallen away from grace.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        For we, through the Spirit,
by faith wait for the hope of righteousness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        For in Christ Jesus
neither circumcision amounts to anything, nor uncircumcision, but faith
working through love.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        You were running well! Who interfered with
you that you should not obey the truth?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        This persuasion is not
from him who calls you.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        A little yeast grows through the whole
lump.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        I have confidence toward you in the Lord that you will
think no other way. But he who troubles you will bear his judgment,
whoever he is.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        But I, brothers, if I still preach circumcision, why am I
still persecuted? Then the stumbling-block of the cross has been
removed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        I wish that those who disturb you would cut themselves
off.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        For you, brothers, were called for freedom. Only don't use
your freedom for gain to the flesh, but through love be servants to one
another.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        For the whole law is fulfilled in one word, in this:
"You shall love your neighbor as yourself."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        But if you bite and
devour one another, be careful that you don't consume one another.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        But I say, walk by the Spirit, and you won't fulfill the lust of
the flesh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        For the flesh lusts against the Spirit, and the
Spirit against the flesh; and these are contrary to one other, that you
may not do the things that you desire.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        But if you are led by the
Spirit, you are not under the law.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Now the works of the flesh
are obvious, which are: adultery, sexual immorality, uncleanness,
lustfulness,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        idolatry, sorcery, hatred, strife, jealousies,
outbursts of anger, rivalries, divisions, heresies,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        envyings,
murders, drunkenness, orgies, and things like these; of which I
forewarn you, even as I also forewarned you, that those who practice
such things will not inherit the Kingdom of God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        But the fruit of the Spirit is love, joy, peace, patience,
kindness, goodness, faithfulness,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        gentleness, and self-control.
Against such things there is no law.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        Those who belong to Christ
have crucified the flesh with its passions and lusts.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        If we live
by the Spirit, let's also walk by the Spirit.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        Let's not become
conceited, provoking one another, and envying one another.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Brothers, even if a man is caught in some fault, you who are
spiritual must restore such a one in a spirit of gentleness; looking to
yourself so that you also aren't tempted.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Bear one another's
burdens, and so fulfill the law of Christ.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        For if a man thinks
himself to be something when he is nothing, he deceives himself.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        But let each man test his own work, and then he will take pride in
himself and not in his neighbor.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        For each man will bear his own
burden.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        But let him who is taught in the word share all good
things with him who teaches.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Don't be deceived. God is not
mocked, for whatever a man sows, that will he also reap.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        For he
who sows to his own flesh will from the flesh reap corruption. But he
who sows to the Spirit will from the Spirit reap eternal life.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Let us not be weary in doing good, for we will reap in due season, if
we don't give up.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        So then, as we have opportunity, let's do what
is good toward all men, and especially toward those who are of the
household of the faith.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        See with what large letters I write to you with my own hand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        As many as desire to look good in the flesh, they compel you to
be circumcised; only that they may not be persecuted for the cross of
Christ.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        For even they who receive circumcision don't keep the
law themselves, but they desire to have you circumcised, that they may
boast in your flesh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        But far be it from me to boast, except in
the cross of our Lord Jesus Christ, through which the world has been
crucified to me, and I to the world.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        For in Christ Jesus neither
is circumcision anything, nor uncircumcision, but a new creation.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        As many as walk by this rule, peace and mercy be on them, and on
God's Israel.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        From now on, let no one cause me any trouble, for
I bear the marks of the Lord Jesus branded on my body.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        The grace of our Lord Jesus Christ be with your spirit,
brothers. Amen.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
