<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Behalf of Euphiletus from Speeches (ENGLISH). Machine readable
					text</title>
				<author>Isaeus</author>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>


			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Isaeus</author>
						<title>Isaeus with an English translation by Edward Seymour Forster,
							M.A.</title>

						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
								Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1962</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="speech"/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English </language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek </language>
				<language ident="latin">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--
<change><date>March 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>September 1992</date><respStmt><name>D. Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed notes and regularized citations</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
			<change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>

			<div n="hypothesis" type="section">
				<p>(By Dionysius of <placeName key="tgn,7016142">Halicarnassus</placeName>) The Deme
					of Erchia is summoned before the court by one of its members who has been
					rejected by its vote and who pleads that he is being unjustly disfranchised. A
					law had been passed by the Athenians ordering that a revision should be made of
					the lists of citizens according to demes, and that anyone who was rejected by
					the votes of his fellow-demesmen should no longer enjoy the rights of
					citizenship; those, however, who were unjustly rejected had the right to appeal
					to the court by summoning the members of the deme, and, if they were again
					excluded, they were to be sold as slaves and their property confiscated. It is
					under this law that Euphiletus, having summoned the demesmen of Erchia on the
					ground that they had unjustly rejected him, instituted the present case. The
					facts have been already skilfully set forth and confirmed by witnesses. The
					following passage, in which the orator seeks to confirm the evidence, is
					composed, in my opinion, with consummate skill, but the reader must decide for
					himself whether my judgement of it is correct. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="1" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Gentlemen, you have heard not only us but also all
					our kinsmen give evidence that Euphiletus here is our brother. Next consider, in
					the first place, what motive our father could have for lying and for having
					adopted Euphiletus as his son, if he were not really so.</p>
			</div>
			<div n="2" type="section">
				<p>You will find that all those who do such things either have no legitimate
					children of their own or else are constrained by poverty to adopt aliens in
					order that they might receive some assistance from them, because they are
					indebted to them for their Athenian citizenship. Our father had neither of these
					motives, for in us he has two legitimate sons, so that he would never have
					adopted Euphiletus because he lacked an heir. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="3" type="section">
				<p>Nor again is he in need of any material support or comfort which Euphiletus could
					give him; for he is possessed of sufficient resources, and further evidence has
					been given you that he brought up Euphiletus and educated him from childhood and
					introduced him to the members of his ward—all of which represents a considerable
					outlay. So that it is unlikely, judges, that my father committed so wicked a
					crime from which he derived no advantage. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="4" type="section">
				<p>Again, as for myself, no one could imagine me to be so completely insane as to
					bear false witness in favor of Euphiletus with the result that I should have to
					share my patrimony with a larger number of heirs. For I should never hereafter
					be at liberty to plead that Euphiletus is not my brother; for none of you would
					listen to me for a moment, if, after now bearing witness that he is my brother
					and making myself liable to the penalties of the law,<note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true">i.e., as a perjurer.</note> I should hereafter openly
					contradict this assertion. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="5" type="section">
				<p>Thus, gentlemen, the probabilities are in favor of my having given true evidence,
					and the same is true of the other relatives. For observe, in the first place,
					that the husbands of our sisters would never have given false evidence in favor
					of Euphiletus; for his mother had become stepmother to our sisters, and it is
					customary for differences to exist between stepmothers and the daughters of a
					former marriage; so that, if their stepmother had borne Euphiletus to any man
					other than our father, our sisters would never have allowed their husbands to
					give evidence in his favor. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="6" type="section">
				<p>Again, our uncle, a relative on our mother's side and no kinsman of Euphiletus,
					would never have consented, judges, to give in favor of Euphiletus's mother
					evidence which was manifestly against our interests, if Euphiletus were an alien
					whom we are attempting to introduce into the family as our own brother.
					Furthermore, judges, how could any of you convict of perjury Demaratus here and
					Hegemon and Nicostratus, who, in the first place, will never be shown to have
					lent themselves to any base action, and who, secondly, being our kinsmen and
					knowing us all, have each borne witness to his own relationship to Euphiletus?
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="7" type="section">
				<p>I should like, then, to hear from the most respectable of our opponents, whether
					he can produce any other sources of evidence to prove his own Athenian
					citizenship than those which we are employing in support of Euphiletus. I do not
					think he could urge any plea except that his mother was a citizen and a married
					woman and his father a citizen, and he would produce his kinsmen to bear witness
					that he was speaking the truth. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="8" type="section">
				<p>Next, judges, if it were our opponents who were on their trial, they would demand
					that you should believe the evidence of their kinsmen rather than their
					accusers; and now, when we produce all these proofs, are they going to demand
					that you should believe what they say, rather than Euphiletus's father and me
					and my brother and the members of the ward and all our kindred? Furthermore, our
					opponents are acting out of personal spite without exposing themselves to any
					risk, while we are all rendering ourselves liable to the penalties of the law in
					giving evidence. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="9" type="section">
				<p>And in addition to the depositions, judges, in the first place, the mother of
					Euphiletus, who is admitted by our opponents to be a citizen, expressed before
					the arbitrators her willingness to swear an oath in the sanctuary of Delphinian
					Apollo that Euphiletus here was the issue of herself and our father; and who had
					better means of knowing than she? Secondly, judges, our father, who naturally is
					better able to recognize his own son than anyone else except his mother, was
					ready on the former occasion, and is ready now, to swear that Euphiletus here is
					his son by a mother who is a citizen and legally married. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="10" type="section">
				<p>In addition to this, judges, I was thirteen years old, as I have already said,
					when he was born, and I am ready to swear that Euphiletus here is my brother by
					the same father. You would be justified then, judges, in regarding our oaths as
					more worthy of credence than the statements of our opponents; for we, knowing
					all the facts, are willing to swear oaths concerning him, while they are
					repeating statements which they have heard from his enemies or uttering their
					own fabrications. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="11" type="section">
				<p>Furthermore, judges, we are producing before you our kinsmen, as we produced them
					before the arbitrators, as witnesses whom there is no reason for you to
					disbelieve; whereas our opponents, when Euphiletus brought his former case
					against the community of the deme and the demarch then in office, who has since
					died, though the case was before the arbitrator for two years, could never find
					a single piece of evidence to show that Euphiletus was the son of any father
					other than our father. In the opinion of the arbitrators this was the strongest
					indication that our opponents were lying, and they both gave their award against
					them. Please take the deposition about the former arbitration.<quote
						type="Deposition"><title>Deposition</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="12" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>You have now heard that my opponents lost their
					case before the arbitrators. I claim, judges, that, just as they would have
					declared, if the arbitrators had decided in their favor, that this was a strong
					proof that Euphiletus is not the son of Hegesippus, so now you should regard as
					equally strong evidence of the truth of our contention the fact that they were
					considered by the arbitrators to be doing Euphiletus an injury in having
					subsequently deleted his name, though he was a citizen and had before been
					legally enrolled. You have, I think, now heard enough, judges, to convince you
					that Euphiletus here is our brother and your fellow-citizen, and that he has
					been unjustly insulted by those who have conspired against him in the deme.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
