<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Lochites from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
      <change when="2016-01-26" who="TDBuck">epidoc and CTS</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg003.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Well then, that Lochites struck me and was the aggressor all who were present when the
          event occurred have testified to you. But this offense should not be regarded as similar
          to other breaches of the law, nor should the penalty imposed for injury to the person be
          no greater than that which is inflicted for cheating a man of money; for you know that
          one's person is of nearest concern to all men, and that it is for the protection of the
          person that we have established laws, that we fight for freedom, that we have our hearts
          set on the democratic form of government, and that all the activities of our lives are
          directed to this end. And so it is reasonable to expect you to punish with the greatest
          severity those who do wrong to you in respect to that which you prize most dearly. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> You will find that our legislators also have had the greatest concern for our persons.
          For, in the first place, it is for this one kind of misdemeanor only that they have
          instituted public and private actions that require no preliminary court-deposit,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The court-deposit refers to money deposited in court by a
            claimant and forfeited by him in case of failure to establish his claim.</note> with the
          intent that each of us, according to what may happen to be within his power and agreeable
          to his wish, may be able to exact punishment from those who wrong him. In the next place,
          in the case of other charges, the culprit may be prosecuted by the injured party only; but
          where assault and battery is involved, as the public interest is affected, any citizen who
          so desires may give notice of a public suit to the Thesmothetes<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The Thesmothetes were the six junior archons. They had jurisdiction over many
            offenses against the state.</note> and appear before your court. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And our lawgivers regarded the giving of blows as an offense of such gravity that even
          for abusive language they made a law to the effect that those who used any of the
          forbidden opprobrious terms should pay a fine of five hundred drachmas. And yet how severe
          should the penalty be on behalf of those who have actually suffered bodily injury, when
          you show yourselves so angry for the protection of those who have merely suffered verbal
          injury? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It would be astonishing if, while you judge to be worthy of death those who were guilty
          of battery under the oligarchy, you shall allow to go unpunished those who, under the
          democracy, are guilty of the same practices. And yet the latter would justly meet with a
          more severe punishment; for they reveal more conspicuously their real baseness. This is
          what I mean: if anyone has the effrontery to transgress the law now, when it is not
          permissible, what would he have done, I ask you, when the government in power actually was
          grateful to such malefactors? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It may be that Lochites will attempt to belittle the importance of the affair, and
          ridiculing my accusation will say that I suffered no injury from his blows and that I am
          unduly exaggerating the gravity of what occurred. My reply to this is, that if no assault
          and battery had been connected with the affair, I should never have come before you; but
          as it is, it is not because of the mere injury inflicted by his blows that I am seeking
          satisfaction from him, but for the humiliation and the indignity; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and it is that sort of thing which free men should especially resent and for which they
          should obtain the greatest requital. I observe that you, when you find anyone guilty of
          the robbery of a temple or of theft, do not assess the fine according to the value of what
          is stolen, but that you condemn all alike to death, and that you consider it just that
          those who attempt to commit the same crimes should pay the same penalty.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For the same argument cf. <bibl n="Lyc. 1.65">Lyc.
              1.65-66</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>You should, therefore, be of the same mind with respect to those who commit battery, and
          not consider whether they did not maul their victims thoroughly, but whether they
          transgressed the law, and you should punish them, not merely for the chance outcome of the
          attack, but for their character as a whole, reflecting that often ere now petty causes
          have been responsible for great evils, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and that, because there are persons who have the effrontery to beat others, there have
          been cases where men have become so enraged that wounds, death, exile, and the greatest
          calamities have resulted. That no one of these consequences happened in my case is not due
          to the defendant; on the contrary, so far as he is concerned they have all taken place,
          and it was only by the grace of fortune and my character that no irreparable harm has been
          done. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I think that you would be as indignant as the circumstances merit if you should reflect
          how much more reprehensible this misdemeanor is than any others. For you will find that
          while the other unjust acts impair life only partially, malicious assault vitiates all our
          concerns, since it has destroyed many households and rendered desolate many cities. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet why need I waste time in speaking of the calamities of the other states? For we
          ourselves have twice seen the democracy overthrown<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In <date
              when="-0411">411 B.C.</date>, by the regime of the Four Hundred, and in <date
              when="-0404">404 B.C.</date> when the Spartans, after the capture of Athens,
            established the Thirty Tyrants in power.</note> and twice we have been deprived of
          freedom, not by those who were guilty of other crimes, but by persons who contemned the
          laws and were willing to be slaves of the enemy while wantonly outraging their
          fellow-citizens. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Lochites is one of these persons. For even though he was too young to have belonged to
          the oligarchy established at that time, yet his character at any rate is in harmony with
          their regime. For it was men of like disposition who betrayed our power to the enemy,
          razed the walls of the fatherland, and put to death without a trial fifteen hundred
            citizens.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 7.67">Isoc. 7.67</bibl>,
            where the same number of victims is given; cf. also <bibl n="Isoc. 4.113">Isoc.
              4.113</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> We may reasonably expect that you, remembering the past, will punish, not only those who
          then did us harm, but also those who wish now to bring our city into the same condition as
          then; and you should punish potential criminals with greater severity than the malefactors
          of the past in so far as it is better to find how to avert future evils than to exact the
          penalty for past misdeeds. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Do not wait for the time when these enemies shall unite, seize an opportune moment, and
          bring ruin upon the whole city, but whenever on any pretext they are delivered into your
          hands, punish them, thinking it a stroke of luck when you catch a man who in petty
          derelictions reveals his complete depravity. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It would indeed have been best, if only some distinguishing mark were borne by men of
          base nature,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">So also <bibl n="Eur. Med. 516-519">Eur. Med.
              516-519</bibl>: <quote><l>O Zeus, ah wherefore hast thou given to men</l><l>Plain
                signs for gold which is but counterfeit,</l><l>But no assay-mark nature-graven
                shows</l><l>On man's form, to discern the base withal.</l></quote>(Translation by
            Way in L.C.L.)</note> that we might punish them before any fellow-citizen has been
          injured by them. But since it is impossible to perceive who such men are before a victim
          has suffered at their hands, at any rate as soon as their character is recognized, it is
          the duty of all men to hate them and to regard them as enemies of all mankind. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Remember, too, that while the poor have no share in the danger of loss of property, yet
          fear of injury to our persons is common to all alike; in consequence, whenever you punish
          thieves and cheats you benefit only the rich, but whenever you chastise those who commit
          mayhem, you give aid to yourselves. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>You should therefore treat trials such as this as of the highest importance; and while in
          suits involving private contracts you should assess the plaintiff's damages at only what
          it is fitting that he should receive, when the case is assault and battery the defendant
          should be required to pay so large a sum that he will in future refrain from his present
          unbridled wantonness. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If, then, you deprive of their property those who conduct themselves with wanton violence
          toward their fellow-citizens and regard no fine as severe enough to punish those who do
          injury to the persons of others and have to pay the penalty with their money, you will
          then have discharged in full measure the duty of conscientious judges. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Indeed in the present case you will thus render the correct judgement, will cause our
          other citizens to be more decorous in conduct, and will make your own lives more secure.
          And it is the part of intelligent judges, while casting their votes for justice in causes
          not their own, at the same time to safeguard their own interests also. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Let no one of you think, just because he observes that I am a poor man and a man of the
          people, that the amount I claim should be reduced. For it is unjust that you should reckon
          the indemnification to be given to plaintiffs who are obscure as of less importance than
          that which men of distinction are to receive, and that the poor be thought inferior to the
          rich. For you would be lowering your own civic status if you should reach any such
          decisions where the many are concerned. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Besides, it would be a most shocking state of affairs if in a democratic state we should
          not all enjoy equal rights; and if, while judging ourselves worthy of holding office, yet
          we deprive ourselves of our legal rights; and if in battle we should all be willing to die
          for our democratic form of government and yet, in our votes as judges, especially favor
          men of property. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>No, if you will be advised by me, you will not assume that position toward your own
          selves. You will not teach the young men to have contempt for the mass of our citizens,
          nor consider that trials of this character are of no concern to you; on the contrary, each
          one of you will cast his ballot as if he were judging his own case. In truth, those who
          dare to transgress the law that protects your persons do injury to all alike. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And so, if you are wise, exhort one another, and reveal to Lochites your own wrath, for
          you know that all individuals of his kind despise the established laws, but regard as law
          the decisions rendered here. I have spoken as well as I could about the matter at issue;
          if anyone present has anything to say on my behalf, let him mount the platform and address
          you.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
