<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Zeus the Tragedian</title>
 <author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Emily James Smith</editor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
 <respStmt>
  <persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
 <date type="release" when="2023-08-11">Perseus 5.0</date>
 <idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5.xml</idno>
 <availability>
 <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
 </availability>
</publicationStmt><sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr>
<title xml:lang="eng">Selections from Lucian</title>
  <editor role="translator">Emily James Smith</editor>
  <author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
  <imprint>
   <publisher>Harper and Brothers</publisher>
	<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
	<date>1892</date>
  </imprint>
 </monogr>
  <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/hvd.hw3j0n?urlappend=%3Bseq=31">The Hathi Trust</ref>
 </biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
 <p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
 <refsDecl n="CTS">
  <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
   replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
   <p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
  </cRefPattern>
 </refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change who="Gregory Crane" when="2023-08-11">Created initial file in repository. The major task was adding section breaks. There are missing sections because the translator silently skipped passages that did not conform with contemporary standards of propiety.</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="eng">
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5" xml:lang="eng">
<head>ZEUS THE TRAGEDIAN.</head>
<head><label>ZEUS</label>. <label>HERA</label>. <label>ATHENE</label>. <label>APHRODITE</label>. <label>CHARACTERS</label>. <label>APOLLO</label>. <label>HERMES</label>. <label>HERAKLES</label>. <label>KOLOSSOS</label>. <label>MOMOS</label>. <label>HERMAGORAS</label>. <label>TIMOKLES</label>. <label>DAMIS.</label>. <label>POSEIDON</label>.</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="1"><p>








<pb n="p.15"/>


<label>Hermes</label>
<l>O Zeus, why wand'rest, self-communing, lone,</l>
<l>And sicklied o'er with this pale student's hue?</l>
<l>Make me the partner of thy sorrow's load,</l>
<l>Nor scorn the prattle of a lowly friend.</l>
</p>


<p><label>Athene</label>
<l>Yea, sire, great Kronides, our father and highest of rulers,</l>
<l>I, the clear-eyed and divine, the Trito-born, clasp thee imploring.</l>
<l>Hide not thy grief in thine heart. Tell it forth that thy children may know it.</l>
<l>What biting care dost thou hold in thy brain and thy bosom? What anguish</l>
<l>Wrings that deep groan from thy soul and yellows thy fair, ruddy color?</l>
</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label>

<l>There no woe that happens, sooth to tell,</l>
<l>No pain, no chance-born theme of tragedy,</l>
<l>Of which the godhead beareth not the load.</l>
</p>


<p><label>Athene</label>
<l>Great heav'n! What prologue doth begin his tale.</l>


<pb n="p.16"/></p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> O earthy offspring of the earth, fell race,
<l>And thou, Prometheus, what woe hast thou wrought!</l>
</p>


<p><label>Athene</label>
<l>What is 't? We are the band of thine own kin.</l>
</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label>
<l>Thunderbolt, sounding afar, how shall thy hurtling crash save me?</l>
</p>


<p><label>Hera</label> Keep your temper, Zeus, since I cannot
answer you in comedy metre as the others do,
nor have I swallowed Euripides whole so as to
take my part in the drama when you give me the
cue. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="2">
<p>Do you imagine that I don't know the
cause of your distress?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> "Thou dost not know, els hadst thou
shrieked aloud."</p>


<p><label>Hera</label> I know that the sum and substance of
your trouble comes from love-making. Of course,
I do not shriek, for I am used to this insulting
treatment at your hands. Undoubtedly you have
come upon some Danae or Semele or Europa
again, and are attacked with love, and so you are
scheming to become a bull or a satyr, or to pour
down as a shower of golden rain through the roof
into your lady-love's lap. These groans, these
tears, this pallor are symptoms of the lover and
nobody else.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="3">
<p><label>Zeus</label> Poor, simple thing, do you think, then,
that my present affairs have to do with love-making and such-like child's play?


<pb n="p.17"/>
</p>


<p><label>Hera</label> Being Zeus, you are disturbed by nothing else, I know.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> O Hera, things divine are in extremity.
As the saying is, it is touch and go with us
whether we are still to be honored and to receive
the gifts that are offered up on earth, or whether
we are to be disregarded altogether and held utterly insignificant.</p>


<p><label>Hera</label> Surely the earth has not produced another race of giants? Or have the Titans broken
their bonds and overpowered their guard, and
taken up arms against us again?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> <l>Take heart. Beneath the earth all things
are well.</l></p>


<p><label>Hera</label> Then what could happen to frighten us?
If you have no anxiety of that kind I do not
see why you have favored us with this little dramatic exhibition.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="4">

<p><label>Zeus</label> Hera, Timokles the Stoic and Damis the
Epicurean held a discussion yesterday on the
doctrine of providence. I do not know how the
question arose, but the audience was large and
respectable, and that, to my mind, was the most
annoying feature of the affair. Damis denied that
the gods exist or have any hand whatever in the
ordering and administration of the world. But
the worthy Timokles strove to defend our side,
and just then a crowd of people streamed in, so
that the meeting came to no decision, but dissolved,



<pb n="p.18"/>



 agreeing to consider the rest of the question later. And now they are all on tiptoe with
eagerness to hear which of the orators will prevail
and be adjudged to set forth the truer cause.
Do you see the danger and the strait we are in,
since our cause stands or falls with a single man?
One of two things will happen: either we shall
be deemed mere names, and so of course disregarded, or else, if Timokles prove the better
speaker, we shall be honored as heretofore.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="5">

<p><label>Hera</label> Really this is very dreadful, and you
were not so far wrong, Zeus, in addressing us in
tragic vein.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> And yet you thought it was some Danae
or Antiope that I was thinking about in such distress. Well, Hermes and Hera and Athene, what
would be best? Take your turns in helping me
to discover.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> I for my part say that an assembly
ought to be called for open discussion.</p>


<p><label>Hera</label> I think precisely as he does.</p>


<p><label>Athene</label> But it strikes me just the other way,
father. I do not think you ought to involve all
heaven in your embarrassment, or show your own
alarm at the affair; but make your arrangements
privately so that Timokles may triumph and
Damis be laughed out of court.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> But, Zeus, this course will not be unperceived, for the philosophers will hold their


<pb n="p.19"/>

tournament in public, and you will be accused of
Caesarism if you do not let all have a voice in
matters so weighty and common to all.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="6">

<p><label>Zeus</label> Very well, then. Summon them at once
and let all appear. For you are right.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Halloo, gods! Come to the assembly!
Do not loiter Gather, all of you! Come! We
are going to discuss great things!</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Hermes, is that bare, unadorned, prosaic
style of announcement the proper thing, particularly when the greatest matters are in question?</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Why, what do you think more proper,
Zeus?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> What do I think more proper? I say
you ought to make your summons impressive by
means of some sort of rhythm, and a sonorous,
poetic form, to bring them the more readily.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Yes; but such things belong to versewriters and declaimers, Zeus, and I am the worst
poet imaginable. I should certainly ruin my summons by having too many feet in it or too few,
and they would laugh at the illiteracy of my composition. I see that even Apollo's verses in his
oracles are sometimes jeered at, though his prophecies are generally very obscure, so that those
who receive them have not much leisure to criticize the versification.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Well, then, string a lot of Homer's verses


<pb n="p.20"/>



together in your summons, and convene us as he
used. Of course you remember them.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> I can't say that I have them very pat.
However, I will try :

<l>Gods and goddesses all, let none fail to answer my summons.</l>
<l>Let not a single nymph or river-god, save only Ocean,</l>
<l>Tarry; but haste ye all to the council that Jove hath appointed.</l>
<l>All are bidden who feast at the hecatomb's glorious banquet,</l>
<l>All, e'en of low degree, or lowest; yea, even the nameless,</l>
<l>Seeing they too have a seat by the altars smoking with victims.</l>

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="7">

<p><label>Zeus</label> Well done, Hermes. You could not have
summoned them better, and the proof is that they
are gathering already. So, receive them and seat
them according to the value of each in material
or workmanship; that is to say, the golden in the
seats of honor, next to these the silver ones, then
those of ivory, then those of bronze or stone; and
in this class preference is to be given to the works
of Pheidias and Alkamenes and Myron and Euphranor and artists of their rank. But thrust
these vulgar ones, the work of bunglers, together
on one side, and let them confine themselves to
silently making a quorum.</p>


<pb n="p.21"/>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Very well. They shall take their seats
in proper order. But I ought to know this: if
one of them is of gold or of great weight but not
well executed-in fact actually amateur's work
and out of drawing—is he to take his seat in front
of the bronzes of Myron and Polykleitos, and the
marbles of Pheidias and Alkamenes, or is preference to be given to workmanship?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> It ought to be; but, nevertheless, the gold
must take precedence.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> I see. Your orders are that they shall
take their seats in order of wealth rather than in
order of merit, in proportion to their taxable
property.
Come to the front seats, then, you golden ones!

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="8">
<p>
It looks as though the barbarians would have the
front seats to themselves. The Greeks, at any
rate, are, as you see, graceful and goodly of aspect and shaped with skill, but they are all alike,
of wood or stone, except the very most valuable
of them, and they are ivory with something of
golden decoration. But they are merely colored and plated with it, and within they, too,
are wooden, and give shelter to whole droves of
mice who inhabit them. But Bendis here, and
Anoubis and Attis beside him, and Mithres and
Men are of solid gold, heavy, and really valuable.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="9">
<p><label>Poseidon</label> Now, Hermes, is this just, to let this


<pb n="p.22"/>



dog-headed Egyptian take precedence of me,
Poseidon?</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> No, Earthshaker; but, you see, Lysippos made you of bronze and poor because the
Corinthians had no gold at the time, and Anoubis
is whole mines richer than you. So you must e'en
put up with being shoved aside, and not lose your
temper if a god with such a great golden muzzle
as his has been preferred to you.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="10">
<p><label>Aphrodite</label> Take me, too, then, Hermes, and
place me somewhere in the front rows, for I am
golden.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Not as far as I can see, Aphrodite.
Unless I am exceedingly blear-eyed, you were
quarried out of the white stone of Pentele, and
then, at the good pleasure of Praxiteles, you became Aphrodite and were handed over to the
Knidians.</p>


<p><label>Aphrodite</label> But I will furnish you a trustworthy
referee in Homer, who, up and down in his poetry,
declares me "golden Aphrodite."</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Oh, Homer says that Apollo, too, is full
of gold and rich, but now you will see him sitting
somewhere in the worst seats, for the robbers
took his crown and stripped the pegs from his
lyre. So you may congratulate yourself that you
are not placed down among the servants.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="11">

<p><label>Kolossos</label> I imagine that no one will venture to
vie with me, for I am Helios, and as you see for



<pb n="p.23"/>


size. For if the Rhodians had not seen fit to
make me abnormally large they could have made
sixteen golden gods for the same money. So I
ought to be considered proportionately rich. And
I exhibit art, too, and accurate workmanship, in
spite of my great stature.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> What is to be done, Zeus? This case,
too, is certainly a hard one to decide, for if I regard his material, he is bronze; but if I compute
how much money it cost to forge him, he ranks
above the highest class.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Why need he be here, anyhow, to comment on the smallness of other people and give
trouble about his seat?


However, O mightiest of the Rhodians, even
you take rank never so much above the golden
gods, how could you take your seat before them
unless you ask them all to get up? If you were
to sit down you would fill the whole Pnyx. So
you would do better to stand during the meeting
and bend over the assembly.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="12">
<p><label>Hermes</label> Here is another nice point to decide
between Dionysos here and Herakles. Both are
bronze; their workmanship is the same, for both
are by Lysippos; and, most vital point of all, they
are equals by birth, being alike sons of Zeus.
Which of them is to have precedence? They
are wrangling about it, as you see.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> We are wasting time, Hermes. We should


<pb n="p.24"/>



have got to business long ago. Let them sit down
now anyhow, each where he likes. By-and-by we
will hold an assembly to debate these questions,
and then I shall know how their ranks ought to
be assigned.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="13">
<p><label>Hermes</label> Good heavens, what a din they make,
crying out, in plain every-day language, "Rations!" and "Where is the nectar?" and "The
ambrosia is giving out!" and "Where are the
hecatombs?" and "The sacrifices are common
property!"</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Call them to order, Hermes. Make them
stop this nonsense and hear why they were convened.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> But, Zeus, they do not all understand
Greek, and I am no polyglot to deliver an announcement to Scythians and Persians and Thracians and Celts all at once. I think I should do
best to enjoin silence by dumb show.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Very well.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="14">
<p><label>Hermes</label> There! Behold them reduced to the
silence of the sophists. Now is your time to address them. See, they are looking towards you
already, awaiting your speech.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Hermes, you are my son, and I don't
mind telling you just how I feel. You know what
aplomb and magniloquence I have always shown
in our assemblies?</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Indeed I do. I was always frightened


<pb n="p.25"/>


when I heard you speak, particularly when you
would threaten to let down that golden rope and
drag from their foundations the earth and the sea
and the gods with them.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> But this time, my child, whether it is the
greatness of the impending dangers or of the audience-for the meeting is well attended, as you
see my presence of mind has utterly deserted
me, and I am trembling with nervousness and my
tongue seems tied. And, most absurd of all, I
have forgotten the opening of my speech, which
I had prepared with a view to making as agreeable a first impression as possible.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> You have spoiled everything. Your
silence is making them suspicious already, and
the more you delay the more overwhelmingly bad
news do they expect.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Do you think, then, that I might begin
to recite to them that introduction of Homer's?</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> What one?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> "Hearken now, ye gods, and every goddess, hearken."</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Stuff! You have recited those opening lines often enough in your cups already. But,
if you like, give up this tiresome business of poetry, and piece together any you choose of Demosthenes's orations against Philip, altering them a
little. That is the way most speaking is done
now, anyhow.


<pb n="p.26"/></p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> That is a good idea-a sort of abridged
rhetoric or oratory made easy for the embarrassed.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="15">

<p><label>Hermes</label> Well, are you never going to begin?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> I imagine, men of Olympus, that you
would gladly give considerable sums to obtain
an idea of what this matter may be with reference to which you are now summoned. This
being the case, you will do well to lend me your
ears with all eagerness. Now the present crisis,
deities, wellnigh declares, with audible voice, that
we must give all our energies to considering the
matters before us, but, as a matter of fact, we
seem to me to treat them with negligence. But
I should like-my Demosthenes fails me—to explain to you why I was so much disturbed as to
call an assembly. Yesterday, as you are aware,
Mnesitheos, the ship-master, offered a sacrifice
of thanksgiving for his ship that was almost lost
off Kaphereus, and we feasted in the Peiraieusas many of us, that is, as Mnesitheos had invited
to the banquet. After the libations you dispersed
in different directions, pursuing your own devices,
while I, seeing that it was not yet late, went up to
the city to stroll about at dusk in the Kerameikos,
pondering on the meanness of Mnesitheos. For
he offered up, by way of feast to sixteen gods,
one cock, aged and asthmatic at that, and four
grains of frankincense, pretty well decayed, so


<pb n="p.27"/>


that it went out immediately on the embers, and
not enough fragrance came out of the smoke to
tickle the tip of your nose. And yet when his
ship was actually going on the rocks and within.
the reef he promised whole hecatombs.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="16">
<p>
Well, revolving this in my mind, I turned up
near the Painted Porch, and there I saw a great
crowd of men gathered, some inside the porch
itself, but most of them in the open air, and some
were shouting, stretched out on the benches. I
guessed what was the case: that they were philosophers of the eristic order, and I determined
to stand by and listen to what they might say. I
happened to have a cloud wrapped round me—a
thick one-so I took on an exterior of their sort,
drew forth my beard, and presented no bad imitation of a philosopher. And so I elbowed my
way through the crowd and got inside without
being recognized, and I found a violent controversy going on between that fox Damis the Epicurean and Timokles the Stoic, the best of men.
Timokles was in a perspiration, and had lost his
voice already with screaming, and Damis was exasperating him still further by sardonic mockery.
Now, if you will believe it, their whole discussion was about us. Damis (confound him) declared that we have no forethought for men or
guardianship of their affairs, asserting that we do
not exist at all, for this was plainly the purport


<pb n="p.28"/>



of his speech. And some there were who applauded him. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="17">
<p>
But the other, Timokles, took our
side and fought for us, and excited himself, and
did his best for us, praising our watchful care,
and rehearsing how all things are arranged and
reduced to regularity and order by us. He, too,
had some applause, but he had already been
speaking too long and his utterance was labored,
so that the crowd looked away from him to Damis. Seeing what was at stake, I bade the night
descend and break up the meeting, and so they
went their ways, agreeing to examine the question
completely the next day. I followed along with
the crowd, and heard them praising Damis's arguments among themselves as they walked home,
and already decidedly siding with him. But there
were some, too, who did not think it right to decide beforehand between the rivals, but to wait
and see what Timokles would say on the morrow.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="18">
<p>

These, deities, are my reasons for summoning
you; no slight ones, if you consider that all our
honor, revenue, and prestige come from men.
And if they should be persuaded either that we
do not exist at all or that we have no forethought
for them, we shall have no more sacrifices and
gifts and honor from earth, and we shall sit idly
in heaven oppressed by hunger when we are deprived of those feasts and national holidays and
games and sacrifices and vigils and processions.


<pb n="p.29"/>


In such a crisis we all ought certainly to devise
some means of safety by which Timokles may be
victorious and be held to make the truer argument, and Damis may be jeered by the audience.
For I myself have small confidence that Timokles
will win by his own exertions unless he also receives assistance from us. Accordingly, Hermes,
announce in due form that remarks are in order.</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> Hear ye, silence! Make no disturbance! Who wishes to speak, of those full-grown
divinities whose right it is?
What is this? Does no one rise? They are all
silent, overwhelmed by the importance of the news.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="19">

<p><label>Momos</label>
<l>Now I would that you all might turn
to earth and to water!</l>
But for my part, Zeus, if I am at liberty to speak
with perfect freedom, I have a good many things
to say.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Speak, Momos, without restraint. I am
sure your frankness will be for our good.</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> Hear, then, deities, what at any rate
I think in my heart of hearts, as they say. You
must know that I have been pretty confidently
expecting that our affairs would come to as bad a
pass as this, and that numbers of sophists like
these would spring up against us, finding grounds
for their temerity in our own conduct. By heaven, we have no right to be angry with Epicurus
or with his disciples and successors if they have


<pb n="p.30"/>



conceived these notions about us. What, then,
could you ask them to think when they see such
anarchy in human life, the best of them neglected,
perishing utterly in poverty and disease and slavery, while worthless blackguards are preferred
to them in honor, and surpass them in riches, and
are placed in authority over their betters; when
they see that sacrilege is not punished but escapes
unnoticed, while sometimes innocent men are impaled on stakes and beaten to death? It is only
natural, then, that when they see such things they
decide as they do, that we have no existence at
all,</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="20">
<p> particularly when they hear the oracles saying
that if a certain man crosses the Halys he will
overthrow a great kingdom, without specifying
whether it will be his own kingdom or his enemy's. And then again the oracle says:
<l>Salamis, dear to the gods, thou shalt slay children of women.</l>

But I imagine both the Persians and the Greeks
were children of women.
And then when they hear from the minstrels
how we fall in love, and receive wounds, and get
put in chains and made servants, and are divided
against ourselves, and have a myriad of troubles,
all the time claiming to be blessed and indestructible, have they not a perfect right to jeer at
us and make us of no account? But we get angry if certain persons who are human beings, and


<pb n="p.31"/>



not altogether devoid of wits, sift these matters
and deny our providence, whereas we ought to
felicitate ourselves if any still continue to sacrifice to sinners like us.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="21">
<p>
And now, Zeus, give me an honest answer to a
question-for we are alone, and there is no mortal
present in the assembly, except Herakles and Dionysos and Ganymedes and Asklepios, who have
somehow got naturalized among us—have you ever
paid enough attention to the people on earth to
distinguish the bad ones from the good? You
cannot say you have. Certainly, unless Theseus
on his
way from Troizen to Athens had incidentally exterminated those malefactors, Skeiron and
the Pine-Bender and Kerkyon and the others
might have continued to live riotously by the
slaughter of wayfarers, as far as you and your
providence are concerned. And if Eurystheus,
living in the earliest times and full of forethought,
had not been moved by philanthropy to inquire
into every one's affairs, and had not sent forth his
servant here, an active man and keen for labors,
you, Zeus, would have given small thought to the
Hydra and the Stymphalian birds and the Thrakian horses and the drunken insolence of the
Kentaurs. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="22">
<p>On the contrary, if I must speak
candidly, we sit and watch for just one thing,
whether haply some one is sacrificing and sending up the savor of burnt-offerings beside the


<pb n="p.32"/>



altars. Everything else drifts down stream as
chance carries it. Accordingly, our present experience is natural, and what we have yet in store
for us, too, when little by little mortals lift their
heads and find that it does them no good to offer
us sacrifices and pageants. Then you will soon
see your Epicurus and your Metrodoros and
your Damis jeering, and the speakers on our side
overcome and stopped by them. Not that Momos has much to lose if he falls into disrepute,
for I was never one of the reputable ones, even
while you were still prosperous and had a monopoly of the sacrifices.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="23">
<p><label>Zeus</label> Do not mind this fellow's babble, deities,
for he was always an ill-conditioned fault-finder.
And, besides, in the words of the great Demosthenes, it is easy to criticise and blame and find
fault-any one who likes can do that; but it is
the gift of a truly sagacious counsellor to point
out how the state of things may be improved,
and this I am sure the rest of you will do, even if
Momos holds his tongue.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="24">
<p><label>Poseidon</label> I, as you know, am generally under
water, and dwell by myself in the deep sea, doing
my best to rescue mariners and forward ships
and temper the winds. Nevertheless, I have a
stake in things up here, too, and it is my opinion
that this Damis ought to be disposed of before
he comes to the contest, either by lightning or


<pb n="p.33"/>


some other means, lest his speech prevail-for
you say, Zeus, that he is a plausible sort of fellow.
In that way we shall show them at the same time
that we take vengeance on people who say such
things against us.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="25">
<p><label>Zeus</label> Are you joking, Poseidon, or have you
clean forgotten that we have nothing to do with
such matters, but that the Fates weave his death
for each man—for one by lightning, for another
by the sword, for a third by fever or consumption? Do you suppose that if this were under
my control I would have let those temple-robbers
go forth unstricken from Pisa the other day, when
they had cut off two locks of my hair weighing
six pounds each? Or would you yourself have
ignored the fisherman from Oreos who carried off
your trident at Geraistos? Above all, we should
seem to have lost self-control in our distress and
to be afraid of Damis's arguments, and therefore
to be getting rid of the man rather than to endure to confront him with Timokles. Should we
not in this way seem to be winning our case
merely by default ?</p>


<p><label>Poseidon</label> Now I thought I had hit on a short
cut to victory.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Nonsense, Poseidon. Your argument is
worthy of one of your own tunny-fish, positively dense. Snatch away the opponent, forsooth, so that he may die unconquered and



<pb n="p.34"/>



leave his arguments behind without attack or
exposure!</p>


<p><label>Poseidon</label> Very well, think of something better
yourselves, if you dismiss my idea with a joke
about the tunnies.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="26">
<p><label>Apollo</label> If it were permitted by law to a beardless youth like me to address the meeting, I could,
perhaps, make a useful contribution to the discussion.</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> In the first place, Apollo, the discussion has to do with such great questions that the
right of speech does not go by years, but is common to all. For it would be a nice thing if, when
we are in the extremest danger, we should quibble about a legal qualification. But, anyhow, you
are already decidedly eligible as a speaker in the
eye of the law, for you emerged long ago from
among the youths; you have been inscribed on
the rolls of the twelve, and you were almost a
member of the council in Kronos's day. So don't
try your youthful airs on us, but speak up boldly
and tell us your views. And do not let the fact
that you are a beardless orator embarrass you,
particularly when you have your son Asklepios
here with a beard to his waist. Moreover, it
would be peculiarly fitting for you to show your
wisdom now of all occasions, unless you have sat
philosophizing with the Muses on Helikon to no
purpose.


<pb n="p.35"/></p>

<p><label>Apollo</label> It is not your business, however, Momos, to give these permissions, but Zeus's, and if
he bids me I might perhaps say something worthy
of the Muses and my exercises on Helikon.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Speak, my child; I give you leave.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="27">
<p><label>Apollo</label> This Timokles is a worthy man and
pious, and perfectly conversant with the methods
of the Stoics, so that he teaches many young men
and levies no small fee therefor.
For he is very
convincing when he discourses with his pupils in
private; but he lacks nerve for public speaking,
and his utterance is untrained-half Greek and
half barbarian. On this account he always raises
a laugh in company, for he does not speak connectedly, but stammers and becomes confused,
most of all when, in spite of this weakness, he
wishes to exhibit elegance of style. His mind is
surpassingly sharp and quick-so they say who
are best informed in the doctrines of the Stoicsbut by his feebleness in speaking and expounding
he spoils his subject-matter and confuses it, and
fails to make his points clear, but rather lays down
enigmatical propositions; and when it is his turn
to answer expresses himself more darkly still.
So he is misunderstood and laughed at. Now
I think one should speak plainly, and take care
above everything that his hearers understand him.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="28">
<p><label>Momos</label> What you say in praise of plain-speaking, Apollo, is very just, though you do not practice


<pb n="p.36"/>



 it very much yourself in your oracles. They
are ambiguous and enigmatical, and in a non-commital way throw most things on disputed ground,
so that the hearers need another Apollo to tell
them what you mean. But what is your advice
in this case? How is Timokles's weakness in argument to be cured?</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="29">
<p><label>Apollo</label> By furnishing him, if we can manage
it, with counsel: one of those clever men who
would deliver worthily whatever Timokles devised and suggested to him.</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> This is certainly a beardless utterance,
and still in want of a school-master! To set up
an advocate in an assemblage of philosophers to
expound Timokles's views to the company! Damis to be present in person, and speak in his own
character, but Timokles to use a mime and pour
whatever he thinks into his ear, and the actor to
deliver it, perhaps himself not understanding what
he hears! Of course it would be ridiculous to
the crowd. But let us consider this rather different idea. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="30">
<p>You say, my admirable friend, that
you are a seer, and you ask a good price for your
services, and once even received bricks of gold.
Why did you not give us an exhibition of your
skill in the nick of time by telling us which of
the Sophists is going to prevail in argument? For,
of course, you know what the issue will be, since
you are a seer.


<pb n="p.37"/></p>

<p><label>Apollo</label> How can I, Momos, when I have no
tripod with me, and no incense and no prophetic
fountain like Kastalia?</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> Look, now, when you have got into a
tight place you run away from conviction.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Never mind, my child. Speak out, and
do not give this backbiter pretexts for slander,
and for saying, in his sneering way, that your
skill is dependent on your tripod and your water
and your incense, and that unless you have these
your art will be lost.</p>


<p><label>Apollo</label> These things, father, are better done in
Delphi or in Kolophon, where I have all the accessories to which I am accustomed. Still, bare
as I am of these and unequipped, I will try to
prophesy which of them will have the mastery.
But you will bear with me if my verses should
nor be very correct.</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> Speak, but only make your remarks
clear, Apollo, so that they will not need an advocate themselves or interpretation. This is not a
case of sheep's flesh and tortoise being boiled together in Lydia. You know what our inquiry is
about.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> What in the world are you going to tell
us, my child? The symptoms that precede the
utterance are already alarming. His color is
fading, his eyes are rolling, his hair is standing
on end, and his gestures are those of a Korybant.

<pb n="p.38"/>

His whole bearing is mystic, frantic,
possessed.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="31">
<p><label>Apollo</label>

<l>Hear now the word divine, declared by the prophet Apollo</l>
<l>Dealing with shuddering strife that men wage, shrill with their screaming,</l>
<l>Armed cap-a-pie with words, with arguments well-compacted.</l>
<l>Hither and yon with the clucking that shifts to the side of the victor</l>
<l>Strike they and bear to earth the towering stern of the plow-tail.</l>
<l>Yet, when the locust shall fall 'neath the crooked claw of the vulture,</l>
<l>Then the rain - bringing crows shall utter their ultimate portent.</l>
<l>Victory lies with the mules, but the ass shall butt his fleet children.</l>

</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Why do you burst out laughing at this,
Momus? Surely there is nothing humorous in
our present situation. Stop, wretch, or you will
choke with laughing.</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> How can I help laughing at such a
clear, straightforward oracle?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Then, perhaps, you will kindly interpret
to us what he says.</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> It is perfectly plain, so that we shall
not need Themistokles. The oracle says clearly
that the seer is a juggler and that we are packasses,

<pb n="p.39"/>

by Zeus! and mules to believe in him, with
not the wit of a locust among us.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="32">

<p><label>Herakles</label> I do not hesitate, father, to express
my views, even though I am only a resident foreigner. My idea is that when they meet and are
already engaged in discussion, then, if Timokles
prove the better man, we will allow the meeting
to proceed to our advantage. But if it turn out
otherwise, then by your leave I will shake the
Porch itself from its foundations and hurl it at
Damis, so that the accursed wretch may not offer
insult to us.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Heavens, Herakles, what a boorish speech,
and how horribly Boeotian! To destroy so many
for the sake of one wretch, and, what is more, the
Porch with Marathon, Miltiades, Kynaegeiros and
all? If all these should perish together, how
would the orators continue to practise, deprived
of the chief theme of their speeches? Moreover,
in your lifetime it was perhaps possible to do
even a thing of that kind; but since you have
become a god, you have learned, I presume, that
the Fates alone control these matters, and we
have no voice in them.</p>


<p><label>Herakles</label> Then, when I was slaying the lion
or the hydra, the Fates were doing these things
by my agency?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Certainly.</p>


<p><label>Herakles</label> And at this moment if any one uses


<pb n="p.40"/>



insolence towards me, by rifling one of my temples or overturning my statue, shall I not destroy
him unless it was long ago so decided by the
Fates?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> By no means.</p>


<p><label>Herakles</label> Then, Zeus, hear me declare myself
frankly, for I am a boor, as the comic poet said,
and I call a spade a spade. If this is our plight,
I shall bid a long farewell to the worship and
savor of burnt-offerings and blood of victims in
heaven, and go off to Hades. There the ghosts,
at least, of the beasts I slew will be afraid of me,
if I have my bow, though I be unarmed beside.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Very well; nothing like a relative for
turning state's evidence, as they say.

You would
have saved Damis the trouble of making these
remarks by suggesting them yourself.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="33">
<p>

But who is this hasty - comer-bronze, wellformed, with a good outline and an obsolete coiffure? It must be your brother, Hermes, the one
that stands in the market-place near the Porch.
At all events, his hollows are full of pitch from
having impressions of him taken daily by the
statuaries.
Why, my child, do you come to us at racing
speed? Have you, perhaps, some fresh news
from earth?</p>


<p><label>Hermagoras</label> Great news, Zeus, and calling for
the greatest attention.</p>


<pb n="p.41"/>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Speak, then, if some new trouble has
arisen unknown to us.</p>


<p><label>Hermagoras</label>
<l>It chanced that even now the brass-workers</l>
<l>Were smearing me with pitch on breast and back.</l>
<l>A breastplate modelled by the mimic's art</l>
<l>Hung round me ludicrous. It was beat out</l>
<l>Merely to take th' impression of my bronze.</l>
<l>But I beheld a crowd approaching. Two</l>
<l>Pale, screaming, quibbling, verbal prize-fighters,</l>
<l>One Damis and the other-</l>
</p>

<p><label>Zeus</label> Drop the iambics, there's a good fellow.
I know whom you mean. But tell me this, whether they have already joined battle.</p>


<p><label>Hermagoras</label> Not yet. They were still skirmishing and attacking each other from afar with
the javelins of abuse.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> What is there left for us to do now,
deities, but bend down and listen to them? So
let the Hours draw the bolt immediately and
chase away the clouds and throw open the gates
of heaven.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="34">
<p>
Heavens, what a crowd has gathered to hear
them! But I am not very well satisfied with
Timokles himself; he is trembling with confusion. He will ruin everything this day. Evidently he will not be able to stand against Damis. However, let us do what in us lies and
pray for him.


<pb n="p.42"/>



"Silence on our side, that Damis, at least, may
not hear us."</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="35">
<p><label>Timokles</label> What is this you say, Damis, you
looter of temples? That the gods do not exist
or exercise providence for men?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> That is what I say; but do you first
answer me, and state what reason you have for
believing in their existence.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> I will not, you wretch. You answer me.</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> I will not. Answer yourself.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> So far our man has been far more successfully and loudly abusive. That's right, Timokles, pour on the abuse. Your strength lies
there, since in other lines he stops your mouth
and makes you dumb as a fish.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> By Heaven, I will not answer you first
if I know it.</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Then put your question, for you beat
me that time by swearing. But spare abusive
language, if you please.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="36">

<p><label>Timokles</label> Very well. Tell me, then, is it your
opinion, accursed wretch, that the gods exert no
providence?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> They do not.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> What, is the universe, then, not the
result of design?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> It is not.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> And did no god arrange the whole
superintendence of things either?</p>


<pb n="p.43"/>


<p><label>Damis</label> No.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> But all things are borne along haphazard by an unreasoning current?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Yes.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> Now can you men endure to hear
this and not stone the guilty wretch?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Why do you stir up the audience against
me, Timokles? And who are you to show anger
in the gods' behalf when they are not angry themselves? At least they have not handled me
roughly, though they have heard me for a long
time, supposing they do hear.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> They hear, Damis, they hear, and
they will take vengeance on you some day.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="37">
<p><label>Damis</label> And when would they have leisure for
my case if, as you say, they are full of cares,
managing the universe, infinite as it is? That is
the reason they have not yet even punished you
for your continual perjuries and your other crimes,
which I will not specify lest I should be driven
to use abusive language myself, contrary to our
agreement. And yet I do not see how they could
produce better proof of their own providence than
by bringing your bad life to a bad end. But
clearly they have gone abroad, across the ocean,
perchance to visit the "blameless Ethiopians."
At least it is their habit to go constantly to dine
with them, and sometimes on their own invitation.


<pb n="p.44"/></p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="38">
<p><label>Timokles</label> What shall I say in reply to such
shameless effrontery?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> What I have been yearning to hear
from you this long time: how you came to believe
in the providence of the gods.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> I was convinced of it first by the
order of natural events: the sun who always travels the same road and the moon similarly, and
the recurring seasons, and the growth of plants,
and the birth of animals, and these animals themselves so ingeniously contrived that they feed
themselves and reason, and move about and walk,
and build houses and make shoes, and all the
rest of it. Do not these seem to you the works
of providence?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Why, Timokles, you have assumed the
very question in dispute, for it remains to be seen.
whether each of these is accomplished by providence. That natural events are such as you describe I, too, admit, but it does not follow of
necessity that they owe their existence to any intelligent foresight. For it is possible that they
had some other origin, and yet have now a consistent and methodical existence. But this forced
action of theirs you call 'order,' and then, forsooth, you fly into a rage if some one rejects your
argument when, after recounting and praising the
nature of objects, you go on to believe that this
is a proof that each of them is also put in its


<pb n="p.45"/>


place by providence. Wherefore, in the words
of the comic poet,
<l>This is too feeble, tell me something else.</l></p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="39">
<p><label>Timokles</label> For my part, I do not think that additional proof is necessary; but still I will go on.
Answer me, do you consider Homer the best of
poets?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Certainly.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> Well, he convinced me by setting
forth the providence of the gods.</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> But, my astonishing friend, every one
will grant you that Homer is a great poet, but not
that he or any poet whatsoever is a reliable witness in these matters. For their concern, I imagine, is not for truth, but to charm their hearers;
and on this account they lull us with metres and
amuse us with stories, and devise the whole thing
in the interests of pleasure. Still, I should be
pleased to hear what passages of Homer chiefly
convinced you.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="40">
<p>
Probably those in which he
speaks of Zeus, and tells how his daughter and
his brother and his wife plotted to put him in
irons. And if Thetis had not perceived what was
going on and called Briareos, our glorious Zeus
would have been seized and tied up. It was in
return for this and to repay his obligation to Thetis that he deceived Agamemnon by sending him
a false dream for the destruction of many Greeks.
Notice that he was unable to launch a thunderbolt

<pb n="p.46"/>

and burn up Agamemnon himself, but must
assume the role of cheat. Or was conviction forced
upon you chiefly when you heard how Diomedes
wounded Aphrodite and then Ares himself at the
suggestion of Athene, and how the gods themselves
fell to after a little and fought duels indiscriminately, gods and goddesses together, and how Athene
overcame Ares because, I imagine, he was weak from
the wound he had already got from Diomedes, and

<l>Hermes, the ready-helper, stoutly stood against
Leto?</l>

Or did the account of Artemis strike you as convincing, telling how her discontented nature was
angered because Oineus did not ask her to his
banquet, and how, accordingly, she let loose upon
his land a certain boar of surpassing size and irresistible strength? Was it, then, by such narratives as these that Homer convinced you?</p>


</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="41">

<p><label>Zeus</label> Alas, alack! What an outcry the crowd
made, deities, applauding Damis! And our man
seems to have lost his head. He is frightened,
certainly, and trembling, and on the point of throwing away his shield. He is already looking about
for some loop-hole through which he can slip and
make his escape.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> Perhaps you do not think that Euripides says anything sound, either, when he introduces the gods themselves upon the stage and
shows them engaged in saving the good among


<pb n="p.47"/>


the heroes, but destroying the wicked and impiety
like yours?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> But, most illustrious of philosophers, if
the dramatists have convinced you by such means
as that, one of two things follows. Either you
believe the actors to be for the moment gods, or
else the divine masks themselves, and the shoes,
and the tunics flowing to the feet, and the cloaks,
and the loose sleeves, and the false paunches, and
the padding, and all the rest of the apparatus
which makes the tragedy impressive, which is
most ridiculous, I think. But whenever Euripides
speaks his own mind, unforced by the exigencies
of the dramas, hear how bold he is:

<l>You see this boundless aether spread on high,</l>
<l>Enfolding earth in damp, encircling arms?</l>
<l>Deem then that this is Zeus, believe this god.</l>

and again,

<l>Zeus,</l>
<l>Whoe'er Zeus is, for I know not, unless</l>
<l>By hearsay,</l>
and other similar passages.</p>


</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="42">

<p><label>Timokles</label> Then all mankind and the nations
have been deceived in believing in the gods and
celebrating their feasts?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> It is a good thing, Timokles, that you
reminded me of the religious opinions among the
nations, the very things which best show that
there is no certainty about gods. For there is


<pb n="p.48"/>



much confusion, and different races have different
faiths. The Scythians worship a sword; the
Thracians, Zamolxis, a fugitive who came to them
from Samos; the Phrygians, Mena; the Ethiopians,
Day; the Assyrians, a dove; the Persians, fire; the
Egyptians, water. Moreover, while this waterworship is common to all the Egyptians, the peculiar god of the people of Memphis is the bull,
and that of the Pelusians is the onion; and others
worship the ibis or the crocodile, and others a
dog-headed creature or a cat or an ape. And,
again, the rural communities differ from one another, so that some men hold the right shoulder
to be a god, but those that dwell opposite to them
the left. And some worship one side of the head,
and others an earthen wine-cup or a bowl. Are
not these things absurd, friend Timokles?</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> Did I not tell you, deities, that all
these things would come to light and be rigorously
investigated?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> You did, Momos, and your censure was
just; and if we escape this present danger, I for
one will try to straighten out these matters.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="43">

<p><label>Timokles</label> But tell me, god-forsaken wretch,
whose work would you call oracles and prophecies
of future events, if not of the gods and their
providence?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Hold your peace, my good fellow, on
the subject of the oracles, for I shall ask you


<pb n="p.49"/>


which of them in particular you would like to recall. Perhaps that one Apollo delivered to the
Lydian, which was neatly double-edged and looked both ways, like some of the Hermae, which are
exactly alike on both sides to whichever part of
them you look. For tell me, will Croesus by
crossing the Halys be more likely to overthrow
his own kingdom or that of Cyros? And yet
that Sardian pest paid no small sum for this reversible utterance.</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> The man is enumerating the very
things I was most afraid of. Where now is our
handsome harper? Go down and defend yourself against these charges of his.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> You strike us when we are down, Momos,
finding fault with us now, when the season is past.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="44">
<p><label>Timokles</label> Beware what you are doing, wretched
Damis. You are all but overturning the very
seats and altars of the gods with your arguments.</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> No, not all their altars, Timokles; for
what harm do they do if they are full of incense
and fragrance? But those of Artemis in Tauris
I should be delighted to see turned upsidedown,
whereon the maiden goddess feasts joyously on
the things we wot of.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Whence has this overwhelming evil come
upon us?
There is not a divinity that the man
stands in awe of. He speaks his mind as freely
as a wench in a procession, and he



<pb n="p.50"/>



<l>Grasps them all in order, deserving and undeserving.</l></p>


<p><label>Momos</label> In truth, Zeus, you would find very few
who do not deserve it among us. And surely the
man will go on to lay hold of even the very greatest.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="45">
<p><label>Timokles</label> Perhaps you do not hear Zeus thundering, you fighter against the gods?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Of course I hear the thunder; but as
to whether it is Zeus who thunders, your knowledge would be more reliable if you had come
from somewhere up there among the gods. For
travellers from Crete tell us a different story:
that a certain tomb is shown in that country, and
beside it stands a pillar telling that Zeus will
thunder no more, being long since dead.</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> I knew long ago that the man was
going to say that. But, Zeus, why have you turned
pale? Why do you tremble so that your teeth
chatter? You must take heart and despise such
manikins.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> What do you say, Momos? Despise
them? Do you not see how large the audience
is, and how they are persuaded against us already,
and how Damis is leading them away with their
ears stopped?</p>


<p><label>Momos</label> But, Zeus, if you liked you could let
down a rope and
<l>Drag not them alone, but earth, too, and the
ocean.</l></p>


<pb n="p.51"/>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="46">
<p><label>Timokles</label> Tell me, wretch, have
at sea?
you ever been
Damis. Yes, often.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> You were carried along then, were
you not, either by the wind striking the main-sail
and filling the staysail, or by the rowers, while
some one person stood at the helm and brought
the vessel through in safety?</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Certainly.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> Then the ship could not sail unless
it was steered; but you imagine that this universe
moves along without pilot or guide?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Well done, Timokles! that is a powerful
comparison.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="47">
<p><label>Damis</label> But, Timokles, darling of the gods, you
would have seen that our pilot was always devising something to our advantage and making his
arrangements at the proper time, and giving his
commands to the sailors in good season, and that
there was nothing useless or foolish about the
ship. On the contrary, everything was altogether
useful and necessary to their management of her.
But this pilot of yours, whom you suppose to
stand at the helm of this great ship, and his crew,
do not order a single thing sensibly or as it ought
to be. The forestay is hauled aft if it so happens,
and the sheets forward. Sometimes the anchors
are of gold, while the stern is ornamented with
lead. Under water the ship's lines are good, but


<pb n="p.52"/>



above the water-line she is shapeless. </p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="48">
<p>And
among the sailors themselves you will find that
one who is lazy, unskilled, and afraid of his duties
draws double or treble pay, while another, who is
an expert swimmer and quick to spring to the
yards, and who knows the best thing to do in
every case, this man is set simply to bale out
bilge-water. You will find the same sort of thing
among the passengers, too. A worthless rascal
occupies the place of honor next the captain, and
receives attention. Another, an indecent fellow,
or a parricide, or a temple-robber, is honored
above others, and has taken possession of the upper deck, while many men of culture are penned
together in a corner of the vessel and trodden
underfoot by those who are really their inferiors.
At any rate, you remarked how Sokrates made
the voyage, and Aristeides and Phokion, without
either daily bread enough or room to stretch their
legs on the bare deck along the hold, and on the
other hand how well Kallias and Meidias and
Sardanapalos fared in their overweening luxury,
spitting on those beneath. </p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="49">
<p>
This is the sort of
thing that goes on in your ship, sage Timokles,
wherefore the shipwrecks are countless. But if
any pilot stood at the helm, and kept a lookout
and ordered everything, he would know in the
first place who were good and who were worthless
of the ship's company, and he would apportion to


<pb n="p.53"/>


each what befitted his merits, giving the better
quarters near himself on deck to the better men,
and the lower parts to the worse, and he would
cause some of the better sort to sit at table together and come to terms of confidence. Among
the sailors a zealous man would be distinguished
by being put on the lookout or made captain of a
watch, or set over all the others. But a lazy shirk
would get the rope's end about his head five times
a day. So, my friend, your comparison seems to
have capsized because it fell into the hands of a
bad pilot.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="50">

<p><label>Momos</label> Things are running with the tide for
Damis now, and he is sailing to victory with a
fair wind.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> Your metaphor is just, Momos, and Timokles invents no forcible argument. He only ladles out easily refuted commonplaces one after
another that are in every one's mouth.</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="51">

<p><label>Timokles</label> Well, since you do not think the analogy of the ship very forcible, listen while I cast
the last blessed anchor I have, which you will not
drag by any device.</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> What in the world is he going to say?</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> For see now whether my syllogism is
fallacious, and whether you can possibly overturn
it. If altars exist, gods exist also. But altars
certainly exist, therefore gods exist also. What
have you to say to that?


<pb n="p.54"/></p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Let me have my laugh out first and
then I will answer you.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> But it looks as if you would never be
done laughing. However, tell me why my speech
struck you as ridiculous.</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Because you do not perceive that you
have slung your anchor on a slender thread,
though it is the last blessed one you have. For
when you have made fast the proposition "gods.
exist" to the proposition "altars exist" you imagine that you have brought it to a safe anchorage.
So since you have nothing more blessed to urge
let us adjourn at once.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="52">

<p><label>Timokles</label> Do you then admit yourself worsted
by crying" Enough?"</p>


<p><label>Damis</label> Yes, Timokles, for you, like a hardpressed fugitive, have taken sanctuary on your
altars, and so, by the blessed anchor, I long
to swear a truce with you on these very altars, so that we may no longer wrangle about
them.</p>


<p><label>Timokles</label> You are chaffing me, you grave-robber, you blackguard, you disgusting beast, you
knavish slave, you refuse! Don't I know who
your father was and your mother, too, and how
you strangled your brother, and are an evil-liver
and corrupter of lads, you filthy, shameless wretch?
Don't run away now, for you are going to get
blows from me, too, before you get off. I am going

<pb n="p.55"/>

to cut your throat directly with this potsherd,
miscreant that you are!</p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg018.perseus-eng5:" n="53">
<p><label>Zeus</label> Damis is running off laughing, deities,
and the other is chasing him with abuse, put out
past bearing by Damis's wealth of impertinence,
and apparently he is going to clip him in the head
with the tile. But what shall we do now?</p>


<p><label>Hermes</label> It seems to me the comic poet was
right when he said:

<l>Do not profess defeat and you will suffer none.</l>
For what great harm is it if a handful of men
go off persuaded to these views, seeing that there
are many who know to the contrary, the majority of the Greeks, a numerous race, and all the
barbarians?</p>


<p><label>Zeus</label> However, Hermes, that was a capital remark that Dareios made about Zopyrus. In the
same way I, too, would rather have one Damis for
my ally than rule ten thousand Babylons.


<pb n="p.56"/>




<pb n="p.57"/>


</p></div>
</div>
</body></text></TEI>

