<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>To Philip</title>
        
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor>George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <date type="print">1928</date>
          <date type="reprint">1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
      <change when="2016-01-29" who="TDB"> CTS and Epidoc update</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg020.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Do not be surprised, Philip, that I am going to begin, not with the discourse which is
          to be addressed to you and which is presently to be brought to your attention, but with
          that which I have written about <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
            >Amphipolis</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName
              key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, a city in <placeName
              key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> near the mouth of the Strymon river, conquered
            and colonized by Athenians in <date when="-0437">437 B.C.</date> It was taken by Philip
            in <date when="-0358">358 B.C.</date>, but the war with <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> was delayed until Philip seized <placeName key="tgn,6004814"
              >Potidaea</placeName>, <date when="-0356">356 B.C.</date></note> For I desire to say a
          few words, by way of preface, about this question, in order that I may make it clear to
          you as well as to the rest of the world that it was not in a moment of folly that I
          undertook to write my address to you, nor because I am under any misapprehension as to the
            infirmity<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates had now passed his ninetieth
            birthday.</note> which now besets me, but that I was led advisedly and deliberately to
          this resolution. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>
           For when I saw that the war in which you and our city had become involved over
            <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName> was proving the source of
          many evils, I endeavored to express opinions regarding this city and territory which, so
          far from being the same as those entertained by your friends, or by the orators among us,
          were as far as possible removed from their point of view. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For they were spurring you on to the war by seconding your covetousness, while I, on the
          contrary, expressed no opinion whatever on the points in controversy, but occupied myself
          with a plea which I conceived to be more than all others conducive to peace, maintaining
          that both you and the Athenians were mistaken about the real state of affairs and that you
          were fighting in support of our interests, and our city in support of your power; for it
          was to your advantage, I urged, that we should possess the territory of <placeName
            key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, while it was in no possible way to our
          advantage to acquire it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Yes, and I so impressed my hearers by my statement of the case that not one of them
          thought of applauding my oratory or the finish and the purity of my style, as some are
          wont to do, but instead they marvelled at the truth of my arguments, and were convinced
          that only on certain conditions could you and the Athenians be made to cease from your
          contentious rivalry. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In the first place, you, for your part, will have to be persuaded that the friendship of
          our city would be worth more to you than the revenues which you derive from <placeName
            key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, while <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> will have to learn, if she can, the lesson that she should avoid
          planting the kind of colonies<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Such as <placeName
              key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>, surrounded by warlike tribes.</note>
          which have been the ruin, four or five times over, of those domiciled in them, and should
          seek out for colonization the regions which are far distant from peoples which have a
          capacity for dominion and near those which have been habituated to subjection—such a
          region as, for example, that in which the Lacedaemonians established the colony of
            <placeName key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName>.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
              ><placeName key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName>, in northern <placeName
              key="tgn,7001242">Africa</placeName>. See Grote, <title>Hist.</title> iii. p.
            445.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In the next place, you will have to realize that by formally surrendering this territory
          to us you would in fact still hold it in your power, and would, besides, gain our good
          will, for you would then have as many hostages of ours to guarantee our friendship as we
          should send out settlers into the region of your influence; while someone will have to
          make our own people see that, if we got possession of <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis"
            >Amphipolis</placeName>, we should be compelled to maintain the same friendly attitude
          toward your policy, because of our colonists there, as we did for the elder Amadocus<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">An alliance was entered into between <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and Amadocus, the powerful Thracian king,
              <date when="-0390">390 B.C.</date> (<bibl n="Xen. Hell. 4.8.26">Xen. Hell.
              4.8.26</bibl>).</note> because of our landholders in the <placeName key="tgn,7010345"
            >Chersonese</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>
           As I continued to say many things of this tenor, those who heard me were inspired
          with the hope that when my discourse should be published you and the Athenians would bring
          the war to an end, and, having conquered your pride, would adopt some policy for your
          mutual good. Whether indeed they were foolish or sensible in taking this view is a
          question for which they, and not I, may fairly be held to account; but in any case, while
          I was still occupied with this endeavor, you and <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> anticipated me by making peace before I had completed my discourse;
          and you were wise in doing so, for to conclude the peace, no matter how, was better than
          to continue to be oppressed by the evils engendered by the war. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But although I was in joyful accord with the resolutions which were adopted regarding the
          peace, and was convinced that they would be beneficial, not only to us, but also to you
          and all the other Hellenes, I could not divorce my thought from the possibilities
          connected with this step, but found myself in a state of mind where I began at once to
          consider how the results which had been achieved might be made permanent for us, and how
          our city could be prevented from setting her heart upon further wars, after a short
          interval of peace.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.172">Isoc.
              4.172-174</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>As I kept going over these questions in my own thoughts, I found that on no other
          condition could <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> remain at peace, unless
          the greatest states of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> should resolve to
          put an end to their mutual quarrels and carry the war beyond our borders into Asia, and
          should determine to wrest from the barbarians the advantages which they now think it
          proper to get for themselves at the expense of the Hellenes. This was, in fact, the course
          which I had already advocated in the <title>Panegyric</title> discourse.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.17">Isoc. 4.17</bibl>, where almost the
            same words are used.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Having pondered on these matters and come to the conclusion that there could never be
          found a subject nobler than this, of more general appeal, or of greater profit to us all,
          I was moved to write upon it a second time. Yet I did not fail to appreciate my own
          deficiencies; I knew that this theme called for a man, not of my years, but in the full
          bloom of his vigor and with natural endowments far above those of other men; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and I realized also that it is difficult to deliver two discourses with tolerable success
          upon the same subject, especially when the one which was first published was so written
          that even my detractors imitate and admire it more than do those who praise it to excess.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nevertheless, disregarding all these difficulties, I have become so ambitious in my old
          age that I have determined by addressing my discourse to you at the same time to set an
          example to my disciples and make it evident to them that to burden our national assemblies
          with oratory and to address all the people who there throng together is, in reality, to
          address no one at all;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The same sentiment is expressed in
              <bibl n="Isoc. L. 1.6">Isoc. Letter 1.6-7</bibl>. See General Introd. pp. xxxvi.
            ff.</note> that such speeches are quite as ineffectual as the legal codes and
            constitutions<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Possibly a disparagement of Plato's
              <title>Republic</title> and <title>Laws</title> (see Blass, <title>Die attische
              Beredsamkeit,</title> ii. p. 4), but more probably of Isocrates' unfriendly rival,
            Antisthenes, who, according to <bibl n="D. L. 6.1.16">Diog. Laert. 6.1.16</bibl>, wrote
            a work <title>On Law, or the Constitution of a State</title>.</note> drawn up by the
          sophists; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and, finally, that those who desire, not to chatter empty nonsense, but to further some
          practical purpose, and those who think they have hit upon some plan for the common good,
          must leave it to others to harangue at the public festivals, but must themselves win over
          someone to champion their cause from among men who are capable not only of speech but of
          action and who occupy a high position in the world—if, that is to say, they are to command
          any attention. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It was with this mind that I chose to address to you what I have to say—not that I
          singled you out to curry your favor, although in truth I would give much to speak
          acceptably to you. It was not, however, with this in view that I came to my decision, but
          rather because I saw that all the other men of high repute were living under the control
          of politics and laws,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See 127 and General Introd. p.
            xlii.</note> with no power to do anything save what was prescribed, and that,
          furthermore, they were sadly unequal to the enterprise which I shall propose; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>while you and you alone had been granted by fortune free scope both to send ambassadors
          to whom ever you desire and to receive them from whom ever you please, and to say whatever
          you think expedient; and that, besides, you, beyond any of the Hellenes, were possessed of
          both wealth and power, which are the only things in the world that are adapted at once to
          persuade and to compel; and these aids, I think, even the cause which I shall propose to
          you will need to have on its side. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I am going to advise you to champion the cause of concord among the Hellenes and of a
          campaign against the barbarian; and as persuasion will be helpful in dealing with the
          Hellenes, so compulsion will be useful in dealing with the barbarians. This, then, is the
          general scope of my discourse. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I must not shrink from telling you plainly of the discouragements I met with from
          some of my associates; for I think the tale will be somewhat to my purpose. When I
          disclosed to them my intention of sending you an address whose aim was, not to make a
          display, nor to extol the wars which you have carried on—for others will do this—but to
          attempt to urge you to a course of action which is more in keeping with your nature, and
          more noble and more profitable than any which you have hitherto elected to follow, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>they were so dismayed, fearing that because of my old age I had parted with my wits, that
          they ventured to take me to task—a thing which up to that time they had not been wont to
          do—insisting that I was applying myself to an absurd and exceedingly senseless
          undertaking. “Think of it!” they said. “You are about to send an address which is intended
          to offer advice to Philip, a man who, even if in the past he regarded himself as second to
          anyone in prudence, cannot now fail, because of the magnitude of his fortunes, to think
          that he is better able than all others to advise himself! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>More than that, he has about him the ablest men in <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
            >Macedonia</placeName>, who, however inexperienced they may be in other matters, are
          likely to know better than you do what is expedient for him. Furthermore, you will find
          that there are many Hellenes living in his country, who are not unknown to fame or lacking
          in intelligence, but men by sharing whose counsel he has not diminished his kingdom but
          has, on the contrary, accomplished deeds which match his dreams. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For what is lacking to complete his success? Has he not converted the Thessalians, whose
          power formerly extended over <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>, into an
          attitude so friendly to him that every Thessalian has more confidence in him than in his
          own fellow countrymen? And as to the cities which are in that region, has he not drawn
          some of them by his benefactions into an alliance with him; and others, which sorely tried
          him, has he not razed to the ground? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Has he not overthrown the Magnesians and the Perrhaebians and the Paeonians, and taken
          them all under his yoke? Has he not made himself lord and ruler of most of the
          Illyrians—all save those who dwell along the Adriatic? Has he not set over all <placeName
            key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> such masters as he pleased?<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For these early conquests of Philip see Grote, <title>Hist.</title> xi. p.
            18.</note> Do you not, then, think that the man who has achieved such great things will
          pronounce the sender of this pamphlet a great simpleton, and will consider that he was
          utterly deluded both as to the power of his words and his own insight?” </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now, how on hearing these words I was at first dumbfounded, and how later, after I had
          recovered myself, I replied to each of their objections, I will forbear to relate, lest I
          should appear in the eyes of some to be too well satisfied with the clever manner in which
          I met their attack. But, at any rate, after I had first rebuked with moderation, as I
          persuaded myself, those who had made bold to criticize me, I finally assured them that I
          would show the speech to no one else in the city but them, and that I would do nothing
          regarding it other than what they should approve. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>On hearing this they went their way, I know not in what state of mind. I only know that
          when, not many days later, the speech was completed and presented to them, they so
          completely reversed their attitude that they were ashamed of their former presumption and
          repented of all they had said, acknowledging that they had never been so mistaken about
          anything in all their lives. They were, in fact, more insistent than I that this speech
          should be sent to you, and prophesied that not only would you and <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> be grateful to me for what I had said but all
            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> as well. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> My purpose in recounting all this is that if, in what I say at the beginning, anything
          strikes you as incredible, or impracticable, or unsuitable for you to carry out, you may
          not be prejudiced and turn away from the rest of my discourse, and that you may not repeat
          the experience of my friends, but may wait with an open mind until you hear to the end all
          that I have to say. For I think that I shall propose something which is in line with both
          your duty and your advantage. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet I do not fail to realize what a great difference there is in persuasiveness
          between discourses which are spoken and those which are to be read, and that all men have
          assumed that the former are delivered on subjects which are important and urgent, while
          the latter are composed for display and personal gain.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. L. 1.2">Isoc. Letter 1.2-3</bibl>. See Jebb, <title>Attic
              Orators</title>, ii. p. 67.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And this is a natural conclusion; for when a discourse is robbed of the prestige of the
          speaker, the tones of his voice, the variations which are made in the delivery, and,
          besides, of the advantages of timeliness and keen interest in the subject matter; when it
          has not a single accessory to support its contentions and enforce its plea, but is
          deserted and stripped of all the aids which I have mentioned; and when someone reads it
          aloud without persuasiveness and without putting any personal feeling into it, but as
          though he were repeating a table of figures,— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>in these circumstances it is natural, I think, that it should make an indifferent
          impression upon its hearers. And these are the very circumstances which may detract most
          seriously also from the discourse which is now presented to you and cause it to impress
          you as a very indifferent performance; the more so since I have not adorned it with the
          rhythmic flow and manifold graces of style which I myself employed when I was younger<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 12.1">Isoc. 12.1-2</bibl>.</note> and
          taught by example to others as a means by which they might make their oratory more
          pleasing and at the same time more convincing. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I have now no longer any capacity for these things because of my years; it is enough
          for me if I can only set before you in a simple manner the actual facts. And I think it
          becomes you also to ignore all else and give your attention to the facts alone. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But you will be in the best position to discover with accuracy whether there is any truth
          in what I say if you put aside the prejudices<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign
              xml:lang="grc">ai( dusxe/reiai</foreign> may mean difficulties or disadvantages
            under which speeches labor which are composed for a reading public, or the prejudices
            against them caused by these disadvantages. The latter seems to be the sense here. See
            Benseler's note.</note> which are held against the sophists and against speeches which
          are composed to be read, and take them up one by one in your thought and scrutinize them,
          not making it a casual task, nor one to be attacked in a spirit of indifference, but with
          the close reasoning and love of knowledge which it is common report that you also
            share.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">“Isocrates addressed him (Philip) as a friend of
            letters and philosophy: a reputation which his choice of Aristotle as an instructor of
            his son, Alexander, tends to bear out” (Grote, <title>Hist.</title> xi. p. 325).</note>
          For if you will conduct your inquiry with these aids instead of relying upon the opinion
          of the masses, you will form a sounder judgement about such discourses. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> This, then, completes what I wanted to say by way of introduction. I shall now proceed
          with the subject in hand. I affirm that, without neglecting any of your own interests, you
          ought to make an effort to reconcile <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> and
            <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
            >Thebes</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The leading states. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.64">Isoc.
            4.64</bibl>.</note> for if you can bring these cities together, you will not find it
          hard to unite the others as well; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for all the rest are under the protection of the aforesaid cities, and fly for refuge,
          when they are alarmed, to one or other of these powers, and they all draw upon them for
          succor. So that if you can persuade four cities only to take a sane view of things, you
          will deliver the others also from many evils. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now you will realize that it is not becoming in you to disregard any of these cities if
          you will review their conduct in relation to your ancestors; for you will find that each
          one of them is to be credited with great friendship and important services to your house:
            <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> is the land of your fathers,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Perdiccas I., the founder of the <placeName key="tgn,5001993"
              >Argive</placeName> dynasty in <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName>,
            was, according to <bibl n="Hdt. 8.137">Hdt. 8.137</bibl>, a descendant of the <placeName
              key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> hero Temenus. See also <bibl n="Hdt. 5.22">Hdt.
              5.22</bibl> and Grote, <title>Hist.</title> iii. p. 432.</note> and is entitled to as
          much consideration at your hands as are your own ancestors; the Thebans honor the
            founder<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Heracles. See General Introd. p. xli.</note> of
          your race, both by processionals and by sacrifices,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At the
            “Festival of Heracles.” <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 6.4.7">Xen. Hell. 6.4.7</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Diod. 15.53">Dio. Sic. 15.53</bibl>.</note> beyond all the other gods; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>the Lacedaemonians have conferred upon his descendants the kingship and the power of
            command<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.62">Isoc. 4.62</bibl> and
            note.</note> for all time; and as for our city, we are informed by those whom we credit
          in matters of ancient history that she aided Heracles to win his immortality<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">According to <bibl n="Diod. 4.39">Dio. Sic. 4.39</bibl> the
            Athenians were the first to offer sacrifices to Heracles as a god.</note>(in what way
          you can easily learn at another time; it would be unseasonable for me to relate it now),
          and that she aided his children to preserve their lives.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >For this statement and the following paragraph see <bibl n="Isoc. 4.56">Isoc.
              4.56-62</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Yes, <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> single-handed sustained the
          greatest dangers against the power of Eurystheus, put an end to his insolence, and freed
          Heracles' sons from the fears by which they were continually beset. Because of these
          services we deserve the gratitude, not only of those who then were preserved from
          destruction, but also of those who are now living; for to us it is due both that they are
          alive and that they enjoy the blessings which are now theirs, since they never could have
          seen the light of day at all had not the sons of Heracles been preserved from death. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Therefore, seeing that these cities have each and all shown such a spirit, no quarrel
          should ever have arisen between you and any one of them. But unfortunately we are all
          prone by nature to do wrong more often than right; and so it is fair to charge the
          mistakes of the past to our common weakness. Yet for the future you must be on your guard
          to prevent a like occurrence, and must consider what service you can render them which
          will make it manifest that you have acted in a manner worthy both of yourself and of what
          these cities have done. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And the opportunity now serves you; for you would only be repaying the debt of gratitude
          which you owed them, but, because so much time has elapsed, they will credit you with
          being first in friendly offices. And it is a good thing to have the appearance of
          conferring benefits upon the greatest states of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName> and at the same time to profit yourself no less than them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But apart from this, if anything unpleasant has arisen between you and any of them, you
          will wipe it out completely; for friendly acts in the present crisis will make you forget
          the wrongs which you have done each other in the past. Yes, and this also is beyond
          question, that all men hold in fondest memory those benefits which they receive in times
          of trouble. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And you see how utterly wretched these states have become because of their warfare, and
          how like they are to men engaged in a personal encounter; for no one can reconcile the
          parties to a quarrel while their wrath is rising; but after they have punished each other
          badly, they need no mediator, but separate of their own accord. And that is just what I
          think these states also will do unless you first take them in hand. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now perhaps someone will venture to object to what I have proposed, saying that I am
          trying to persuade you to set yourself to an impossible task, since the Argives could
          never be friendly to the Lacedaemonians, nor the Lacedaemonians to the Thebans, and since,
          in general, those who have been accustomed throughout their whole existence to press their
          own selfish interests can never share and share alike with each other. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Well, I myself do not believe that at the time when our city was the first power in
            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, or again when <placeName
            key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> occupied that position, any such result could
          have been accomplished,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The following paragraphs betray a
            cynicism which is foreign to the <bibl n="Isoc. 4.">Isoc. 4.</bibl>See General Introd.
            p. xxxvi.</note> since the one or the other of these two cities could easily have
          blocked the attempt; but as things are now, I am not of the same mind regarding them. For
          I know that they have all been brought down to the same level by their misfortunes, and so
          I think that they would much prefer the mutual advantages which would come from a unity of
          purpose to the selfish gains which accrued from their policy in those days.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.8 and <bibl n="Isoc. 4.17">Isoc. 4.17</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, while I grant that no one else in the world could reconcile these cities,
          yet nothing of the sort is difficult for you; for I see that you have carried through to a
          successful end many undertakings which the rest of the world looked upon as hopeless and
          unthinkable, and therefore it would be nothing strange if you should be able single-handed
          to affect this union. In fact, men of high purposes and exceptional gifts ought not to
          undertake enterprises which any of the common run might carry out with success, but rather
          those which no one would attempt save men with endowments and power such as you possess.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I marvel that those who think that none of these proposals could possibly be carried
          out are not aware, either by their own knowledge or by tradition, that there have been
          many terrible wars after which the participants have come to an understanding and rendered
          great services to one another. For what could exceed the enmity which the Hellenes felt
          toward Xerxes? Yet everyone knows that we and the Lacedaemonians came to prize his
            friendship<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The expression is loose. He means that the
            hatred for <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> under Xerxes changed to
            friendship under Artaxerxes when the Peace of Antalcidas was made. Cf. Sparta's “love”
            for <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> mentioned in <bibl n="Isoc. 12.102"
              >Isoc. 12.102-103</bibl>.</note> more than that of those who helped us to establish
          our respective empires. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But why speak of ancient history, or of our dealings with the barbarians? If one should
          scan and review the misfortunes of the Hellenes in general, these will appear as nothing
          in comparison with those which we Athenians have experienced through the Thebans and the
            Lacedaemonians.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Especially at the close of the
            Peloponnesian War. See <bibl n="Isoc. 14.31">Isoc. 14.31</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 3.5.8">Xen. Hell. 3.5.8</bibl>.</note> Nevertheless, when the
          Lacedaemonians took the field against the Thebans and were minded to humiliate <placeName
            key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName> and break up the league of her cities, we sent a
          relief expedition<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Under Chabrias, against Agesilaus, <date
              when="-0378">378 B.C.</date>
            <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.4">Xen. Hell. 5.4</bibl>; Grote, <title>Hist.</title> ix. p.
            343.</note> and thwarted the desires of the Lacedaemonians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And again, when fortune shifted her favor<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName
              key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> became the supreme power in <placeName
              key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> by the battle of Leuctra, <date when="-0371">371
              B.C.</date></note> and the Thebans and the Peloponnesians were one and all trying to
          devastate <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>, we alone among the Hellenes
            formed<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><date when="-0361">361 B.C.</date></note> an
          alliance with the Lacedaemonians and helped to save them from destruction.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In <date when="-0362">362 B.C.</date>, when Epaminondas, at
            the head of the Thebans and their allies, including the Argives, Arcadians, Messenians,
            and the Eleans, marched on <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> to destroy
            her, the Athenians dispatched Iphicrates with an army of twelve thousand to the rescue.
            See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.105">Isoc. 8.105</bibl>; <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 6.5.23">Xen. Hell.
              6.5.23 ff.</bibl>; Grote, <title>Hist.</title> x. pp. 89 ff.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So then, seeing that such great reversals are wont to occur, and that our states care
          nothing about their former enmities or about their oaths or about anything else save what
          they conceive to be expedient for themselves, and that expediency is the sole object to
          which they give their affections and devote all their zeal, no man, unless obsessed by
          utter folly, could fail to believe that now also they will show the same disposition,
          especially if you take the lead in their reconciliation, while selfish interests urge and
          present ills constrain them to this course. I, for my part, believe that, with these
          influences fighting on your side, everything will turn out as it should. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I think that you can get most light on the question whether these cities are
          inclined toward peace with each other or toward war, if I review, not merely in general
          terms nor yet with excessive detail, the principal facts in their present situation. And
          first of all, let us consider the condition of the Lacedaemonians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The Lacedaemonians were the leaders of the Hellenes,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            hegemony of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> lasted from the battle of
              <placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>, <date when="-0405">405
              B.C.</date>, to the battle of Leuctra, <date when="-0371">371 B.C.</date></note> not
          long ago, on both land and sea, and yet they suffered so great a reversal of fortune when
          they met defeat at Leuctra that they were deprived of their power over the Hellenes, and
          lost such of their warriors as chose to die rather than survive defeat at the hands of
          those over whom they had once been masters. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, they were obliged to look on while all the Peloponnesians, who formerly had
          followed the lead of <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> against the rest
          of the world, united with the Thebans and invaded their territory; and against these the
          Lacedaemonians were compelled to risk battle, not in the country to save the crops, but in
          the heart of the city,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Epaminondas (see 44 and note)
            actually entered <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. <bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 7.5.11">Xen. Hell. 7.5.11</bibl>.</note> before the very seat of their
          government, to save their wives and children—a crisis in which defeat meant instant
          destruction, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and victory has none the more delivered them from their ills; nay, they are now warred
          upon by their neighbors<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Argives and the Messenians were
            allied with Philip against <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. See <bibl
              n="Dem. 6.9">Dem. 6.9, 15</bibl>.</note>; they are distrusted by all the
            Peloponnesians<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Besides the Argives and Messenians, also
            the Arcadians, the Megalopolitans, the Eleans, and the Sicyonians. <bibl n="Diod. 16.39"
              >Dio. Sic. 16.39</bibl>.</note>; they are hated by most of the Hellenes<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Especially by the Athenians and the Thebans. <bibl
              n="Dem. 16.22">Dem. 16.22-23</bibl>.</note>; they are harried and plundered day and
          night by their own serfs<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Helots.</note>; and not a day
          passes that they do not have to take the field or fight against some force or other, or
          march to the rescue of their perishing comrades. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the worst of their afflictions is that they live in continual fear that the Thebans
          may patch up their quarrel with the Phocians<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName
              key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> was the principal enemy of the Phocians in the
            Sacred War, which was now drawing to a close. For this war see Grote,
              <title>Hist.</title> xi. p. 45.</note> and, returning again,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">As in the campaign referred to in 44, which ended with the battle of
              <placeName key="perseus,Mantinea">Mantinea</placeName>.</note> ring them about with
          still greater calamities than have befallen them in the past. How, then, can we refuse to
          believe that people so hard pressed would gladly see at the head of a movement for peace a
          man who commands confidence and has the power to put an end to the wars in which they are
          involved? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now as to the Argives, you will see that in some respects they are no better off than
          the Lacedaemonians, while in others their condition is worse; for they have been in a
          state of war with their neighbors<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Spartans.</note> from
          the day they founded their city, just as have the Lacedaemonians; but there is this
          difference, that the neighbors of the Lacedaemonians are weaker than they, while those of
          the Argives are stronger—a condition which all would admit to be the greatest of
          misfortunes. And so unsuccessful are they in their warfare that hardly a year passes that
          they are not compelled to witness their own territory being ravaged and laid waste.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">This was done by the Spartans six years before this. <bibl
              n="Diod. 16.39">Dio. Sic. 16.39</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But what is most deplorable of all is that, during the intervals when their enemies cease
          from harrying them, they themselves put to death the most eminent and wealthy of their
            citizens;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The conflict between democracy and oligarchy,
            which raged with varying intensity in most of the Greek cities, in <placeName
              key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> was most bitter. In <date when="-0371">371
              B.C.</date> occurred a massacre in which twelve hundred of the leading men were slain
            by the mob. <bibl n="Diod. 15.57">Dio. Sic. 15.57-58</bibl>; Grote, <title>Hist.</title>
            ix. p. 417.</note> and they have more pleasure in doing this than any other people have
          in slaying their foes. The cause of their living in such disorder is none other than the
          state of war; and if you can put a stop to this, you will not only deliver them from these
          evils but you will cause them to adopt a better policy with respect to their other
          interests as well. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And as for the condition of the Thebans, surely you have not failed to note that also.
          They won a splendid victory<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Battle of Leuctra, <date
              when="-0371">371 B.C.</date></note> and covered themselves with glory, but because
          they did not make good use of their success they are now in no better case than those who
          have suffered defeat and failure. For no sooner had they triumphed over their foes than,
          neglecting everything else, they began to annoy the cities of the <placeName
            key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName>;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Epaminondas
            invaded the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> in 369, 368, 366, 362,
            stirring up the cities there against <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>.
              <bibl n="Diod. 15.62">Dio. Sic. 15.62-75</bibl>.</note> they made bold to reduce
            <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> to subjection;<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">By conquering Alexander of Pherae. <bibl n="Diod. 15.67">Dio. Sic.
              15.67</bibl>.</note> they threatened their neighbors, the Megarians;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Megarians sided with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName> when Agesilaus invaded <placeName key="tgn,7002683"
              >Boeotia</placeName> in 378. <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.4.41">Xen. Hell.
            5.4.41</bibl>.</note> they robbed our city of a portion of its territory;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The border town of Oropus, <date when="-0366">366 B.C.</date>
            <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 7.4.1">Xen. Hell. 7.4.1</bibl>.</note> they ravaged <placeName
            key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Dem. 18.99">Dem. 18.99</bibl>.</note> they sent men-of-war to <placeName
            key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">One
            hundred ships under Epaminondas, <date when="-0364">364 B.C.</date>
            <bibl n="Diod. 15.78">Dio. Sic. 15.78-79</bibl>.</note> as if they purposed to rule both
          land and sea; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and, finally, they began war upon the Phocians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Ten years,
              <date from="-0356" to="-0346">356-346 B.C.</date> See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.50"
              >Isoc. 5.50</bibl>.</note> expecting that in a short time they would conquer their
          cities, occupy all the surrounding territory, and prevail over all the treasures at
            <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName><note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            Phocians met their expenses in the war from the rich treasures in the Temple of Apollo
            at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>.</note> by the outlay of their own
          funds. But none of these hopes has been realized; instead of seizing the cities of the
          Phocians they have lost cities of their own;<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName
              key="tgn,7011034">Orchomenus</placeName>, Coroneia, Corsiae. <bibl n="Diod. 16.33"
              >Dio. Sic. 16.33-58</bibl>.</note> and now when they invade the enemy's territory they
          inflict less damage upon them than they suffer when they are retreating to their own
          country; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for while they are in Phocian territory they succeed in killing a few hireling<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Phocian forces were composed mainly of mercenaries.</note>
          soldiers who are better off dead than alive, but when they retreat they lose of their own
          citizens those who are most esteemed and most ready to die for their fatherland. And so
          completely have their fortunes shifted, that whereas they once hoped that all <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> would be subject to them, now they rest upon
            you<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The war was concluded shortly after this by the
            intervention of Philip against the Phocians.</note> the hopes of their own deliverance.
          Therefore I think that the Thebans also will do with alacrity whatever you command or
          advise. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It would still remain for me to speak about our city, had she not come to her senses
          before the others and made peace; but now I need only say this: I think that she will join
          forces with you in carrying out your policy, especially if she can be made to see that
          your object is to prepare for the campaign against the barbarians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> That it is not, therefore, impossible for you to bring these cities together, I think
          has become evident to you from what I have said. But more than that, I believe I can
          convince you by many examples that it will also be easy for you to do this. For if it can
          be shown that other men in the past have undertaken enterprises which were not, indeed,
          more noble or more righteous than that which I have advised, but of greater magnitude and
          difficulty, and have actually brought them to pass, what ground will be left to my
          opponents to argue that you will not accomplish the easier task more quickly than other
          men the harder? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Consider first the exploits of Alcibiades.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the career
            of the brilliant, unscrupulous Alcibiades see Grote, <title>Hist.</title> vi. pp. 301
            ff., vii. 49 ff., and <bibl n="Plut. Alc. 1">Plut. Alc.</bibl></note> Although he was
          exiled from <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName><note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">He was exiled on the charge of having profaned the Eleusinian
            Mysteries.</note> and observed that the others who had before labored under this
          misfortune had been cowed<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For example, Themistocles.</note>
          because of the greatness of the city, yet he did not show the same submissive spirit as
          they; on the contrary, convinced that he must attempt to bring about his return by force,
          he deliberately chose to make war upon her.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By stirring up
            and aiding, through his great personal influence and his sagacity, all the enemies of
              <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in the Peloponnesian War.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now if one should attempt to speak in detail of the events of that time, he would find it
          impossible to recount them all exactly, and for the present occasion the recital would
          perhaps prove wearisome. But so great was the confusion into which he plunged not only
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> but <placeName key="tgn,7011065"
            >Lacedaemon</placeName> and all the rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName> as well, that we, the Athenians, suffered what all the world
            knows;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The defeat at <placeName key="tgn,6000070"
              >Aegospotami</placeName>, and after that the rule of the “thirty tyrants,” and later
            the “decarchy.”</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>that the rest of the Hellenes fell upon such evil days that even now the calamities
          engendered in the several states by reason of that war are not yet forgotten;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Under the rule of the decarchies described in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.111">Isoc. 4.111 ff.</bibl></note> and that the Lacedaemonians, who then
          appeared to be at the height of their fortune, are reduced to their present state of
          misfortune,—all on account of Alcibiades.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Isocrates does
            not much exaggerate the mischief he wrought in Greek affairs generally.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For because they were persuaded by him to covet the sovereignty of the sea, they lost
          even their leadership on land; so that if one were to assert that they became subject to
          the dominion of their present ills<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For this play of words—
              <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)rxh/</foreign>“beginning,” <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >a)rxh/</foreign>“dominion” — cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.119">Isoc. 4.119</bibl>, <bibl
              n="Isoc. 3.28">Isoc. 3.28</bibl>, <bibl n="Isoc. 8.101">Isoc. 8.101</bibl>.</note>
          when they attempted to seize the dominion of the sea, he could not be convicted of
          falsehood. Alcibiades, however, after having caused these great calamities, was restored
          to his city, having won a great reputation, though not, indeed, enjoying the commendation
          of all.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At length Alcibiades fell out with <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>' enemies, and began to intrigue in her favor;
            and so effectively did he work that his services were recognized at home and he was
            welcomed back to take again a leading part in the life of <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, <date when="-0408">408 B.C.</date> There
            appears to have been no open opposition to his return. The many who distrusted him
            probably thought him less dangerous at home than in exile.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The career of Conon,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.142">Isoc.
              4.142 ff.</bibl></note> not many years later, is a counterpart to that of Alcibiades.
          After his defeat in the naval engagement in the <placeName key="tgn,7002638"
            >Hellespont</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The battle of <placeName
              key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>.</note> for which not he but his fellow
          commanders were responsible, he was too chagrined to return home; instead he sailed to
            <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>, where he spent some time attending to
          his private interests.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 9.52">Isoc. 9.52
              ff.</bibl></note> But learning that Agesilaus had crossed over into Asia with a large
            force<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See 86, 87, and <bibl n="Isoc. L. 9.13">Isoc.
              Letter 9.13-14</bibl>.</note> and was ravaging the country, he was so dauntless of
          spirit </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>that, although he possessed no resource whatever save his body and his wits, he was yet
          confident that he could conquer the Lacedaemonians, albeit they were the first power in
            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> on both land and sea; and, sending word
          to the generals of the Persian king, he promised that he would do this. What need is there
          to tell more of the story? For he collected a naval force off <placeName key="tgn,7011266"
            >Rhodes</placeName>, won a victory over the Lacedaemonians in a sea-fight,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Battle of <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>,
              <date when="-0394">394 B.C.</date> There is a dramatic significance in the fact that
            Conon fought in the battle of <placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName> which
            gave <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> the supremacy and in the battle
            of <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName> which took it from her.</note>
          deposed them from their sovereignty, and set the Hellenes free.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">From Spartan rule.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And not only did he rebuild the walls of his country,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">He
            restored the walls which had been torn down as one of the terms imposed upon <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> after the battle of <placeName
              key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>. <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 4.8.9">Xen. Hell. 4.8.9
              ff.</bibl></note> but he restored <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>
          to the same high repute from which she had fallen. And yet who could have expected that a
          man whose own fortunes had fallen so low would completely reverse the fortunes of
            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, degrading some of the Hellenic states
          from places of honor and raising others into prominence? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Again, there is the case of Dionysius<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Dionysius, the
            Elder, tyrant of <placeName key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, <date
              from="-0406" to="-0367">406-367 B.C.</date></note>(for I desire you to be convinced
          by many instances that the course of action to which I am urging you is an easy one). He
          was a person of small account among the Syracusans in birth,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Diod. 13.96">Dio. Sic. 13.96</bibl>.</note> in reputation, and in
          all other respects;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Yet Isocrates once wrote to him a most
            respectful letter ( <bibl n="Isoc. L. 1">Isoc. Letter 1</bibl>).</note> yet, being
          inspired by a mad and unreasoning passion for monarchy, and having the hardihood to do
          anything which advanced him to this goal, he made himself master of <placeName
            key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName>, conquered all the states in <placeName
            key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> which were of Hellenic origin, and surrounded
          himself with a power on both land and sea<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A navy of three
            hundred and ten ships, <bibl n="Diod. 14.42">Dio. Sic. 14.42</bibl>, and an army of a
            hundred thousand men more or less, <bibl n="Diod. 2.5">Dio. Sic. 2.5</bibl>.</note>
          greater than any man before his time had possessed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Then again, Cyrus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cyrus the Great, founder of the Persian
            Empire, <bibl n="Isoc. 9.37">Isoc. 9.37</bibl>.</note>(that we may take account of the
          barbarians also), not withstanding the fact that as a child he was exposed by his mother
          on the public highway<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.132">Isoc.
              5.132</bibl> and <bibl n="Hdt. 1.108">Hdt. 1.108</bibl>.</note> and was picked up by a
          Persian woman,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl n="Hdt. 1.112">Hdt. 1.112
            ff.</bibl></note> so completely reversed his fortunes that he became master of all Asia.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now if Alcibiades in exile, and Conon after a disastrous defeat, and Dionysius, a man of
          no repute, and Cyrus, with his pitiable start in life, advanced so far and achieved such
          mighty deeds, how can we fail to expect that you, who are sprung from such ancestors, who
          are king of <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> and master of so many
          peoples, will effect with ease this union which we have discussed? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Consider how worthy a thing it is to undertake, above all, deeds of such a character
          that if you succeed you will cause your own reputation to rival that of the foremost men
          of history, while if you fall short of your expectations you will at any rate win the good
          will of all the Hellenes—which is a better thing to gain than to take by force many
          Hellenic cities;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. L. 2.21">Isoc. Letter
              2.21</bibl>: “It is a much greater glory to capture the good will of states than their
            fortifications.”</note> for achievements of the latter kind entail envy and hostility
          and much opprobrium, but that which I have urged entails none of these things. Nay, if
          some god were to give you the choice of the interests and the occupations in which you
          would wish to spend your life, you could not, at least if you took my advice, choose any
          in preference to this; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="69" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for you will not only be envied of others, but you will also count yourself a happy man.
          For what good fortune could then surpass your own? Men of the highest renown will come as
          ambassadors from the greatest states to your court; you will advise with them about the
          general welfare, for which no other man will be found to have shown a like concern; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="70" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>you will see all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> on tiptoe with interest
          in whatever you happen to propose; and no one will be indifferent to the measures which
          are being decided in your councils, but, on the contrary, some will seek news of how
          matters stand, some will pray that you will not be thwarted in your aims, and others will
          fear lest something befall you before your efforts are crowned with success. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="71" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If all this should come to pass, would you not have good reason to be proud? Would you
          not rejoice throughout your life in the knowledge that you had been a leader in such great
          affairs? And what man that is even moderately endowed with reason would not exhort you to
          fix your choice above all upon that course of action which is capable of bearing at one
          and the same time the twofold fruits, if I may so speak, of surpassing joys and of
          imperishable honors? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="72" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now I should content myself with what I have already said on this topic, had I not
          passed over a certain matter—not that it slipped my memory, but because I hesitated to
          speak of it—which I am now resolved to disclose to you. For I think that it is profitable
          for you to hear about it, and that it is becoming in me to speak, as I am wont to do,
          without reserve. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="73" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I observe that you are being painted in false colors by men who are jealous of you,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Demosthenes and his party. On Isocrates and Demosthenes see
            Havet, Introd. to Cartelier's <bibl n="Isoc. 15.">Isoc. 15.</bibl>pp. xlviii ff.</note>
          for one thing, and are, besides, in the habit of stirring up trouble in their own
          cities—men who look upon a state of peace which is for the good of all as a state of war
          upon their selfish interests. Heedless of all other considerations, they keep talking
          about your power, representing that it is being built up, not in behalf of <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, but against her, that you have for a long time
          been plotting against us all, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="74" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and that, while you are giving it out that you intend to go to the rescue of the
            Messenians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Messenians were at war with <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and in alliance with Philip. <bibl
              n="Paus. 4.28.2">Paus. 4.28.2</bibl>.</note> if you can settle the Phocian question,
          you really design to subdue the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> to
          your rule. The Thessalians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.20">Isoc.
              5.20</bibl>.</note> they say, and the Thebans, and all those who belong to the
            Amphictyony,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Amphictyony was an association of states
            for the protection of the worship of Apollo at <placeName key="perseus,Delphi"
              >Delphi</placeName> (Grote, <title>Hist.</title> ii. pp. 284 ff.). The members of the
            Amphictyony, among whom the Thebans and the Thessalians were prominent, were now engaged
            in the Sacred War against the Phocians, seeking to wrest from the latter the control of
            the Temple. In 338 B. C. Philip had been invited by the Amphictyony to join them against
            the Phocians.</note> stand ready to follow your lead while the Argives, the Messenians,
          the Megalopolitans,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 5.49">Isoc. 5.49
              ff.</bibl></note> and many of the others are prepared to join forces with you and wipe
          out the Lacedaemonians; and if you succeed in doing this, you will easily be master of the
          rest of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="75" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>By speaking this rubbish, by pretending to have exact knowledge and by speedily effecting
          in words the overthrow of the whole world, they are convincing many people. They convince,
          most of all, those who hunger for the same calamities as do the speech-makers; next, those
          who exercise no judgement about their common welfare, but, utterly obtuse in their own
          perceptions, are very grateful to men who pretend to feel alarm and fear in their behalf;
          and lastly, those who do not deny that you appear to be plotting against the Hellenes, but
          are of the opinion that the purpose with which you are charged is a worthy ambition. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="76" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For these latter are so far divorced from intelligence that they do not realize that one
          may apply the same words in some cases to a man's injury, in others to his advantage. For
          example, if at the present moment one were to say that the King of Asia was plotting
          against the Hellenes, and had made preparations to send an expedition against us, he would
          not he saying anything disparaging of him; nay, he would, on the contrary, make us think
          more highly of his courage and his worth. But if, on the other hand, one should bring this
          charge against one of the descendants of Heracles, who made himself the benefactor of all
            <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, he would bring upon him the greatest
          opprobrium. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="77" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For who would not feel indignation and loathing if a man should be found to be plotting
          against those in whose behalf his ancestor elected to live a life of perils, and if he
          made no effort to preserve the good will which the latter had bequeathed as a legacy to
          his posterity, but, heedless of these examples, set his heart on reprehensible and wicked
          deeds? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="78" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> You ought to give these matters careful thought, and not look on with indifference while
          rumors are springing up around you of the sort which your enemies seek to fasten upon you,
          but which your friends, to a man, would not hesitate to deny. And yet it is in the
          feelings of both these parties that you can best see the truth as to your own interests.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="79" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Perhaps, however, you conceive that it argues a mean spirit to pay attention to the
          drivelers who heap abuse upon you and to those who are influenced by what they say,
          especially when your own conscience is free from any sense of guilt. But you ought not to
          despise the multitude nor count it a little thing to have the respect of the whole world;
          on the contrary, you ought then, and only then, to be satisfied that you enjoy a
          reputation which is good and great and worthy of yourself and of your forefathers and of
          the achievements of your line, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="80" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>when you have brought the Hellenes to feel toward you as you see the Lacedaemonians feel
          toward their kings,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. L. 2.6">Isoc. Letter
              2.6</bibl>.</note> and as your companions feel toward yourself. And it is not
          difficult for you to attain this if you determine to show yourself equally friendly to
          all, and cease treating some of the cities as friends and others as strangers, and if,
          furthermore, you fix your choice upon the kind of policy by which you can make yourself
          trusted by the Hellenes and feared by the barbarians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="81" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And do not be surprised (as I said in my letter to Dionysius after he had made himself
          master of <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>) that I, who am not a general
          nor a public orator nor in any other position of authority, have expressed myself to you
          more boldly than the others. The fact is that nature has placed me more at a disadvantage
          than any of my fellow-citizens for a public career:<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Isocrates dwells on his disabilities repeatedly. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. L. 1.9">Isoc.
              Letter 1.9</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. L. 8.7">Isoc. Letter 8.7</bibl>; and <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.9-10">Isoc. 12.9-10</bibl>. See General Introd. p. xix.</note> I was not
          given a strong enough voice nor sufficient assurance to enable me to deal with the mob, to
          take abuse, and bandy words with the men who haunt the rostrum; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="82" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but, though some will condemn my taste in saying so, I do lay claim to sane judgement and
          good education, and I would count myself in comparison with others not among the last, but
          among the foremost. And that is why I endeavor in this way, for which my nature and powers
          are suited, to give advice to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and to
          the Hellenes at large and to the most distinguished among men. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="83" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now regarding myself, and regarding the course which you should take toward the
          Hellenes, perhaps no more need be said. But as to the expedition against Asia, we shall
          urge upon the cities which I have called upon you to reconcile that it is their duty to go
          to war with the barbarians, only when we see that they have ceased from discord. For the
          present, I shall address myself to you, not, however, with the same confidence as I had at
          that period of my life when I was writing on this same subject. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="84" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For then I challenged my audience to visit their ridicule and contempt upon me if I did
          not manifestly treat the question in a way which was worthy of the matter in hand and of
          my reputation and of the time which I had devoted to the discourse.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.14">Isoc. 4.14</bibl>.</note> But now I dread lest what I say
          may fall far short of every claim I then made; for, apart from the other disabilities
          under which I labor, my <title>Panegyricus</title>, which has enriched the other men who
          make philosophy their business,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Not an empty boast. See
            Havet, Introduction to Cartelier's <bibl n="Isoc. 15">Isoc. 15</bibl> pp. lxxv
            ff.</note> has left me quite impoverished, because I am neither willing to repeat what I
          have written in that discourse nor am I at my age able to cast about for new things. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="85" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>However, I must not shirk my task, but must say in support of the enterprise which I have
          proposed whatever occurs to me as likely to persuade you to undertake it. For even if I
          fall short in any degree, and am not able to write in the style of my former publications,
          I think that I shall at any rate present an attractive sketch for those who have the
          energy to elaborate the details and carry the work to completion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="86" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The point of departure, then, which I have taken for my whole discussion is, I believe,
          the one which is proper for those who urge an expedition against Asia.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.15">Isoc. 4.15</bibl>.</note> For one
          must undertake nothing until he finds the Hellenes doing one of two things: either
          actually supporting the undertaking or according it their entire approval. It was this
          which Agesilaus, for all that he was looked upon as the most sagacious of the
          Lacedaemonians, disregarded, not because of incapacity but because of ambition. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="87" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For he had two aims, which, though laudable, were not consistent, and could not he
          carried out at the same time, since he was resolved both to make war against the King and
          to restore his friends to their cities and put them in control of affairs.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The same explanation of Agesilaus's failure is given in <bibl
              n="Isoc. L. 9.13">Isoc. Letter 9.13</bibl>.</note> Naturally the result of his efforts
          in behalf of his friends was that the Hellenes were involved in troubles and perils, and,
          owing to the confusion which arose at home, had neither the time nor the power to make war
          upon the barbarians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="88" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So from the mistakes of inadvertence at that time it is easy to draw the lesson that
          those who would take sane counsel must not begin a war against the King until someone has
          composed the quarrels of the Hellenes and has cured them of the madness which now afflicts
          them. And this is just what I have advised you to do. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="89" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> On these points no man of intelligence would venture to contradict me. But I think that
          if any of the others should be prompted to advise you in favor of the expedition against
          Asia, they would resort to a plea of this kind: that it has been the fortune of all who
          have undertaken a war against the King, without exception, to rise from obscurity to
          brilliant distinction, from poverty to wealth, and from low estate to be masters of many
          lands and cities. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="90" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I, however, am not going to urge you on such grounds, but by the example of men who were
          looked upon as failures: I mean those who took the field with Cyrus and Clearchus.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.145-149">Isoc. 4.145-149</bibl>, where
            the same episode is used to the same point in similar language.</note> Every one agrees
          that these won as complete a victory in battle over all the forces of the King as if they
          had come to blows with their womenfolk, but that at the very moment when they seemed to be
          masters of the field they failed of success, owing to the impetuosity of Cyrus. For he in
          his exultation rushed in pursuit far in advance of the others; and, being caught in the
          midst of the enemy, was killed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="91" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the King, not withstanding that his foes had suffered so severe a loss, felt so
          thorough a contempt for his own forces that he invited Clearchus and the other captains to
          a parley, promising to give them great gifts and to pay their soldiers their wages in full
          and to give them safe convoy home; then, having lured them by such prospects, and having
          assured them by the most solemn pledges known to the Persians, he seized them and put them
          to death, deliberately choosing to outrage the gods rather than risk a clash with our
          soldiers, bereft though they now were of Cyrus's aid. And what challenge could be nobler
          or more convincing than this? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="92" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it is evident that, if it had not been for Cyrus, even that army would have
          overthrown the power of the King. But for you it is easy both to guard against the
          disaster which befell at that time and to equip yourself with an armament much stronger
          than that which defeated the forces of the King. How, then, since you possess both these
          advantages, can you fail to undertake this expedition with all confidence? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="93" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And let no one suppose that I desire to conceal the fact that I have in some instances
          expressed myself in the same manner as upon a former occasion. For, coming to the same
          thoughts, I have preferred not to go through the effort of striving to phrase differently
          what has already been well expressed.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This apology is
            curious, since Greek orators habitually repeated identical passages in dealing with the
            same situations. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.74">Isoc. 15.74</bibl>.</note> It is true that if
          I were making an epideictic speech<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.55">Isoc. 15.55</bibl>. An “epideictic” speech was a lecture whose aim was
            to display the rhetorical powers of the speaker.</note> I should try to avoid
          scrupulously all such repetitions; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="94" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but now that I am urging my views upon you, I should have been foolish if I had spent
          more time on the style than on the subject matter, and if, furthermore, seeing that the
          other orators make free with my writings, I alone had abstained from what I have said in
          the past. So, then, I may perhaps be allowed to use what is my own, if at any time I am
          greatly pressed and find it suitable, although I would not now any more than in times past
          appropriate anything from the writings of other men. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="95" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> We may, then, regard these points as settled. But next in order I think that I should
          speak of the war-strength which will he available to you as compared with that which
          Clearchus and his followers had. First and most important of all, you will have the good
          will of the Hellenes if you choose to abide by the advice which I have given you
          concerning them; they, on the other hand, found the Hellenes intensely hostile because of
          the decarchies<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.110">Isoc. 4.110
              ff.</bibl></note> which the Lacedaemonians had set up; for the Hellenes thought that,
          if Cyrus and Clearchus should succeed, their yoke would be heavier still, but that if the
          King conquered they would be delivered from their present hardships; and this is just what
          did happen to them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="96" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Besides, you will find as many soldiers at your service as you wish, for such is now the
          state of affairs in <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> that it is easier to
          get together a greater and stronger army from among those who wander in exile than from
          those who live under their own polities.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.168">Isoc. 4.168</bibl> and note.</note> But in those days there was no
          body of professional soldiers, and so, being compelled to collect mercenaries from the
          several states, they had to spend more money on bounties<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Cyrus gave Clearchus about ten thousand pounds with which to levy mercenaries. <bibl
              n="Xen. Anab. 1.1.9">Xen. Anab. 1.1.9</bibl>.</note> for their recruiting agents than
          on pay for the troops. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="97" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And, lastly, if we should be inclined to make a careful review of the two cases and
          institute a comparison between you, who are to be at the head of the present expedition
          and to decide on every measure, and Clearchus, who was in charge of the enterprise of that
          day, we should find that he had never before been in command of any force whatever on
          either land or sea and yet attained renown from the misfortune which befell him on the
          continent of Asia; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="98" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>while you, on the contrary, have succeeded in so many and such mighty achievements that
          if I were making them the subject of a speech before another audience, I should do well to
          recount them, but, since I am addressing myself to you, you would rightly think it
          senseless and gratuitous in me to tell you the story of your own deeds. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="99" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It is well for me to speak to you also about the two Kings, the one against whom I am
          advising you to take the field, and the one against whom Clearchus made war, in order that
          you may know the temper and the power of each. In the first place, the father<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Artaxerxes II., <date from="-0405" to="-0359">405-359
              B.C.</date></note> of the present King once defeated our city<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">This is inexact. He is probably thinking of the defeat of the
            Athenians in the Peloponnnesian War in which <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName> had the assistance of <placeName key="tgn,7000231"
              >Persia</placeName>; but Artaxerxes II. came to the throne in the year of the battle
            of <placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>.</note> and later the city of
          the Lacedaemonians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At the battle of <placeName
              key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName> with the help of Conon, <date when="-0394">394
              B.C.</date></note> while this King<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Artaxerxes III.,
              <date from="-0359" to="-0339">359-339 B.C.</date></note> has never overcome
          anyone of the armies which have been violating his territory. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="100" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Secondly, the former took the whole of Asia from the Hellenes by the terms of the
            Treaty<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Treaty of Antalcidas. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.115"
              >Isoc. 4.115 ff.</bibl>, 175 ff.</note>; while this King is so far from exercising
          dominion over others that he is not in control even of the cities which were surrendered
          to him; and such is the state of affairs that there is no one who is not in doubt what to
          believe—whether he has given them up because of his cowardice, or whether they have
          learned to despise and contemn the power of the barbarians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="101" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Consider, again, the state of affairs in his empire. Who could hear the facts and not be
          spurred to war against him? <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> was, it is
          true, in revolt<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.140">Isoc. 4.140</bibl>,
            161.</note> even when Cyrus made his expedition; but her people nevertheless were living
          in continual fear lest the King might some day lead an army in person and overcome the
          natural obstacles which, thanks to the <placeName key="tgn,1127805">Nile</placeName>,
          their country presents, and all their military defenses as well. But now this King has
          delivered them from that dread; for after he had brought together and fitted out the
          largest force he could possibly raise and marched against them, he retired from <placeName
            key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> not only defeated, but laughed at and scorned as
          unfit either to be a king or to command an army. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="102" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Furthermore, <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> and <placeName
            key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,7002470"
            >Cilicia</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.161">Isoc.
              4.161</bibl>.</note> and that region from which the barbarians used to recruit their
          fleet, belonged at that time to the King, but now they have either revolted from him or
          are so involved in war and its attendant ills that none of these peoples is of any use to
          him; while to you, if you desire to make war upon him, they will be serviceable. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="103" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And mark also that Idrieus,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.162">Isoc.
              4.162</bibl>.</note> who is the most prosperous of the present rulers of the mainland,
          must in the nature of things be more hostile to the interests of the King than are those
          who are making open war against him; verily he would be of all men the most perverse if he
          did not desire the dissolution of that empire which outrages his brother,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Mausolus.</note> which made war upon himself, and which at all
          times has never ceased to plot against him in its desire to be master of his person and of
          all his wealth. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="104" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It is through fear of these things that he is now constrained to pay court to the King
          and to send him much tribute every year; but if you should cross over to the mainland with
          an army, he would greet you with joy, in the belief that you were come to his relief; and
          you will also induce many of the other satraps to throw off the King's power if you
          promise them “freedom” and scatter broadcast over Asia that word which, when sown among
          the Hellenes, has broken up both our empire and that of the Lacedaemonians.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">“Freedom” of the Greeks from Athenian tyranny was the avowed
            object of the Spartans in the Peloponnesian War, <bibl n="Thuc. 4.86">Thuc. 4.86</bibl>.
            Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.122">Isoc. 4.122</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="105" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I might go on and endeavor to speak at greater length on how you could carry on the war
          so as to triumph most quickly over the power of the King; but as things are, I fear that I
          might lay myself open to criticism if, having had no part in a soldier's life, I should
          now venture to advise you, whose achievements in war are without parallel in number and
          magnitude. Therefore on this subject I think I need say nothing more. But to proceed with
          the rest of my discourse, I believe that both your own father<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Amyntas. II.</note> and the founder of your kingdom,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Perdiccas I. See 32, note.</note> and also the progenitor of your race<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Heracles. The latter was precluded by his divinity; Amyntas
            and Perdiccas by their death.</note>— were it lawful for Heracles and possible for the
          others to appear as your counsellors—would advise the very things which I have urged. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="106" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I draw my inference from their actions while they lived. For your father, in dealing with
          those states which I am urging you to cultivate, kept on friendly terms<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">With <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, <bibl
              n="Aeschin. 2.26">Aeschin. 2.26</bibl>; with <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName>, <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.2.38">Xen. Hell. 5.2.38</bibl>.</note> with
          them all. And the founder of your empire, although he aspired higher than did his fellow
            citizens<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Of <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
              >Argos</placeName>.</note> and set his heart on a king's power, was not minded to take
          the same road as others who set out to attain a like ambition. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="107" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For they endeavored to win this honor by engendering factions, disorder, and bloodshed in
          their own cities; he, on the other hand, held entirely aloof from Hellenic territory, and
          set his heart upon occupying the throne of <placeName key="tgn,7002715"
            >Macedon</placeName>. For he knew full well that the Hellenes were not accustomed to
          submit to the rule of one man, while the other races were incapable of ordering their
          lives without the control of some such power. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="108" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And so it came about, owing to his unique insight in this regard, that his kingship has
          proved to be quite set apart from that of the generality of kings: for, because he alone
          among the Hellenes did not claim the right to rule over a people of kindred race, he alone
          was able to escape the perils incident to one-man power. For history discovers to us the
          fact that those among the Hellenes who have managed to acquire such authority have not
          only been destroyed themselves but have been blotted, root and branch, from the face of
          the earth;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Pisistratidae of <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. A recent case in point was the murder of
            Alexander of Pherae. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.5">Isoc. 2.5</bibl>.</note> while he, on the
          contrary, lived a long and happy life and left his seed in possession of the same honors
          which he himself had enjoyed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="109" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Coming now to Heracles, all others who praise him harp endlessly on his valor or recount
          his labors; and not one, either of the poets or of the historians, will be found to have
          commemorated his other excellences—I mean those which pertain to the spirit. I, on the
          other hand, see here a field set apart and entirely unworked—a field not small nor barren,
          but teeming with many a theme for praise and with glorious deeds, yet demanding a speaker
          with ability to do them justice. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="110" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If this subject had claimed my attention when I was younger, I should have found it easy
          to prove that it was more by his wisdom, his lofty ambition, and his justice than by his
          strength of body that your ancestor surpassed all who lived before his day. But
          approaching the subject at my present age, and seeing what a wealth of material there is
          in it to discuss, I have felt that my present powers were unequal to the task, and I have
          also realized that my discourse would run on to twice the length of that which is now
          before you to be read. For these reasons, then, I have refrained from touching upon his
          other exploits and have singled out one only—a story which is pertinent and in keeping
          with what I have said before, while being of a length best proportioned to the subject now
          in hand. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="111" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When Heracles saw that <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> was rife with
          wars and factions and many other afflictions, he first brought these troubles to an end
          and reconciled the cities with each other,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See Diod. iv.
            17.</note> and then showed by his example to coming generations with whom and against
          whom it was their duty to go to war. For he made an expedition against <placeName
            key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl n="Isoc. 9.16"
              >Isoc. 9.16</bibl>.</note> which was in those days the strongest power in <placeName
            key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName>, and so far did he excel in generalship those who at
          a later time waged war against this same city, that, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="112" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>while they with the combined strength of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>
          found it difficult to take <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> after a siege
          which lasted ten years, he, on the other hand, in less than as many days, and with a small
          expedition, easily took the city by storm. After this, he put to death to a man all the
            princes<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Chiefs, of barbarian tribes, such as Diomedes,
            Mygdon, Sarpedon, Busiris, Antaeus.</note> of the tribes who dwelt along the shores of
          both continents<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="tgn,1000003"
              >Europe</placeName> and Asia. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.35">Isoc. 4.35</bibl>.</note>; and
          these he could never have destroyed had he not first conquered their armies. When he had
          done these things, he set up the Pillars of Heracles, as they are called, to be a trophy
          of victory over the barbarians, a monument to his own valor and the perils he had
          surmounted, and to mark the bounds of the territory of the Hellenes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="113" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> My purpose in relating all this is that you may see that by my words I am exhorting you
          to a course of action which, in the light of their deeds, it is manifest that your
          ancestors chose as the noblest of all. Now, while all who are blessed with understanding
          ought to set before themselves the greatest of men as their model, and strive to become
          like him, it behoves you above all to do so. For since you have no need to follow alien
          examples but have before you one from your own house, have we not then the right to expect
          that you will be spurred on by this and inspired by the ambition to make yourself like the
          ancestor of your race? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="114" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I do not mean that you will be able to imitate Heracles in all his exploits; for even
          among the gods there are some who could not do that; but in the qualities of the spirit,
          in devotion to humanity, and in the good will which he cherished toward the Hellenes, you
          can come close to his purposes. And it lies in your power, if you will heed my words, to
          attain whatever glory you yourself desire; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="115" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for it is easier for you to rise from your present station and win the noblest fame than
          it has been to advance from the station which you inherited to the fame which is now
            yours.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Repeated in <bibl n="Isoc. L. 3.5">Isoc. Letter
              3.5</bibl>.</note> And mark that I am summoning you to an undertaking in which you
          will make expeditions, not with the barbarians against men who have given you no just
          cause, but with the Hellenes against those upon whom it is fitting that the descendants of
          Heracles should wage war. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="116" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And do not be surprised if throughout my speech I am trying to incline you to a policy
          of kindness to the Hellenes and of gentleness and humanity. For harshness is, I observe,
          grievous both to those who exercise it and to those upon whom it falls, while gentleness,
          whether in man or in the other animals, bears a good name; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="117" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>nay, in the case of the gods also we invoke as the “Heavenly Ones” those who bless us
          with good things, while to those who are agents of calamities and punishments we apply
          more hateful epithets; in honor of the former, both private persons and states erect
          temples and altars, whereas we honor the latter neither in our prayers nor in our
          sacrifices, but practice rites to drive away their evil presence.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The contrast is between Zeus, Apollo, Athena, etc., and under-world deities
            Hades, Persephone, the Furies, etc.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="118" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Bearing ever in mind these truths, you should habitually act and strive to the end that
          all men shall cherish even more than they do now such an opinion of your character.
          Indeed, those who crave a greater fame than that of other men must map out in their
          thoughts a course of action which, while practicable, is at the same time close to the
          ideal, and seek to carry it into effect as opportunity presents a way. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="119" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> From many considerations you may realize that you ought to act in this way, but
          especially from the experiences of Jason.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Jason, tyrant of
            Pherae, in <placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName>. His “talked-of” expedition
            against <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> is mentioned also by <bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 6.1.12">Xen. Hell. 6.1.12</bibl>. See General Introd. p. xl,
            footnote.</note> For he, without having achieved anything comparable to what you have
          done, won the highest renown, not from what he did, but from what he said; for he kept
          talking as if he intended to cross over to the continent and make war upon the King. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="120" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Now since Jason by use of words alone advanced himself so far, what opinion must we
          expect the world will have of you if you actually do this thing; above all, if you
          undertake to conquer the whole empire of the King, or, at any rate, to wrest from it a
          vast extent of territory and sever from it—to use a current phrase—“Asia from <placeName
            key="tgn,7002470">Cilicia</placeName> to Sinope”<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A catch
            phrase for the territory of <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName>. Cf.
            “Asia from <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName> to Sinope” in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.162">Isoc. 4.162</bibl>.</note>; and if, furthermore, you undertake to
          establish cities in this region, and to settle in permanent abodes those who now, for lack
          of the daily necessities of life, are wandering from place to place and committing
          outrages upon whomsoever they encounter?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. L. 9.9">Isoc. Letter 9.9</bibl>. Cf. 96; <bibl n="Isoc. 4.168">Isoc.
              4.168</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 8.24">Isoc. 8.24</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="121" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If we do not stop these men from banding together, by providing sufficient livelihood for
          them, they will grow before we know it into so great a multitude as to be a terror no less
          to the Hellenes than to the barbarians. But we pay no heed to them; nay, we shut our eyes
          to the fact that a terrible menace which threatens us all alike is waxing day by day. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="122" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It is therefore the duty of a man who is high-minded, who is a lover of <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, who has a broader vision than the rest of the
          world, to employ these bands in a war against the barbarians, to strip from that empire
          all the territory which I defined a moment ago, to deliver these homeless wanderers from
          the ills by which they are afflicted and which they inflict upon others, to collect them
          into cities, and with these cities to fix the boundary of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>, making of them buffer states to shield us all. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="123" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For by doing this, you will not only make them prosperous, but you will put us all on a
          footing of security. If, however, you do not succeed in these objects, this much you will
          at any rate easily accomplish,—the liberation of the cities which are on the coast of
          Asia. But no matter what part of this undertaking you are able to carry out, or only
          attempt to carry out, you cannot fail to attain distinguished glory; and it will be well
          deserved if only you will make this the goal of your own efforts and urge on the Hellenes
          in the same course. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="124" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For as things now are, who would not have reason to be amazed<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For this and what follows cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.133">Isoc.
            4.133-136</bibl>.</note> at the turn events have taken and to feel contempt for us, when
          among the barbarians, whom we have come to look upon as effeminate and unversed in war and
          utterly degenerate from luxurious living,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Persian
            effeminacy is described at length in <bibl n="Isoc. 4.150">Isoc. 4.150 ff.</bibl></note>
          men have arisen<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Dareius, Xerxes.</note> who thought
          themselves worthy to rule over <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, while
          among the Hellenes no one has aspired so high as to attempt to make us masters of Asia?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="125" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nay, we have dropped so far behind the barbarians that, while they did not hesitate even
          to begin hostilities against the Hellenes, we do not even have the spirit to pay them back
          for the injuries we have suffered at their hands. On the contrary, although they admit
          that in all their wars they have no soldiers of their own nor generals nor any of the
          things which are serviceable in times of danger, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="126" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but have to send and get all these from us,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.135">Isoc. 4.135</bibl>.</note> we have gone so far in our passion to
          injure ourselves that, whereas it lies in our power to possess the wealth of the
          barbarians in security and peace, we continue to wage war upon each other over
            trifles,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.133">Isoc.
            4.133-136</bibl>.</note> and we actually help to reduce to subjection those who
            revolt<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.134">Isoc.
            4.134</bibl>.</note> from the authority of the King, and sometimes, unwittingly, we ally
          ourselves with our hereditary foes<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl n="Isoc. 4.157"
              >Isoc. 4.157</bibl>.</note> and seek to destroy those who are of our own race. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="127" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Therefore, since the others are so lacking in spirit, I think it is opportune for you to
          head the war against the King; and, while it is only natural for the other descendants of
          Heracles, and for men who are under the bonds of their polities and laws, to cleave fondly
          to that state in which they happen to dwell, it is your privilege, as one who has been
          blessed with untrammeled freedom,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. 14, 15.</note> to
          consider all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> your fatherland,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.81">Isoc. 4.81</bibl>.</note> as did the
          founder of your race, and to be as ready to brave perils for her sake as for the things
          about which you are personally most concerned. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="128" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Perhaps there are those—men capable of nothing else but criticism—who will venture to
          rebuke me because I have chosen to challenge you to the task of leading the expedition
          against the barbarians and of taking Hellas under your care, while I have passed over my
          own city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="129" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Well, if I were trying to present this matter to any others before having broached it to
          my own country, which has thrice<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Twice from the
            barbarians—at Marathon and <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>; once from
            the Spartans at the battle of <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>, where the
            navy under Conon put an end to the Spartan hegemony.</note> freed Hellas—twice from the
          barbarians and once from the Lacedaemonian yoke—I should confess my error. In truth,
          however, it will be found that I turned to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> first of all and endeavored to win her over to this cause with all
          the earnestness of which my nature is capable,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the
              <title>Panegyricus</title>.</note> but when I perceived that she cared less for what I
          said than for the ravings of the platform orators,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See
            General Introd. p. xxxviii.</note> I gave her up, although I did not abandon my efforts.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="130" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Wherefore I might justly be praised on every hand, because throughout my whole life I
          have constantly employed such powers as I possess in warring on the barbarians, in
          condemning those who opposed my plan, and in striving to arouse to action whoever I think
          will best be able to benefit the Hellenes in any way or to rob the barbarians of their
          present prosperity. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="131" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Consequently, I am now addressing myself to you, although I am not unaware that when I am
          proposing this course many will look at it askance, but that when you are actually
          carrying it out all will rejoice in it; for no one has had any part in what I have
          proposed, but when the benefits from it shall have been realized in fact, everyone without
          fail will look to have his portion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="132" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Consider also what a disgrace it is to sit idly by and see Asia flourishing more than
            <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and the barbarians enjoying a greater
            prosperity<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.132">Isoc. 4.132</bibl>,
            184, 187.</note> than the Hellenes; and, what is more, to see those who derive their
          power from Cyrus, who as a child was cast out by his mother on the public highway,
          addressed by the title of “The Great King,” while the descendants of Heracles, who because
          of his virtue was exalted by his father to the rank of a god,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 1.50">Isoc. 1.50</bibl>.</note> are addressed by meaner
            titles<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Spartan kings are merely “kings,” while the
            Persian king is “The Great King.”</note> than they. We must not allow this state of
          affairs to go on; no, we must change and reverse it entirely. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="133" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Rest assured that I should never have attempted to persuade you to undertake this at all
          had power and wealth been the only things which I saw would come of it; for I think that
          you already have more than enough of such things, and that any man is beyond measure
          insatiable who deliberately chooses the extreme hazard of either winning these prizes or
          losing his life. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="134" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>No, it is not with a view to the acquisition of wealth and power that I urge this course,
          but in the belief that by means of these you will win a name of surpassing greatness and
          glory. Bear in mind that while we all possess bodies that are mortal, yet by virtue of
          good will and praise and good report and memory which keeps pace with the passage of time
          we partake of immortality<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.37">Isoc.
              2.37</bibl>.</note>— a boon for which we may well strive with all our might and suffer
          any hardship whatsoever. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="135" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>You may observe that even common citizens of the best sort, who would exchange their
          lives for nothing else, are willing for the sake of winning glory to lay them down in
            battle;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 9.3">Isoc. 9.3</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 6.109">Isoc. 6.109</bibl>.</note> and, in general, that those who crave
          always an honor greater than they already possess are praised by all men, while those who
          are insatiable with regard to any other thing under the sun are looked upon as intemperate
          and mean.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The same sentiment is in <bibl n="Isoc. L. 3.4"
              >Isoc. Letter 3.4</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="136" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But more important than all that I have said is the truth that wealth and positions of
          power often fall into the hands of our foes, whereas the good will of our fellow
          countrymen and the other rewards which I have mentioned are possessions to which none can
          fall heir but our own children, and they alone. I could not, therefore, respect myself if
          I failed to advance these motives in urging you to make this expedition and wage war and
          brave its perils. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="137" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> You will best resolve upon this question if you feel that you are summoned to this task,
          not by my words only, but by your forefathers, by the cowardice of the Persians, and by
          all who have won great fame and attained the rank of demigods because of their campaigns
          against the barbarians, and, most of all, by the present opportunity, which finds you in
          the possession of greater power than has any of those who dwell in <placeName
            key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName>, and finds him against whom you are to make war
          more cordially hated and despised by the world at large than was ever any king before him.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="138" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I should have given much to be able to blend into one all the speeches I have delivered
          on this question; for the present discourse would then appear more worthy of its theme.
          But, as things are, it devolves upon you to search out and consider, from all my speeches,
          the arguments which bear upon and urge you to this war; for so you will best resolve upon
          the matter. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="139" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now I am not unaware that many of the Hellenes look upon the King's power as
            invincible.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.138">Isoc. 4.138
              ff.</bibl></note> Yet one may well marvel at them if they really believe that the
          power which was subdued to the will of a mere barbarian—an ill-bred<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cyrus. See 66.</note> barbarian at that—and collected in the cause of slavery,
          could not be scattered by a man of the blood of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>, of ripe experience in warfare, in the cause of freedom—and that too
          although they know that while it is in all cases difficult to construct a thing, to
          destroy it is, comparatively, an easy task. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="140" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Bear in mind that the men whom the world most admires and honors are those who unite in
          themselves the abilities of the statesman and the general. When, therefore, you see the
          renown which even in a single city is bestowed on men who possess these gifts, what manner
          of eulogies must you expect to hear spoken of you, when among all the Hellenes you shall
          stand forth as a statesman who has worked for the good of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>, and as a general who has overthrown the barbarians? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="141" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I, for my part, think that this will set a limit to human endeavor; for no other man will
          ever be able to do deeds greater than these, because among the Hellenes there will never
          be again so great an enterprise as that of leading us forward out of our innumerable wars
          into a spirit of concord; nor, among the barbarians, is it likely that so great a power
          will ever be built up again if once you shatter that which they now possess. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="142" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore, in generations yet to come, no one, no matter how surpassing his genius, will
          ever be in a position to do so great a thing. Yes, and speaking of those who lived before
          your time, I could show that their deeds are excelled by the things which you have even
          now accomplished, in no specious sense but in very truth; for since you have overthrown
          more nations than any of the Hellenes has ever taken cities, it would not be hard for me
          to prove, comparing you with each of them in turn, that you have accomplished greater
          things than they. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="143" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But I have deliberately abstained from this mode of comparison, and for two reasons:
          because some writers employ it in season and out of season, and also because I am
          unwilling to represent those whom the world regards as demigods as of less worth than men
          who are now living. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="144" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Ponder well the fact (to touch upon examples from the distant past) that while no man,
          whether poet or writer of prose, would applaud the wealth of Tantalus, or the rule of
          Pelops, or the power of Eurystheus, all the world, with one accord, would praise—next to
          the unrivalled excellence of Heracles and the goodness of Theseus—the men who marched
          against <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName> and all others who have proved to
          be like them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="145" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet we know that the bravest and most famous of them held their sway in little
          villages and petty islands; nevertheless they left behind them a name which rivals that of
          the gods and is renowned throughout the world. For all the world loves, not those who have
          acquired the greatest power for themselves alone, but those who have shown themselves to
          be the greatest benefactors of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="146" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And you will observe that this is the opinion which men hold, not of these heroes only,
          but of all mankind. Thus, no one would praise our city either because she was once
          mistress of the sea, or because she extorted such huge sums of money from her allies and
          carried them up into the Acropolis,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The treasury of the
            Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName> was originally in the
            island of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>; later it was transferred to
            the Parthenon at <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> nor yet,
          surely, because she obtained power over many cities—power to devastate them, or aggrandize
          them, or manage them according to her pleasure (for all these things it was possible for
          her to do); </p>
      </div>
      <div n="147" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>no, all these things have been the source of many complaints against her, while because
          of the battle of Marathon, the naval battle at <placeName key="tgn,7002340"
            >Salamis</placeName>, and most of all because her citizens abandoned their own homes to
          insure the deliverance of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">For these services see <bibl n="Isoc. 4.91">Isoc.
              4.91-96</bibl>.</note> she enjoys the encomiums of all mankind. The same opinion is
          held regarding the Lacedaemonians also; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="148" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>their defeat at <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName> is more
          admired than their many victories; the trophy<note anchored="true" resp="ed">He means the
            spot where the trophy was raised, marked later by the column erected by the Greeks.
              <bibl n="Hdt. 7..228">Hdt. 7..228</bibl>.</note> which was erected by the barbarians
          over the Lacedaemonians is an object of affectionate regard and of pilgrimages, while the
          trophies erected by the Lacedaemonians over their enemies call forth, not praise, but
          odium; for the former is regarded as a proof of valor, the latter of selfish greed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="149" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now if, after examining and reviewing all these admonitions in your own mind, you feel
          that my discourse is in any part rather weak and inadequate,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For like apologies see <bibl n="Isoc. 15.9">Isoc. 15.9</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.4">Isoc. 12.4</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. L. 6.6">Isoc. Letter
            6.6</bibl>.</note> set it down to my age, which might well claim the indulgence of all;
          but if it is up to the standard of my former publications, I would have you believe that
          it was not my old age that conceived it but the divine will that prompted it, not out of
          solicitude for me, but because of its concern for <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>, and because of its desire to deliver her out of her present
          distress and to crown you with a glory far greater than you now possess. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="150" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I think that you are not unaware in what manner the gods order the affairs of mortals:
          for not with their own hands do they deal out the blessings and curses that befall us;
          rather they inspire in each of us such a state of mind that good or ill, as the case may
          be, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="151" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>is visited upon us through one another. For example, it may be that even now the gods
          have assigned to me the task of speech while to you they allot the task of action,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. L. 9.17">Isoc. Letter 9.17</bibl>.</note>
          considering that you will be the best master in that province, while in the field of
          speech I might prove least irksome to my hearers. Indeed, I believe that even your past
          achievements would never have reached such magnitude had not one of the gods helped you to
          succeed; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="152" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and I believe he did so, not that you might spend your whole life warring upon the
          barbarians in <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> alone, but that, having been
          trained and having gained experience and come to know your own powers in these campaigns,
          you might set your heart upon the course which I have urged upon you. It were therefore
          shameful, now that fortune nobly leads the way, to lag behind and refuse to follow whither
          she desires to lead you forward. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="153" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It is my belief that, while you ought to honor everyone who has any praise for your past
          accomplishments, you ought to consider that those laud you in the noblest terms who judge
          your nature capable of even greater triumphs, and not those whose discourse has gratified
          you for the moment only, but those who will cause future generations to admire your
          achievements beyond the deeds of any man of the generations that are past. I would like to
          say many things in this strain, but I am not able; the reason why, I have stated more
          often than I ought. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="154" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It remains, then, to summarize what I have said in this discourse, in order that you may
          see in the smallest compass the substance of my counsels. I assert that it is incumbent
          upon you to work for the good of the Hellenes, to reign as king over the Macedonians,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The indigenous Macedonians are regarded as half
            barbarians.</note> and to extend your power over the greatest possible number of the
          barbarians. For if you do these things, all men will be grateful to you: the Hellenes for
          your kindness to them; the Macedonians if you reign over them, not like a tyrant, but like
          a king; and the rest of the nations, if by your hands they are delivered from barbaric
          despotism and are brought under the protection of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="155" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> How well this discourse has been composed with respect to appropriateness and finish of
          style is a question which it is fair to ask my hearers to answer; but that no one could
          give you better advice than this, or advice more suited to the present situation—of this I
          believe that I am well assured.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
