<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Spudias</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>This man Spudias and I, men of the jury, are married to two sisters, daughters of
                    Polyeuctus. Polyeuctus having died without male issue, I am forced to go to law
                    with the defendant in regard to the property which has been left. And if, men of
                    the jury, I had not shown all zeal and eagerness in my desire to find a
                    settlement and to submit the matters at issue to our friends, I should have
                    blamed myself for not choosing to suffer a trifling loss rather than engage in a
                    troublesome lawsuit. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>But, as it is, the more gentleness and consideration I used in talking with the
                    defendant, the more contempt he showed toward me. And now it appears that in my
                    contest with him we are in no sense on equal terms, but he can take the matter
                    lightly, since he has been accustomed to come often before you, whereas I fear
                    this very thing, that because of my lack of experience I may prove unable to
                    explain my case to you. None the less, men of the jury, I beg you to give heed.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>Polyeuctus was a man of Teithras,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Teithras was a
                        deme of the tribe Oeneïs.</note> not unknown, it may well be, to some of
                    you. This Polyeuctus, since he had no male children, adopted Leocrates, the
                    brother of his own wife; but since he had two daughters by the sister of
                    Leocrates, he gave the elder to me in marriage with a portion of forty minae,
                    and the younger to Leocrates.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Marriage between
                        uncle and niece was allowed in ancient <placeName key="tgn,7001393"
                            >Athens</placeName>. A man might even marry his half-sister (See <bibl
                            n="Dem. 57.2">Dem. 57.2</bibl>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>So matters stood, when a quarrel came about between Polyeuctus and Leocrates, as
                    to the nature of which I know of nothing which it is incumbent upon me to
                    relate, and Polyeuctus took away his daughter<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >This can mean only that he induced his daughter to go before the Archon and
                        demand a divorce.</note> and gave her in marriage to this man Spudias. After
                    this Leocrates, being greatly incensed, brought suit against Polyeuctus and
                    Spudias here, and they were forced to render an accounting in regard to all the
                    matters at issue, and in the end a settlement was reached on the terms that
                    Leocrates, on receiving back all that he had brought into the estate, should be
                    reconciled with Polyeuctus, and that final releases should be given from all
                    demands made by each upon the other. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>Now, why is it, men of the jury, that I have told you this? Because I did not
                    receive the whole of my wife’s portion, but a thousand drachmae were left unpaid
                    with the understanding that I should receive them on the death of Polyeuctus;
                    and so long as Leocrates was the heir of Polyeuctus, it was he who was
                    responsible to me for the debt; but when Leocrates had left the family, and
                    Polyeuctus was seriously ill, then, men of the jury, to secure the ten minae, I
                    took a mortgage on this house, the rents accruing from which Spudias seeks to
                    prevent me from collecting. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>In the first place, then, I shall bring before you as witnesses those who were
                    present when Polyeuctus betrothed his daughter to me with a portion of forty
                    minae; then I shall prove that what I received was less by a thousand drachmae;
                    and further that Polyeuctus always admitted that he was in my debt, and that he
                    introduced to me Leocrates as guarantor<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That
                        is, as the person who would be responsible for payment after his own
                        death.</note>; and that at his death he directed by his will that pillars
                    should be set up on the house in my favor for a thousand drachmae due on account
                    of my wife’s portion.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Please call the
                        witnesses.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>This, then, men of the jury, is one of the charges which I make against Spudias.
                    And in this matter what stronger or more solid ground could I have in coming
                    before you than the law which expressly ordains that, in all cases where men
                    have given a mortgage, there shall be no right of action for them or for their
                    heirs? But nevertheless it is to dispute this just provision that Spudias has
                    come here. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>A second claim, men of the jury, is the following: Aristogenes has deposed that
                    Polyeuctus, when about to die, charged that there were due him from Spudias two
                    minae with interest (this was the price of a domestic slave whom the defendant
                    had bought from Polyeuctus, but had neither paid the money nor has now entered
                    it in the general account); and furthermore there are eighteen hundred drachmae,
                    regarding which I am myself at a loss to know what reasonable thing he will have
                    to say. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>He had borrowed the money from the wife of Polyeuctus, and there are papers which
                    that lady left behind at her death, and the lady’s brothers are witnesses, for
                    they were present at all times and questioned her on every point, that there
                    might be no unpleasantness between us. It is, then, an outrageous and cruel
                    thing, men of the jury, when I on my part, for everything which I either bought
                    from Polyeuctus during his lifetime or received from his wife, have duly paid
                    the price and the interest as well, and am now bringing into the general account
                    everything which I owed, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>that this fellow should show no regard either for your laws or for the will of
                    Polyeuctus, or for the papers which have been left, or for those who knew the
                    facts, but in the face of all this should have come into court to contest my
                    plea.Please take first the law which denies the right of action for mortgaged
                    property against the holders of the mortgage, then the papers which were left,
                    and the deposition of Aristogenes.<quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Papers">
                        <title>Papers</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>I wish now, men of the jury, to instruct you in detail also regarding the other
                    claims which I make. They received from the wife of Polyeuctus a bowl, which
                    they pawned together with some pieces of jewelry, and this they have not
                    redeemed and brought into the general account, as Demophilus, to whom it was
                    pawned, will testify. They have also some stuff for hangings,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The word literally means <q type="">tent,</q> and it is so rendered by
                        some scholars in this passage. Harpocration takes it to mean <q type="">a
                        parasol.</q></note> which they received, but they do not account for this
                    either; and many more articles of the same sort. And finally, although my wife
                    advanced a mina of silver and expended it on her father’s behalf for the feast
                    of the dead,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Properly, <q type="">the Nemeseia,</q> a
                        festival celebrated every year on the fifth day of the month Boedromion
                        (September).</note> the defendant refuses to contribute his share even of
                    this; nay, what he has received he keeps; of other items he receives his due
                    portion; but these claims he thus openly refuses to meet.<milestone ed="P"
                        unit="para"/></p>
                <p>Now that these matters too may not be left neglected, take, please, the
                    depositions regarding them all.<quote type="Depositions"><p>
                            <title>Depositions</title>
                        </p>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>It may well be, men of the jury, that Spudias will make no statement to meet
                    these facts; for he will not be able to do so, clever though he is; but will
                    accuse Polyeuctus and his wife, and will declare that they did all these things
                    under my influence and as favors to me, and that he is being greatly injured in
                    many other respects, and has brought action against me; for this is what he
                    undertook to say before the arbitrator also. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>But for my part, men of the jury, in the first place I do not think that a
                    defence of that sort is legitimate, or that it is proper, when one is manifestly
                    shown to be in the wrong, for him to shift the charges and have recourse to
                    accusation and calumny; nay, for his counter-charges, if he is suffering any
                    wrong, he will plainly receive satisfaction, but for the claims made on him, he
                    will give it. For how could I now defend myself against the slanders of these
                    men, if I passed over the matters upon which you are to give your verdict? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>In the next place I wonder, if he had true and just demands to make, why it was
                    that, when our friends wished to settle our differences, and many conferences
                    were held, he could not abide by their decision. And yet who could better have
                    exposed the baselessness of claims advanced by him or by me than those who were
                    present at all these transactions, who knew the facts as well as we did
                    ourselves, and who were impartial friends of us both? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>But this was plainly not to the interest of my opponent—that he should be openly
                    convicted by our friends and find a settlement in this way. For do not imagine,
                    men of the jury, that men who know all these facts, and who now at their own
                    risk are giving testimony in my favor, would then, when they had been put under
                    oath, have formed a different conclusion about them. However, though you had
                    none of these facts to aid you, even so it is not difficult to form an opinion
                    as to which of the two parties is speaking the truth. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>For regarding the house, if he maintains that Polyeuctus was induced by me to
                    order that mortgage-pillars be set up for the thousand drachmae, yet surely,
                    Spudias, I did not use my influence to induce the witnesses to give false
                    testimony in my interest,—witnesses who were present when he betrothed to me his
                    daughter, who knew that I received less than the entire marriage portion, who
                    heard him when he acknowledged that he was in my debt and also when he had
                    introduced Leocrates as the one who should make payment, and who finally were
                    present when the will was made. For with all these persons it was no longer a
                    question of favoring me in these matters, but of risking a charge of giving
                    false testimony, if they deposed to what was not the truth. Let us, then, have
                    no more of that matter; but what will you say to this, Spudias? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>And see that you give these gentlemen a precise answer. If he does not, do you
                    all demand it of him. For, when Polyeuctus gave these directions in his will,
                    the defendant’s wife was present, and you may be sure that she reported to him
                    the will of her father, especially if he did not receive an equal share, but was
                    at a disadvantage in all respects; and the defendant himself was invited to be
                    present, so that it is not open to him to say that we managed this in secret and
                    kept them in the dark. For although he was invited to be present, he said that
                    he was busy himself, but that it would be enough if his wife were there. What
                    more would you have? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>When Aristogenes gave him an exact account of all these matters, even then he
                    made no comment, and though Polyeuctus lived on more than five days after this,
                    he neither showed any vexation on going to the house, nor made any protest, nor
                    did his wife, who was present from the first on all these occasions. It would
                    appear, then, that Polyeuctus was not induced by me to favor me in these
                    matters; the act was your own. Keep these facts, then, clearly in your minds,
                    men of the jury, and if he now tries to make any slanderous statements about the
                    matter, confront him with them.But first, that you may be fully assured that
                    matters are as I have stated, hear the witnesses. Read.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>Well then, men of the jury, in the matter of the one thousand drachmae, to prove
                    that Polyeuctus mortgaged the house to me honestly, and for an existing debt, I
                    have the testimony of my opponent himself and his wife in addition to these
                    other witnesses whose depositions have been put in; for they concurred at the
                    time, and made no objection either to Polyeuctus who lived so many days after,
                    or to Aristogenes, when they first heard of the will. But assuredly, if the
                    house was honestly mortgaged, it is impossible for you, if you bear the law in
                    mind, to acquit Spudias as to this part of the case. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>Now consider also the matter of the twenty minae, which he does not bring into
                    the account; for in this again the defendant himself will be my strongest
                    witness—not by words, heaven knows, such as he utters now in opposing my
                    suit—words are a criterion of no worth—but by manifest act. By doing what, men
                    of the jury? To this I bid you now to give close heed, in order that, if he
                    really dares to utter any slanders about the mother of our wives or about the
                    documents, your knowledge of the facts may make it impossible for him to deceive
                    you by his talk. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>These papers were left by the wife of Polyeuctus, as I just now said. The seals
                    being acknowledged both by the defendant’s wife and by mine, we both, being
                    present, broke them and took copies, and then sealed up the papers again, and
                    deposited them in the hands of Aristogenes. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>Now, note this, men of the jury, note this, I beg of you. There was in the papers
                    mention of the two minae, the price of the slave—and it was not only Polyeuctus
                    on his death-bed who had made this claim—and there was mention of the eighteen
                    hundred drachmae. When he read this, if what was written did not concern him at
                    all and was untrue, why pray did he not at once protest about it? Why did he
                    join in sealing again papers which were false and of no worth? This of course no
                    one in the world would do, if he did not concur in all that was written. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>But surely, men of the jury, this is an outrageous thing if these men are to be
                    permitted now to dispute matters to which they have themselves given assent, and
                    you are to find no basis for judgement in the fact that all of us are wont, when
                    charges are made against us that are unjust and untrue, not to keep silent, but
                    to dispute them on the spot, and that those who do not do this, if they contest
                    them subsequently, are accounted rascals and tricksters. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p>Now Spudias knows this as well as I, and I think even better, inasmuch as he
                    comes oftener before your court, yet he feels no shame in saying things that
                    contradict all that he has himself done. And yet full often when you become
                    conscious of one single piece of fraud, you treat it as evidence against the
                    other charges; but the defendant is found to have been convicted by himself of
                    falsehood on every point.Take, please, the deposition, proving that the seals of
                    the papers were acknowledged at the time by the wife of the defendant, and that
                    the papers are now deposited, sealed by Spudias.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>Since, then, these facts have been so convincingly established, there is no
                    further need, I think, of more words. For when I am able to produce both laws
                    and witnesses in support of everything that I have said, and also admissions
                    made in my favor by my opponent himself, what further need can there be for a
                    long argument? However, if Spudias perchance waxes indignant about the marriage
                    portion and maintains that he is being defrauded to the amount of one thousand
                    drachmae, he will be lying. For, while he disputes my claim to this sum, he has
                    received not less, but more, as will presently be made clear to you. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>Nay more, even if all these statements of his were indeed true, it is not just, I
                    take it, if the laws are good for anything, that I should lose the marriage
                    portion which was promised me, or that Polyeuctus, if he chose to give a smaller
                    portion to one daughter and a larger to the other, should now be thwarted. For
                    it was open to you, Spudias, not to marry his daughter, unless the thousand
                    drachmae were given to you as well as to me. However you received no less than
                    I, as I shall show.But, first, take the deposition which shows on what terms the
                    lady was given to him.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>But how can it be that he has received as much as I, one may ask, if in his case
                    the jewelry and the apparel, to the value of a thousand drachmae, were reckoned
                    in the forty minae, while to me the ten minae were paid separately and in
                    addition? This is precisely what I am going to explain. For Spudias, men of the
                    jury, received his wife from Leocrates with the jewelry and apparel on which
                    Polyeuctus set a value to Leocrates of more than a thousand drachmae, while in
                    my case, if you set what was sent to me over and above the marriage portion—all
                    that I have in my possession—over against what was given to Spudias, you will
                    find them practically equal over and above what was reckoned in the thousand
                    drachmae; </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>so that it was only fair that these articles should be included in the forty
                    minae, seeing that Polyeuctus had charged them against Leocrates, and they were
                    more than had been given me.Now please take this inventory and read to the
                    jurymen what each of us has in his possession; after that, read the deposition
                    of the arbitrators, that they may see that Spudias has received even far more
                    than I, and that Leocrates made complaint regarding this, and that the
                    arbitrators rendered this decision.<quote type="Inventory"><p>
                            <title>Inventory</title>
                        </p>
                    </quote><quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>Is it not plain, then, that the defendant has long had in his possession forty
                    minae as his wife’s marriage portion, whereas I received the thirty minae, just
                    as he did, but not only did not receive the thousand drachmae, but am now
                    actually in jeopardy regarding them, charged with possessing them wrongfully. It
                    was for this reason, men of the jury, that Spudias would not leave to our
                    friends the settlement of his claims against me, since the result would have
                    been that all these falsehoods of his would have been exposed, for they had been
                    present at all these transactions and knew all about them, and would therefore
                    not have permitted him to say whatever he pleased; whereas in your court he
                    thinks that by his falsehoods he will get the better of me and my statement of
                    the truth. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>And yet I have set forth to you clearly all my charges, as well as I could do it
                    myself, while my opponent evaded coming before those acquainted with the facts
                    thinking that he would be unable to lead them astray. Do not you, then, men of
                    the jury, do not you any more than they suffer him to have recourse to lies and
                    calumnies, but bear in mind what you have heard; for you know all the facts of
                    the case, unless perhaps I have omitted something, since I have been forced to
                    speak with but scant water in the water-clock.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
