<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader type="text">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Athenogenes from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
                <author>Hyperides</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>


            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Hyperides</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>

        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
                <refState unit="fragment"/>
            </refsDecl>

            <refsDecl n="speech=5">
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="fragment"/>
            </refsDecl>
        <refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="fragment" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div[@type='translation']/tei:div[@n='$1'])"><p>This pointer pattern extracts fragment</p></cRefPattern>
</refsDecl></encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English</language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
<change><date>May 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>June 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>4/30/93</date><respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>add refdecl, changed some of the FRAG attributes that had commentary in them, made notes have a space after them.</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
            <change when="2014-10-01" who="#Stella #Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0030.tlg003.perseus-eng1" type="translation" xml:lang="eng"><div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When I told her what had happened and explained
                    that Athenogenes was rude to me and unwilling to come to any reasonable
                    agreement, she said that he was always like that and told me not to worry, as
                    she would support me in everything herself. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
                <p>Her manner when she said this could not have been more sincere, and she took the
                    most solemn oaths to prove that she was thinking only of my welfare and was
                    telling me the plain truth. So, to be quite honest with you, gentlemen of the
                    jury, I took her at her word. That is how love, I suppose, upsets a man's
                    natural balance when it takes a woman as its ally. She, at any rate, by this act
                    of wholesale trickery pocketed, as a reward for her kindness, a further three
                    hundred drachmas, ostensibly to buy a girl. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
                <p>Perhaps there is nothing very surprising, gentlemen of the jury, in my having
                    been taken in like this by Antigone, a woman who was, I am told, the most gifted
                    courtesan of her time and who has continued to practise as a procuress . . . has
                    ruined the house of . . . of the deme Chollidae which was equal to any. And yet
                    if that was how she behaved on her own, what do you think her plans are now when
                    she has taken Athenogenes into partnership, who is a speechwriter, a man of
                    affairs and, most significant of all, an Egyptian? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
                <p>At all events, to make a long story short, she finally sent for me again later
                    and said that after a long talk with Athenogenes she had with difficulty managed
                    to persuade him to release Midas and both his sons for me for forty minas.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">This was a high price for three slaves.
                        Demosthenes tells us that the total cost of his father's fifty-two slaves
                        (thirty-two swordsmiths and twenty couchmakers) was 230 minas, i.e., an
                        average of just under eight pounds per head. (<bibl n="Dem. 27.9">Dem. 27.
                            9</bibl>.)</note> She told me to produce the money as quickly as I could
                    before Athenogenes changed his mind on any point. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
                <p>After I had collected it from every source and been a nuisance to my friends I
                    deposited the forty minas in the bank and came to Antigone. She brought us both
                    together, Athenogenes and myself, and after reconciling us asked us to treat
                    each other as friends in future. I consented to this and Athenogenes, the
                    defendant, replied that I had Antigone to thank for what had passed. “And now,”
                    he said, “I will show you how well I am going to treat you for her sake.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">For the explanation of this offer see
                        Introduction.</note> You are going to put down the money,” he went on, “for
                    the liberation of Midas and his sons. Instead I will sell them to you formally
                    as your own, so that no one shall interfere with, or seduce the boy, and also so
                    that the slaves themselves shall abstain from being troublesome, for fear of the
                    consequences. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
                <p>But this is the chief advantage: under the present arrangement they would think
                    that it was I who had freed them; whereas, if you buy them formally first and
                    then liberate them afterwards at your leisure, they will be doubly grateful to
                    you. However,” he said, “you will become responsible for what money they owe: a
                    debt for some sweet oil to Pancalus and Procles<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The name is given as Polycles in § 10.</note> and any other sums which
                    customers have invested in the perfumery in the ordinary course. It is a
                    trifling amount and much more than counterbalanced by the stocks in the shop,
                    sweet oil, scent-boxes, myrrh” (and he mentioned the names of some other
                    things), “which will easily cover all the debts.” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
                <p>There, so it seems, gentlemen of the jury, lay the catch, the real point of the
                    elaborate plot. For if I used the money to buy their freedom I was simply losing
                    whatever I gave him without suffering any serious harm. But if I bought them
                    formally and agreed to take over their debts assuming, since I had no previous
                    information, that these were negligible, he meant to set all his creditors and
                        contributors<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">I.e., friends who had made
                        loans to the business. The money would be repaid in instalments free of
                        interest. Cf. §§ 9 and 11.</note> on me, using the agreement as a trap. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
                <p>And that is just what he did. For when I accepted his proposals he immediately
                    took a document from his lap and began to read the contents, which were the text
                    of an agreement with me. I listened to it being read, but my attention was
                    concentrated on completing the business I had come for. He sealed the agreement
                    directly in the same house, so that no one with any interest in me should hear
                    the contents, and added with my name that of Nicon of Cephisia. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
                <p>We went to the perfumery and deposited the document with Lysicles of Leuconoe,
                    and I put down the forty minas and so made the purchase. When this was settled I
                    was visited by the creditors, to whom Midas owed money, and the contributors
                    too, who talked things over with me. In three months all the debts had been
                    declared, with the result that, including repayment of contributions, I owed, as
                    I said just now, about five talents. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
                <p>When I realized what a plight I was in, at long last I called together my friends
                    and relatives and we read the copy of the agreement in which the names of
                    Pancalus and Polycles<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The name is given as
                        Procles in § 6. It is not known which is the correct form.</note> were
                    expressly written with the statement that certain sums were owing to them for
                    sweet oil. These were small amounts, and they were justified in saying that the
                    oil in the shop was equal in value to the money. But the majority of the debts,
                    including the largest, were not given specifically; they were mentioned as an
                    unimportant item in a sort of footnote which ran: </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
                <p>“and any debt which Midas may owe to any other person.” Of the contributions one
                    was noted of which three instalments for repayment were still outstanding.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">See § 7, note.</note> This was given in the name
                    of Dicaeocrates. But the others, on the strength of which Midas had acquired
                    everything and which were of recent date, were not entered by him in the
                    agreement but kept secret. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
                <p>On thinking it over we decided to go to Athenogenes and broach the matter. We
                    found him near the perfume stalls and asked him whether he was not ashamed of
                    being a liar and trapping us with the agreement by not declaring the debts
                    beforehand. He replied that he did not know what debts we meant and that we made
                    no impression on him; he had in safe-keeping a document relating to me which
                    covered the transaction. A crowd gathered and overheard the incident, as our
                    altercation took place in the market. Although they gave him a slating and told
                    us to arrest him summarily as a kidnapper,<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Summary arrest (<foreign xml:lang="greek">a)pagwgh/</foreign>) by which the
                        injured party seized the criminal and took him before the magistrate, could
                        be used against various types of offender, e.g., thieves and kidnappers.
                        Athenogenes was not actually a kidnapper, but he was driving a man to debt,
                        which, though it did not lead to enslavement, might result in total <foreign xml:lang="greek">atimi/a</foreign>.</note> we thought it best not to do
                    so. Instead we summoned him before you, as the law permits. First of all then,
                    the clerk shall read you the agreement; for you shall have the actual text of
                    the document as evidence of the plot, for which Athenogenes and no other is to
                    blame. Read the agreement.<quote type="Agreement"> </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/><quote>Well, gentlemen of the jury, you have heard
                        the facts in detail. But Athenogenes will presently tell you that in law
                        whatever agreements one man makes with another are binding.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">This law is quoted elsewhere,e.g., by <bibl n="Dem. 47.77">Dem. 47.77</bibl>.</note> Yes, my friend, just
                        agreements. But if they are unjust, the opposite is true: the law forbids
                        that they be binding. I will quote the laws themselves to make this clearer
                        to you. For you have reduced me to such a state of fear lest I shall be
                        ruined by you and your craftiness that I have been searching the laws night
                        and day and studying them to the neglect of everything else. </quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
                <p><quote>The first law, then, stipulates that people shall not tell lies in the
                        market, which seems to me a most admirable provision.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The first of these two laws cited by the plaintiff is
                            mentioned also by <bibl n="Dem. 20.9">Dem. 20.9</bibl>. It was enforced
                            by the ten agoranomoi, whose duty it was to guard against fraud in all
                            questions of purchase. See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 51">Aristot. Ath.
                                Pol. 51</bibl>. For the second law compare <bibl n="Aeschin. 3.249">Aeschin. 3.249</bibl> and <bibl n="Plat. Laws 915c">Plat. Laws. 915
                                c.</bibl></note> Yet you lied in the middle of the market when you
                        made the agreement to defraud me. But if you show that you declared to me
                        beforehand the contributions and the debts, or that you wrote in the
                        agreement the names of those whose existence I later discovered, I have no
                        quarrel with you; I admit that I owe the money. </quote></p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
                <p>After this there is a second law, covering agreements between individuals, which
                    states that whenever anyone sells a slave, he must declare in advance any
                    physical disability from which the man suffers. Otherwise the slave in question
                    can be returned to the vendor. And yet if a slave can be returned simply because
                    of some weakness due to mischance which the master keeps secret at the time of
                    the sale, how can you fail to take the responsibility for the crimes which you
                    deliberately planned? But the epileptic slave does not involve the buyer in
                    fresh expense, whereas Midas, whom you sold to me, has even lost my friends'
                    money. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
                <p>Consider the legal position, Athenogenes, as regards free persons as well as
                    slaves. No doubt you know as everyone does that the children of married women
                    are legitimate. Yet the mere act of betrothing a woman on the part of a father
                    or brother was not enough for the lawmaker. On the contrary, he wrote expressly
                    in the law<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">This law is mentioned by Demosthenes
                            (<bibl n="Dem. 44.49">Dem. 44.49</bibl>) and quoted in <bibl n="Dem. 46.18">Dem. 46.18</bibl>, from which the text is here
                        reconstructed.</note> : “whomsoever any man has lawfully betrothed as wife,
                    her children shall be legitimate”; not: “if any man has betrothed some other
                    woman on the pretence that she is his daughter.” He lays it down that just
                    betrothals shall be valid and unjust ones invalid. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
                <p>Moreover the law dealing with wills is very similar to this.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">This law is quoted in <bibl n="Dem. 46.14">Dem.
                        46.14</bibl>. Compare <bibl n="Isaeus 6.10">Isaeus 6.10</bibl>; <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 35">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 35</bibl>. As Colin points
                        out, the comparison between <foreign xml:lang="greek">sunqh=kai</foreign>
                        (an agreement and <foreign xml:lang="greek">diaqh/lkh</foreign> a will)
                        seems closer in Greek than in English.</note> It allows a man to bequeath
                    his property as he wishes unless he is affected by old age, illness or insanity,
                    and provided he is not influenced by a woman or imprisoned or otherwise coerced.
                    But if even our own personal property cannot be administered according to an
                    unjust will, surely Athenogenes who is disposing of my property through his
                    agreement cannot enforce such terms. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
                <p>Apparently if a man respects the wishes of his own wife in making his will it
                    will be invalid. Then must I, who was influenced by the mistress of Athenogenes,
                    accept the contract and be ruined too,<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        argument is rather condensed; the contrast is this: A will may be otherwise
                        just and yet it becomes invalid when made under the influence of a wife.
                        Therefore, a fortiori, this contract becomes invalid because (1) it was not
                        just in other respects, (2) it was made under the influence of a woman less
                        reputable than a wife.</note> even though I can claim the very powerful help
                    of the law, having been compelled by these people to conclude the agreement? Do
                    you insist on the agreement when you and your mistress laid a trap for me to get
                    it signed? In circumstances where the laws relating to conspiracy proclaim that
                    you are guilty, are you expecting actually to make a profit? You were not
                    content with the forty minas for the perfumery. No; you robbed me of a further
                    five talents as though I were caught . . .<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        exact words cannot be restored but the sense is: “It is absurd for
                        Athenogenes, a shrewd business man, to plead ignorance, when I with no
                        experience of the market discovered the facts so soon without
                        effort.”</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="section">
                <p>the affairs of the market, but by simply waiting I discovered all the debts and
                    loans in three months. Whereas this man had two generations of perfume sellers
                    behind him; he used to sit in the market every day, was the owner of three
                    stalls and had accounts submitted to him monthly and still he did not know his
                    debts. Though an expert in other matters he was a complete simpleton in dealing
                    with his slave, and though he knew, apparently, of some of the debts, he pleads
                    ignorance of others—to suit his convenience. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="section">
                <p>In using an argument like this, gentlemen of the jury, he is accusing, not
                    excusing, himself, since he is admitting that I need not pay the debts. For if
                    he says that he did not know the full amount owing, surely he cannot claim that
                    he informed me of the debts beforehand; and I am not bound to pay those of which
                    the seller did not notify me. You knew that Midas owed this money, Athenogenes,
                    as I think we all realize for several reasons, and chiefly because you summoned
                    Nicon to give security for me<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">This passage was
                        restored by Blass, partly following Revillout, to give the following
                        meaning: “ . . . because you summoned Nicon to give security for me, knowing
                        that I could not meet the debts alone without his help. And indeed I cannot,
                        but I want to get to grips with this claim of yours that you did not know
                        who had invested what sums, or what the individual debts were. Let us
                        consider it in this way.” For Nicon see § 8.</note> . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="section">
                <p>in this way. If ignorance prevented you from informing me in advance of all the
                    debts, and if I thought when I concluded the agreement that your statement
                    covered them all, which of us has to pay them? The subsequent purchaser, or the
                    man who owned the business originally, when the money was borrowed? Personally I
                    think that you are liable. But if it turns out that we disagree on this, let the
                    law be our arbiter, which was made neither by lovers nor men with designs on
                    other people's property but by that great democrat Solon. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="section">
                <p>He knew that sales are constantly taking place in the city and passed a law,
                    which everyone admits to be just, stating that any offences or crimes committed
                    by a slave shall be the responsibility of the master who owns him at the
                        time.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">This law, which does not seem to be
                        mentioned elsewhere, is not strictly applicable here, since the plaintiff
                        had agreed in his contract to assume responsibility for Midas's debts.
                        However, it was a fair law, and if Athenogenes had not intended to take
                        advantage of the plaintiff he would have been willing to observe it.
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">zhmi/an e)rga/zesqai</foreign>, which appears
                        to be an old legal phrase, is variously understood. Other interpretations
                        than that adopted in the translation are: (1) to incur loss, (2) to incur a
                        fine.</note> This is only fair; for if a slave gains any success or brings
                    in earnings, his owner enjoys the benefits. But you ignore the law and talk
                    about agreements being broken. Solon did not consider that a decree, even when
                    constitutionally proposed, should override the law.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">This provision of Solon is mentioned by <bibl n="Andoc. 1.87">Andoc. 1.87</bibl> and by <bibl n="Dem. 23.87">Dem.
                            23.87</bibl>.</note> Yet you maintain that even unjust agreements take
                    precedence over all the laws. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="section">
                <p>Besides this, gentlemen of the jury, he was saying to my father and my other
                    relatives that . . .<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The sense evidently is:
                        “that he offered me the one boy as a present and asked me to leave
                        Midas.”Cf.§ 27.</note> telling me to leave Midas for him instead of buying
                    him, but that I refused and wanted to buy them all. I gather that he is even
                    going to mention these points to you with the idea of convincing you of his
                    moderation, if you please. He must think that he is going to address a set of
                    fools who will not realize his effrontery. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="section">
                <p>You must hear what happened; for you will see that it fits in with the rest of
                    their plot. He sent me the boy, whom I mentioned just now, with the message that
                    he could not stay with me unless I freed his father and brother. When I had
                    already agreed to put down the money for the three of them, Athenogenes
                    approached some of my friends and said: </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="section">
                <p>“Why does Epicrates want to give himself extra trouble when he could take the boy
                    and use . . .?” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="section">
                <p>I am not a seller of perfume<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The general sense
                        of this mutilated passage is restored by Colin, in his translation, as
                        follows: “Despite his dishonest purpose, I accepted his word, and when he
                        offered me the boy, raised no objection over the price. I thus agreed to pay
                        40 minas, but I now find I must produce five talents for a perfumery in
                        which I have no interest.”</note> and I do not practise any other trade. I
                    simply farm the property which my father gave me, and I was landed in the
                    purchase by these people. Which is more probable, Athenogenes, that I set my
                    heart on your trade in which I was not proficient, or that you and your mistress
                    had designs on my money? Personally, I think that you are indicated. Therefore,
                    gentlemen of the jury, you could fairly excuse me for being cheated by . . . and
                    for having had the misfortune to fall in with a man like this, but to
                    Athenogenes . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="section">
                <p>all to be mine and the profits of the fraud to be his. . . . that I took Midas .
                    . . whom he says he was reluctant to let go. But for the boy whom, we are told,
                    he originally offered me for nothing, he has now been paid a far higher price
                    than he is worth; and yet in the end the boy will not be my property but will be
                    freed on the strength of your verdict.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        point of this remark is not clear. The plaintiff might mean that if he wins
                        his case the boy will be freed, since he never intended to buy him as a
                        slave; but the following sentence suggests that he has in mind at present
                        the consequences of his condemnation.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="section">
                <p>However I do not think myself that in addition to my other troubles I deserve to
                    be disfranchised by Athenogenes.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Disfranchisement could only follow upon condemnation if the plaintiff
                        failed to obtain one-fifth of the votes and so became liable to pay <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)pwbeli/a</foreign>,i.e., compensation to Athenogenes
                        at the rate of one-sixth of the sum in question. On failure to pay this he
                        would become liable to prosecution again (<foreign xml:lang="greek">di/kh
                            e)cou/lhs</foreign>) and if condemned would have to pay a fine to the
                        state too. Finally as a state debtor he would be liable to loss of civic
                        rights (<foreign xml:lang="greek">a)timi/a</foreign>). The payment of
                            <foreign xml:lang="greek">e)pwbeli/a</foreign> certainly obtained in
                        mercantile, and some other cases, and probably in cases of damage also. See
                            <bibl n="Andoc. 1.73">Andoc. 1.73</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 21.44">Dem.
                            21.44</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 27.67">Dem. 27.67</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 28.21">Dem. 28.21</bibl>, <bibl n="Dem. 47.64">Dem.
                        47.64</bibl>; <bibl n="Aeschin. 1.163">Aeschin. 1.163</bibl>.</note> For I
                    should be receiving harsh treatment indeed, gentlemen of the jury, if . . . of
                    the metics to come unguarded. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="section">
                <p>During the war against Philip he left the city just before the battle and did not
                    serve with you at <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>. Instead,
                    he moved to <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, disregarding the
                        law<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">This law, which is not mentioned by any
                        other writer appears to be the same as the one subsequently read out (§ 33)
                        which forbade resident aliens to emigrate in time of war. It is not clear,
                        however, why the clause quoted here should relate to an attempted return on
                        the part of the lawbreaker rather than to his actual departure. If the
                        plaintiff is making a valid point we must assume that the law existed before
                        the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, since it
                        was then that Athenogenes left <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. If so, it must have applied to resident aliens only
                        (as indeed appears from § 33 to have been the case) for had it applied to
                        citizens, Lycurgus would surely have mentioned it in his speech against
                        Leocrates, as he was there concerned with just this question. It is
                        possible, however, that Hyperides is alluding to some provision which did
                        not come into force until the time of emergency after <placeName key="tgn,7010731">Chaeronea</placeName>, but is attempting to impose on
                        the ignorance of his hearers.</note> which says that a man who moves in
                    wartime shall be indicted and summarily arrested if he returns. The reason for
                    the move, it seems, was this: he thought that the city of <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> would survive, whereas he had passed a
                    sentence of death on ours. His daughters whom he had brought up in the
                    prosperity which you provided . . . he married off . . . with the intention of
                    returning later to carry on his business when peace was established. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="section">
                <p>. . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="section">
                <p>after disregarding the agreement which we all make with the state, he insists on
                    his private contract with me, as if anyone would believe that a man who made
                    light of his duty to you would have cared about his obligations to me. He is so
                    degraded and so true to type wherever he is, that even after his arrival at
                        <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> when they had made him a
                    citizen he became the tool of Mnesias the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName><note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Mnesias the <placeName key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> is mentioned as a traitor by
                        Demosthenes. (See <bibl n="Dem. 18.295">Dem. 18.295</bibl>, where, however,
                        the name is spelt <foreign xml:lang="greek">*mnase/as</foreign>.)</note>
                    and, after being made a magistrate by him, expelled the citizens from the city.
                    The men themselves will bear witness to this; for they are here in exile.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">As these men were still in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, Alexander's decree of
                            <date>424</date> B.C., providing that exiles should return, cannot yet
                        have been issued. Hence we have a terminus ante quem for the speech.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="32" subtype="section">
                <p>And you, gentlemen of the jury, took them in when they were banished; you made
                    them citizens and granted them a share of all your privileges. Remembering,
                    after more than a hundred and fifty years,<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        Athenians sent women and children to <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName> before the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>. (See <bibl n="Cic. Off. 3.11.48">Cic. de Offic. 3.
                            11.48</bibl>.) Hence we have a rough terminus post quem for the
                        speech.</note> the help they gave you against the barbarian, you felt that
                    when men had been of service to you in times of danger you should protect them
                    in their misfortune. But this abandoned wretch, who forsook you and was enrolled
                    at <placeName key="tgn,5004287">Troezen</placeName>, engaged in nothing that was
                    worthy either of the constitution or the spirit of that city. He treated those
                    who had welcomed him so cruelly that . . . in the Assembly . . . fled.<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">The sense appears to be, as Colin suggests, that
                        he was accused in the Assemhly of the Troezenians, and, fearing punishment,
                        fled back to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="33" subtype="section">
                <p>To prove that what I say is true the clerk will read you first the law, which
                    forbids metics to move in war time, then the evidence of the Troezenians and
                    also the Troezenians' decree passed by them in honor of your city, in return for
                    which you welcomed them and made them citizens. Read.<quote type="Law. Evidence. Decree"/>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="34" subtype="section">
                <p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now take the evidence of the father-in-law<note resp="#Loeb" anchored="true">Revillout suggests that the defendant called for
                        the father-in-law to give evidence that Athenogenes had been lavishing all
                        his money on Antigone.</note> . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="35" subtype="section">
                <p>the way in which Athenogenes has plotted against me and also his behavior towards
                    you. If a man has been vicious in his private life and given up hope of his
                    city's safety; if he has deserted you and expelled the citizens from the town of
                    his adoption, will you not punish him when he is in your power? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="36" subtype="section">
                <p>For my part, gentlemen of the jury, I beg you most earnestly to show me mercy.
                    Remember in this trial that you ought to have pity . . . suffer nothing if he is
                    convicted . . . </p>
            </div>
            <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="fragment">
                <p>...</p>
            </div>
        </div></body>
    </text>
</TEI>