<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Injuries of the Head</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 20, 2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							<date>1886</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Aph.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Epid.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<div type="section" n="1">
				<head>Part 1</head>
				<p>MEN'S heads are by no means all like to one another, nor are the sutures of the
					head of all men constructed in the same form. Thus, whoever has a prominence in
					the anterior part of the head (by prominence is meant the round protuberant part
					of the bone which projects beyond the rest of it), in him the sutures of the
					head take the form of the Greek letter <hi rend="ital">tau</hi>, T; for the head
					has the shorter line running transverse before the prominence, while the other
					line runs through the middle of the head, all the way to the neck. But whoever
					has the prominence in the back part of the head, in him the sutures are
					constructed in quite the opposite form to the former; for in this case the
					shorter line runs in front of the prominence, while the longer runs through the
					middle all along to the forehead. But whoever has a prominence of the head both
					before and behind, in him the sutures resemble the Greek letter <hi rend="ital"
						>eta</hi> E; for the long lines of the letter run transverse before each
					prominence while the short one runs through the middle and terminates in the
					long lines. But whoever has no prominence on either part he has the sutures of
					the head resembling the Greek letter chi; for the one line comes transverse to
					the temple while the other passes along the middle of the head. The bone at the
					middle of the head is double, the hardest and most compact part being the upper
					portion, where it is connected with the skin, and the lowest, where it is
					connected with the meninx (dura mater); and from the uppermost and lowermost
					parts the bone gradually becomes softer and less compact, till you come to the
						<hi rend="ital">diploe</hi>. The diploe is the most porous, the softest, and
					most cavernous part. But the whole bone of the head, with the,<pb n="p.146"/>
					exception of a small portion of the uppermost and lowermost portions of it, is
					like a sponge; and the bone has in it many juicy substances, like caruncles; and
					if one will rub them with the fingers, some blood will issue from them. There
					are also in the bone certain very slender and hollow vessels full of blood. So
					it is with regard to hardness, softness, and porosity.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="2">
				<head>Part 2</head>
				<p>In respect to thickness and thinness; the thinnest and weakest part of the whole
					head is the part about the bregma; and the bone there has the smallest and
					thinnest covering of flesh upon it, and the largest proportion of brain is
					situated in that region of the head. And hence it happens that from similar or
					even smaller wounds and instruments, when a person is wounded to the same or a
					less degree, the bone of the head there is more contused, fractured, and
					depressed; and that injuries there are more deadly and more difficult to cure;
					and it is more difficult to save one's life in injuries there than in any other
					part of the head; that from having sustained a similar or even a less wound a
					man will die, and that, too, in a shorter space of time than from a wound in any
					other part of the head. For the brain about the bregma feels more quickly and
					strongly any mischief that may occur to the flesh or the bone; for the brain
					about the bregma is in largest quantity, and is covered by the thinnest bone and
					the least flesh. Of the other portions, the weakest is that about the temples;
					for it is the conjunction of the lower jaw with the cranium, and there is motion
					there up and down as at a joint; and the organ of hearing is near it; and
					further, a hollow and important vein runs along the temple. But the whole bone
					of the head behind the vertex and the ear is stronger than the whole anterior
					part, and the bone itself has a larger and deeper covering of flesh upon it. And
					hence it follows, that when exposed to the same or even greater injuries from
					instruments of the same or greater size, the bone is less liable to be fractured
					and depressed than elsewhere; and that in a fatal accident the patient will live
					longer when the wound is in the posterior part of the head than when elsewhere;
					and that pus takes longer time to form and penetrate through the bone to the
					brain, owing to the thickness of the bone; and moreover, as<pb n="p.147"/> there
					is less brain in that part of the head, more persons who are wounded in the back
					part of the head escape than of those who wounded in the anterior part. And in
					fatal cases, a man will survive longer in winter than in summer, whatever be the
					part of the head in which the wound is situated.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="3">
				<head>Part 3</head>
				<p>As to the <hi rend="ital">haedrae</hi> (dints <hi rend="ital">or</hi> marks?) of
					sharp and light weapons, when they take place in the bone without fissure,
					contusion, or depression inwards (and these take place equally in the anterior
					and posterior part of the head), death, when it does occur, does not properly
					result from them. A suture appearing in a wound, when the bone is laid bare, on
					whatever part of the head the wound may have been inflicted, is the weakest
					point of the head to resist a blow or a weapon, when the weapon happens to be
					impinged into the suture itself; but more especially when this occurs in the
					bregma at the weakest part of the head, and the sutures happen to be situated
					near the wound, and the weapon has hit the sutures themselves. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="4">
				<head>Part 4</head>
				<p>The bone in the head is liable to be wounded in the following modes, and there
					are many varieties in each of these modes of fracture: When a wounded bone
					breaks, in the bone comprehending the fissure, contusion necessarily takes place
					where the bone is broken; for an instrument that breaks the bone occasions a
					contusion thereof more or less, both at the fracture and in the parts of the
					bone surrounding the fracture. This is the first mode. But there are all
					possible varieties of fissures; for some of them are fine, and so very fine that
					they cannot be discovered, either immediately after the injury, or during the
					period in which it would be of use to the patient if this could be ascertained.
					And some of these fissures are thicker and wider, certain of them being very
					wide. And some of them extend to a greater, and some to a smaller, distance. And
					some are more straight, nay, completely straight; and some are more curved, and
					that in a remarkable degree. And some are deep, so as to extend downwards and
					through the whole bone; and some are less so, and do not penetrate through the
					whole bone.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="5">
				<head>Part 5</head>
				<p>But a bone may be contused, and yet remain in its natural condition without any
					fracture in it; this is the second mode.<pb n="p.148"/> And there are many
					varieties of contusion; for they occur to a greater or less degree, and to a
					greater depth, so as sometimes to extend through the whole bone; or to a less
					depth, so as not to extend through the whole bone; and to a greater and smaller
					length and breadth. But it is not possible to recognize any of these varieties
					by the sight, so as to determine their form and extent; neither, indeed, is it
					visible to the eyes when any mischief of this kind takes place, and immediately
					after the injury, whether or not the bone has been actually bruised, as is
					likewise the case with certain fractures at a distance from the seat of
					injury.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="6">
				<head>Part 6</head>
				<p>And the bone being fractured, is sometimes depressed inwards from its natural
					level along with the fractures, otherwise there would be no depression; for the
					depressed portion being fractured and broken off, is pushed inwards, while the
					rest of the bone remains in its natural position; and in this manner a fracture
					is combined with the depression. This is the third mode. There are many
					varieties of depression, for it may comprehend a greater and a small extent of
					bone, and may either be to a greater depth, or less so, and more
					superficial.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="7">
				<head>Part 7</head>
				<p>When a <hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>, or dint of a weapon, takes place in a bone,
					there may be a fracture combined with it; and provided there be a fracture,
					contusion must necessarily be joined, to a greater or less extent, in the seat
					of the dint and fracture, and in the bone which comprehends them. This is the
					fourth mode. And there may be a <hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>, or indentation of
					the bone, along with contusion of the surrounding bone, but without any fracture
					either in the hedra or in the contusion inflicted by the weapon. But the
					indentation of a weapon takes place in a bone, and is called <hi rend="ital"
						>hedra</hi>, when the bone remaining in its natural state, the weapon which
					struck against the bone leaves its impression on the part which it struck. In
					each of these modes there are many varieties, with regard to the contusion and
					fracture, if both these be combined with the <hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>, or if
					contusion alone, as it has been already stated that there are many varieties of
					contusion and fracture. And the <hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>, <hi rend="ital"
						>or</hi> dint, of itself may be longer and shorter, crooked, straight, and
					circular; and there are many varieties of this mode, according to the shape of
					the weapon; and they may<pb n="p.149"/> be more or less deep, and narrower or
					broader, and extremely broad. When a part is cleft, the cleft or notch which
					occurs in the bone, to whatever length or breadth, is a <hi rend="ital"
						>hedra</hi>, if the other bones comprehending the cleft remain in their
					natural position, and be not driven inwards; for in this case it would be a
					depression, and no longer a <hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="8">
				<head>Part 8</head>
				<p>A bone may be injured in a different part of the head from that on which the
					person has received the wound, and the bone has been laid bare. This is the
					fifth mode. And for this misfortune, when it occurs, there is no remedy; for
					when this mischief takes place, there is no means of ascertaining by any
					examination whether or not it has occurred, or on what part of the head.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="9">
				<head>Part 9</head>
				<p>Of these modes of fracture, the following require trepanning: the contusion,
					whether the bone be laid bare or not; and the fissure, whether apparent or not.
					And if, when an indentation (<hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>) by a weapon takes place
					in a bone it be attended with fracture and contusion, and even if contusion
					alone, without fracture, be combined with the indentation, it requires
					trepanning. A bone depressed from position rarely requires trepanning; and those
					which are most pressed and broken require trepanning the least; neither does an
					indentation (<hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>) without fracture and contusion require
					trepanning; nor does a notch, provided it is large and wide; for a notch and a
					hedra are the same.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="10">
				<head>Part 10</head>
				<p> In the first place, one must examine the wounded person, in what part of the
					head the wound is situated, whether in the stronger or weaker parts; and
					ascertain respecting the hairs about the wound, whether they have been cut off
					by the instrument, and have gone into the wound; and if so, one should declare
					that the bone runs the risk of being denuded of flesh, and of having sustained
					some injury from the weapon. These things one should say from a distant
					inspection, and before laying a hand on the man; but on a close examination one
					should endeavor to ascertain clearly whether the bone be denuded of flesh or
					not; and if the denuded bone be visible to the eyes, this will be enough; but
					otherwise an examination must be made with the sound. And if you find the bone
					denuded of the flesh,<pb n="p.150"/> and not safe from the wound, you must first
					ascertain the state of the bone, and the extent of the mischief, and of what
					assistance it stands in need. One should also inquire of the wounded person how
					and in what way he sustained the injury; and if it be not apparent whether the
					bone has sustained an injury or not, it will be still more necessary, provided
					the bone be denuded, to make inquiry how the wound occurred, and in what manner;
					for when contusions and fractures existin the bone, but are not apparent, we
					must ascertain, in the first place from the patient's answers, whether or not
					the bone has sustained any such injuries, and then find out the nature of the
					case by word and deed, with the exception of sounding. For sounding does not
					discover to us whether the bone has sustained any of these injuries or not; but
					sounding discovers to us an indentation inflicted by a weapon, and whether a
					bone be depressed from its natural position, and whether the bone be strongly
					fractured; all which may also be ascertained visibly with the eyes.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="11">
				<head>Part 11</head>
				<p>And a bone sustains fractures, either so fine as to escape the sight, or such as
					are apparent, and contusions which are not apparent, and depression from its
					natural position, especially when one person is intentionally wounded by
					another, or when, whether intentionally or not, a blow or stroke is received
					from an elevated place, and if the instrument in the hand, whether used in
					throwing or striking, be of a powerful nature, and if a stronger person wound a
					weaker. Of those who are wounded in the parts about the bone, or in the bone
					itself, by a fall, he who falls from a very high place upon a very hard and
					blunt object is in most danger of sustaining a fracture and contusion of the
					bone, and of having it depressed from its natural position; whereas he that
					falls upon more level ground, and upon a softer object, is likely to suffer less
					injury in the bone, or it may not be injured at all. Of those instruments which,
					falling upon the head, wound the parts about the bone, or the bone itself, that
					which falls from a very high place, and the least on a level with the person
					struck, and which is at the same time very hard, very blunt, and very heavy, and
					which is the least light, sharp, and soft, such an instrument would occasion a
					fracture and<pb n="p.151"/> contusion of the bone. And there is most danger that
					the bone may sustain these injuries, under such circumstances, when the wound is
					direct and perpendicular to the bone, whether struck from the hand or from a
					throw, or when any object falls upon the person, or when he is wounded by
					falling, or in whatever way the bone sustains a direct wound from this
					instrument. Those weapons which graze the bone obliquely are less apt to
					fracture, contuse, or depress the bone, even when the bone is denuded of flesh;
					for in some of those wounds thus inflicted the bone is not laid bare of the
					flesh. Those instruments more especially produce fractures in the bone, whether
					apparent or not, and contusions, and inward depression of the bone, which are
					rounded, globular, smooth on all sides, blunt, heavy, and hard; and such weapons
					bruise, compress, and pound the flesh; and the wounds inflicted by such
					instruments, whether obliquely or circularly, are round, and are more disposed
					to suppurate, and to have a discharge, and take longer time to become clean; for
					the flesh which has been bruised and pounded must necessarily suppurate and
					slough away. But weapons of an oblong form, being, for the most part, slender,
					sharp, and light, penetrate the flesh rather than bruise it, and the bone in
					like manner; and such an instrument may occasion a <hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>
					and a cut (for a <hi rend="ital">hedra</hi> and a cut are same thing); but
					weapons of this description do not produce contusions, nor fractures, nor
					depressions inwardly. And in addition the appearances in the bone, which you
					call detect by the sight, you should make inquiry as to all these particulars
					(for they are symptoms of a greater or less injury), whether the wounded person
					was stunned, and whether darkness was diffused over his eyes, and whether he had
					vertigo, and fell to the ground.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="12">
				<head>Part 12</head>
				<p>When the bone happens to be denuded of flesh by the weapon, and when the wound
					occurs upon the sutures, it is difficult to distinguish the indentation (<hi
						rend="ital">hedra</hi>) of a weapon which is clearly recognized in other
					parts of the bone, whether it exist or not, and especially if the <hi
						rend="ital">hedra</hi> be seated in the sutures themselves. For the suture
					being rougher than the rest of the bone occasions confusion, and it is not clear
					which is the suture, and which the mark inflicted by the instrument, unless the
						latter<pb n="p.152"/> (<hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>) be large. Fracture also
					for the most part is combined with the indentation when it occurs in the
					sutures; and this fracture is more difficult to discern when the bone is broken,
					on this account, that if there be a fracture, it is situated for the most part
					in the suture. For the bone is liable to be broken and slackened there, owing to
					the natural weakness of the bone there, and to its porosity, and from the suture
					being readily ruptured and slackened: but the other bones which surround the
					suture remain unbroken, because they are stronger than the suture. For the
					fracture which occurs at the suture is also a slackening of the suture, and it
					is not easy to detect whether the bone be broken and slackened by the
					indentation of a weapon occurring in the suture, or from a contusion of the bone
					at the sutures; but it is still more difficult to detect a fracture connected
					with contusion. For the sutures, having the appearance of fissures, elude the
					discernment and sight of the physician, as being rougher than the rest of the
					bone, unless the bone be strongly cut and slackened (for a cut and a <hi
						rend="ital">hedra</hi> are the same thing). But it is necessary, if the
					wound has occurred at the sutures, and the weapon has impinged on the bone or
					the parts about it, to pay attention and find out what injury the bone has
					sustained. For a person wounded to the same, or a much smaller, extent, and by
					weapons of the same size and quality, and even much less, will sustain a much
					greater injury, provided he has received the blow at the sutures, than if it was
					elsewhere. And many of these require trepanning, but you must not apply the
					trepan to the sutures themselves, but on the adjoining bone.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="13">
				<head>Part 13</head>
				<p>And with regard to the cure of wounds in the head, and the mode of detecting
					injuries in the bone which are not apparent, the following is my opinion:- In a
					wound of the head, you must not apply anything liquid, not even wine, but as
					little as possible, nor a cataplasm, nor conduct the treatment with tents, nor
					apply a bandage to an ulcer on the head, unless it be situated on the forehead,
					in the part which is bare of hairs, or about the eyebrow and eye, for wounds
					occurring there require cataplasms and bandages more than upon any other part of
					the head. For the rest of the head surrounds the whole forehead, and the <pb
						n="p.153"/>wounds wherever situated become inflamed and swelled, owing to an
					influx of blood from surrounding parts. And neither must you apply cataplasms
					and bandages to the forehead at all times; but when the inflammation is stopped
					and the swelling has subsided, you must give up the cataplasms and bandages. A
					wound in any other part of the head must not be treated with tents, bandages, or
					cataplasms, unless it also requires incision. You must perform incision on
					wounds situated on the head and forehead, whenever the bone is denuded of flesh,
					and appears to have sustained some injury from the blow, but the wound has not
					sufficient length and breadth for the inspection of the bone, so that it may be
					seen whether it has received any mischief from the blow, and of what nature the
					injury is, and to what extent the flesh has been contused, and whether the bone
					has sustained any injury, or whether it be uninjured by the blow, and has
					suffered no mischief; and with regard to the treatment, what the wound, and the
					flesh, and the injury of the bone stand in need of. Ulcers of this description
					stand in need of incision; and, if the bone be denuded of the flesh, and if it
					be hollow, and extend far obliquely, we cut up the cavity wherever the medicine
					cannot penetrate readily, whatever medicine it may be; and wounds which are more
					inclined to be circular and hollow, and for the most part others of the like
					shape, are cut up by making double incision in the circle lengthways, according
					to the figure of the man, so as to make the wound of a long form. Incisions may
					be practiced with impunity on other parts of the head, with the exception of the
					temple and the parts above it, where there is a vein that runs across the
					temple, in which region an incision is not to be made. For convulsions seize on
					a person who has been thus treated; and if the incision be on the left temple,
					the convulsions seize on the right side; and if the incision be on the right
					side, the convulsions take place on the left side.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="14">
				<head>Part 14</head>
				<p>When, then, you lay open a wound in the head on account of the bones having been
					denuded of the flesh, as wishing to ascertain whether or not the bone has
					received an injury from the blow, you must make an incision proportionate to the
					size of the wound, and as much as shall be judged necessary. And <pb n="p.154"
					/>in making the incision you must separate the flesh from the bone where it is
					united to the membrane (<hi rend="ital">pericranium?</hi>) and to the bone, and
					then fill the whole wound with a tent, which will expand the wound very wide
					next day with as little pain as possible; and along with the tents apply a
					cataplasm, consisting of a mass (<hi rend="ital">maza</hi>) of fine flour
					pounded in vinegar, or boiled so as to render it as glutinous as possible. On
					the next day, when you remove the tent, having examined the bone to see what
					injury it has sustained, if the wound in the bone be not right seen by you, nor
					can you discover what mischief the bone itself has sustained, but the instrument
					seems to have penetrated to the bone so as to have injured it, you must scrape
					the bone with a raspatory to a depth and length proportionate to the suture of
					the patient, and again in a transverse direction, for the sake of the fractures
					which are not seen, and of the contusions which are not discovered, as not being
					accompanied with depression of the bone from its natural position. For the
					scraping discovers the mischief, if the injuries in the bone be not otherwise
					manifest. And if you perceive an indentation (<hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>) left
					in the bone by the blow, you must scrape the dint itself and the surrounding
					bones, lest, as often happens, there should be a fracture and contusion, or a
					contusion alone, combined with the dint, and escape observation. And when you
					scrape the bone with the raspatory, and it appears that the wound in the bone
					requires the operation, you must not postpone it for three days, but do it
					during this period, more especially if the weather be hot, and you have had the
					management of the treatment from commencement. If you suspect that the bone is
					broken or contused, or has sustained both these injuries, having formed your
					judgement from the severity of the wound, and from the information of the
					patient, as that the person who inflicted the wound, provided it was done by
					another person, was remarkably strong, and that the weapon by which he was
					wounded was of a dangerous description, and then that the man had been seized
					with vertigo, dimness of vision, and stupor, and fell to the ground,- under
					these circumstances, if you cannot discover whether the bone be broken,
					contused, or both the one and the other, nor can see<pb n="p.155"/> the truth of
					the matter, you must dissolve the jet-black ointment, and fill the wound with it
					when this dissolved, and apply a linen rag smeared with oil, and then a
					cataplasm of the maza with a bandage; and on the next day, having cleaned out
					the wound, scrape the bone with the raspatory. And if the bone is not sound, but
					fractured and contused, the rest of it which is scraped will be white; but the
					fracture and contusion, having imbibed the preparation, will appear black, while
					the rest of the bone is white. And you must again scrape more deeply the
					fracture where it appears black; and, if you thus remove the fissure, and cause
					it to disappear, you may conclude that there has been a contusion of the bone to
					a greater or less extent, which has occasioned the fracture that has disappeared
					under the raspatory; but it is less dangerous, and a matter of less consequence,
					when the fissure has been effaced. But if the fracture extend deep, and do not
					seem likely to disappear when scraped, such an accident requires trepanning. But
					having performed this operation, you must apply the other treatment to the
					wound.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="15">
				<head>Part 15</head>
				<p>You must be upon your guard lest the bone sustain any injury from the fleshy
					parts if not properly treated. When the bone has been sawed and otherwise
					denuded, whether it be actually sound, or only appears to be so, but has
					sustained some injury from the blow, there may be danger of its suppurating
					(although it would not otherwise have done so), if the flesh which surrounds the
					bone be ill cured, and become inflamed and strangled; for it gets into a febrile
					state, and becomes much inflamed. For the bone acquires heat and inflammation
					from the surrounding flesh, along with irritation and throbbing, and the other
					mischiefs which are in the flesh itself, and from these it gets into a state of
					suppuration. It is a bad thing for the flesh (<hi rend="ital"
					>granulations?</hi>) in an ulcer to be moist and mouldy, and to require a long
					time to become clean. But the wound should be made to suppurate as quickly as
					possible; for, thus the parts surrounding the wound would be the least disposed
					to inflammation, and would become the soonest clean; for the flesh which has
					been chopped and bruised by the blow, must necessarily suppurate and slough
					away. But when cleaned the wound must <pb n="p.156"/>be dried, for thus the
					wound will most speedily become whole, when flesh devoid of humors grows up, and
					thus there will be no fungous flesh in the sore. The same thing applies to the
					membrane which surrounds the brain: for when, by sawing the bone, and removing
					it from the meninx, you lay the latter bare, you must make it clean and dry as
					quickly as possible, lest being in a moist state for a considerable time, it
					become soaked therewith and swelled; for when these things occur, there is
					danger of its mortifying.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="16">
				<head>Part 16</head>
				<p>A piece of bone that must separate from the rest of the bone, in consequence of a
					wound in the head, either from the indentation (<hi rend="ital">hedra</hi>) of a
					blow in the bone, or from the bone being otherwise denuded for a long time,
					separates mostly by becoming exsanguous. For the bone becomes dried up and loses
					its blood by time and a multiplicity of medicines which are used; and the
					separation will take place most quickly, if one having cleaned the wound as
					quickly as possible will next dry it, and the piece of bone, whether larger or
					smaller. For a piece of bone which is quickly dried and converted, as it were,
					into a shell, is most readily separated from the rest of the bone which retains
					its blood and vitality; for, the part having become exsanguous and dry, more
					readily drops off from that which retains its blood and is alive.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="17">
				<head>Part 17</head>
				<p>Such pieces of bone as are depressed from their natural position, either being
					broken off or chopped off to a considerable extent, are attended with less
					danger, provided the membrane be safe; and bones which are broken by numerous
					and broader fractures are still less dangerous and more easily extracted. And
					you must not trepan any of them, nor run any risks in attempting to extract the
					pieces of bone, until they rise up of their own accord, upon the subsidence of
					the swelling. They rise up when the flesh (<hi rend="ital">granulations</hi>)
					grows below, and it grows from the diploe of the bone, and from the sound
					portion, provided the upper table alone be in a state of necrosis. And the flesh
					will shoot up and grow below the more quickly, and the pieces of bone ascend, if
					one will get the wound to suppurate and make it clean as quickly as possible.
					And when both the tables of the<pb n="p.157"/> bone are driven in upon the
					membrane, I mean the upper and lower, the wound, if treated in the same way,
					will very soon get well, and the depressed bones will quickly rise up.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="18">
				<head>Part 18</head>
				<p>The bones of children are thinner and softer, for this reason, that they contain
					more blood [than those of adults]; and they are porous and spongy, and neither
					dense nor hard. And when wounded to a similar or inferior degree by weapons of
					the same or even of an inferior power, the bone of a young person more readily
					and quickly suppurates, and that in less time than the bone of an older person;
					and in accidents, which are to prove fatal, the younger person will die sooner
					than the elder. But if the bone is laid bare of flesh, one must attend and try
					to find out, what even is not obvious to the sight, and discover whether the
					bone be broken and contused, or only contused; and if, when there is an
					indentation in the bone, whether contusion, or fracture, or both be joined to
					it; and if the bone has sustained any of these injuries, we must give issue to
					the blood by perforating the bone with a small trepan, observing the greatest
					precautions, for the bone of young persons is thinner and more superficial than
					that of elder persons.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="19">
				<head>Part 19</head>
				<p>When a person has sustained a mortal wound on the head, which cannot be cured,
					nor his life preserved, you may form an opinion of his approaching dissolution,
					and foretell what is to happen from the following symptoms which such a person
					experiences. When a bone is broken, or cleft, or contused, or otherwise injured,
					and when by mistake it has not been discovered, and neither the raspatory nor
					trepan has been applied as required, but the case has been neglected as if the
					bone were sound, fever will generally come on if in winter, and in summer the
					fever usually seizes after seven days. And when this happens, the wound loses
					its color, and the inflammation dies in it; and it becomes glutinous, and
					appears like a pickle, being of a tawny and somewhat livid color; and the bone
					then begins to sphacelate, and turns black where it was white before, and at
					last becomes pale and blanched. But when suppuration is fairly established in
					it, small blisters form on the tongue and he dies delirious. And, for the most
					part, <pb n="p.158"/>convulsions seize the other side of the body; for, if the
					wound be situated on the left side, the convulsions will seize the right side of
					the body; or if the wound be on the right side of the head, the convulsion
					attacks the left side of the body. And some become apoplectic. And thus they die
					before the end of seven days, if in summer; and before fourteen, if in winter.
					And these symptoms indicate, in the same manner, whether the wound be older or
					more recent. But if you perceive that fever is coming on, and that any of these
					symptoms accompany it, you must not put off, but having sawed the bone to the
					membrane (<hi rend="ital">meninx</hi>), or scraped it with a raspatory (and it
					is then easily sawed or scraped), you must apply the other treatment as may seem
					proper, attention being paid to circumstances.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="20">
				<head>Part 20</head>
				<p> When in any wound of the head, whether the man has been trepanned or not, but
					the bone has been laid bare, a red and erysipelatous swelling supervenes in the
					face, and in both eyes, or in either of them, and if the swelling be painful to
					the touch, and if fever and rigor come on, and if the wound look well, whether
					as regards the flesh or the bone, and if the parts surrounding the wound be
					well, except the swelling in the face, and if the swelling be not connected with
					any error in the regimen, you must purge the bowels in such a case with a
					medicine which will evacuate bile; and when thus purged the fever goes off, the
					swelling subsides, and the patient gets well. In giving the medicine you must
					pay attention to the strength of the patient.<note>The practice advocated in
						this paragraph is alluded to by Paulus AEgineta, in his chapter on Fractures
						of the Skull. (vi., 90.)</note></p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="21">
				<head>Part 21</head>
				<p> With regard to trepanning, when there is a necessity for it, the following
					particulars should be known. If you have had the management of the case from the
					first, you must not at once saw the bone down to the meninx; for it is not
					proper that the membrane should be laid bare and exposed to injuries for a
					length of time, as in the end it may become fungous. And there is another danger
					if you saw the bone down to the meninx and remove it at once, lest in the act of
					sawing you should wound the meninx. But in trepanning, when only a very little
					of the bone remains to be sawed through, and the bone can be moved, <pb
						n="p.159"/>you must desist from sawing, and leave the bone to fall out of
						itself.<note>The operation here described by our author is the more
						deserving of attention, as it appears to have been peculiar to him. It is
						not described by Celsus, Paulus AEgineta, Albucasis, nor any one of the
						ancient authorities, as far as I can find; neither am I aware of its having
						been attempted in modern times. The object of it, however, seems to be very
						rational, namely, to avoid doing serious injury to the dura mater by tearing
						the bone forcibly from it at once.</note> For to a bone not sawed through,
					and where a portion is left of the sawing, no mischief can happen; for the
					portion now left is sufficiently thin. In other respects you must conduct the
					treatment as may appear suitable to the wound. And in trepanning you must
					frequently remove the trepan, on account of the heat in the bone, and plunge it
					in cold water. For the trepan being heated by running round, and heating and
					drying the bone, burns it and makes a larger piece of bone around the sawing to
					drop off, than would otherwise do. And if you wish to saw at once down to the
					membrane, and then remove the bone, you must also, in like manner, frequently
					take out the trepan and dip it in cold water. But if you have not charge of the
					treatment from the first, but undertake it from another after a time, you must
					saw the bone at once down to the meninx with a serrated trepan, and in doing so
					must frequently take out the trepan and examine with a sound (specillum), and
					otherwise along the tract of the instrument. For the bone is much sooner sawn
					through, provided there be matter below it and in it, and it often happens that
					the bone is more superficial, especially if the wound is situated in that part
					of the head where the bone is rather thinner than in other parts. But you must
					take care where you apply the trepan, and see that you do so only where it
					appears to be particularly thick, and having fixed the instrument there, that
					you frequently make examinations and endeavor by moving the bone to bring it up.
					Having removed it, you must apply the other suitable remedies to the wound. And
					if, when you have the management of the treatment from the first, you wish to
					saw through the bone at once, and remove it from the membrane, you must, in like
					manner, examine the tract of the instrument frequently with the sound,<pb
						n="p.160"/> and see that it is fixed on the thickest part of the bone, and
					endeavor to remove the bone by moving it about. But if you use a perforator (<hi
						rend="ital">trepan?</hi>), you must not penetrate to the membrane, if you
					operate on a case which you have had the charge of from the first, but must
					leave a thin scale of bone, as described in the process of sawing.</p>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
