<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>For Callias from Speeches (English). Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Lysias</author>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <extent>about 544Kb</extent>

      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Lysias</author>
            <title>Lysias with an English translation by W.R.M. Lamb, M.A.</title>

            <imprint>
              <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                Ltd.</publisher>
              <date>1930</date>
            </imprint>
          </monogr>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>

    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="speech"/>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
<change><date>2/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>revise markup</item>
</change>
<change><date>6/92</date><respStmt><name>wmerrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>checkmark</item>
</change>
<change><date>10/92</date><respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed the notes and regularized tagging capitalization; combined the two Lysias files</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <p>
        <milestone n="Intro" unit="part"/><milestone n="1" unit="section"/><milestone ed="P"
          unit="para"/>If Callias had anything else than his life at stake in this trial, gentlemen
        of the jury, I should be content with what you have heard from the other speakers; but, as
        it is, and when he urges and requests me, and he is not only a friend of mine but was one of
        my father's so long as he lived, and we have had many arrangements between us, I feel it
        would be disgraceful not to support Callias so far as justice requires and my ability
        permits. <milestone n="Narr" unit="part"/>
        <milestone n="Proof" unit="part"/><milestone n="2" unit="section"/>I did expect, indeed,
        that the character that he showed as an alien residing in this city would far more readily
        gain for him some benefit at your hands than allow him to face so grave a danger because of
        such accusations as you have heard. But I find that these designing persons make life no
        less dangerous for those who have done no wrong than for those who are guilty of many
        misdeeds. <milestone n="3" unit="section"/>You, however, ought not to credit the statements
        of mere servants and discredit those of the accused; for you should reflect that no one,
        either private citizen or magistrate, has ever indicted Callias before, and that while
        dwelling in this city he has bestowed many benefits upon you, and has arrived at his time of
        life with a blameless reputation; whereas these men, having spent their lives in committing
        serious offences and incurring a variety of troubles, make their speeches to-day with an air
        of having performed a great service, merely in the hope of freedom.<note anchored="true"
          resp="Loeb">A slave whose accusation was accepted as true was rewarded with freedom. Cf.
            <bibl n="Lys. 7.16">Lys. 7.16</bibl>.</note> And I am not surprised; <milestone n="4"
          unit="section"/>for they know that, if they are convicted of lying, they will suffer
        nothing worse than their actual lot; while if they succeed in deceiving you they will be rid
        of their present troubles. Yet surely such men as these, whether accusers or witnesses,
        should win no credit, when they have a great profit to make for themselves by their
        statements concerning others; much rather should it be given to those who, to uphold the
        public weal,<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Perhaps Callias was employed by the stewards
          of the sacred treasure of the Parthenon, and was accused of embezzling some of it.</note>
        involve themselves in danger. <milestone n="5" unit="section"/>The trial, in my opinion,
        ought to be regarded, not as the personal affair of the accused, but as the common concern
        of everybody in the city; for these<note anchored="true" resp="Loeb">Others besides Callias
          appear to have been involved in the accusation.</note> are not the only people who own
        servants; they are owned by everyone else, and looking at the fate of the accused will no
        longer ask themselves by what great service to their masters they might gain their freedom,
        but by what lying information about them.<gap/>
        <milestone n="Concl" unit="part"/></p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
