<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Lacritus </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>The Phaselites,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Phaselis was a town in Bithynia,
                        on the southern coast of Asia Minor.</note> men of the jury, are up to no
                    new tricks; they are merely doing what it is their wont to do. For they are the
                    cleverest people at borrowing money on your exchange; but, as soon as they get
                    it and have drawn up a maritime contract, they straightway forget the contract
                    and the laws, and that they are under obligation to pay back what they have
                    received. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>They consider that, if they pay their debts, it is like having lost something of
                    their own private property, and, instead of paying, they invent sophisms, and
                    special pleas, and pretexts; and are the most unprincipled and dishonest of men.
                    Here is a proof of this. Out of the hosts of people, both Greeks and barbarians,
                    who frequent your exchange, the Phaselites alone have more lawsuits, whenever
                    the courts sit,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The courts for the settlement
                        of maritime cases sat from September to April, the period when the sea was
                        closed to navigation. See <bibl n="Dem. 33.23">Dem. 33.23</bibl>.</note>
                    than all others put together. That is the sort of people they are. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>But I, men of the jury, lent money to Artemo, this fellow's brother, in
                    accordance with the commercial laws for a voyage to Pontus and back. As he died
                    before having repaid me the money I have brought this suit against Lacritus here
                    in accordance with the same laws under which I made the contract, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>since he is the brother of Artemo and has possession of all his property, both
                    all that he left here and all that he had at Phaselis, and is the heir to his
                    whole estate; and since he can show no law which gives him the right to hold his
                    brother's property and to have administered it as he pleased, and yet to refuse
                    to pay back money which belongs to others and to say now that he is not the.
                    heir, but has nothing to do with the dead man's affairs. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>Such is the rascality of this fellow, Lacritus; but I beg of you, men of the
                    jury, to give me a favorable hearing in regard to this matter and, if I prove to
                    you that he has wronged us, who lent the money, and you as well, to render us
                    the aid that is our due. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>I myself, men of the jury, had not the slightest acquaintance with these men; but
                    Thrasymedes the son of Diophantus, that well-known Sphettian,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Sphettus was a deme of the tribe Acamantis.</note> and
                    Melanopus, his brother, are friends of mine, and we are on the most intimate
                    terms possible. These men came up to me with Lacritus here, whose acquaintance
                    they had made in some way or other—how, I do not know,—</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>and asked me to lend money to Artemo, this man's brother, and to Apollodorus for
                    a voyage to Pontus, that they might be engaged in a trading enterprise.
                    Thrasymedes like myself knew nothing of the rascality of these people, but
                    supposed them to be honorable men and such as they pretended and declared
                    themselves to be; and that they would do all that they promised and that this
                    fellow Lacritus undertook that they should do. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>He was utterly deceived, and had no idea what monsters these men were with whom
                    he was associating. I allowed myself to be persuaded by Thrasymedes and his
                    brother, and upon the assurance given me by this Lacritus, that his brothers
                    would do everything that was right, I, with the help of a Carystian,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Carystus was a town in Euboea.</note> who was a
                    friend of mine, lent thirty minae in silver. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>I wish you first, men of the jury, to hear the agreement in accordance with which
                    we lent the money, and the witnesses who were present when the loan was made;
                    after that I shall take up the remaining features of the case, and show you how
                    like burglars they acted in the matter of this loan.Read the agreement, and then
                    the depositions. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p><quote type="Agreement"><title>Agreement</title>Androcles of Sphettus and
                        Nausicrates of Carystus lent to Artemo and Apollodorus, both of Phaselis,
                        three thousand drachmae in silver for a voyage from Athens to Mendê or
                            Scionê,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Towns in the peninsula of
                            Pallenê, in Chalcidicê. Weather conditions would determine which port
                            should be entered.</note> and thence to Bosporus—or if they so choose,
                        for a voyage to the left parts of the Pontus as far as the Borysthenes,<note
                            resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The modern Dnieper.</note> and thence back
                        to Athens, on interest at the rate of two hundred and twenty-five drachmae
                        on the thousand; but, if they should sail out from Pontus to Hieron<note
                            resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was a place, called Hieron from a
                            temple of Zeus, at the entrance to the Thracian Bosporus on the Asiatic
                            side.</note> after the rising of Arcturus,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">About the middle of September. This was considered a
                            perilous season for navigation; hence the higher rate of
                            interest.</note> at three hundred on the thousand, on the security of
                        three thousand jars of wine of Mendê, which shall be conveyed from Mendê or
                        Scionê in the twenty-oared ship of which Hyblesius is owner.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p><quote type="continued">They give these goods as security, owing no money upon
                        them to any other person, nor will they make any additional loan upon this
                        security; and they agree to bring back to Athens in the same vessel all the
                        goods put on board in Pontus as a return cargo; and, if the goods are
                        brought safe to Athens, the borrowers are to pay to the lenders the money
                        due in accordance with the agreement within twenty days after they shall
                        have arrived at Athens, without deduction save for such jettison as the
                        passengers shall have made by common agreement, or for money paid to
                        enemies; but without deduction for any other loss. And they shall deliver to
                        the lenders in their entirety the goods offered as security to be under
                        their absolute control until such time as they shall themselves have paid
                        the money due in accordance with the agreement.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p><quote type="continued">And, if they shall not pay it within the time agreed
                        upon, it shall be lawful for the lenders to pledge the goods or even to sell
                        them for such price as they can get; and if the proceeds fall short of the
                        sum which the lenders should receive in accordance with the agreement, it
                        shall be lawful for the lenders, whether severally or jointly, to collect
                        the amount by proceeding against Artemo and Apollodorus, and against all
                        their property whether on land or sea, wheresoever it may be, precisely as
                        if judgement had been rendered against them and they had defaulted in
                        payment.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p><quote type="continued">And, if they do not enter Pontus, but remain in the
                        Hellespont ten days after the rising of the dogstar,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">The ten days following the rising of Sirius—July 25 to
                            August 5—were, it was thought, apt to be stormy.</note> and disembark
                        their goods at a port where the Athenians have no right of reprisals,<note
                            resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In such ports Athenian ships would be
                            safe.</note> and from thence complete their voyage to Athens, let them
                        pay the interest written into the contract the year before.<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">If the return voyage is delayed until the legal year has
                            expired (at the summer solstice) the rate of interest is to remain
                            unchanged.</note> And if the vessel in which the goods shall be conveyed
                        suffers aught beyond repair, but the security is saved, let whatever is
                        saved be the joint property of the lenders. And in regard to these matters
                        nothing shall have greater effect than the agreement.<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">That is, the terms of the contract shall be absolute.
                            Compare <bibl n="Dem. 35.39">Dem. 35.39</bibl>.</note><milestone ed="P"
                            unit="para"/>Witnesses: Phormio of Peiraeus, Cephisodotus of Boeotia,
                        Heliodorus of Pitthus.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Pittus (Pithus) was
                            a deme of the tribe Cecropis.</note></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Now read the depositions.<quote type="Deposition"
                            ><title>Deposition</title><p>Archenomides, son of Archedamas, of
                            Anagyrus, deposes that Androcles of Sphettus, Nausicrates of Carystus,
                            and Artemo and Apollodorus, both of Phaselis, deposited articles of
                            agreement with him, and that the agreement is still in custody in his
                            hands.</p></quote>Read also the deposition of those who were
                        present.<quote type="Deposition"><title>Deposition</title>Theodotus,
                        privileged alien, Charinus, son of Epichares, of Leuconium, Phormio, son of
                        Ctephisophon, of Peiraeus, Cephisodotus of Boeotia and Heliodorus of Pitthus
                        depose that they were present when Androcles lent to Artemo three thousand
                        drachmae in silver, and that they know they deposited the agreement with
                        Archenomides of Anagyrus.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>In accordance with this agreement, men of the jury, I lent the money to Artemo,
                    this man's brother, at the request of Lacritus, and upon his engaging that I
                    should receive everything that was my due in accordance with the agreement under
                    which the loan was made. Lacritus himself drew up the agreement and joined in
                    sealing it after it was written; for his brothers were still youngish, in fact
                    mere boys, but he was Lacritus, of Phaselis, a personage of note, a pupil of
                        Isocrates.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The noted orator, essayist, and
                        teacher of rhetoric.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>It was he who managed the whole matter, and he bade me look to him; for he
                    declared that he would himself do everything that was right for me, and that he
                    would stay in Athens, while his brother Artemo would sail in charge of the
                    goods. At that time, men of the jury, when he wanted to get the money from us,
                    he declared that he was both the brother and the partner of Artemo, and spoke
                    with wondrous persuasiveness; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>but, as soon as they got possession of the money, they divided it, and used it as
                    they pleased; while as for the maritime agreement on the terms of which they
                    secured the money, in no matter great or small did they carry out its
                    provisions, as the facts themselves make clear. And in all these things this
                    fellow Lacritus was the prime mover. I shall take up the clauses of the contract
                    one by one, and shall show that in no single instance have these men done what
                    was right. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>In the first place it stands written that they borrowed from us thirty minae on
                    three thousand jars<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The <foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >kera/mion</foreign> held about six gallons.</note> of wine, giving out
                    that they possessed security for thirty minae more, so that the price of the
                    wine would amount to a talent of money, including the expenses to be incurred in
                    the stowage of the wine; and that these three thousand jars were to be conveyed
                    to Pontus in the twenty-oared ship, of which Hyblesius was owner. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>These provisions, men of the jury, stand written in the agreement which you have
                    heard. But instead of three thousand jars, these men did not put even five
                    hundred on board the boat; and instead of having bought the quantity of wine
                    which they should have, they used the money in whatever way they pleased; as for
                    those three thousand jars which the agreement called for, they never meant nor
                    intended to put them on board.</p>
                <p>To prove that these statements of mine are true, take the deposition of those who
                    sailed with them in the same ship. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p><quote type="Deposition"><title>Deposition</title><milestone ed="P" unit="para"
                        />Erasicles deposes that he was pilot of the ship of which Hyblesius was
                        owner, and that to his knowledge Apollodorus<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">Perhaps a bit of carelessness on the part of the writer
                            of this spurious deposition. In <bibl n="Dem. 34.16">Dem. 34.16</bibl>
                            we are told that it was Artemo who was to sail with the cargo.</note>
                        was conveying in the ship four hundred and fifty jars of Mendaean wine, and
                        no more; and that Apollodorus conveyed no other cargo in the ship to
                            Pontus.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Hippias, son of Athenippus, of
                        Halicarnassus, deposes that he too sailed in the ship of Hyblesius as
                        supercargo of the vessel and that to his knowledge Apollodorus of Phaselis
                        was conveying in the ship from Mendê to Pontus four hundred and fifty jars
                        of Mendaean wine, and no other cargo.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>In
                        addition to these, written affidavits<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >Affidavits, taken down in writing in the presence of witnesses
                            appointed for the purpose, and verified by them under oath, were
                            accepted as evidence when the individuals could not be present in
                            person.</note> were submitted by Archiades, son of Mnesonidas,of
                        Acharnae, Sostratus, son of Philip, of Histiaea, Eumarichus, son of Euboeus,
                        of Histiaea, Philtiades, son of Ctesias, of Xypetê, and Dionysius, son of
                        Democratides, of Cholleidae.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Acharnae was a
                            deme of the tribe Oeneïs, Xypetê a deme of the tribe Cecropis, and
                            Cholleidae a deme of the tribe Aegeis.</note></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>In regard, then, to the quantity of wine which it was their duty to put on board
                    the ship that was what they contrived to do; and from this point they began from
                    its very first clause to violate the agreement and to fail to perform what it
                    required. The next clause that stands written in the agreement states that they
                    pledge these goods free from all encumbrances; that they owe nothing to anyone
                    upon them; and that they will not secure further loans upon them from anyone.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>This is expressly stated, men of the jury. But what have these men done?
                    Disregarding the terms of the agreement they borrow money from a certain youth,
                    whom they deceived by stating that they owed nothing to anybody. Thus they
                    cheated us, and without our knowledge borrowed money upon our security, and they
                    also deceived that young man who lent them the money by alleging that the goods
                    upon which they borrowed from him were unencumbered. Such are the rascalities of
                    these men, and they are all clever devisings of this man Lacritus.To prove that
                    I am speaking the truth and that they did borrow additional sums contrary to the
                    agreement, the clerk shall read you the deposition of the man himself who made
                    the additional loan. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Read the deposition.<quote type="Deposition"
                            ><title>Deposition</title><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Aratus of
                        Halicarnassus deposes that he lent to Apollodorus eleven minae in silver on
                        the merchandise which he was conveying in the ship of Hyblesius to Pontus,
                        and on the goods purchased there as a return cargo; and that he was unaware
                        that the defendant had borrowed money from Androcles; for otherwise he would
                        not himself have lent the money to Apollodorus.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>Such are the rascalities of these men. But after this it stands written in the
                    agreement, men of the jury, that when they should have sold in Pontus the goods
                    which they brought thither, they should purchase with the proceeds other goods
                    as a return cargo, and should bring this return cargo back to Athens; and that
                    when they should have reached Athens, they should within twenty days repay us in
                    certified coin<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Certified, that is, as to weight
                        and fineness. Tampering with gold and silver coins seems not to be a merely
                        modern device.</note>; and that pending the payment we should have control
                    of the goods, and that they should deliver them to us in their entirety until we
                    should get back our money. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>These terms stand written thus precisely in the agreement. But these people, men
                    of the jury, have here shown most strikingly their own insolence and
                    shamelessness, and that they paid not the slightest heed to the terms written in
                    the agreement; but regarded the agreement as mere trash and nonsense. For they
                    neither purchased any other goods in Pontus nor took on board any return cargo
                    to be conveyed to Athens; and we who had lent the money, when these men
                    themselves returned from Pontus, had nothing which we could lay hold of or keep
                    in possession until we should recover our money; for these men brought nothing
                    whatsoever into your harbor. Nay, we have suffered the most unheard-of
                    treatment, men of the jury. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>In our own city, without ourselves having committed any wrong, or having had
                    judgement rendered against us in their favor, we have been robbed of our own
                    possessions by these men who are Phaselites, just as if rights of reprisal had
                    been given to Phaselites against Athenians.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">On
                        the right of reprisal, cf. <bibl n="Dem. 35.13">Dem. 35.13</bibl> above, and
                        see Smith, <title>Dictionary of Antiquities</title>, art. “Sylae.”</note>
                    For when they refuse to pay back what they received, what other name can one
                    give to such people, than that they take by force the goods of others? For my
                    own part, I have never heard of a more abominable act than that which these men
                    have committed in relation to us, and that, too, while admitting that they
                    received the money from us. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>For whereas all clauses in contracts which are open to dispute require a judicial
                    decision, men of the jury, those on the contrary which are admitted by both the
                    contracting parties, and concerning which there exist maritime agreements, are
                    held by all men to be final; and the parties are bound to abide by what is
                    written. That these men, however, have fulfilled not a single one of the
                    provisions of the agreement, but that from the very first they meditated fraud
                    and purposed dishonest action has been thus clearly proven against them by the
                    depositions of witnesses and by themselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>You must now hear the most outrageous thing which this fellow Lacritus has done;
                    for it was he who managed the whole affair. When they arrived here they did not
                    put into your port, but came to anchor in Thieves' Harbor,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Some small inlet, which cannot be identified with certainty,
                        used by thieves and smugglers. See Judeich, <title>Topographie von
                            Athen</title>, p. 450.</note> which is outside of the signs marking your
                    port; and to anchor in Thieves' Harbor is the same as if one were to anchor in
                    Aegina or Megara; for anyone can sail forth from that harbor to whatever point
                    he wishes and at any moment he pleases. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>Well, their vessel lay at anchor there for more than twenty-five days, and these
                    men walked about in your sample-market.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A place
                        in the market where samples of goods could be displayed. Compare <bibl
                            n="Dem. 50.24">Dem. 50.24</bibl>.</note> We on our part talked to them
                    and bade them see to it that we received our money back as soon as possible; and
                    they agreed, and said they were trying to arrange that very thing. While we thus
                    approached them, we at the same time kept an eye on them to see whether they
                    disembarked anything from the ship, or paid any harbor-dues.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The books of the harbor-masters would show whether the tax
                        of 2 percent had been collected, and thus whether any goods had been
                        landed.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>But when they had been in town a good many days, and we found that nothing had
                    been disembarked from the ship, nor had any harbor-dues been paid in their name,
                    we began from then on to press them more and more with our demands. And when we
                    made ourselves burdensome to them, this fellow Lacritus, the brother of Artemo,
                    answered that they would be unable to pay us, for all their goods were lost; and
                    Lacritus declared he could make out a good case in the matter.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">A sharp thrust at the sophist, ever ready “to make the worse
                        the better reason.”</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>We, men of the jury, were indignant at these words, but we gained nothing by our
                    indignation, for these men cared not a fig for it. Nevertheless we asked them in
                    what way the goods had been lost. This man, Lacritus, said that the ship had
                    been wrecked while sailing along the coast from Panticapaeum to Theodosia,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Panticapaeum is the modern Kertsch, and
                        Theodosia the modern Kaffa in the Crimea.</note> and that in the wreck of
                    the vessel the goods of his brothers which were at the time on board were lost;
                    there was on board salt fish, Coan wine, and sundry other things; this, they
                    said, had been put on board as a return cargo, and they had intended to bring it
                    to Athens, had it not been lost in the ship. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>That is what he said; but it is worth your while to learn the abominable
                    wickedness of these men, and their mendacity. Concerning the vessel which was
                    wrecked they had no contract,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The speaker's
                        contention is that even if the ship was wrecked, that fact does not release
                        Lacritus from his obligation; for the loan made by Androcles was secured not
                        by the ship, which appears to have been mortgaged to Antipater, but upon the
                        cargo of Mendaean wine and the return cargo which was to have been brought
                        from Pontus. The wares lost (by jettison when the ship was damaged) were
                        not, the speaker holds, the return cargo. That the ship was not actually
                        lost seems a necessary inference from <bibl n="Dem. 35.28">Dem.
                        35.28</bibl>, where it is stated that she returned to Athens.</note> but it
                    was another man who had lent from Athens upon the freight to Pontus, and on the
                    vessel itself. (Antipater was the lender's name; he was a Citian<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Citium is a port in Cyprus.</note> by birth.)
                    The Coan wine (eighty jars of wine that had turned sour) and the salt fish were
                    being transported in the vessel for a certain farmer from Panticapaeum to
                    Theodosia for the use of the laborers on his farm. Why, then, do they keep
                    alleging these excuses? It is in no wise fitting. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>Now please take the deposition first that of Apollonides, showing that it was
                    Antipater who lent money upon the vessel, and that these men were in no wise
                    affected by the shipwreck; and then that of Erasicles and that of Hippias,
                    showing that only eighty jars were being transported in the vessel.<quote
                        type="Depositions"><title>Depositions</title>Apollonides of Halicarnassus
                        deposes that to his knowledge Antipater, a Citian by birth, lent money to
                        Hyblesius for a voyage to Pontus on the ship of which Hyblesius was in
                        command, and on the freight to Pontus, and that he was himself part-owner of
                        the ship with Hyblesius; that slaves of his own were passengers on the ship;
                        and that, when the ship was wrecked, his servants were present and reported
                        the fact to him, and also the further fact that the ship, having no
                            cargo,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">No full cargo, that is; merely
                            the salt fish and the Coan wine mentioned above.</note> was wrecked
                        while sailing along the coast to Theodosia from Panticapaeum.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="section">
                <p><quote type="continued"><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Erasicles deposes that he
                        sailed with Hyblesius as pilot of the ship to Pontus, and when the ship was
                        sailing along the coast to Theodosia from Panticapaeum he knows that the
                        ship had no cargo; and that Apollodorus, the very man who is now defendant
                        in this suit,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If this clause is not an
                            interpolation, we must assume that Apollodorus was being sued as
                            co-defendant with Lacritus. But this whole inserted document may well be
                            spurious.</note> had no wine on board the vessel, but that about eighty
                        jars of Coan wine were being conveyed for a certain man of
                        Theodosia.Hippias, son of Athenippus, of Halicarnassus, deposes that he
                        sailed with Hyblesius as supercargo of the ship, and that when the ship was
                        sailing along the coast to Theodosia from Panticapaeum, Apollodorus put on
                        board the ship one or two hampers of wool, eleven or twelve jars of salt
                        fish, and goat-skins—two or three bundles—and nothing else.In addition to
                        these, written affidavits<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note 17
                            above.</note> were submitted by Euphiletus, son of Damotimus, of
                        Aphidnae, Hippias, son of Timoxenus, of Thymaetadae, Sostratus, son of
                        Philip, of Histiaea, Archenomides, son of Strato, of Thria. and Philtiades,
                        son of Ctesicles, of Xypetê.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Aphidnae was a
                            deme of the tribe Acantis; Thymaetadae, a deme of the tribe
                            Hippothontis; Thria, a deme of the tribe Oeneïs; and Xypetê, a deme of
                            the tribe Cecropis.</note></quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="section">
                <p>Such is the shamelessness of these men. Now, men of the jury, take thought in
                    your own minds, whether you ever knew or heard of any people importing wine by
                    way of trade from Pontus to Athens, and especially Coan wine. The very opposite
                    is, of course, the case. Wine is carried to Pontus from places around us, from
                    Peparethus, and Cos, and Thasos<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Peparethus,
                        Cos, and Thasos were all islands in the Aegean.</note> and Mendê, and from
                    all sorts of other places; whereas the things imported here from Pontus are
                    quite different. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="section">
                <p>When we refused to let them off, and questioned them as to whether any of the
                    goods were saved in Pontus, the defendant, Lacritus, answered that one hundred
                    Cyzicene staters<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note 11 on <bibl
                            n="Dem. 34.23">Dem. 34.23</bibl>.</note> were saved; and that his
                    brother had lent this sum in gold in Pontus to a certain shipowner of Phaselis,
                    a fellow-countryman and friend of his; and that he was unable to get it back, so
                    that this also was as good as lost. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="section">
                <p>This is what was said by this fellow, Lacritus; but the agreement, men of the
                    jury, does not say this. It bids these men to take on board a return cargo, and
                    bring it back to Athens; not to lend our property without our consent to
                    whomsoever in Pontus they pleased, but to deliver it in its entirety to us at
                    Athens, until we should recover all the money which we had lent.<milestone
                        ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, please read the agreement again.<quote
                        type="Agreement">
                        <title>Agreement</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="section">
                <p>Does the agreement, men of the jury, bid these men lend our money, and that to a
                    man whom we do not know, and have never seen? Or does it bid them put on board
                    their ship a return cargo and convey it to Athens, and there display it to us,
                    and deliver it to us in its entirety? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="section">
                <p>The agreement does not permit anything to have greater effect than the terms
                    contained in it, nor that anyone should bring forward any law or decree or
                    anything else whatever to contravene its provisions; yet these men from the very
                    outset paid no heed to this agreement, but made use of our money as if it had
                    been their very own; so rascally are they as sophists and dishonest as men. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="section">
                <p>For my own part, I swear by Zeus the king and by all the gods, I never made it a
                    matter of reproach to anyone, men of the jury, nor blamed him, if he chose to be
                    a sophist and to pay money to Isocrates; I should be mad if I concerned myself
                    about anything of that sort. But, by Zeus, I do not think it right that men,
                    because they look down on people and think themselves clever, should covet the
                    property of others and seek to defraud them, trusting in their power of speech.
                    That is the part of a rascally sophist, who should be made to suffer for it.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="section">
                <p>This fellow Lacritus, men of the jury, has not come into court relying on the
                    justice of his case, but realizing perfectly what he and his brothers have done
                    in the matter of this loan; and because he considers that he is clever and will
                    easily provide arguments to defend evil practices,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The close parallel between this passage and the portrayal of
                        the “school” of Socrates in <bibl>Aristoph. Cl.</bibl> will hardly escape
                        the reader.</note> he thinks he will lead you astray just as he pleases. For
                    it is precisely in these matters that he professes himself to be clever, and he
                    asks money, and collects pupils, promising to instruct them in these very
                    things. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="section">
                <p>In the first place, he instructed his own brothers in this art, which you, men of
                    the jury, see to be evil and unjust—the art of borrowing on your exchange money
                    for a maritime adventure, and then defrauding the lenders, and refusing to pay
                    them. How could there be men baser than the one who teaches such an art, or than
                    those who learn of him? Since, then, he is so clever, and trusts in his power of
                    speaking and in the one thousand drachmae which he has paid to his teacher, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="section">
                <p>bid him show you, either that they did not borrow the money from us, or that,
                    having borrowed it, they have paid it back; or that agreements for overseas
                    trade ought not to be binding; or that it is right for people to use money for
                    some other purpose than that for which they received it under agreement. Let him
                    prove to you whatever one of these propositions he chooses. If he can so prove
                    it to you who sit to decide cases of mercantile contracts, I certainly concede
                    that he is the cleverest of men. But I know well that he would not be able to
                    prove it to you or induce you to believe any one of them. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="section">
                <p>But apart from all this, suppose, by heaven, men of the jury, that the case were
                    reversed,—that it was not this man's dead brother who owed me the money, but
                    that I owed his brother a talent, or eighty minae, or more or less; do you fancy
                    that this fellow, Lacritus, would employ the same language that he now so
                    lavishly uses? Or would say that he is not the heir and has nothing to do with
                    his brother's affairs? Or that he would not exact payment from me mercilessly,
                    as he has from the others who owed anything to the deceased, whether in Phaselis
                    or anywhere else? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="section">
                <p>And, if any one of us, being defendant in a suit brought by him, had dared to
                    enter a special plea declaring that the action was not one that could be brought
                    into court, I know well that he would have waxed indignant, and would have
                    protested to you, declaring that he was suffering treatment that was outrageous
                    and contrary to law, if anyone voted that his action, being a mercantile one,
                    was not one that could be brought. Then, Lacritus, if you consider this just for
                    yourself, why should it not be just for me? Do not the same laws stand written
                    for us all? And have we not all the same rights in regard to mercantile suits?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="section">
                <p>But he is a man so vile, so surpassing all human kind in baseness, that he seeks
                    to induce you to vote that this mercantile action cannot be brought when you are
                    now sitting to judge mercantile suits.What is it you would have, Lacritus? Is it
                    not enough that we should be robbed of the money we lent you but should we also
                    be given over to prison by you, if we do not pay the costs adjudged against us?
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="section">
                <p>Would it not be outrageous, and cruel, and shameful, for you, men of the jury, if
                    those who have lent money in your port for an adventure overseas, and have been
                    defrauded of it, should be led off to prison by those who borrowed and are
                    seeking to evade payment? Is it this, Lacritus, that you would have these
                    gentlemen sanction? But, men of the jury, where are we to obtain justice in the
                    matter of commercial contracts? Before what magistrates, or at what time? Before
                    the Eleven<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A board of police commissioners,
                        having jurisdiction in the case of capital crimes, and charged with the
                        custody of those convicted.</note>? But they bring into court burglars and
                    thieves and other evil-doers who are charged with capital crimes. Before the
                        Archon<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The archon (<foreign xml:lang="grc"
                            >e)pw/numos</foreign>) had the duty of passing judgement upon complaints
                        of parents, orphans, and unmarried girls who had inherited property. See
                            <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 56.6">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 56.
                        6-7</bibl>.</note>? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="section">
                <p>But it is for heiresses, and orphans, and parents that the Archon is appointed to
                    care. Then before the King-archon<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The functions
                        of the King-archon were largely religious, and the gymnesiarchs, or
                        superintendents of the festal games, were under his control. See <bibl
                            n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 57</bibl>.</note>? But we
                    are not gymnesiarchs, nor are we indicting anyone for impiety. Or will the
                        Polemarch<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The third archon, originally
                        minister of war, presided over the court in which cases regarding the rights
                        of aliens were settled. See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 58">Aristot. Ath.
                            Pol. 58</bibl>.</note> bring us into court? Yes, for disregard of a
                    patron, or for having no patron.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A resident
                        alien was required to be enrolled under some citizen as patron.</note> Well
                    then, the Generals<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Ten Generals were appointed
                        annually, one of whom had judicial functions connected with the appointment
                        of trierarchs. See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 61.1">Aristot. Ath. Pol.
                            61.1</bibl>.</note> are left. But they appoint the trierarchs; they
                    bring no mercantile suits into court. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="section">
                <p>I, however, am a merchant, and you are the brother and heir of a merchant, who
                    got from me money for a mercantile venture. Before whom, then, should this suit
                    be entered? Tell me, Lacritus; only say what is just and according to law. But
                    there lives no man clever enough to be able to say anything that is just in
                    connection with a case like yours. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="section">
                <p>It is not in these matters only, men of the jury, that I have suffered outrageous
                    wrongs at the hands of this man Lacritus; for, besides being defrauded of my
                    money, I should have been brought into the gravest danger, so far as his power
                    went, if the agreement made with these men had not come to my aid by bearing
                    witness that I lent the money for a voyage to Pontus and back to Athens. For you
                    know, men of the jury, how severe the law is, if any Athenian transports corn to
                    any other port than the port of Athens, or lends money for use in any market
                    save that of Athens; you know what penalties there are in such cases, and how
                    severe and to be dreaded they are. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="section">
                <p>However, read them the law itself, that they may have more exact
                        information.<quote type="Law"><title>Law</title>It shall be unlawful for any
                        Athenian or any alien residing at Athens or for any person over whom they
                        have control, to lend money on any vessel which is not going to bring to
                        Athens grain or the other articles specifically mentioned.<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">The reader does not quote the law in full, but abridges
                            it, and adds this clause as a sort of “et cetera.”</note> And if any man
                        lends out money contrary to this decree, information and an account of the
                        money shall be laid before the harbor-masters in the same manner as is
                        provided in regard to the ship and the grain. And he shall have no right to
                        bring action for the money which he has lent for a voyage to any other place
                        than to Athens, and no magistrate shall bring any such suit to
                        trial.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="section">
                <p>The law, men of the jury, is thus severe. But these men, the most abominable of
                    humankind, although it stands expressly written in the agreement that the money
                    should come back to Athens, allowed what they borrowed from us at Athens to be
                    conveyed to Chios. For when the Phaselite shipowner wanted to borrow other money
                    in Pontus from a certain Chian, and the Chian declared he would not lend it
                    unless he should receive as security all the goods which the shipowner had on
                    board or in his keeping, and unless those who had made the former loan should
                    consent to this, these men nevertheless permitted these goods of ours to become
                    security for the Chian, and put them all into his control. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="section">
                <p>On these terms they sailed back from Pontus with the Phaselite shipowner and the
                    Chian who had made the loan, and put into Thieves' Harbor, without anchoring in
                    your port. And now, men of the jury, money which was lent for a voyage from
                    Athens to Pontus and back again from Pontus to Athens has been brought to Chios
                    by these men. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="section">
                <p>It is, therefore, just as I assumed at the beginning of my speech—you are wronged
                    no less than we who lent the money. Consider, men of the jury, how the wrong
                    touches you also. When a man seeks to set himself above your laws, and makes of
                    no effect nautical agreements, but does away with them, and has sent away to
                    Chios money lent here on our exchange, is it not clear that such a man wrongs
                    you as well as us </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="section">
                <p>My words, men of the jury, are addressed to these people only, for it was to them
                    that I lent the money. It will remain for them to deal with that Phaselite
                    shipowner, their own countryman, to whom they say they lent the money unknown to
                    us and contrary to the agreement. For we do not know what transactions were
                    entered into by them with their countryman; but they know themselves. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="section">
                <p>This we hold to be a just course; and we beg you, men of the jury, to come to the
                    aid of us who are being wronged, and to punish those who devise evil and resort
                    to sophistries, as these men do. If you do this, you will be found to have
                    decided in accordance with your own interests, and will rid yourselves of all
                    the rascalities of unprincipled men, which certain ones of them are employing in
                    regard to maritime contracts.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
