<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Against Euthynus from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div n="1" type="section"><p>
         I have no lack of reasons for speaking in behalf of the plaintiff Nicias; for it so
          happens that he is my friend, that he is in need, that he is the victim of injustice, and
          that he has no ability as a speaker; for all these reasons, therefore, I am compelled to
          speak on his behalf. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="2" type="section"><p>
         The circumstances in which the transaction between Nicias and Euthynus came to be made I
          shall relate to you in as few words as I can. This Nicias, the plaintiff, after the Thirty
          Tyrants came into power and his enemies threatened to expunge his name from the number of
          those who were to have the rights of citizenship, and to include him in Lysander's<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">A list of citizens deprived of civic rights and enrolled for
            military service under the Spartan general Lysander, who after taking Athens had set up
            the government of the Thirty. Cf. <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 2.3">Xen. Hell. 2.3</bibl>.</note>
          list, being in fear of the state of affairs, mortgaged his house, sent his slaves outside
          of Attica, conveyed his furniture to my house, gave in trust three talents of silver to
          Euthynus, and went to live in the country. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="3" type="section"><p>
        Not long after this, desiring to take ship, he asked for the return of his money;
          Euthynus restored two talents, but denied that he had received the third. At that time
          Nicias was unable to take any further action, but he went to his friends and with
          complaints and recriminations told them how he had been treated. And yet he regarded
          Euthynus so highly and was in such fear of the government that he would sooner by far have
          been defrauded of a small sum and held his peace than have made complaints where no loss
          was suffered. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="4" type="section"><p>
         Such are the facts. But our cause presents difficulties. For Nicias, both when he was
          depositing the money and when he tried to get it back, had no one with him, either freeman
          or slave<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Transactions with a banker were generally
            conducted without witnesses; see <bibl n="Isoc. 17.2">Isoc. 17.2</bibl>.</note>; thus it
          is impossible either by torture of slaves or by testimony to get at the facts, but it is
          by circumstantial evidence that we must plead and you must judge which side speaks the
          truth. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="5" type="section"><p>
         I think that you all know that malicious prosecution is most generally attempted by
          those who are clever speakers but possess nothing, whereas the defendants lack skill in
          speaking but are able to pay money. Well, Nicias is better off than Euthynus, but has less
          ability as a speaker; so that there is no reason why he should have proceeded against
          Euthynus unjustly. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="6" type="section"><p>
        No indeed, but from the very facts in the case anyone can see that it is far more
          probable that Euthynus received the money and then denied having done so than that Nicias
          did not entrust it to him and then entered his complaint. For it is self-evident that it
          is always for the sake of gain that men do wrong. Now those who defraud others are in
          possession of the fruit of their crimes, but their accusers do not even know if they shall
          get back anything. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="7" type="section"><p>
        Besides, when conditions in the city were unsettled and the courts were suspended, it was
          useless for Nicias to sue Euthynus and the latter had no cause for fear though guilty of
          the fraud. It was not surprising, therefore, at a time when those who had borrowed money
          even in the presence of witnesses denied it, that Euthynus should have robbed him of what
          he had received from him when neither was accompanied by witnesses. And it is not probable
          that at a time when not even those to whom money was justly owed could recover it, Nicias
          should have believed that he could obtain anything by an unjust accusation. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="8" type="section"><p>
         And again, even if nothing had stood in his way and he could have brought a false
          accusation against him and wished to do so, it can easily be seen that Nicias would not
          have proceeded against Euthynus. For those who desire to act in this way do not begin with
          their friends, but in alliance with them proceed against others and accuse those for whom
          they have neither respect nor fear, persons whom they see to be rich, but friendless and
          helpless. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="9" type="section"><p>
        Well then, in the case of Euthynus the opposite is true; he is the cousin of Nicias and
          has greater ability in speech and action, and although he has little money, he has many
          friends. In consequence, he is the last person whom Nicias would have proceeded against.
          And, in my opinion, knowing as I do their intimacy, neither would Euthynus ever have acted
          unjustly toward Nicias if he could have defrauded someone else of so large a sum. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="10" type="section"><p>
        But as it was, their transaction was simple.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See textual
            note.</note> It is possible to choose whomever you please from the whole body of
          citizens for accusation, but you can defraud only the man who has entrusted a deposit with
          you. Thus Nicias, if he had desired to get money by blackmail, would not have proceeded
          against Euthynus, but the latter, when he resorted to fraud, had no other victim
          available. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="11" type="section"><p>
         But here is the strongest evidence and sufficient in every respect. When the charge was
          made, the oligarchy was in power, in which the situation of the two men was as follows:
          Nicias, even if he had been accustomed in former times to bring malicious accusations,
          then would have given up the practice, whereas Euthynus, even if he had never before given
          a thought to wrongdoing, then would have been tempted to act thus. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="12" type="section"><p>
        For his misdeeds were bringing him honors, but Nicias, because of his wealth, was the
          object of plotting. For you are all aware that, at that time, it was a greater danger to
          be wealthy than to engage in wrongdoing, for the evil-doers were seizing the property of
          others, whereas the rich were losing their own. For it was the custom of those in whose
          hands the control of the city was, not to punish those who were guilty of offenses, but to
          despoil the possessors of property, and they regarded the criminals as loyal and the
          wealthy as inimical.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Lys. 12.5">Lys. 12.5
              ff.</bibl></note>
        
      </p></div>
      <div n="13" type="section"><p>
        Consequently it was not the problem before Nicias how he might get possession of the
          property of others by bringing malicious accusations, but how he might not be made a
          victim of wrongdoing, although himself innocent. For while any man who possessed the
          influence of Euthynus could steal what he had received on deposit and also bring charges
          against those to whom he had lent nothing, yet those who were in Nicias' position were
          compelled to absolve their debtors of just debts and to surrender their own property to
          blackmailers. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="14" type="section"><p>
        Euthynus himself could testify to the truth of what I say; for he knows that Timodemus
          extorted thirty minas from Nicias, not by demanding the payment of a debt, but by
          threatening him with summary arrest. And yet is it probable that Nicias went so far in
          folly that he was bringing malicious charges against others when his own life was in
          jeopardy; 
      </p></div>
      <div n="15" type="section"><p>
        that he was plotting to get the goods of others when he was unable to protect his own;
          that he was making other enemies in addition to those he already had; that he was unjustly
          accusing persons from whom, even if they confessed the theft, he could not have exacted
          punishment; and that he was trying to get the better of others at the time when even to
          have equality with them was beyond his power; and, finally, at the time when he was being
          forced to pay back what he had not received, he hoped to collect what he had not lent?
        
      </p></div>
      <div n="16" type="section"><p>
         Enough has been said concerning these matters. Perhaps Euthynus will repeat what indeed
          he has already said, that, if he had been trying to defraud Nicias, he never would have
          returned two-thirds of the deposit, while withholding merely the third part, but that
          whether he was intent upon acting unjustly or wished to act justly, he would have had the
          same intention in regard to the whole amount. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="17" type="section"><p>
        But you all know, I think, that all men, when they set about committing a crime, at the
          same time are looking about for a plea in defense; consequently, it should occasion no
          surprise that Euthynus, in view of this very argument, committed the crime. Besides, I
          could point out other men also who, after having received money, have restored the major
          portion of it, but retained a small part, and men who, though guilty of dishonesty in
          petty contracts, yet in important ones have shown themselves honest; 
      </p></div>
      <div n="18" type="section"><p>
        therefore, Euthynus is not the only person, nor yet the first, who has acted so. You must
          remember that, if you ever countenance such a plea by defendants, you will be establishing
          a legal provision as to the way a fraud should be committed; consequently, in the future,
          holders of deposits will indeed return a part, but will retain a part for themselves. For
          it will be to their advantage, if they can use their repayment of some as presumptive
          proof so that they will not be punished for their stealing the rest. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="19" type="section"><p>
         Consider, also, that it is easy to use on behalf of Nicias arguments similar to those
          employed in the defense of Euthynus. For instance, when Nicias recovered the two talents,
          no one was present as his witness; so that, if he wanted to make a malicious accusation
          and that seemed best to him, it is obvious that he would not have acknowledged the receipt
          of even the two talents, but would have made the same plea for the entire amount; in that
          case, Euthynus would now be liable to lose even a larger sum, and at the same time he
          would not be able to use the presumptive proof on which he now depends. 
      </p></div>
      <div n="20" type="section"><p>
         And, furthermore, no one can point to any culpable motive whatever that led Nicias to
          enter an accusation against Euthynus, but as to Euthynus, it is easy to see the reasons
          which induced him to commit a crime in that manner. For then Nicias was in adversity, all
          his relations and friends had heard him say that he had deposited his money with Euthynus.
        
      </p></div>
      <div n="21" type="section"><p>
        Euthynus knew, therefore, that many persons were aware that the money was in his keeping,
          but that no one knew the amount; in consequence he thought that if he diminished the
          amount he would not be found out, but if he withheld the whole sum, his guilt would be
          manifest. Therefore, he chose to take enough and have left a plea in his defense rather
          than to pay nothing back and be left without a possibility of denial.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The loss of a formal conclusion, or Epilogue, to the speech is suggested by
            the abrupt ending.</note>
      </p></div>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
