<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Apollodorus Against Callipus </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by Norman W. DeWitt, Ph.D.,
                            and Norman J. DeWitt, Ph.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1949</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>There is no situation harder to deal with, men of the jury, than when a man
                    possessing both reputation and ability to speak is audacious enough to lie and
                    is well provided with witnesses. For it becomes necessary for the defendant, no
                    longer to speak merely about the facts of the case, but about the character of
                    the speaker as well, and to show that he ought not to be believed on account of
                    his reputation. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>If you are to establish the custom, that those who are able speakers and who
                    enjoy a reputation are more to be believed than men of less ability, it will be
                    against yourselves that you will have established this custom. I beg you
                    therefore, if you ever decided any other case upon its merits, without becoming
                    partisans of either side, whether the plaintiff's or the defendant's, but
                    looking to justice alone, to decide the present case upon these principles. And
                    I shall set forth the facts to you from the beginning. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>Lycon, the Heracleote,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><placeName
                            key="tgn,7018769">Heraclea</placeName>, a colony of the Megarians and
                        Boeotians on the coast of <placeName key="tgn,7016608">Bithynia</placeName>,
                        on the <placeName key="tgn,7016619">Black Sea</placeName>.</note> men of the
                    jury, of whom the plaintiff himself makes mention, was a customer of my father's
                    bank like the other merchants, a guest friend of Aristonoüs of Decelea<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Decelea, a deme of the tribe
                        Hippothontis.</note> and Archebiades of Lamptrae,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Lamptrae, a deme of the tribe Erectheïs.</note> and a man of
                    prudence. This Lycon, when he was about to set out on a voyage to <placeName
                        key="tgn,1000172">Libya</placeName>, reckoned up his account with my father
                    in the presence of Archebiades and Phrasias, and ordered my father to pay the
                    money which he left (it was sixteen minae forty drachmae, as I shall show you
                    very clearly) to Cephisiades, saying that this Cephisiades was a partner of his,
                    a resident of Scyros,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Scyros, an island in the
                            <placeName key="tgn,7002675">Aegean</placeName>, east of <placeName
                            key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>.</note> but was for the time being
                    abroad on another mercantile enterprise. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>He instructed Archebiades and Phrasias to point him out and introduce him to my
                    father, when he should return from his journey. It is the custom of all bankers,
                    when a private person deposits money and directs that it be paid to a given
                    person, to write down first the name of the person making the deposit and the
                    amount deposited, and then to write on the margin “to be paid to so-and-so”; and
                    if they know the face of the person to whom payment is to be made, they do
                    merely this, write down whom they are to pay; but, if they do not know it, it is
                    their custom to write on the margin the name also of him who is to introduce and
                    point out the person who is to receive the money. For a grievous misfortune
                    befell this Lycon. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>No sooner had he set out, and was sailing around the Argolic gulf, than his ship
                    was captured by pirate vessels and his goods taken to <placeName
                        key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>, while he himself was shot down by an
                    arrow, and met his death. Immediately after this mischance this man Callippus
                    came to the bank, and asked whether they knew Lycon, the Heracleote. Phormion,
                    who is here present, answered that they knew him. “Was he a customer of yours?”
                    “He was,” said Phormion, “but why do you ask?” “Why?” said he, “I will tell you.
                    He is dead, and, as it happens, I am proxenos<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                        >The proxenos was sort of consular agent, empowered to act in the interest
                        of his country and his countryman in a foreign state.</note> of the
                    Heracleotes. I demand therefore that you show me your books, that I may know
                    whether he has left any money; for I must of necessity look after the affairs of
                    all the men of <placeName key="tgn,7008299">Heraclea</placeName>.” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>On hearing this, men of the jury, Phormion immediately showed him the books, and,
                    when he had done so, and Callippus (it was he himself, and not another) had read
                    them, and had seen in them the entry, “Lycon, the Heracleote, sixteen hundred
                    and forty drachmae, to be paid to Cephisiades; Archebiades of Lamptrae will
                    identify Cephisiades,” he went off in silence and for more than five months made
                    no mention of the matter. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>After this Cephisiades, having returned to <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
                        >Athens</placeName>, came to the bank and demanded the money, and in the
                    presence of Archebiades and Phrasias, men of the jury, the persons whom Lycon
                    had introduced to my father, and had hidden to identify Cephisiades, when he
                    should return and in the presence of other witnesses also, Phormion, who is here
                    in court, counted out and paid him the sixteen minae forty drachmae.</p>
                <p>To prove that I am speaking the truth, the clerk shall read you the depositions
                    which bear upon all these facts.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>That all I have told you is true, men of the jury, you have learned from the
                    depositions. However, a long time after this, the plaintiff Callippus came up to
                    my father in the city, and asked him if Cephisiades, to whom according to the
                    entry in the book the money left by Lycon the Heracleote was to be paid, had
                    returned to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. On my father's
                    replying that he thought so, but, if he wanted to go down to the Peiraeus, he
                    would find out the truth, Callippus said to him, “Do you know, Pasion, what it
                    is that I am asking you?”— </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>(and by Zeus and Apollo and Demeter, I shall make no false statement to you, men
                    of the jury, but shall relate to you what I heard from my father)—“You have a
                    chance,” he continued, “to do a good turn to me, and no harm to yourself. It
                    happens that I am proxenos of the Heracleotes, and you would be glad, I should
                    think, to have me get the money rather than an alien who resides in Scyros, and
                    is a man of no account. Matters have turned out like this. Lycon was without
                    children, and has left, as I am informed, no heir in his house. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>More than this, when he was brought to <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
                        >Argos</placeName>, wounded, he gave to Strammenus, the <placeName
                        key="tgn,5001993">Argive</placeName> proxenos of the Heracleotes, the
                    property which was brought in with him. I, therefore, am likewise in a position
                    to claim the money that is here; for I think it is right that I should have it.
                    Do you, therefore, if Cephisiades has not recovered it, say, if he should come
                    here, that I dispute his claim; and if he has recovered it, say that I came with
                    witnesses and demanded that the money be produced, or the person who has
                    received it; and, if anyone tries to defraud me, let him know that he is
                    defrauding a proxenos.” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>After he had spoken thus, my father answered, “Callippus, I want to oblige you (I
                    should be mad, if I did not), but on this condition, that I shall not damage my
                    own reputation, nor suffer any loss through the business; to suggest what you
                    propose to Archebiades and Aristonoüs and to Cephisiades himself, can cause me
                    no trouble; but if they do not choose to do as you say at my suggestion, you
                    must talk to them yourself.” “Be easy in your mind, Pasion,” said he; “if you
                    like, you will force them to do what I want.” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>This, men of the jury, is what the plaintiff said to my father, and what my
                    father repeated to Archebiades and Cephisiades at the plaintiff's request and as
                    a favor to him; and from this, little by little, this suit has been got up. I
                    was ready to swear by the most solemn of oaths, that I verily heard these
                    statements from my father. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>The plaintiff, however, who demands that you believe him as one speaking the
                    truth, waited for three years after my father had spoken for the first time to
                    Archebiades and the other friends of Cephisiades, and after they had refused to
                    pay any attention to Callippus or to what he said; then, when he learned that my
                    father was in poor health, and had difficulty in coming up to the city, and that
                    his sight was failing, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>he brought an action against him, not indeed an action for money, like the
                    present one, but an action for damages, declaring that my father had wrought him
                    injury by paying to Cephisiades the money which Lycon, the Heracleote, had left
                    in his keeping after having promised not to pay it without the plaintiff's
                    consent. After he had brought suit, he took back the papers from the public
                    arbitrator, and challenged my father to refer the case to Lysitheides, a friend
                    of Callippus himself and of Isocrates and Aphareus,<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">These were doubtless the famous orator and the tragic
                        poet.</note> and an acquaintance of my father. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>My father gave his consent, and during his lifetime Lysitheides despite his
                    intimacy with these men did not venture to commit any wrong against us. And yet
                    some of the plaintiff's friends are so lacking in shame, that they had the
                    audacity to depose that Callippus challenged my father to take an oath, and that
                    my father refused to swear before Lysitheides; and they imagine that they can
                    convince you that in that case Lysitheides, a friend of Callippus and the one
                    acting as arbitrator in the case, would have refrained from making an immediate
                    award against my father, especially since my father thus refused to make himself
                    the judge of his own case.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">By refusing, that
                        is, to take the oath on the basis of which the award would have been
                        made.</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>That I am telling the truth and that these men are lying, is proved, I claim, by
                    the very fact that Lysitheides would have made the award against my father, and
                    that I should now be defendant in an ejectment suit, and not in an action for
                    money; and, besides this, I shall bring before you as witnesses the persons who
                    were present on the various occasions when I met the plaintiff before
                        Lysitheides.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>That he did not challenge my father to an oath at that time, but now maligns him
                    after his death, and brings forward his own intimates who recklessly bear false
                    witness against me, you can easily see from the circumstantial evidence and from
                    the deposition. And that I was ready on my father's behalf to take the oath
                    which the law prescribes when an heir is sued in court on a charge brought
                    against one who is dead,— </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>that, namely, I believed that my father never agreed to pay the plaintiff the
                    money which Lycon left, and that the plaintiff was not introduced to my father
                    by Lycon; and Phormion was ready to swear that in very truth he had himself
                    reckoned up the amount with Lycon in the presence of Archebiades, and that
                    instructions were given him to pay the money to Cephisiades, and that
                    Archebiades had identified Cephisiades for him; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>also that when Callippus came for the first time to the bank, saying that Lycon
                    was dead and that he, Callippus, claimed the right to inspect the books to see
                    whether the Heracleote had left any money, he, Phormion, had at once shown him
                    the books, and that Callippus, after seeing the entry that payment was to be
                    made to Cephisiades, went away in silence, without filing any counterclaim or
                    making any protest to him about the payment of the money—in proof of all these
                    matters the clerk shall read you the depositions which establish both facts, and
                    also the law.<quote type="Depositions">
                        <title>Depositions</title>
                    </quote><quote type="Law">
                        <title>Law</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>Now, men of the jury, I shall show you that Lycon had no dealings with Callippus;
                    for I think this will be something to confound the impudent assurance of this
                    man, who asserts that this money was given to him by Lycon as a present. Lycon
                    had lent to Megacleides of <placeName key="perseus,Eleusis">Eleusis</placeName>
                    and his brother Thrasyllus the sum of forty minae for a voyage to Acê<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Acê, a town on the coast of <placeName
                            key="tgn,6004687">Phoenicia</placeName>.</note> but, when they changed
                    their minds and decided not to risk the voyage to that point, Lycon, after
                    making some complaints against Megacleides regarding the interest, and believing
                    that he had been deceived, quarrelled with him and went to law for the purpose
                    of recovering his loan. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>The proceedings were prolonged, as so large a sum was at stake, yet Lycon never
                    at any time called in Callippus for consultation; he sought the aid of
                    Archebiades and the friends of Archebiades, and it was Archebiades who brought
                    about a settlement between them.</p>
                <p>To prove that I am speaking the truth, I shall bring before you Megacleides
                    himself as a witness to these facts.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>You see, men of the jury, how intimate Lycon was with Callippus. He neither
                    called him in for consultation about his affairs, nor did he ever put up at the
                    home of Callippus as a guest; and this very fact is the one thing to which the
                    plaintiff's friends have not ventured to depose, that, namely, he ever did put
                    up at his house; for they knew well that, if they told any such lie as this,
                    they would at once be convicted by the slaves when these were put to the
                    torture. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>But I wish to mention to you a piece of circumstantial evidence so striking, that
                    it will, I think, convince you that Callippus has uttered nothing but a pack of
                    lies. If Lycon, men of the jury, had been as fond of the plaintiff and as
                    intimate with him as the plaintiff claims, and had wished to give him this money
                    as a present in the event of anything happening to himself, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>would it not have been better to have left the money outright in the custody of
                    Callippus, in which case, if he returned safe, he would have recovered it duly
                    and justly from one who was his friend and his proxenos, and, if anything had
                    happened to him, he would have given the money outright as he purposed? Would
                    this, I ask, not have been better than leaving it in the bank? For my part, I
                    think the former course would have been fairer and more highminded. However, he
                    is seen to have done nothing of the kind, so you must regard this as presumptive
                    evidence; no; he gave written and oral instructions that it was to Cephisiades
                    that the money was to be paid. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>I would have you regard the following point also, men of the jury. Callippus was
                    one of your citizens, a man able both to render a service and to do an injury,
                    while Cephisiades was a resident alien and a person without influence; so one
                    cannot suppose that my father would have taken the side of Cephisiades in
                    defiance of justice rather than do what was right for the plaintiff. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>Ah, but he will say perhaps, that my father got some private profit out of the
                    money, and therefore took sides with Cephisiades rather than with the plaintiff.
                    Then we are to believe, in the first place, that he wronged a man who would be
                    able to do him injury to twice the amount of his gains, and secondly that my
                    father in this instance was a base lover of gain, whereas in regard to special
                    taxes and public services and gifts to the state he was not. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>And did he, who never wronged a stranger, wrong Callippus? And did the plaintiff,
                    as he alleges, tender an oath to my father as to one who was a worthy man and
                    would tell no falsehood, and yet does he now speak of him as a base fellow, who
                    erases records of deposits? And, if my father refused to take the oath, as the
                    plaintiff claims, or to make payment, how could he have escaped immediate
                    condemnation? Who can believe this, men of the jury? I certainly think no one
                    can. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>And has Archebiades forsooth sunk to such an extreme of baseness as to testify
                    against Callippus, a fellow-demesman of his own, one in public life, and an
                    official, and to say that I am telling the truth while Callippus is lying, and
                    all this, when he knows that, if Callippus chooses to proceed against him for
                    false testimony, or to do no more than put him on oath, he will be compelled to
                    take whatever oath Callippus may require? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>And again, can anyone persuade you that Archebiades would perjure himself in
                    order that Cephisiades, a resident alien, might get the money, or Phormion
                    either, a man whom Callippus charges with having expunged some records of
                    deposit? It is not a probable thing, men of the jury. Nor is it right to judge
                    either Archebiades or my father guilty of any act of baseness; you know that my
                    father was too emulous of honor to indulge in any base or shameful practices,
                    and that his relations with Callippus were not such as to lead him through
                    contempt to do him an injury. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="section">
                <p>Callippus indeed does not appear to me to be a man of such slight importance as
                    to be treated with contempt—a man of such influence that last year, after he had
                    instituted this action against me, and had challenged me to refer the matter to
                    Lysitheides for arbitration (and I, although scorned by him, yet took wise
                    counsel in this at any rate—I made the reference in due legal form, and carried
                    the matter before the magistrate), Callippus, I say, induced the arbitrator, who
                    had been designated according to the laws, to pronounce his award without taking
                    oath, although I protested that he should give it on oath as the laws ordain,
                    his purpose being that he might be able to say before you, that Lysitheides, a
                    good and worthy man, had already given a decision regarding the matters at
                    issue. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="section">
                <p>Lysitheides, men of the jury, so long as my father lived, would probably not have
                    wronged him either with or without an oath, for he had a regard for him; but for
                    me he had no regard, while not upon his oath, although perhaps, if put upon his
                    oath, he would have abstained from wronging me in his own interest. This is why
                    he made the award without taking an oath.<milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>To prove
                    that I am speaking the truth, I shall, in regard to these matters also, bring
                    forward as witnesses those who were present.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="section">
                <p>That Callippus is able to achieve his ends contrary to the laws and contrary to
                    justice, you have heard, men of the jury, from the deposition. I, on my part,
                    beseech you on my own behalf and on my father's, to bear in mind that, in
                    support of all that I have said, I have produced before you witnesses and
                    circumstantial evidence and laws and sworn statements; and in the case of the
                    plaintiff I have shown that, while, if he had any claim to this money, he might
                    have proceeded against Cephisiades, who admits that he collected the money and
                    has it in his possession, and still take these pledges from me, he does not
                    proceed against him, although he knows that the money is not in our hands—I
                    beseech you to remember all these facts, and to give a verdict in my favor. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="section">
                <p>If you do this, you will have rendered a decision both just and in accordance
                    with the laws, and moreover one that is worthy of yourselves and of my father;
                    since for myself, I should rather let you take everything I have, than pay an
                    unjust claim as the victim of a malicious suit.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
