<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Passing of Peregrinus</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor>Austin Morris Harmon, 1878-1950</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>OCRd, tagged and added initial corrections to  the text</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg001.1st1K-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:1lg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1936</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202111">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">

<head>The Passing of Peregrinus<note><p>An account of the life and death of a Cynic philosopher
who for a time in his early life went over to Christianity,
practising it to the point of imprisonment under a very
tolerant administration, and after returning to Cynicism
became in his old age so enamoured of Indic ideas and precedents that he cremated himself at Olympia, just after the
games of A.D. 165, even as Calanus had done at Susa in the
presence of Alexander the Great and as Zarmarus had done
at Athens, after initiation into the mysteries, in the presence
of Augustus.</p>
<p>Writing soon after the event, of which he was a witness,
Lucian makes his main theme the story of what went on at
Olympia. The earlier life of Peregrinus is portrayed incidentally in a speech attributed by Lucian to someone whose name
he aa not know, but clearly made by Lucian himself (p. 8,
n. 2).</p>
<p>Lucian believes himself to be exposing a sham, whose
zeal was not at all for truth but only for applause and renown.
Many notable modern critics, including Zeller, Bernays,
Croiset, and Wilamowitz, dissent from his interpretation,
discerning in the man an earnest seeker after truth; for to
them thirst for glory is not an adequate explanation of his
final act. This point of view hardly embodies sufficient
recognition of the driving force of that motive with Greeks,
and particularly Greeks of the second century (Nock, Converston, p. 201). Greek writers recognised it as a possible
explanation of the behaviour of Calanus and of Zarmarus.
In this case, Lucian not only knew the man but knew others
who knew him: for instance, Demonax. Assuredly, the
interpretation that he gives is not his alone. Perhaps it is
not so far wrong after all. Certainly there are authentic
features in it, like the attempt of Proteus to get back the
inheritance he had previously renounced and bestowed upon
his native city, which make it impossible to see in him the
earnest and steadfast man” that Aulus Gellius thought him.</p></note></head>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="1"><p>


Best wishes from Lucian to Cronius.<note n="v.5.p.3.n.1"><p>The greeting here employed (its sense might perhaps be more adequately rendered by “Good issues to all your doings”) marks Cronius as a Platonist. Lucian himself (Lapsus, 4) ascribes its origin to Plato, and he employs it in addressing the philosopher Nigrinus (I, p. 98). A Platonist named Cronius is more than once mentioned by Porphyry, but to identify the two would contribute next to nothing to our knowledge of either. </p></note></p>

<p>
Unlucky Peregrinus, or, as he delighted to style
himself, Proteus,<note n="v.5.p.3.n.2"><p>Cf. Aulus Gellius, XII, 11: philosophum nomine Peregrinum, cui postea cognomentum Proteus factum est, virum gravem et constantem, etc. Lucian calls him Peregrinus Proteus in Demonax, 21 (I, p. 156), but simply Proteus the Cynic in adv. Indoct., 14 (III, p. 192), and he is Proteus to the Philostrati (cf. Vit. Soph. II, 1, 33 and for the elder Philostratus the title of his lost work Proteus the Cynic ; or, the Sophist), to Tatian (Orat. ad Graecos, 25), and to Athenagoras (Legat. de Christian., 26). The name Peregrinus is used in Aulus Gellius, VIII, 3, Ammianus Marcellinus, X XIX, 1, 39, Tertullian ad Martyres, 4, and Eusebius, Chron., Vol. II, p. 170, Schéne. From the passage in Gellius cited above we can infer only that he did not hear the sobriquet Proteus when he was in Athens. The manner of its employment by Lucian is sufficient evidence that it did not originate with Lucian, or after the death of Peregrinus. It was probably applied to him towards the close of his career. That it bears a sense very like what Lucian attributes to it is clear from Maximus of Tyre, VIII, 1. In § 27 Lucian professes to have heard that he wanted to change it to Phoenix after his decision to immolate himself. </p></note> has done exactly what Proteus
in Homer did.<note n="v.5.p.3.n.3"><p>The transformations of the sea-god in his effort to escape from Menelaus, who wanted to consult him, are told in the Odyssey, IV, 454-459. </p></note> After turning into everything for
the sake of notoriety and achieving any number of
transformations, here at last he has turned into fire;
so great, it seems, was the love of notoriety that
eae be him. And now your genial friend has got
imself carbonified after the fashion of Empedocles,
except that the latter at least tried to escape





<pb n="v.5.p.5"/>

observation when he threw himself into the crater,<note n="v.5.p.5.n.1"><p>Of Aetna; it was said that the manner of his death remained unknown until the mountain cast up one of his golden sandals. </p></note>
while this gentleman waited for that one of the
Greek festivals which draws the greatest crowds,
heaped up a very large pyre, and leaped into it
before all those witnesses; he even addressed the
Greeks on the subject not many days before his
venture.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
I think I can see you laughing heartily at the old
man’s drivelling idiocy—indeed, I hear you give
tongue as you naturally would: “Oh, the stupidity !
Oh, the vainglory! Oh”—everything else that we
are in the habit of saying about it all. Well, you
are doing this at a distance and with far greater
security, but I said it right by the fire and even
earlier in a great crowd of listeners, angering some
of them—as many as admired the old man’s
fool-hardiness; but there were others beside myself
who laughed at him. However, I narrowly missed
getting torn limb from limb for you by the Cynics
just as Actaeon was by his dogs or his cousin Pentheus
by the Maenads.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="3"><p>

The complete mise en scéne of the affair was as
follows. You know, of course, what the playwright
was like and what spectacular performances he
presented his whole life long, outdoing Sophocles
and Aeschylus. As for my part in it, as soon as I
came to Elis, in going up? by way of the gymnasium
I overheard a Cynic bawling out the usual street-corner invocations to Virtue in a loud, harsh voice,
and abusing everyone without exception. Then
his harangue wound up with Proteus, and to the best


<pb n="v.5.p.7"/>

of my ability I shall try to quote for you the very
words he said. You will find the style familiar, of
course, as you have often stood near them while
they were ranting.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
“Does anyone dare,” he said, ‘to call Proteus
vainglorious, O Earth, O sun, O rivers, O sea, O
Heracles, god of our fathers!—Proteus, who was
imprisoned in Syria, who renounced five thousand
talents in favour of his native land, who was banished
from the city of Rome, who is more conspicuous
than the sun, who is able to rival Olympian Zeus
himself? Because he has resolved to depart from
life by way of fire, are there people who attribute
this to vainglory? Why, did not Heracles do so?
Did not Asclepius and Dionysus,<note n="v.5.p.7.n.1"><p>The cases of Dionysus and Asclepius were not quite parallel. Zeus could not have Asclepius raising the dead, and so transferred his activities to a higher sphere by means of the thunderbolt. It was Semele, the mother of Dionysus, whom his other bolt carbonised; but as it certainly effected, even if only incidentally, the translation of Dionysus, and as one of the epigrams in the Anthology (XVI, 185) similarly links Dionysus with Heracles as having achieved immortality by fire, it is hard to see why so many editors have pruned the exuberance of Theagenes by excising mention of Dionysus from his remarks. Cf. Parl. of the Gods, 6 (p. 425). </p></note> by grace of the
thunderbolt? Did not Empedocles end by leaping
into the crater?”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
When Theagenes<note n="v.5.p.7.n.2"><p>We learn elsewhere in this piece that Theagenes lived in Patras and had property worth fifteen talents, obtained by lending money. Bernays (Lucian und die Kyniker, pp. 13-18) is very likely right in thinking this to be the man whose death in Rome is described by Galen (Meth. Med., 13, 15: X, 909 Kiihn), but he makes rather too much of tha passage as an endorsement of Theagenes. ; </p></note>—for that was the bawler’s ,
name—said that, I asked a bystander, “What is the
meaning of his talk about fire, and what have Heracles
and Empedocles to do with Proteus?” “Before
long,” he replied, “Proteus is going to burn himself
up at the Olympic festival.” “How,” said I, “and
why?” Then he undertook to tell me, but the
Cynic was bawling, so that it was impossible to hear
anyone else. I listened, therefore, while he flooded




<pb n="v.5.p.9"/>

us with the rest of his bilge-water and got off a
lot of amazing hyperbole about Proteus, for, not
deigning to compare him with the man of Sinope,<note n="v.5.p.9.n.1"><p>Diogenes, </p></note>
or his teacher Antisthenes, or even with Socrates
himself, he summoned Zeus to the lists. Then,
however, he decided to keep them about equal, and
thus concluded his speech:
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
“These are the two
noblest masterpieces that the world has seen—the
Olympian Zeus, and Proteus; of the one, the creator
and artist was Phidias, of the other, Nature. But
now this holy image is about to depart from among
men to gods, borne on the wings of fire, leaving us
bereft.” After completing this discourse with
copious perspiration, he shed tears in a highly
ridiculous way and tore his hair, taking care not to
pull very hard; and at length he was led away,
sobbing as he went, by some of the Cynics, who
strove to comfort him.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
After him, another man went up at once,<note n="v.5.p.9.n.2"><p>Evidently the Cynic had spoken from a high place (perhaps the portico of the asium) to which the new speaker now ascends. What Lucian has previously said (§ 2), together with his failure here to say a word about the identity or personality of the author of these remarks, puts it beyond doubt that the “other man” is Lucian himself, and that he expects his readers to draw this inference. The device is so transparent that its intent can be regarded only as artistic. It is employed also in The Hunuch, 10 (p. 341). Somewhat similar is his borrowing a Prologue from Menander to speak for him in The Mistaken Critic (p. 379). </p></note> not permitting the throng to disperse, but pouring a libation
on the previous sacrificial offerings while they were
still ablaze. At first he laughed a long time, and
obviously did it from the heart. Then he began
somewhat after this fashion: “Since that accursed
Theagenes terminated his pestilential remarks with
the tears of Heraclitus, I, on the contrary, shall
begin with the laughter of Democritus.” And
again he went on laughing a long time, so that he




<pb n="v.5.p.11"/>

drew most of us into doing likewise.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
Then, changing
countenance, he said, “Pray, what else, gentlemen,
are we to do when we hear utterances so ridiculous,
and see old men all but standing on their heads in
public for the sake of a little despicable notoriety?
That you may know what manner of thing is this
‘holy image’ which is about to be burned up, give
me your ears, for I have observed his character
and kept an eye on his career from the beginning,
and have ascertained various particulars from his
fellow-citizens and people who cannot have helped
knowing him thoroughly.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

“This creation and masterpiece of nature, this
Polyclitan canon,<note n="v.5.p.11.n.1"><p>The proportions of the statue of a naked youth carrying a spear (the Doryphorus), made by Polyclitus, were analysed by the sculptor himself in a book called the Canon, and universally accepted as canonical for the male figure. </p></note> as soon as he came of age, was
taken in adultery in Armenia and got a sound
thrashing, but finally jumped down from the roof
and made his escape, with a radish stopping his
vent. Then he corrupted a handsome boy, and by
paying three thousand drachmas to the boy’s parents,
who were poor, bought himself off from being brought
before the governor of the province of Asia.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
“All this and the like of it I propose to pass over ;
for he was still unshapen clay, and our ‘holy
image’ had not yet been consummated for us.
What he did to his father, however, is very well
worth hearing; but you all know it—you have
heard how he strangled the aged man, unable to
tolerate his living beyond sixty years. Then,
when the affair had been noised abroad, he condemned himself to exile and roamed about, going
to one country after another.



<pb n="v.5.p.13"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
“It was then that he learned the wondrous lore
of the Christians, by associating with their priests
and scribes in Palestine. And—how else could it
be P—in a trice he made them all look like children ;
for he was prophet, cult-leader, head of the synagogue, and everything, all by himself. He interpreted and explained some of their books and even
composed many, and they revered him as a god, made
use of him as a lawgiver, and set him down as a
protector, next after that other, to be sure, whom<note n="v.5.p.13.n.1"><p>The sense of the unemended text here is ‘ protector ; that great man, to be sure, they still worship,” etc. </p></note>
they still worship, the man who was crucified in
Palestine because he introduced this new cult into
the world.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
“Then at length Proteus was apprehended for this
and thrown into prison, which itself gave him no
little reputation as an asset for his future career and
the charlatanism and notoriety-seeking that he was
enamoured of. Well, when he had been imprisoned,
the Christians, regarding the incident as a calamity,
left nothing undone in the effort to rescue him.
Then, as this was impossible, every other form of
attention was shown him, not in any casual way but
with assiduity ; and from the very break of day aged
widows and orphan children could be seen waiting
near the prison, while their officials even slept inside
with him after bribing the guards. Then elaborate
meals were brought in, and sacred books of theirs
were read aloud, and excellent Peregrinus—for he
still went by that name—was called by them ‘ the
new Socrates.’


<pb n="v.5.p.15"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
“Indeed, people came even from the cities in Asia,
sent by the Christians at their common expense,
to succour and defend and encourage the hero. They
show incredible speed whenever any such public
action is taken; for in no time they lavish their all.
So it was then in the case of Peregrinus; much money
came to him from them by reason of his imprisonment, and he procured not a little revenue from it.
</p>

<p>
The poor wretches have convinced themselves,
first and foremost, that they are going to be immortal
and live for all time, in consequence of which they
despise death and even willingly give themselves
into custody, most of them. Furthermore, their
first lawgiver<note n="v.5.p.15.n.1"><p>From the wording of this sentence the allusion is so obviously to Christ himself that one is at a loss to understand why Paul, let alone Moses, should have been suggested. For the doctrine of brotherly love cf. Matt. 23, 8: πάντες δὲ ὑμεῖς ἀδελφοί ἐστε. </p></note> persuaded them that they are all
brothers of one another after they have transgressed
once for all by denying the Greek gods and by
worshipping that crucified sophist himself and living
under his laws. Therefore they despise all things
indiscriminately and consider them common property,
receiving such doctrines traditionally without any
definite evidence. So if any charlatan and trickster,
able to profit by occasions, comes among them, he
quickly acquires sudden wealth by imposing upon
simple folk.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
“However, Peregrinus was freed by the then
governor of Syria, a man who was fond of philosophy.<note n="v.5.p.15.n.2"><p>The Roman governor of the province of Syria is meant. Identification is impossible because the date of the imprisonment of Peregrinus cannot be fixed. </p></note>. Aware of his recklessness and that he



<pb n="v.5.p.17"/>

would gladly die in order that he might leave behind
him a reputation for it, he freed him, not considering him worthy even of the usual chastisement.<note n="v.5.p.17.n.1"><p>“The usual chastisement” (Allinson’s phrase) was scourging. </p></note>
Upon returning to his home, he found that the matter
of his father’s murder was still at fever heat and that
there were many who were for pressing the charge
against him. Most of his possessions had been
carried off during his absence, and only his farms
remained, amounting to fifteen talents; for the
entire property which the old man left had been
worth perhaps thirty talents, not five thousand as
that utterly ridiculous Theagenes asserted. Even the
entire city of Parium,<note n="v.5.p.17.n.2"><p>A small (but not really so contemptible) Greek town on the Hellespont, site of a Roman colony since Augustus. See Sir W. Leaf, Strabo on the Troad, pp. 80-85. </p></note> taking along with it the five
that are its neighbours, would not fetch that much,
including the men, the cattle, and all the rest of
their belongings.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
“However, the charge and complaint was still
aglow, and it was probable that before long somebody
would appear against him; above all, the people
themselves were enraged, mourning over a good old
man (as he was called by those who had seen him) so
impiously slain. But observe what a plan our clever
Proteus discovered to cope with all this, and how he
escaped the danger. Coming before the assembly
of the Parians—he wore his hair long by now, dressed
in a dirty mantle, had a wallet slung at his side, the
staff was in his hand, and in general he was very
histrionic in his get-up—manifesting himself to
them in this guise, he said that he relinquished to the



<pb n="v.5.p.19"/>

state all the property which had been left him by his
father of blessed memory. When the people, poor
folk agape for largesses,<note n="v.5.p.19.n.1"><p>The phrase is F. D. Allinson’s. </p></note> heard that, they lifted their
voices forthwith: ‘The one and only philosopher!
The one and only patriot! The one and only rival
of Diogenes and Crates!’ His enemies were
muzzled, and anyone who tried to mention the murder
was at once pelted with stones.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
“He left home, then, for the second time, to roam
about, possessing an ample source of funds in the
Christians, through whose ministrations he lived in
unalloyed prosperity. For a time he battened himself thus; but then, after he had transgressed in some
way even against them—he was seen, I think,
eating some of the food that is forbidden them<note n="v.5.p.19.n.2"><p>In Acts 15, 29 the apostles and the elder brethren prescribe abstaining “from sacrifices offered to idols, and from blood, and from things strangled’? (eidoAd8ura kat alya Kat amucrd). Probably what Lucian has in mind is pagan sacrificial meats. This may be just a guess, from the way he puts it; but if so, it is highly plausible on account of the </p></note>—
they no longer accepted him, and so, being at a loss,
he thought he must sing a palinode and demand his
possessions back from his city. Submitting a petition, he expected to recover them by order of the
Emperor. Then, as the city sent representatives to
oppose the claim, he achieved nothing, but was
directed to abide by what he had once for all determined, under no compulsion from anyone.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
“Thereafter he went away a third time, to Egypt,
to visit Agathobulus,<note n="v.5.p.19.n.3"><p>In Demonax, 3, Lucian alludes to Agathobulus as one of those with whom Demonax had studied. The teacher of Peregrinus was therefore reputable as well as famous. </p></note> where he took that wonderful
course of training in asceticism, shaving one half of
his head, daubing his face with mud, and demonstrating what they call‘ indifference’ by erecting his
notorious indifference of the Cynics towards what they ate.
Peregrinus may have signalised his relapse to Cynicism by
sampling a “dinner of Hecate” at the cross-roads.





<pb n="v.5.p.21"/>

yard amid a thronging mob of bystanders,<note n="v.5.p.21.n.1"><p>The allusion is to that variety of “indifferent” action (.e. neither good nor bad) ascribed to Diogenes himself by Dio Chrysostom VI, 16-20 (pp. 203-204 z). </p></note> besides
giving and taking blows on the back-sides with a
stalk of fennel, and playing the mountebank even
more audaciously in many other ways.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="18"><p>
“From there, thus equipped, he set sail for Italy
and immediately after disembarking he fell to abusing
everyone, and in particular the Emperor,<note n="v.5.p.21.n.2"><p>Antoninus Pius. </p></note> knowing
him to be mild and gentle, so that he was safe in
making bold. The Emperor, as one would expect,
cared little for his libels and did not think fit to punish
for mere words a man who only used philosophy as a
cloak, and above all, a man who had made a profession of abusiveness. But in our friend’s case, even
from this his reputation grew, among simple folk anyhow, and he was a cynosure for his recklessness, until
finally the city prefect, a wise man, packed him off for
immoderate indulgence in the thing, saying that the
city had no need of any such philosopher. However,
this too made for his renown, and he was on everybody’s lips as the philosopher who had been banished
for his frankness and excessive freedom, so that in this
respect he approached Musonius, Dio, Epictetus, and
anyone else who has been in a similar predicament.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
“Coming at last to Greece under these circumstances, at one moment he abused the Eleans, at
another he counselled the Greeks to take up arms
against the Romans,<note n="v.5.p.21.n.3"><p>The life of Antoninus Pius (Script. Hist. Aug.), § 5, notes suppression of a rebellion in Achaia, </p></note> and at another he libelled a man
outstanding in literary attainments and position
because he had been a benefactor to Greece in many




<pb n="v.5.p.23"/>

ways, and particularly because he had brought water
to Olympia and prevented the visitors to the festival
from dying of thirst, maintaining that he was making
the Greeks effeminate, for the spectators of the
Olympic games ought to endure their thirst—yes,
by Heaven, and even to lose their lives, no doubt,
many of them, through the frequent distempers
which formerly ran riot in the vast crowd on account
of the dryness of the place!<note n="v.5.p.23.n.1"><p>The man was the famous Herodes Atticus. For the aqueduct built by him at Olympia see Frazer’s Pausanias, Vol. IV, pp. 72 ff. Philostratus (Vit. Soph. II, 1, 33) records that Herodes was often berated by Proteus, to whom on one occasion he hinted that it might at least be done in Greek. </p></note> And he said this while
he drank that same water!
When they almost killed him with stones, mobbing
him with one accord, he managed to escape death at
the moment by fleeing to Zeus for sanctuary (stout
fellow !),

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
and afterwards, at the next Olympiad, he
gave the Greeks a speech which he had composed
during the four years that had intervened, praising
the man who had brought in the water and defending
himself for running away at that time.
“At last he was disregarded by all and no longer
so admired; for all his stuff was stale and he could
not turn out any further novelty with which to
surprise those who came in his way and make them
marvel and stare at him—a thing for which he had a
fierce craving from the first. So he devised this
ultimate venture of the pyre, and spread a report
among the Greeks immediately after the last
Olympic games that he would burn himself up at the
next festival.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="21"><p>

And now, they say, he is playing the
mountebank over that very thing, digging a pit,


<pb n="v.5.p.25"/>

collecting logs, and promising really awesome fortitude.<note n="v.5.p.25.n.1"><p>Thanks to Paul Graindor, the date of the Olympiads mentioned in connection with Peregrinus can now be determined. He has deduced from the apparent ages of the children represented in the exedra erected ty Herodes on the comlotion of his aqueduct that this took place in a.d. 153 (Hérode Atticus et Sa Famille, pp. 87-88). His deduction finds support in the text of Lucian as soon as we recognise that Lucian is talking about four different Olympiads, not three. The first is that on which Peregrinus criticised the aqueduct, which will be the year of its completion, a.d. 153. At the nezt (τὴν ἑξῆς, A.D. 157) he withdrew his criticism. The Olympiad just after which he announced his intention of cremating himself need not and cannot be identical with the one of a.D. 157; it is called by the speaker the last, or previous (τὴν ἐμπρόσθεν), and the text clearly implies a lapse of time. It must therefore be the one of a.d. 161. Then comes the fourth, on which the cremation took place, dated by Eusebius in a.d. 165. </p></note>
</p>

<p>
“What he should have done, I think, was first and
foremost to await death and not to cut and run from
life ; but if he had determined to be off at all costs, not
to use fire or any of these devices out of tragedy, but
to choose for his departure some other form of death
out of the myriads that there are. If, however, he is
partial to fire as something connected with Heracles,.
why in the world did he not quietly select a wellwooded mountain and cremate himself upon it in
solitude, taking along only one person such as
Theagenes here for his Philoctetes?<note n="v.5.p.25.n.2"><p>Philoctetes had helped Heracles to cremate himself on Mt. Oeta by kindling the pyre for him. </p></note> On the contrary, it is in Olympia, at the height of the festival,
all but in the theatre, that he plans to roast himself—
not undeservedly, by Heracles, if it is right for
parricides and for atheists to suffer for their hardinesses.<note n="v.5.p.25.n.3"><p>As the cremation actually took place at Harpina, two miles away from Olympia, and on the day after the festival closed, it may be that religious scruples (cf. § 26) caused Peregrinus to modify an original plan which involved its taking place at Olympia itself while the festival was in progress. </p></note> And from that point of view he seems to be
getting about it very late in the day; he ought long
ago to have been flung into the bull of Phalaris<note n="v.5.p.25.n.4"><p>See Phalaris I, 11-12 (Vol. I, pp. 17 ff.). </p></note> to
pay the fitting penalty instead of opening his mouth
to the flames once for all and expiring in a trice. For






<pb n="v.5.p.27"/>

people tell me that no other form of death is quicker
than that by fire; you have only to open your mouth,
and die forthwith.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
“The spectacle is being planned, I suppose, as
Something awe-inspiring—a fellow getting burnt up
in a holy place where it is impious even to bury the
others who die. But you have heard, no doubt, that
long ago a man who wished to become famous burned
the temple of Ephesian Artemis, not being able to
attain that end in any other way.<note n="v.5.p.27.n.1"><p>Herostratus, in356 3.0, The Ephesians sought to defeat his object by forbidding anyone for all time to mention his name (Valerius Maximus, VIII, 14, 5). The prohibition, which very likely was accompanied by a curse, was far from ineffective, for nearly all ancient authors who mention the story, including Cicero and Plutarch, omit the name just as Lucian does, </p></note> He himself has
something similar in mind, so great is the craving for
fame that has penetrated him to the core.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="23"><p>

“He alleges, however, that he is doing it for the
sake of his fellow men, that he may teach them to
despise death and endure what is fearsome. For my
part, I should like to ask, not him but you, whether
you would wish malefactors to become his disciples
in this fortitude of his, and to despise death and
burning and similar terrors. No, you would not, I
am very sure. How, then, is Proteus to draw distinctions in this matter, and to benefit the good
without making the bad more adventurous and
daring?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

“Nevertheless, suppose it possible that only those
will present themselves at this affair who will see it
to their advantage. Once more I shall question you:
would you desire your children to become imitators of
such a man? You will not say so. But why did I
ask that question, when even of his disciples them-



<pb n="v.5.p.29"/>

selves not one would imitate him? In fact, the thing
for which one might blame Theagenes most of all is
that although he copies the man in everything else,
he does not follow his teacher and take the road
with him, now that he is off, as he says, to join
Heracles; why, he has the opportunity to attain
absolute felicity instanter by plunging headlong into
the fire with him!</p>

<p>
“Emulation is not a matter of wallet, staff, and
mantle; all this is safe and easy and within anyone’s
power. One should emulate the consummation and
culmination, build a pyre of fig-wood logs as green as
can be, and stifle one’s selfin the smoke of them. Fire
itself belongs not only to Heracles and Asclepius,
but to doers of sacrilege and murder, who can be
seen enduring it by judicial sentence. Therefore it
is better to employ smoke, which would be peculiar
and belong only to you and your like.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
“Besides, if Heracles really did venture any such
act, he did it because he was ailing, because the blood
of the Centaur, as the tragedies tell us, was preying
upon him; but for what reason does this man throw
himself bodily into the fire? Oh, yes! to demonstrate his fortitude, like the Brahmans, for Theagenes
thought fit to compare him with them, just as if
there could not be fools and notoriety-seekers even
among the Indians. Well, then, let him at least
imitate them. They do not leap into the fire (so
Onesicritus says, Alexander’s navigator, who saw
Calanus burning), but when they have built their
pyre, they stand close beside it motionless and en-


<pb n="v.5.p.31"/>

dure being toasted; then, mounting upon it, they
cremate themselves decorously, without the slightest
alteration of the position in which they are lying.</p>

<p>
“In this man’s case, what great thing will it be if
he tumbles in and dies in the sudden grip of the fire?
It is not beyond expectation that he will jump out
half consumed, unless, as they say, he is going to see
to it that the pyre is deep down in a pit.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
There are
people who say that he has even changed his mind,
and is telling certain dreams, to the effect that
Zeus does not permit pollution of a holy place.<note n="v.5.p.31.n.1"><p>See above, p. 25, and n. 3. </p></note> But
let him be assured on that score; I would take my
oath to it that no one of the gods would be angry if
Peregrinus should die a rogue’s death. Moreover, it
is not easy for him to withdraw now; for his Cynic
associates are urging him on and pushing him into
the fire and inflaming his resolution; they will not
let him shirk it. If he should pull a couple of them
into the fire along with him when he jumps in, that
would be the only nice thing about his performance.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="27"><p>

“Thave heard that he no longer deigns to be called
Proteus but has changed his name to Phoenix,
because the phoenix, the Indian bird, is said to mount
a pyre when it is very far advanced in age. Indeed,
he even manufactures myths and repeats certain
oracles, ancient, of course, to the purport that he
is to become a guardian spirit of the night; it is
plain, too, that he already covets altars and expects
to be imaged in gold.


<pb n="v.5.p.33"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="28"><p>
“By Zeus, it would be nothing unnatural if, among
all the dolts that there are, some should be found to
assert that they were relieved of quartan fevers by
him, and that in the dark they had encountered the
guardian spirit of the night! Then too these accursed
disciples of his will make an oracular shrine, I suppose,
with a holy of holies, at the site of the pyre, because
the famous Proteus, son of Zeus, the progenitor of
his name, was given to soothsaying.<note n="v.5.p.33.n.1"><p>Athenagoras reports that Parium, where Peregrinus was born, cherished a statue of him from which oracles were derived (Leg. de Christ., 26). </p></note> I pledge m
word, too, that priests of his will be appointed, wit
whips or branding-irons or some such flummy-diddle,
or even that a nocturnal mystery will be got up in his
honour, including a torch festival at the site of the
pye.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="29"><p>
"Theagenes, as I have been told by one of my
friends, recently said that the Sibyl had made a
prediction about all this; in fact, he quoted the verses from memory :

<quote>
<l>But when the time shall come that Proteus, noblest of Cynics,</l>
<l>Kindleth fire in the precinct of Zeus, our Lord of the Thunder,</l>
<l>Leapeth into the flame, and cometh to lofty Olympus,</l>
<l>Then do I bid all alike who eat the fruit of the ploughland </l>
<l>Honour to pay unto him that walketh abroad in the night-time,</l>
<l>Greatest of spirits, thronéd with Heracles and Hephaestus.</l>
</quote>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="30"><p>
“That is what Theagenes alleges he heard from
the Sibyl. But I will quote him one of the oracles of



<pb n="v.5.p.35"/>

Bacis dealing with these matters.<note n="v.5.p.35.n.1"><p>Lucian gives the Cynic a Roland for his Oliver. Bacis was a title rather than a name, and in early Greece prophets who bore it were little less numerous than the Sibyls. Naturally it was a convenient tag for a spurious oracle, whether composed with fraudulent intention or, as often in Aristophanes, for fun. </p></note> Bacis expresses
himself as follows, with a very excellent moral :

<cit>
<quote>
<l>Nay, when the time shall come that a Cynic with names that are many</l>
<l>Leaps into roaring flame, soul-stirred by a passion for glory,</l>
<l>Then it is meet that the others, the jackals that follow his footsteps,</l>
<l>Mimic the latter end of the wolf that has taken departure.</l>
<l>But if a dastard among them shall shun the might of Hephaestus,</l>
<l>Let him be pelted with stones forthwith by all the Achaeans,</l>
<l>Learning, the frigid fool, to abjure all fiery speeches,</l>
<l>He that has laden his wallet with gold by the taking of usance ;</l>
<l>Thrice five talents he owns in the lovely city of Patras.</l>
</quote>
<bibl>Iliad, XIV, 1.</bibl>
</cit>
What do you think, gentlemen? That Bacis is a worse soothsayer than the Sibyl? It is high time,
then, for these wondrous followers of Proteus to
look about for a place in which to aerify themselves—for that is the name they give to cremation.”<note n="v.5.p.35.n.2"><p>Below (§ 33), Proteus speaks of being “ commingled with the ether.” </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="31"><p>
When he had said these words, all the bystanders
shouted: “Let them be burned right now; they
deserve the flames!” And the man got down again
laughing; but “Nestor failed not to mark the
din: 3 I mean Theagenes. When he heard the
shouting he came at once, took the platform, and fell to




<pb n="v.5.p.37"/>

ranting and telling countless malicious tales about the
man who had just got down—I do not know what
that excellent gentleman’s name was. For my part,
I left him splitting his lungs and went off to see the
athletes, as the Hellanodicae were said to be already
in the Plethrium.<note n="v.5.p.37.n.1"><p>According to Pausanias (VI, 23, 2), a place in the Gymnasium of Elis where the officials of the games (Hellanodicae) determined by lot the matching of the athletes. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="32"><p>

Well, there you have what happened at Elis; and
when we reached Olympia, the rear chamber<note n="v.5.p.37.n.2"><p>Of the temple of Zeus; as it was open at the end, it formed a sort of portico. Cf. Runaways, 7; Herodotus, 1. </p></note> was
full of people criticising Proteus of praising his
purpose, so that most of them even came to blows.
Finally, Proteus himself appeared, escorted by a
countless multitude, after the contest of the heralds,
and had somewhat to say about himself, telling of the
life that he had led and the risks that he had run,
and of all the troubles that he had endured for
philosophy’s sake. His speech was protracted, though
I heard but little on account of the number of
bystanders. Afterwards, fearing to be crushed in
such a throng, because I saw this happening to
many, I went away, bidding a long farewell to the
sophist enamoured of death who was pronouncing his
own funeral oration before his demise.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="33"><p>

This much, however, I overheard; he said that he
wanted to put a tip of gold on a golden bow;<note n="v.5.p.37.n.3"><p>Pandarus the Trojan (Iliad, IV, 111) put a tip of gold on the bow he had fashioned of horn. The golden bow (βιῷ) of Peregrinus is his life (βίῳ). </p></note> for
one who had lived as Heracles should die like Heracles
and be commingled with the ether. “And I wish,”
said he, “to benefit mankind by showing them the





<pb n="v.5.p.39"/>

way in which one should despise death; wherefore
all men ought to play Philoctetes to me.” The
more witless among the people began to shed tears
and call out: “Preserve your life for the Greeks!”
but the more virile part bawled “Carry out your
purpose!” by which the old man was immoderately
upset, because he hoped that all would cling to him
and not give him over to the fire, but retain him in
life—against his will, naturally! That “Carry out
your purpose” assailing him quite unexpectedly
caused him to turn still paler, although his colour was
already deathly, and even to tremble slightly, so
that he brought his speech to an end.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="34"><p>
You can imagine, I expect, how I laughed; for it
was not fitting to pity a man so desperately in love
with glory beyond all others who are driven by the
same Fury. Anyhow, he was being escorted by
crowds and getting his fill of glory as he gazed at the
number of his admirers, not knowing, poor wretch,
that men on their way to the cross or in the grip of the
executioner have many more at their heels.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="35"><p>
Soon the Olympic games were ended, the most
splendid Olympics that I have seen, though it was
then the fourth time that I had been a spectator.
As it was not easy to secure a carriage, since many were
leaving at the same time, I lingered on against my
will, and Peregrinus kept making postponements, but
at last had announced a night on which he would
stage his cremation; so, as one of my friends had
invited me to go along, I arose at midnight and took
the road to Harpina, where the pyre was. This is
quite twenty furlongs from Olympia as one goes past


<pb n="v.5.p.41"/>

the hippodrome towards the east. As soon as we
arrived, we found a pyre built in a pit about six feet
deep. It was composed mostly of torchwood, and
the interstices filled with brush, that it might take
fire quickly.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="36"><p>
When the moon was rising—for she
too had to witness this glorious deed—he came
forward, dressed in his usual fashion, and with him
the leaders of the Cynics; in particular, the gentleman from Patras, with a torch—no bad understudy.
Proteus too was bearing a torch. Men, approaching
from this side and that, kindled the fire into a very
great flame, since it came from torchwood and brush.
Peregrinus—and give me your close attention now !—
laying aside the wallet, the cloak, and that notable
Heracles-club, stood there in a shirt that was downright
filthy. Then he requested incense to throw on the
fire; when someone had proffered it, he threw it on,
and gazing towards the south—even the south, too,
had to do with the show<note n="v.5.p.41.n.1"><p>C. R. Lanman (in Allinson, Lucian: Selected Writings, p. 200) thus explains the mystic allusion to the South: “It is to be noted that Yama—the first man who died and found out for all men the pathway ‘to a distant home, a dwellingplace secure ’—conducts souls to the ‘ Blessed Fathers’ in the south, the region of the Manes. See Atharvaveda 18, 3, 13; 4, 40, 2. So the monthly offerings (¢raddhas) to the Manes are performed in such a way that they end in the south (Manu’s Laws, 3,214). The invoking of the daipoves is in accord with Hindu thought; eg. the liturge in Hiranyakegin’s Grhya-sutra, 2, 10° (see F. Max Müller’s Sacred Books of the Kast, XXX, p. 226), after inviting the Manes, sprinkles water towards the south, saying: ‘ Divine waters, send us Agni.’ The νεκράγγελοι and νερτεροδρόμοι in 41 may be an echo of Yama’s messengers that has reached Lucian. See Atharvaveda 18, 2, 27 and H. C. Warren’s Buddhism in Translations, pp. 225-262.” </p></note>—he said: “Spirits of my
mother and my father, receive me with favour.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="37"><p>
With that he leaped into the fire; he was not visible,
however, but was encompassed by the flames, which
had risen to a great height.
Once more I see you laughing, Cronius, my



<pb n="v.5.p.43"/>

urbane friend, at the dénouement of the play. For
my own part, when he called upon the guardian
spirits of his mother, I did not criticise him very
strongly, but when he invoked those of his father as
well, I recalled the tales that had been told about his
murder, and I could not control my laughter. The
Cynics stood about the pyre, not weeping, to be sure,
but silently evincing a certain. amount of grief as
they gazed into the fire, until my gorge rose at them,
and I said: “Let us go away, you simpletons. It is
not an agreeable spectacle to look at an old man who
has been roasted, getting our nostrils filled with a
villainous reek. Or are you waiting for a painter to
come and picture you as the companions of Socrates
in prison are portrayed beside him?” They were
indignant and reviled me, and several even took to
their sticks. Then, when I threatened to gather up
a few of them and throw them into the fire, so that
they might follow their master, they checked themselves and kept the peace.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="38"><p>

As I returned, I was thinking busily, my friend,
reflecting what a strange thing love of glory is;
how this passion alone is unescapable even by those
who are considered wholly admirable, let alone that
man who in other respects had led a life that was
insane and reckless, and not undeserving of the fire.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="39"><p>
Then I encountered many people coming out to see
the show themselves, for they expected to find him
still alive. You see, on the day before it had been
given out that he would greet the rising sun, as, in fact,
they say the Brahmans do, before mounting the pyre.

<pb n="v.5.p.45"/>

Well, I turned back most of them by saying the
deed had been done already, those to whom it was
not in itself highly desirable to see the actual spot,
anyhow, and gather up some relic of the fire.
In that business, I assure you, my friend, I had no
end of trouble, telling the story to all while they
asked questions and sought exact information.
Whenever I noticed a man of taste, I would tell him
the facts without embellishment, as I have to you;
but for the benefit of the dullards, agog to listen,
I would thicken the plot a bit on my own account,
saying that when the pyre was kindled and Proteus
flung himself bodily in, a great earthquake first took
place, accompanied by a bellowing of the ground, and
then a vulture, flying up out of the midst of the flames,
went off to Heaven,<note n="v.5.p.45.n.1"><p>At the death of Plato and of Augustus it was an eagle; in the case of Polycarp, a dove. </p></note> saying, in human speech, with
a loud voice:

<quote><l>I am through with the earth; to Olympus I fare.</l></quote>

They were wonder-struck and blessed themselves
with a shudder, and asked me whether the vulture
sped eastwards or westwards; I made them whatever
reply occurred to me.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="40"><p>
On my return to the festival, I came upon a greyhaired man whose face, I assure you, inspired confidence in addition to his beard and his general air
of consequence, telling all about Proteus, and how,
since his cremation, he had beheld him in white
raiment a little while ago, and had just now left him
walking about cheerfully in the Portico of the Seven
Voices,<note n="v.5.p.45.n.2"><p>This was a portico on the east side of the Altis which had a sevenfold echo (Pausan., V, 21, 17; Pliny, XXXVI, 100). </p></note> wearing a garland of wild olive. Then on




<pb n="v.5.p.47"/>

top of it all he put the vulture, swearing that he
himself had seen it flying up out of the pyre, when I
myself had just previously let it fly to ridicule fools
and dullards.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="41"><p>
Imagine what is likely to happen in his honour
hereafter, how many bees will not settle on the
place, what cicadas will not sing upon it, what crows
will not fly to it, as they did to the tomb of Hesiod,<note n="v.5.p.47.n.1"><p>See Pausanias (IX, 38, 3): when Orchomenus was afflicted by a plague, the Delphic priestess told its people that their only salvation was to bring there from Naupactus the bones of Hesiod, and that a crow would show them the tomb. Her words were borne out by the event. </p></note>
and so forth! As to statues, I know that many will
be set up right soon by the Eleans themselves and
also by the other Greeks, to whom he said he had
sent letters. The. story is that he despatched
missives to almost all the famous cities—testamentary
dispositions, so to speak, and exhortations and
prescriptions—and he appointed a number of
ambassadors for this purpose from among his comrades, styling them “messengers from the dead”
and “underworld couriers.”<note n="v.5.p.47.n.2"><p>In the letters of Ignatius he recommends to the Church of Smyrna the election of a special messenger, styled “ambassador of God’? (θεοπρεσβευτής : ad Smyrn., 11) or “courier of God’? (θεοδρόμος : ad Polyc., 7), to be sent to Syria. The verbal coincidence is notable (cf. Lightfoot), and seems to indicate a knowledge of these letters, but on the part of Peregrinus, not Lucian. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="42"><p>
So ended that poor wretch Proteus, a man who (to
put it briefly) never fixed his gaze on the verities,
but always did and said everything with a view to
glory and the praise of the multitude, even to the



<pb n="v.5.p.49"/>

extent of leaping into fire, when he was sure not to
enjoy the praise because he could not hear it.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="43"><p>
I shall add one thing more to my story before I
stop, in order that you may be able to have a good
laugh. For of course you have long known that other
tale of mine, as you heard it from me at once, when
on my return from Syria I recounted how I sailed from
the Troad in his company, and about his self-indulgence on the voyage, and the handsome boy
whom he had persuaded to turn Cynic that he too
might have an Alcibiades, and how, when we were
disturbed during the night in mid-Aegean by a
tempest that descended and raised an enormous
sea, this wondrous person who was thought to be
superior to death fell to walling along with the
women!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="44"><p>
Well, a short time before his end, about nine
days, it may be, having eaten more than enough, I
suppose, he was sick during the night and was taken
with a very violent fever. This was told me by
Alexander the physician, who had been called in to
see him. He said that he found him rolling on the
ground, unable to stand the burning, pleading very
passionately for a drink of cold water, but that he
would not give it to him. Moreover, he told him,
he said, that Death, if he absolutely wanted him, had
come to his door spontaneously, so that it would be
well to go along, without asking any favour from the
fire; and Proteus replied: “But that way would not
be so notable, being common to all men.”
aside Levi's interpretation of dyad as meaning lutta d’amore,
but his own defence of it as meaning “‘discrimen” does not
properly reckon with the context. -The archetype had a
peculiar pointed w, frequently confused with a: and , and
these with it.


<pb n="v.5.p.51"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg042.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="45"><p>
That is Alexander’s story. And I myself not many
days previously saw him smeared with ointment in
order that the sharp salve might relieve his vision by
making him shed tears. Do you get the idea?
Aeacus is reluctant to receive people with weak eyes!
It is as if a man about to go up to the cross should
nurse the bruise on his finger. What do you think
Democritus would have done, had he seen this?
Would not he have laughed at the man as roundly
as he deserved? And yet, where could he have got
that much laughter? Well, my friend, you may have
your laugh also, particularly when you hear the rest
of them admiring him.

<pb n="v.5.p.55"/>
</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>
