<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Onetor 2 </title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>There is one proof which I omitted in my former speech, quite as important as any
                    of those which were brought forward, to prove that these men did not pay the
                    marriage-portion to Aphobus. This I shall speak of first, and shall then
                    undertake to refute the falsehoods which the defendant has uttered before you.
                    For the fellow, men of the jury, when he first determined to lay claim to the
                    property of Aphobus, declared that he had paid as the marriage-portion, not a
                    talent, as he now alleges, but eighty minae; and he set up pillars<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">To signify that the property was
                        mortgaged.</note> on the house for two thousand drachmae, and on the land
                    for a talent, wishing to preserve both the one and the other for Aphobus. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>When, however, the trial against him had been decided, and he saw what your
                    attitude was toward those who were too brazen in their wrongdoings, he came to
                    his senses, and concluded that I should appear to be suffering outrageous
                    treatment, if, after being robbed of such large sums, I should be unable to
                    recover anything whatever from Aphobus, who had my property in his possession,
                    but it should become clear that I was prevented by the defendant from recovering
                    anything. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>What, then, does he do? He removes the pillars from the house, and declares that
                    the marriage-portion was a talent only, which sum was guaranteed by a mortgage
                    on the land. Yet, if the inscription on the house was set up by him in fairness
                    and sincerity, it is plain that the one on the land was also. But if he set up a
                    false inscription in the former case with the intent to commit fraud, it is
                    probable that the latter one was false also. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>This matter you should consider, not in the light of the proofs which I have
                    advanced, but from the conduct of Onetor himself. No man on earth compelled him;
                    he took down the pillars himself; and thus by his own act he makes clear that he
                    is a liar. To prove that these statements of mine are true, that he even now
                    declares that the land is mortgaged for a talent, but that he laid claim to two
                    thousand drachmae more on the house, and took the pillars down after the suit
                    was decided, I shall bring forward witnesses who know the facts.Now take the
                        deposition.<quote type="Deposition">
                        <title>Deposition</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>It is plain, then, that Onetor having put up pillars on the house for two
                    thousand drachmae, and on the land for a talent, intended to push his claim as
                    though he had paid eighty minae. Could you have stronger proof that there is not
                    a word of truth in what he now says, than the fact that his present story is
                    different from the one he told at first about the same matters? To me it seems
                    that no stronger proof than this could be found. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>Now note the shamelessness of the man. He had the audacity to say before you that
                    he is not depriving me of what the land is worth beyond a talent, and that, too,
                    when he has himself fixed its value as nothing more. With what end in view,
                    Onetor, did you fix your pillars on the house for the two thousand extra
                    drachmae, when you were demanding eighty minae, if the land was really worth
                    more, instead of securing the two thousand drachmae also by a mortgage on the
                    land? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>Or, when it suits your purpose to save all of the property of Aphobus, is the
                    land to be worth a talent only, and are you to hold the house on a mortgage of
                    two thousand drachmae more; and the marriage-portion being eighty minae, will
                    you claim the right to hold both the land and the house; or again, when this is
                    not to your interest, is all to be different: the house is to be worth a talent,
                    because now it is I that hold it, and what is left of the farm is to be worth
                    not less than two talents, in order that it may seem that I am wronging Aphobus,
                    not myself being robbed? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>Do you see that, while you pretend to have paid the dowry, you are shown not to
                    have paid it in any way whatsoever? For that line of conduct is sincere and free
                    from guile, which remains throughout such as it was at the first, but you are
                    proven to have followed the contrary course, so as to fulfil your service as an
                    underling to my detriment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>It is worth while to consider in the light of these facts what sort of an oath he
                    would have sworn, if an oath had been tendered him. For, when he declared that
                    the dowry was eighty minae, if one had granted that he should recover that sum
                    on condition of his swearing that this statement of his was true, what would he
                    have done? Is it not plain that he would have taken the oath? What can he say to
                    deny that he would have sworn it under those circumstances, when he demands the
                    right to do so now? Well then, his own words prove that he would have perjured
                    himself; for he now claims that he paid, not eighty minae, but a talent. What
                    reason is there why one should believe that he is forswearing himself in one
                    statement rather than in the other? Or what opinion should one rightly hold of a
                    man who thus lightly convicts himself of perjury? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>But perhaps not all of his acts have been of this nature, nor is he proven in
                    every instance to be a trickster. Yet it has been shown that he sought in
                    Aphobus's interest to have the damages fixed at a talent, and himself offered to
                    act as bail for the payment to me of that sum. Yet observe that this is a proof
                    not only that his wife was living with Aphobus and that Onetor was on intimate
                    terms with him, but also that he had not paid the dowry. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>For what man would be so foolish as, first, to pay out so large a sum, then to
                    take as security a single piece of property, the title to which was under
                    dispute, and finally, not satisfied with his previous losses and assuming that
                    the one who had wronged him was now going to act justly, to become his bail for
                    the damages assessed by the court? Nobody would, to my thinking. The assumption
                    is not even rational, that a man unable to recover a talent for himself, should
                    promise to pay that sum to another, and further to give bail for it. No; from
                    these facts alone it is clear that he has never paid the dowry, but as a close
                    friend of Aphobus he took this mortgage in return for my large property, wishing
                    to make his sister jointly with Aphobus an inheritor of my estate. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>Then he seeks now to deceive and beguile you by claiming that he set up the
                    pillars before judgement was given against Aphobus. Aye, Onetor; but not before
                    it was given by you, if what you now say is true. For it is clear that you acted
                    as you did because you were convinced of his guilt. Again, this language of
                    yours is absurd, as though you, men of the jury, did not know that all those who
                    commit frauds of this sort determine what they are going to say, and that no one
                    ever lost a suit through keeping quiet, or admitting that he was in the wrong;
                    but it is, I think, when he has been convicted of making a false statement, that
                    men know what manner of man he is. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>And this is what appears to me to be exactly the plight of Onetor. For tell me,
                    how can it be just, if you set up pillars for eighty minae, that the dowry
                    should be eighty minae; and, if for more, more; and, if for less, less? Or how
                    is it just, when your sister up to this present day has never lived with any
                    other man, or been separated from Aphobus, when you have neither paid the dowry,
                    nor been willing to have recourse to the torture, or to any other fair means of
                    determining the matters at issue, that because you claim to have set up pillars,
                    the farm shall belong to you? I certainly do not see how it can be. It is the
                    truth to which we must look, not to arguments which a man has contrived (as you
                    are doing) in order to seem to speak with some plausibility. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Then—the most outrageous thing of all—suppose you had in reality paid the
                    marriage-portion (which you have not paid), whose fault was it? Was it not
                    yours? For you paid it on the security of my property. Was it not ten full years
                    before he became your brother-in-law that Aphobus took possession of my estate
                    for which judgement has been rendered against him? And was it right for you to
                    recover the whole amount, while I, who had been awarded damages against him, I,
                    an orphan who had been wronged and robbed of a marriage-portion that was
                    genuine, I who with better right than any other man should have been exempted
                    from the risk of having to pay costs,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note
                            <emph>a</emph> on <bibl n="Dem. 27.67">Dem. 27.67</bibl></note> should
                    be forced to suffer thus, and should have recovered nothing whatever, though
                    ready to meet any of your<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The pronoun is in the
                        plural and refers to Onetor and Aphobus.</note> proposals, had you been
                    willing to do anything that justice required?</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
