<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - Ecclesiastes</title>
                
                <editor role="editor">Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc default="false">
                <biblStruct default="false">
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor role="editor">
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl>
                  <!-- <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>-->
             <refState unit="chapter"/><refState unit="verse"/></refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage default="false">
                <language ident="en">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc><!--
            <change>
                <date>14-Oct-99</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>Anne Mahoney</name>
                    <resp>markup</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Initial markup from flat ASCII text</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>5/27/09</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>RS</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>
                    $Log: world.english.xml,v $
			Revision 1.2  2010-06-29 22:00:29  student
			fixing place tags - AD

			Revision 1.1  2009/10/08 19:10:56  rsingh04
			began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

			Revision 1.3  2009/05/27 16:11:31  rsingh04
			added/fixed cvs log keyword
                </item>
            </change>
        --><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change></revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="Ecclesiastes" type="book">
                <head>Ecclesiastes</head>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="1" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        The words of the Preacher, the son of David, king in Jerusalem:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        "Vanity of vanities," says the Preacher; "Vanity of vanities,
all is vanity."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        What does man gain from all his labor in which he
labors under the sun?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        One generation goes, and another generation
comes; but the earth remains forever.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        The sun also rises, and the
sun goes down, and hurries to its place where it rises.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        The wind
goes toward the south, and turns around to the north. It turns around
continually as it goes, and the wind returns again to its courses.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        All the rivers run into the sea, yet the sea is not full. To the
place where the rivers flow, there they flow again.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        All things
are full of weariness beyond uttering. The eye is not satisfied with
seeing, nor the ear filled with hearing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        That which has been is
that which shall be; and that which has been done is that which shall
be done: and there is no new thing under the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Is there a
thing of which it may be said, "Behold, this is new?" It has been long
ago, in the ages which were before us.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        There is no memory of the
former; neither shall there be any memory of the latter that are to
come, among those that shall come after.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        I, the Preacher, was king over Israel in Jerusalem.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        I
applied my heart to seek and to search out by wisdom concerning all
that is done under the sky. It is a heavy burden that God has given to
the sons of men to be afflicted with.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        I have seen all the works
that are done under the sun; and, behold, all is vanity and a chasing
after wind.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        That which is crooked can't be made straight; and
that which is lacking can't be counted.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        I said to myself,
"Behold, I have obtained for myself great wisdom above all who were
before me in Jerusalem. Yes, my heart has had great experience of
wisdom and knowledge."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to
know madness and folly. I perceived that this also was a chasing after
wind.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        For in much wisdom is much grief; and he who increases
knowledge increases sorrow.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="2" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        I said in my heart, "Come now, I will test you with mirth:
therefore enjoy pleasure;" and, behold, this also was vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        I
said of laughter, "It is foolishness;" and of mirth, "What does it
accomplish?"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        I searched in my heart how to cheer my flesh with wine, my
heart yet guiding me with wisdom, and how to lay hold of folly, until I
might see what it was good for the sons of men that they should do
under heaven all the days of their lives.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        I made myself great
works. I built myself houses. I planted myself vineyards.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        I made
myself gardens and parks, and I planted trees in them of all kinds of
fruit.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        I made myself pools of water, to water from it the forest
where trees were reared.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        I bought men-servants and maid-servants,
and had servants born in my house. I also had great possessions of
herds and flocks, above all who were before me in Jerusalem;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        I
also gathered silver and gold for myself, and the treasure of kings and
of the provinces. I got myself men-singers and women-singers, and the
delights of the sons of men -- musical instruments, and that of all
sorts.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        So I was great, and increased more than all who were
before me in Jerusalem. My wisdom also remained with me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Whatever my eyes desired, I didn't keep from them. I didn't withhold my
heart from any joy, for my heart rejoiced because of all my labor, and
this was my portion from all my labor.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Then I looked at all the
works that my hands had worked, and at the labor that I had labored to
do; and, behold, all was vanity and a chasing after wind, and there was
no profit under the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        I turned myself to consider wisdom, madness, and folly: for
what can the king's successor do? Just that which has been done long
ago.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Then I saw that wisdom excels folly, as far as light excels
darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        The wise man's eyes are in his head, and the fool
walks in darkness -- and yet I perceived that one event happens to them
all.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Then said I in my heart, "As it happens to the fool, so
will it happen even to me; and why was I then more wise?" Then said I
in my heart that this also is vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        For of the wise man, even
as of the fool, there is no memory for ever, seeing that in the days to
come all will have been long forgotten. Indeed, the wise man must die
just like the fool!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        So I hated life, because the work that is worked under the
sun was grievous to me; for all is vanity and a chasing after wind.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        I hated all my labor in which I labored under the sun, seeing
that I must leave it to the man who comes after me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Who knows
whether he will be a wise man or a fool? Yet he will have rule over all
of my labor in which I have labored, and in which I have shown myself
wise under the sun. This also is vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Therefore I began to cause my heart to despair concerning all
the labor in which I had labored under the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        For there is a
man whose labor is with wisdom, with knowledge, and with skillfulness;
yet he shall leave it for his portion to a man who has not labored for
it. This also is vanity and a great evil.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        For what has a man of
all his labor, and of the striving of his heart, in which he labors
under the sun?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        For all his days are sorrows, and his travail is
grief; yes, even in the night his heart takes no rest. This also is
vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        There is nothing better for a man than that he should
eat and drink, and make his soul enjoy good in his labor. This also I
saw, that it is from the hand of God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        For who can eat, or who
can have enjoyment, more than I?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        For to the man who pleases him,
God gives wisdom, knowledge, and joy; but to the sinner he gives
travail, to gather and to heap up, that he may give to him who pleases
God. This also is vanity and a chasing after wind.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="3" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        For everything there is a season, and a time for every purpose
under heaven:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        A time to be born,
   And a time to die;
A time to plant,
   And a time to pluck up that which is planted;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        A time to kill,
   And a time to heal;
A time to break down,
   And a time to build up;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        A time to weep,
   And a time to laugh;
A time to mourn,
   And a time to dance;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        A time to cast away stones,
   And a time to gather stones together;
A time to embrace,
   And a time to refrain from embracing;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        A time to seek,
   And a time to lose;
A time to keep,
   And a time to cast away;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        A time to tear,
   And a time to sew;
A time to keep silence,
   And a time to speak;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        A time to love,
   And a time to hate;
A time for war,
   And a time for peace.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        What profit has he who works in that in which he labors?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        I have seen the burden which God has given to the sons of men to
be afflicted with.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        He has made everything beautiful in its time.
He has also set eternity in their hearts, yet so that man can't find
out the work that God has done from the beginning even to the end.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        I know that there is nothing better for them than to rejoice,
and to do good as long as they live.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Also that every man should
eat and drink, and enjoy good in all his labor, is the gift of God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        I know that whatever God does, it shall be forever. Nothing can
be added to it, nor anything taken from it; and God has done it, that
men should fear before him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        That which is has been long ago, and
that which is to be has been long ago: and God seeks again that which
is passed away.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Moreover I saw under the sun, in the place of justice, that
wickedness was there; and in the place of righteousness, that
wickedness was there.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        I said in my heart, "God will judge the
righteous and the wicked; for there is a time there for every purpose
and for every work."
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        I said in my heart, "As for the sons of
men, God tests them, so that they may see that they themselves are like
animals.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        For that which happens to the sons of men happens to
animals. Even one thing happens to them. As the one dies, so the other
dies. Yes, they have all one breath; and man has no advantage over the
animals: for all is vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        All go to one place. All are from
the dust, and all turn to dust again.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Who knows the spirit of
man, whether it goes upward, and the spirit of the animal, whether it
goes downward to the earth?"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        Therefore I saw that there is nothing better, than that a man
should rejoice in his works; for that is his portion: for who can bring
him to see what will be after him?
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="4" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Then I returned and saw all the oppressions that are done
under the sun: and, behold, the tears of those who were oppressed, and
they had no comforter; and on the side of their oppressors there was
power; but they had no comforter.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Therefore I praised the dead
who have been long dead more than the living who are yet alive.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Yes, better than them both is him who has not yet been, who has not
seen the evil work that is done under the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        Then I saw all the
labor and achievement that is the envy of a man's neighbor. This also
is vanity and a striving after wind.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        The fool folds his hands
together and ruins himself.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Better is a handful, with quietness, than two handfuls with
labor and chasing after wind.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Then I returned and saw vanity
under the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        There is one who is alone, and he has neither son
nor brother. There is no end to all of his labor, neither are his eyes
satisfied with wealth. For whom then, do I labor, and deprive my soul
of enjoyment? This also is vanity, yes, it is a miserable business.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Two are better than one, because they have a good reward for
their labor.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        For if they fall, the one will lift up his fellow;
but woe to him who is alone when he falls, and doesn't have another to
lift him up.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Again, if two lie together, then they have warmth;
but how can one keep warm alone?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        If a man prevails against one
who is alone, two shall withstand him; and a threefold cord is not
quickly broken.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Better is a poor and wise youth than an old and foolish king
who doesn't know how to receive admonition any more.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        For out of
prison he came forth to be king; yes, even in his kingdom he was born
poor.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        I saw all the living who walk under the sun, that they
were with the youth, the other, who succeeded him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        There was no
end of all the people, even of all them over whom he was -- yet those
who come after shall not rejoice in him. Surely this also is vanity and
a chasing after wind.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="5" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Guard your steps when you go to God's house; for to draw near
to listen is better than to give the sacrifice of fools, for they don't
know that they do evil.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Don't be rash with your mouth, and don't
let your heart be hasty to utter anything before God; for God is in
heaven, and you on earth. Therefore let your words be few.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        For as
a dream comes with a multitude of cares, so a fool's speech with a
multitude of words.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        When you vow a vow to God, don't defer to pay
it; for he has no pleasure in fools. Pay that which you vow.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        It
is better that you should not vow, than that you should vow and not
pay.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Don't allow your mouth to lead you into sin. Don't protest
before the messenger that this was a mistake. Why should God be angry
at your voice, and destroy the work of your hands?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        For in the
multitude of dreams there are vanities, as well as in many words: but
you must fear God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        If you see the oppression of the poor, and the violent taking
away of justice and righteousness in a district, don't marvel at the
matter: for one official is eyed by a higher one; and there are
officials over them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Moreover the profit of the earth is for all.
The king profits from the field.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        He who loves silver shall not be satisfied with silver; nor
he who loves abundance, with increase: this also is vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        When
goods increase, those who eat them are increased; and what advantage is
there to its owner, except to feast on them with his eyes?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        The sleep of a laboring man is sweet, whether he eats little
or much; but the abundance of the rich will not allow him to sleep.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        There is a grievous evil which I have seen under the sun:
wealth kept by its owner to his harm.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        Those riches perish by
misfortune, and if he has fathered a son, there is nothing in his hand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        As he came forth from his mother's womb, naked shall he go again
as he came, and shall take nothing for his labor, which he may carry
away in his hand.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        This also is a grievous evil, that in all
points as he came, so shall he go. And what profit does he have who
labors for the wind?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        All his days he also eats in darkness, he
is frustrated, and has sickness and wrath.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Behold, that which I have seen to be good and proper is for
one to eat and to drink, and to enjoy good in all his labor, in which
he labors under the sun, all the days of his life which God has given
him; for this is his portion.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Every man also to whom God has
given riches and wealth, and has given him power to eat of it, and to
take his portion, and to rejoice in his labor -- this is the gift of
God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        For he shall not often reflect on the days of his life;
because God occupies him with the joy of his heart.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="6" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, and it is
heavy on men:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        a man to whom God gives riches, wealth, and honor,
so that he lacks nothing for his soul of all that he desires, yet God
gives him no power to eat of it, but an alien eats it. This is vanity,
and it is an evil disease.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        If a man fathers a hundred children, and lives many years, so
that the days of his years are many, but his soul is not filled with
good, and moreover he has no burial; I say, that an untimely birth is
better than he:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        for it comes in vanity, and departs in darkness,
and its name is covered with darkness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Moreover it has not seen
the sun nor known it. This has rest rather than the other.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Yes,
though he live a thousand years twice told, and yet fails to enjoy
good, don't all go to one place?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        All the labor of man is for his
mouth, and yet the appetite is not filled.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        For what advantage has
the wise more than the fool? What has the poor man, that knows how to
walk before the living?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Better is the sight of the eyes than the
wandering of the desire. This also is vanity and a chasing after wind.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Whatever has been, its name was given long ago; and it is known
what man is; neither can he contend with him who is mightier than he.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        For there are many words that create vanity. What does that
profit man?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        For who knows what is good for man in life, all the
days of his vain life which he spends like a shadow? For who can tell a
man what will be after him under the sun?
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="7" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        A good name is better than fine perfume; and the day of death
better than the day of one's birth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        It is better to go to the
house of mourning than to go to the house of feasting: for that is the
end of all men, and the living should take this to heart.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Sorrow
is better than laughter; for by the sadness of the face the heart is
made good.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        The heart of the wise is in the house of mourning; but
the heart of fools is in the house of mirth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        It is better to hear
the rebuke of the wise, than for a man to hear the song of fools.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        For as the crackling of thorns under a pot, so is the laughter of the
fool. This also is vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Surely extortion makes the wise man
foolish; and a bribe destroys the understanding.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Better is the
end of a thing than its beginning.

   The patient in spirit is better than the proud in spirit.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Don't be hasty in your spirit to be angry, for anger rests in the bosom
of fools.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Don't say, "Why were the former days better than
these?" For you do not ask wisely about this.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Wisdom is as good as an inheritance. Yes, it is more
excellent for those who see the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        For wisdom is a defense,
even as money is a defense; but the excellency of knowledge is that
wisdom preserves the life of him who has it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        Consider the work of God, for who can make that straight,
which he has made crooked?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        In the day of prosperity be joyful,
and in the day of adversity consider; yes, God has made the one side by
side with the other, to the end that man should not find out anything
after him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        All this have I seen in my days of vanity: there is a
righteous man who perishes in his righteousness, and there is a wicked
man who lives long in his evil-doing.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Don't be overly righteous,
neither make yourself overly wise. Why should you destroy yourself?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Don't be too wicked, neither be foolish. Why should you die
before your time?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        It is good that you should take hold of this.
Yes, also from that don't withdraw your hand; for he who fears God will
come forth from them all.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        Wisdom is a strength to the wise man
more than ten rulers who are in a city.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Surely there is not a
righteous man on earth, who does good and doesn't sin.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="21"/>
                        Also
don't take heed to all words that are spoken, lest you hear your
servant curse you;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="22"/>
                        for often your own heart knows that you
yourself have likewise cursed others.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="23"/>
                        All this have I proved in
wisdom. I said, "I will be wise;" but it was far from me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="24"/>
                        That
which is, is far off and exceedingly deep. Who can find it out?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="25"/>
                        I turned around, and my heart sought to know and to search out, and to
seek wisdom and the scheme of things, and to know that wickedness is
stupidity, and that foolishness is madness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="26"/>
                        I find more bitter than death the woman whose heart is snares
and traps, whose hands are chains. Whoever pleases God shall escape
from her; but the sinner will be ensnared by her.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="27"/>
                        Behold, this have I found, says the Preacher, one to another,
to find out the scheme;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="28"/>
                        which my soul still seeks; but I have
not found: one man among a thousand have I found; but a woman among all
those have I not found.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="29"/>
                        Behold, this only have I found: that God
made man upright; but they search for many schemes.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="8" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Who is like the wise man? And who knows the interpretation of
a thing? A man's wisdom makes his face shine, and the hardness of his
face is changed.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        I say, "Keep the king's command!" because of the
oath to God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Don't be hasty to go out of his presence. Don't
persist in an evil thing, for he does whatever pleases him,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        for
the king's word is supreme. Who can say to him, "What are you doing?"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Whoever keeps the commandment shall not come to harm, and his
wise heart will know the time and procedure.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        For there is a time
and procedure for every purpose, although the misery of man is heavy on
him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        For he doesn't know that which will be; for who can tell him
how it will be?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        There is no man who has power over the spirit to
contain the spirit; neither does he have power over the day of death.
There is no discharge in war; neither shall wickedness deliver those
who practices it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        All this have I seen, and applied my mind to every work that
is done under the sun. There is a time in which one man has power over
another to his hurt.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        So I saw the wicked buried. Indeed they
came also from holiness. They went and were forgotten in the city where
they did this. This also is vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        Because sentence against an
evil work is not executed speedily, therefore the heart of the sons of
men is fully set in them to do evil.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Though a sinner commits
crimes a hundred times, and lives long, yet surely I know that it will
be better with those who fear God, who are reverent before him.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        But it shall not be well with the wicked, neither shall he lengthen
days like a shadow; because he doesn't fear God.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        There is a vanity which is done on the earth, that there are
righteous men to whom it happens according to the work of the wicked.
Again, there are wicked men to whom it happens according to the work of
the righteous. I said that this also is vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Then I commended
mirth, because a man has no better thing under the sun, than to eat,
and to drink, and to be joyful: for that will accompany him in his
labor all the days of his life which God has given him under the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        When I applied my heart to know wisdom, and to see the
business that is done on the earth (for also there is that neither day
nor night sees sleep with his eyes),
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        then I saw all the work of
God, that man can't find out the work that is done under the sun,
because however much a man labors to seek it out, yet he won't find it.
Yes, moreover, though a wise man thinks he can comprehend it, yet he
won't be able to find it.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="9" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        For all this I laid to my heart, even to explore all this:
that the righteous, and the wise, and their works, are in the hand of
God; whether it is love or hatred, man doesn't know it; all is before
them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        All things come alike to all. There is one event to the
righteous and to the wicked; to the good, to the clean, to the unclean,
to him who sacrifices, and to him who doesn't sacrifice. As is the
good, so is the sinner; he who takes an oath, as he who fears an oath.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        This is an evil in all that is done under the sun, that there is
one event to all: yes also, the heart of the sons of men is full of
evil, and madness is in their heart while they live, and after that
they go to the dead.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        For to him who is joined with all the living
there is hope; for a living dog is better than a dead lion.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        For
the living know that they will die, but the dead don't know anything,
neither do they have any more a reward; for the memory of them is
forgotten.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Also their love, their hatred, and their envy has
perished long ago; neither have they any more a portion forever in
anything that is done under the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Go your way -- eat your bread with joy, and drink your wine
with a merry heart; for God has already accepted your works.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Let
your garments be always white, and don't let your head lack oil.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Live joyfully with the wife whom you love all the days of your life of
vanity, which he has given you under the sun, all your days of vanity:
for that is your portion in life, and in your labor in which you labor
under the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Whatever your hand finds to do, do it with your
might; for there is no work, nor device, nor knowledge, nor wisdom, in
Sheol, where you are going.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        I returned, and saw under the sun, that the race is not to
the swift, nor the battle to the strong, neither yet bread to the wise,
nor yet riches to men of understanding, nor yet favor to men of skill;
but time and chance happen to them all.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        For man also doesn't
know his time. As the fish that are taken in an evil net, and as the
birds that are caught in the snare, even so are the sons of men snared
in an evil time, when it falls suddenly on them.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        I have also seen wisdom under the sun in this way, and it
seemed great to me.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        There was a little city, and few men within
it; and a great king came against it, besieged it, and built great
bulwarks against it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        Now a poor wise man was found in it, and he
by his wisdom delivered the city; yet no man remembered that same poor
man.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Then said I, Wisdom is better than strength. Nevertheless
the poor man's wisdom is despised, and his words are not heard.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        The words of the wise heard in quiet are better than the cry of him who
rules among fools.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        Wisdom is better than weapons of war; but one
sinner destroys much good.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="10" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Dead flies cause the oil of the perfumer to send forth an
evil odor; so does a little folly outweigh wisdom and honor.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        A
wise man's heart is at his right hand, but a fool's heart at his left.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        Yes also, when the fool walks by the way, his understanding
fails him, and he says to everyone that he is a fool.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        If the
spirit of the ruler rises up against you, don't leave your place; for
gentleness lays great offenses to rest.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        There is an evil which I have seen under the sun, the sort of
error which proceeds from the ruler.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Folly is set in great
dignity, and the rich sit in a low place.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        I have seen servants
on horses, and princes walking like servants on the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        He
who digs a pit may fall into it; and whoever breaks through a wall may
be bitten by a snake.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Whoever carves out stones may be injured
by them. Whoever splits wood may be endangered thereby.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        If the
ax is blunt, and one doesn't sharpen the edge, then he must use more
strength; but skill brings success.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        If the snake bites before it is charmed, then is there no
profit for the charmer's tongue.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        The words of a wise man's
mouth are gracious; but a fool is swallowed by his own lips.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        The beginning of the words of his mouth is foolishness; and the end of
his talk is mischievous madness.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        A fool also multiplies words.

   Man doesn't know what will be; and that which will be after him, who
can tell him?
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="15"/>
                        The labor of fools wearies every one of them; for
he doesn't know how to go to the city.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="16"/>
                        Woe to you, land, when your king is a child,
   And your princes eat in the morning!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="17"/>
                        Happy are you, land,
      when your king is the son of nobles,
   And your princes eat in due season,
   For strength, and not for drunkenness!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="18"/>
                        By slothfulness the roof sinks in;
   And through idleness of the hands the house leaks.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="19"/>
                        A feast is made for laughter,
   And wine makes the life glad;
   And money is the answer for all things.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="20"/>
                        Don't revile the king, no, not in your thoughts;
   And don't revile the rich in your bedchamber:
   For a bird of the sky may carry your voice,
   And that which has wings may tell the matter.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="11" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Cast your bread on the waters;
   For you shall find it after many days.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Give a portion to seven, yes, even to eight;
   For you don't know what evil will be on the earth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        If the clouds are full of rain, they empty themselves on the
      earth;
   And if a tree falls toward the south, or toward the north,
   In the place where the tree falls, there shall it be.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        He who observes the wind won't sow;
   And he who regards the clouds won't reap.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        As you don't know what is the way of the wind,
   Nor how the bones grow in the womb of her who is with child;
   Even so you don't know the work of God who does all.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        In the morning sow your seed,
   And in the evening don't withhold your hand;
   For you don't know which will prosper, whether this or that,
   Or whether they both will be equally good.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        Truly the light is sweet,
   And a pleasant thing it is for the eyes to see the sun.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Yes, if a man lives many years, let him rejoice in them all;
   But let him remember the days of darkness, for they shall be many.
   All that comes is vanity.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Rejoice, young man, in your youth,
   And let your heart cheer you in the days of your youth,
   And walk in the ways of your heart,
   And in the sight of your eyes;
   But know that for all these things God will bring you into judgment.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        Therefore remove sorrow from your heart,
   And put away evil from your flesh;
   For youth and the dawn of life are vanity.
                    </p>
                </div>
                <div part="N" sample="complete" org="uniform" n="12" type="chapter">
                    <milestone unit="verse" n="1"/>
                    <p>
                        Remember also your Creator in the days of your youth,
   Before the evil days come, and the years draw near,
   When you will say, "I have no pleasure in them;"
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="2"/>
                        Before the sun, the light, the moon, and the stars are darkened,
   And the clouds return after the rain;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="3"/>
                        In the day when the keepers of the house shall tremble,
   And the strong men shall bow themselves,
   And the grinders cease because they are few,
   And those who look out of the windows are darkened,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="4"/>
                        And the doors shall be shut in the street;
   When the sound of the grinding is low,
   And one shall rise up at the voice of a bird,
   And all the daughters of music shall be brought low;
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="5"/>
                        Yes, they shall be afraid of heights,
   And terrors will be in the way;
   And the almond tree shall blossom,
   And the grasshopper shall be a burden,
   And desire shall fail;
   Because man goes to his everlasting home,
   And the mourners go about the streets:
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="6"/>
                        Before the silver cord is severed,
   Or the golden bowl is broken,
   Or the pitcher is broken at the spring,
   Or the wheel broken at the cistern,
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="7"/>
                        And the dust returns to the earth as it was,
   And the spirit returns to God who gave it.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="8"/>
                        Vanity of vanities, says the Preacher;
   All is vanity!
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="9"/>
                        Further, because the Preacher was wise, he still taught the
people knowledge. Yes, he pondered, sought out, and set in order many
proverbs.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="10"/>
                        The Preacher sought to find out acceptable words, and
that which was written blamelessly, words of truth.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="11"/>
                        The words
of the wise are like goads; and like nails well fastened are words from
the masters of assemblies, which are given from one shepherd.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="12"/>
                        Furthermore, my son, be admonished: of making many books there is no
end; and much study is a weariness of the flesh.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="13"/>
                        This is the end of the matter. All has been heard. Fear God,
and keep his commandments; for this is the whole duty of man.
                        <milestone unit="verse" n="14"/>
                        For God will bring every work into judgment, with every hidden thing,
whether it is good, or whether it is evil.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
