<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Plataicus from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg012.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Since we Plataeans know, Athenians, that it is your custom not only zealously to come to
          the rescue of victims of injustice, but also to requite your benefactors with the utmost
          gratitude, we have come as suppliants to beg you not to remain indifferent to our having
          been driven from our homes in time of peace by the Thebans. And since many peoples in the
          past have fled to you for protection and have obtained all they craved, we think it
          beseems you more than others to show solicitude for our city; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for victims of a greater injustice than ourselves, or any who have been plunged into
          calamities so great, you could not find anywhere, nor any people who for a longer time
          have maintained toward your city a more loyal friendship.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Cf. Herodotus vi. 108. Athens and Platea were allied as early as <date when="-0510">510
              B.C.</date></note> Furthermore, we have come here to ask you for assistance of such a
          kind that your granting it will involve you in no danger whatever and yet will cause all
          the world to regard you as the most scrupulous and most just of all the Greeks. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If we did not observe that the Thebans have schemed to win you over, by fair means or
          foul, to their contention that they have done us no wrong, we could have finished our plea
          in a few words. But since we have reached such a state of misfortune that we must
          struggle, not only against them, but also against the ablest of your orators, men whom
          they have hired with our resources to be their advocates<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Athenian venal advocates are meant.</note> we must explain our cause at greater length.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It is difficult indeed not to speak inadequately on the subject of our wrongs. For what
          eloquence could match our misfortunes, or what orator could adequately denounce the wrongs
          the Thebans have done? Nevertheless, we must try to the best of our ability to make their
          transgressions known. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And the chief cause of our indignation is that we are so far from being judged worthy of
          equality with the rest of the Greeks that, although we are at peace<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">This seems to be a reference to the peace of <date when="-0374">374
              B.C.</date>, made between Athens and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName> (see Jebb, <title>Attic Orators</title> ii. p. 177).</note> and
          although treaties exist, we not only have no share in the liberty which all the rest
          enjoy, but that we are not considered worthy of even a moderate condition of servitude.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> We therefore beg of you, citizens of Athens, that you listen to our plea in a friendly
          spirit, reflecting that for us the most preposterous outcome of all would be, if those who
          have always been hostile to your city shall have regained their freedom through your
          efforts, but we, even when we supplicate you, should fail to obtain the same treatment as
          is accorded to your greatest enemies. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> As for the events which have occurred in the past, I see no reason why I should speak of
          them at length. For who does not know that the Thebans have portioned out our land for
          pasturage and have razed our city to the ground? But it is with respect to their argument,
          by which they hope to deceive you, that we shall try to inform you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> At times, you know, they attempt to maintain that they have subjected us to this
          treatment because we were unwilling to be members of their federation.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, to join the Boeotian Confederation, of which
              <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> held the hegemony, and thus to be
            tributary ( <foreign xml:lang="greek">SUNTELEI=N</foreign>) to the Thebans.</note> But I
          ask you to consider, first, if on such grounds it is just to inflict penalties so contrary
          to justice and so cruel; next, if it seems to you consistent with the dignity of the city
          of the Plataeans, without their consent but under compulsion, to accept such dependence
          under the Thebans. For my part, I consider that there exists no people more overbearing
          than those who blot out the cities of each of us and compel us, when we have no use for
          it, to participate in their form of polity. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Besides this, they are clearly inconsistent in their dealings with others and with us.
          For when they were unable to gain our consent, they should have gone no farther than to
          compel us to submit to the hegemony of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>
          as they compelled <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName> and <placeName
            key="perseus,Tanagra">Tanagra</placeName>; for in that case we should not have suffered
          irremediable misfortunes. But as it is, they have made it clear that it was not their
          intention to give us that status; on the contrary, it was our territory they coveted. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I wonder to what precedent in the past they will appeal, and what conceivable
          interpretation of justice they will give, when they admit that they dictate to us in such
          matters. For if it is to our ancestral customs they look, they ought not to be ruling over
          our other cities, but far rather to be paying tribute to the Orchomenians<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="tgn,7011034">Orchomenus</placeName>,
            stronghold of the Minyans in prehistoric times, joined the Boeotian Confederacy after
            the battle of Leuctra, <date when="-0371">371 B.C.</date></note>; for such was the case
          in ancient times. And if they hold that the treaties are valid, which indeed in justice
          they should be, how can they avoid admitting that they are guilty of wrong and are
          violating them? For these treaties direct that our cities, the small as well as the large,
          shall all alike be autonomous. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I imagine that on the subject of the treaties they will not venture to show their
          impudence, but will resort to the argument that we were taking the side of the
          Lacedaemonians in the war and that by destroying us they have benefited the entire
            confederacy.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Evidently a reference to the Second Athenian
            Confederacy, organized in <date when="-0377">377 B.C.</date> and directed against
              <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. cf. p. 147.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In my opinion, however, no complaint and no accusation should have greater validity than
          the oaths and the treaties. Nevertheless, if any people are to suffer because of their
          alliance with the Lacedaemonians, it was not the Plataeans who, of all the Greeks, if
          justice were done, would have been selected; for it was not of our own free will, but
          under compulsion, that we were subservient to the Lacedaemonians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Why, who could believe that we had reached such a degree of folly as to have valued more
          highly a people who reduced our fatherland to slavery than the people who had given us a
          share in their own city?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, the Athenians; see
            Introduction.</note> No indeed, but it was difficult for us to attempt a revolt when we
          had so small a city ourselves and the Lacedaemonians possessed power so great, and when
          besides a Spartan governor occupied it with a garrison, and also a large army was
          stationed at <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName>,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.4.13">Xen. Hell. 5.4.13-22</bibl>. Cleombrotus, king
            of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, in the beginning of <date
              when="-0378">378 B.C.</date>, occupied <placeName key="perseus,Plataea"
              >Plataea</placeName> and <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName>. Sphodrias
            was the governor or harmost.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>of such strength that we should have been destroyed by it not only more quickly than by
          the Thebans, but also with greater right. For it was not fitting that the Thebans in time
          of peace should harbor a grudge against us for what happened at that time, whereas the
          Lacedaemonians, if they had been betrayed by us during the war, with good reason would
          have punished us most severely. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And I think that you are not unaware that many other Greeks, although with their bodies
          they were compelled to follow the Lacedaemonians, yet in sympathy they were on your side.
          What conclusion must we suppose that these others will reach, if they hear that the
          Thebans have persuaded the Athenian people that none ought to be spared who have been
          subject to the Lacedaemonians? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it will be clearly evident that the Thebans' argument has no other meaning; since it
          is no accusation against our city in particular that has led them to destroy it but, on
          the contrary, they will be able to bring that same charge also against those others. These
          are matters which demand your deliberation and concern, lest the overbearing ways of the
          Thebans shall reconcile those who formerly hated the rule of the Lacedaemonians and cause
          them to believe that the alliance with them is their own salvation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Remember also that you undertook your most recent war,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
              ><date from="-0378" to="-0374">378-374 B.C.</date></note> not to secure the
          freedom of either yourselves or your allies (for you all enjoyed that already), but in
          behalf of those who were being deprived of their autonomy in violation of the oaths and
          covenants. But surely it would be the most outrageous thing in the world, if you are going
          to permit these cities, which you thought ought not to be in servitude to the
          Lacedaemonians, now to be destroyed by the Thebans—men who are so far from emulating your
          clemency that it would have been better for us to suffer at the hands of this city that
          fate which is regarded as the most dreadful of all misfortunes, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>to be taken prisoners of war, than to have got them as neighbors; for those whose cities
          were taken by you by storm were straightway freed of a Spartan governor and of slavery,
          and now they have share in a Council and in freedom, whereas, of those who live anywhere
          near the Thebans, some are no less slaves than those who have been bought with money, and
          as for the rest, the Thebans will not stop until they have brought them to the condition
          in which we now are. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>They accuse the Lacedaemonians because they occupied the Cadmea and established garrisons
          in their cities, yet they themselves, not sending garrisons, but razing the walls of some
          and entirely destroying others, think they have committed no atrocity; nay, they have come
          to such a pitch of shamelessness that while they demand that all their allies should be
          guardians of the safety of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, yet they
          arrogate to themselves the right to impose slavery upon everybody else. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet what man would not detest the greedy spirit of these Thebans, who seek to rule
          the weaker, but think they must be on terms of equality with the stronger and who begrudge
          your city the territory ceded by the Oropians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Oropus, a
            town on the frontier between <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName> and
              <placeName key="tgn,7002683">Boeotia</placeName>, was long a bone of contention. In
              <date when="-0412">412 B.C.</date> it was treacherously taken by <placeName
              key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName> (Thucydides viii. 60); at some time after
              <date when="-0402">402 B.C.</date> it was under Athenian protection; in <date
              when="-0366">366 B.C.</date> Oropus was again seized by <placeName
              key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, but in <date when="-0338">338 B.C.</date>
            Philip gave the town to Athens.</note> yet themselves forcibly seize and portion out
          territory not their own? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And not content with their other base misrepresentations, they now say that they pursued
          this course for the common good of the allies. And yet what they ought to have done,
          inasmuch as there is an Hellenic Council<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Athens' Second
            Confederacy, organized in <date when="-0377">377 B.C.</date> For this Council cf. § 18
            above.</note> here and your city is more competent than <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
            >Thebes</placeName> to advise prudent measures, is, not to be here now to defend the
          acts they have already committed, but to have come to you for consultation before they
          took any such action. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But as it is, having now pillaged our possessions, acting alone, they have come here to
          give a share of their disrepute to all their allies. And that disrepute, if you are wise,
          you will shun, since it is far more honorable to compel them to emulate your
          scrupulousness than that you allow yourselves to be persuaded to share in the lawlessness
          of these people, whose principles are wholly alien to those of the rest of mankind. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I presume that it is clear to all that it is incumbent upon the wise, in time of war
          to strive in every way to get the better of the enemy, but when peace is made, to regard
          nothing as of greater importance than their oaths and their covenants. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The Thebans, however, in the former circumstances, in all their embassies would plead the
          cause of "freedom" and "independence"; but now that they believe they have secured license
          for themselves, disregarding everything else, they have the effrontery to speak in defense
          of their private gain and of their own acts of violence, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and they assert that it is to the advantage of their allies that the Thebans should have
          our country—fools that they are, not to know that no advantage ever accrues to those who
          unjustly seek greedy gain; on the contrary, many a people that have unjustly coveted the
          territory of others have with justice brought into the greatest jeopardy their own. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But one thing the Thebans will not be able to say—that they remain loyal to their
          associates, though there is reason to fear that we, having recovered our country, will
          desert to the Lacedaemonians; for you will find, Athenians, that we have twice been
            besieged<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By the Thebans in 427 (Thucydides iii. 52) and
            again in <date when="-0373">373 B.C.</date></note> and forced to surrender because of
          our friendship for you, while the Thebans often have wronged this city. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>It would be a laborious task to recount their treacheries in the past, but when the
          Corinthian war broke out because of their overbearing conduct and the Lacedaemonians had
          marched against them, although the Thebans had been saved by you, they were so far from
          showing their gratitude for this service that, when you had put an end to the war, they
          abandoned you and entered into the alliance with the Lacedaemonians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The people of <placeName key="tgn,7002670">Chios</placeName>, of Mytilen, and of
            <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName> remained loyal, but the
          Thebans, although they dwelt in a city of such importance, did not have the fortitude even
          to remain neutral, but were guilty of such cowardice and baseness as to give their solemn
          oath to join the Lacedaemonians in attacking you, the saviors of their city. For this they
          were punished by the gods, and, after the Cadmea was captured, they were forced to take
          refuge here in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. By this they furnished
          the crowning proof of their perfidy; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for when they had again been saved by your power and were restored to their city, they
          did not remain faithful for a single instant, but immediately sent ambassadors to
            <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>, showing themselves ready to be
          slaves and to alter in no respect their former agreements with <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. Why need I speak at greater length? For if the
          Lacedaemonians had not ordered them to take back their exiles and exclude the murderers,
          nothing would have hindered them from taking the field as allies of those who had injured
          them, against you their benefactors. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And these Thebans, who have recently behaved in such fashion toward your city and in
          times past have been guilty of betraying <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>
          as a whole,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the Persian Wars.</note> have seen fit to
          demand for themselves forgiveness for their evil deeds willingly committed and so
          monstrous, yet to us, for acts done under compulsion, they think no mercy ought to be
          shown, but they, true Thebans as they are, have the effrontery to reproach others for
          siding with the Lacedaemonians, when they, as we all know, have for the longest time been
          in servitude to them and have fought more zealously for Spartan domination than for their
          own security! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>In what invasion into your country of all that have ever been made have they failed to
          take part? Who, more consistently than they, have been your enemies and ill-wishers? In
          the Decelean War<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Decelean War is the name given to the
            latter part (<date from="-0413" to="-0404">413-404 B.C.</date>) of the
            Peloponnesian War when a Spartan force occupied the Attic post, Decelea, in <date
              when="-0413">413 B.C.</date></note> were they not authors of more mischief than the
          other invaders? When misfortune befell you,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A reference to
            the Athenian naval defeat at <placeName key="tgn,6000070">Aegospotami</placeName>, in
              <date when="-0405">405 B.C.</date></note> did not they alone of the allies<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">This is an exaggeration; not only the Thebans, but the
            Corinthians and other Peloponnesians, voted for the destruction of Athens, but
              <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> refused; cf. <bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 2.2.19">Xen. Hell. 2.2.19-20</bibl>.</note> vote that your city should
          be reduced to slavery and its territory be abandoned to pasturage as was the plain of
            <placeName key="tgn,7018211">Crisa</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">After the
            first Sacred War, at the end of the sixth century B.C., the plain of <placeName
              key="tgn,7018211">Crisa</placeName>, between <placeName key="perseus,Delphi"
              >Delphi</placeName> and the Corinthian Gulf, was declared holy ground and was
            dedicated to Apollo.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>so that if the Lacedaemonians had been of the same opinion as the Thebans, there would
          have been nothing to prevent the authors of the salvation of all the Greeks<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In the Persian Wars.</note> from being themselves enslaved by
          the Greeks and from plunging into the most grievous misfortunes? And yet what benefaction
          of their own could they adduce great enough to wipe out the hatred caused by these wrongs
          which you would justly feel toward them? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Accordingly, to these Thebans no plea is left, such is the magnitude of their crimes,
          and to those who wish to speak on their behalf only this—that <placeName key="tgn,7002683"
            >Boeotia</placeName> is now fighting in defense of your country, and that, if you put an
          end to your friendship with them, you will be acting to the detriment of your allies; for
          it will be a matter of great consequence if the city of <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
            >Thebes</placeName> takes the side of the Lacedaemonians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>My opinion is, however, that it is neither profitable to the allies that the weaker
          should be in servitude to the stronger (in past times, in fact, we went to war to protect
          the weak), nor that the Thebans will be so mad as to desert the alliance and hand over
          their city to the Lacedaemonians; this is not because I have confidence in the character
          of the Thebans, but because I know that they are well aware that one of two fates
          necessarily awaits them—either resisting, to die and to suffer such cruelties as they have
          inflicted, or else, going into exile, to be in want and deprived of all their hopes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Well then, are their relations with their fellow-citizens agreeable, some of whom they
          have put to death and others they have banished and robbed of their property? Or are they
          on friendly terms with the other Boeotians, whom they not only attempt to rule without
          warrant of justice, but have also in some instances razed their walls and have
          dispossessed others of their territory? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But assuredly they cannot again take refuge in your city either, Athenians, the city
          which they will be discovered to have so consistently betrayed. It is inconceivable,
          therefore, that they will care to get into a quarrel with you over an alien city<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, <placeName key="perseus,Plataea"
            >Plataea</placeName>.</note> and on that account so rashly and so inevitably to lose
          their own; on the contrary, in all their dealings with you they will behave in much more
          seemly fashion, and the more they fear for themselves the more they will cultivate your
          friendship. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Indeed they have proved to you how people of such character should be treated by their
          conduct in the matter of Oropus<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. § 20.</note>; for when
          they hoped that they would have license to do as they pleased they did not treat you as
          allies, but as ruthlessly wronged you as they would have dared to act against their
          deadliest enemies. But as soon as you in requital voted to exclude them from the
            peace,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><date when="-0374">374 B.C.</date>, between Athens
            and <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>.</note> they left off their
          arrogance and came to you in more humble mood than we Plataeans are in now. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If, then, some of their orators seek to frighten you, arguing that there is danger of the
          Thebans' changing sides and going over to the enemy, you must not credit what they say;
          for they are constrained by compulsions so peremptory that they would much sooner submit
          to your government than tolerate the alliance with the Lacedaemonians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But even if they were likely to act altogether otherwise, not even then, in my opinion,
          does it become you to have greater regard for the city of the Thebans than for your oaths
          and treaties, when you remember, first, that it is your ancient tradition to fear, not
          dangers, but acts of infamy aid dishonor; next, that it usually happens that victory in
          war is not for those who destroy cities by violence, but for those who govern <placeName
            key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> in a more scrupulous and clement manner.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf., however, <bibl n="Isoc. 12.185">Isoc.
            12.185</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And this could be proved by numerous instances; but as for those which have occurred in
          our own time at any rate, who does not know that the Lacedaemonians shattered your
            power,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At <placeName key="tgn,6000070"
              >Aegospotami</placeName>, <date when="-0405">405 B.C.</date></note> which was thought
          to be irresistible—although at first they possessed slight resources for the war waged at
          sea, but they won the Greeks over to their side because of that general belief—and that
          you in turn took the leadership away from them, although you depended on a city without
          walls and in evil plight,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A reference to the beginning of
            the Corinthian War, <date when="-0395">395 B.C.</date> Athens had been compelled by
              <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> to destroy her Long Walls and
            fortifications after her defeat in <date when="-0404">404 B.C.</date></note> but
          possessed Justice as your ally? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And that the Persian king was not responsible for this outcome recent years have clearly
          shown; for when he stood aloof from the conflict, and your situation was desperate, and
          when almost all the cities were in servitude to the Lacedaemonians, nevertheless you were
          so superior to them in the war that they were glad to see the conclusion of peace. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Let no one of you, then, be afraid, if Justice is with him, to take such dangers upon
          himself, nor think that allies will be lacking, if you are willing to aid all who are
          victims of wrong, and not the Thebans alone; if you now cast your vote against them, you
          will cause many to desire your friendship. For if you show yourselves ready to war upon
          all alike in defense of the treaties, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>who will be so insane as to prefer to join those who try to enslave than to be in company
          with you who are fighting for their freedom? But if you are not so minded, what reason
          will you give, if war breaks out again, to justify your demand that the Greeks should join
          you, if you hold out to them independence and then grant to the Thebans to destroy any
          city they desire? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>How can you avoid the charge of acting with inconsistency if, while you do not prevent
          the Thebans from violating their oaths and treaties, yet you pretend that you are making
          war on the Lacedaemonians on behalf of the same obligations? Or again, if you abandoned
          your own possessions in your desire to strengthen the alliance as much as possible, yet
          are about to permit the Thebans to keep the territory of others and act in such fashion as
          to injure your reputation with all the world? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But this would be the crowning outrage—if you have determined to stand by those who have
          been the constant allies of the Lacedaemonians when the Lacedaemonians demand of them an
          action which violates the treaty, and yet shall permit us, who have been your allies for
          the longest time, and were subservient to the Lacedaemonians under compulsion in the last
          war only, to become for that reason the most miserable of all mankind. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For who could be found to be more unhappy than we are who, in one day deprived of our
          city, our lands, and our possessions, and being destitute of all necessities alike, have
          become wanderers and beggars, not knowing whither to turn and, whatever our habitation,
          finding no happiness there? For if we fall in with the unfortunate, we grieve that we must
          be compelled, in addition to our own ills, to share in the ills of others; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and if we encounter those who fare well, our lot is even harder to bear, not because we
          envy them their prosperity, but because amid the blessings of our neighbors we see more
          clearly our own miseries—miseries so great that we spend no day without tears, but spend
          all our time mourning the loss of our fatherland and bewailing the change in our fortunes.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>What, think you, is our state of mind when we see our own parents unworthily cared for in
          their old age, and our children, instead of being educated as we had hoped when we begat
          them, often because of petty debts reduced to slavery,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Lys. 12.98">Lys. 12.98</bibl>.</note> others working for hire, and the rest
          procuring their daily livelihood as best each one can, in a manner that accords with
          neither the deeds of their ancestors, nor their own youth, nor our own self-respect? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But our greatest anguish of all is when one sees separated from each other, not only
          citizens from citizens, but also wives from husbands, daughters from mothers, and every
          tie of kinship severed; and this has befallen many of our fellow-citizens because of
          poverty. For the destruction of our communal life has compelled each of us to cherish
          hopes for himself alone. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I presume that you yourselves are not ignorant of the other causes of shame that poverty
          and exile bring in their train,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The unhappy lot of the
            exile is a commonplace in Greek poetry and prose; cf. Tyrtaeus, frag. 10.</note> and
          although we in our hearts bear these with greater difficulty than all the rest, yet we
          forbear to speak of them since we are ashamed to enumerate one by one our own misfortunes.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> All these things we ask you to bear in mind and to take some measure of consideration
          for us. For indeed we are not aliens to you; on the contrary, all of us are akin to you in
          our loyalty and most of us in blood also; for by the right of intermarriage<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Plataeans were granted Athenian citizenship after the
            destruction of their city in <date when="-0427">427 B.C.</date> This honor included the
            right of intermarriage.</note> granted to us we are born of mothers who were of your
          city. You cannot, therefore, be indifferent to the pleas we have come to make. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For it would be the cruellest blow of all, if you, having long ago bestowed upon us the
          right of a common citizenship with yourselves, should now decide not even to restore to us
          our own. Furthermore, it is not reasonable that, while every individual who is the victim
          of injustice receives pity at your hands, yet an entire city so lawlessly destroyed should
          be unable in the slightest degree to win commiseration from you, especially when it has
          taken refuge with you who in former times incurred neither shame nor infamy when you
          showed pity for suppliants. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For when the Argives came to your ancestors and implored them to take up for burial the
          bodies of the dead at the foot of the Cadmea,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.55">Isoc. 4.55</bibl> (Vol. I, p. 153).</note> your forefathers yielded to
          their persuasion and compelled the Thebans to adopt measures more conformable to our
          usage, and thus not only gained renown for themselves in those times, but also bequeathed
          to your city a glory never to be forgotten for all time to come, and this glory it would
          be unworthy of you to betray. For it is disgraceful that you should pride yourselves on
          the glorious deeds of your ancestors and then be found acting concerning your suppliants
          in a manner the very opposite of theirs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And yet the entreaties that we have come here to make are of far more weight and are
          more just; for the Argives came to you as suppliants after they had invaded an alien
          territory, whereas we have come after having lost our own; they called upon you to take up
          the bodies of their dead, but we do it for the rescue of the survivors. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But it is not an equal or even similar evil that the dead should be denied burial and
          that the living should be despoiled of their fatherland and all their goods besides: nay,
          in the former case it is a greater disgrace for those who prevent the burial than for
          those who suffer the misfortune, but in the latter, to have no refuge, to be without a
          fatherland, daily to suffer hardships and to watch without having the power to succor the
          suffering of one's own, why need I say how far this has exceeded all other calamities?
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For these reasons we supplicate you one and all, Athenians, to restore to us our land
          and city, reminding the older men among you how piteous a thing it is that men of their
          age should be seen in misfortune and in lack of their daily bread; and the younger men we
          beg and implore to succor their equals in age and not to let them suffer still more evils
          than those I have described. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Alone of the Greeks you Athenians owe us this contribution of succor, to rescue us now
          that we have been driven from our homes. It is a just request, for our ancestors, we are
          told, when in the Persian War your fathers had abandoned this land, alone of those who
          lived outside of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> shared in their
          perils and thus helped them to save their city.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.93">Isoc. 12.93</bibl>.</note> It is but just, therefore, that we should
          receive in return the same benefaction which we first conferred upon you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If, however, you have determined to have no regard for our persons, yet it is not in
          your interest to let our country at any rate be ravaged, a country in which are left the
          most solemn memorials of your own valor and of that of all the others who fought at your
          side. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For while all other trophies have been erected by one city victorious over another, those
          were in commemoration of the victory of all <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Greece</placeName> pitted against all the power of Asia. Although the Thebans have good
          reason for destroying these trophies, since memorials of the events of that time bring
          shame to them, yet it is proper that you should preserve them; for the deeds done there
          gave you the leadership of the Greeks. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And it is right that you should remember both the gods and the heroes who haunt that
          place and not permit the honors due them to be suppressed; for it was after favorable
          sacrifice to them that you took upon yourselves a battle so decisive that it established
          the freedom of both the Thebans and all the other Greeks besides. You must also take some
          thought of your ancestors and not be negligent of the piety due to them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Pray what would be their feelings—if we may assume that the dead yonder possess any
          perception of what takes place here<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This proviso is
            frequently found in Greek literature; cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 19.42">Isoc. 19.42</bibl>;
              <bibl n="Isoc. 9.2">Isoc. 9.2</bibl>.</note>—if they should perceive that, although
          you are masters, those who saw fit to be the slaves of barbarians had become despots over
          all the other Greeks and that we, who fought at your side for freedom, alone of the
          Greeks, have been driven from our homes, and that the graves of their companions in peril
          do not receive the customary funereal offerings through the lack of those to bring them,
          and that the Thebans, who were drawn up in battle array with the enemy, hold sway over
          that land? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Remember, too, that you used to bring bitter reproach against the Lacedaemonians because,
          to gratify the Thebans who were the betrayers of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Greece</placeName>, they destroyed us, its benefactors. Do not, therefore, allow your
          city to incur these foul accusations and do not prefer the insolence of the Thebans to
          your own fair fame. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Although many things remain to be said which might induce you to have greater regard for
          our safety, I cannot include them all in my discourse; but it is proper that you
          yourselves, having not only observed all that I have passed over but also having recalled
          especially your oaths and your treaties, and then our devotion to you and the hostility of
          the Thebans, should give a righteous judgement in our cause.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
