<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Anacharsis, or Athletics</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor>Austin Morris Harmon, 1878-1950</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>OCRd, tagged and added initial corrections to  the text</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg001.1st1K-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1925</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">4</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202129">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<head>Anacharsis, or Athletics<note><p>Taking us back to the early sixth century, Lucian lets us
listen to a conversation about Greek athletics between Solon,
the Athenian lawgiver, and that legendary figure, the
Scythian Anacharsis, who came to Greece in the quest of
wisdom just as Solon himself had gone to Egypt and
Lycurgus of Sparta to Crete.</p>
<p>K. G. Jacob, who tried to make out that Lucian was an
ardent reformer, laid great stress on this dialogue as a tract
designed to restore the importance of athletics in Greek education by recalling how much they meant in the good old days.
But Lucian, who in any case was no laudator temporis acti, says
nothing of any significance elsewhere to indicate either that
he thought athletics especially in need of reform or that he
felt any particular interest in them; and if the Anacharsis
had been written for any such purpose, surely it would have
ended with the conversion of the Scythian to the standpoint
of the Greek.</p>
<p>Let us say rather that Lucian, who was especially
interested in Anacharsis and Solon, as we see from his
Scythian, wished, perhaps for the edification of an Athenian
audience, to present them in conversation, and shrewdly
picks athletics for their theme as that feature of Greek
civilization which would be most striking and least intelligible to the foreigner, the ‘child of Nature.’</p>

<p>
The conversation takes place in the Lyceum at Athens
The opening sentence assumes that Anacharsis has just
been enquiring about something else, and now turns to a
new topic.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>


<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
And why are your young men doing all this,
Solon? Some of them, locked in each other’s arms,
are tripping one another up, while others are choking
and twisting each other and grovelling together in
the mud, wallowing like swine. Yet, in the beginning, as soon as they had taken their clothes off, they
put oil on themselves and took turns at rubbing each
other down very peacefully—I saw it. Since then, I
do not know what has got into them that they push
one another about with lowered heads and butt their
foreheads together like rams. And see there! That
man picked the other one up by the legs and threw
him to the ground, then fell down upon him and
will not let him get up, shoving him all down
into the mud; and now, after winding his legs about
his middle and putting his forearm underneath his
throat, he is choking the poor fellow, who is slapping
him sidewise on the shoulder, by way of begging off,
I take it, so that he may not be strangled completely.<note n="v.4.p.3.n.1"><p>The under man is trying to break his opponent’s hold, a "half Nelson,” by striking him on the upper arm. </p></note>
Even out of consideration for the oil, they do not
avoid getting dirty; they rub off the ointment,
plaster themselves with mud, mixed with streams of


<pb n="v.4.p.5"/>

sweat, and make themselves a laughing-stock, to me
at least, by slipping through each other's hands
like eels.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
Another set is doing the same in the uncovered part
of the court, though not in mud. They have a layer
of deep sand under them in the pit, as you see, and
not only besprinkle one another but of their own
accord heap the dust on themselves like so many
cockerels, in order that it may be harder to break away
in the clinches, I suppose, because the sand takes off
the slipperiness and affords a firmer grip on a dry
surface.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
Others, standing upright, themselves covered with
dust, are attacking each other with blows and
kicks. This one here looks as if he were going to
spew out his teeth, unlucky man, his mouth is so full
of blood and sand ; he has had a blow on the jaw, as
you see. But even the official there does not separate
them and break up the fight—I assume from his
purple cloak that he is one of the officials; on the
contrary, he urges them on and praises the one who
struck the blow.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
Others in other places are all exerting themselves ;
they jump up and down as if they were running, but
stay in the same place; and they spring high up and
kick the air.<note n="v.4.p.5.n.1"><p>“The exercise is that known in the modern gymnasium as ‘knees up,’ and is apparently the same as that described by Seneca (Ep. xv.) as the ‘fuller’s jump,’ from its resemblance to the action of a fuller jumping up and down on the clothes in his tub.” E. N. Gardiner, Greek Athletic Sports and Festivals, p. 298 </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
I want to know, therefore, what good it can be to
do all this, because to me at least the thing looks
more like insanity than anything else, and nobody can
easily convince me that men who act in that way are
not out of their minds.



<pb n="v.4.p.7"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
<label>SOLON</label>
It is only natural, Anacharsis, that what they are
doing should have that appearance to you, since it is
unfamiliar and very much in contrast with Seythian
customs. In like manner you yourselves probably
have much io your education and training which
would appear strange to us Greeks if one of us
should look in upon it as you are doing now. But
have no fear, my dear sir; it is not insanity, and it is
not out of brutality that they strike one another and
tumble each other in the mud, or sprinkle each other
with dust. The thing has a certain usefulness, not
unattended by pleasure, and it gives much strength
to their bodies. As a matter of fact, if you stop for
some time, as I think you will, in Greece, before long
you yourself will be one of the muddy or dusty set ;
so delightful and at the same time so profitable will
the thing seem to you.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Get out with you, Solon! You Greeks may have
those benefits and pleasures. For my part, if one of
you should treat me like that, he will find out that
we do not carry these daggers at our belts for
nothing!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>

But tell me, what name do you give to
these performances? What are we to say they are
doing?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
The place itself, Anacharsis, we call a gymnasium,
and it is consecrated to Lyceian Apollo; you see his
statue—the figure leaning against the pillar, with the
bow in his left hand; his right arm bent back above

<pb n="v.4.p.9"/>

his head indicates that the god is resting, as if after
long exertion.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>

As for these forms of athletics, that
one yonder in the mud is called wrestling, and the
men in the dust are wrestling too. When they stand
upright and strike one another, we call it the pancratium.<note n="v.4.p.9.n.1"><p>Solon’s statement is not quite full enough. The pancratium included not only boxing, but kicking and wrestling, and was practised not only upright but on the ground. fi was a rough and tumble affair, in which only gouging and biting were barred. Some, at least, of the wrestlers in the mud were engaged, strictly speaking, in the pancratium, as the choking and striking show. </p></note>. We have other such athletic exercises,
too—boxing, throwing the discus, and jumping—
in all of which we hold contests, and the winner is
considered best in his class and carries off the prizes.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
And these prizes of yours, what are they?

</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
At the Olympic games, a wreath made of wild
olive, at the Isthmian one of pine, and at the
Nemean one of parsley, at the Pythian some of the
apples sacred to Apollo, and with us at the
Panathenaea, the oil from the holy olive.<note n="v.4.p.9.n.2"><p>The one planted on the Acropolis by Athena. As to the prize in the Pythia, it may have been apples before the reorganization of the games in 586. But in that year the competition had prizes “in kind,” spoils of the Crisaean war (χρηματίτης ἀπὸ λαφύρων: Marmor Parium) ; and from 582 it was orepavirns, like the other three Panhellenic Festivals, with a wreath of laurel. </p></note> What
made you laugh, Anacharsis? Because you think
these prizes trivial ?
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
No, the prizes that you have told off are absolutely
imposing, Solon; they may well cause those who
have offered them to glory in their munificence and
the contestants themselves to be tremendously eager



<pb n="v.4.p.11"/>

to carry off such guerdons, so that they will go
through all these preliminary hardships and risks,
getting choked and broken in two by one another,
for apples and parsley, as if it were not possible for
anyone who wants them to get plenty of apples
without any trouble, or to wear a wreath of parsley
or of pine without having his face bedaubed with
mud or letting himself be kicked in the belly by
his opponent !

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
<label>SOLON</label>
But, my dear fellow, it is not the bare gifts that
we have in view! They are merely tokens of the
victory and marks to identify the winners. But the
reputation that goes with them is worth everything
to the victors, and to attain it, even to be kicked is
nothing to men who seek to capture fame through
hardships. Without hardships it cannot be acquired ;
the man who covets it must put up with many unpleasantnesses in the beginning before at last he can
expect the profitable and delightful outcome of his
exertions,
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
By this delightful and profitable outcome, Solon,
you mean that everybody will see them wearing
wreaths and will applaud them for their victory after
having pitied them a long time beforehand for their
hard knocks, and that they will be felicitous to have
apples and parsley in compensation for their hardships !
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
You are still unacquainted with our ways, I tell
you. After a little you will think differently about

<pb n="v.4.p.13"/>

them, when you go to the games and see that great
throng of people gathering to look at such spectacles,
and amphitheatres filling that will hold thousands, and
the contestants applauded, and the one among them
who succeeds in winning counted equal to the gods.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
That is precisely the most pitiable part of it, Solon,
if they undergo this treatment not before just a few
but in the presence of so many spectators and witnesses of the brutality, who no doubt felicitate them
on seeing them streaming with blood or getting
strangled by their opponents; for these are the
extreme felicities that go with their victory! With
us Scythians, Solon, if anyone strikes a citizen, or
assaults him and throws him down, or tears his
clothing, the elders impose severe penalties upon
him, even if the offence takes place before just a
few witnesses, not to speak of such great assemblies
as that at the Isthmus and that at Olympia which
you describe. I assure you, I cannot help pitying
the contestants for what they go through, and
I am absolutely amazed at the spectators, the
prominent men who come, you say, from all sides
to the games, if they neglect their urgent business
and fritter their time away in such matters. I cannot
yet conceive what pleasure it is to them to see
men struck, pummelled, dashed on the ground, and
crushed by one another.


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
<label>SOLON</label>
If it were the time, Anacharsis, for the Olympic
or the Isthmian or the Panathenaic games, what

<pb n="v.4.p.15"/>

takes place there would itself have taught you that
we had not spent our energy on all this in vain.
Just by talking about the delightfulness of the doings
there, one cannot convince you of it as thoroughly
as if you yourself, sitting in the midst of the spectators,
were to see manly perfection, physical beauty,
wonderful condition, mighty skill, irresistible
strength, daring, rivalry, indomitable resolution, and
inexpressible ardour for victory. I am very sure that
you would never have stopped praising and cheering
and clapping.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
No doubt, Solon; and laughing and gibing, into
the bargain; for I see that all these things which
you have enumerated—the perfection, the condition,
the beauty, the daring—are being wasted for you
without any great object in view, since your
country is not in peril nor your farm-lands being
ravaged, nor your friends and kinsmen insolently
carried off. So the competitors are all the more
ridiculous if they are the flower of the country, as
you say, and yet endure so much for nothing, making
themselves miserable and defiling their beautiful,
great bodies with sand and black eyes to get
possession of an apple and an olive-branch when
they have won! You see, I like to keep mentioning
the prizes, which are so fine! But tell me, do all
the contestants get them ?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Not by any means; only one among them all, the
victor.

<pb n="v.4.p.17"/>

<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Then do so many undergo hardships upon the
uncertain and precarious chance of winning, Solon,
knowing too that there will surely be but one
winner and very many losers, who, poor fellows, will
have received blows and in some cases even wounds
for nothing?

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>

<label>SOLON</label>
It seems, Anacharsis, that you have never yet
done any thinking about the proper way to direct a
state; otherwise you would not disparage the best
of institutions. If ever you make it your object to
find out how a state is to be organized in the best
way possible, and how its citizens are to reach the
highest degree of excellence, you will then praise
these exercises and the rivalry which we display in
regard to them, and you will know that they have .
much that is useful intermingled with the hardships,
even if you now think our energy is spent on them
for nothing.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
T assure you, Solon, I had no other object in coming
to your country from Scythia, over such a vast
stretch of land and across the wide and tempestuous
Euxine, than to learn the laws of the Greeks, to
observe your institutions, and to acquaint myself
with the best form of polity. Thatis why I selected
you in particular out ofall the Athenians for my friend
and host, in deference to your reputation, for I used
to hear that you were a maker of laws, an inventor of
excellent institutions, an introducer of advantageous
practices, and in a word, the fashioner of a polity. So


<pb n="v.4.p.19"/>

do be quick about teaching me and making a disciple
of me. For my part I would gladly sit beside you
without meat or drink as long as you could endure
to talk, and listen to you with avidity while you
described government and laws.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
<label>SOLON</label>
To describe everything, my friend, in brief compass
is not an easy task, but if you take it up a little at
a time, you will find out in detail all the opinions
we hold about the gods and about parents, marriage,
and everything else. And I shall now tell you what
we think about our young men, and how we deal
with them from the time when they begin to know
good from bad, to be physically mature, and to bear
hardships, in order that you may learn why we prescribe these exercises for them and compel them to
train their bodies. It is not simply on account of
the contests, in order that they may be able to take
the prizes—very few out of the entire number have
the capacity for that—but because we seek a certain
greater good from it for the entire state and for the
young men themselves. There is another competition
which is open to all good citizens in common, and
a wreath that is not made of pine or olive or parsley,
but contains in itself all human felicity,—that is to
say, freedom for each individual singly and for
the state in general, wealth, glory, enjoyment of
ancestral feast-days, safety for one’s family, and in
short, the fairest blessings that one could pray to
receive from the gods. All these things are interwoven in the wreath that I speak of and accrue from
the contest to which these exercises and hardships
lead.

<pb n="v.4.p.21"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Then, Solon, you amazing person, when you had
such magnificent prizes to tell of, you spoke of apples
and parsley and a sprig of wild olive and a bit
of pine?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
But really, Anacharsis, even those prizes will no
longer appear trivial to you when you understand what
I mean. They originate in the same purpose, and
are all small parts of that greater contest and of the
wreath of complete felicity which I mentioned. Our
conversation, departing somehow or other from the
natural sequence, touched first upon the doings at
the Isthmus and Olympia and Nemea. However, as
we are at leisure and you are eager, you say, to hear,
it will be an easy matter for us to hark back to the
-beginning, to the common competition which is, as I
say, the object of all these practices.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
It would be better, Solon, to do so, for by keeping
to the highway our talk would make greater progress,
and perhaps knowing these prizes may persuade me
never again to laugh at those others, if I should see a
man putting on airs because he wears a wreath of wild
olive or parsley. But if it is all the same to you, let
us go into the shade over yonder and sit on the
benches, so as not to be annoyed by the men who
are shouting at the wrestlers. Besides—I may as
well be frank !—I no longer find it easy to stand the
sun, which is fierce and burning as it beats upon my
bare head. I thought it best to leave my cap at

<pb n="v.4.p.23"/>

home, so as not to be the only person among you in
a foreign costume.<note n="v.4.p.23.n.1"><p>A great pointed cap of felt or skin was part of the Scythian costume. The Greeks went bare-headed, unless they were ill, or on a journey, or regularly exposed to bad weather, like sailors and farm-labourerr, who wore a similar but smaller cap. </p></note>_ But the season of the year is the
very fieriest, for the star which you call the Dog burns
everything up and makes the air dry and parching,
and the sun, now hanging overhead at midday,
produces this blazing heat, insupportable to the body.
I wonder, therefore, how it is that you, an elderly
man, do not perspire in the heat as I do, and do not
seem to be troubled by it at all; you do not even
look about for a shady spot to enter, but stand the
sun with ease.
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
These useless exertions, Anacharsis, the continual
somersaults in the mud and the open-air struggles
in the sand give us our immunity from the shafts of
the sun and we have no further need of a cap to
keep its rays from striking our heads.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
Let us go, however. And take care not to regard
everything that I may say to you as a law, so as to
believe it at all hazards. Whenever you think I am
incorrect in anything that I say, contradict me at
once and set my reasoning straight. One thing or
the other, certainly, we cannot fail to accomplish :
either you will become firmly convinced after you
have exhausted all the objections that you think
ought to be made, or else I shall be taught that I am
not correct in my view of the matter. In that event
the entire city of Athens could not be too quick to



<pb n="v.4.p.25"/>

acknowledge its gratitude to you, because in so far
as you instruct me and convert me to a better
view, you will have conferred the grgatest possible
benefit upon her. For I could not keep anything
from her, but shall at once contribute it all to
the public. Taking my stand in the Pnyx, I shall
say to everyone: “Men of Athens, I made you
the laws which I thought would’ be most beneficial
to the city, but this guest of mine”—and then
I shall point to you, Anacharsis,—“a Scythian,
indeed, but a man of learning, has converted me and
taught me other better forms of education and
training. Therefore let him be written down as
your benefactor, and set his statue up in bronze
beside the Namesakes<note n="v.4.p.25.n.1"><p>The ten Athenian tribes ‘were named after legendary heroes whose statues stood in the Potters’ Quarter. </p></note> or on the Acropolis beside
Athena.” You may be very sure that the city of
Athens will not be ashamed to learn what is to her
advantage from a foreign guest.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Ah! that is just what I used to hear about you
Athenians, that you never really mean what you say.
For how could I, a nomad and a rover, who have lived
my life on a wagon, visiting different lands at different
seasons, and have never dwelt in a city or seen one
until now—how could I hold forth upon statecraft
and teach men sprung from the soil, who have
inhabited this very ancient city for so many years in
law and order? Above all, how could I teach you,
Solon, who from the first, they say, have made it a
special study to know how the government of a state


<pb n="v.4.p.27"/>

can be conducted best and what laws it should
observe to be prosperous? However, in this too,
since you are a law-giver, I must obey you; so I
shall contradict you if I think that you are incorrect
in anything that you say, in order that I may learn
my lesson more thoroughly.
See, we have escaped the sun and are now in the
shade ; here is a very delightful and opportune seat
on the cool stone. So begin at the beginning and
tell why you take your young men in hand and train
them from their very boyhood, how they turn out
excellent men as a result of the mud and the
exercises, and what the dust and the somersaults
contribute to their excellencé. That is what I was
most eager to hear at the beginning: the rest you
shall teach me later, as opportunity offers, each
particular in its turn. But bear this in mind, please,
Solon, throughout your talk, that you will be
speaking to a foreigner. I say this in order that
you may not make your explanations too involved or
too long, for I am afraid that I may forget the
commencement if the sequel should be too profuse
in its flow.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
<label>SOLON</label>
You yourself, Anacharsis, can regulate that better,
wherever you think that my discussion is not fully
clear, or that it is meandering far from its channel
in a random stream; for you can interpose any
question that you will, and cut it short. But if
what I say is not foreign to the case and beside the
mark, there will be nothing, I suppose, to hinder,
even if I should speak at length, since that is the

<pb n="v.4.p.29"/>

tradition in the court of the Areopagus, which
judges our cases of manslaughter. Whenever it
goes up to the Areopagus and holds a sitting to
judge a case of manslaughter or premeditated
wounding or arson, an opportunity to be heard is
given to each party to the case, and the plaintiff and
defendant plead in turn, either in person or through
professional speakers whom they bring to the bar to
plead in their behalf. As long as they speak about
the case, the court tolerates them and listens in
silence ; but if anyone prefaces his speech with an introduction in order to make the court more favourable,
or brings emotion or exaggeration into the case—
tricks that are often devised by the disciples of
rhetoric to influence the judges,—then the crier
appears and silences them at once, preventing them
from talking nonsense to the court and from
tricking the case out in words, in order that the
Areopagites may see the facts bare.
So, Anacharsis, I make you an Areopagite for the
present. Listen to me according to the custom of
the court and tell me to be silent if you perceive
that I am plying you with rhetoric. But as long as
what I say is germane to the case, let me have the
right to speak at length. Besides, we are not going
to converse in the sun now, so that you would find
it burdensome if my talk were prolonged ; the shade
is thick, and we have plenty of time.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
What you say is reasonable, Solon, and already I
am more than a little grateful to you for incidentally
teaching me about what takes place in the Areopagus,

<pb n="v.4.p.31"/>

which is truly admirable and what good judges
would do, who intend to cast their ballot in
accordance with the facts. On these conditions,
therefore, proceed, and in my _ capacity of
Areopagite, since you have made me that, I shall
give you a hearing in the manner of that court.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
<label>SOLON</label>
Then you must first let me tell you briefly what
our ideas are about a city and its citizens. We
consider that a city is not the buildings, such as walls
and temples and docks. These constitute a firm-set,
immovable body, so to speak, for the shelter and
protection of the community, but the whole
significance is in the citizens, we hold, for it is they _
who fill it, plan and carry out everything, and keep
it safe; they are something like what the soul is
within the individual. So, having noted this, we
naturally take care of the city’s body, as you see,
beautifying. it so that it may be as fair as possible,
not only well furnished inside with buildings but
most securely fenced with these external ramparts.
But above all and at all hazards we endeavour to
insure that the citizens shall be virtuous in soul and
strong in body, thinking that such men, joined
together in public life, will make good use of themselves in times of peace, will bring the city safe
out of war, and will keep it always free and
prosperous.
Their early upbringing we entrust to mothers,
nurses, and tutors, to train and rear them with

<pb n="v.4.p.33"/>

liberal teachings; but when at length they become
able to understand what is right, when modesty,
shame, fear, and ambition spring up in them, and
when at length their very bodies seem well fitted
for hardships as they get firmer and become more
strongly compacted, then we take them in hand and
teach them, not only prescribing them certain disciplines and exercises for the soul, but in certain
other ways habituating their bodies also to hardships. We have not thought it sufficient for each
man to be as he was born, either in body or
in soul, but we want education and disciplines
for them by which their good traits may be much
improved and their bad altered for the better. We
take example from the farmers, who shelter and
enclose their plants while they are small and young,
so that they may not be injured by the breezes:
but when the stalk at last begins to thicken, they
prune away the excessive growth and expose them
te the winds to be shaken and tossed, in that way
making them more fruitful.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
Their souls we fan into flame with music and
arithmetic at first and we teach them to write their
letters and to read them trippingly. As they
progress, we recite for them sayings of wise men,
deeds of olden times, and helpful fictions, which we
have adorned with metre that they may remember
them better. Hearing of certain feats of arms and
famous exploits, little by little they grow covetous


<pb n="v.4.p.35"/>

and are incited to imitate them, in order that they
too may be sung and admired by men of after time.
Both Hesiod and Homer have composed much
poetry of that sort for us.</p>

<p>
When they enter political life and have at length
to handle public affairs—but this, no doubt, is foreign
to the case, as the subject proposed for discussion at
the outset was not how we discipline their souls, but
why we think fit to train their bodies with hardships
like these. Therefore I order myself to be silent,
without waiting for the crier to do it, or for you, the
Areopagite ; it is out of deference, I suppose, that
you tolerate my saying so much that is beside the
point.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Tell me, Solon, when people do not say what is
most essential in the Areopagus, but keep it to
themselves, has the court devised no penalty for
them ?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Why did you ask me that question? I do not
understand.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Because you propose to pass over what is best
and: for me most delightful to hear about, what
concerns the soul, and to speak of what is less
essential, gymnastics and physical exercises.
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Why, my worthy friend, I remember your admonitions in the beginning and do not wish the discussion

<pb n="v.4.p.37"/>

to meander out of its channel for fear of confusing your
memory with its flow. However, I shall discuss this,
too, in brief, as best I can. To consider it carefully
would be matter for another conversation.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
We harmonize their minds by causing them to
learn by heart the laws of the community, which are
exposed in public for everyone to read, written in
large letters, and tell what one should do and what
one should refrain from doing ; also by causing them
to hold converse with good men, from whom they
learn to say what is fitting and do what is right, to
associate with one another on an equal footing, not to
aim at what is base, to seek what is noble, and to do
no violence. These men we call sophists and philosophers. Furthermore, assembling them in the theatre,
we instruct them publicly through comedies and
tragedies, in which they behold both the virtues and
the vices of the ancients, in order that they may
recoil from the vices and emulate the virtues. The
comedians, indeed, we allow to abuse and ridicule
any citizens whom they perceive to be following
practices that are base and unworthy of the city, not
only for the sake of those men themselves, since they
are made better by chiding, but for the sake of the
general public, that they may shun castigation for
similar offences.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
I have seen the tragedians and comedians that
you are speaking of, Solon, if I am not mistaken ;
they<note n="v.4.p.37.n.1"><p>The tragedians. There may be a lacuna in the text. </p></note> had on heavy, high footgear, clothing that
was gay with gold stripes, and very ludicrous head-


<pb n="v.4.p.39"/>

pieces with great, gaping mouths; they shouted
loudly from out of these, and strode about in the
footgear, managing somehow or other to do it safely.
The city was then holding a feast, in honour, I think,
of Dionysus. The comedians were shorter, nearer
to the common level, more human, and less given
to shouting, but their headpieces were far more
ludicrous. In fact the whole audience laughed at
them; but they all wore long faces while they
listened to the tall fellows, pitying them, I suppose,
because they were dragging such clogs about!
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
It was not the actors that they pitied, my dear
fellow. No doubt the poet was presenting some
calamity of old to the spectators and declaiming
mournful passages to the audience by which his
hearers were moved to tears. Probably you also saw
flute-players at that time, and others who sang in
concert, standing in a circle. Even singing and
flute-playing is not without value, Anacharsis.
By all these means, then, and others like them,
we whet their souls and make them better.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>
As to their bodies—for that is what you were
especially eager to hear about—we train them as
follows. When, as I said,<note n="v.4.p.39.n.1"><p>Pp. 33 </p></note> they are no longer soft
and wholly strengthless, we strip them, and think it
best to begin by habituating them to the weather,
making them used to the several seasons, so as not
to be distressed by the heat or give in to the cold.
Then we rub them with olive-oil and supple them
in order that they may be more elastic, for since
we believe that leather, when softened by oil, is
harder to break and far more durable, lifeless as it


<pb n="v.4.p.41"/>

is, it would be extraordinary if we should not think
that the living body would be put in better condition
by the oil.
After that, having invented many forms of athletics and appointed teachers for each, we teach one,
for instance, boxing, and another the pancratium, in
order that they may become accustomed to endure
hardships and to meet blows, and not recoil for fear
of injuries. This helps us by creating in them two
effects that are most useful, since it makes them not
only spirited in facing dangers and unmindful of
their bodies, but healthy and strong into the
bargain.
Those of them who put their bent heads together
and wrestle learn to fall safely and get up easily, to
push, grip and twist in various ways, to stand being
choked, and to lift their opponent high in the air.
They too are not engaging in useless exercises; on
the contrary, they indisputably acquire one thing,
which is first and greatest: their bodies become less
susceptible and more vigorous through being exercised
thoroughly. There is something else, too, which
itself is not trivial: they become expert as a result
of it, in case they should ever come to need what
they have learned in battle. Clearly such a man,
when he closes with an enemy, will trip and throw
him more quickly, and when he is down, will know
how to get up again most easily. For we make all
these preparations, Anacharsis, with a view to that
contest, the contest under arms, and we expect to
find men thus disciplined far superior, after we have
suppled and trained their bodes naked, and so
have made them healthier and stronger, light and

<pb n="v.4.p.43"/>

elastic, and at the same time too heavy for their
opponents.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
You can imagine, I suppose, the consequence—
what they are likely to be with arms in hand when
even unarmed they would implant fear in the enemy.
They show no white and ineffective corpulence or
pallid leanness, as if they were women’s bodies
bleached out in the shade, quivering and streaming
with profuse sweat at once and panting beneath the
helmet, especially if the sun, as at present, blazes
with the heat of noon. What use could one make
of men like that, who get thirsty, who cannot stand
dust, who break ranks the moment they catch sight
of blood, who lie down and die before they get
within a spear’s cast and come to grips with the
enemy?
But these young men of ours have a ruddy
skin, coloured darker by the sun, and manly faces ;
they reveal great vitality, fire, and courage; they
are aglow with such splendid condition; they are
neither lean and emaciated nor so full-bodied as
to be heavy, but symmetrical in their lines; they
have sweated away the useless and superfluous part
of their tissues, but what made for strength and
elasticity is left upon them uncontaminated by what
is worthless, and they maintain it vigorously. In fact,
athletics do in our bodies just what winnowers do to
wheat: they blow away the husks and the chaff, but
separate the grain out cleanly and accumulate it for
future use.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
Consequently a man like that cannot help keeping
well and holding out protractedly under exhausting
labours ; it would be long before he would begin

<pb n="v.4.p.45"/>

to sweat, and he would rarely be found ill. It
is as if you should take firebrands and throw them
simultaneously into the wheat itself and into its
straw and chaff—for I am going back again to the
winnower. The straw, I take it, would blaze up
far more quickly, while the wheat would burn
slowly, not with a great blaze springing up nor
at a single burst, but smouldering gradually, until in
course of time it too was totally consumed.
Neither illness nor fatigue, then, could easily
invade and rack such a body, or readily overmaster
it; for it has been well stocked within and very
strongly fortified against them without, so as not
to admit them, nor yet to receive either sun itself
or frost to the detriment of the body. To prevent
giving way under hardships, abundant energy that
gushes up from within, since it has been made
ready long beforehand and stored away for the
emergency, fills them at once, watering them with
vigour, and makes them unwearying for a very long
period, for their great preliminary hardships and
fatigues do not squander their strength but increase
it; the more you fan its flame, the greater it
becomes.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>
Furthermore, we train them to be good runners,
habituating them to hold out for a long distance,
and also making them light-footed for extreme
speed in a short distance. And the running is not
done on hard, resisting ground but in deep sand,
where it is not easy to plant one’s foot solidly
or to get a purchase with it, since it slips from under
one as the sand gives way beneath it. We also
train them to jump a ditch, if need be, or any other
obstacle, even carrying lead weights as large as they

<pb n="v.4.p.47"/>

can grasp. Then too they compete in throwing
the javelin for distance. And you saw another
implement in the gymnasium, made of bronze, circular, resembling a little shield without handle or
straps; in fact, you tested it as it lay there, and
thought it heavy and hard to hold on account of
its smoothness. Well, they throw that high into the
air and also to a distance, vying to see who can
go the farthest and throw beyond the rest. This
exercise strengthens their shoulders and puts muscle
into their arms and legs.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>
As for the mud and the dust, which you thought
rather ludicrous in the beginning, you amazing
person, let me tell you why it is put down. In
the first place, so that instead of taking their
tumbles on a hard surface they may fall with impunity on a soft one; secondly, their slipperiness
is necessarily greater when they are sweaty and
muddy. This feature, in which you compared them
to eels, is not useless or ludicrous; it contributes not a little to strength and muscle when
both are in this condition and each has to grip
the other firmly and hold him fast while he
tries to slip away. And as for picking up a.
man who is muddy, sweaty, and oily while he
does his best to break away and squirm out of
your hands, do not think it a trifle! All this,
as I said before, is of use in war, in case one
should need to pick up a wounded friend and carry
him out of the fight with ease, or to snatch up
an enemy and come back with him in one’s arms,
So we train them beyond measure, setting them
hard tasks that: they may manage smaller ones with
far greater ease.

<pb n="v.4.p.49"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>
The dust we think to be of use for the opposite
purpose, to prevent them from slipping away when
they are grasped. After they have been trained
in the mud to hold fast what eludes them because
of its oiliness, they are given practice in escaping
out of their opponent’s hands when they themselves
are caught, even though they are held in a sure grip.
Moreover, the dust, sprinkled on when the sweat is
pouring out in profusion, is thought to check it; it
makes their strength endure long, and hinders them
from being harmed by the wind blowing upon their
bodies, which are then unresisting and have the
pores open. Besides, it rubs off the dirt and makes
the man cleaner. I should like to put side by side
one of those white-skinned fellows who have lived
in the shade and any one you might select of the
athletes in the Lyceum, after I had washed off the
mud and the dust, and to ask you which of the two
you would pray to be like. I know that even
without testing each to see what he could do, you
would immediately choose on first sight to be firm
and hard rather than delicate and mushy and white
because your blood is scanty and withdraws to the
interior of the body.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>
That, Anacharsis, is the training we give our
young men, expecting them to become stout
guardians of our city, and that we shall live in
freedom through them, conquering our foes if they
attack us and keeping our neighbours in dread of us,
so that most of them will cower at our feet and pay
tribute. In peace, too, we find them far better,
for nothing that is base appeals to their ambitions


<pb n="v.4.p.51"/>

and idleness does not incline them to arrogance,
but exercises such as these give them diversion and
keep them occupied. The chief good of the public
and the supreme felicity of the state, which I
mentioned before, are attained when our young men,
striving at our behest for the fairest objects, have been
most efficiently prepared both for peace and for
war.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p>
<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Then if the enemy attack you, Solon, you yourselves will take the field rubbed with oil and
covered with dust, shaking your fists at them, and
they, of course, will cower at your feet and run away,
fearing that while they are agape in stupefaction
you may sprinkle sand in their mouths, or that after
jumping behind them so as to get on their backs,
you may wind your legs about their bellies and
strangle them by putting an arm under their
helmets. Yes, by Zeus, they will shoot their arrows,
naturally, and throw their spears, but the missiles
will not affect you any more than as if you were
statues, tanned as you are by the sun and supplied
in abundance with blood. You are not straw or
chaff, so as to give in quickly under their blows;
it would be only after Jong and strenuous effort, when
you are all cut up with deep wounds, that you
would show a few drops of blood. This is the gist
of what you say, unless I have completely misunderstood your comparison.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="32"><p>
Or else you will
then assume those panoplies of the comedians and
tragedians, and if a sally is proposed to you, you
will put on those wide-mouthed headpieces in order

<pb n="v.4.p.53"/>

that you may be more formidable to your opponents
by playing bogey-man, and will of course wear those
high shoes, for they will be light to run away in,
if need be, and hard for the enemy to escape from,
if you go in pursuit, when you take such great strides
in chase of them.
No, I am afraid that all these clever tricks of
yours are silliness, nothing but child’s play, amusements for your young men who have nothing to do
and want to lead an easy life. If you wish, whatever
betides, to be free and happy, you will require other
forms of athletics and real training, that is to say,
under arms, and you will not compete against each
other in sport, but against the enemy, learning
courage in perilous conflict. So let them give up
the dust and the oil; teach them to draw the bow
and throw the spear; and do not give them light
javelins that can be deflected by the wind, but let
them have a heavy lance that whistles when it is
hurled, a stone as large as they can grasp, a double
axe, a target in their left hand, a breastplate, and
a helmet.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="33"><p>
In your present condition, it seems to me that
you are being saved by the grace of some god or
other, seeing that you have not yet been wiped out
by the onfall ef a handful of light-armed troops.
Look here, if I should draw this little dirk at my belt
and fall upon all your young men by myself, I should
capture the gymnasium with a mere hurrah, for they
would run away and not one would dare to face the
steel; no, they would gather about the statues and
hide behind the pillars, making me laugh while
most of them cried and trembled. Then you would
see that they were no longer ruddy-bodied as they

<pb n="v.4.p.55"/>

are now; they would all turn pale on the instant,
dyed to another hue by fright. Profound peace has
brought you to such a pass that you could not easily
endure to see a single plume of a hostile helmet.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="34"><p>

<label>SOLON</label>
The Thracians who campaigned against us with
Eumolpus did not say so, Anacharsis, nor your
women who marched against the. city with
Hippolyta,<note n="v.4.p.55.n.1"><p>The Amazons. </p></note> nor any others who have tested us under
arms. It does not follow, my unsophisticated friend,
that because our young men’s bodies are thus naked
while we are developing them, they are therefore
undefended by armour when we lead them out
into dangers. When they become efficient in themselves, they are then trained with arms and can
make far better use of them because they are so well
conditioned.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Where do you do this training under arms? I
have not seen anything of the sort in the city,
though I have gone all about the whole of it.
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
But you would see it, Anacharsis, if you should
stop with us longer, and also arms for every man in
great quantity, which we use when it is necessary,
and crests and trappings and horses, and cavalrymen
amounting to nearly a fourth of our citizens. But
to bear arms always and carry a dirk at one’s belt is,
we think, superfluous in time of peace ; in fact, there
is a penalty prescribed for anyone who carries


<pb n="v.4.p.57"/>

weapons unnecessarily within the city limits or brings
armour out into a public place. As for your people,
you may be pardoned for always living under arms.
Your dwelling in unfortified places makes it easy to
attack you, and your wars are very numerous, and
nobody knows when someone may come upon him
asleep, drag him down from his wagon, and kill him.
Besides, your distrust of one another, inasmuch as
your relations with each other are adjusted by
individual caprice and not by law, makes steel always
necessary, so as to be at hand for defence if anyone
should use violence.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="35"><p>
<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Then is it possible, Solon, that while you think it
superfluous to carry weapons without urgent reason,
and are careful of your arms in order that they may
not be spoiled by handling, keeping them in store
with the intention of using them some day, when
need arises ; yet when no danger threatens you wear
out the bodies of your young men by mauling them
and wasting them away in sweat, not husbanding
their strength until it is needed but expending it
fruitlessly in the mud and dust?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Apparently, Anacharsis, you think that strength
is like wine or water or some other liquid. Anyhow,
you are afraid that during exertions it may leak
away unnoticed as if from an earthen jar, and then

<pb n="v.4.p.59"/>

be gone, leaving our bodies empty and dry, since
they are not filled up again with anything from
within. As a matter of fact, this is not the case, my
friend: the more one draws it out by exertions, the
more it flows in, like the fable of the Hydra, if you
have heard it, which says that when one head was
cut off, two others always grew up in ‘its place.
But if a man is undeveloped from the beginning, and
untempered, and has an insufficient substratum of
reserve material, then he may be injured and reduced
in flesh by exertions. Something similar is the case
with a fire and a lamp; for with one and the same
breath you can start the fire afresh and speedily
make it greater, stimulating it with your blowing,
and you can put out the light of the lamp, which
has not an adequate supply of fuel to maintain itself
against the oppvsing blast: the root from which it
sprang was not strong, I suppose.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="36"><p>

<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
I do not understand this at all, Solon; what you
have said is too subtle for me, requiring keen intellect
and penetrating discernment. But do by all means
tell me why it is that in the Olympic and Isthmian
and Pythian and the other games, where many, you
say, come together to see the young men competing,
you never match them under arms but bring them
out naked and show them receiving kicks and blows,
and when they have won you give them apples and
parsley. It is worth while to know why you do so

<pb n="v.4.p.61"/>

<label>SOLON</label>
We think, Anacharsis, that their zeal for the
athletic exercises will be increased if they see those
who excel in them receiving honours and having
their names proclaimed before the assembled Greeks.
For this reason, expecting to appear unclothed
before so many people, they try to attain good
physical condition so that they may not be ashamed
of themselves when they are stripped, and each
makes himself as fit to win as he can. Furthermore,
the prizes, as I said before, are not trivial—to be
praised by the spectators, to become a man of mark,
and to be pointed at with the finger as the best of
one’s class. Therefore many of the spectators, who
are still young enough for training, go away immoderately in love with manfulness and hard work
as a result of all this. Really, Anacharsis, if the
love of fame should be banished out of the world,
what new blessing should we ever acquire, or who
would want to do any glorious deed? But as things
are, even from these contests they give you an opportunity to infer what they would be in war, defending
country, children, wives, and fanes with weapons
and armour, when contending naked for parsley and
apples they bring into it so much zeal for victory.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="37"><p>

What would your feelings be if you should see
quail-fights and cock-fights here among us, and no
little interest taken in them? You would laugh, of
course, particularly if you discovered that we do it in
compliance with law, and that all those of military age
are required to present themselves and watch the
birds spar to the uttermost limit of exhaustion. Yet
this is not laughable, either : their souls are gradually
penetrated by an appetite for dangers, in order that

<pb n="v.4.p.63"/>

they may not seem baser and more cowardly than
the cocks, and may not show the white feather early
on account of wounds or weariness or any other
hardship.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="38"><p>

As for testing them under arms, and watching
them get wounded—no! It is bestial and terribly
cruel and, more than that, unprofitable to kill off
the most efficient men who can be used to better
advantage against the enemy.
As you say that you intend to visit the rest of
Greece, Anacharsis, bear it in mind if ever you go to
Sparta not to laugh at them, either, and not to suppose that they are exerting themselves for nothing
when they rush together and strike one another in
the theatre over a ball, or when they go into a place
surrounded by water, divide into companies and treat
one another like enemies, naked as with us, until one
company drives the other out of the enclosure,
crowding them into the water—the Heraclids driving
out the Lycurgids, or the reverse—after which there
is peace in future and nobody would think of striking
a blow. Above all, do not laugh if you see them
getting flogged at the altar and dripping blood while
their fathers and mothers stand by and are so far
from being distressed by what is going on that they
actually threaten to punish them if they should not
bear up under the stripes, and beseech them to
endure the pain as long as possible and be staunch
under the torture. Asa matter of fact, many have
died in the competition, not deigning to give in before
the eyes of their kinsmen while they still had life in
them, or even to move a muscle of their bodies; you
will see honours paid to their statues, which have
been set up at public cost by the state of Sparta.

<pb n="v.4.p.65"/>

When you see all that, do not suppose them crazy,
and do not say that they are undergoing misery without any stringent reason, since it is due neither to a
tyrant’s violence nor to an enemy’s maltreatment.
Lycurgus, their law-giver, could defend it by telling
you many good reasons which he has discerned for
punishing them; he is not unfriendly to them,
and does not do it out of hatred, nor is he
wantonly wasting the young blood of the city, but
he desires that those who are destined to preserve
their country should be tremendously staunch and
superior to every fear. Yet, even if Lycurgus does
not say so, you see for yourself, I suppose, that such
aman, on being captured in war, would never betray
any Spartan secret under torture inflicted by the
enemy, but would laugh at them and take his
whipping, matching himself against his flogger to see
which would give in.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="39"><p>
<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
But how about Lycurgus himself, Solon? Did he
get flogged in his youth, or was he then over the agelimit for the competition, so that he could introduce
such an innovation with impunity ?
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
He was an old man when he made the laws for
them on his return from Crete. He had gone to
visit the Cretans because he was told that they
enjoyed the best laws, since Minos, a son of Zeus,
had been their law-giver.

<pb n="v.4.p.67"/>

<label>ANACHARSIS</label>
Then why is it, Solon, that you have not imitated
Lycurgus and do not flog your young men? It isa
splendid practice, and worthy of you Athenians !
</p>
<p><label>SOLON</label>
Because we are content, Anacharsis, with these
exercises, which are our own; we do not much care
to copy foreign fashions.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
No: you understand, I think, what it is like to be
flogged naked, holding up one’s arms, for no advantage either to the individual himself or to the city in
general. Oh, if ever I am at Sparta at the time
when they are doing this, I expect I shall very soon
be stoned to death by them publicly for laughing at
them every time I see them getting beaten like
robbers or sneak-thieves or similar malefactors.
Really, it seems to me that the city stands in need
of hellebore<note n="v.4.p.67.n.1"><p>The specific for insanity. </p></note> if it mishandles itself so ridiculously.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg034.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="40"><p>
<label>SOLON</label>
Do not think, my worthy friend, that you are winning your case by default, or in the absence of your
adversaries, as the only speaker. There will be
someone or other in Sparta who will reply to you
properly in defence of this.
However, as I have told you about our ways and
you do not seem to be much pleased with them, I do
not think it will be unfair to ask you to tell me in


<pb n="v.4.p.69"/>

your turn how you Scythians discipline your young
men, what exercises you use in bringing them up,
and how you make them good men.
</p>
<p><label>ANACHARSIS</label>
It is entirely fair, to be sure, Solon, and I shall tell
you the Scythian customs, which are not imposing,
perhaps, or on the same plane as yours, since we
should not dare to receive a single blow in the face ;
we are cowards! They shall be told, however, no
matter what they are. But let us put off the
discussion, if you will, till to-morrow, so that I may
quietly ponder a little longer over what you have
said, and get together what I must say, going over
it in my memory. At present, let us go away
with this understanding, for it is now evening.

<pb n="v.4.p.73"/>
</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>
