<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Second Epistle of Clement to the Corinthians</title>
        <author>Clement of Rome</author>
        <editor role="translator">Kirsopp Lake</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
            <name/>
        </respStmt>
          <funder n="org:Tufts">Tufts University</funder>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
        <date type="release">2019</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <biblStruct>
          <monogr>
            <author>Clement of Rome</author>
            <editor role="translator">Kirsopp Lake</editor>
            <title>The Apostolic Fathers</title>
            <imprint>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>                           
              <publisher>William Heinemann</publisher>
              <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>       
              <publisher>The Macmillan Company</publisher>
              <date>1912</date>
            </imprint>
            <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          </monogr>
          <ref target="https://archive.org/details/in.ernet.dli.2015.232411/page/n133/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
        </biblStruct>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
        <cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <editorialDecl>
        <quotation marks="none"/>
          <correction method="silent" status="medium"><p>Perseus OCR in house AbbyyFR; single pass proofreading</p></correction>
      </editorialDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English</language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
        <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2019-03-18" who="Lisa Cerrato">basic structural markup and single pass editing</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  
  <text xml:lang="eng">
		<body>
		  <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg1271.tlg002.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
		    <pb xml:id="p.129"/>
<head>THE SECOND EPISTLE OF CLEMENT TO THE CORINTHIANS</head>

<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
    <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Brethren, we must think of Jesus Christ as of<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The need for thinking highly of Christ, and prizing our salvation</note> God, as of <q>the Judge of the living and the dead</q> and we must not think little of our salvation, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>for if we think little of him we also hope to obtain but little. And those who listen as though it were a little matter are sinning, and we also are sinning, if we do not know whence and by whom, and to what place we were called, and how great sufferings Jesus Christ endured for our sake. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>What return, then, shall we make to him, or what fruit shall we offer worthy of that which he has given us? And how great a debt of holiness do we owe him? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For he gave us the light, he called us <q>son,</q> as a Father, he saved us when we were perishing. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>What praise, then, or what reward shall we give him in return for what we received? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>We were maimed in our understanding, worshipping<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The state of the unconverted</note> stone, and wood, and gold, and silver, and copper, the works of men, and our whole life was nothing else than death. We were covered with darkness, and our eyes were full of mist; but we <pb xml:id="p.131"/> have received our sight, and by his will we have cast off the cloud which covered us.  </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>For he had pity on us, and saved us in his mercy, and regarded the great error and destruction which was in us, and our hopelessness of salvation save from him;	 </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>for he called us when we were not, and it was his will that out of nothing we should come to being.</p></div>
    </div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent"><q>Rejoice thou barren that barest not; break<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Prophecies of the church, and their interpretation</note> forth and cry thou that travailest not; for the children of the deserted are many more than hers that hath a husband.</q> In saying, <q>Rejoice thou barren that barest not,</q> he meant us, for our church was barren before children were given her. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And in saying, <q>Cry thou that travailest not,</q> he means this,—that we should offer our prayers in sincerity to God, and not grow wreary as women that give birth. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And in saying, <q>For the children of the deserted are many more than hers that hath a husband,</q> he meant that our people seemed to be deserted by God, but that now we who have believed have become many more than those who seemed to have God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And another Scripture also says, <q>I came not to call righteous, but sinners</q>; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>He means that those who are perishing must be saved, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>for it is great and wonderful to give strength, not to the things which are standing, but to those which are falling. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>So Christ also willed to save the perishing, and he saved many, coming and calling us who were already perishing.</p></div>
 </div>
		      <pb xml:id="p.133"/>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Seeing, then, that he has shewn such mercy<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Our duty to Christ</note> towards us, first that we who are living do not sacrifice to the dead gods, and do not worship them, but through him know the father of truth, what is the true knowledge concerning him<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The Greek is as ambiguous as the English, but this <q>him</q> no doubt refers to the <q>father of truth.</q></note> except that we should not deny him through whom we knew him? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And he himself also says, <q>Whosoever confessed me before men, I will confess him before my Father</q>; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>this then is our reward, if we confess him through whom we were saved. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>But how do we confess him? By doing what he says, and not disregarding his commandments, arid honouring him not only with our lips, but <q>with all our heart and all our mind.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And he says also in Isaiah, <q>This people honoureth me with their lips, but their heart is far from me.</q></p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us, then, not merely call him Lord, for this<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The necessity for good works</note> will not save us. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For he says, <q>Not everyone that saith to me Lord, Lord, shall be saved, but he that doeth righteousness.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>So then, brethren, let us confess him in our deeds, by loving one another, by not committing adultery, nor speaking one against another, nor being jealous, but by being self-controlled, merciful, good; and we ought to <pb xml:id="p.135"/> sympathise with each other, and not to be lovers of money. By these deeds we confess him, and not by the opposite kind. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And we must not fear men rather than God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>For this reason, if you do these things, the Lord said, <q>If ye be gathered together with me in my bosom, and do not my commandments, I will cast you out, and will say to you, Depart from me, I know not whence ye are, ye workers of iniquity.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">The source of this and the quotation in v. 2-4 is unknown: it is often supposed to have been the Gospel of the Egyptians, but there is no clear evidence of this.</note></p></div>
    
</div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Whehefore, brethren, let us forsake our sojourning<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to abandon the world</note> in this world, and do the will of him who called us, and let us not fear to go forth from this world, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>for the Lord said, <q>Ye shall be as lambs in the midst of wolves,</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>and Peter answered and said to him, <q>If then the wolves tear the lambs?</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Jesus said to Peter, <q>Let the lambs have no fear of the wolves after their death; and do ye have no fear of those that slay you, and can do nothing more to you, but fear him who after your death hath power over body and soul, to cast them into the flames of hell.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And be well assured, brethren, that our sojourning in this world in the flesh is a little thing and lasts a short time, but the promise of Christ is great and wonderful, and brings us rest, in the kingdom which is to come and in everlasting life. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>What then shall <pb xml:id="p.137"/> we do to attain these things save lead a holy and righteous life, and regard the things of this world as not our own, and not desire them? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>For by desiring to obtain these things we fall from the way of righteousness.</p></div></div>

		      
		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And the Lord says:—<q>No servant can serve<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The opposition between this world and the world to come</note> two masters.</q> If we desire to serve both God and Mammon it is unprofitable to us, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p><q>For what is the advantage if a man gain the whole world but lose his soul?</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Now the world that is, and the world to come are two enemies. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>This world speaks of adultery, and corruption, and love of money, and deceit, but that world bids these things farewell. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>We cannot then be the friends of both; but we must bid farewell to this world, to consort with that which is to come. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>We reckon that it is better to hate the things which are here, for they are little, and short-lived, and corruptible, but to love the things which are there, the good things which are incorruptible. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>For if we do the will of Christ we shall gain rest; but if not, nothing shall rescue us from eternal punishment, if we neglect his commandments. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>And the Scripture also says in Ezekiel that, <q>if Noah and Job and Daniel arise, they shall not rescue their children in the captivity.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>But if even such righteous men as these cannot save their children by their own righteousness, with <pb xml:id="p.139"/>  what confidence shall we enter into the palace of God, if we keep not our baptism pure and undefiled? Or who shall be our advocate if we be not found to have pious and righteous works?</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
		          <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">So then, my brethren, let us contend, knowing<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to strive well in the contest of life</note> that the contest is close at hand, and that many make voyages for corruptible prizes, but not all are crowned, save those who have toiled much, and contended well. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let us then contend that we may all be crowned. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us run the straight course, the immortal contest, and let many of us sail to it, and contend, that we may also receive the crown, and if we cannot all receive the crown, let us at least come near to it. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>We must remember that if he who takes part in the contest for a corruptible prize be detected in unfairness, he is flogged, taken up, and thrown off the course. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>What do you think? What shall he suffer who cheats in the contest for that which is incorruptible? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>For of those who have not kept the seal of baptism he says:—<q>Their worm shall not die, and their fire shall not be quenched, and they shall lie a spectacle for all flesh.</q></p></div></div>
		          
		          <pb xml:id="p.141"/>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us repent then while we are on the earth.<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Call to repentance and purity</note> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For we are clay in the hand of the workman; for just as the potter, if he make a vessel, and it be bent or broken in his hand, models it afresh, but if he has come so far as to put it into the fiery oven, he can do nothing to mend it any more; so also let us, so long as we are in this world, repent with all our heart of the wicked deeds which we have done in the flesh, that we may be saved by the Lord, while we have a time for repentance. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For after we have departed from this world, we can no longer make confession, or repent any more in that place. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>So then, brethren, if we do the will of the Father, if we keep the flesh pure, and if we observe the commandments of the Lord, we shall obtain eternal life. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>For the Lord says in the Gospel, <q>If ye did not guard that which is small, who shall give you that which is great? For I tell you that he who is faithful in that which is least, is faithful also in that which is much.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>He means, then, this:— Keep the flesh pure, and the seal of baptism undefiled, that we may obtain eternal life.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">And let none of you say that this flesh is not<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The resurrection of the flesh</note> judged and does not rise again. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Understand: in what state did you receive salvation, in what state did you receive your sight, except in this flesh?	 </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>We <pb xml:id="p.143"/> must therefore guard the flesh as a temple of God, </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>for as you were called in the flesh, you shall also come in the flesh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>If Christ, the Lord who saved us, though he was originally spirit, became flesh and so called us, so also we shall receive our reward in this flesh. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>Let us then love one another, that we may all attain to the kingdom of God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p rend="indent">While we have opportunity to be healed let<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Call to repentance</note> us give ourselves to God, who heals us, giving him his recompense. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8"><p>What recompense? Repentance from a sincere heart. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9"><p>For he has knowledge of all things beforehand, and knows the things in our hearts. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10"><p>Let us then give him praise, not only with our mouth, but also from our heart, that he may receive us as sons. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11"><p>For the Lord said <q>My brethren are these who do the will of my Father.</q></p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Wherefore, my brethren, let us do the will of<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to godliness and warning against vice</note> the father who called us, that we may live, and let us rather follow after virtue, but give up vice as the forerunner of our sins, and let us flee from ungodliness lest evil overtake us. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For, if we are zealous to do good, peace will follow after us. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>For this cause it is not possible for a man to find it,<note resp="editor" type="footnote">i.e. peace.</note> when they bring in human fears, and prefer the pleasures <pb xml:id="p.145"/> of the present to the promises of the future. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For they do not know how great torment the pleasures of the present entail, and what is the joy of the promised future. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And if they did these things by themselves it could be endured, but, as it is, they are continuing in teaching evil to innocent souls, and do not know that they will incur a double judgment, both themselves and their hearers.</p></div>
		      </div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then serve God with a pure heart, and<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Warning against doubt</note> we shall be righteous, but if we do not serve him, because we do not believe the promise of God, we shall be miserable. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For the prophetic word also says:—<q>Miserable are the double-minded that doubt in their heart, who say. These things we heard long ago and in the time of our fathers, but we have waited from day to day, and have seen none of them.</q></p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p><q rend="merge">O foolish men! compare yourselves to a tree; take a vine; first it sheds its leaves, then there comes a bud, after this the unripe grape, then the full bunch.</q> </p></div>
		        <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p><q rend="merge">So also my people has had tumults and afflictions; afterwards it shall receive the good things.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">The additional clause at the end of this quotation seems to show that it is not derived from I. Clement, but directly from the <q>prophetic word,</q> cf. note on p. 51.</note> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Therefore,	my	brethren, let us not be double-minded, but let us be patient in hope, that we may also receive the reward. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p><q>For he is faithful who promised</q> to pay to each mall the recompense of his deeds. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>If then we do righteousness before <pb xml:id="p.147"/>  God we shall enter into his kingdom, and shall receive the promises <q>which ear hath not heard, nor hath eye seen, neither hath it entered into the heart of man.</q></p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then wait for the kingdom of God, from<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Interpretation of a Saying of the Lord</note> hour to hour, in love and righteousness, seeing that we know not the day of the appearing of God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For when the Lord himself was asked by someone when his kingdom would come, he said: <q>When the two shall be one, and the outside as the inside, and the male with the female neither male nor female.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">The same saying, or very nearly so, is quoted from Cassianus by Clement of Alexandria (<bibl><title>Strom.</title> iii. 13</bibl>), and the latter states that it is from the Gospel of the Egyptians. But the whole question has been complicated by the discovery of Grenfell and Hunt’s <q>Lost Gospel</q> (<bibl><title>Oxyrhynchus papyri</title>, vol. iv. pp. 22 ff.</bibl>), which seems to refer to a similar saying, and the problem of the mutual relations between these documents is still unsolved.</note> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Now <q>the two are one</q> when we speak with one another in truth, and there is but one soul in two bodies without dissimulation. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>And by <q>the outside as the inside</q> he means this, that the inside is the soul, and the outside is the body. Therefore, just as your body is visible, so let your soul be apparent in your good works. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And by <q>the male with the female neither male nor female</q> he means this, that when a brother sees a sister he should have no  <pb xml:id="p.149"/> thought of her as female, nor she of him as male.<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Or, if <foreign xml:lang="grc">αὑτοῦ</foreign> be read instead of <foreign xml:lang="grc">αὐτοῦ</foreign>, <q>nor have any thought of himself as male.</q></note> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>When you do this, he says, the kingdom of my Father will come.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Therefore, brethren, let us at last repent<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The need for repentance</note> forthwith, and be sober for our good, for we are full of much folly and wickedness; let us wipe off from<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The impression made on <q>those without</q></note> ourselves our former sins, and let us gain salvation by repenting with all our souls. Let us not be men-pleasers, and let us wish to please by our righteousness not ourselves alone, but also those who are without, that the name be not blasphemed on our account. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For the Lord says, <q>Every way is my name blasphemed among all the heathen,</q> and again, <q>Woe unto him on whose account my name is blasphemed.</q><note resp="editor" type="footnote">The source of this quotation is unknown.</note> Wherein is it blasphemed? </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>In that you do not do what I desire. For when the heathen hear from our mouth the oracles of God, they wonder at their beauty and greatness; afterwards, when they find out that our deeds are unworthy of the words which we speak, they turn from their wonder to blasphemy, saying that it is a myth and delusion. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For when they hear from us that God says: <q>It is no credit to you, if ye love them that love you, but it is a credit to you, if ye love your enemies, and those that hate you</q>;— when they hear this they wonder at this extraordinary <pb xml:id="p.151"/> goodness; but when they see that we not only do not love those that hate us, but not even those who love us, they laugh us to scorn, and the name is blasphemed.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Thus, brethren, if we do the will of our Father,<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The preexistent Church</note> God, we shall belong to the first Church, the spiritual one which was created before the sun and moon; but if we do not the will of the Lord, we shall fall under the scripture, which says, <q>My house became a den of brigands.</q> Therefore let us choose to belong to the Church of life, that we may win salvation. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Now I imagine that you are not ignorant that the living <q>Church is the body of Christ.</q> For the scripture says, <q>God made man male and female</q>; the male is Christ, the female is the Church. And moreover the books and the Apostles declare that the Church belongs not to the present, but has existed from the beginning; for she was spiritual, as was also our Jesus, but he was made manifest in the last days that he might save us;<note resp="editor" type="footnote">The translation <q>she was made . . . that she might save us</q> is grammatically more probable, but seems to be excluded both by the context and by the history of doctrine.</note> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>and the Church, which is spiritual, was made manifest in the flesh of Christ, showing us that if any of us guard her in the flesh without corruption, he shall receive her back again in the Holy Spirit. <pb xml:id="p.153"/> For this flesh is an anti-type of the Spirit; no one<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The Flesh and the Spirit</note> therefore who has corrupted the anti-type shall receive the reality. So, then, he means this, brethren: Guard the flesh, that you may receive the Spirit. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Now if we say that the flesh is the Church, and the Spirit is Christ, of course he who has abused the flesh, has abused the Church. Such a one therefore will not receive the Spirit, which is Christ. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>So great a gift of life and immortality has this flesh the power to receive, if the Holy Spirit be joined to it, nor can any man express or speak of the things <q>which the Lord hath prepared</q> for his elect.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Now I think that I have given no mean advice<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to holiness and prayer</note> concerning self-control, and if any man follow it, he shall have no regret, but shall save both himself and me his counsellor; for it is no small reward to turn to salvation a soul that is wandering and perishing. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For this is the recompense which we can pay to God, who created us, if he who speaks and hears both speak and hear with faith and love. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us then remain righteous and holy in our faith, that we may pray with confidence to God, who says, <q>While thou art speaking I will say. Behold here am I.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For this saying is the sign of a great promise; for the Lord says that he is more ready to give than we to ask. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>Let us then accept such great goodness, and not grudge ourselves the gaining of such benefits, <pb xml:id="p.155"/> for as great joy as these words offer to those who do them so severe a condemnation do they threaten to the disobedient.</p></div></div>


		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Seeing therefore, brethren, that we have<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The profit of repentance</note> received no small opportunity for repentance; let us, now that we have time, turn to the God who calls us, while we still have one who awaits us. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For if we bid farewell to these enjoyments, and conquer our soul, by giving up its wicked lusts, we shall share in the mercy of Jesus. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>But you know that <q>the day</q> of judgment is already<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The danger of the Judgment</note> <q>approaching as a burning oven, and some<note resp="editor" type="footnote">Possibly the text is corrupt: Lightfoot’s conjecture would be translated, <q>the powers of heaven,</q> but the text may be defended as a reference to the early Christian belief in seven concentric heavens surrounding the Earth.</note> of the heavens shall melt,</q> and the whole earth shall be as lead melting in the fire, and then shall be made manifest the secret and open deeds of men. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Almsgiving is therefore good even as penitence<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Almsgiving</note> for sin; fasting is better than prayer, but the giving of alms is better than both; and love <q>covers a multitude of sins,</q> but prayer from a good conscience rescues from death. Blessed is every man who is found full of these things; for almsgiving lightens sin.</p></div></div>
		          <pb xml:id="p.157"/>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="17">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then repent with our whole heart, that<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Exhortation to repentance</note> none of us perish by the way. For if we have commandments to do this also, to tear men away from idols and to instruct them, how much more is it our duty to save from perishing a soul that already knows God?	 </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let us then help one another, and bring back those that are weak in goodness, that we may all be saved, and convert and exhort one another. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>And let us not merely seem to believe<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Not merely during the exhortation of the Elders</note> and pay attention now, while we are being exhorted by the Elders, but also when we have gone home let us remember the commandments of the Lord, and let us not be dragged aside by worldly lusts, but let us try to come here more frequently, and to make progress in the commands of the Lord; that wre may <q>all have the same mind</q> and be gathered together unto life. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>For the Lord said: <q>I come to gather together all the nations, tribes, and languages.</q> Now by this he means the day of his appearing.<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Warning of the Judgment</note> when he will come and ransom each of us according to his works. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p>And the unbelievers <q>shall see his glory</q> and might, and they shall be amazed when they see the sovereignty of the world given to Jesus and shall say: Woe unto us, that it was thou, and we knew it not, and did not believe, and were not obedient to the Elders, when they told us of our salvation. <q>And their worm shall not die and their fire shall not be quenched, and they shall be a <pb xml:id="p.159"/> spectacle to all flesh.</q> </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6"><p>He means that day of judgment, when they shall see those who were ungodly among us and perverted the commandments of Jesus Christ. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7"><p>But the righteous who have done good, and have endured torture, and have hated the indulgences of the soul, when they see how those who have done amiss, and denied Jesus by word or deed, are punished with terrible torture in unquenchable fire, shall give <q>glory to their God,</q> saying, There shall be hope for him who has served God with all his heart.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="18">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Let us then also belong to them who give<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The need of striving</note> thanks, who have served God, and not to the ungodly who are judged. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>For I myself too am altogether sinful, and I have not yet escaped temptation, but I am still in the midst of the devices of the devil, yet I am striving to follow after righteousness, that I may have the strength at least to draw near to it, in fear of the judgment to come.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="19">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Therefore, brothers and sisters, following the<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Attention to the Scriptures</note> God of truth, I am reading you an exhortation to pay attention to that which is written, that you may both save yourselves and him who is the reader<note resp="editor" type="footnote">It is probable though not quite certain that this refers to a definite order of <q>Readers</q> in the Church.</note> among you. For as a reward I beg of you that you repent with all your heart, and give to yourselves salvation and life. For if we do this we shall set a mark for all the <pb xml:id="p.161"/> younger, who wish to work in the cause of piety and the goodness of God. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>And let us not be displeased or be vexed in our foolishness when any one admonishes us, and turns us from unrighteousness to righteousness. For sometimes when we do evil we do not know it because of the double-mindedness and unbelief which is in our breasts, and we are <q>darkened in our understanding</q> by vain desires. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>Let us then do righteousness, that we may be saved at the end. Blessed are they who obey these instructions: though they suffer for a short time in this world, they shall gather the immortal fruit of the resurrection. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>Let not, then, the pious grieve if he endure sorrow at this present time; a time of blessedness awaits him; he shall live again with the fathers above, and rejoice to an eternity wherein is no sorrow.</p></div></div>

		      <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="20">
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">But neither let it grieve your mind that we see<note resp="editor" type="marginal">The prosperity of the righteous</note> the unrighteous enjoying wealth, and the servants of God oppressed. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p>Let us then have faith, brothers and sisters: we are contending in the contest of the living God, and we are being trained by the life which now is, that we may gain the crown in that which is to come. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p>None of the righteous has attained a reward quickly, but waits for it; </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p>for if God should pay the recompense of the righteous speedily, we should immediately be training ourselves in commerce and not in godliness; for we should seem to be righteous when we were pursuing not <pb xml:id="p.163"/> piety but gain. For this reason divine judgment punishes<note resp="editor" type="footnote">This translation takes the aorist as gnomic, and regards <q>spirit</q> as meaning a human spirit. But Harnack prefers to take the aorist as historical and refers the passage to the fall of Satan.</note> a spirit which is not righteous and loads it with chains. </p></div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5"><p rend="indent">To the only invisible God, the father of truth.<note resp="editor" type="marginal">Doxology</note> who sent forth to us the Saviour and prince of immortality, through whom he also made manifest to to us truth and the life of heaven, to him be the glory for ever and ever. Amen.</p>
		          <p rend="center">The Second Epistle of Clement to the Corinthians.</p></div></div>
		         
</div></body></text></TEI>

