<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Estate of Astyphilus from Speeches (ENGLISH). Machine readable
					text</title>
				<author>Isaeus</author>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>


			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Isaeus</author>
						<title>Isaeus with an English translation by Edward Seymour Forster,
							M.A.</title>

						<imprint>
							<publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
								Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
							<date>1962</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="speech"/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English </language>
				<language ident="greek">Greek </language>
				<language ident="latin">Latin </language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<!--
<change><date>March 1992</date><respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
</change>
<change><date>September 1992</date><respStmt><name>D. Smith</name><resp>(n/a)</resp></respStmt><item>fixed notes and regularized citations</item>
</change>
<change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
			<change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>

			<div n="hypothesis" type="section">
				<p>Astyphilus and the speaker of this oration were half-brothers, children of the
					same mother. On the death of Astyphilus a certain Cleon, his first cousin,
					produced a will, alleging that it had been made in favor of his own son. The
					brother of Astyphilius attacks the will as being a forgery. The discussion turns
					on a question of fact. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="1" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Astyphilus, the owner of the estate, was my
					half-brother, gentlemen, the son of my mother. He went abroad with the force
					which sailed to <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>, and died
					there. I shall try and prove to you what I stated in my affidavit, namely, that
					the deceased did not adopt a son, that he did not bequeath his property, that he
					left no will, and that no one except myself has a right to the estate of
					Astyphilus.</p>
			</div>
			<div n="2" type="section">
				<p>Cleon, my adversary, is first cousin to Astyphilus on his father's side, and his
					son, whom he pretends that Astyphilus adopted, is his first cousin once removed.
					Cleon's father, however, passed by adoption into another family, and they still
					belong to that family, so that in law they have no sort of relationship with
					Astyphilus. Seeing that they had no claim on these grounds, gentlemen, they
					concocted a will, which, as I think I shall be able to prove, is a forgery, and
					are trying to deprive me of my brother's estate. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="3" type="section">
				<p>So confident, indeed, has Cleon here always been, and still is, that no one but
					himself is to have the estate, that, as soon as the news of Astyphilus's death
					was reported—my father being ill at the time and I abroad on military service—he
					entered into possession of the landed estate and declared that anything else
					which Astyphilus left belonged to his own son, without ever giving you the
					opportunity to decide the matter. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="4" type="section">
				<p>When, however, my brother's remains were brought home, the person who claims to
					have been long ago adopted as his son did not lay them out or bury them, but
					Astyphilus's friends and companions-in-arms, seeing that my father was ill and I
					was abroad, themselves laid out the remains and carried out all the other
					customary rites, and conducted my father, ill though he was, to the tomb, well
					knowing the affection in which Astyphilus held him. I will produce before you
					the friends of the deceased, who were amongst those who were present, as
					witnesses of this.<quote type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="5" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>That Cleon did not bury Astyphilus, even he
					himself would not deny, and evidence of the fact has been given you. On my
					return home I found my opponents in enjoyment of the property of the deceased;
					[;I, therefore, sought out Cleon, who informed me that];<note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true">There is a lacuna in the text at this point. “Post <foreign
							xml:lang="greek">ta\ e)kei/nou</foreign> est lacuna. [; <foreign
							xml:lang="latin">Adii Cleonem, qui dixit]; suum filium ab Astyphilo
							adoptatum esse</foreign>” (Dobree,<title>Adversaria</title>, 1. p.
						305).</note> his son had been adopted by Astyphilus, and that the latter had
					left a will to this effect in the keeping of Hierocles of Iphistiadae.<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">A deme of the tribe Acamantis, situated on the
						left bank of the Cephissus.</note> On hearing this from him I proceeded to
					the house of Hierocles, knowing full well that he was on terms of the closest
					possible intimacy with Cleon, </p>
			</div>
			<div n="6" type="section">
				<p>though I never thought that he would dare to lie against the wishes of Astyphilus
					now that he was dead, especially as he was his uncle as well as mine.<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The sister of Hierocles was mother of Astyphilus
						and of the speaker, cf. <bibl n="Isaeus 9.23">Isaeus 9.23</bibl>, <bibl
							n="Isaeus 9.27">Isaeus 9.27</bibl>.</note> Nevertheless, gentlemen,
					regardless of these considerations, Hierocles in reply to my questions stated
					that the will was in his possession and said that he had received it from
					Astyphilus when he was on the point of sailing to <placeName
						key="perseus,Mytilene">Mytilene</placeName>. And to prove that he made these
					statements, please read this deposition.<quote type="Deposition"
							><title>Deposition</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="7" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Since, then, gentlemen, no one of my brother's
					relatives was present when he died and I was abroad when his remains were
					brought hither, I am obliged to use the actual statements of my adversaries to
					prove that the will is a forgery. It is only reasonable to suppose that
					Astyphilus did not merely feel a desire to adopt a son, but also provided that
					whatever dispositions he made should be as effectual as possible, and that,
					whomsoever he adopted, that person should both possess his estate and have
					access to his ancestral altars and perform all the customary rites for himself
					after his death and for his forefathers. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="8" type="section">
				<p>He would be assured that all these intentions would be best effected, not if he
					made his will without the attestation of any of his friends, but if he summoned
					first his kinsmen, then the members of his ward and deme, and finally as many as
					possible of his other acquaintances; for then anyone who might claim the estate
					either as next-of-kin or as legatee could be easily convicted of false
					pretences. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="9" type="section">
				<p>Astyphilus is shown to have taken none of these precautions, and not to have
					summoned any of the persons whom I have mentioned when he made the will which my
					opponents allege that he made—unless, indeed, anyone has been suborned by them
					to state that he was present. I will myself produce all these persons before you
					as witnesses.<quote type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="10" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Cleon will perhaps contend that you ought not to
					draw any conclusions from the evidence of these witnesses, because they merely
					depose that they have no knowledge of the making of this will by Astyphilus. But
					in my opinion, since the controversy is about a will and about the adoption of a
					son by Astyphilus, more weight should be attached by you to the evidence of the
					intimate friends of the deceased, when they declare that they were not present
					on so important an occasion, than to the evidence of those who have no
					connection with him, to the effect that they were present. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="11" type="section">
				<p>Moreover, Cleon himself, being apparently no fool, when Astyphilus was adopting
					his son and making the will, ought to have summoned any relatives whom he knew
					to be in the city and practically any other person with whom he knew Astyphilus
					to be intimate. For no one could have prevented Astyphilus from devising his
					property to whomsoever he wished; but the fact that the will was not made in
					secret, would have been strong evidence in Cleon's favor. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="12" type="section">
				<p>Furthermore, gentlemen, if Astyphilus wished that no one should know that he was
					adopting Cleon's son or that he had left a will, no one else's name ought to
					have been inscribed in the document as witness; but if it appears that he made a
					will in the presence of witnesses, and those witnesses were not taken from among
					those who were most intimate with him but were chance persons, is there any
					probability that the will is genuine? </p>
			</div>
			<div n="13" type="section">
				<p>For my part I cannot believe that anyone, when he was adopting a son, would have
					ventured to summon as witnesses any other persons except those with whom he was
					about to leave that son, to take his own place as an associate for the future in
					their religious and civic acts. Moreover, no one ought to be ashamed of
					summoning the largest possible number of witnesses to the execution of such a
					will, when there is a law which permits a man to bequeath his property to
					whomsoever he wishes. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="14" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now consider the matter, gentlemen, from the point
					of view of the date which my opponents assign to the will. They say that he made
					these dispositions when he was sailing for <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene"
						>Mytilene</placeName> on military service; it is clear then from their
					account that he knew beforehand all that fate had in store for him! For he
					served first at <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, then in
						<placeName key="tgn,7001399">Thessaly</placeName> and again throughout the
					Theban war,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See Introduction.</note> and
					wherever else he heard of an army being collected, he went abroad holding a
					command; yet never on his departure for any one of these campaigns did he leave
					a will behind him. The expedition to <placeName key="perseus,Mytilene"
						>Mytilene</placeName> was his last, for in it he perished. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="15" type="section">
				<p>Who among you can believe it possible that the decrees of fate should correspond
					so exactly with Astyphilus's conduct, that when he was preparing for other
					campaigns and was well aware that he was going to run risks on all of them, on
					no previous occasion did he make any disposition of his property, yet when he
					was about to set out on his last expedition, going out as a volunteer with every
					prospect of returning safe and sound from this campaign, on this occasion only
					did he make a will and then sail away and lose his life? How can you credit such
					a coincidence? </p>
			</div>
			<div n="16" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But besides this, judges, I will produce still
					stronger indications that there is no truth in what my opponents say. I will
					prove to you that Astyphilus had no such bitter enemy as Cleon, and hated him so
					much and with such good cause, that he would have been much more likely to have
					arranged that no one of his family should ever speak to Cleon than to have
					adopted his son. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="17" type="section">
				<p>For the death of Euthycrates, the father of Astyphilus, is said to have been
					caused by an assault made upon him by Thudippus, the father of Cleon here, in
					the course of a quarrel which arose between them over the division of their
					land, and he is said to have received such treatment that he fell ill as a
					result of the blows and died not many days later. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="18" type="section">
				<p>That this story is true, many of the Araphenians,<note resp="Loeb"
						anchored="true">Members of the deme of <placeName key="perseus,Araphen"
							>Araphen</placeName> in Eastern Attica, to which both the brothers
						belonged.</note> who were tilling their land at the time, would probably
					testify for me, but I could not find anyone to give positive evidence in so
					grave a matter. Hierocles, the man who alleges that the will was deposited in
					his custody, saw Euthycrates struck, but I am sure that he would not be willing
					to give evidence to the detriment of the will which he is himself producing. But
					for all that, summon Hierocles that he may give his evidence before the court or
					else swear to his ignorance of the fact.<quote type="Oath of Ignorance"
							><title>Oath of Ignorance</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="19" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I was quite sure he would say this; for it is
					quite in the same character for a man to swear that he is ignorant of facts
					which he really knows and to be willing to pledge his oath to the truth of what
					has never really happened. However, to prove that Euthycrates, the father of
					Astyphilus, on his death-bed charged his friends never to allow any of
					Thudippus's family to come near his tomb, I will produce as witness before you
					the husband of Astyphilus's aunt.<quote type="Evidence"
						><title>Evidence</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="20" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Astyphilus, then, hearing of this in childhood
					from his uncle and his other relatives, as soon as he reached the age of reason,
					would never speak to Cleon, and maintained this attitude up to his death,
					holding the opinion that it was impious to speak to the son of Thudippus, when
					the latter was charged with so grave a crime against his father. To prove that
					he remained throughout his life at variance with Cleon, I will produce as
					witnesses before you those who know the facts.<quote type="Witnesses"
							><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="21" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It would have been only natural, I suppose, for
					Astyphilus, whenever he was at home, to attend the sacrifices, at which all the
					Athenians entertain one another, accompanied by Cleon rather than by anyone
					else, since he was of the same deme and his cousin and, moreover, intended to
					adopt his son. The clerk shall, therefore, read you the deposition of the
					demesmen to prove that on no occasion was he accompanied by him.<quote
						type="Deposition"><title>Deposition</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="22" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Such then being the relations between Cleon and
					the deceased, he now demands that his son should inherit his property. Yet why
					should I speak of Cleon? It is rather Hierocles, the uncle of the deceased and
					of me, who has had the audacity to come here with a forged will and declare that
					Astyphilus left it in his keeping. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="23" type="section">
				<p>And yet, Hierocles, though you received many kindnesses from my father
					Theophrastus, when you were less prosperous than you are now, and from
					Astyphilus, you are paying to neither of them the return which is their due; for
					you are robbing me, the son of Theophrastus and your own nephew, of property
					which the laws awarded to me, and you are slandering the memory of the dead
					Astyphilus and doing your best to put his bitterest enemies in possession of his
					property. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="24" type="section">
				<p>Nay, before any formal claim was laid to the estate, Hierocles, well aware that
					the estate was coming by rights to me and to no one else, went round in turn to
					all the friends of the deceased, hawking his scheme and trying to persuade men
					who had no title to it to claim the estate, saying that he was Astyphilus's
					uncle and would show that he had left a will, if anyone would go shares with
					him; and now that he has made a bargain with Cleon and divided up my brother's
					property, he will demand to be believed on the ground that he is speaking the
					truth. He would, I believe, be delighted even to take an oath, if anyone were to
					propose it to him. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="25" type="section">
				<p>For me, though he is my kinsman, he refuses to testify even to events which have
					actually happened, but with my opponent, who is no relative of his, he
					co-operates in telling lies and has brought a document in his favor to prove
					events which have never occurred; for he considers that to make money is much
					more important than his kinship with me. To prove that he went round and
					promised to produce a will in favor of anyone who would share the estate with
					him, I will produce as witnesses the actual persons to whom he addressed
						himself.<quote type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="26" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>What name ought to be given, gentlemen, to this
					man, who is willing so lightly for his own profit to slander one who is dead?
					This evidence will furnish you with a strong presumption that he is not
					producing this will in favor of Cleon for nothing, but has received a
					recompense. Such, however, are the artifices which they are concerting against
					me; for each regards as clear gain anything that he can filch from the property
					of Astyphilus. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="27" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I have proved to you to the best of my ability
					that the will is not genuine, and that Cleon and Hierocles are seeking to
					mislead you; I will now proceed to show that, even if I had borne no
					relationship to Astyphilus, I have a better right to his property than my
					opponents. For when my father Theophrastus received my mother—who was also the
					mother of Astyphilus—in marriage from Hierocles, she brought with her
					Astyphilus, then a young child, and he lived continuously in our house, and was
					brought up by my father. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="28" type="section">
				<p>When I was born and was of an age to be instructed, I was educated with him.
					Please take this deposition, and after it that of the masters whose classes we
						attended.<quote type="Depositions"
						><title>Depositions</title></quote><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>My father,
					gentlemen, planted the paternal estate of Astyphilus and continued to cultivate
					it and doubled its value. Let the witnesses of this also, please, come up.<quote
						type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="29" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When my brother came of age, he received all his
					possessions in so correct and regular a manner that he never had any complaint
					to make against my father. After this my father gave Astyphilus's sister in
						marriage<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This duty would naturally fall to
						the brother when he came of age; but Astyphilus preferred that his
						stepfather should act for him.</note> to a man of his choice and managed
					everything else to Astyphilus's complete satisfaction; for the latter thought
					that he had received an ample proof from my father of his goodwill towards him,
					in the fact that he had been brought up by him from early childhood. Those who
					know the facts are my witnesses before you about his sister's betrothal.<quote
						type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="30" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>My father took Astyphilus with him when he was a
					child, as also he took me, to the religious ceremonies on every occasion; he
					also introduced him to the confraternity of Heracles in order that he might
					become a member of this association. The other members will themselves bear
					witness to this.<quote type="Witnesses"
						><title>Witnesses</title></quote><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Next
					consider, gentlemen, my own relations with my brother. In the first place, I was
					brought up with him from infancy; secondly, I never had a quarrel with him, but
					he had a great affection for me, as all the members of our family and our
					friends know. I should like them to come forward and testify to you.<quote
						type="Witnesses"><title>Witnesses</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="31" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Can you imagine, gentlemen, that Astyphilus,
					detesting Cleon so heartily and having experienced so many kindnesses at the
					hands of my father, would himself have adopted a son of one of his enemies or
					bequeathed his property to him, to the detriment of his benefactors and
					relatives? Personally, I regard it as impossible, even though Hierocles produces
					forged wills ten times over: no, I am convinced that, because I am his brother
					and we were bound together by every other tie, I have a much stronger claim than
					the son of Cleon; </p>
			</div>
			<div n="32" type="section">
				<p>for it was positively indecent in them to put forward pretensions to the estate
					of Astyphilus, when they were on the terms with him that I have described and
					never buried his remains, but entered into possession before performing the
					customary rites over him. Further, they intend now to demand the succession to
					Astyphilus's property not only because of the will which they allege to exist,
					but also by a comparison of their relationship and mine, on the ground that
					Cleon was a first cousin of the deceased on his father's side. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="33" type="section">
				<p>There is little likelihood, however, gentlemen, of your paying any attention to
					his claim of kinship; for no one, after passing by adoption into another family,
					has ever inherited from the family out of which he was adopted, unless he
					re-entered it in the proper legal manner.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There
						is obviously a lacuna in the text at this point, which must have contained a
						reference to the devices whereby Cleon attempted to obtain the recognition
						of his son by the member of Astyphilus's ward.</note><gap/>These men,<note
						resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., the fellow-wardsmen of Astyphilus.</note>
					however, well knowing that Astyphilus never adopted Cleon's son, though he has
					often presented himself, have never given him any share in the victims. Please
					take this deposition also.<quote type="Deposition"
						><title>Deposition</title></quote>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="34" type="section">
				<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I call upon you, therefore, to decide between us
					after considering our declarations under oath. Cleon declares that his son was
					adopted by Astyphilus and that the latter made dispositions to this effect; this
					I deny and declare that all Astyphilus's possessions belong to me, because I am
					his brother, as my opponents are themselves well aware. Do not, therefore,
					gentlemen, give Astyphilus an adopted son whom he himself never in his life
					adopted, but confirm in my favor the laws which you yourselves enacted; for it
					is in conformity with them that I make my claim, addressing to you a most pious
					prayer, that you should establish me as heir of my brother's property. </p>
			</div>
			<div n="35" type="section">
				<p>I have shown that he never devised his estate to anyone, and I have produced
					witnesses in support of all my statements. Assist me, therefore, and, if Cleon
					is a more clever speaker than I am, let not his talent avail him unsupported by
					law and justice, but constitute yourselves arbitrators on the whole case. You
					are gathered here that the impudent may gain no advantage and the weaker may
					venture to assert their righteous claims, knowing full well that you are intent
					upon justice and upon nothing else. Take, therefore, my part, all of you,
					gentlemen; </p>
			</div>
			<div n="36" type="section">
				<p>for if you allow yourselves, under the persuasion of Cleon, to give any other
					verdict, consider the responsibility which you will assume. First, you will send
					the bitterest enemies of Astyphilus to his tomb to celebrate the rites over him;
					secondly, you will make of none effect the injunctions of Euthycrates, the
					father of Astyphilus, which he himself never transgressed up to the end of his
					life; lastly, you will convict Astyphilus after his death of consummate folly.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div n="37" type="section">
				<p>For if he adopted this man as his son with whose father he was on terms of the
					bitterest enmity, will not those who hear of it imagine that he was mad or that
					his senses had been impaired by drugs? Further, judges, you will be allowing me,
					after having been brought up under the same roof and educated with Astyphilus,
					to be deprived of his estate by Cleon. I beg and beseech you by every means in
					my power to give your verdict in my favor; for then you would best gratify the
					wishes of Astyphilus and save me from injustice.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
