<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	  <teiHeader type="text">
		    <fileDesc>
			      <titleStmt>
				        <title>On Regimen in Acute Diseases</title>
				        <author>Hippocrates</author>
				        <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				        <funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			      </titleStmt>
			      <publicationStmt>
				        <publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				        <pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				        <date>February 20, 2003</date>
			      </publicationStmt>
			      <sourceDesc>
				        <biblStruct>
					          <monogr>
						            <title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						            <author>Hippocrates</author>
						            <editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						            <imprint>
							              <pubPlace>William Wood &amp; Company</pubPlace>
							              <publisher>Dover</publisher>
							              <date>1886</date>
						            </imprint>
					          </monogr>
				        </biblStruct>
			      </sourceDesc>
		    </fileDesc>
		    <encodingDesc>
         <refsDecl n="CTS">
            <cRefPattern n="section"
                         matchPattern="(\w+)"
                         replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
               <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
            </cRefPattern>
         </refsDecl>
      </encodingDesc>

		    <profileDesc>
			      <langUsage>
				        <language ident="eng">English</language>
			      </langUsage>
		    </profileDesc>
	  <revisionDesc>
<change when="2016-06-29" who="Thibault Clérice">Bumped URN</change>
<change when="2016-06-24" who="Thibault Clérice">Epidoc + CapiTainS</change>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
	  <text xml:lang="en">
		    <body>
         <div xml:lang="eng"
              type="translation"
              n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0627.tlg004.perseus-eng2">
			         <pb n="p.60"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 1</head>
				           <p>Those who composed what are called "The Cnidian Sentences"<note>The Cnidian
						Sentences in all probability were the results of the observations and
						theories made in the Temple of Health at Cnidos. We may reasonably conclude
						from what we know of them, that, like the Coacae Praenotiones at Cos, the
						Cnidian Sentences at Cnidos were looked up to in the time of Hippocrates as
						the great guides to medical practice. How much, then, it is to be regretted
						that they have not come down to us like the other! It is clear, however,
						from Galen's commentary, that the work was extant in his time, and from it,
						as will be seen, we are enabled to draw a few particulars respecting the
						theoretical and practical views of the Cnidians. Le Clerc considers it
						likely that Euryphon was the author of the Cnidian Sentences (Hist. Phys.,
						i., 3, 30); but it is evident, from the terms in which Hippocrates refers to
						them, that they were not the work of a single author. He makes mention, it
						will be remarked, of more than one person being concerned in remodelling
						them.</note> have described accurately what symptoms the sick experience in
					every disease, and how certain of them terminate; and in so far a man, even who
					is not a physician, might describe them correctly, provided he put the proper
					inquiries to the sick themselves what their complaints are. But those symptoms
					which the physician ought to know beforehand without being informed of them by
					the patient, are, for the most part, omitted, some in one case and some in
					others, and certain symptoms of vital importance for a conjectural
						judgment.<note>By this our author means that the Cnidians neglected
						Prorrhetics and prognostics. This must be obvious to every person who had
						entered properly into the spirit of the Hippocratic system of
						medicine.</note> But when, in addition to the diagnosis, they describe how
					each complaint should be treated, in these cases I entertain a still greater
					difference of opinion with them respecting the rules they have laid down; and
					not only do I not agree with them on this account, but also because the remedies
					they use are few in number; for, with the exception of acute diseases, the only
						medi-<pb n="p.61"/>cines which they give are drastic purgatives, with whey,
					and milk at certain times. If, indeed, these remedies had been good and suitable
					to the complaints in which they are recommended, they would have been still more
					deserving of recommendation, if, while few in number, they were sufficient; but
					this is by no means the case. Those, indeed, who have remodeled these
					"Sentences" have treated of the remedies applicable in each complaint more in a
					medical fashion. But neither have the ancients written anything worth regimen,
					although this be a great omission. Some of them, indeed, were not ignorant of
					the many varieties of each complaint, and their manifold divisions, but when
					they wish to tell clearly the numbers (species?) of each disease they do not
					write for their species would be almost innumerable if every symptom experienced
					by the patients were held to constitute a disease, and receive a different
					name.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 2</head>
				           <p>For my part, I approve of paying attention to everything relating to the art, and
					that those things which can be done well or properly should all be done
					properly; such as can be quickly done should be done quickly; such as can be
					neatly done should be done neatly; such operations as can be performed without
					pain should be done with the least possible pain; and that all other things of
					the like kind should be done better than they could be managed by the
					attendants. But I would more especially commend the physician who, in acute
					diseases, by which the bulk of mankind are cut off, conducts the treatment
					better than others. Acute diseases are those which the ancients named pleurisy,
					pneumonia, phrenitis, lethargy, causus, and the other diseases allied to these,
					including the continual fevers. For, unless when some general form of
					pestilential disease is epidemic, and diseases are sporadic and [not] of a
					similar character, there are more deaths from these diseases than from all the
					others taken together. The vulgar, indeed, do not recognize the difference
					between such physicians and their common attendants, and are rather disposed to
					commend and censure extraordinary remedies. This, then, is a great proof that
					the common people are most incompetent, of themselves, to form a judgment how
					such diseases should be treated: since persons who are not physicians pass for
						physicians<pb n="p.62"/> owing most especially to these diseases, for it is
					an easy matter to learn the names of those things which are applicable to
					persons laboring under such complaints. For, if one names the juice of ptisan,
					and such and such a wine, and hydromel, the vulgar fancy that he prescribes
					exactly the same things as the physicians do, both the good and the bad, but in
					these matters there is a great difference between them.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 3</head>
				           <p> But it appears to me that those things are more especially deserving of being
					consigned to writing which are undetermined by physicians, notwithstanding that
					they are of vital importance, and either do much good or much harm. By
					undetermined I mean such as these, wherefore certain physicians, during their
					whole lives, are constantly administering unstrained ptisans, and fancy they
					thus accomplish the cure properly, whereas others take great pains that the
					patient should not swallow a particle of the barley (thinking it would do much
					harm), but strain the juice through a cloth before giving it; others, again,
					will neither give thick ptisan nor the juice, some until the seventh day of the
					disease, and some until after the crisis. Physicians are not in the practice of
					mooting such questions; nor, perhaps, if mooted, would a solution of them be
					found; although the whole art is thereby exposed to much censure from the
					vulgar, who fancy that there really is no such science as medicine, since, in
					acute diseases, practitioners differ so much among themselves, that those things
					which one administers as thinking it the best that can be given, another holds
					to be bad; and, in this respect, they might say that the art of medicine
					resembles augury, since augurs hold that the same bird (omen) if seen on the
					left hand is good, but if on the right bad: and in divination by the inspection
					of entrails you will find similar differences; but certain diviners hold the
					very opposite of these opinions. I say, then, that this question is a most
					excellent one, and allied to very many others, some of the most vital importance
					in the Art, for that it can contribute much to the recovery of the sick, and to
					the preservation of health in the case of those who are well; and that it
					promotes the strength of those who use gymnastic exercises, and is useful to
					whatever one may wish to apply it.</p>
			         </div>
			         <pb n="p.63"/>
			         <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 4</head>
				           <p> Ptisan, then, appears to me to be justly preferred before all the other
					preparations from grain in these diseases, and I commend those who made this
						choice,<note>Our author now enters upon the consideration of one of his
						principal objects in the preent work, namely, to describe the modes of
						preparing ptisan (<hi rend="ital">or</hi>the decoction of barley), and its
						uses in acute diseases. He is so full on this subject that the present
						treatise is quoted by Athenaeus (Deipnos. ii., 16), by the name of the work
						On the Ptisan. Galen states that, on the principle that diseases are to be
						cured by their contraries, as the essence of a febrile disease is combined
						of heat and dryness, the indication of a cure is to use means of a cooling
						and moistening nature, and that the ptisan fulfils both these
						objects.</note> for the mucilage of it is smooth, consistent, pleasant,
					lubricant, moderately diluent, quenches thirst if this be required, and has no
					astringency; gives no trouble nor swells up in the bowels, for in the boiling it
					swells up as much as it naturally can. Those, then, who make use of ptisan in
					such diseases, should never for a day allow their vessels to be empty of it, if
					I may say so, but should use it and not intermit, unless it be necessary to stop
					for a time, in order to administer medicine or a clyster. And to those who are
					accustomed to take two meals in the day it is to be given twice, and to those
					accustomed to live upon a single meal it is to be given once at first, and then,
					if the case permit, it is to be increased and given twice to them, if they
					appear to stand in need of it. At first it will be proper not to give a large
					quantity nor very thick, but in proportion to the quantity of food which one has
					been accustomed to take, and so as that the veins may not be much emptied. And,
					with regard to the augmentation of the dose, if the disease be of a drier nature
					than one had supposed, one must not give more of it, but should give before the
					draught of ptisan, either hydromel or wine, in as great quantity as may be
					proper; and what is proper in each case will be afterward stated by us. But if
					the mouth and the passages from the lungs be in a proper state as to moisture,
					the quantity of the draught is to be increased, as a general rule, for an early
					and abundant state of moisture indicates an early crisis, but a late and
					deficient moisture indicates a slower crisis. And these things are as I have
					stated for the most part; but many other things are omitted which are important
					to the prognosis, as will be explained afterwards. And the more <pb n="p.64"/>
					that the patient is troubled with purging, in so much greater quantity is it to
					be given until the crisis, and moreover until two days beyond the crisis, in
					such cases as it appears to take place on the fifth, seventh, or ninth day, so
					as to have respect both for the odd and even day: after this the draught is to
					be given early in the day, and the other food in place is to be given in the
					evening. These things are proper, for the most part, to be given to those who,
					from the first, have used ptisan containing its whole substance; for the pains
					in pleuritic affections immediately cease of their own accord whenever the
					patients begin to expectorate anything worth mentioning, and the purgings become
					much better, and empyema much more seldom takes place, than if the patients used
					a different regimen, and the crises are more simple, occur earlier, and the
					cases are less subject to relapses.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 5</head>
				           <p> Ptisans are to be made of the very best barley, and are to be well boiled, more
					especially if you do not intend to use them strained. For, besides the other
					virtues of ptisan, its lubricant quality prevents the barley that is swallowed
					from proving injurious, for it does not stick nor remain in the region of the
					breast; for that which is well boiled is very lubricant, excellent for quenching
					thirst, of very easy digestion, and very weak, all which qualities are wanted.
					If, then, one do not pay proper attention to the mode of administering the
					ptisan, much harm may be done; for when the food is shut up in the bowels,
					unless one procure some evacuation speedily, before administering the draught,
					the pain, if present, will be exasperated; and, if not present, it will be
					immediately created, and the respiration will become more frequent, which does
					mischief, for it dries the lungs, fatigues the hypochondria, the hypogastrium,
					and diaphragm. And moreover if, while the pain of the side persists, and does
					not yield to warm fomentations, and the sputa are not brought up, but are viscid
					and unconcocted, unless one get the pain resolved, either by loosening the
					bowels, or opening a vein, whichever of these may be proper;- if to persons so
					circumstanced ptisan be administered, their speedy death will be the result. For
					these reasons, and for others of a similar kind still more, those who use
					unstrained ptisan die on the seventh day, or still earlier, some<pb n="p.65"/>
					being seized with delirium, and others dying suffocated with orthopnoee and
					riles. Such persons the ancients thought <hi rend="ital">struck</hi>, for this
					reason more especially, that when dead the affected side was livid, like that of
					a person who had been struck. The cause of this is that they die before the pain
					is resolved, being seized with difficulty of respiration, and by large and rapid
					breathing, as has been already explained, the spittle becoming thick, acid, and
					unconcocted, cannot be brought up, but, being retained in the bronchi of the
					lungs, produces riles; and, when it has come to this, death, for the most part,
					is inevitable; for the sputa being retained prevent the breath from being drawn
					in, and force it speedily out, and thus the two conspire together to aggravate
					the sputa being retained renders the respiration frequent, while the respiration
					being frequent thickens the sputa, and prevents them from being evacuated. These
					symptoms supervene, not only if ptisan be administered unseasonably, but still
					more if any other food or drink worse than ptisan be given.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 6</head>
				           <p> For the most part, then, the results are the same, whether the patient have used
					the unstrained ptisan or have used the juice alone; or even only drink; and
					sometimes it is necessary to proceed quite differently. In general, one should
					do thus: if fever commences shortly after taking food, and before the bowels
					have been evacuated, whether with or without pain, the physician ought to
					withhold the draught until he thinks that the food has descended to the lower
					part of the belly; and if any pain be present, the patient should use oxymel,
					hot if it is winter, and cold if it is summer; and, if there be much thirst, he
					should take hydromel and water. Then, if any pain be present, or any dangerous
					symptoms make their appearance, it will be proper to give the draught neither in
					large quantity nor thick, but after the seventh day, if the patient be strong.
					But if the earlier-taken food has not descended, in the case of a person who has
					recently swallowed food, and if he be strong and in the vigor of life, a clyster
					should be given, or if he be weaker, a suppository is to be administered, unless
					the bowels open properly of themselves. The time for administering the draught
					is to be particularly observed at the commencement and during the whole illness;
					when, then, the feet <pb n="p.66"/> are cold, one should refrain from giving the
					ptisan, and more especially abstain from drink; but when the heat has descended
					to the feet, one may then give it; and one should look upon this season as of
					great consequence in all diseases, and not least in acute diseases, especially
					those of a febrile character, and those of a very dangerous nature. One may
					first use the juice, and then the ptisan, attending accurately to the rules
					formerly laid down.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 7</head>
				           <p> When pain seizes the side, either at the commencement or at a later stage, it
					will not be improper to try to dissolve the pain by hot applications. Of hot
					applications the most powerful is hot water in a bottle, or bladder, or in a
					brazen vessel, or in an earthen one; but one must first apply something soft to
					the side, to prevent pain. A soft large sponge, squeezed out of hot water and
					applied, forms a good application; but it should be covered up above, for thus
					the heat will remain the longer, and at the same time the vapor will be
					prevented from being carried up to the patient's breath, unless when this is
					thought of use, for sometimes it is the case. And further, barley or tares may
					be infused and boiled in diluted vinegar, stronger than that it could be drunk,
					and may then be sewed into bladders and applied; and one may bran in like
					manner. Salts or toasted millet in woolen bags are excellent for forming a dry
					fomentation, for the millet is light and soothing. A soft fomentation like this
					soothes pains, even such as shoot to the clavicle. Venesection, however, does
					not alleviate the pain unless when it extends to the clavicle. But if the pain
					be not dissolved by the fomentations, one ought not to foment for a length of
					time, for this dries the lungs and promotes suppuration; but if the pain point
					to the clavicle, or if there be a heaviness in the arm, or about the breast, or
					above the diaphragm, one should open the inner vein at the elbow, and not
					hesitate to abstract a large quantity, until it become much redder, or instead
					of being pure red, it turns livid, for both these states occur. But if the pain
					be below the diaphragm, and do not point to the clavicle, we must open the belly
					either with black hellebore or peplium, mixing the black hellebore with carrot
					or seseli, or cumin, or anise, or any other of the fragrant herbs; and with the
					peplium the juice of sulphium (asafoetida), for these substances,<pb n="p.67"/>
					when mixed up together, are of a similar nature. The black hellebore acts more
					pleasantly and effectually than the peplium, while, on the other hand, the
					peplium expels wind much more effectually than the black hellebore, and both
					these stop the pain, and many other of the laxatives also stop it, but these two
					are the most efficacious that I am acquainted with. And the laxatives given in
					draughts are beneficial, when not very unpalatable owing to bitterness, or any
					other disagreeable taste, or from quantity, color, or any apprehension. When the
					patient has drunk the medicine, one ought to give him to swallow but little less
					of the ptisan than what he had been accustomed to; but it is according to rule
					not to give any draughts while the medicine is under operation; but when the
					purging is stopped then he should take a smaller draught than what he had been
					accustomed to, and afterwards go on increasing it progressively, until the pain
					cease, provided nothing else contra-indicate. This is my rule, also, if one
					would use the juice of ptisan (for I hold that it is better, on the whole, to
					begin with taking the decoction at once, rather than by first emptying the veins
					before doing so, or on the third, fourth, fifth, sixth, or seventh day, provided
					the disease has not previously come to a crisis in the course of this time), and
					similar preparations to those formerly described are to be made in those
					cases.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 8</head>
				           <p> Such are the opinions which I entertain respecting the administering of the
					ptisan; and, as regards drinks, whichsoever of those about to be described may
					be administered, the same directions are generally applicable. And here I know
					that physicians are in the practice of doing the very reverse of what is proper,
					for they all wish, at the commencement of diseases, to starve their patients for
					two, three, or more days, and then to administer the ptisans and drinks; and
					perhaps it appears to them reasonable that, as a great change has taken place in
					the body, it should be counteracted by another great change. Now, indeed, to
					produce a change is no small matter, but the change must be effected well and
					cautiously, and after the change the administration of food must be conducted
					still more so. Those persons, then, would be most injured if the change is not
					properly managed, who used <pb n="p.68"/> unstrained ptisans; they also would
					suffer who made use of the juice alone; and so also they would suffer who took
					merely drink, but these least of all.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 9</head>
				           <p> One may derive information from the regimen of persons in good health what
					things are proper; for if it appear that there is a great difference whether the
					diet be so and so, in other respects, but more especially in the changes, how
					can it be otherwise in diseases, and more especially in the most acute? But it
					is well ascertained that even a faulty diet of food and drink steadily
					persevered in, is safer in the main as regards health than if one suddenly
					change it to another. Wherefore, in the case of persons who take two meals in
					the day, or of those who take a single meal, sudden changes induce suffering and
					weakness; and thus persons who have not been accustomed to dine, if they shall
					take dinner, immediately become weak, have heaviness over their whole body, and
					become feeble and languid, and if, in addition, they take supper, they will have
					acid eructations, and some will have diarrhoea whose bowels were previously dry,
					and not having been accustomed to be twice swelled out with food and to digest
					it twice a day, have been loaded beyond their wont. It is beneficial, in such
					cases, to counterbalance this change, for one should sleep after dinner, as if
					passing the night, and guard against cold in winter and heat in summer; or, if
					the person cannot sleep, he may stroll about slowly, but without making stops,
					for a good while, take no supper, or, at all events, eat little, and only things
					that are not unwholesome, and still more avoid drink, and especially water. Such
					a person will suffer still more if he take three full meals in the day, and more
					still if he take more meals; and yet there are many persons who readily bear to
					take three full meals in the day, provided they are so accustomed. And,
					moreover, those who have been in the habit of eating twice a day, if they omit
					dinner, become feeble and powerless, averse to all work, and have heartburn;
					their bowels seem, as it were, to hang loose, their urine is hot and green, and
					the excrement is parched; in some the mouth is bitter, the eyes are hollow, the
					temples throb, and the extremities are cold, and the most of those who have thus
					missed their dinner cannot eat supper; or, if they do <pb n="p.69"/>sup, they
					load their stomach, and pass a much worse night than if they had previously
					taken dinner. Since, then, an unwonted change of diet for half a day produces
					such effects upon persons in health, it appears not to be a good thing either to
					add or take from. If, then, he who was restricted to a single meal, contrary to
					usage, having his veins thus left empty during a whole day, when he supped
					according to custom felt heavy, it is probable that if, because he was uneasy
					and weak from the want of dinner, he took a larger supper than wont, he would be
					still more oppressed; or if, wanting food for a still greater interval, he
					suddenly took a meal after supper, he will feel still greater oppression. He,
					then, who, contrary to usage, has had his veins kept empty by want of food, will
					find it beneficial to counteract the bad effects during that day as follows: let
					him avoid cold, heat, and exertion, for he could bear all these ill; let him
					make his supper considerably less than usual, and not of dry food, but rather
					liquid; and let him take some drink, not of a watery character, nor in smaller
					quantity than is proportionate to the food, and on the next day he should take a
					small dinner, so that, by degrees, he may return to his former practice. Persons
					who are bilious in the stomach bear these changes worst, while those who are
					pituitous, upon the whole, bear the want of food best, so that they suffer the
					least from being restricted to one meal in the day, contrary to usage. This,
					then, is a sufficient proof that the greatest changes as to those things which
					regard our constitutions and habits are most especially concerned in the
					production of diseases, for it is impossible to produce unseasonably a great
					emptying of the vessels by abstinence, or to administer food while diseases are
					at their acme, or when inflammation prevails; nor, on the whole, to make a great
					change either one way or another with impunity.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 10</head>
				           <p> One might mention many things akin to these respecting the stomach and bowels,
					to show how people readily bear such food as they are accustomed to, even if it
					is not naturally good, and drink in like manner, and how they bear unpleasantly
					such food as they are not accustomed to, even although not bad, and so in like
					manner with drink; and as to the effects of eating much flesh, contrary to
					usage, or garlic, or asafoetida, or the stem of the <pb n="p.70"/>plant which
					produces it, or things of a similar kind possessed of strong properties, one
					would be less surprised if such things produce pains in the bowels, but rather
					when one learned what trouble, swelling, flatulence, and tormina the cake (maza)
					will raise in the belly when eaten by a person not accustomed to it; and how
					much weight and distention of the bowels bread will create to a person
					accustomed to live upon the maza; and what thirst and sudden fullness will be
					occasioned by eating hot bread, owing to its desiccant and indigestible
					properties; and what different effects are produced by fine and coarse bread
					when eaten contrary to usage, or by the cake when usually dry, moist, or viscid;
					and what different effects polenta produces upon those who are accustomed and
					those who are unaccustomed to the use of it; or drinking of wine or drinking of
					water, when either custom is suddenly exchanged for the other; or when, contrary
					to usage, diluted wine or undiluted has been suddenly drunk, for the one will
					create water-brash in the upper part of the intestinal canal and flatulence in
					the lower, while the other will give rise to throbbing of the arteries,
					heaviness of the head, and thirst; and white and dark-colored wine, although
					both strong wines, if exchanged contrary to usage, will produce very different
					effects upon the body, so that one need the less wonder that a sweet and strong
					wine, if suddenly exchanged, should have by no means the same effect.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 11</head>
				           <p> Let us here briefly advert to what may be said on the opposite side; namely,
					that a change of diet has occurred in these cases, without any change in their
					body, either as to strength, so as to require an increase of food, or as to
					weakness, so as to require a diminution. But the strength of the patient is to
					be taken into consideration, and the manner of the disease, and of the
					constitution of the man, and the habitual regimen of the patient, not only as
					regards food but also drink. Yet one must much less resort to augmentation,
					since it is often beneficial to have recourse to abstraction, when the patient
					can bear it, until the disease having reached its acme and has become concocted.
					But in what cases this must be done will be afterwards described. One might
					write many other things akin to those which have been <pb n="p.71"/> now said,
					but there is a better proof, for it is not akin to the matter on which my
					discourse has principally turned, but the subject-matter itself is a most
					seasonable proof. For some at the commencement of acute diseases have taken food
					on the same day, some on the next day; some have swallowed whatever has come in
					their way, and some have taken <hi rend="ital">cyceon</hi>.<note>The <hi rend="ital">cyceon</hi>was a mixture of various articles of food, but
						generally contained cheese, honey, and wine. See Athenaeus (Deipnos, ii.).
						It is described by Homer as the potion which Circe administered to the
						followers of Ulysses. (Odyss. x., 235). There is freqent mention of it in
						the Hippocratic treatises, as at De Diaeta, ii.; de Muliebribus, ii.; and in
						the works of the other medical authors.</note> Now all these things are
					worse than if one had observed a different regimen; and yet these mistakes,
					committed at that time, do much less injury than if one were to abstain entirely
					from food for the first two or three days, and on the fourth or fifth day were
					to take such food; and it would be still worse, if one were to observe total
					abstinence for all these days, and on the following days were to take such a
					diet, before the disease is concocted;<note>The meaning here is somewhat
						obscure, but appears to be this: that if a patient fast for the first two or
						three days, and take food of a heavy nature on the fourth or fifth, he will
						be much injured, but that the mistake will be still more fatal if the fast
						be continued for the first four or five days, and if he then indulge freely
						in food at the end of these.</note> for in this way death would be the
					consequence to most people, unless the disease were of a very mild nature. But
					the mistakes committed at first were not so irremediable as these, but could be
					much more easily repaired. This, therefore, I think a strong proof that such or
					such a draught need not be prescribed on the first days to those who will use
					the same draughts afterwards. At the bottom, therefore, they do not know,
					neither those using unstrained ptisans, that they are hurt by them, when they
					begin to swallow them, if they abstain entirely from food for two, three, or
					more days; nor do those using the juice know that they are injured in swallowing
					them, when they do not commence with the draught seasonably. But this they guard
					against, and know that it does much mischief, if, before the disease be
					concocted, the patient swallow unstrained ptisan, when accustomed to use
					strained. All these things are strong proofs that physicians do not conduct the
					regimen of patients properly, but that in those diseases in<pb n="p.72"/> which
					total abstinence from food should not be enforced on patients that will be put
					on the use of ptisans, they do enforce total abstinence; that in those cases in
					which there should be no change made from total abstinence to ptisans, they do
					make the change; and that, for the most part, they change from abstinence to
					ptisans, exactly at the time when it is often beneficial to proceed from ptisans
					almost to total abstinence, if the disease happen to be in the state of
					exacerbation. And sometimes crude matters are attracted from the head, and
					bilious from the region near the chest, and the patients are attacked with
					insomnolency, so that the disease is not concocted; they become sorrowful,
					peevish, and delirious; there are flashes of light in their eyes, and noises in
					their ears; their extremities are cold, their urine unconcocted; the sputa thin,
					saltish, tinged with an intense color and smell; sweats about the neck, and
					anxiety; respiration, interrupted in the expulsion of the air, frequent and very
					large; expression of the eyelids dreadful; dangerous <hi rend="ital">deliquia</hi>; tossing of the bed-clothes from the breast; the hands
					trembling, and sometimes the lower lip agitated. These symptoms, appearing at
					the commencement, are indicative of strong delirium, and patients so affected
					generally die, or if they escape, it is with a deposit, hemorrhage from the
					nose, or the expectoration of thick matter, and not otherwise. Neither do I
					perceive that physicians are skilled in such things as these; how they ought to
					know such diseases as are connected with debility, and which are further
					weakened by abstinence from food, and those aggravated by some other irritation;
					those by pain, and from the acute nature of the disease, and what affections and
					various forms thereof our constitution and habit engender, although the
					knowledge or ignorance of such things brings safety or death to the patient. For
					it is a great mischief if to a patient debilitated by pain, and the acute nature
					of the disease, one administer drink, or more ptisan, or food, supposing that
					the debility proceeds from inanition. It is also disgraceful not to recognize a
					patient whose debility is connected with inanition, and to pinch him in his
					diet; this mistake, indeed, is attended with some danger, but much less than the
					other, and yet it is likely to expose one to much greater derision, for if
					another physician, or a private<pb n="p.73"/> person, coming in and knowing what
					has happened, should give to eat or drink those things which the other had
					forbidden, the benefit thus done to the patient would be manifest. Such mistakes
					of practitioners are particularly ridiculed by mankind, for the physician or
					nonprofessional man thus coming in, seems as it were to resuscitate the dead. On
					this subject I will describe elsewhere the symptoms by which each of them may be
					recognized.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 12</head>
				           <p> And the following observations are similar to those now made respecting the
					bowels. If the whole body rest long, contrary to usage, it does not immediately
					recover its strength; but if, after a protracted repose, it proceed to labor, it
					will clearly expose its weakness. So it is with every one part of the body, for
					the feet will make a similar display, and any other of the joints, if, being
					unaccustomed to labor, they be suddenly brought into action, after a time. The
					teeth and the eyes will suffer in like manner, and also every other part
					whatever. A couch, also, that is either softer or harder than one has been
					accustomed to will create uneasiness, and sleeping in the open air, contrary to
					usage, hardens the body. But it is sufficient merely to state examples of all
					these cases. If a person having received a wound in the leg, neither very
					serious nor very trifling, and he being neither in a condition very favorable to
					its healing nor the contrary, at first betakes himself to bed, in order to
					promote the cure, and never raises his leg, it will thus be much less disposed
					to inflammation, and be much sooner well, than it would have been if he had
					strolled about during the process of healing; but if upon the fifth or sixth
					day, or even earlier, he should get up and attempt to walk, he will suffer much
					more then than if he had walked about from the commencement of the cure, and if
					he should suddenly make many laborious exertions, he will suffer much more than
					if, when the treatment was conducted otherwise, he had made the same exertions
					on the same days. In fine, all these things concur in proving that all great
					changes, either one way or another, are hurtful. Wherefore much mischief takes
					place in the bowels, if from a state of great inanition more food than is
					moderate be administered (and also in the rest of the body,<pb n="p.74"/> if
					from a state of great rest it be hastily brought to greater exertion, it will be
					much more injured), or if from the use of much food it be changed to complete
					abstinence, and therefore the body in such cases requires protracted repose, and
					if, from a state of laborious exertion, the body suddenly falls into a state of
					ease and indolence, in these cases also the bowels would require continued
					repose from abundance of food, for otherwise it will induce pain and heaviness
					in the whole body.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 13</head>
				           <p> The greater part of my discourse has related to changes, this way or that. For
					all purposes it is profitable to know these things, and more especially
					respecting the subject under consideration,- that in acute diseases, in which a
					change is made to ptisans from a state of inanition, it should be made as I
					direct; and then that ptisans should not be used until the disease be concocted,
					or some other symptom, whether of evacuation or of irritation, appear in the
					intestines, or in the hypochondria, such as will be described. Obstinate
					insomnolency impairs the digestion of the food and drink, and in other respects
					changes and relaxes the body, and occasions a heated state, and heaviness of the
						head.<note>Galen finds the language in this last sentence so confused, that
						he does not hesitate to declare that he is convinced the work must have been
						left by Hippocrates in an unfinished state, and not published until after
						his death.</note>
               </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 14</head>
				           <p> One must determine by such marks as these, when sweet, strong, and dark wine,
					hydromel, water and oxymel, should be given in acute diseases. Wherefore the
					sweet affects the head less than the strong, attacks the brain less, evacuates
					the bowels more than the other, but induces swelling of the spleen and liver; it
					does not agree with bilious persons, for it causes them to thirst; it creates
					flatulence in the upper part of the intestinal canal, but does not disagree with
					the lower part, as far as regards flatulence; and yet flatulence engendered by
					sweet wine is not of a transient nature, but rests for a long time in the
					hypochondria. And therefore it in general is less diuretic than wine which is
					strong and thin; but sweet wine is more expectorant than the other. But when it
					creates thirst, it is less expectorant in such cases than the other wine, but if
					it do not create thirst, it promotes expecto-<pb n="p.75"/>ration better than
					the other. The good and bad effects of a white, strong wine, have been already
					frequently and fully stated in the disquisition on sweet wine; it is determined
					to the bladder more than the other, is diuretic and laxative, and should be very
					useful in such complaints; for if in other respects it be less suitable than the
					other, the clearing out of the bladder effected by it is beneficial to the
					patient, if properly administered. There are excellent examples of the
					beneficial and injurious effects of wine, all which were left undetermined by my
					predecessors. In these diseases you may use a yellow wine, and a dark austere
					wine for the following purposes: if there be no heaviness of the head, nor
					delirium, nor stoppage of the expectoration, nor retention of the urine, and if
					the alvine discharges be more loose and like scrapings than usual, in such cases
					a change from a white wine to such as I have mentioned, might be very proper. It
					deserves further to be known, that it will prove less injurious to all the parts
					above, and to the bladder, if it be of a more watery nature, but that the
					stronger it is, it will be the more beneficial to the bowels.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 15</head>
				           <p> Hydromel, when drunk in any stage of acute disease, is less suitable to persons
					of a bilious temperament, and to those who have enlarged viscera, than to those
					of a different character; it increases thirst less than sweet wine; it softens
					the lungs, is moderately expectorant, and alleviates a cough; for it has some
					detergent quality in it, whence it lubricates the sputum. Hydromel is also
					moderately diuretic, unless prevented by the state of any of the viscera. And it
					also occasions bilious discharges downwards, sometimes of a proper character,
					and sometimes more intense and frothy than is suitable; but such rather occurs
					in persons who are bilious, and have enlarged viscera. Hydromel rather produces
					expectoration, and softening of the lungs, when given diluted with water. But
					unmixed hydromel, rather than the diluted, produces frothy evacuations, such as
					are unseasonably and intensely bilious, and too hot; but such an evacuation
					occasions other great mischiefs, for it neither extinguishes the heat in the
					hypochondria, but rouses it, induces inquietude, and jactitation of the limbs,
					and ulcerates the intestines and anus. The remedies for all these will be
					described afterwards. <pb n="p.76"/>By using hydromel without ptisans, instead
					of any other drink, you will generally succeed in the treatment of such
					diseases, and fail in few cases; but in what instances it is to be given, and in
					what it is not to be given, and wherefore it is not to be given,- all this has
					been explained already, for the most part. Hydromel is generally condemned, as
					if it weakened the powers of those who drink it, and on that account it is
					supposed to accelerate death; and this opinion arose from persons who starve
					themselves to death, some of whom use hydromel alone for drink, as fancying that
					it really has this effect. But this is by no means always the case. For
					hydromel, if drunk alone, is much stronger than water, if it do not disorder the
					bowels; but in some respects it is stronger, and in some weaker, than wine that
					is thin, weak, and devoid of <hi rend="ital">bouquet</hi>. There is a great
					difference between unmixed wine and unmixed honey, as to their nutritive powers,
					for if a man will drink double the quantity of pure wine, to a certain quantity
					of honey which is swallowed, he will find himself much stronger from the honey,
					provided it do not disagree with his bowels, and that his alvine evacuations
					from it will be much more copious. But if he shall use ptisan for a draught, and
					drink afterward hydromel, he will feel full, flatulent, and uncomfortable in the
					viscera of the hypochondrium; but if the hydromel be taken before the draught,
					it will not have the same injurious effects as if taken after it, but will be
					rather beneficial. And boiled hydromel has a much more elegant appearance than
					the unboiled, being clear, thin, white, and transparent, but I am unable to
					mention any good quality which it possesses that the other wants. For it is not
					sweeter than the unboiled, provided the honey be fine, and it is weaker, and
					occasions less copious evacuations of the bowels, neither of which effects is
					required from the hydromel. But one should by all means use it boiled, provided
					the honey be bad, impure, black, and not fragrant, for the boiling will remove
					the most of its bad qualities and appearances.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 16</head>
				           <p> You will find the drink, called oxymel, often very useful in these complaints,
					for it promotes expectoration and freedom of breathing. the following are the
					proper occasions for administering it. When strongly acid it has no mean
					operation in<pb n="p.77"/> rendering the expectoration more easy, for by
					bringing up the sputa, which occasion troublesome hawking, and rendering them
					more slippery, and, as it were, clearing the windpipe with a feather, it
					relieves the lungs and proves emollient to them; and when it succeeds in
					producing these effects it must do much good. But there are cases in which
					hydromel, strongly acid, does not promote expectoration, but renders it more
					viscid and thus does harm, and it is most apt to produce these bad effects in
					cases which are otherwise of a fatal character, when the patient is unable to
					cough or bring up the sputa. On this account, then, one ought to consider
					beforehand the strength of the patient, and if there be any hope, then one may
					give it, but if given at all in such cases it should be quite tepid, and in by
					no means large doses. But if slightly acrid it moistens the mouth and throat,
					promotes expectoration, and quenches thirst; agrees with the viscera seated in
					the hypochondrium, and obviates the bad effects of the honey; for the bilious
					quality of the honey is thereby corrected. It also promotes flatulent discharges
					from the bowels, and is diuretic, but it occasions watery discharges and those
					resembling scrapings, from the lower part of the intestine, which is sometimes a
					bad thing in acute diseases, more especially when the flatulence cannot be
					passed, but rolls backwards; and otherwise it diminishes the strength and makes
					the extremities cold, this is the only bad effect worth mentioning which I have
					known to arise from the oxymel. It may suit well to drink a little of this at
					night before the draught of ptisan, and when a considerable interval of time has
					passed after the draught there will be nothing to prevent its being taken. But
					to those who are restricted entirely to drinks without draughts of ptisan, it
					will therefore not be proper at all times to give it, more especially from the
					fretting and irritation of the intestine which it occasions, (and these bad
					effects it will be the more apt to produce provided there be no faeces in the
					intestines and the patient is laboring under inanition,) and then it will weaken
					the powers of the hydromel. But if it appears advantageous to use a great deal
					of this drink during the whole course of the disease, one should add to it
					merely as much vinegar as can just be perceived by the taste, for thus what
						is<pb n="p.78"/> prejudicial in it will do the least possible harm, and what
					is beneficial will do the more good. In a word, the acidity of vinegar agrees
					rather with those who are troubled with bitter bile, than with those patients
					whose bile is black; for the bitter principle is dissolved in it and turned to
					phlegm, by being suspended in it; whereas black bile is fermented, swells up,
					and is multiplied thereby: for vinegar is a melanogogue. Vinegar is more
					prejudicial to women than to men, for it creates pains in the uterus.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 17</head>
				           <p> I have nothing further to add as to the effects of water when used as a drink in
					acute diseases; for it neither soothes the cough in pneumonia, nor promotes
					expectoration, but does less than the others in this respect, if used alone
					through the whole complaint. But if taken intermediate between oxymel and
					hydromel, in small quantity, it promotes expectoration from the change which it
					occasions in the qualities of these drinks, for it produces, as it were, a
					certain overflow. Otherwise it does not quench the thirst, for it creates bile
					in a bilious temperament, and is injurious to the hypochondrium; and it does the
					most harm, engenders most bile, and does the least good when the bowels are
					empty; and it increases the swelling of the spleen and liver when they are in an
					inflamed state; it produces a gurgling noise in the intestines and swims on the
					stomach; for it passes slowly downwards, as being of a coldish and indigestible
					nature, and neither proves laxative nor diuretic; and in this respect, too, it
					proves prejudicial, that it does not naturally form does in the intestines: and,
					if it be drunk while the feet are cold, its injurious effects will be greatly
					aggravated, in all those parts to which it may be determined. When you suspect
					in these diseases either strong heaviness of the head, or mental alienation, you
					must abstain entirely from wine, and in this case use water, or give weak,
					straw-colored wine, entirely devoid of <hi rend="ital">bouquet</hi>, after which
					a little water is to be given in addition; for thus the strength of the will
					less affect the head and the understanding: but in which cases water is mostly
					to be given for drink, when in large quantity, when in moderate, when cold, and
					when hot; all these things have either been discussed already or will be treated
					of at the proper time. In like manner, with respect to all the others, such as
					barley-water, the<pb n="p.79"/> drinks made from green shoots, those from
					raisins, and the skins of grapes and wheat, and bastard saffron, and myrtles,
					pomegranates, and the others, when the proper time for using them is come, they
					will be treated of along with the disease in question, in like manner as the
					other compound medicines.</p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="section">
				           <head>PART 18</head>
				           <p> The bath is useful in many diseases, in some of them when used steadily, and in
					others when not so. Sometimes it must be less used than it would be otherwise,
					from the want of accommodation; for in few families are all the conveniences
					prepared, and persons who can manage them as they ought to be. And if the
					patient be not bathed properly, he maybe thereby hurt in no inconsiderable
					degree, for there is required a place to cover him that is free of smoke,
					abundance of water, materials for frequent baths, but not very large, unless
					this should be required. It is better that no friction should be applied, but if
					so, a hot soap (<hi rend="ital">smegma</hi>) must be used in greater abundance
					than is common, and an affusion of a considerable quantity of water is to be
					made at the same time and afterwards repeated. There must also be a short
					passage to the basin, and it should be of easy ingress and egress. But the
					person who takes the bath should be orderly and reserved in his manner, should
					do nothing for himself, but others should pour the water upon him and rub him,
					and plenty of waters, of various temperatures, should be in readiness for the
						<hi rend="ital">douche</hi>, and the affusions quickly made; and sponges
					should be used instead of the comb (<hi rend="ital">strigil</hi>), and the body
					should be anointed when not quite dry. But the head should be rubbed by the
					sponge until it is quite dry; the extremities should be protected from cold, as
					also the head and the rest of the body; and a man should not be washed
					immediately after he has taken a draught of ptisan or a drink; neither should he
					take ptisan as a drink immediately after the bath. Much will depend upon whether
					the patient, when in good health, was very fond of the bath, and in the custom
					of taking it: for such persons, especially, feel the want of it, and are
					benefited if they are bathed, and injured if they are not. In general it suits
					better with cases of pneumonia than in ardent fevers; for the bath soothes the
					pain in the side, chest, and back; concocts the sputa, promotes expectoration,
						<pb n="p.80"/>improves the respiration, and allays lassitude; for it soothes
					the joints and outer skin, and is diuretic, removes heaviness of the head, and
					moistens the nose. Such are the benefits to be derived from the bath, if all the
					proper requisites be present; but if one or more of these be wanting, the bath,
					instead of doing good, may rather prove injurious; for every one of them may do
					harm if not prepared by the attendants in the proper manner. It is by no means a
					suitable thing in these diseases to persons whose bowels are too loose, or when
					they are unusually confined, and there has been no previous evacuation; neither
					must we bathe those who are debilitated, nor such as have nausea or vomiting, or
					bilious eructations; nor such as have hemorrhage from the nose, unless it be
					less than required at that stage of the disease (with those stages you are
					acquainted), but if the discharge be less than proper, one should use the bath,
					whether in order to benefit the whole body or the head alone. If then the proper
					requisites be at hand, and the patient be well disposed to the bath, it may be
					administered once every day, or if the patient be fond of the bath there will be
					no harm, though he should take it twice in the day. The use of the bath is much
					more appropriate to those who take unstrained ptisan, than to those who take
					only the juice of it, although even in their case it may be proper; but least of
					all does it suit with those who use only plain drink, although, in their case
					too it may be suitable; but one must form a judgment from the rules laid down
					before, in which of these modes of regimen the bath will be beneficial, and in
					which not. Such as want some of the requisites for a proper bath, but have those
					symptoms which would be benefited by it, should be bathed; whereas those who
					want none of the proper requisites, but have certain symptoms which
					contraindicate the bath, are not to be bathed. </p>
			         </div>
			         <div type="textpart" n="appendix" subtype="section">
				           <head>APPENDIX </head>
				           <div type="textpart" n="1" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 1</head>
					             <p>Ardent fever (causus) takes place when the veins, being dried up in the
						summer season, attract acrid and bilious humors to themselves; and strong
						fever seizes the whole body, which experiences aches of the bones, and is in
						a state of lassitude and<pb n="p.81"/> pain. It takes place most commonly
						from a long walk and protracted thirst, when the veins being dried up
						attract acrid and hot defluxions to themselves. The tongue becomes rough,
						dry, and very black; there are gnawing pains about the bowels; the alvine
						discharges are watery and yellow; there is intense thirst, insomnolency, and
						sometimes wandering of the mind. To a person in such a state give to drink
						water and as much boiled hydromel of a watery consistence as he will take;
						and if the mouth be bitter, it may be advantageous to administer an emetic
						and clyster; and if these things do not loosen the bowels, purge with the
						boiled milk of asses. Give nothing saltish nor acrid, for they will not be
						borne; and give no draughts of ptisan until the crisis be past. And the
						affection is resolved if there be an epistaxis, or if true critical sweats
						supervene with urine having white, thick, and smooth sediments, or if a
						deposit take place anywhere; but if it be resolved without these, there will
						be a relapse of the complaint, or pain in the hips and legs will ensue, with
						thick sputa, provided the patient be convalescent. Another species of ardent
						fever: belly loose, much thirst, tongue rough, dry, and saltish, retention
						of urine, insomnolency, extremities cold. In such a case, unless there be a
						flow of blood from the nose, or an abscess form about the neck, or pain in
						the limbs, or the patient expectorate thick sputa (these occur when the
						belly is constipated), or pain of the hips, or lividity of the genital
						organs, there is no crisis; tension of the testicle is also a critical
						symptom. Give attractive draughts.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="2" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 2</head>
					             <p>Bleed in the acute affections, if the disease appear strong, and the patients
						be in the vigor of life, and if they have strength. If it be quinsy or any
						other of the pleuritic affections, purge with electuaries; but if the
						patient be weaker, or if you abstract more blood, you may administer a
						clyster every third day, until he be out of danger, and enjoin total
						abstinence if necessary.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="3" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 3</head>
					             <p>Hypochondria inflamed not from retention of flatus, tension of the diaphragm,
						checked respiration, with dry orthopnoea, when no pus is formed, but when
						these complaints are connected with obstructed respiration; but more
						especially strong pains of the liver, heaviness of the spleen, and other
						phlegmasiae and in-<pb n="p.82"/>tense pains above the diaphragm, diseases
						connected with collections of humors,- all these diseases do not admit of
						resolution, if treated at first by medicine, but venesection holds the first
						place in conducting the treatment; then we may have recourse to a clyster,
						unless the disease be great and strong; but if so, purging also may be
						necessary; but bleeding and purging together require caution and moderation.
						Those who attempt to resolve inflammatory diseases at the commencement by
						the administration of purgative medicines, remove none of the morbific
						humors which produce the inflammation and tension; for the diseases while
						unconcocted could not yield, but they melt down those parts which are
						healthy and resist the disease; so when the body is debilitated the malady
						obtains the mastery; and when the disease has the upper hand of the body, it
						does not admit of a cure.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="4" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 4</head>
					             <p> When a person suddenly loses his speech, in connection with obstruction of
						the veins,- if this happen without warning or any other strong cause, one
						ought to open the internal vein of the right arm, and abstract blood more or
						less according to the habit and age of the patient. Such cases are mostly
						attended with the following symptoms: redness of the face, eyes fixed, hands
						distended, grinding of the teeth, palpitations, jaws fixed, coldness of the
						extremities, retention of airs in the veins.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="5" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 5</head>
					             <p> When pains precede, and there are influxes of black bile and of acrid
						humors, and when by their pungency the internal parts are pained, and the
						veins being pinched and dried become distended, and getting inflamed attract
						the humors running into the parts, whence the blood being vitiated, and the
						airs collected there not being able to find their natural passages, coldness
						comes on in consequence of this stasis, with vertigo, loss of speech,
						heaviness of the head, and convulsion, if the disease fix on the liver, the
						heart, or the great vein (vena cava?); whence they are seized with epilepsy
						or apoplexy, if the defluxions fall upon the containing parts, and if they
						are dried up by airs which cannot make their escape; such persons having
						been first tormented are to be immediately bled at the commencement, while
						all the peccant vapors and humors are buoyant, for then the cases more
						easily admit of a cure; and then supporting the strength and<pb n="p.83"/>
						attending to the crisis, we may give emetics, unless the disease be
						alleviated; or if the bowels be not moved, we may administer a clyster and
						give the boiled milk of asses, to the amount of not less than twelve
						heminae, or if the strength permit, to more than sixteen.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="6" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 6</head>
					             <p> Quinsy takes place when a copious and viscid defluxion from the head, in the
						season of winter or spring, flows into the jugular veins, and when from
						their large size they attract a greater defluxion; and when owing to the
						defluxion being of a cold and viscid nature it becomes enfarcted,
						obstructing the passages of the respiration and of the blood, coagulates the
						surrounding blood, and renders it motionless and stationary, it being
						naturally cold and disposed to obstructions. Hence they are seized with
						convulsive suffocation, the tongue turning livid, assuming a rounded shape,
						and being vent owing to the veins which are seated below the tongue (for
						when an enlarged uvula, which is called <hi rend="ital">uva</hi>, is cut, a
						large vein may be observed on each side). These veins, then, becoming
						filled, and their roots extending into the tongue, which is of a loose and
						spongy texture, it, owing to its dryness receiving forcibly the juice from
						the veins, changes from broad and becomes round, its natural color turns to
						livid, from a soft consistence it grows hard, instead of being flexible it
						becomes inflexible, so that the patient would soon be suffocated unless
						speedily relieved. Bleeding, then, in the arm, and opening the sublingual
						veins, and purging with the electuaries, and giving warm gargles, and
						shaving the head, we must apply to it and the neck a cerate, and wrap them
						round with wool, and foment with soft sponges squeezed out of hot water;
						give to drink water and hydromel, not cold; and administer the juice of
						ptisan when, having passed the crisis, the patient is out of danger. When,
						in the season of summer or autumn, there is a hot and nitrous defluxion from
						the head (it is rendered hot and acrid by the season), being of such a
						nature it corrodes and ulcerates, and fills with air, and orthopnoea
						attended with great dryness supervenes; the fauces, when examined, do not
						seem swollen; the tendons on the back part of the neck are contracted, and
						have the appearance as if it were tetanus; the voice is lost, the breathing
						is small, and<pb n="p.84"/> inspiration becomes frequent and laborious. In
						such persons the trachea becomes ulcerated, and the lungs engorged, from the
						patient's not being able to draw in the external air. In such cases, unless
						there be a spontaneous determination to the external parts of the neck, the
						symptoms become still more dreadful, and the danger more imminent, partly
						owing to the season, and the hot and acrid humors which cause the
						disease.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="7" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 7</head>
					             <p> When fever seizes a person who has lately taken food, and whose bowels are
						loaded with faeces which have been long retained, whether it be attended
						with pain of the side or not, he ought to lie quiet until the food descend
						to the lower region of the bowels, and use oxymel for drink; but when the
						load descends to the loins, a clyster should be administered, or he should
						be purged by medicine; and when purged, he should take ptisan for food and
						hydromel for drink; then he may take the cerealia, and boiled fishes, and a
						watery wine in small quantity, at night, but during the day, a watery
						hydromel. When the flatus is offensive, either a suppository or clyster is
						to be administered; but otherwise the oxymel is to be discontinued, until
						the matters descend to the lower part of the bowels, and then they are to be
						evacuated by a clyster. But if the ardent fever (causus) supervene when the
						bowels are empty, should you still judge it proper to administer purgative
						medicine, it ought not be done during the first three days, nor earlier than
						the fourth. When you give the medicine, use the ptisan, observing the
						paroxysms of the fevers, so as not to give it when the fever is setting in,
						but when it is ceasing, or on the decline, and as far as possible from the
						commencement. When the feet are cold, give neither drink nor ptisan, nor
						anything else of the kind, but reckon it an important rule to refrain until
						they become warm, and then you may administer them with advantage. For the
						most part, coldness of the feet is a symptom of a paroxysm of the fever
						coming on; and if at such a season you apply those things, you will commit
						the greatest possible mistake, for you will augment the disease in no small
						degree. But when the fever ceases, the feet, on the contrary, become hotter
						than the rest of the body; for when the heat leaves the feet, it is kindled
						up in the breast, and sends its flame up to the head. And when<pb n="p.85"/>
						all the heat rushes upwards, and is exhaled at the head, it is not to be
						wondered at that the feet become cold, being devoid of flesh, and tendinous;
						and besides, they contract cold, owing to their distance from the hotter
						parts of the body, an accumulation of heat having taken place in the chest:
						and again, in like manner, when the fever is resolved and dissipated, the
						heat descends to the feet, and, at the same time, the head and chest become
						cold. Wherefore one should attend to this; that when the feet are cold, the
						bowels are necessarily hot, and filled with nauseous matters; the
						hypochondrium distended: there is jactitation of the body, owing to the
						internal disturbance; and aberration of the intellect, and pains; the
						patient is agitated, and wishes to vomit, and if he vomits bad matters he is
						pained; but when the heat descends to the feet, and the urine passes freely,
						he is every way lightened, even although he does not sweat; at this season,
						then, the ptisan ought to be given; it would be death to give it before.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="8" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 8</head>
					             <p>When the bowels are loose during the whole course of fevers, in this case we
						are most especially to warm the feet, and see that they are properly treated
						with cerates, and wrapped in shawls, so that they may not become colder than
						the rest of the body; but when they are hot, no fomentation must be made to
						them, but care is to be taken that they do not become cold; and very little
						drink is to be used, either cold water or hydromel. In those cases of fever
						where the bowels are loose, and the mind is disordered, the greater number
						of patients pick the wool from their blankets, scratch their noses, answer
						briefly when questions are put to them, but, when left to themselves, utter
						nothing that is rational. Such attacks appear to me to be connected with
						black bile. When in these cases there is a colliquative diarrhoea, I am of
						opinion that we ought to give the colder and thicker ptisans, and that the
						drinks ought to be binding, of a vinous nature, and rather astringent. In
						cases of fever attended from the first with vertigo, throbbing of the head,
						and thin urine, you may expect the fever to be exacerbated at the crisis;
						neither need it excite wonder, although there be delirium. When, at the
						commencement, the urine is cloudy or thick, it is proper to purge gently,
						provided this be otherwise proper; but when the urine at first is<pb n="p.86"/> thin, do not purge such patients, but, if thought necessary,
						give a clyster; such patients should be thus treated; they should be kept in
						a quiet state, have unguents applied to them, and be covered up properly
						with clothes, and they should use for drink a watery hydromel, and the juice
						of ptisan as a draught in the evening; clear out the bowels at first with a
						clyster, but give no purgative medicines to them, for, if you move the
						bowels strongly, the urine is not concocted, but the fever remains long,
						without sweats and without a crisis. Do not give draughts when the time of
						the crisis is at hand, if there be agitation, but only when the fever abates
						and is alleviated. It is proper to be guarded at the crises of other fevers,
						and to withhold the draughts at that season. Fevers of this description are
						apt to be protracted, and to have determinations, if the inferior
						extremities be cold, about the ears and neck, or, if these parts are not
						cold, to have other changes; they have epistaxis, and disorder of the
						bowels. But in cases of fever attended with nausea, or distention of the
						hypochondria, when the patients cannot lie reclined in the same position,
						and the extremities are cold, the greatest care and precaution are
						necessary; nothing should be given to them, except oxymel diluted with
						water; no draught should be administered, until the fever abate and the
						urine be concocted; the patient should be laid in a dark apartment, and
						recline upon the softest couch, and he should be kept as long as possible in
						the same position, so as not to toss about, for this is particularly
						beneficial to him. Apply to the hypochondrium linseed by inunctions, taking
						care that he do not catch cold when the application is made; let it be in a
						tepid state, and boiled in water and oil. One may judge from the urine what
						is to take place, for if the urine be thicker, and more yellowish, so much
						the better; but if it be thinner, and blacker, so much the worse; but if it
						undergo changes, it indicates a prolongation of the disease, and the
						patient, in like manner, must experience a change to the worse and the
						better. Irregular fevers should be let alone until they become settled, and,
						when they do settle, they are to be treated by a suitable diet and medicine,
						attending to the constitution of the patient.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="9" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 9</head>
					             <p>The aspects of the sick are various; wherefore the physician <pb n="p.87"/>should pay attention, that he may not miss observing the exciting causes,
						as far as they can be ascertained by reasoning, nor such symptoms as should
						appear on an even or odd day, but he ought to be particularly guarded in
						observing the odd days, as it is in them, more especially, that changes take
						place in patients. He should mark, particularly, the first day on which the
						patient became ill, considering when and whence the disease commenced, for
						this is of primary importance to know. When you examine the patient, inquire
						into all particulars; first how the head is, and if there be no headache,
						nor heaviness in it; then examine if the hypochondria and sides be free of
						pain; for if the hypochondrium be painful, swelled, and unequal, with a
						sense of satiety, or if there be pain in the side, and, along with the pain,
						either cough, tormina, or belly-ache, if any of these symptoms be present in
						the hypochondrium, the bowels should be opened with clysters, and the
						patient should drink boiled hydromel in a hot state. The physician should
						ascertain whether the patient be apt to faint when he is raised up, and
						whether his breathing be free; and examine the discharges from the bowels,
						whether they be very black, or of a proper color, like those of persons in
						good health, and ascertain whether the fever has a paroxysm every third day,
						and look well to such persons on those days. And should the fourth day prove
						like the third, the patient is in a dangerous state. With regard to the
						symptoms, black stools prognosticate death; but if they resemble the
						discharges of a healthy person, and if such is their appearance every day,
						it is a favorable symptom; but when the bowels do not yield to a
						suppository, and when, though the respiration be natural, the patient when
						raised to the night table, or even in bed, be seized with deliquium, you may
						expect that the patient, man or woman, who experiences these symptoms, is
						about to fall into a state of delirium. Attention also should be paid to the
						hands, for if they tremble, you may expect epistaxis; and observe the
						nostrils, whether the breath be drawn in equally by both; and if expiration
						by the nostrils be large, a convulsion is apt to take place; and should a
						convulsion occur to such a person, death may be anticipated, and it is well
						to announce it beforehand.</p>
				           </div>
				           <pb n="p.88"/>
				           <div type="textpart" n="10" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 10</head>
					             <p> If, in a winter fever, the tongue be rough, and if there be swoonings, it is
						likely to be the remission of the fever. Nevertheless such a person is to be
						kept upon a restricted diet, with water for drink, and hydromel, and the
						strained juices, not trusting to the remission of the fevers, as persons
						having these symptoms are in danger of dying; when, therefore, you perceive
						these symptoms, announce this prognostic, if you shall judge proper, after
						making the suitable observations. When, in fevers, any dangerous symptom
						appears on the fifth day, when watery discharges suddenly take place from
						the bowels, when deliquium animi occurs, or the patient is attacked with
						loss of speech, convulsions, or hiccup, under such circumstances he is
						likely to be affected with nausea, and sweats break out under the nose and
						forehead, or on the back part of the neck and head, and patients with such
						symptoms shortly die, from stoppage of the respiration. When, in fevers,
						abscesses form about the legs, and, getting into a chronic state, are not
						concocted while the fever persists, and if one is seized with a sense of
						suffocation in the throat, while the fauces are not swelled, and if it do
						not come to maturation, but is repressed, in such a case there is apt to be
						a flow of blood from the nose; if this, then, be copious, it indicates a
						resolution of the disease, but if not, a prolongation of the complaint; and
						the less the discharge, so much worse the symptoms, and the more protracted
						the disease; but if the other symptoms are very favorable, expect in such a
						case that pains will fall upon the feet; if then they attack the feet, and
						if these continue long in a very painful, and inflamed state, and if there
						be no resolution, the pains will extend by degrees to the neck, to the
						clavicle, shoulder, breast, or to some articulation, in which an
						inflammatory tumor will necessarily form. When these are reduced, if the
						hands are contracted, and become trembling, convulsion and delirium seize
						such a person; but blisters break out on the eyebrow, erythema takes place,
						the one eyelid being tumefied overtops the other, a hard inflammation sets
						in, the eye become strongly swelled, and the delirium increases much, but
						makes its attacks rather at night than by day. These symptoms more
						frequently occur on odd than on even<pb n="p.89"/> days, but, whether on the
						one or the other, they are of a fatal character. Should you determine to
						give purgative medicines in such cases, at the commencement, you should do
						so before the fifth day, if there be borborygmi in the bowels, or, if not,
						you should omit the medicines altogether. If there be borborygmi, with
						bilious stools, purge moderately with scammony; but with regard to the
						treatment otherwise, administer as few drinks and draughts as until there be
						some amendment, and the disease is past the fourteenth day. When loss of
						speech seizes a person, on the fourteenth day of a fever, there is not
						usually a speedy resolution, nor any removal of the disease, for this
						symptom indicates a protracted disease; and when it appears on that day, it
						will be still more prolonged. When, on the fourth day of a fever, the tongue
						articulates confusedly, and when there are watery and bilious discharges
						from the bowels, such a patient is apt to fall into a state of delirium; the
						physician ought, therefore, to watch him, and attend to whatever symptoms
						may turn up. In the season of summer and autumn an epistaxis, suddenly
						occurring in acute diseases, indicates vehemence of the attack, and
						inflammation in the course of the veins, and on the day following, the
						discharge of thin urine; and if the patient be in the prime of life, and if
						his body be strong from exercise, and brawny, or of a melancholic
						temperament, or if from drinking has trembling hands, it may be well to
						announce beforehand either delirium or convulsion; and if these symptoms
						occur on even days, so much the better; but on critical days, they are of a
						deadly character. If, then, a copious discharge of blood procure an issue to
						the fullness thereof about the nose, or what is collected about the anus,
						there will be an abscess, or pains in the hypochondrium, or testicles, or in
						the limbs; and when these are resolved, there will be a discharge of thick
						sputa, and of smooth, thin urine. In fever attended with singultus, give
						asafoetida, oxymel, and carrot, triturated together, in a draught; or
						galbanum in honey, and cumin in a linctus, or the juice of ptisan. Such a
						person cannot escape, unless critical sweats and gentle sleep supervene, and
						thick and acrid urine be passed, or the disease terminate in <pb n="p.90"/>an abscess: give pine-fruit and myrrh in a linctus, and further give a
						very little oxymel to drink; but if they are very thirsty, some
						barley-water. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="11" subtype="part">
					             <head>PART 11</head>
					             <p> Peripneumonia, and pleuritic affections, are to be thus observed: If the
						fever be acute, and if there be pains on either side, or in both, and if
						expiration be if cough be present, and the sputa expectorated be of a blond
						or livid color, or likewise thin, frothy, and florid, or having any other
						character different from the common, in such a case, the physician should
						proceed thus: if the pain pass upward to the clavicle, or the breast, or the
						arm, the inner vein in the arm should be opened on the side affected, and
						blood abstracted according to the habit, age, and color of the patient, and
						the season of the year, and that largely and boldly, if the pain be acute,
						so as to bring on deliquium animi, and afterwards a clyster is to be given.
						But if the pain be below the chest, and if very intense, purge the bowels
						gently in such an attack of pleurisy, and during the act of purging give
						nothing; but after the purging give oxymel. The medicine is to be
						administered on the fourth day; on the first three days after the
						commencement, a clyster should be given, and if it does not relieve the
						patient, he should then be gently purged, but he is to be watched until the
						fever goes off, and till the seventh day; then if he appear to be free from
						danger, give him some unstrained ptisan, in small quantity, and thin at
						first, mixing it with honey. If the expectoration be easy, and the breathing
						free, if his sides be free of pain, and if the fever be gone, he may take
						the ptisan thicker, and in larger quantity, twice a day. But if he do not
						progress favorably, he must get less of the drink, and of the draught, which
						should be thin, and only given once a day, at whatever is judged to be the
						most favorable hour; this you will ascertain from the urine. The draught is
						not to be given to persons after fever, until you see that the urine and
						sputa are concocted (if, indeed, after the administration of the medicine he
						be purged frequently, it may be necessary to give it, but it should be given
						in smaller quantities and thinner than usual, for from inanition he will be
						unable to sleep, or digest properly, or wait the crisis); but when the
						melting down of crude matters has <pb n="p.91"/>taken place, and his system
						has cast off what is offensive, there will then be no objection. The sputa
						are concocted when they resemble pus, and the urine when it has reddish
						sediments like tares. But there is nothing to prevent fomentations and
						cerates being applied for the other pains of the sides; and the legs and
						loins may be rubbed with hot oil, or anointed with fat; linseed, too, in the
						form of a cataplasm, may be applied to the hypochondrium and as far up as
						the breasts. When pneumonia is at its height, the case is beyond remedy if
						he is not purged, and it is bad if he has dyspnoea, and urine that is thin
						and acrid, and if sweats come out about the neck and head, for such sweats
						are bad, as proceeding from the suffocation, rales, and the violence of the
						disease which is obtaining the upper hand, unless there be a copious
						evacuation of thick urine, and the sputa be concocted; when either of these
						come on spontaneously, that will carry off the disease. A linctus for
						pneumonia: Galbanum and pine-fruit in Attic honey; and southernwood in
						oxymel; make a decoction of pepper and black hellebore, and give it in cases
						of pleurisy attended with violent pain at the commencement. It is also a
						good thing to boil opoponax in oxymel, and, having strained it, to give it
						to drink; it answers well, also, in diseases of the liver, and in severe
						pains proceeding from the diaphragm, and in all cases in which it is
						beneficial to determine to the bowels or urinary organs, when given in wine
						and honey; when given to act upon the bowels, it should be drunk in larger
						quantity, along with a watery hydromel.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="12" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 12</head>
					             <p> A dysentery, when stopped, will give rise to an aposteme, or tumor, if it do
						not terminate in fevers with sweats, or with thick and white urine, or in a
						tertian fever, or the pain fix upon a varix, or the testicles, or on the
						hip-joints.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="13" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 13</head>
					             <p> In a bilious fever, jaundice coming on with rigor before the seventh day
						carries off the fever, but if it occur without the fever, and not at the
						proper time, it is a fatal symptom.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="14" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 14</head>
					             <p> When the loins are in a tetanic state, and the spirits in the veins are
						obstructed by melancholic humors, venesection will afford relief. But when,
						on the other hand, the anterior tendons are strongly contracted, and if
						there be sweats about the neck<pb n="p.92"/> and face, extorted by the
						violent pain of the parched and dried tendons of the sacral extremity (these
						are very thick, sustaining the spine, and giving rise to very great
						ligaments, which terminate in the feet,) in such a case, unless fever and
						sleep come on, followed by concocted urine and critical sweats, give to
						drink a strong Cretan wine, and boiled barley-meal for food; anoint and rub
						with ointments containing wax; bathe the legs and feet in hot water, and
						then cover them up; and so in like manner the arms, as far as the hands, and
						the spine, from the neck to the sacrum, are to be wrapped in a skin smeared
						with wax; this must extend to the parts beyond, and intervals are to be left
						for applying fomentations, by means of leather bottles filled with hot
						water, then, wrapping him up in a linen cloth, lay him down in bed. Do not
						open the bowels, unless by means of a suppository, when they have been long
						of being moved. If there be any remission of the disease, so far well, but
						otherwise, pound of the root of bryonia in fragrant wine, and that of the
						carrot, and give to the patient fasting early in the morning, before using
						the affusion, and immediately afterwards let him eat boiled barley-meal in a
						tepid state, and as much as he can take, and in addition let him drink, if
						he will, wine well diluted. If the disease yield to these means, so much the
						better, but, if otherwise, you must prognosticate accordingly.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="15" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 15</head>
					             <p> All diseases are resolved either by the mouth, the bowels, the bladder, or
						some other such organ. Sweat is a common form of resolution in all these
						cases.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="16" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 16</head>
					             <p> You should put persons on a course of hellebore who are troubled with a
						defluxion from the head. But do not administer hellebore to such persons as
						are laboring under empyema connected with abscesses, haemoptysis, and
						intemperament, or any other strong cause, for it will do no good; and if any
						thing unpleasant occur the hellebore will get the blame of it. But if the
						body have suddenly lost its powers, or if there be pain in the head, or
						obstruction of the ears and nose, or ptyalism, or heaviness of the limbs, or
						an extraordinary swelling of the body, you may administer the hellebore,
						provided these symptoms be not connected with drinking, nor with immoderate
						venery; nor with <pb n="p.93"/>sorrow, vexation, nor insomnolency, for, if
						any of these causes exist, the treatment must have respect to it.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="17" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 17</head>
					             <p> From walking arise pains of the sides, of the back, of the loins, and of the
						hip-joint, and disorder of the respiration has often been from the same
						cause, for, after excesses of wine and flatulent food, pains shoot to the
						loins and hips, accompanied with dysuria. Walking is the cause of such
						complaints, and also of coryza and hoarseness.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="18" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 18</head>
					             <p> Disorders connected with regimen, for the most part, make their attack
						accordingly as any one has changed his habitual mode of diet. For persons
						who dine contrary to custom experience much swelling of the stomach,
						drowsiness, and fullness; and if they take supper over and above, their
						belly is disordered; such persons will be benefited by sleeping after taking
						the bath, and by walking slowly for a considerable time after sleep; if,
						then, the bowels be moved, he may dine and drink a small quantity of wine
						not much diluted; but if the bowels are not opened, he should get his body
						rubbed with hot oil, and, if thirsty, drink of some weak and white wine, or
						a sweet wine, and take repose; if he does not sleep he should repose the
						longer. In other respects he should observe the regimen laid down for those
						who have taken a debauch. With regard to the bad effects of drinks, such as
						are of a watery nature pass more slowly through the body, they regurgitate,
						as it were, and float about the hypochondria, and do not flow readily by
						urine; when filled up with such a drink, he should not attempt any violent
						exertion, requiring either strength or swiftness, but should rest as much as
						possible until the drink has been digested along with the food; but such
						drinks as are stronger or more austere, occasion palpitation in the body and
						throbbing in the head, and in this case the person affected will do well to
						sleep, and take some hot draught for which he feels disposed; for abstinence
						is bad in headache and the effects of a surfeit. Those who, contrary to
						usage, restrict themselves to one meal, feel empty and feeble, and pass hot
						urine in consequence of the emptiness of their vessels; they have a salt and
						bitter taste in the mouth; they tremble at any work they attempt; their
						temples throb; and they cannot digest their supper so well as if they had
							<pb n="p.94"/>previously taken their dinner. Such persons should take
						less supper than they are wont, and a pudding of barley-meal more moist than
						usual instead of bread, and of potherbs the dock, or mallow, and ptisan, or
						beets, and along with the food they should take wine in moderation, and
						diluted with water; after supper they should take a short walk, until the
						urine descend and be passed; and they may use boiled fish. Articles of food
						have generally such effects as the following: Garlic occasions flatulence
						and heat about the chest, heaviness of the head, and nausea, and any other
						habitual pain is apt to be exasperated by it; it is diuretic, which, in so
						far, is a good property which it possesses; but to eat it when one means to
						drink to excess, or when intoxicated. Cheese produces flatulence and
						constipation, and heats the other articles of food; and it gives rise to
						crudities and indigestion, but it is worst of all to eat it along with drink
						after a full meal. Pulse of all kinds are flatulent, whether raw, boiled, or
						fried; least so when macerated in water, or in a green state; they should
						not be used except along with food prepared from the cerealia. Each of these
						articles, however, has bad effects peculiar to itself. The vetch, whether
						raw or boiled, creates flatulence and pain. The lentil is astringent, and
						disorders the stomach if taken with its hull. The lupine has the fewest bad
						effects of all these things. The stalk and the juice of silphium
						(asafoetida), pass through some people's bowels very readily, but in others,
						not accustomed to them, they engender what is called dry cholera; this
						complaint is more especially produced by it if mixed with much cheese, or
						eaten along with beef. Melancholic diseases are most particularly
						exacerbated by beef, for it is of an unmanageable nature, and requires no
						ordinary powers of stomach to digest it; it will agree best with those who
						use it well boiled and pretty long kept. Goat's flesh has all the bad
						properties of beef; it is an indigestible, more flatulent and engenders acid
						eructations and cholera; such as has a fragrant smell, is firm, and sweet to
						the taste, is the best, when well baked and cooled; but those kinds which
						are disagreeable to the taste, have a bad smell, and are hard, such are
						particularly bad, and especially if very fresh; it is best in summer and
						worst <pb n="p.95"/>in autumn. The flesh of young pigs is bad, either when
						it is too raw or when it is over-roasted, for it engenders bile and
						disorders the bowels. Of all kinds of flesh, pork is the best; it is best
						when neither very fat, nor, on the other hand, very lean, and the animal had
						not attained the age of what is reckoned an old victim; it should be eaten
						without the skin, and in a coldish state.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="19" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 19</head>
					             <p> In dry cholera the belly is distended with wind, there is rumbling in the
						bowels, pain in the sides and loins, no dejections, but, on the contrary,
						the bowels are constipated. In such a case you should guard against
						vomiting, but endeavor to get the bowels opened. As quickly as possible give
						a clyster of hot water with plenty of oil in it, and having rubbed the
						patient freely with unguents; put him into hot water, laying him down in the
						basin, and pouring the hot water upon him by degrees; and if, when heated in
						the bath, the bowels be moved, he will be freed from the complaint. To a
						person in such a complaint it will do good if he sleep, and drink a thin,
						old, and strong wine; and you should give him oil, so that he may settle,
						and have his bowels moved, when he will be relieved. He must abstain from
						all other kinds of food; but when the pain remits, give him asses milk to
						drink until he is purged. But if the bowels are loose, with bilious
						discharges, tormina, vomitings, a feeling of suffocation, and gnawing pains,
						it is best to enjoin repose, and to drink hydromel, and avoid vomiting.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="20" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 20</head>
					             <p> There are two kinds of dropsy, the one anasarca, which, when formed, is
						incurable; the other is accompanied with emphysema (tympanites?) and
						requires much good fortune to enable one to triumph over it. Laborious
						exertion, fomentation, and abstinence (are to be enjoined). The patient
						should eat dry and acrid things, for thus will he pass the more water, and
						his strength be kept up. If he labors under difficulty of breathing, if it
						is the summer season, and if he is in the prime of life, and is strong,
						blood should be abstracted from the arm, and then he should eat hot pieces
						of bread, dipped in dark wine and oil, drink very little, and labor much,
						and live on well-fed pork, boiled with vinegar, so that he may be able to
						endure hard exercises.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="21" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 21</head>
					             <p> Those who have the inferior intestines hot, and who pass <pb n="p.96"/>acrid
						and irregular stools of a colliquative nature, if they can bear it, should
						procure revulsion by vomiting with hellebore; but if not, should get a thick
						decoction of summer wheat in a cold state, lentil soup, bread cooked with
						cinders, and fish, which should be taken boiled if they have fever, but
						roasted if not feverish; and also dark-colored wine if free of fever; but
						otherwise they should take the water from medlars, myrtles, apples,
						services, dates, or wild vine. If there be no fever, and if there be
						tormina, the patient should drink hot asses' milk in small quantity at
						first, and gradually increase it, and linseed, and wheaten flour, and having
						removed the bitter part of Egyptian beans, and ground them, sprinkle on the
						milk and drink; and let him eat eggs half-roasted, and fine flour, and
						millet, and perl-spelt (chondrus) boiled in milk;- all these things should
						be eaten cold, and similar articles of food and drink should be
						administered. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="22" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 22</head>
					             <p> The most important point of regimen to observe and be guarded about in
						protracted diseases, is to pay attention to the exacerbations and remissions
						of fevers, so as to avoid the times when food should not be given, and to
						know when it may be administered without danger; this last season is at the
						greatest possible distance from the exacerbation.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="23" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 23</head>
					             <p> One should be able to recognize those who have headache from gymnastic
						exercises, or running, or walking or hunting, or any other unseasonable
						labor, or from immoderate venery; also those who are of a pale color, or
						troubled with hoarseness; those who have enlarged spleen, those who are in a
						state of anaemia, those who are suffering from tympanites, those having dry
						cough and thirst, those who are flatulent, and have the course of the blood
						in their veins intercepted; those persons whose hypochondria, sides, and
						back are distended: those having torpor; those laboring under amaurosis, or
						having noises in their ears; those suffering from incontinence of urine or
						jaundice, or whose food is passed undigested; those who have discharges of
						blood from the nose or anus, or who have flatulence and intense pain, and
						who cannot retain the wind. In these cases you may do mischief, but cannot
						possibly do any good by purging, but may interrupt the spontaneous
						remissions and crises of the complaints.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="24" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 24</head>
					             <p> If you think it expedient to let blood, see that the bowels <pb n="p.97"/>be
						previously settled, and then bleed; enjoin abstinence, and forbid the use of
						wine; and complete the cure by means of a suitable regimen, and wet
						fomentations. But if the bowels appear to be constipated, administer a
						soothing clyster.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="25" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 25</head>
					             <p> If you think it necessary to give medicines, you may safely purge upwards by
						hellebore, but none of those should be purged downwards. The most effectual
						mode of treatment is by the urine, sweats, and exercise; and use gentle
						friction so as not to harden the constitution; and if he be confined to bed
						let others rub him. When the pain is seated above the diaphragm, place him
						erect for the most part, and let him be as little reclined as possible; and
						when he is raised up let him be rubbed for a considerable time with plenty
						of hot oil. But if the pains be in the lower belly below the diaphragm, it
						will be useful to lie reclined and make no motion, and to such a person
						nothing should be administered except the friction. Those pains which are
						dissolved by discharges from the bowels, by urine, or moderate sweats, cease
						spontaneously, if they are slight, but if strong they prove troublesome; for
						persons so affected either die, or at least do not recover without further
						mischief, for they terminate in abscesses.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="26" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 26</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">A draught for a dropsical person.</hi> Take three
						cantharides, and removing their head, feet, and wings, triturate their
						bodies in three cupfuls (cyathi) of water, and when the person who has drunk
						the draught complains of pain, let him have hot fomentations applied. The
						patient should be first anointed with oil, should take the draught fasting,
						and eat hot bread with oil.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="27" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 27</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">A styptic.</hi> Apply the juice of the fig inwardly to the
						vein; or having moulded biestings into a tent, introduce up the nostril, or
						push up some chalcitis with the finger, and press the cartilages of the
						nostrils together; and open the bowels with the boiled milk of asses: or
						having shaved the head apply cold things to it if in the summer season. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="28" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 28</head>
					             <p> The sesamoides purges upwards when pounded in oxymel to the amount of a
						drachm and a half, and drunk; it is combined with the hellebores, to the
						amount of the third part, and thus it is less apt to produce
						suffocation.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="29" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 29</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">Trichiasis.</hi> Having introduced a thread into the eye of
							a<pb n="p.98"/> needle push it through the upper part of the distended
						eyelid, and do the same at the base of it; having stretched the threads tie
						a knot on them, and bind up until they drop out: and, if this be sufficient,
						so far well; but if otherwise, you must do the same thing again. And
						hemorrhoids, in like manner, you may treat by transfixing them with a needle
						and tying them with a very thick and large woolen thread; for thus the cure
						will be more certain. When you have secured them, use a septic application,
						and do not foment until they drop off, and always leave one behind; and when
						the patient recovers, let him be put upon a course of hellebore. Then let
						him be exercised and sweated; the friction of the gymnasium and wrestling in
						the morning will be proper; but he must abstain from running, drinking, and
						all acrid substances, except marjoram; let him take an emetic every seven
						days, or three times in a month; for thus will he enjoy the best bodily
						health. Let him take straw-colored, austere, and watery wine, and use little
						drink.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="30" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 30</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">For persons affected with empyema.</hi> Having cut some
						bulbs or squill, boil in water, and when well boiled, throw this away, and
						having poured in more water, boil until it appear to the touch soft and
						well-boiled; then triturate finely and mix roasted cumin, and white sesames,
						and young almonds pounded in honey, form into an electuary and give; and
						afterwards sweet wine. In draughts, having pounded about a small acetabulum
						of the white poppy, moisten it with water in which summer wheat has been
						washed, add honey, and boil. Let him take this frequently during the day.
						And then taking into account what is to happen, give him supper.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="31" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 31</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">For dysentery.</hi> A fourth part of a pound of cleaned
						beans, and twelve shoots of madder having been triturated, are to be mixed
						together and boiled, and given as a linctus with some fatty substance.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="32" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 32</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">For diseases of the eyes.</hi> Washed spodium (tutty?) mixed
						with grease, and not of a thinner consistence than dough, is to be carefully
						triturated, and moistened with the juice of unripe raisins; and having dried
						in the sun, moisten until it is of the consistence of an ointment. When it
						becomes again dry, let it<pb n="p.99"/> be finely levigated, anoint the eyes
						with it, and dust it upon the angles of the eyes.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="33" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 33</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">For watery eyes.</hi> Take one drachm of ebeny and nine
						oboli of burnt copper, rub them upon a whetstone, add three oboli of
						saffron; triturate all these things reduced to a fine powder, pour in an
						Attic hemina of sweet wine, and then place in the sun and cover up; when
						sufficiently digested, use it.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="34" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 34</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">For violent pains of the eyes.</hi> Take of chalcitis, and
						of raisin, of each 1 dr., when digested for two days, strain; and pounding
						myrrh and saffron, and having mixed must, with these things, digest in the
						sun; and with this anoint the eyes when in a state of severe pain. Let it be
						kept in a copper vessel. </p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="35" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 35</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">Mode of distinguishing persons in an hysterical fit.</hi>
						Pinch them with your fingers, and if they feel, it is hysterical; but if
						not, it is a convulsion.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="36" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 36</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">To persons in coma,</hi> (dropsy?) give to drink meconium
							(<hi rend="ital">euphorbia peplus?</hi>) to the amount of a round Attic
							<hi rend="ital">leciskion</hi> (small acetabulum).</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="37" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 37</head>
					             <p> Of squama aeris, as much as three specilla can contain, with the gluten of
						summer wheat: levigate, pound, form into pills, and give; it purges water
						downwards.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="38" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 38</head>
					             <p>
						               <hi rend="ital">A medicine for opening the bowels.</hi> Pour upon figs the
						juice of spurge, in the proportion of seven to one: then put into a new
						vessel and lay past when properly mixed. Give before food.</p>
				           </div>
				           <div type="textpart" n="39" subtype="chapter">
					             <head>PART 39</head>
					             <p> Pounding meconium, pouring on it water, and straining, and mixing flour, and
						baking into a cake, with the addition of boiled honey, give in affections of
						the anus and in dropsy; and after eating of it, let the patient drink of a
						sweet watery wine, and diluted hydromel prepared from wax: or collecting
						meconium, lay it up for medicinal purposes.</p>
				           </div>
			         </div>

			         <pb n="p.100"/>
		       </div>
      </body>
	  </text>
</TEI>
