<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Archidamus</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
          <date type="print">1928</date>
          <date type="reprint">1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg016.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Doubtless some of you are astonished that I, who heretofore have observed the
            customs<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName> the young were not supposed to appear in public places. Plutarch
            states (<bibl n="Plut. Lyc. 25">Plut. Lyc. 25</bibl>) that men were not allowed even in
            the market-place until after they were thirty years old.</note> of the state more
          faithfully, I dare say, than any other of my generation, have now so completely changed
          that I have come forward, in spite of my youth, to offer counsel regarding a subject which
          even our elders hesitate to discuss. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The fact is that if any of those who are accustomed to address you had spoken in a manner
          worthy of the state, I should strictly have held my peace; but now, since I see that they
          are either seconding the demands of the enemy, or opposing them but feebly, or have kept
          silent altogether, I have risen to set forth my own views on this subject, feeling that it
          would be disgraceful if by keeping the place appropriate to my years I should allow the
          state to pass measures unworthy of itself. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Moreover, I think that although on other matters it may be proper for men of my age to
          keep silent, yet on the question of war it is fitting that they most of all should give
          counsel who will also have the greatest part in the dangers, especially since the power to
          judge of what ought to be done is an endowment common to all of us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For if it were established that older men always know what is best, while the younger are
          never correct in their views, it would be right to exclude us from giving counsel; but
          since it is not by the number of our years that we differ in wisdom from one another, but
          by our natural endowments and by our cultivation of them, why should you not make trial of
          both the young and the old, in order that you may be in a position to choose from all
          courses which are proposed that which is the most expedient? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>I am amazed at those who think that we are fit to command ships of war and to lead armies
          in the field,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Archidamus had commanded Spartan armies in
            370 and 367. See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 6.4.17">Xen. Hell. 6.4.17</bibl> and vii. 1.
            28.</note> where bad judgement on our part would involve the state in many grave
          disasters, and yet do not think that we ought to express our views on matters which you
          are about to decide, wherein if we proved to be right we should benefit you all, while if,
          on the other hand, we failed of your assent we should ourselves perhaps suffer in
          reputation, but should not in any way impair the commonwealth. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> It is not, I assure you, because I am ambitious to be an orator, nor because I am
          prepared to change my former mode of life that I have spoken as I have about these things,
          but because I want to urge you not to reject any time of life, but to seek among all ages
          for the man who can offer good advice on the problems which now confront us; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for never since we have dwelt in <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> has
          any war or any peril come upon us in which so much has been at stake as in this question
          which we are now assembled to discuss. For while in times past we fought that we might
          have dominion over the other states, now we must fight that we ourselves may not be forced
          to do their bidding—which is proof of a free spirit, to preserve which no hardship on
          earth is too great to endure, not for us alone, but for all others as well who have not
          renounced every claim to manhood but still make even slight pretensions to courage. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> As for myself, at any rate, if I may speak my own mind, I had rather die this moment for
          not complying with the dictates of the foe than live many times my allotted span of life
          at the price of voting what the Thebans demand. For I should feel disgraced, I who am
          descended from Heracles,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Spartan kings claimed descent
            from Heracles <bibl n="Isoc. 4.62">Isoc. 4.62</bibl>.</note> who am the son of the
          ruling king and likely myself to attain to this honor,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Archidamus became king after the death of Agesilaus in <date when="-0361">361
              B.C.</date></note> if I did not strive with all the strength that is in me to prevent
          this territory, which our fathers left to us, from becoming the possession of our slaves.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And I expect you also to share my feelings when you reflect that, while until the present
          day we seem to have been unfortunate in our contest with the Thebans,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Since the battle of Leuctra.</note> and to have been overcome in body because
          of the mistakes of our leader,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cleombrotus the king was
            partly blamed for the Spartan defeat at Leuctra.</note> yet up to this moment we possess
          our spirits unconquered; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>but that if through fear of the dangers which now threaten us we relinquish anything that
          is ours, we shall justify the boasts of the Thebans, and erect against ourselves a trophy
          far more imposing and conspicuous than that which was raised at Leuctra; for the one will
          stand as a memorial of our ill-fortune; the other, of our abject spirit. Let no man,
          therefore, persuade you to fasten such a disgrace upon the state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And yet our allies<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Especially the Corinthians. See
            Introduction.</note> have been only too zealous in advising you that you must give up
            <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> and make peace. Because of this
          they merit your indignation far more than those who revolted<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The Arcadians had joined the Thebans in invading <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. The Argives, Eleans, and Achaeans had also
            forsaken <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and gone over partly or
            wholly to the Thebans.</note> from you at the beginning. For the latter, when they had
          forsaken your friendship, destroyed their own cities, plunging them into civil strife and
          massacres and vicious forms of government.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Such
            disturbances and changes of government took place about this time in <placeName
              key="tgn,7002735">Arcadia</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
              >Argos</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7011098">Sicyon</placeName>, <placeName
              key="perseus,Elis">Elis</placeName>, and Phlius. See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 7.1">Xen.
              Hell. 7.1-4</bibl>. By vicious forms of government Archidamus probably refers to the
            democracies which in various places had been set up instead of the earlier
            oligarchies.</note> These men, on the other hand, come here to inflict injury upon us;
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for they are trying to persuade us to throw away in one brief hour the glory which our
          forefathers amid manifold dangers during the course of seven hundred years<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">A round number for the period between <date when="-1104">1104
              B.C.</date>, the traditional date when the sons of Heracles took <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, and the date of the present oration, <date
              when="-0366">366 B.C.</date></note> acquired and bequeathed to us—a disaster more
          humiliating to <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> and more terrible than
          any other they could ever have devised. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So far do they go in their selfish greed, so great is the cowardice which they impute to
          us, that they, who have time and again called upon us to make war in defense of their own
            territory,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Especially <placeName key="perseus,Corinth"
              >Corinth</placeName> and Phlius. See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 4.4.7">Xen. Hell.
              4.4.7</bibl> and 15.</note> think we ought not to risk battle for <placeName
            key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>, but, in order that they may themselves
          cultivate their lands in security, seek to convince us that we ought to yield to the enemy
          a portion of our own; and, besides all that, they threaten that if we do not comply with
          these terms, they will make a separate peace. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For my part, I do not think that our risk without their alliance will be as much more
          serious for us as it will be more glorious and splendid and notable in the eyes of all
          mankind; for to endeavor to preserve ourselves and to prevail over our enemies, not
          through the aid of others, but through our own powers, is in keeping with the past
          achievements of our state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Although I have never been fond of oratory, having in fact always thought that those who
          cultivate the power of speech are somewhat lacking in capacity for action,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">An allusion to the traditional Spartan fondness for brevity
            and distrust of eloquence.</note> yet at the moment there is nothing I should value more
          than the ability to speak as I desire about the question now before us; for in the present
          crisis I am confident that with this aid I could render a very great service to the state.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> First, I think that I ought to explain to you in what way we acquired <placeName
            key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>, and for what reasons you settled in the
          Peloponnesus—you who from of old are Dorians. And the reason why I shall go back to remote
          times is that you may understand why your enemies are trying to rob you of this country,
          which you acquired, no less than <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>
          itself, with a just title. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When Heracles had put off this life and from being mortal became a god, his sons at
          first went on divers wanderings and faced many perils because of the power of their
            enemies;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the return of the the sons of Heracles and
            details connected therewith see <bibl n="Apollod. 2.8.2">Apollod. 2.8.2-4</bibl>, and
            Frazer's notes on this passage (Loeb Classical Library, Vol.I). Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.54"
              >Isoc. 4.54-58</bibl> and notes.</note> but after the death of Eurystheus they fixed
          their habitation among the Dorians. In the third generation thereafter they came to
            <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, desiring to consult the oracle about
          certain matters. Apollo, however, made them no answer to the questions which they asked,
          but merely bade them seek the country of their fathers. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Searching into the meaning of the oracle, they found, first, that <placeName
            key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName> belonged to them by right of their being next of
          kin, for after the death of Eurystheus they were the sole survivors of Perseus' line;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Sthenelus, father of Eurystheus, was a son of Perseus. For the
            manner of Eurystheus' death see <bibl n="Isoc. 4.60">Isoc. 4.60</bibl>.</note> next,
          that <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> was theirs by right of gift, for
          when Tyndareus, having been driven from his throne,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Tyndareus, son of Perieres and of Perseus' daughter, Gorgophone, was king of <placeName
              key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> until driven out by his half-brother
            Hippocoön and by Hippocoön's sons. See <bibl n="Apollod. 3.10.5">Apollod.
            3.10.5</bibl>.</note> was restored to it by Heracles,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Heracles slew Hippocoön and his twenty sons and restored Tyndareus.</note> after Castor
          and Polydeuces had vanished from among men,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Castor was
            slain during a foray in <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>. His
            brother, Polydeuces, who according to most accounts was a son of Zeus by Leda, while
            Castor was a son of Tyndareus by Leda, refused to accept immortality unless it was
            shared by his brother. Zeus, therefore, granted that the two brothers dwell, on
            alternate days, among the gods and among men. According to others both were sons of
            Zeus. Hence Isocrates can refer to their kinship with Heracles, the son of Zeus and
            Alcmene. See <bibl n="Apollod. 3.11.2">Apollod. 3.11.2</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 10.61"
              >Isoc. 10.61</bibl>.</note> he gave the land to Heracles because of this act of
          kindness and also because of the kinship of Heracles and his own sons; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and lastly, they found that <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> was
          theirs as a prize taken in war, for Heracles, when he had been robbed of the cattle from
            Erytheia,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">To fetch the cattle of Geryon from Erytheia, an
            island off the coast of <placeName key="tgn,1000095">Spain</placeName>, was the tenth
            labor imposed on Heracles by Eurystheus. See <bibl n="Apollod. 2.5.10">Apollod.
              2.5.10</bibl>.</note> by Neleus and all his sons except Nestor, had taken the country
          captive and slain the offenders, but had committed the city to Nestor's charge, believing
          him to be prudent, because, although the youngest of his brethren, he had taken no part in
          their iniquity. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Assuming this to be the purport of the oracle, they joined forces with your forefathers
          and organized an army, sharing meantime their own country with their followers,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, the common folk of the Dorians as distinguished from
            the descendants of Heracles, the ancestors of Archidamus.</note> but receiving from them
          the kingship as the prize reserved for themselves alone; then having confirmed these
          covenants by mutual pledges, they set out upon the expedition. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The perils which befell them on the march, and the other incidents<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Such as are told in <bibl n="Apollod. 2.8.3">Apollod. 2.8.3</bibl>.</note>
          which have no bearing on the present theme, I need not take the time to describe. Let it
          suffice that, having conquered in war those who dwelt in the regions which I have
          mentioned, they divided their kingdom into three parts.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Procles and Eurysthenes, twin sons of Aristodemus, along with Temenos and Cresphontes,
            sons of Aristomachus, drew lots for <placeName key="perseus,Argos">Argos</placeName>,
              <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>, and <placeName
              key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>.</note> Now you men of <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> have until this day remained faithful to the
          oaths and to the covenants which you made with my forefathers; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>therefore in time past you have fared better than the rest of the world, and in time to
          come you may reasonably hope, if you continue as you have been, to fare better than at
          present. But the Messenians went so far in their wickedness that they plotted against and
          slew Cresphontes, albeit he was the founder of their state, the sovereign of their land, a
          descendant of Heracles, and once the leader of their armies. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>His sons, however, escaped the perils which confronted them and threw themselves upon the
          mercy of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, beseeching us to come to the
          aid of their dead father<note anchored="true" resp="ed">According to the usual account, it
            was Aepytus, a son of Cresphontes, who avenged the death of his father. <bibl
              n="Apollod. 2.8.5">Apollod. 2.8.5</bibl>.</note> and offering us their land. And you,
          after inquiring of Apollo, and being directed by him to accept this gift and avenge the
          wronged, thereupon beleaguered the Messenians, forced them to surrender, and thus gained
          possession of their territory. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have not, it is true, recounted in detail our original titles to this land (for the
          present occasion does not permit me to go into legendary history, and I have had to set
          them forth with too great brevity for clearness); yet I am sure that even this brief
          statement makes it evident to all that there is no difference whatever between the way in
          which we acquired the land which is acknowledged to be ours and the land to which our
          claim is disputed. For we inhabit <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>
          because the sons of Heracles gave it to us, because Apollo directed us to do so, and
          because we fought and conquered those who held it; and <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
            >Messene</placeName> we received from the same people, in the same way, and by taking
          the advice of the same oracle. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>To be sure, if we are in a mood not to defend our title to anything, not even if they
          demand that we abandon <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> itself, it is
          idle to be concerned about <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>; but if
          not one of you would consent to live if torn from the fatherland, then you ought to be of
          the same mind about that country; for in both cases we can advance the same justifications
          and the same reasons for our claim. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Then again you are doubtless well aware that possessions, whether private or public,
          when they have remained for a long time in the hands of their owner, are by all men
          acknowledged to be hereditary and incontestable. Now we took <placeName
            key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> before the Persians acquired their
            kingdom<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In <date when="-0559">559 B.C.</date>, when Cyrus
            became ruler of <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>.</note> and became
          masters of the continent, in fact before a number of the Hellenic cities were even
          founded. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet notwithstanding that we hold these titles, the Thebans would on the one hand
          restore Asia as his ancestral right to the barbarian,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By
            the peace terms of Pelopidas. See introduction to this oration.</note> who has not yet
          held sway over it for two hundred years, while on the other hand they would rob us of
            <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>, which we have held for more than
          twice that length of time;<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="perseus,Messene"
              >Messene</placeName> was not actually subdued until <date from="-0724" to="-0723"
              >724-723 B.C.</date> Perhaps Isocrates is speaking loosely, or perhaps he follows
            another source than Pausanias, who is almost our sole authority for this period.
            However, the conquests of Alcamenes took place about <date when="-0786">786 B.C.</date>,
            and Isocrates perhaps refers to this or a similar event. See <bibl n="Paus. 4.4.3">Paus.
              4.4.3</bibl>. Dinarchus (<bibl n="Din. 1.73">Din. 1.73</bibl>) gives the same figure
            as lsocrates.</note> and although it was only the other day that they razed both
            <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Plataea"
            >Plataea</placeName> to the ground,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName
              key="perseus,Plataea">Plataea</placeName> was destroyed about <date when="-0372">372
              B.C.</date>, and <placeName key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName> shortly after. See
              <bibl n="Diod. 15.46.4">Dio. Sic. 15.46.4</bibl> and <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 6.3.1">Xen.
              Hell. 6.3.1</bibl>. Others give the date as <date when="-0374">374 B.C.</date></note>
          yet now, after a lapse of four hundred years, they propose to settle their colonists in
            <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> acting in both cases contrary to
          the oaths and covenants.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. the Peace of Antalcidas. See
              <bibl n="Isoc. 4.115">Isoc. 4.115 ff.</bibl> and note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Were they restoring those who are truly Messenians, they would still be acting unjustly,
          but at least they would have a more plausible pretext for wronging us; but as the case
          stands, it is the Helots whom they are trying to settle on our frontier,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See introduction.</note> so that the worst fate which
          threatens us is not that we shall be robbed of our land contrary to justice, but that we
          shall see our slaves made masters of it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> You will perceive still more clearly from what follows both that we are now dealt with
          most unfairly and that in the past we held <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
            >Messene</placeName> justly. For in the many wars which have befallen us we have before
          this at times been forced to make peace when we were in much worse case than our
            foes.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">such were the Peace of Nicias (<date when="-0421"
              >421 B.C.</date>, Thucyd. v. 18), the Peace of Antalcidas, and the separate peace
            between <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> (<bibl n="Xen. Hell. 6.2.1">Xen. Hell.
              6.2.1</bibl>).</note> But, although our treaties were concluded under circumstances in
          which it was impossible for us to seek any advantage, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>yet, while there were other matters about which differences arose, neither the Great King
          nor the city of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> ever charged us with
          having acquired <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> unjustly. And yet how
          could we find a more thoroughgoing judgement on the justice of our case than this, which
          was rendered by our enemies and made at a time when we were beset with misfortunes? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> That oracle, moreover, which all would acknowledge to be the most ancient and the most
          widely accepted and the most trustworthy in existence, recognized <placeName
            key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> as ours, not only at the time when it
          commanded us to receive the country as a gift from the sons of Cresphontes and to go to
          the aid of the wronged, but also later, when the war dragged on and both sides sent
          delegations to <placeName key="perseus,Delphi">Delphi</placeName>, the Messenians
          appealing for deliverance and we inquiring how we could most speedily make ourselves
          masters of their city, the god gave them no answer, thus showing that their appeal was
          unjust, while to us he revealed both what sacrifices we should perform and to whom we
          should send for aid.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">in the second Messenian War,
              <date from="-0685" to="-0668">685-668 B.C.</date>, the Athenians are said to
            have sent Tyrtaeus, the lame school-master, to the aid of the Spartans. See Pausanias
            iv. 15.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And yet how could anyone furnish testimony more significant or clearer than this? For it
          has been shown, first of all (since nothing prevents our restating these points briefly),
          that we received the country from its rightful owners; secondly, that we took it by war,
          precisely as most of the cities in those days were founded; further, that we drove out
          those who had grievously sinned against the children of Heracles—men who by right should
          have been banished from the sight of all mankind; and, finally, it has been shown that the
          length of our tenure, the judgement of our enemies, and the oracles of Apollo all confirm
          our right to the possession of <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Anyone of these facts is enough to refute the assertions of those who presume to allege
          against us either that we now refuse to conclude peace because of a desire for
          aggrandizement, or that we then made war on the Messenians because we coveted what was not
          our own. I might perhaps say more than this about our acquisition of <placeName
            key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>, but I consider what I have already said to be
          sufficient </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Those who advise us to make peace declare that prudent men ought not to take the same
          view of things in fortunate as in unfortunate circumstances, but rather that they should
          always consult their immediate situation and accommodate themselves to their fortunes, and
          should never entertain ambitions beyond their power, but should at such times seek, not
          their just rights but their best interests. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In all else I agree with them, but no man could ever persuade me that one should ever
          deem anything to be of greater consequence than justice;<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >For this Isocratean idealism cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 8.31">Isoc. 8.31-35</bibl>.</note> for
          I see that our laws have been made to secure it, that men of character and reputation
          pride themselves upon practicing it, and that it constitutes the chief concern of all
          well-regulated states; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>further, I observe that the wars of the past have in the end been decided, not in
          accordance with the strongest forces, but in accordance with justice; and that, in
          general, the life of man is destroyed by vice and preserved by virtue. Therefore those
          should not lack courage who are about to take up arms in a just cause, but far more those
          who are insolent and do not know how to bear their good fortune with moderation.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 1.42">Isoc. 1.42</bibl> and <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.31">Isoc. 12.31-32</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Then, too, there is this point to consider: At present we are all agreed as to what is
          just, while we differ as to what is expedient. But now that two good things are set before
          us, the one evident, the other doubtful, how ridiculous you would make yourselves if you
          should reject that course which is acknowledged to be good and decide to take that which
          is debatable, especially when your choice is a matter of such importance! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For according to my proposal you would not relinquish a single one of your possessions
          nor fasten any disgrace upon the state; nay, on the contrary, you would have good hope
          that taking up arms in a just cause you would fight better than your foes. According to
          their proposal, on the other hand, you would withdraw at once from <placeName
            key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>, and, having first committed this wrong
          against yourselves, you would perhaps fail to secure both what is expedient and what is
          just—and everything else which you expect to gain. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For as yet it is by no means evident that if we do as we are bidden we shall henceforth
          enjoy lasting peace. For I think you are not unaware that all men are wont to discuss just
          terms with those who defend their rights, while in the case of those who are over-ready to
          do what they are commanded they keep adding more and more to the conditions which at first
          they intended to impose; and thus it happens that men of a warlike temper obtain a more
          satisfactory peace than those who too readily come to terms. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But lest I should seem to dwell too long on this point, I shall abandon all such
          considerations and turn at once to the simplest of my proofs. If no people, after meeting
          with misfortune, ever recovered themselves or mastered their enemies, then we cannot
          reasonably hope to win victory in battle; but if on many occasions it has happened that
          the stronger power has been vanquished by the weaker, and that the besiegers have been
          destroyed by those confined within the walls, what wonder if our own circumstances
          likewise should undergo a change? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now in the case of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> I can cite no
          instance of this kind, for in times past no nation stronger than ourselves ever invaded
          our territory;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, before the Theban invasion of <date
              when="-0369">369 B.C.</date></note> but in the case of other states there are many
          such examples which one might use, and especially is this true of the city of the
          Athenians. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For we shall find that as a result of dictating to others they lost repute with the
          Hellenes, while by defending themselves against insolent invaders they won fame among all
          mankind. Now if I were to recount the wars of old which they fought against the Amazons or
          the Thracians or the Peloponnesians<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.56">Isoc. 4.56</bibl> and 70.</note> who under the leadership of Eurystheus
          invaded <placeName key="tgn,7002681">Attica</placeName>, no doubt I should be thought to
          speak on matters ancient and remote from the present situation; but in their war against
          the Persians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.71">Isoc.
            4.71-98</bibl>.</note> who does not know from what hardships they arose to great
          good-fortune? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For they alone of those who dwelt outside of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName>, although they saw that the strength of the barbarians was
          irresistible, did not think it honorable to consider the terms imposed upon them,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">These terms were to give earth and water, in token of
            submission, to the heralds of the Great King. <bibl n="Hdt. 7.133">Hdt.
            7.133</bibl>.</note> but straightway chose to see their city ravaged rather than
          enslaved. Leaving their own country,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.96">Isoc. 4.96</bibl>.</note> and adopting Freedom as their fatherland,
          they shared the dangers of war with us, and wrought such a change in their fortunes that,
          after being deprived of their own possessions for but a few days, they became for many
          years masters of the rest of the world.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.72">Isoc. 4.72</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>
          <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, however, is not the only instance by
          which one might show how great are the advantages of daring to resist one's enemies. There
          is also the case of the tyrant Dionysius, who, when he was besieged by the Carthaginians,
          seeing not a glimmer of hope for deliverance, but being hard pressed both by the war and
          by the disaffection of his citizens, was, for his part, on the point of sailing away, when
          one of his companions made bold to declare that “royalty is a glorious shroud.”<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, it is a glorious thing to die a king. For the event,
              <date when="-0396">396 B.C.</date>, See <bibl n="Diod. 14.58">Dio. Sic. 14.58</bibl>,
            and for the anecdote, <bibl n="Diod. 14.8.5">Dio. Sic. 14.8.5</bibl> and <bibl
              n="Ael. VH 4.8">Ael. Var. Hist. 4.8</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Ashamed of what he had planned to do, and taking up the war afresh, he destroyed
          countless hosts of the Carthaginians,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><bibl
              n="Diod. 14.72.6">Dio. Sic. 14.72.6</bibl>, says the shore was strewn with
            corpses.</note> strengthened his authority over his subjects, acquired far greater
          dominion than he had possessed before, ruled with absolute power until his death,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Dionysius died in the spring of <date when="-0367">367
              B.C.</date></note> and left his son in possession of the same honors and powers as he
          himself had enjoyed. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Similar to this was the career of Amyntas, king of the Macedonians. Worsted in battle by
          the neighboring barbarians, and robbed of all <placeName key="tgn,7006667"
            >Macedonia</placeName>, he at first proposed to quit the country and save his life, but
          hearing someone praise the remark made to Dionysius, and, like Dionysius, repenting of his
          decision, Amyntas seized a small fortified post, sent out thence for reinforcements,
          recovered the whole of <placeName key="tgn,7006667">Macedonia</placeName> within three
          months, spent the remainder of his days on the throne, and finally died of old age.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Amyntas, defeated by the Illyrians, won such a victory in
              <date when="-0393">393 B.C.</date> See <bibl n="Diod. 14.92.3">Dio. Sic.
              14.92.3</bibl>. Amyntas was father of Philip, and reigned from 394 to <date
              when="-0370">370 B.C.</date></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But we should both grow weary, you with listening and I with speaking, if we were to
          examine every incident of this sort; nay, if we were to recall also our experience with
            <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, while we should be grieved over past
          events, we should gain better hopes for the future. For when they ventured to withstand
          our inroads and our threats,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Of Agesilaus in 394, 378, and
              <date when="-0377">377 B.C.</date>; of Phoebidas in 382, and of Cleombrotus in 378 and
              <date when="-0376">376 B.C.</date></note> fortune so completely reversed their
          situation that they, who at all other times have been in our power, now assert their right
          to dictate to us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Seeing, then, that such great reversals have taken place, he is a very foolish person
          who thinks that they will fail to occur in our case; nay, we must endure for the present
          and be of good courage with regard to the future, knowing that states repair such
          disasters by the aid of good government and experience in warfare; and on this point no
          one would dare contradict me when I say that we have greater experience in military
          matters than any other people, and that government as it ought to be exists among us
          alone. With these two advantages on our side, we cannot fail to prove more successful in
          our undertakings than those who have paid but slight attention to either government or
          war. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> There are those who condemn war and dwell on its precariousness, employing many other
          proofs, but particularly our own experiences, and express surprise that men should see fit
          to rely on an expedient so difficult and hazardous. But I know of many who through war
          have acquired great prosperity, and many who have been robbed of all they possessed
          through keeping the peace; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for nothing of this kind is in itself absolutely either good or bad, but rather it is the
          use we make of circumstances and opportunities which in either case must determine the
          result. Those who are prosperous should set their hearts on peace, for in a state of peace
          they can preserve their present condition for the greatest length of time; those, however,
          who are unfortunate should give their minds to war, for out of the confusion and
          innovation resulting from it they can more quickly secure a change in their fortunes. But
          we, I fear, will be seen to have pursued exactly the opposite course; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for when we might have lived at ease, we made more wars than were necessary, but now,
          when we have no choice but to risk battle, we desire tranquility and deliberate about our
          own security. And yet those who wish to be free ought to shun a peace whose terms are
          dictated by the enemy as being not far removed from slavery, and should make treaties only
          when they have defeated their adversaries, or when they have made their forces equal to
          those of the enemy; for the kind of peace which each side will obtain will be decided by
          the manner in which they conclude the war. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Bearing these facts in mind, you must not rashly commit yourselves to shameful terms,
          nor let it appear that you are more remiss in your deliberations about your country than
          about the rest of the world. Let me recall to your minds that formerly, if a single
          Lacedaemonian gave aid to one of our allied cities when it was pressed by siege, all men
          would concede that its deliverance was due to him. Now the older among you could name the
          greater number of these men, but I, too, can recount the most illustrious of them: </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Pedaritus,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Harmost of <placeName key="tgn,7002670"
              >Chios</placeName> in <date when="-0412">412 B.C.</date>, who was successful against
            the Athenians for a time, but was defeated and slain in <date when="-0412">412
              B.C.</date> See Thucyd. viii. 55. 3.</note> sailing to <placeName key="tgn,7002670"
            >Chios</placeName>, saved that city; Brasidas entered <placeName
            key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName> and, having rallied about him a few of
          those who were under siege, defeated the besiegers<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Brasidas
            entered <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName> in <date when="-0422"
              >422 B.C.</date>, and in command of 150 hoplites sallied out against Cleon, the
            Athenian general. The greater part of the besieged forces was commanded by Clearidas.
            Brasidas lost his life in the engagement which followed, and became after his death a
            local hero at <placeName key="perseus,Amphipolis">Amphipolis</placeName>. See Thucyd. v.
            8-11.</note> in battle in spite of their numbers; Gylippus, by bringing aid to the
          Syracusans, not only saved them from destruction, but also captured the entire armament of
          the enemy, which dominated them both by land and by sea.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In
            the memorable Sicilian expedition of <date when="-0414">414 B.C.</date> Gylippus
            defeated the Athenian general Nicias and took his entire forces captive.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And yet is it not shameful that in those days single men among us were strong enough to
          protect the cities of others, but now all of us together are not able, nor do we attempt,
          to save our own city? Is it not shameful that, when we fought for others, we filled
            <placeName key="tgn,1000003">Europe</placeName> and Asia with trophies, but now, when
          our own country is so openly outraged, we cannot show that we have fought in her behalf a
          single battle worthy of note?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, since the battle of
            Leuctra. In addition to others mentioned above, Agesilaus, father of Archidamus, had won
            many victories in <placeName key="tgn,7002294">Asia Minor</placeName> (<date
              from="-0396" to="-0394">396-394 B.C.</date>).</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Is it not shameful, finally, that other cities have endured the last extremities of siege
          to preserve our empire,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For example, <placeName
              key="tgn,5004258">Thespiae</placeName>. See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 6.3">Xen. Hell.
              6.3</bibl>. For other examples see <bibl n="Paus. 9.14">Paus. 9.14</bibl>, and <bibl
              n="Diod. 15.57">Dio. Sic. 15.57</bibl> and 69.</note> while we ourselves see no reason
          why we should bear even slight hardships to prevent our being forced to do anything
          contrary to our just rights, but are to be seen even at this moment feeding teams of
          ravenous horses,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Horses were kept for racing, and were
            regarded as an expensive luxury.</note> although, like men reduced to the direst
          extremities and in want of their daily bread, we sue for peace in this fashion? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But it would be of all things the most outrageous if we who are accounted the most
          energetic of the Hellenes should be more slack than the rest in our deliberations upon
          this question. What people do we know, worth mentioning at all, who after a single defeat
          and a single invasion of their country have in so cowardly a fashion agreed to do
          everything demanded of them? How could such men hold out against a long season of
          misfortune? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Who would not censure us if, while the Messenians withstood siege for twenty years in
          order to retain <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName>,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">In the first Messenian war, <date from="-0743" to="-0724">743-724
              B.C.</date>
            <bibl n="Paus. 4.13.4">Paus. 4.13.4</bibl>.</note> we should so quickly withdraw from it
          under a treaty and should take no thought of our forefathers, but should allow ourselves
          to be persuaded by words to throw away this territory which they acquired by dint of
          struggles and wars? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> There are those, however, who care for none of these things, but, overlooking all
          considerations of shame, counsel you to follow a course which will bring disgrace upon the
          state. And so anxious are they to persuade you to give up <placeName key="perseus,Messene"
            >Messene</placeName> that they have dared to dwell on the weakness of <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and the strength of the enemy, and now they
          challenge us who oppose them to say from what quarter we expect reinforcements to come,
          seeing that we exhort you to make war. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For my part, I consider that the strongest and surest ally we can have is just dealing,
          for it is probable that the favor of the gods will be with those who deal justly—that is,
          if we may judge the future by the past; and in addition to this ally are good government
          and sober habits of life, and a willingness to battle to the death against the enemy, and
          the conviction that nothing is so much to be dreaded as the reproaches of our
          fellow-citizens—qualities which we possess in larger measure than any other people in
          existence. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>With these allies I would far rather go to war than with multitudes of soldiers, for I
          know that those of our people who first came to this country did not prevail over their
          adversaries through numbers, but through the virtues which I have just set forth.
          Therefore we ought not to stand in fear of our enemies because they are many, but should
          much rather take courage when we see that we ourselves have borne up under our misfortunes
          as no other people have ever done, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and that we still remain faithful to the customs and ways of life which we established
          here in the very beginning, while the rest of the Hellenes are not able to stand even
          their good fortune, but have become completely demoralized, some of them seizing the
          cities of their allies,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That is, those of the Theban
            league. Isocrates is here describing <placeName key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>
            and especially her allies in the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName>.</note> others opposing them in this; some disputing with
          their neighbors about territory, others, again, indulging their envy of one another<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See note a, p. 352. <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 7.1.32">Xen. Hell.
              7.1.32</bibl>, says that the Thebans and Eleans were no less pleased at the defeat of
            their allies, the Arcadians, in the “tearless” battle of <date when="-0367">367
              B.C.</date> than were the Lacedaemonians.</note> rather than making war against us.
          Therefore I wonder at those who look for a stronger ally than is found in the blundering
          of our enemies. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But if I must also speak of aid from the outside, I think that many will be disposed to
          assist us.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> see <bibl n="Isoc. 8.105">Isoc. 8.105</bibl> and <bibl
              n="Isoc. 5.44">Isoc. 5.44</bibl>. Among the states in <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
              >Peloponnesus</placeName>, Phlius, <placeName key="perseus,Heraea">Heraea</placeName>,
            and <placeName key="tgn,7011034">Orchomenus</placeName> in <placeName key="tgn,7002735"
              >Arcadia</placeName> were still true to <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName>. (<bibl n="Xen. Hell. 7.2.1">Xen. Hell. 7.2.1</bibl>, <bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 6.5.22">Xen. Hell. 6.5.22</bibl>, and <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 6.5.11">Xen.
              Hell. 6.5.11</bibl>.) The reference is to Dionysius the younger, who began to reign
              <date from="-0367" to="-0366">367-366 B.C.</date> His father had given aid to
              <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> on various occasions. See
            Underhill's note on <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.1.28">Xen. Hell. 5.1.28</bibl> (<placeName
              key="tgn,7011931">Oxford</placeName> edition). Nectanebos (<date from="-0378"
              to="-0364">378-364 B.C.</date>) was king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
              >Egypt</placeName> at this time. <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName>
            generally supported those who fought against the Persians, and now the Theban enemies of
              <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> were in league with <placeName
              key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>. As to the dynasts of Asia see <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.162">Isoc. 4.162</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 5.103">Isoc. 5.103</bibl>.
            Probably such powerful rulers as Mausolus of Caria, who revolted from <placeName
              key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName> in <date when="-0362">362 B.C.</date>, are here
            meant, as well as the rulers of <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName>. See
              <bibl n="Isoc. 5.102">Isoc. 5.102</bibl> and <bibl n="Isoc. 4.134">Isoc.
            4.134</bibl>.</note> For I know, in the first place, that the Athenians, although they
          may not hold with us in everything, yet if our existence were at stake would go to any
          length to save us; in the second place, that some of the other states would consult our
          interest as if it were their very own; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>again, that the tyrant Dionysius, and the king of <placeName key="tgn,7016833"
            >Egypt</placeName>, and the various dynasts throughout Asia, each so far as he has the
          power, would willingly lend us aid; and, furthermore, that the Hellenes who rank first in
          wealth and stand foremost in reputation and who desire the best of governments,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Those who sympathize with an oligarchy such as the Spartan
            government. <foreign xml:lang="greek">oi( be/ltistoi</foreign> is almost technical for
            “the aristocratic party.” as <foreign xml:lang="greek">ta\ be/ltista</foreign> for an
            aristocratic government. Cf. <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 5.2.6">Xen. Hell. 5.2.6</bibl>. Such
            people might be expected to form a conspiracy to set up an oligarchy favorable to
              <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>.</note> even though they have not
          yet allied themselves with us, are with us at least to the extent of wishing us well, and
          that upon them we have good reason to rest great hopes for the future. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Also I think that not only the people of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName> in general but even the adherents of democracy,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Those in <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>
            who are not definitely committed to an oligarchic government.</note> whom we consider to
          be especially unfriendly to us, are already yearning for our protection. For by revolting
          from us they have gained nothing of what they anticipated; on the contrary, they have got
          just the opposite of freedom; for having slain the best of their citizens, they are now in
          the power of the worst; instead of securing self-government, they have been plunged into
          misgovernment of many terrible kinds; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>accustomed as they have been in the past to march with us against others, they now behold
          the rest taking the field against themselves; and the war of factions, of whose existence
          in other territories they used to know only by report, they now see waged almost every day
          in their own states. They have been so levelled by their misfortunes that no man can
          discern who among them are the most wretched; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for not one of their states is unscathed, not one but has neighbors ready to do it
          injury; in consequence, their fields have been laid waste, their cities sacked, their
          people driven from their homes, their constitutions overturned, and the laws abolished
          under which they were once the most fortunate among the Hellenes.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The Acheans (<bibl n="Plb. 2.38">Polyb. 2.38.6</bibl>) and the Mantineans
              (<bibl n="Ael. VH 2.22">Ael. Var. Hist. 2.22</bibl>) were famed for their excellent
            laws.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>They feel such distrust and such hatred of one another that they fear their
          fellow-citizens more than the enemy; instead of preserving the spirit of accord and mutual
          helpfulness which they enjoyed under our rule, they have become so unsocial that those who
          own property had rather throw their possessions into the sea than lend aid to the needy,
          while those who are in poorer circumstances would less gladly find a treasure than seize
          the possessions of the rich; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>having ceased sacrificing victims at the altars they slaughter one another<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Possibly Isocrates may have in mind the massacre at <placeName
              key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName> in <date when="-0392">392 B.C.</date> (<bibl
              n="Xen. Hell. 4.4.3">Xen. Hell. 4.4.3</bibl>), the murder of certain Achaean
            suppliants, who took refuge in the temple of Heliconian Poseidon (Pausanias vii. 25), or
            the slaughter of 1200 prominent citizens in <placeName key="perseus,Argos"
              >Argos</placeName> in <date when="-0371">371 B.C.</date> (Diodorus xv. 58). Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 5.52">Isoc. 5.52</bibl>.</note> there instead; and more people are in exile
          now from a single city than before from the whole of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
            >Peloponnesus</placeName>. But although the miseries which I have recounted are so many,
          those which remain unmentioned far outnumber them; for all the distress and all the horror
          in the world have come together in this one region. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="69" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>With these miseries some states are already replete; others too will shortly have their
          fill, and then they will seek to find some relief for the troubles which now beset them.
          For do not imagine that they will continue to put up with these conditions; for how could
          men who grew weary even of prosperity endure for a long time the pressure of adversity?
          And so not only if we fight and conquer, but even if we keep quiet and bide our time, you
          will see them veer round and come to regard alliance with us as their only safety. Such,
          then, are the hopes which I entertain. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="70" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> However, so far am I from complying with the enemy's demands that, if none of these
          hopes should be realized and we should fail to obtain help from any quarter, but on the
          contrary some of the Hellenes should wrong us and the rest should look on with
          indifference—even so I should not alter my opinion; but I would undergo all the hazards
          which spring from war before I would agree to these terms. For I should be equally
          chagrined in either case—if we charged our forefathers with having deprived the Messenians
          of their land unjustly, or if, although insisting that they acquired it rightly and
          honorably, we made any concession regarding this territory contrary to our just rights.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="71" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nay, we must follow neither course, but must consider how we may carry on the war in a
          manner worthy of Spartans, and not prove those who are wont to eulogize our state to be
          liars, but so acquit ourselves that they shall seem to have told less than the truth about
          us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="72" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now I certainly believe that nothing worse will befall us in the future than what we
          endure at present, but that, on the contrary, our enemies will plan and act in such a way
          that they themselves will right our fortunes; but if we should after all be disappointed
          in our hopes, and should find ourselves hemmed in on every side and be no longer able to
          hold our city, then, hard as may be the step which I am about to propose, yet I shall not
          hesitate to proclaim it boldly; for that which I shall propose to you is a nobler course
          to be heralded abroad among the Hellenes, and more in keeping with our own pride, than
          that which is urged by some among you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="73" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For I declare that we must send our parents and our wives and children and the mass of
          the people away from <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>, some to
            <placeName key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>, some to <placeName key="tgn,7000639"
            >Cyrene</placeName>, others to the mainland of Asia,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Greek emigration from the home country was commonly towards the far west (<placeName
              key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName>), the east (coast of <placeName key="tgn,7002294"
              >Asia Minor</placeName>), or the south (<placeName key="tgn,7000639"
              >Cyrene</placeName>). Moreover, Dionysius the tyrant of <placeName
              key="perseus,Syracuse">Syracuse</placeName> and the “dynasts” in <placeName
              key="tgn,1000004">Asia</placeName> were friendly to the Spartans (see § 63), and
              <placeName key="tgn,7000639">Cyrene</placeName> was a Spartan settlement (see <bibl
              n="Isoc. 5.5">Isoc. 5.5</bibl>).</note> where the inhabitants will all gladly welcome
          them with gifts of ample lands and of the other means of livelihood as well, partly in
          gratitude for favors which they have received and partly in expectation of the return of
          favors which they first bestow. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="74" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Those of us, on the other hand, who are willing and able to fight must remain behind,
          abandon the city and all our possessions except what we can carry with us, and having
          seized some stronghold which will be the most secure and the most advantageous for
          carrying on the war, harry and plunder our enemies both by land and by sea until they
          cease from laying claim to what is ours. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="75" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>If we have the courage for such a course and never falter in it, you will see those who
          now issue commands imploring and beseeching us to take back <placeName
            key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> and make peace. For what state in the
            <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> could withstand a war such as
          would in all likelihood be waged if we so willed? What people would not be stricken with
          dismay and terror at the assembling of an army which had carried out such measures, which
          had been roused to just wrath against those who had driven it to these extremes, and which
          had been rendered desperate and reckless of life— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="76" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>an army which, in its freedom from ordinary cares and in having no other duty but that of
          war, would resemble a mercenary force, but in point of native valor and of disciplined
          habits would be like no army that could be levied in all the world—an army, moreover,
          which would have no fixed government, but would be able to bivouac in the open fields and
          to range the country at will, readily making itself neighbor to any people at its
          pleasure, and regarding every place which offered advantages for waging war as its
          fatherland? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="77" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For my part, I believe that if this proposal were merely put in words and scattered
          broadcast among the Hellenes, our enemies would be thrown into utter confusion; and still
          more would this be so if we were put to the necessity of carrying it into effect. For what
          must we suppose their feelings will be when they themselves suffer injury, but are
          powerless to inflict injury upon us; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="78" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>when they see their own cities reduced to a state of siege, while we shall have taken
          such measures that our own city cannot henceforth experience a like calamity; and when,
          furthermore, they perceive that it is easy for us to procure food both from our existing
          stores and from the spoils of war, but difficult for them, inasmuch as it is one thing to
          provide for an army such as ours and another to feed the crowds in cities? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="79" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But bitterest of all will it be for them when they learn that the members of our
          households have all along been living in comfort and plenty, whereas they will see their
          own people destitute every day of the necessities of life, and will not be able even to
          alleviate their distress, but if they till the soil, they will lose both crop and seed,
          and if they allow it to lie unworked, they will be unable to hold out any time at all.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="80" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But perhaps, you will object, they will join forces and with their united armies will
          follow us up and prevent us from doing them harm. Yet what better thing could we wish than
          to find close at hand, drawn up in line of battle and encamped against us face to face on
          the same difficult ground, an undisciplined and motley rabble, serving under many leaders?
          For there would be need of no great effort on our part; no, we should quickly force them
          to give battle, choosing the moment propitious for ourselves and not for them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="81" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But the remainder of the day would fail me if I undertook to set forth the advantages we
          should gain by such a course. This much, at any rate, is clear to all—that we have been
          superior to all the Hellenes, not because of the size of our city or the number of its
            inhabitants,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
              >Sparta</placeName> was about six miles in circumference. The number of pure Spartan
            inhabitants never exceeded 10,000.</note> but because the government which we have
          established is like a military camp, well administered and rendering willing obedience to
          its officers.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The whole life of a Spartan youth was
            supervised by military officers of one sort or another. Those over twenty years of age
            ate at a common table, or military mess. War was the first and only duty of a Spartan
            citizen, and obedience more important even than life.</note> If, then, we shall create
          in reality that which it has profited us to imitate, there can be no doubt that we shall
          easily overcome our foes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="82" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> We know, moreover, that those who became the founders of this city entered the
            <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName> with but a small army and yet made
          themselves masters of many powerful states.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For example, of
              <placeName key="perseus,Corinth">Corinth</placeName>, <placeName key="tgn,7011098"
              >Sicyon</placeName> and <placeName key="perseus,Megara">Megara</placeName>.</note> It
          were fitting, then, to imitate our forefathers and, by retracing our steps, now that we
          have stumbled in our course, try to win back the honors and the dominions which were
          formerly ours. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="83" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But, monstrous above all things would be our conduct if, knowing well that the Athenians
          abandoned their country to preserve the freedom of the Hellenes,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.96">Isoc. 4.96</bibl>.</note> we should lack the courage
          to give up our city even to preserve our own lives, and should refuse, when it behoves us
          to set the example for others in such deeds, even to imitate the conduct of the Athenians.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="84" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Even more should we deserve the ridicule of men if, having before us the example of the
          Phocaeans who, to escape the tyranny of the Great King, left Asia and founded a new
          settlement at <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Massilia</placeName>,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The first party of the Phocaeans left Asia about <date when="-0524">524
              B.C.</date> Besieged by Harpalus, they swore that never would they return to their
            city until the iron which they had cast into the sea should rise and float on the water.
            See Horace, <title>Epode.</title> xvi., and <bibl n="Hdt. 1.165">Hdt. 1.165</bibl>. A
            second group came to <placeName key="tgn,7008781">Marseilles</placeName> later. See
              <bibl n="Paus. 10.8.4">Paus. 10.8.4</bibl>.</note> we should sink into such abjectness
          of spirit as to submit to the dictates of those whose masters we have always been
          throughout our history. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="85" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But we must not let our minds dwell on the day when we shall have to send away from us
          those who are nearest and dearest to us; no, we must at once begin to look forward to that
          good time when, victorious over our foes, we shall restore our city, bring back our own
          people, and prove to the world that while we now have experienced reverses unjustly, in
          times past we justly claimed precedence over all others. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="86" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>This, then, is how matters stand: I have made this proposal, not with the thought that we
          must put it into effect forthwith, nor that there is in our circumstances no other means
          of deliverance, but because I wish to urge your minds to the conviction that we must
          endure, not only these, but even much worse misfortunes before conceding such terms
          regarding <placeName key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> as are being urged upon us.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="87" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I should not so earnestly exhort you to carry on the war if I did not see that the peace
          resulting from my proposals will be honorable and enduring, while that which would result
          from the counsel of certain men among you will not only be disgraceful, but will last no
          time at all. For if we permit the Helots to settle on our borders and allow <placeName
            key="perseus,Messene">Messene</placeName> to flourish undisturbed, who does not know
          that we shall be involved in constant turmoils and dangers all our lives? Therefore, those
          who talk about “security” are blind to the fact that they are providing us with peace for
          a few days only, while contriving a state of war which will never end. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="88" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I should like to ask these men in what cause they think we ought to fight and die. Is it
          not cause enough when the enemy make demands that are contrary to justice, when they cut
          off a portion of our territory, when they free our slaves and settle them in the land
          which our fathers bequeathed to us, yes, and not only rob us of our possessions but in
          addition to all our other miseries involve us in disgrace? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="89" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For my part, I think that in such a cause as this we ought to endure, not only war, but
          even exile and death; for it is far better to end our lives in the possession of the high
          reputation which we now enjoy than to go on living with the infamy which we shall bring
          upon ourselves if we do what we are commanded to do. In a word, if I may speak without
          reserve, it is preferable for us to suffer annihilation, rather than derision, at the
          hands of our foes. For men who have lived in such high repute and in such pride of spirit
          must do one of two things—either be first among the Hellenes, or perish utterly, having
          done no ignominious deed but having brought their lives to an honorable close. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="90" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Reflecting upon these things, we must not be faint of heart, nor follow the judgements
          of our allies, whom in former times we claimed the right to lead, but, having duly weighed
          the matter for ourselves, we should choose, not what is easiest for them, but what will be
          in keeping with <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> and with our
          achievements in the past. For not every people can adopt the same measures in the same
          situation, but each must follow the principles which from the very first they have made
          the foundation of their lives. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="91" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>No one, for example, would reproach Epidaurians or Corinthians or Phliasians if they
          thought of nothing else than to escape destruction and save their own lives; we men of
            <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName>, however, cannot seek our
          deliverance at all costs, but if to “safety” we cannot add “with honor,” then for us death
          with good repute is preferable; for those who lay claim to valor must make it the supreme
          object of their lives never to be found doing a shameful thing. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="92" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the cowardice of states is made manifest in deliberations like these no less than in
          the perils of war; for the greatest part of what takes place on the battle-field is due to
          fortune, but what is resolved upon here is a token of our very spirit. Wherefore we should
          strive for success in the measures to be adopted here with an emulation no less keen than
          we show in the lists of war. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="93" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I marvel at those who are willing to die for their personal glory, but have not the same
          feeling for the glory of the state, for which we may well suffer anything whatsoever to
          avoid bringing shame upon our city, nor should we permit it to abandon the post in which
          it was established by our forefathers. It is true that many difficulties and dangers beset
          us; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="94" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>these we must avoid, but first and foremost we should be careful that we are never found
          doing any cowardly deed or making any unjust concessions to the foe; for it would be
          shameful if we, who once<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Spartan supremacy lasted,
            theoretically, more than thirty years, from the end of the Peloponnesian War (<date
              when="-0404">404 B.C.</date>) to the battle of Leuctra. Meantime, however, the
            Athenians secured for a short period their second naval empire (<date when="-0378">378
              B.C.</date>).</note> were thought worthy to rule the Hellenes, should be seen carrying
          out their commands, and should fall so far below our forefathers that, while they were
          willing to die in order that they might dictate to others,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Thucydides, i. 140, puts in the mouth of Pericles the assertion that the Spartans
            prefer to resolve their complaints by war and not by words, dictating terms instead of
            bringing charges.</note> we would not dare to hazard a battle in order that we might
          prevent others from dictating to us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="95" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> We may well be ashamed when we think of the Olympian and the other national assemblies,
          where every one of us used to be more envied and more admired than the athletes who carry
          off victories in the games. But who would dare attend them now, when instead of being
          honored he would be scorned, when instead of being sought out by all because of his valor,
          he would be conspicuous among all for his cowardice, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="96" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and when, more than all this, he would see our slaves bringing from the land which our
          fathers bequeathed to us first-fruits of the harvest and sacrifices greater than our own,
          and would hear from their lips such taunts as you would expect from men who once were
          subjected to the strictest bondage but now have made a treaty with their masters on terms
          of equality? How keenly every one of us would smart under these insults no man alive could
          set forth in words. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="97" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> These are the things about which we must take counsel, and we must not wait to indulge
          our resentment until that will no longer avail us, but must consider now how we may
          prevent such a disaster. For it is disgraceful that we, who in former times would not
          allow even free men the right of equal speech, are now openly tolerating licence of speech
          on the part of slaves.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Others translate <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">i)shgari/as</foreign> as “political unity” and understand <foreign
              xml:lang="greek">tw=n e)leuqe/rwn</foreign> to refer to the allies of <placeName
              key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>. But the passage is probably better taken as
            referring to the military harshness of the Spartans toward any and all with whom they
            came in contact, as, for instance, when Astyochus started to beat free men for speaking
            too freely (see <bibl n="Thuc. 8.84">Thuc. 8.84</bibl>).</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="98" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For thus we shall give ground for the suspicion that in time past we have been nothing at
          all but idle boasters, that by nature we are no different from the rest of mankind, and
          that the sternness and dignity of manner which we cultivate is not natural, but a mere
          pose. Let us, therefore, give no such occasion to those who are wont to speak ill of us,
          but let us endeavor to confute their words by patterning our actions after those of our
          forefathers. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="99" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Remember the men who at Dipaea<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In <date when="-0471">471
              B.C.</date> See <bibl n="Hdt. 9.35">Hdt. 9.35</bibl>, and <bibl n="Paus. 8.8.4">Paus.
              8.8.4</bibl>.</note> fought against the Arcadians, of whom we are told that, albeit
          they stood arrayed with but a single line of soldiery, they raised a trophy over thousands
          upon thousands; remember the three hundred who at Thyrea<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In
              <date when="-0542">542 B.C.</date> See <bibl n="Hdt. 1.82">Hdt. 1.82</bibl>, and <bibl
              n="Paus. 2.38.5">Paus. 2.38.5</bibl>. lsocrates confuses two contests, one earlier,
            where three hundred Argives fought against three hundred Spartans, one later, where both
            sides matched their full forces.</note> defeated the whole <placeName key="tgn,5001993"
            >Argive</placeName> force in battle; remember the thousand who went to meet the foe at
            <placeName key="perseus,Thermopylae">Thermopylae</placeName>, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="100" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>who, although they engaged seven hundred thousand of the barbarians, did not flee nor
          suffer defeat, but laid down their lives on the spot where they were stationed,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.90">Isoc. 4.90-92</bibl>.</note>
          acquitting themselves so nobly that even those who eulogize them with all the resources of
          art can find no praises equal to their valor. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="101" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Let us, then, remembering all these things, take up the war with greater vigor, and let
          us not delay in the expectation that others will remedy our present misfortunes, but since
          these have occurred in our own time, let us ourselves endeavor also to end them. It is
          just in such emergencies as these that men of worth must show their superiority; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="102" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for prosperity helps to hide the baseness even of inferior men,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For the thought compare <bibl n="Dem. 2.20">Dem. 2.20</bibl>.</note> but
          adversity speedily reveals every man as he really is; and in adversity we of <placeName
            key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> must show whether we have been in any wise
          better nurtured and trained to valor than the rest of mankind. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="103" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But indeed we are in no wise without hope that out of our present misfortunes may come a
          happy issue. For you are, I am sure, not unaware that ere now many events have occurred of
          such a nature that, at first, all regarded them as calamities and sympathized with those
          on whom they had fallen, while later everyone came to see that these same reverses had
          brought about the greatest blessings. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="104" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But why need I mention remote instances? Even now we should find that those states which
          are foremost—<placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and <placeName
            key="perseus,Thebes">Thebes</placeName>, I mean—have not derived their great progress
          from peace, but that, on the contrary, it was in consequence of their recovery from
          previous reverses in war that one of them was made leader of the Hellenes,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The Athenians won their second naval supremacy after the
            reverses of the Peloponnesian war.</note> while the other has at the present time become
          a greater state than anyone ever expected she would be. Indeed, honors and distinctions
          are wont to be gained, not by repose, but by struggle, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="105" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and these we should strive to win, sparing neither our bodies nor our lives nor anything
          else which we possess. For if we succeed, and are able to raise our city again to the
          eminence from which she has fallen, we shall be more admired than our ancestors, and shall
          not only leave to our descendants no opportunity to surpass our valor, but shall make
          those who wish to sing our praise despair of saying anything equal to our achievements.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="106" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Nor must you forget that the attention of the whole world is fixed upon this assembly and
          on the decision which you shall reach here. Let each one of you, therefore, govern his
          thoughts as one who is giving an account of his own character in a public theater, as it
          were, before the assembled Hellenes. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="107" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now it is a simple matter to reach a wise decision on this question. For if we are
          willing to die for our just rights, not only shall we gain renown, but in time to come we
          shall be able to live securely; but if we show that we are afraid of danger, we shall
          plunge ourselves into endless confusion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="108" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Let us, therefore, challenge one another to pay back to our fatherland the price of our
          nurture, and not suffer <placeName key="tgn,7011065">Lacedaemon</placeName> to be outraged
          and contemned, nor cause those who are friendly to us to be cheated of their hopes, nor
          let it appear that we value life more highly than the esteem of all the world, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="109" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>always remembering that it is a nobler thing to exchange a mortal body for immortal
          glory, and to purchase with a life which at best we shall retain for only a few years a
          fame which will abide with our descendants throughout all the ages<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For the language cf. <bibl n="Dem. 60.27">Dem. 60.27</bibl>, and <bibl
              n="Hyp. 6.24">Hyp. 6.24</bibl>.</note>—a far nobler course than to cling greedily to a
          little span of life and cover ourselves with great disgrace! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="110" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But I think that you would most of all be aroused to prosecute the war if in imagination
          you could see your parents and your children standing, as it were, beside you, the former
          exhorting you not to disgrace the name of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta"
            >Sparta</placeName>, nor the laws under which we were reared, nor the memory of the
          battles fought in their time; the latter demanding the restoration of the country which
          their forefathers bequeathed to them, together with the dominion and the leadership among
          the Hellenes which we ourselves received from our fathers. Not a word could we say in
          answer; never could we deny the justice of either plea. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="111" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I do not know what more I need to add, save only this much—that while numberless wars
          and dangers have fallen to the lot of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName>,
          the enemy have never yet raised a trophy over us when a king from my house was our leader.
          And prudent men, when they have leaders under whom they win success in their battles,
          should also give heed to them, in preference to all others, when they give counsel
          regarding impending wars.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
