<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader type="text">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Num. </title>
				<author n="Appian">Appian</author>
				<editor role="editor">Horace White</editor>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
<name>William Merrill</name>
<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
<name>David Smith</name>
</respStmt>
<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
			</titleStmt><publicationStmt><publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher><pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace><authority>Perseus Project</authority></publicationStmt>
			
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Appian</author>
						<title>The Foreign Wars</title>
						<editor role="editor">Horace White</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>THE MACMILLAN COMPANY</publisher>
							<date>1899</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		
		<encodingDesc>
			<!--<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="medium" method="silent">&Perseus.OCR;</correction>
			</editorialDecl>-->
			<refsDecl n="CTS">
				<cRefPattern n="fragment" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts fragmentary quote</p>
				</cRefPattern>
				
			</refsDecl>
			<!--<refsDecl>
				refState unit="text"/>
				refState unit="section"/>
				</refsDecl>-->
		</encodingDesc>
		
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="eng">English</language>
				<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
				<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		
		
		<revisionDesc><!--
			<change><date>13-Nov-02</date><respStmt><name>DMM</name><resp>markup</resp></respStmt>
				<item>
					$Log: appian.fw_eng.xml,v $
					Revision 1.1  2009-10-07 21:00:33  rsingh04
					began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

					Revision 1.7  2009/08/19 15:57:58  lcerrato
					fixing Athenaeus refs

					Revision 1.6  2009/07/06 17:34:09  student
					edited entity tags CEH

					Revision 1.5  2009/02/27 22:29:25  rsingh04
					fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

					Revision 1.4  2009/01/29 17:19:10  rsingh04
					fixed chunking scheme
					
					Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 21:10:51  packel
					places/dates now actually tagged
					
					Revision 1.2  2004/08/10 13:09:32  amahoney
					fix the XML files so they are valid, make the SGML obsolete so no one is confused
					
				</item></change><change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>--><change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
			<change when="2016-01-05" who="TDBuck">p4 to p5</change>
		</revisionDesc></teiHeader>
	
	
	<text xml:lang="eng">
				<body>
					<div type="edition" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0551.tlg010.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
					<head>NUMIDIAN AFFAIRS</head>
					<div subtype="chapter" type="textpart" n="1">
						<div n="I" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							<bibl>FROM THE VATICAN MSS. OF CARDINAL MAI</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 644</note>
								BOMILCAR being under accusation fled before his trial, <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C. <date when="-0110">110</date></note> and with him Jugurtha, who uttered that famous saying about bribetakers, that "the whole city of Rome could be bought if a purchaser could be found for it."</p></quote>
						</cit></div>
						<div n="II" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							<bibl>FROM PEIRESC</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 645</note>
								Metellus went back to the African province, where he <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0109">109</date></note> was accused by the soldiers of slothfulness toward the enemy and of cruelty toward his own men, because he punished offenders severely.</p></quote>
						</cit></div>
						<div n="III" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							<bibl>FROM PEIRESC</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 646</note>
								Metellus put the whole senate of Vacca to death because <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0108">108</date></note> they had betrayed the Roman garrison to Jugurtha, and with them, also, Turpilius, the prefect of the guard, a Roman citizen, who was under suspicion of being in league with the enemy. After Jugurtha had delivered up to Metellus certain Thracian and Ligurian deserters, the latter cut off the hands of some, and others he buried in the earth up to their stomachs, and after transfixing them with arrows and darts set fire to them while they were still alive.</p></quote>
						</cit></div>
						<div n="IV" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							<bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							<quote><p><note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">Y.R. 647</note>
								When Marius arrived at Cirta messengers came to him  from Bocchus asking that he would send somebody to hold  a conference with him. He accordingly sent Aulus Manlius, <note resp="HW" place="marg" anchored="true">B.C.<date when="-0107">107</date></note> his lieutenant, and Cornelius Sulla, his quæstor. To them Bocchus said that he fought against the Romans on account of the acts of Marius, who had taken from him the territory which he himself had taken from Jugurtha. To this complaint of Bocchus, Manlius replied that the Romans had taken this territory from Syphax by the law of war, and had made a present of it to Masinissa, and that such gifts were made by the Romans to be kept by those who received them during the pleasure of the Senate and people of Rome. Nor did the Romans take back their gifts without reason. Masinissa was dead, and Jugurtha, who had murdered his grandchildren, was at war with the Romans. "It is not right," he said, "that an enemy should keep the gift that we made to a friend, nor should you think that you can take from Jugurtha property that belongs to the Romans." These were the words of Manlius concerning the territory in question.</p></quote>
						</cit></div>
						<div n="V" type="textpart" subtype="fragment"><cit>
							<bibl>FROM "THE EMBASSIES"</bibl>
							<quote><p>Bocchus sent another embassy who were to solicit peace from Marius and urge Sulla to assist them in the negotiation. These ambassadors were despoiled by robbers on the road, but Sulla received them kindly and entertained them until Marius returned from Gætulia. Marius advised them to urge Bocchus to consult with Sulla as to all his affairs. Accordingly, when Bocchus was inclined to betray Jugurtha he sent messengers around to the neighboring Ethiopians (who extend from eastern Ethiopia westward to the Mauritanian Mount Atlas) under pretence of raising a new army, and then asked Marius to send Sulla to him for a conference, and Marius did so. In this way Bocchus himself, and his friend Magdalses, and a certain freedman of Carthage, named Cornelius, deceived Apsar, the friend of Jugurtha, who had been left in Bocchus' camp to keep watch on his doings.</p></quote>
						</cit></div>
					</div>
					</div>
				</body>
			</text>
			
			</TEI>