<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

    <teiHeader type="text">

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Against Philocles </title>
                <author>Dinarchus</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Dinarchus</author>
                        <title>Minor Attic Orators in two volumes, 2, with an English translation by
                            J. O. Burtt, M.A</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1962</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="en">English </language>
                <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <!--
            <change>
                <date>April and May 1992</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                    <resp>(n/a)</resp>
                </respStmt>
                <item>SGML markup</item>
            </change>
        <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split composite text and converted to unicode</item>
      </change>-->
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
        </revisionDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
        <body>
            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>What in Heaven's name are we to say about such men as this? How will you deal
                    with the wickedness of Philocles, who has been convicted by the Areopagus not
                    once only but three times, as you all know, and as you were recently informed in
                    the Assembly? He has lied before all the Athenians and the surrounding crowd,
                    saying that he would prevent Harpalus from putting into the <placeName
                        key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>, when he had been appointed by you
                    as general in command of Munichia and the dockyards, </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>and he dared to take bribes against you all, against your country and your wives
                    and children; he has broken the oath which he swore between the statue of Athena
                    and the table; and he proposed a decree against himself imposing the death
                    penalty on him if he had accepted any of the money which Harpalus brought into
                    the country. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>Yet despite this he dared to come and show himself to you when you knew that he
                    had been proved answerable on all these counts. It is not justice on which he is
                    relying, Athenians; for what has he to do with justice? No, it is audacity and
                    effrontery, in virtue of which he has seen fit to take bribes in the past, to
                    the utter disregard of yourselves and the course of justice in the city, and has
                    now come forward to explain that he is guilty of none of these things. So
                    complete has been his contempt for your apathy. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>The law of the city, which binds us all, lays it down that if anyone breaks an
                    agreement made in the presence of one of the citizens he shall be liable as an
                    offender. Shall this man, who has deceived every Athenian, betrayed the trust
                    which he did not deserve to receive from you, and so done everything in his
                    power to ruin all the city's institutions, claim that he is coming to make his
                    defence against the charge laid against him? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>It is my personal opinion, Athenians, if I am to speak the truth,—as I must,—that
                    there is no question whether the reports bearing on Philocles are true or false;
                    you have simply to consider now the punishment mentioned in the decree and to
                    decide whether you ought to fine a man who has done the city so much harm or
                    sentence him to death,—as he proposed in the decree against
                    himself,—confiscating the property which he has amassed from perquisites like
                    this. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Do you think that this question of the gold is the
                    first occasion when Philocles has shown his dishonesty and that he has never
                    taken bribes against you before? You are wrong. He has been like this a long
                    time, though you did not notice it; indeed you have been fortunate not to have
                    met with his venality on more important occasions; for there is no greater
                    menace than a man whose dishonesty passes unobserved. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>Athenians, will you not all unite in killing one who has plunged many of our
                    citizens into such deep disgrace and guilt, who first opened the way for the
                    gold that has been distributed, exposing the whole of <placeName
                        key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> to blame? Or will you consent to
                    hear this man, who has done so much to harm you, argue that the council of the
                    Areopagus has falsified the reports and that, while he is just and upright and
                    incorruptible, it has published all this in return for favors or bribes? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>Do you realize that, although in the case of other offences you must first
                    consider critically and with deliberation, discovering the truth, and only then
                    administer punishment to the offenders, nevertheless, in cases of obvious and
                    unquestioned treason, you should give first place to anger and the vengeance
                    that goes with it? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>Do you think this man would refrain from selling any one of the things most vital
                    in the city, when you, relying on his loyalty and honesty, had placed him in
                    charge of it? Do you think that there are any triremes in the dockyards which he
                    would not let go, or that he would trouble to keep anything safe, if there was a
                    prospect of escaping detection and receiving double the amount of gold which he
                    has now received? Nothing, gentlemen, is beyond a man of this type. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>For if anyone values silver and gold more highly than his loyalty to you and has
                    no more regard for an oath or for honor and right than he has for making money,
                    then that man, in so far as he is able, will sell Munichia if he has a buyer; he
                    will signal to the enemy and reveal your secrets, he will betray your army and
                    your fleet. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Therefore, Athenians, do not imagine that, in
                    assessing the penalty, you are merely going to judge of the crimes which
                    Philocles has actually committed; you will bear in mind those which he would
                    have committed, had it been in his power. Thank the gods, now that you know the
                    defendant's character, that you have suffered no more grievous harm at his
                    hands, and punish him as your duty and his baseness demand. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>This man, Athenians, has held a cavalry command, three or four times, over
                    reputable men; he has been appointed a general by you more than ten times,
                    unworthy though he was, and has enjoyed honor and aroused emulation because of
                    his reputation for loyalty towards you. Yet he sold and betrayed the dignity of
                    a command conferred by us, reducing himself to the level of Aristogiton and
                    changing from a general into a hireling and a traitor. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>Is this a reason why you, the injured parties, should give way to feelings of
                    consideration for such a person when he himself showed no consideration in
                    treating you and your fellows as he did? Those who could justly claim your pity,
                    Athenians, are not the like of him,—far from it,—they are those whom Philocles
                    would have betrayed if he had had the chance of a good price; and among them are
                    the promontory and harbors, and the dockyards which your ancestors built and
                    left you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>You must remember these, Athenians, and not make light of the reports published
                    by the council. Treat this case<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The sense of
                        this passage is evident, though it is not clear whether Dinarchus is
                        expressing himself loosely or whether, as Blass suggests, a few words have
                        dropped out of the text.</note> as you treated those on which you have
                    already passed judgement. For it is shameful to grow weary of punishing men who
                    have proved traitors to the city, and shameful that any lawbreakers and
                    reprobates should survive, when the gods have exposed them and surrendered them
                    to you for punishment, having seen that the whole people had accused Philocles
                    and handed him over first of all to meet with his deserts before you. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>By Zeus the Savior, I am ashamed that you should
                    need us to encourage you and goad you on before you proceed to punish the
                    defendant now on trial. Are you not eyewitnesses of the crimes he has committed?
                    The whole people considered that it was not safe or right to trust him with
                    their children and so rejected him as Supervisor of the Ephebi. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>Will you, the guardians of democracy and law, spare a man who has behaved like
                    this; you to whom the fortune of lot has entrusted the protection<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Some such meaning seems called for as is
                        presumed by Reiske, but the actual Greek words supplied by him make the
                        future participle <foreign xml:lang="grc">dika/sontas</foreign> rather
                        awkward.</note> of the people by means of the judgement you will give? You
                    are the supreme court of justice in the city. Will you acquit a man guilty of
                    taking bribes and every other crime, who, as I said just now, is unique among
                    criminals in that he has been reported not once merely but three times and might
                    already have been rightly made liable three times to the death penalty by his
                    own decree. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>Then why will you wait, Athenians? What further crimes do you wish to hear of
                    greater than those we have mentioned? Was it not you and your ancestors who made
                    no allowance for Timotheus,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This passage
                        corresponds almost word for word with <bibl n="Din. 1.14">Din. 1.14</bibl>.
                        See note on that.</note> though he had sailed round the <placeName
                        key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnese</placeName> and beaten the Spartans in the
                    sea-fight at <placeName key="tgn,7010886">Corcyra</placeName>, though his father
                    was Conon who liberated <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> and he
                    himself had taken <placeName key="tgn,7002673">Samos</placeName>, <placeName
                        key="perseus,Methone">Methone</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Pydna"
                        >Pydna</placeName>, Potidaea, and twenty cities besides? You did not take
                    this record into consideration at all, or allow such services to outweigh the
                    case before you or the oaths which you swear before giving your verdict, but
                    fined him a hundred talents, because Aristophon said he had been bribed by the
                    Chians and Rhodians. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>Will you then acquit<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">An apodosis conveying some
                        such meaning as this, which is needed to complete the sense of the sentence,
                        seems to have dropped out of the Greek text.</note> this abominable man,
                    reported not by one individual but by the whole council of the Areopagus, after
                    an investigation, to be holding bribes against you; who, though he has ample
                    means and no male heirs and lacks nothing else that a normal man could need, did
                    not withhold his hand from the bribes offered against his country or suppress
                    his natural depravity, but destroyed entirely his reputation for loyalty towards
                    you, by ranging himself with those whom he once professed to oppose and proving
                    that his counterfeited honesty was sham? </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Let every one of you bear these points in mind,
                    Athenians, and remember the present circumstances, which call for good faith,
                    not corruption. You must hate the wicked, wipe out such monsters from the city,
                    and show the world that the mass of people have not been corrupted with a few
                    orators and generals and are not cowed by their reputation; for they realize
                    that with integrity and agreement among ourselves we shall easily triumph, by
                    the grace of the gods, if anyone unjustly attacks us, but that with bribery and
                    treason and the allied vices practiced by men like this no city could survive.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>Therefore, Athenians, do not admit any request or plea for pity; do not condone
                    the guilt which you have seen fastened upon the defendants in the plain light of
                    facts, or invalidate the council's report<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Some
                        words have clearly dropped out from this passage. No certain restoration is
                        possible, although the general sense is not difficult to conjecture. The
                        restoration of Sauppe is followed in the translation.</note>; but one and
                    all assist your country and the laws, since both are now on trial against this
                    man's iniquity. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>The whole country will be affected by the verdict you are about to give: the
                    shrines which have been erected in it, the agelong traditions, and the
                    constitution which your ancestors have handed down to you. It is not a question
                    of Philocles alone; for he has condemned himself to death long ago. In
                    addressing these entreaties to you I am urging a far juster plea than the men
                    who have committed these shameful acts: I am asking you not to desert the things
                    for which your ancestors faced many dangers, not to turn the city's honor into
                    utter shame, and not to let personal regard for the defendants override your
                    respect for the laws, the people's decrees, and the reports of the council. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>>For let me make it quite clear to you, Athenians, quite clear, that you are
                    being applauded universally in consequence of the inquiries held upon this
                    money, and that men who have been convicted of taking bribes against their own
                    country are regarded as wicked and injurious, haters of democracy, professing,
                    as they do, to be your friends and to work for the city's interests, and having
                    made their reputation thanks to you.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                        concluding sentences of the speech are lost.</note></p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
