<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On Hunting</title>
				<author>Xenophon</author>
				<editor role="transl">E. C. Marchant, G. W. Bowersock, tr. Constitution of the
					Athenians.</editor>
				<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
				<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
					<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
					<name>William Merrill</name>
					<name>Elli Mylonas</name>
					<name>David Smith</name>
				</respStmt>
				<funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB Project</funder>

			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
				<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
			</publicationStmt>


			<notesStmt>
				<note anchored="true">Text scanned at St. Olaf 1990.</note>
			</notesStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<author>Xenophon</author>
						<title>Xenophon in Seven Volumes, 7</title>
						<editor role="transl">E. C. Marchant, G. W. Bowersock, tr. Constitution of
							the Athenians.</editor>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Harvard University Press, Cambridge, MA; William Heinemann,
								Ltd., London.</publisher>
							<date>1925</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>

		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<refsDecl n="CTS">
				<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
					replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and section</p>
				</cRefPattern>
				<cRefPattern n="chapter" matchPattern="(\w+)"
					replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
					<p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
				</cRefPattern>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<!--<refState unit="text"/>-->
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="eng">English</language>
				<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
		<revisionDesc>
			<change when="2016-12-06" who="Lisa Cerrato">CTS and EpiDoc conversion</change>
			<change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
			<change when="2014-07-01" who="Stella Dee">split speeches and converted to unicode</change>
			<change when="1992-10-29" who="das">added HEAD's and REFDECL's; glued minor works together</change>
			<change when="1992-08-11" who="das">changed chapters to div2's</change>
			<change when="1992-06-01" who="wpm and das">tagged text to conform with prose.e dtd.</change>
		</revisionDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text>

		<body>
			<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0032.tlg014.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Game and hounds are the invention of gods, of
						Apollo and Artemis. They bestowed it on Cheiron and honoured him therewith
						for his righteousness. And he, receiving it, rejoiced in the gift, and used
						it. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>And he had for pupils in venery and in other noble pursuits—Cephalus,
						Asclepius, Meilanion, Nestor, Amphiaraus, Peleus, Telamon, Meleager,
						Theseus, Hippolytus, Palamedes, Odysseus, Menestheus, Diomedes, Castor,
						Polydeuces, Machaon, Podaleirius, Antilochus, Aeneas, Achilles, of whom each
						in his time was honoured by gods. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>Let no man marvel that the more part of these, even though they pleased gods, died none the
							less; for that was nature’s work; but the praise of them grew
							mightily;—nor yet that not all of these flourished at one time. For
							Cheiron’s lifetime sufficed for all. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>For Zeus and Cheiron were brethren, sons of one sire, but the mother of the
						one was Rhea, of the other the nymph Nais: and so, though he was born before
						these, he died after them, for he taught Achilles. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Through the heed they paid to hounds and
						hunting and the rest of their scholarship they excelled greatly and were
						admired for their virtue. Cephalus was carried away by a goddess.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Aurora.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>Asclepius won yet,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The <foreign
						xml:lang="grc">κὰι</foreign> before <foreign xml:lang="grc"
							>ὑπὸ</foreign> in the text should probably be placed before
						<foreign xml:lang="grc">μειζόνων</foreign>.</note> greater
						preferment—to raise the dead, to heal the sick; and for these things he has
						everlasting fame as a god among men. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>Meilanion was so peerless in love of toil that, though the princeliest of
						that age were his rival suitors for the greatest Lady of the time, only he
						won Atalanta. Nestor’s virtue is an old familiar tale to Greek ears; so
						there is no need for me to tell of it. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>Amphiaraus when he fought against <placeName key="perseus,Thebes"
							>Thebes</placeName>, gained great praise and won from the gods the
						honour of immortality. Peleus stirred a desire even in the gods to give him
						Thetis and to hymn their marriage in Cheiron’s home. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p>Telamon waxed so mighty that he wedded from the greatest city the maiden of
						his choice, Periboea, daughter of Alcathus: and when the first of the
						Greeks, Heracles son of Zeus, distributed the prizes of valour after taking
							<placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>, to him he gave Hesione/.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p>As for Meleager, the honours that he won are manifest; and it was not by his
						own fault that he came to sorrow when his father in old age forgot the
							goddess.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., when his father Oeneus
							forgot Artemis,—a lapse which led ultimately to the death of
							Meleager.</note> Theseus single-handed slew the enemies of all
							<placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>; and because he enlarged
						greatly the borders of his country he is admired to this day. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p>Hippolytus was honoured by Artemis and held converse with her; and for his
						prudence and holiness he was counted happy when he died. Palamedes far
						outstripped the men of his generation in wisdom while he lived; and being
						unjustly slain he won from the gods such vengeance as fell to the lot of no
						other mortal. But his end was not compassed by those<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">Odysseus and Diomedes, who, according to one account,
							drowned Palamedes when he was fishing. The reference here may be to this
							version. In <title>Memorabilia</title> 4.2.4 X. follows the commoner
							version that Odysseus got P. put to death by a false charge of
							treachery; and in the <title>Odyssey</title> attributed to the
							rhetorician Alcidamus, Diomedes and Sthenelus are associated with
							Odysseus in bringing this charge. In revenge for his death his father
							Nauplius caused the shipwreck of the Greek fleet off the south of
								<placeName key="tgn,7002677">Euboea</placeName>.</note> whom some
						imagine, else could not the one of them have been well-nigh the best, and
						the other the peer of the good; but bad men did the deed. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
					<p>Menestheus through the heed he paid to hunting, so far surpassed others in
						love of toil that the first of the Greeks confessed themselves his inferiors
						in feats of war, all save Nestor; and he, it is said,<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">In <title>Iliad</title> 2.555.</note> outdid not, but
						rivalled him. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
					<p>Odysseus and Diomedes were brilliant in every single deed, and in short, to
						them was due the capture of <placeName key="perseus,Troy">Troy</placeName>.
						Castor and Polydeuces, through the renown that they won by displaying in
							<placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> the arts they learned of
						Cheiron, are immortal. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
					<p>Machaon and Podaleirius, schooled in all the selfsame arts, proved in crafts
						and reasonings and wars good men. Antilochus, by giving his life for his
							father,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">How Antilochus, son of Nestor,
							saved his father’s life is told by Pindar in the sixth
								<title>Pythian</title>.</note> won such glory that he alone was
						proclaimed among the Greeks as <q type="emph">the Devoted Son.</q> </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
					<p>Aeneas saved the gods of his father’s and his mother’s family, and withal his
						father himself; wherefore he bore away fame for his piety, so that to him
						alone among all the vanquished at <placeName key="perseus,Troy"
							>Troy</placeName> even the enemy granted not to be despoiled. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
					<p>Achilles, nursed in this schooling, bequeathed to posterity memorials so
						great and glorious that no man wearies of telling and hearing of him. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>These, whom the good love even to this day and
						the evil envy, were made so perfect through the care they learned of Cheiron
						that, when troubles fell upon any state or any king in <placeName
							key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>, they were composed through their
						influence; or if all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName> was at
						strife or at war with all the Barbarian powers, these brought victory to the
						Greeks, so that they made <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Greece</placeName>
						invincible. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Therefore I charge the young not to despise
						hunting or any other schooling. For these are the means by which men become
						good in war and in all things out of which must come excellence in thought
						and word and deed. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The first pursuit, therefore, that a young man
						just out of his boyhood should take up is hunting, and afterwards he should
						go on to the other branches of education, provided he has means. He must
						look to his means, and, if they are sufficient, spend as much as the benefit
						to himself is worth; or, if they are insufficient, at least let him supply
						enthusiasm, in no way coming short of his power.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">The text of this paragraph is open to suspicion. The
							words from <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἶτα</foreign> to <foreign
								xml:lang="grc">ἔχοντα</foreign> may be an afterthought.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I will give a list and a description of the
						intending hunter’s outfit, and the explanation of each item, in order that
						he may understand the business before he puts his hand to it. And let no one
						regard these details as trivial; inasmuch as nothing can be done without
						them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The net-keeper should be a man with a keen
						interest in the business, one who speaks Greek, about twenty years old,
						agile and strong, and resolute, that, being well qualified to overcome his
						tasks, he may take pleasure in the business. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>The purse-nets should be made of fine Phasian<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">i.e., Colchian. Much flax and linen was exported from
								<placeName key="tgn,7016642">Colchis</placeName>.</note> or
						Carthaginian flax, and the road-nets and hayes of the same material.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Let the purse-nets be of nine threads woven in
						three strands, each strand consisting of three threads. The proper length
						for these nets is forty-five inches, the proper width of the meshes six
						inches. The cords that run round<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The cords
							meant here are those that ran round the mouth of the purse, and served
							as a running noose to close it when the hare got in.</note> them must be
						without knots, so that they may run easily. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p>The road-nets should be of twelve threads, and the hayes of sixteen. The
						length of the road-nets may be twelve, twenty-four or thirty-feet; that of
						the hayes sixty, a hundred and twenty, or a hundred and eighty feet. If they
						are longer, they will be unwieldy. Both kinds should be thirty knots<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., ten meshes, so that the extreme
							height, if the net was fully stretched, would be five feet. Poachers now
							use slip-knots or nets about four feet deep with a mesh of
							two-and-a-half inches.</note> high, and should have meshes of the same
						width as those of the purse-nets. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>At the elbows at either end let the road-nets have slip-knots of string and
						the hayes metal rings,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The rings running
							down the two sides were used for joining two nets together.</note> and
						let the cords<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., the cords running along
							the top and bottom of the nets.</note> be attached by loops. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>The stakes for the purse-nets should be thirty inches long, but some should
						be shorter. Those of unequal length are for use on sloping ground, to make
						the height of the nets equal, while those of the same length are used on the
						level. These stakes must be so shaped at the top that the nets will pull off
						readily and they must be smooth.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The author
							means, I think, to imply a contrast between the stakes of the purse-nets
							and those of the other nets. The second <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>αὗται</foreign> in the text can scarcely be right: possibly
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">καὶ αὗται λεῖαι</foreign> should be
							omitted, or <foreign xml:lang="grc">αὐταί</foreign>, <gloss>they
							themselves,</gloss> read with Dindorf.</note> The stakes for the road-nets
						should be twice the length of these, and those for the hayes forty-five
						inches long. The latter<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Or perhaps he means
							both sets. </note> should have little forks with shallow grooves, and
						all should be stout, of a thickness proportioned to the length. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>The number of stakes used for the hayes may be large or small; fewer are
						required if the nets are strained tight when set up, more if they are slack.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p>A calf-skin bag will be wanted for carrying the purse-nets and road-nets and
						hayes and the bill-hooks for cutting wood and stopping gaps where necessary.
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The hounds used are of two kinds, the
						Castorian and the Vulpine.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Both are
							Laconian varieties, the Castorian being much the larger. The Vulpine
							resembled a fox; hence the erroneous idea that it was a hybrid between
							dog and fox (O. Keller, <title>die antike Tierwelt</title>, i.
							121).</note> The Castorian is so called because Castor paid special
						attention to the breed, making a hobby of the business. The Vulpine is a
						hybrid between the dog and the fox: hence the name. In the course of time
						the nature of the parents has become fused. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>Inferior specimens (that is to say, the majority) show one or more of the
						following defects. They are small, hook-nosed, grey-eyed, blinking,
						ungainly, stiff, weak, thin-coated, lanky, ill-proportioned, cowardly,
						dull-scented, unsound in the feet. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>Now small dogs often drop out of the running through their want of size;
						hook-nosed dogs have no mouth and can’t hold the hare; grey-eyed dogs and
						blinkers have bad sight; ungainly dogs look ugly; stiff ones are in a bad
						way at the end of the hunt; no work can be got out of the weak and the
						thin-coated ones; those that are lanky and ill-proportioned are heavy movers
						and carry themselves anyhow; cowards leave their work and give up and slink
						away from the sun into shady places and lie down; dogs with no nose seldom
						scent the hare and only with difficulty; and those with bad feet, even if
						they are plucky, can’t stand the hard work, and tire because they are
						foot-sore. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Moreover, hounds of the same breed vary much
						in behaviour when tracking. Some go ahead as soon as they find the line
						without giving a sign, and there is nothing to show that they are on it.
						Some move the ears only, but keep the tail still; others keep the ears still
						and wag the tip of the tail. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p>Others prick up the ears<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Greek hound had
							short ears (cf. 4.1) like a foxterrier.</note> and run frowning along
						the track, dropping their tails and putting them between their legs. Many do
						none of these things, but rush about madly round the track, and when they
						happen upon it, stupidly trample out the traces, barking all the time. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>Others again, continually circling and straying, get ahead of the line when
						clean off it and pass the hare, and every time they run against the line,
						begin guessing, and if they catch sight of the hare, tremble and never go
						for her until they see her stir. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>Hounds that run forward and frequently examine the discoveries of the others
						when they are casting about and pursuing have no confidence in themselves;
						while those that will not let their cleverer mates go forward, but fuss and
						keep them back, are confident to a fault. Others will drive ahead, eagerly
						following false lines and getting wildly excited over anything that turns
						up, well knowing that they are playing the fool; others will do the same
						thing in ignorance. Those that stick to game paths and don’t recognise the
						true line are poor tools. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>A hound that ignores the trail<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><q type="written">The trail of
							the hare is the path she takes in going to her seat.</q>—Beckford.</note>
						and races over the track of the hare on the run is ill-bred. Some, again,
						will pursue hotly at first, and then slack off from want of pluck; others
						will cut in ahead and then get astray; while others foolishly dash into
						roads and go astray, deaf to all recall. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p>Many abandon the pursuit and go back through their hatred of game, and many
						through their love of man. Others try to mislead by baying on the track,
						representing false lines as true ones. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p>Some, though free from this fault, leave their own work when they hear a
						shout from another quarter while they are running, and make for it
						recklessly. When pursuing some are dubious, others are full of assumptions
						but their notions are wrong. Then there are the skirters, some of whom
						merely pretend to hunt, while others out of jealousy perpetually scamper
						about together beside the line. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Now most of these faults are natural defects,
						but some by which hounds are spoilt are due to unintelligent training.
						Anyhow such hounds may well put a keen hunter off the sport. What hounds of
						the same breed<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The author’s ideal harrier
							is clearly the Castorian.</note> ought to look like and what they should
						be in other respects I will now explain. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>First, then, they should be big. Next, the
						head should be light, flat<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">In
							profile.</note> and muscular; the lower parts of the forehead sinewy;
						the eyes prominent, black and sparkling; the forehead broad, with a deep
						dividing line; the ears small and thin with little hair behind; the neck
						long, loose and round; the chest broad and fairly fleshy; the
						shoulder-blades slightly outstanding from the shoulders; the forelegs short,
						straight, round and firm; the elbows straight<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">i.e., not bent inwards or outwards.</note>; the ribs not
						low down on the ground,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">So Pollux read, for
							he says 
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">μὴ πρὸς τὴν γῆν βαθυνομένας.</foreign> The sense is then that the ribs are not to
							be low on the ground when the hound is couchant, but well tucked up
							behind. <foreign xml:lang="grc">ἐπίπαν βαθείας</foreign>, <gloss>deep
							throughout,</gloss> would apply to the depth from wall to wall, and the meaning
							would be that the ribs are to contract towards the flanks.</note> but
						sloping in an oblique line; the loins fleshy, of medium length, and neither
						too loose nor too hard; the flanks of medium size; the hips round and fleshy
						at the back, not close at the top, and smooth on the inside<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">i.e., without folds in the coat towards the
							loins.</note>; the under part of the belly itself slim; the tail long,
						straight and thin; the thighs hard; the shanks<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">From the elbows to the feet.</note> long, round and
						solid; the hind-legs much longer than the fore-legs and slightly bent; the
						feet round. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>Hounds like these will be strong in appearance, agile, well-proportioned, and
						speedy; and they will have a jaunty expression and a good mouth. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When tracking they should get out of the game
						paths quickly, hold their heads well down and aslant, smiling when they find
						the scent and lowering their ears; then they should all go forward together
						along the trail towards the form circling frequently,<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">A participle to govern <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>κύκλους πολλοὺς</foreign> has dropped out of the text.</note>
						with eyes continually on the move and tails wagging. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>As soon as they are close on the hare, they should let the huntsman know,
						quickening the pace and showing more emphatic signs by their excitement,
						movements of the head and eyes, changes of attitude, by looking up and
						looking into the covert and returning again and again to the hare’s form, by
						leaps forward, backward and to the side, displays of unaffected agitation
						and overpowering delight at being near the hare. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>They should pursue with unremitting vigour,
						giving tongue and barking freely, dogging the hare’s steps wherever she
						goes. They should be fast and brilliant in the chase, frequently casting
						about and giving tongue in the right fashion; and they should not leave the
						track and go back to the huntsman. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Along with this appearance and behaviour they
						should have pluck, keen noses, sound feet and good coats. They will be
						plucky if they don’t leave the hunting-ground when the heat is oppressive;
						keen-nosed if they smell the hare on bare, parched and sunny ground in the
						dog days<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The older commentators are
							probably right in understanding the allusion to be to the Dog-star, not
							to the Sun.</note>; sound in the feet if at the same season their feet
						are not torn to bits during a run in the mountains; they will have a good
						coat if the hair is fine, thick and soft. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>The colour of the hounds should not be entirely tawny, black or white; for
						this is not a sign of good breeding: on the contrary, unbroken colour
						indicates a wild strain. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>So the tawny and the black hounds should show a patch of white about the
						face, and the white hounds a tawny patch. At the top of the thighs the hair
						should be straight and thick, and on the loins and at the lower end of the
						tail, but it should be moderately thick higher up. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It is advisable to take the hounds to the
						mountains often, but less frequently to cultivated land. For in the
						mountains it is possible to track and follow a hare without hindrance,
						whereas it is impossible to do either in cultivated land owing to the game
						paths. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It is also well to take the hounds out into
						rough ground, whether they find a hare or not; for they get sound in the
						feet, and hard work in such country is good for their bodies. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p>In summer they should be out till midday, in winter at any hour of the day,
						in autumn at any time except midday, and before evening during the spring;
						for at these times the temperature is mild. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The scent of the hare lies long in winter
						owing to the length of the nights, and for a short time in summer for the
						opposite reason. In the winter, however, there is no scent in the early
						morning whenever there is a white frost or the earth is frozen hard. For
						both white and black frost hold heat; since the one draws it out by its own
						strength, and the other congeals it. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>The hounds’ noses, too, are numbed by the cold, and they cannot smell when
						the tracks are in such a state until the tracks thaw in the sun or as day
						advances. Then the dogs can smell and the scent revives. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>A heavy dew, again, obliterates scent by carrying it downwards; and storms,
						occurring after a long interval, draw smells from the ground<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign xml:lang="grc">ἄγειν τῆς
								γῆς</foreign> has no parallel in Greek prose: perhaps <foreign
									xml:lang="grc">ἐκ</foreign> has fallen out or <foreign
										xml:lang="grc">τὴν γῆν</foreign> should be read.</note> and make
						the earth bad for scent until it dries. South winds spoil scent, because the
						moisture scatters it, but north winds concentrate and preserve it, if it has
						not been previously dissolved. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>Heavy showers drown it, and so does light rain, and the moon deadens it by
						its warmth,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Or <gloss>deadens the heat</gloss> if we
							read <foreign xml:lang="grc">τὸ θερμόν</foreign> with Gesner. But
							the Greeks did attribute heat to the moon.</note> especially when at the
						full. Scent is most irregular at that time, for the hares, enjoying the
						light, fling themselves high in the air and jump a long way, frolicking with
						one another; and it becomes confused when foxes have crossed it. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p>Spring with its genial temperature yields a clear scent, except where the
						ground is studded with flowers and hampers the hounds by mingling the odours
						of the flowers with it. In summer it is thin and faint, for the ground,
						being baked, obliterates what warmth it possesses, which is thin; and the
						hounds’ noses are not so good at that season, because their bodies are
						relaxed. In the autumn it is unimpeded; for the cultivated crops have been
						harvested and the weeds have withered, so that the odours of the herbage do
						not cause trouble by mingling with it. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>In winter and summer and autumn the scent lies straight in the main. In
						spring it is complicated; for though the animal couples at all times, it
						does so especially at this season;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
							<q type="emph">March hare.</q></note> so instinct prompts them to roam about together,
						and this is the result they produce. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The scent left by the hare in going to her
						form lasts longer than the scent of a running hare. For on the way to the
						form the hare keeps stopping, whereas when on the run she goes fast;
						consequently the ground is packed with it in the one case, but in the other
						is not filled with it. In coverts it is stronger than in open ground,
						because she touches many objects while running about and sitting up. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>They find a resting-place where there is
						anything growing or lying on the ground, underneath anything, on the top of
						the objects, inside, alongside, well away or quite near or fairly near;
						occasionally even in the sea<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <q type="emph">The
							Hare,</q> <title>Fur and Feather</title> Series, p. 38 f.</note> by
						springing on to anything she<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
							fluctuation between plural and singular is in the Greek.</note> can
						reach, or in fresh water, if there is anything sticking out or growing in
						it, the hare,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The distinction is not, as
							often supposed, between hares with different <title>habits</title>
							(<gloss>squatters,</gloss> <foreign xml:lang="grc">εὑναῖοι,</foreign> and
							<gloss>roamers,</gloss> <foreign xml:lang="grc">δρομαῖοι</foreign>—a non-existent
							distinction), but merely between the behaviour of all hares in different
							circumstances. The unusual, but not unexampled, position of the
							article—<foreign xml:lang="grc">ὁ</foreign> and <foreign
								xml:lang="grc">οἱ</foreign>—has misled interpreters. Blane saw
							the true meaning.</note> when going to her </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p>form generally choosing a sheltered place for it in cold weather and a cool
						one in hot, but in spring and autumn a place exposed to the sun; but hares
						on the run do not do that, because they are scared by the hounds. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p>When she sits, she puts the hind-legs under the flanks, and most commonly
						keeps the fore-legs close together and extended, resting the chin on the
						ends of the feet, and spreading the ears over the shoulder-blades, so
							that<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">I do not think that <foreign
								xml:lang="grc">εἷτα δὲ</foreign> can mean this, and suspect
								that <foreign xml:lang="grc">εἷτα</foreign> is wrong.</note> she
						covers the soft parts. The hair too, being thick and soft, serves as a
						protection. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p>When awake she blinks her eyelids; but when she is asleep the eyelids are
						wide open and motionless, and the eyes still. She moves her nostrils
						continually when sleeping, but less frequently when awake. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
					<p>When the ground is bursting with vegetation they frequent the fields rather
						than the mountains. Wherever she may be she remains there when tracked,
						except when she is suddenly alarmed at night; in which case she moves off.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The animal is so prolific that at the same
						time she is rearing one litter, she produces another and she is pregnant.
						The scent of the little leverets is stronger than that of the big ones; for
						while their limbs are still soft they drag the whole body on the ground.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
					<p>Sportsmen, however, leave the very young ones to the goddess.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Artemis.</note> Yearlings go very fast in
						the first run, but then flag, being agile, but weak. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Find the hare’s track by beginning with the
						hounds in the cultivated lands and gradually working downwards.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The cultivated land is on the lower slopes
							of the mountains.</note> To track those that do not come into cultivated
						land, search<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">There is evidently a gap in
							the Greek before <foreign xml:lang="grc">τοὺς λειμῶνας</foreign>,
							which has nothing to govern it.</note> the meadows, valleys, streams,
						stones and woody places. If she moves off, don’t shout, or the hounds may
						get wild with excitement and fail to recognise the tracks. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
					<p>Hares when found by hounds and pursued sometimes cross brooks and double back
						and slip into gullies or holes. The fact is they are terrified not only of
						the hounds, but of eagles as well; for they are apt to be snatched up while
						crossing hillocks and bare ground until<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Not
							<gloss>so long as</gloss>; cf. 14.</note> they are yearlings, and the bigger ones are
						run down and caught by the hounds. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The swiftest are those that frequent
						mountains; those of the plain are not so speedy; and those of the marshes
						are the slowest. Those that roam over any sort of country are difficult to
						chase, since they know the short cuts. They run mostly uphill<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e. when pursued.</note> or on the level,
						less frequently in uneven ground, and very seldom downhill. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
					<p>When being pursued they are most conspicuous across ground that has been
						broken up, if they have some red in their coats, or across stubble, owing to
						the shadow they cast. They are also conspicuous in game paths and on roads
						if these are level, since the bright colour of their coats shows up in the
						light. But when their line of retreat is amongst stones, in the mountains,
						over rocky or thickly wooded ground they cannot be seen owing to the
						similarity of colouring. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
					<p>When they are well ahead of the hounds, they will stop, and sitting up will
						raise themselves and listen for the baying or the footfall of the hounds
						anywhere near; and should they hear the sound of them from any quarter, they
						make off. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
					<p>Occasionally, even when they hear no sound, some fancy or conviction prompts
						them to jump hither and thither past and through the same objects, mixing
						the tracks as they retreat. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
					<p>The longest runners are those that are found on bare land, because they are
						exposed to view; the shortest, those found in thick covers, since the
						darkness hinders their flight.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>There are two species of hare.<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The common hare and a smaller variety of the
							same; which is said to be <q type="emph">more brindled in colour</q> than the larger
							kind. See <q type="emph">The Hare</q> in <title>Fur and Feather</title> Series,
							p.5.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
					<p>The large are dark brown, and the white patch on the forehead is large; the
						smaller are chestnut, with a small white patch. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
					<p>The larger have spots round the scut, the smaller at the side of it. The eyes
						in the large species are blue, in the small grey. The black at the tip of
						the ear is broad in the one species, narrow in the other. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
					<p>The smaller are found in most of the islands, both desert and inhabited. They
						are more plentiful in the islands than on the mainland, for in the majority
						of these there are no foxes to attack and carry off the hares and their
						young; nor eagles, for they haunt big mountains rather than small, and the
						mountains in the islands, generally speaking, are rather small. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
					<p>Hunters seldom visit the desert islands, and there are few people in the
						inhabited ones, and most of them are not sportsmen; and if an island is
						consecrated, one may not even take dogs into it. Since, then, but few of the
						old hares and the leverets that they produce are exterminated by hunting,
						they are bound to be abundant. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The sight of the hare is not keen for several
						reasons. The eyes are prominent; the lids are too small and do not give
						protection to the pupils; consequently the vision is weak and blurred. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="27">
					<p>Added to this, though the animal spends much time asleep, it gets no benefit
						from that, so far as seeing goes. Its speed, too, accounts in no small
						degree for its dim sight. For it glances at an object and is past it in a
						flash, before realising its nature. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="28">
					<p>And those terrors, the hounds, close behind them when they are pursued
						combine with these causes to rob them of their wits. The consequence is that
						the hare bumps against many obstacles unawares and plunges into the net.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="29">
					<p>If she ran straight, she would seldom meet with this mishap. But instead of
						that she comes round and hugs the place where she was born and bred, and so
						is caught. In a fair run she is seldom beaten by the hounds owing to her
						speed. Those that are caught are beaten in spite of their natural
						characteristics through meeting with an accident. Indeed, there is nothing
						in the world of equal size to match the hare as a piece of mechanism. For
						the various parts that make up her body are formed as follows. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="30">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The head is light, small, drooping, narrow at
						the front; the ears are upright;<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><q type="mentioned">The ears
							are upright</q> is not in the MSS., and is inserted from Pollux. As our
							author is enumerating those characteristics of the hare that make for
							speed, it is not quite certain that the words are his, but see
							33.</note> the neck is thin, round, not stiff, and fairly long; the
						shoulder-blades are straight and free at the top; the fore-legs are agile
						and close together; the chest is not broad; the ribs are light and
						symmetrical; the loins are circular; the rump is fleshy; the flanks are soft
						and fairly spongy; the hips are round, well filled out, and the right
						distance apart at the top; the thighs are small and firm, muscular on the
						outside and not puffy on the inside; the shanks are long and firm; the
						fore-feet are extremely pliant and narrow and straight and the hind-feet
						hard and broad; and all four are indifferent to rough ground; the hind-legs
						are much longer than the fore-legs, and slightly bent outwards; the coat is
						short and light. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="31">
					<p>With such a frame she cannot fail to be strong, pliant and very agile.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Here is a proof of her agility. When going
						quietly, she springs—no one ever saw or ever will see a hare
						walking—bringing the hind-feet forward in advance of the fore-feet and
						outside them; and that is how she runs. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="32">
					<p>This is obvious when snow is on the ground. The scut is of no assistance in
						running, for it is not able to steer the body owing to its shortness. The
						hare does this by means of one of her ears; and when she is roused by the
						hounds she drops one ear on the side on which she is being pressed and
						throws it aslant, and then bearing on this she wheels round sharply and in a
						moment leaves the assailant far behind. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="33">
					<p>So charming is the sight that to see a hare tracked, found, pursued and
						caught is enough to make any man forget his heart’s desire. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="34">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When hunting on cultivated land avoid growing
						crops and let pools and streams alone. It is unseemly and wrong to interfere
						with them, and there is a risk of encouraging those who see to set
						themselves against the law.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Both text and
							meaning are doubtful here. By <q type="mentioned">the law</q> is probably meant the law (or
							custom?) that allowed hunters to hunt over growing crops. See
							12.5.</note> On days on which there is no hunting,<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">i.e., during festivals.</note> all hunting tackle should
						be removed. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The trappings of hounds are collars, leashes,
						and surcingles. The collars should be soft and broad, so as not to chafe the
						hounds’ coat. The leashes should have a noose for the hand, and nothing
						else; for if the collar is made in one piece with the leash, perfect control
						of the hounds is impossible. The straps of the surcingles should be broad,
						so as not to rub the flanks, and they should have little spurs sewed on to
						them, to keep the breed pure. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Hounds should not be taken out hunting when
						off their feed, since this is a proof that they are ailing; nor when a
						strong wind is blowing, since it scatters the scent and they cannot smell,
						and the purse-nets will not stand in position, nor the hayes. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>But when neither of these hindrances prevents, have the hounds out every
						other day. Do not let them take to pursuing foxes; for it is utter ruin, and
						they are never at hand when wanted. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>Vary the hunting-ground frequently, so that the hounds may be familiar with
						the hunting-grounds and the master with the country. Start early, and so
						give the hounds a fair chance of following the scent. A late start robs the
						hounds of the find and the hunters of the prize; for the scent is by its
						nature too thin to last all day. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Let the net-keeper wear light clothing when he
						goes hunting. Let him set up the purse-nets in winding, rough, steep,
						narrow, shady paths, brooks, ravines, running watercourses (these are the
						places in which the hare is most apt to take refuge: a list of all the
						others would be endless), leaving </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>unobstructed and narrow passages to and through these places, just about
						daybreak, and not too early, so that in case the line of nets be near the
						growth to be searched, the hare may not be frightened by hearing the noise
						close by (if the distance is considerable, it matters less if the work is
						done early), seeing that the nets stand clear so that nothing may cling to
							them.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This portentous sentence is a
							literal presentation of the Greek text, which, however, is rather
							uncertain. If the nets are fixed near the covert before daybreak, the
							hare is likely to stir at the noise. After daybreak she will not
							stir.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>He must fix the stakes asland,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., sloping
							towards the side from which the hare will come. The nets, of course,
							hang on the other side of the stakes.</note> so that when pulled they
						may stand the strain. On the tops of them let him put an equal number of
							meshes,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">If <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>ἴσους</foreign> means <gloss>equal in number,</gloss> more than one mesh is to
							be put in the groove of each stake, so that the top of the row of nets
							will be puckered. Perhaps, however, <q type="emph">level in height</q> is the
							sense.</note> and set the props<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Small
							sticks were used for propping up the purse on the inside, and the purse
							was propped higher towards the middle; it ended in a point, so that it
							resembled the net on a woman’s head.</note> uniformly, raising the purse
						towards the centre. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>To the cord<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See 2.4. The stone serves as an
							anchor when the net falls off the stakes.</note> let him attach a long,
						big stone, so that the net may not pull away when the hare is inside. Let
						him make his line long and high,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The stakes
							must not be too deep in the ground, or the nets will not be high
							enough.</note> so that the hare may not jump over.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>When it comes to tracking the hare, he must
						not be too zealous. To do everything possible to effect a quick capture
						shows perseverance, but is not hunting.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>These remarks read like an afterthought.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Let him stretch the hayes on level ground and
						put the road-nets<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The hayes and purse-nets
							seem to be connected in the same series; but the road-nets seem to be
							independent screens.</note> in roads and from game tracks into the
						adjacent ground, fastening down the (lower) cords to the ground, joining the
						elbows, fixing the stakes between the selvedges,<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">We are to think of a series of nets joined together.
							These stakes will be inserted in the top and bottom line of meshes. The
							selvedge runs along the top and bottom of the net.</note> putting the
						ends on the top of the stakes and stopping the byways. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p>Let him mount guard, going round the nets. If a purse-net is pulling its
						stake out of line, let him put it up. When the hare is being chased into the
						purse-nets he must run forward and shout as he runs after her. When she is
						in, he must calm the excitement of the hounds, soothing without touching
						them. He must also shout to the huntsman and let him know that the hare is
						caught, or that she has run past on this or that side, or that he has not
						seen her, or where he caught sight of her. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Let the huntsman go out to the hunting ground
						in a simple light dress and shoes, carrying a cudgel in his hand, and let
						the net-keeper follow. Let them keep silence while approaching the ground,
						so that, in case the hare is near, she may not move off on hearing voices.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
					<p>Having tied the hounds separately to the trees so that they can easily be
						slipped, let him set up the purse-nets and hayes<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">Neither here nor in 26 is there any reference to the
							road-nets. It is impossible to suggest a reason for this, and perhaps
							the necessary words have dropped out in both places, as might easily
							happen.</note> in the manner described. After this let the net-keeper
						keep guard, and let the huntsman take the hounds and go to the place in the
						hunting ground where the hare may be lurking; and after </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
					<p>registering a vow to Apollo and Artemis the Huntress to give them a share of
						the spoil, let him loose one hound, the cleverest at following a track, at
						sunrise in winter, before dawn in summer, and some time between at other
						seasons. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
					<p>As soon as the hound picks up a line from the network of tracks that leads
						straight ahead, let him slip another. If the track goes on, let him set the
						others going one by one at short intervals, and follow without pressing
						them, accosting each by name, but not often, that they may not get excited
						too soon. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
					<p>They will go forward full of joy and ardour, disentangling the various
						tracks, double or triple—springing forward now beside, now across the same
						ones—tracks interlaced or circular, straight or crooked, close or scattered,
						clear or obscure, running past one another with tails wagging, ears dropped
						and eyes flashing. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
					<p>As soon as they are near the hare they will let the huntsman know by the
						quivering of the whole body as well as the tail, by making fierce rushes, by
						racing past one another, by scampering along together persistently, massing
						quickly, breaking up and again rushing forward. At length they will reach
						the hare’s form and will go for her. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
					<p>She will start up suddenly, and will leave the hounds barking and baying
						behind her as she makes off. Let the huntsman shout at her as she runs,
						<q type="spoken">Now, hounds, now! Well done! Bravo, hounds! Well done, hounds!</q> Wrapping
						his cloak round his arm and seizing his cudgel he must follow up behind the
						hare and not try to head her off, since that is useless. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
					<p>The hare, making off, though out of sight, generally doubles back to the
						place where she is found. Let him call out<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>i.e., at the moment when the hare, making for the place where she was
							found, comes near the nets. Something is amiss with the text here. The
							<q type="mentioned">man</q> is, of course, the net-keeper. He, too, has a cudgel, but the
							author has not said so.</note> to the man, <q type="spoken">Hit her, boy; hit her, hit
						her!</q> and the man must let him know whether she is caught or not.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>If she is caught in the first run, let him
						call in the hounds and look for another. But if not, he must follow up at
						top speed and not let her go, but stick to it persistently. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
					<p>If the hounds come on her again in the pursuit, let him cry, <q type="spoken">Good, good,
						hounds; after her, hounds!</q> If they have got so far ahead of him that he
						cannot overtake them by following up and is quite out of the running, or if
						he cannot see them though they are moving about somewhere near or sticking
						to the tracks, let him find out by shouting as he runs past to anyone near,
						<q type="spoken">Hullo! have you seen the hounds?</q> </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
					<p>As soon as he has found out, let him stand near if they are on the track, and
						cheer them on, running through the hounds’ names, using all the variations
						of tone he can produce, pitching his voice high and low, soft and loud.
						Amongst other calls, if the chase is in the mountains, let him sing out,
						<q type="spoken">Oho, hounds, oho!</q><note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Imitating the call of
							the Bacchic revellers, <q type="emph">the Hounds of Madness,</q> on Mount
							Cithaeron.</note> If they are not clinging to the track, but are
						over-running, let him call them in with, <q type="spoken">Back, hounds, back with you!</q> </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
					<p>As soon as they are close on the tracks, let him cast them round,<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Nowadays hounds are left to make their own
							cast and are only assisted when they fail to recover the line.</note>
						making many circles, and wherever they find the track dim, let him stick a
						pole in the ground as a mark, and beginning from this mark keep them
						together until they clearly recognise the track, encouraging and coaxing
						them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
					<p>As soon as the track is clear they will be off in hot pursuit, hurling
						themselves on it, jumping beside it, working together, guessing, signalling
						to one another and setting bounds for one another that they can recognise.
						When they are thus scurrying in a bunch along the track, let him follow up
						without pressing them, or they may over-run the line through excess of zeal.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>As soon as they are near the hare and give the
						huntsman clear evidence of the fact, let him take care, or in her terror of
						the hounds she will slip away and be off. The hounds, wagging their tails,
						colliding and frequently jumping over one another, and baying loudly, with
						heads uplifted and glances at the huntsman, showing him plainly that they
						have the real thing now, will rouse the hare for themselves and go for her,
						giving tongue. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="24">
					<p>If she plunges into the purse-nets or bolts past them on the inside or
						outside, the net-keeper must in each event make it known by shouting. If she
						is caught, look for another; if not, continue the pursuit, using the same
						methods of encouragement. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="25">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>As soon as the hounds are getting tired of
						pursuing and the day is far advanced, it is time for the huntsman to search
						for the hare, worn out as she is, passing over nothing growing or lying on
						the ground, retracing his steps continually for fear of an oversight—since
						the animal rests in a small space and is too tired and frightened to get
						up,—bringing the hounds along, encouraging and exhorting the gentle
						frequently, the wilful sparingly, the average sort in moderation, until he
						kills her in a fair run or drives her into the purse-nets. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="26">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>After this take up the purse-nets and<note
							resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Where are the road-nets?</note> hayes, rub
						down the hounds and leave the hunting-ground, after waiting, if it be an
						afternoon in summer, in order that the hounds’ feet may not be overheated on
						the road. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>For breeding purposes, relieve the bitches of
						work in the winter, that the rest may help them to produce a fine litter
						towards spring, which is the best growing season for hounds. They are in
						heat for fourteen days. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>Mate them with good dogs near the end of the period, that they may the sooner
						become pregnant. When they are near their time do not take them out hunting
						continually, but only now and then, or love of work may result in a
						miscarriage. The period of gestation is sixty days. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>After the birth of the puppies leave them with the mother and do not place
						them under another bitch; for nursing by a foster mother does not promote
						growth, whereas the mother’s milk and breath do them good, and they like her
						caresses. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>As soon as the puppies can get about, give them milk for a year, and the food
						that will form their regular diet, and nothing else. For heavy feeding warps
						the puppies’ legs and sows the seeds of disease in the system, and their
						insides go wrong. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Give the hounds short names, so as to be able
						to call to them easily. The following are the right sort: Psyche, Thymus,
						Porpax, Styrax, Lonché, Lochus, Phrura, Phylax, Taxis, Xiphon, Phonax,
						Phlegon, Alcé, Teuchon, Hyleus, Medas, Porthon, Sperchon, Orgé, Bremon,
						Hybris, Thallon, Rhomé, Antheus, Hebe, Getheus, Chara, Leusson, Augo, Polys,
						Bia, Stichon, Spudé, Bryas, Oenas, Sterrus, Craugê, Caenon, Tyrbas, Sthenon,
						Aether, Actis, Aechmé, Noës, Gnomé, Stibon, Hormé.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">The names are significant of the colour, strength,
							spirit, sagacity or behaviour of the hounds. Hebe and Psyche are still
							in the list of bitches’ names, and modern equivalents of several of the
							other names are in use, e.g., Lance (Lonché), Sentinel (Phylax),
							Ecstasy (Chara), Blueskin (Oenas), Crafty (Medas), Hasty (Sperchon),
							Vigorous (Thallon), Impetus (Hormé), Counsellor (Noës), Bustler (dog)
							or Hasty (bitch); cf. Sperchon. For <foreign xml:lang="grc"
								>Πολύς</foreign> we should probably read <foreign xml:lang="grc"
									>Πολεύς</foreign>, <q type="emph">Rover.</q></note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Take the bitches to the hunting ground at
						eight months, the dogs at ten. Do not slip them on the trail that leads to
						the form, but keep them in long leashes and follow the tracking hounds,
						letting the youngsters run to and fro in the tracks.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">But how is the hunter to know whether the hounds are on
							the trail leading to the form or on the track of a running hare?</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>As soon as the hare is found, if they shape well for the run don’t let them
						go at once; but as soon as the hare has got so far ahead in the run that
						they can’t see her, send them along. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>For if the huntsman slips good-looking, plucky runners close to the hare, the
						sight of her will cause them to strain themselves and crack, since their
						bodies are not yet firm. So she should be very careful about this. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p>But if they are poor runners there is no reason why he should not let them
						go, for as they have no hope of catching the hare from the first, they will
						not meet with this accident. On the other hand, let the youngsters follow
						the track of the hare on the run until they catch her; and when she is
						caught, give her to them to break up.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Not
							to eat. Some hunters object more or less strongly to this injunction;
							but Beckford (<title>Thoughts on Hunting</title>), quoted by Blane, goes
							so far as to say, <q type="written">I think it but reasonable to give the hounds a hare
							sometimes. I always gave mine the last they killed, if I thought they
							deserved her.</q></note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p>As soon as they show reluctance to stick to it and begin scattering, call
						then in, until they grow accustomed to keep on till they find the hare, lest
						if they get into the way of misbehaving when they seek her, they end by
						becoming skirters—a vile habit. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Give them their food near the purse-nets so
						long as they are young, while the nets are being taken up, so that if they
						have gone astray in the hunting ground, through inexperience, they may come
						back safe for their meal. This will be discontinued when they come to regard
						the game as an enemy; they will be too intent on that to worry about their
						food. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
					<p>As a rule when they are hungry the master should feed the hounds himself; for
						when they are not hungry they do not know to whom that is due; but when they
						want food and get it, they love the giver. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Track the hare when it snows so hard that the
						ground is covered; but if there are black spaces, she will be hard to find.
						When it is cloudy and the wind is in the north, the tracks lie plain on the
						surface for a long time, because they melt slowly; but only for a short time
						if the wind is south and the sun shines, since they soon melt away.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>But when it snows without stopping, don’t
						attempt it, since the tracks are covered; nor when there is a high wind,
						since they are buried in the snowdrifts it causes. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>On no account have the hounds out with you for this kind of sport, for the
						snow freezes their noses and feet, and destroys the scent of the hare owing
						to the hard frost. But take the hayes, and go with a companion to the
						mountains, passing over the cultivated land, and as soon as the tracks are
						found, follow them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>If they are complicated, go back from the same ones to the same place and
						work round in circles and examine them, trying to find where they lead. The
						hare roams about uncertain where to rest, and, moreover, it is her habit to
						be tricky in her movements, because she is constantly being pursued in this
						manner. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>As soon as the track is clear, push straight ahead. It will lead either to a
						thickly wooded spot or to a steep declivity. For the gusts of wind carry the
						snow over such places; consequently many resting-places are left, and she
						looks for one of these. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p>As soon as the tracks lead to such a place, don’t go near, or she will move
						off, but go round and explore.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The object
							is to make sure whether the track really does end there or not. If it
							does, he is to go on to seek another hare. <q type="written">My father used to relate
							that in his student days an old forester on his brother-in-law’s estate,
							when he wanted to make sure of supplying a hare for his master’s
							visitors, would surround the hare’s form in the early morning, and the
							hare would not leave her form for hours.</q> A. Korte
								(<title>Hermes,</title>
							<date when="1918">1918</date>, p. 317).</note> For she is probably
						there, and there will be no doubt about the matter, since the tracks will
						nowhere run out from such places. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>As soon as it is evident that she is there, leave her—for she will not
						stir—and look for another before the tracks become obscure, and take care,
						in case you find others, that you will have enough daylight left to surround
						them with nets. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>When the time has come, stretch the hayes round each of them in the same way
						as in places where no snow lies, enclosing anything she may be near, and as
						soon as they are up, approach and start her. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>If she wriggles out of the hayes, run after her along the tracks. She will
						make for other places of the same sort, unless indeed she squeezes herself
						into the snow itself. Wherever she may be, mark the place and surround it;
						or, if she doesn’t wait, continue the pursuit. For she will be caught even
						without the hayes; for she soon tires owing to the depth of the snow, and
						because large lumps of it cling to the bottom of her hairy feet. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>For hunting fawns and deer<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">The red deer is meant. Hunting the calves immediately
							after their birth seems a poor game; but no doubt they were good
							eating.</note> use Indian<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Thibet dogs,
							called by Grattius (159) Seres.</note> hounds; for they are strong, big,
						speedy and plucky, and these qualities render them capable of hard work.
						Hunt the calves in spring, since they are born at that season. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>First go to the meadows and reconnoitre, to discover where hinds are most
						plentiful. Wherever they are, let the keeper of the hounds<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">The <q type="soCalled">Keeper of hounds</q> has not been mentioned in
							connection with hare hunting. Apparently he is the person to whom all
							these instructions are addressed.</note> go with the hounds and javelins
						to this place before daybreak and tie up the dogs to trees some distance
						off, so that they may not catch sight of the hinds and bark, and let him
						watch from a coign of vantage. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>At daybreak he will see every dam leading her fawn to the place where she
						means to lay it. When they have put them down, suckled them, and looked
						about to make sure that they are not seen, they move away into the offing
						and watch their calves. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>On seeing this, let him loose the dogs, and taking the javelins approach the
						spot where he saw the nearest fawn laid, carefully observing the positions
						so as not to make a mistake, since they look quite different when approached
						from what they seemed to be at a distance. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p>As soon as he sees the fawn, let him go close up to it. It will keep still,
						squeezing its body tight against the ground, and will let itself be lifted,
						bleating loudly, unless it is wet through, in which case it will not stay,
						since the rapid condensation of the moisture in its body by the cold causes
						it to make off. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>But it will be caught by the hounds if hotly pursued. Having taken it, let
						him give it to the net-keeper. It will cry out; and the sight and the sound
						between them will bring the hind running up to the holder, in her anxiety to
						rescue it. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>That is the moment to set the hounds on her, and ply the javelms. Having
						settled this one, let him proceed to tackle the rest, hunting them in the
						same manner. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Young fawns are caught by this method; but big
						ones are difficult to catch. For they graze with their dams and other deer;
						and when pursued they make off in the midst of them, or sometimes in front,
						but rarely in the rear. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p>The hinds trample on the hounds in their efforts to defend their fawns;
						consequently it is not easy to catch them, unless a man gets amongst them at
							once<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The author has omitted to explain
							how this is to be done.</note> and scatters them, so that one of the
						fawns is isolated. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p>The result of this strain on the hounds is that they are left behind in the
						first run; for the absence of the hinds fills the creature with terror, and
						the speed of fawns at that age is without parallel. But they are soon caught
						in the second or third run, since their bodies are still too young to stand
						the work. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Caltrops are set for deer in the mountains,
						about meadows and streams and glades, in alleys and cultivated lands that
						they frequent. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
					<p>The caltrops should be made of plaited yew, stripped of the bark, so as not
						to rot. They should have circular crowns, and the nails should be of iron
						and wood alternately, plaited into the rim,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>The <gloss>rim</gloss> (an unsatisfactory rendering) is the same thing as the
							<q type="mentioned">crown.</q></note> the iron nails being the longer, so that the wooden ones
						will yield to the foot and the others hurt it. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
					<p>The noose of the cord to be laid on the crown and the cord itself should be
						of woven esparto,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Yates (<title>Textrinum
								Antiquorum</title>) believes that the plant meant is Spanish broom
							(Genista). But it is indeed the grass <q type="mentioned">esparto,</q> Stipa
							tenacissima.</note> since this is rot-proof. The noose itself and the
						cord must be strong; and the clog attached must be of common or evergreen
						oak, twenty-seven inches long, not stripped of the bark, and three inches
						thick. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>To set the caltrops make a round hole in the
						ground fifteen inches deep, of the same size at the top as the crowns of the
						traps, but tapering towards the bottom. Make shallow drills in the ground
						for the cord and the clog to lie in. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
					<p>Having done this lay the caltrop on the hole a little below the surface, and
						level, and put the noose of the cord round the top. Having laid the cord and
						the clog in their places, lay spindle-wood twigs on the top, not letting
						them stick out beyond the circle, and on these any light leaves in season.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
					<p>Next throw some earth on them, beginning with the surface soil taken from the
						holes, and on top of this some unbroken soil from a distance, in order that
						the position may be completely concealed from the deer. Remove any earth
						remaining over to a place some distance from the caltrop; for if the deer
						smells earth recently disturbed, it shies; and it is not slow to smell it.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
					<p>Accompanied by the hounds, inspect the traps set in the mountains, preferably
						at daybreak (but it should be done also at other times during the day), in
						the cultivated lands early. For in the mountains deer may be caught in the
						daytime as well as at night owing to the solitude; but on cultivated land
						only at night, because they are afraid of human beings in the daytime. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>On coming across a caltrop upset, slip the
						hounds, give them a hark-forward, and follow along the track of the clog,
						noticing which way it runs. That will be clear enough for the most part: for
						the stones will be displaced and the trail of the clog will be obvious in
						the cultivated ground; and if the deer crosses rough places, there will be
						fragments of bark torn from the clog on the rocks, and the pursuit will be
						all the easier. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>If the deer is caught by the fore-foot it will
						soon be taken, as it hits every part of its body and its face with the clog
						during the run; or if by the hindleg, the dragging of the clog hampers the
						whole body; and sometimes it dashes into forked branches of trees, and
						unless it breaks the cord, is caught on the spot. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
					<p>But, whether you catch it in this way or by wearing it out, don’t go near it;
						for it will butt, if it’s a stag, and kick, and if it’s a hind, it will
						kick. So throw javelins at it from a distance.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>In the summer months they are also caught by
						pursuit without the aid of a caltrop; for they get dead beat, so that they
						are hit standing. When hard pressed, they will even plunge into the sea and
						into pools in their bewilderment; and occasionally they drop from want of
						breath. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>For hunting the wild boar provide yourself
						with Indian, Cretan, Locrian and Laconian<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>i.e., Laconian hounds of the Castorian variety; see 3.5.</note> hounds,
						boar nets, javelins, spears and caltrops. In the first place the hounds of
						each breed must be of high quality, that they may be qualified to fight the
						beast. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>The nets must be made of the same flax as those used for hares, of forty-five
						threads woven in three strands, each strand containing fifteen threads. The
						height should be ten knots, counted from the top,<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">This means, I believe, ten meshes, so that the net would
							be about 150 inches high. Otto Manns (<title>Uber die Jagd bei den
								Grieschen</title>), however, thinks that the net was five feet high
							only, i.e., four meshes (cf. 4.5); but (1) it is hard to see how <q type="emph">four
							meshes</q> can be got out of <q type="emph">ten knots,</q> and (2) the <q type="emph">bosom</q> (see 7)
							requires a considerably greater height than five feet.</note> and the
						depths of the meshes fifteen inches. The ropes at top and bottom must be
						half as thick again as the nets. There must be metal rings at the elbows,
						and the ropes must be inserted under the meshes, and their ends must pass
						out through the rings.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The ends of the
							upper ropes appear to have been used for fastening the nets
							together.</note> Fifteen nets are sufficient.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">It is strange that the author does not state the length
							of the nets.</note>
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The javelins must be of every variety, the
						blades broad and keen, and the shafts strong. The spears must have blades
						fifteen inches long, and stout teeth at the middle of the socket, forged in
						one piece but standing out; and their shafts must be of cornel wood, as
						thick as a military spear. The caltrops must be similar to those used in
						hunting deer. There must be several huntsmen, for the task of capturing the
						beast is no light one even for a large number of men. I will now explain how
						to use each portion of the outfit in hunting. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>First then, when the company reach the place
						where they suppose the game to lurk, let them slip one of the Laconian
						hounds, and taking the others in leash, go round the place with the hound.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p>As soon as she has found his tracks, let the field follow, one behind
						another, keeping exactly to the line of the track. The huntsmen also will
						find many evidences of the quarry, the tracks in soft ground, broken
						branches where the bushes are thick, and marks of his tusks wherever there
						are trees. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>The hound following the track will, as a rule, arrive at a well-wooded spot.
						For the beast usually lies in such places, since they are warm in winter and
						cool in summer. As soon as the hound reaches the lair, she will bark. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>But in most cases the boar will not get up. So take the hound and tie her up
						with the others at a good distance from the lair, and have the nets put up
						in the convenient anchorages, hanging the meshes on forked branches of
						trees. Out of the net itself make a long projecting bosom, putting sticks
						inside to prop it up on both sides, so that the light of day may penetrate
						as much as possible into the bosom through the meshes, in order that the
						interior may be as light as possible when the boar rushes at it. Fasten the
						(lower) rope to a strong tree, not to a bush, since the bushes give way at
						the bare stem.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The text is doubtful. I now
							think <foreign xml:lang="grc">συγκλῶνται</foreign> probable for
							<foreign xml:lang="grc">συνέχονται</foreign>.</note> Wherever
						there is a gap between a net and the ground,<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">The text is again uncertain, but the sense is clear. I
							incline to <foreign xml:lang="grc">ὑπὸ δ᾽
								ἑκάστην</foreign>.</note> fill in the places that afford no anchorage
						with wood, in order that the boar may rush into the net, and not slip out.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>As soon as they are in position, let the party
						go to the hounds and loose them all, and take the javelins and the spears
						and advance. Let one man, the most experienced, urge on the hounds, while
						the others follow in regular order, keeping well behind one another, so that
						the boar may have a free passage between them; for should he beat a retreat
						and dash into a crowd, there is a risk of being gored, since he spends his
						rage on anyone he encounters. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>As soon as the hounds are near the lair, they
						will go for him. The noise will cause him to get up, and he will toss any
						hound that attacks him in front. He will run and plunge into the nets; or if
						not, you must pursue him. If the ground where he is caught in the net is
						sloping, he will quickly get up; if it is level, he will immediately stand
						still, intent on himself. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p>At this moment the hounds will press their attack, and the huntsmen must
						fling their javelins at him warily, and pelt him with stones, gathering
						round behind and a good way off, till he shoves hard enough to pull the rope
						of the net tight. Then let the most experienced and most powerful man in the
						field approach him in front and thrust his spear into him. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p>If, in spite of javelins and stones, he refuses to pull the rope tight, but
						draws back, wheels round and marks his assailant, in that case the man must
						approach him spear in hand, and grasp it with the left in front and the
						right behind, since the left steadies while the right drives it. The left
						foot must follow the left hand forward, and the right foot the other hand.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
					<p>As he advances let him hold the spear before him, with his legs not much
						further apart than in wrestling, turning the left side towards the left
						hand, and then watching the beast’s eye and noting the movement of the
						fellow’s head. Let him present the spear, taking care that the boar doesn’t
						knock it out of his hand with a jerk of his head, since he follows up the
						impetus of the sudden knock. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
					<p>In case this accident should happen, the man must fall on his face and clutch
						the undergrowth beneath him, for, if the beast attacks him in this position,
						he is unable to lift the man’s body owing to the upward curve of his tusks;
						but if his body is off the ground, the man is certain to be gored.
						Consequently the boar tries to lift him up, and, if he cannot, he stands
						over and tramples on him. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
					<p>For a man in this critical situation there is only one escape from these
						disasters. One of his fellow huntsmen must approach with a spear and provoke
						the boar by making as though he would hurl it; but he must not hurl it, or
						he may hit the man on the ground. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
					<p>On seeing this the boar will leave the man under him and turn savagely and
						furiously on his tormentor. The other must jump up instantly, remembering to
						keep his spear in his hand as he rises, for safety without victory is not
						honourable. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
					<p>He must again present the spear in the same way as before, and thrust it
						inside the shoulder-blade where the throat is, and push with all his might.
						The enraged beast will come on, and but for the teeth of the blade, would
						shove himself forward along the shaft far enough to reach the man holding
						the spear. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>His strength is so great that he has some
						peculiar properties which one would never imagine him to possess. Thus, if
						you lay hairs on his tusks immediately after he is dead, they shrivel up,
						such is the heat of the tusks. While he is alive they become intensely hot
						whenever he is provoked, or the surface of the hounds’ coats would not be
						singed when he tries to gore them and misses. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>All this trouble, and even more, the male
						animal causes before he is caught. If the creature in the toils is a sow,
						run up and stick her, taking care not to be knocked down. Such an accident
						is bound to result in your being trampled and bitten. So don’t fall under
						her, if you can help it. If you get into that position unintentionally, the
						same aids to rise that are used to assist a man under a boar are employed.
						When on your feet again, you must ply the spear until you kill her. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Another way of capturing them is as follows.
						The nets are set up for them at the passages from glens into oak coppices,
						dells and rough places, on the outskirts of meadows, fens and sheets of
						water. The keeper, spear in hand, watches the nets. The huntsmen take the
						hounds and search for the likeliest places. As soon as the boar is found, he
						is pursued. If he falls into the net, the net-keeper must take </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
					<p>his spear, approach the boar, and use it as I have explained. The boar is
						also captured, in hot weather, when pursued by the hounds; for in spite of
						his prodigious strength, the animal tires with hard breathing. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
					<p>Many hounds are killed in this kind of sport, and the huntsmen themselves run
						risks, whenever in the course of the pursuit they are forced to approach a
						boar with their spears in their hands, when he is tired or standing in water
						or has posted himself by a steep declivity or is unwilling to come out of a
						thicket; for neither net nor anything else stops him from rushing at anyone
						coming near him. Nevertheless approach they must in these circumstances, and
						show the pluck that led them to take up this hobby. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="22">
					<p>They must use the spear and the forward position of the body as explained;
						then, if a man does come to grief, it will not be through doing things the
						wrong way.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Caltrops are also set for them as for the deer
						and in the same places. The routine of inspection and pursuit, the methods
						of approach and the use of the spear are the same. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="23">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>The young pigs are not to be caught without
						difficulty. For they are not left alone so long as they are little, and when
						the hounds find them or they see something coming, they quickly vanish into
						the wood; and they are generally accompanied by both parents, who are fierce
						at such times and more ready to fight for their young than for themselves.
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Lions, leopards, lynxes, panthers, bears and
						all similar wild beasts are captured in foreign countries, about Mt.
						Pangaeus and Cittus beyond Macedonia, on Mysian Olympus and Pindus, on Nysa
						beyond Syria, and in other mountain ranges capable of supporting such
						animals. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>On the mountains they are sometimes poisoned, owing to the difficulty of the
						ground, with aconite. Hunters put it down mixed with the animals’ favourite
						food round pools and in other places that they frequent. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>Sometimes, while they are going down to the plain at night, they are cut off
						by parties of armed and mounted men. This is a dangerous method of capturing
						them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>Sometimes the hunters dig large, round, deep holes, leaving a pillar of earth
						in the middle. They tie up a goat and put it on the pillar in the evening,
						and pile wood round the hole without leaving an entrance, so that the
						animals cannot see what lies in front. On hearing the bleating in the night,
						the beasts run round the barrier, and finding no opening, jump over and are
						caught. </p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>With the practical side of hunting I have
						finished. But the advantages that those who have been attracted by this
						pursuit will gain are many. For it makes the body healthy, improves the
						sight and hearing, and keeps men from growing old; and it affords the best
						training for war. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>In the first place, when marching over rough roads under arms, they will not
						tire: accustomed to carry arms for capturing wild beasts, they will bear up
						under their tasks. Again, they will be capable of sleeping on a hard bed and
						of guarding well the place assigned to them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>In an attack<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The word <foreign
						xml:lang="grc">πρόσοδος</foreign> in this sense is a hunters’
							term.</note> on the enemy they will be able to go for him and at the
						same time to carry out the orders that are passed along, because they are
						used to do the same things on their own account when capturing the game. If
						their post is in the van they will not desert it, because they can endure.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>In the rout of the enemy they will make straight for the foe without a slip
						over any kind of ground, through habit. If part of their own army has met
						with disaster in ground rendered difficult by woods and defiles or what not,
						they will manage to save themselves without loss of honour and to save
						others. For their familiarity with the business will give them knowledge
						that others lack. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p>Indeed, it has happened before now, when a great host of allies has been put
						to flight, that a little band of such men, through their fitness and
						confidence, has renewed the battle and routed the victorious enemy when he
						has blundered owing to difficulties in the ground. For men who are sound in
						body and mind may always stand on the threshold of success. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>It was because they knew that they owed their successes against the enemy to
						such qualities that our ancestors looked after the young men. For in spite
						of the scarcity of corn it was their custom from the earliest times not to
						prevent hunters from hunting over any growing crops; and, in addition, not
						to permit hunting at </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>night within a radius of many furlongs from the city, so that the masters of
						that art might not rob the young men of their game. In fact they saw that
						this is the only one among the pleasures of the younger men that produces a
						rich crop of blessings. For it makes sober and upright men of them, because
						they are trained in the school of truth<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>i.e., a training that really builds up the character. There is an
							implied contrast with the imposture of the education given by
							sophists.</note> (and they perceived </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>that to these men they owed their success in war, as in other matters); and
						it does not keep them from any other honourable occupation they wish to
						follow, like other and evil pleasures that they ought not to learn. Of such
						men, therefore, are good soldiers and good generals made. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p>For they whose toils root out whatever is base and froward from mind and body
						and make desire for virtue to flourish in their place—they are the best,
						since they will not brook injustice to their own city nor injury to its
						soil. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Some say that it is not right to love hunting,
						because it may lead to neglect of one’s domestic affairs. They are not aware
						that all who benefit their cities and their friends are more attentive to
						their domestic affairs than other men. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p>Therefore, if keen sportsmen fit themselves to be useful to their country in
						matters of vital moment, neither will they be remiss in their private
						affairs: for the state is necessarily concerned both in the safety and in
						the ruin of the individual’s domestic fortunes. Consequently such men as
						these save the fortunes of every other individual as well as their own. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
					<p>But many of those who talk in this way, blinded by jealousy, choose to be
						ruined through their own evil rather than be saved by other men’s virtue.
						For most pleasures are evil, and by yielding to these they are encouraged
						either to say or to do what is wrong. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
					<p>Then by their frivolous words they make enemies, and by their evil deeds
						bring diseases and losses and death on themselves, their children and their
						friends, being without perception of the evils, but more perceptive than
						others of the pleasures. Who would employ these to save a state? </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
					<p>From these evils, however, everyone who loves that which I recommend will
						hold aloof, since a good education teaches a man to observe laws, to talk of
						righteousness and hear of it. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
					<p>Those, then, who have given themselves up to continual toil and learning hold
						for their own portion laborious lessons and exercises, but they hold safety
						for their cities. But if any decline to receive instruction because of the
						labour and prefer to live among untimely pleasures, they are by nature
						utterly evil. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
					<p>For they obey neither laws nor good words, for because they toil not, they do
						not discover what a good man ought to be, so that they cannot be pious or
						wise men; and being without education they constantly find fault with the
						educated. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
					<p>In these men’s hands, therefore, nothing can prosper. All discoveries that
						have benefited mankind are due to the better sort.<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">The argument, such as it is, would be better with <q type="emph">the
							toilers,</q> for <gloss>the better sort,</gloss> and the next words would then be <gloss>those
							who are willing to toil, therefore, are the better men.</gloss></note> Now the
						better sort are those who are willing to toil. And this has been proved by a
						great example. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
					<p>For among the ancients the companions of Cheiron to whom I referred learnt
						many noble lessons in their youth, beginning with hunting; from these
						lessons there sprang in them great virtue, for which they are admired even
						today. That all desire Virtue is obvious, but because they must toil if they
						are to gain her, the many fall away. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="19">
					<p>For the achievement of her is hidden in obscurity, whereas the toils
						inseparable from her<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign
							xml:lang="grc">αὐτῷ</foreign>, <gloss>it,</gloss> i.e., the achievement,
							would be an improvement.</note> are manifest.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>It may be that, if her body were visible, men
						would be less careless of virtue, knowing that she sees them as clearly as
						they see her. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="20">
					<p>For when he is seen by his beloved every man rises above himself and shrinks
						from what is ugly and evil in word or deed, for fear of being seen by him.
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="21">
					<p>But in the presence of Virtue men do many evil and ugly things, supposing
						that they are not regarded by her because they do not see her. Yet she is
						present everywhere because she is immortal, and she honours those who are
						good to her, but casts off the bad. Therefore, if men knew that she is
						watching them, they would be impatient to undergo the toils and the
						discipline by which she is hardly to be captured, and would achieve her.
					</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			<div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I am surprised at the sophists, as they are
						called, because, though most of them profess to lead the young to virtue
						they lead them to the very opposite. We have never seen anywhere the man
						whose goodness was due to the sophists of our generation. Neither do their
						contributions to literature tend to make men good: but they have written
					</p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2">
					<p>many books on frivolous subjects, books that offer the young empty pleasures,
						but put no virtue into them. To read them in the hope of learning something
						from them is mere waste of time, and they keep one from useful occupations
						and teach what is bad. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3">
					<p>Therefore their grave faults incur my graver censure. As for the style of
						their writings, I complain that the language is far-fetched, and there is no
						trace in them of wholesome maxims by which the young might be trained to
						virtue. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4">
					<p>I am no professor, but I know that the best thing is to be taught what is
						good by one’s own nature, and the next best thing is to get it from those
						who really know something good instead of being taught by masters of the art
						of deception. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="5">
					<p>I daresay that I do not express myself in the language of a sophist; in fact,
						that is not my object: my object is rather to give utterance to wholesome
						thoughts that will meet the needs of readers well educated in virtue. For
						words will not educate, but maxims, if well found. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="6">
					<p>Many others besides myself blame the sophists of our generation—philosophers
						I will not call them —because the wisdom they profess consists of words and
						not of thoughts.</p>
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>I am well aware that someone, perhaps one of
						this set,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., a sophist. But the text of
							what follows is open to suspicion.</note> will say that what is well and
						methodically written<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"><foreign
							xml:lang="grc">ἐγνωσμένα,</foreign> <gloss>thought,</gloss> would be a great
							improvement on <foreign xml:lang="grc">γεγραμμένα,</foreign>
							<gloss>written.</gloss></note> is not well and methodically written—for hasty and
						false censure will come easily to them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="7">
					<p>But my aim in writing has been to produce sound work that will make men not
						wiseacres, but wise and good. For I wish my work not to seem useful, but to
						be so, that it may stand for all time unrefuted. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="8">
					<p>The sophists talk to deceive and write for their own gain, and do no good to
						anyone. For there is not, and there never was, a wise man among them;
						everyone of them is content to be called a sophist, which is a term of
						reproach among sensible men. So my advice is: </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="9">
					<p>Avoid the behests of the sophists, and despise not the conclusions of the
						philosophers; for the sophists hunt the rich and young, but the philosophers
						are friends to all alike: but as for men’s fortunes, they neither honour nor
						despise them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="10">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>Envy not those either who recklessly seek
						their own advantage whether in private or in public life<note resp="Loeb"
							anchored="true">Professional politicians.</note> —bear in mind that the
						best of them, though they are favourably judged, are envied, and the bad
						both fare badly and are unfavourably judged. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="11">
					<p>For engaged in robbing private persons of their property, or plundering the
						state, they render less service than private persons when plans for securing
						the common safety are afoot,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., they
							contrive to <q type="emph">save their pockets.</q></note> and in body they are
						disgracefully unfit for war because they are incapable of toil. But huntsmen
						offer their lives and their property in sound condition for the service of
						the citizens. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="12">
					<p>These attack the wild beasts, those others their friends. And whereas those
						who attack their friends earn infamy by general consent, huntsmen by
						attacking the wild beasts gain a good report. For if they make a capture,
						they win victory over enemy forces: and if they fail, they are commended, in
						the first place, because they assail powers hostile to the whole community;
						and, secondly, because they go out neither to harm a man nor for sordid
						gain. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="13">
					<p>Moreover, the very attempt makes them better in many ways and wiser; and we
						will give the reason. Unless they abound in labours and inventions and
						precautions, they cannot capture game. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="14">
					<p>For the forces contending with them, fighting for their life and in their own
						home, are in great strength; so that the huntsman’s labours are in vain,
						unless by greater perseverance and by much intelligence he can overcome
						them. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="15">
					<p><milestone unit="para" ed="P"/>In fine, the politician whose objects are
						selfish practises for victory over friends, the huntsman for victory over
						common foes. This practice makes the one a better, the other a far worse
						fighter against all other enemies. The one takes prudence with him for
						companion in the chase, the other base rashness. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="16">
					<p>The one can despise malice and avarice, the other cannot. The language of the
						one is gracious,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">i.e., kindly and pleasant;
							not reckless and shameless like that of the politicians.</note> of the
						other ugly. As for religion, nothing checks impiety in the one, the other is
						conspicuous for his piety. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="17">
					<p>In fact, an ancient story has it that the gods delight in this business, both
						as followers and spectators of the chase. Therefore, reflecting on these
						things, the young who do what I exhort them to do will put themselves in the
						way of being dear to the gods and pious men, conscious that one or other of
						the gods is watching their deeds. These will be good to parents, good to the
						whole city, to every one of their friends and fellow-citizens. </p>
				</div>
				<div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="18">
					<p>For all men who have loved hunting have been good: and not men only, but
						those women also to whom the goddess<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
							>Artemis.</note> has given this blessing, Atalanta and Procris and
						others like them.</p>
				</div>
			</div>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>

</TEI>
