<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - Mark</title>
                
                <editor>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor>
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="verse"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and verse</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="chapter"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            
            <refsDecl>
                <!--<refState delim=" " unit="book"/>-->
                <refState delim=":" unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>
            
            <!--<refsDecl>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>-->
        </encodingDesc>
        
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-10-19" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion</change>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2010-06-29" who="student">fixing place tags AD</change>
            <change when="2009-10-08" who="rsingh04">began reorganizing texts module by collection.created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files</change>
            <change when="2009-05-27" who="rsingh04">added/fixed cvs log keyword</change>
            <change when="1999-10-14" who="Anne Mahoney">Initial markup from flat ASCII text</change>
</revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0031.tlg002.perseus-eng2">
                <head>The Gospel According to Mark</head>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        The beginning of the gospel of Jesus Christ, the Son of God.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        As it is written in the prophets,
"Behold, I send my messenger before your face,
   Who will prepare your way before you.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        The voice of one crying in the wilderness,
   'Make ready the way of the Lord!
   Make his paths straight!'"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        John came baptizing in the wilderness and preaching the
baptism of repentance for forgiveness of sins.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        All the country of
Judea and all those of Jerusalem went out to him. They were baptized by
him in the Jordan river, confessing their sins.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        John was clothed
with camel's hair and a leather belt around his loins. He ate locusts
and wild honey.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        He preached, saying, "After me comes he who is
mightier than I, the thong of whose sandals I am not worthy to stoop
down and loosen.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        I baptized you in water, but he will baptize you
in the Holy Spirit."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        It happened in those days, that Jesus came from Nazareth of
Galilee, and was baptized by John in the Jordan.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        Immediately
coming up from the water, he saw the heavens parting, and the Spirit
descending on him like a dove.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        A voice came out of the sky, "You
are my beloved Son, in whom I am well pleased."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        Immediately the Spirit drove him out into the wilderness.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        He was there in the wilderness forty days tempted by Satan. He
was with the wild animals; and the angels ministered to him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Now after John was taken into custody, Jesus came into
Galilee, preaching the gospel of the Kingdom of God,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        and saying,
"The time is fulfilled, and the Kingdom of God is at hand! Repent, and
believe in the gospel."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        Passing along by the sea of Galilee, he saw Simon and Andrew
the brother of Simon casting a net in the sea, for they were fishermen.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        Jesus said to them, "Come after me, and I will make you into
fishers for men."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        Immediately they left their nets, and followed him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        Going on a little further from there, he saw James the son of Zebedee,
and John, his brother, who were also in the boat mending the nets.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        Immediately he called them, and they left their father, Zebedee,
in the boat with the hired servants, and went after him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        They
went into Capernaum, and immediately on the Sabbath day he entered into
the synagogue and taught.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        They were astonished at his teaching,
for he taught them as having authority, and not as the scribes.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        Immediately there was in their synagogue a man with an unclean spirit,
and he cried out,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        saying, "Ha! What do we have to do with you,
Jesus, you Nazarene? Have you come to destroy us? I know you who you
are: the Holy One of God!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        Jesus rebuked him, saying, "Be quiet, and come out of him!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        The unclean spirit, convulsing him and crying with a loud
voice, came out of him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        They were all amazed, so that they
questioned among themselves, saying, "What is this? A new teaching? For
with authority he commands even the unclean spirits, and they obey
him!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        The report of him went out immediately everywhere into all
the region of Galilee and its surrounding area.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        Immediately, when they had come out of the synagogue, they
came into the house of Simon and Andrew, with James and John.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        Now Simon's wife's mother lay sick with a fever, and immediately they
told him about her.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        He came and took her by the hand, and raised
her up. The fever left her, and she served them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        At evening,
when the sun had set, they brought to him all who were sick, and those
who were possessed by demons.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        All the city was gathered together
at the door.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        He healed many who were sick with various diseases,
and cast out many demons. He didn't allow the demons to speak, because
they knew him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        Early in the night, he rose up and went out, and departed
into a deserted place, and prayed there.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        Simon and those who
were with him followed after him;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        and they found him, and told
him, "Everyone is looking for you."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        He said to them, "Let's go elsewhere into the next towns,
that I may preach there also, because for this reason I came forth."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        He went into their synagogues throughout all Galilee, preaching
and casting out demons.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        There came to him a leper, begging him, kneeling down to him,
and saying to him, "If you want to, you can make me clean."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        Being moved with compassion, he stretched out his hand, and
touched him, and said to him, "I want to. Be made clean."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="42"><p>
                        When
he had said this, immediately the leprosy departed from him, and he was
made clean.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="43"><p>
                        He strictly warned him, and immediately sent him
out,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="44"><p>
                        and said to him, "See you say nothing to anybody, but go
show yourself to the priest, and offer for your cleansing the things
which Moses commanded, for a testimony to them."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="45"><p>
                        But he went out, and began to proclaim it much, and to spread
about the matter, so that Jesus could no more openly enter into a city,
but was outside in desert places: and they came to him from everywhere.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
                    

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        When he entered again into Capernaum after some days, it was
heard that he was in the house.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Immediately many were gathered
together, so that there was no more room, not even around the door; and
he spoke the word to them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        Four people came, carrying a paralytic
to him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        When they could not come near to him for the crowd, they
removed the roof where he was. When they had broken it up, they let
down the mat that the paralytic was lying on.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Jesus, seeing their
faith, said to the paralytic, "Son, your sins are forgiven you."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        But there were some of the scribes sitting there, and
reasoning in their hearts,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        "Why does this man speak blasphemies
like that? Who can forgive sins but God alone?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        Immediately Jesus, perceiving in his spirit that they so
reasoned within themselves, said to them, "Why do you reason these
things in your hearts?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        Which is easier, to tell the paralytic,
'Your sins are forgiven;' or to say, 'Arise, and take up your bed, and
walk?'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        But that you may know that the Son of Man has authority
on earth to forgive sins" -- he said to the paralytic --
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        "I tell
you, arise, take up your mat, and go to your house."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        He arose, and immediately took up the mat, and went out in
front of them all; so that they were all amazed, and glorified God,
saying, "We never saw anything like this!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        He went out again by the seaside. All the multitude came to
him, and he taught them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        As he passed by, he saw Levi, the son
of Alphaeus, sitting at the tax office, and he said to him, "Follow
me." And he arose and followed him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        It happened, that he was reclining at the table in his house,
and many tax collectors and sinners sat down with Jesus and his
disciples, for there were many, and they followed him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        The
scribes and the Pharisees, when they saw that he was eating with the
sinners and tax collectors, said to his disciples, "Why is it that he
eats and drinks with tax collectors and sinners?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        When Jesus heard it, he said to them, "Those who are healthy
have no need for a physician, but those who are sick. I came not to
call the righteous, but sinners to repentance."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        John's disciples and the Pharisees were fasting, and they
came and asked him, "Why do John's disciples and the disciples of the
Pharisees fast, but your disciples don't fast?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        Jesus said to them, "Can the groomsmen fast while the
bridegroom is with them? As long as they have the bridegroom with them,
they can't fast.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        But the days will come when the bridegroom will
be taken away from them, and then will they fast in that day.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        No
one sews a piece of unshrunk cloth on an old garment, or else the patch
shrinks and the new tears away from the old, and a worse hole is made.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        No one puts new wine into old wineskins, or else the new wine
will burst the skins, and the wine pours out, and the skins will be
destroyed; but they put new wine into fresh wineskins."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        It happened that he was going on the Sabbath day through the
grain fields, and his disciples began, as they went, to pluck the ears
of grain.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        The Pharisees said to him, "Behold, why do they do
that which is not lawful on the Sabbath day?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        He said to them, "Did you never read what David did, when he
had need, and was hungry -- he, and they who were with him?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        How
he entered into the house of God when Abiathar was high priest, and ate
the show bread, which it is not lawful to eat except for the priests,
and gave also to those who were with him?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        He said to them, "The
Sabbath was made for man, not man for the Sabbath.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        Therefore the
Son of Man is lord even of the Sabbath."
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        He entered again into the synagogue, and there was a man there
who had his hand withered.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        They watched him, whether he would
heal him on the Sabbath day, that they might accuse him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        He said
to the man who had his hand withered, "Stand up."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        He said to
them, "Is it lawful on the Sabbath day to do good, or to do harm? To
save a life, or to kill?" But they were silent.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        When he had
looked around at them with anger, being grieved at the hardening of
their hearts, he said to the man, "Stretch out your hand." He stretched
it out, and his hand was restored as healthy as the other.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        The
Pharisees went out, and immediately conspired with the Herodians
against him, how they might destroy him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        Jesus withdrew to the sea with his disciples, and a great
multitude followed him from Galilee, from Judea,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        from Jerusalem,
from Idumaea, beyond the Jordan, and those from around Tyre and Sidon.
A great multitude, hearing what great things he did, came to him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        He spoke to his disciples that a little boat should stay near him
because of the crowd, so that they wouldn't press on him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        For he
had healed many, so that as many as had diseases pressed on him that
they might touch him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        The unclean spirits, whenever they saw
him, fell down before him, and cried, "You are the Son of God!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        He sternly warned them that they should not make him known.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        He went up into the mountain, and called to himself those
whom he wanted, and they went to him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        He appointed twelve, that
they might be with him, and that he might send them out to preach,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        and to have authority to heal sicknesses and to cast out demons:
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        Simon, to whom he gave the name Peter;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        James the son of
Zebedee; John, the brother of James, and he surnamed them Boanerges,
which means, Sons of Thunder;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        Andrew; Philip; Bartholomew;
Matthew; Thomas; James, the son of Alphaeus; Thaddaeus; Simon the
Zealot;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        and Judas Iscariot, who also betrayed him.

   He came into a house.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        The multitude came together again, so
that they could not so much as eat bread.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        When his friends heard
it, they went out to seize him: for they said, "He is insane."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        The scribes who came down from Jerusalem said, "He has Beelzebul," and,
"By the prince of the demons he casts out the demons."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        He summoned them, and said to them in parables, "How can
Satan cast out Satan?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        If a kingdom is divided against itself,
that kingdom cannot stand.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        If a house is divided against itself,
that house cannot stand.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        If Satan has risen up against himself,
and is divided, he can't stand, but has an end.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        But no one can
enter into the house of the strong man to plunder, unless he first
binds the strong man; and then he will plunder his house.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        Most
assuredly I tell you, all of the sons of men's sins will be forgiven
them, including their blasphemies with which they may blaspheme;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        but whoever may blaspheme against the Holy Spirit never has
forgiveness, but is guilty of an eternal sin"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        -- because they
said, "He has an unclean spirit."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        His mother and his brothers came, and standing outside, they
sent to him, calling him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        A multitude was sitting around him,
and they told him, "Behold, your mother, your brothers, and your
sisters are outside looking for you."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        He answered them, "Who are my mother and my brothers?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        Looking around at those who sat around him, he said, "Behold, my mother
and my brothers!
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        For whoever does the will of God, the same is
my brother, and my sister, and mother."
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="4">
                    

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        Again he began to teach by the seaside. A great multitude was
gathered to him, so that he entered into a boat in the sea, and sat
down. All the multitude were on the land by the sea.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        He taught
them many things in parables, and told them in his teaching,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        "Listen! Behold, the farmer went out to sow,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        and it happened, as
he sowed, some seed fell by the road, and the birds came and devoured
it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Others fell on the rocky ground, where it had little soil,
and immediately it sprang up, because it had no depth of soil.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        When the sun had risen, it was scorched; and because it had no root, it
withered away.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        Others fell among the thorns, and the thorns grew
up, and choked it, and it yielded no fruit.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        Others fell into the
good ground, and yielded fruit, growing up and increasing. Some brought
forth thirty times, some sixty times, and some one hundred times as
much."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        He said, "Whoever has ears to hear, let him hear."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        When he was alone, those who were around him with the twelve
asked him about the parables.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        He said to them, "To you is given
the mystery of the Kingdom of God, but to those who are outside, all
things are done in parables,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        that 'seeing they may see, and not
perceive; and hearing they may hear, and not understand; lest perhaps
they should turn again, and their sins should be forgiven them.'"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        He said to them, "Don't you understand this parable? How will
you understand all of the parables?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        The farmer sows the word.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        These are the ones by the road, where the word is sown; and when
they have heard, immediately Satan comes, and takes away the word which
has been sown in them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        These in like manner are those who are
sown on the rocky places, who, when they have heard the word,
immediately receive it with joy.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        They have no root in
themselves, but are short-lived. When oppression or persecution arises
because of the word, immediately they stumble.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        Others are those
who are sown among the thorns. These are those who have heard the word,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        and the cares of this age, and the deceitfulness of riches, and
the lusts of other things entering in choke the word, and it becomes
unfruitful.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        These are those which were sown on the good ground:
such as hear the word, and accept it, and bear fruit, some thirty
times, some sixty times, and some one hundred times."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        He said to them, "Is the lamp brought to be put under a
basket or under a bed? Isn't it put on a lampstand?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        For there is
nothing hidden, except that it should be made known; neither was
anything made secret, but that it should come to light.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        If any
man has ears to hear, let him hear."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        He said to them, "Take heed what you hear. With whatever
measure you measure, it will be measured to you, and more will be given
to you who hear.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        For whoever has, to him will more be given, and
he who doesn't have, from him will be taken away even that which he
has."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        He said, "The Kingdom of God is as if a man should cast seed
on the earth,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        and should sleep and rise night and day, and the
seed should spring up and grow, he doesn't know how.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        For the
earth bears fruit: first the blade, then the ear, then the full grain
in the ear.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        But when the fruit is ripe, immediately he puts
forth the sickle, because the harvest has come."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        He said, "How will we liken the Kingdom of God? Or with what
parable will we illustrate it?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        It's like a grain of mustard
seed, which, when it is sown in the earth, though it is less than all
the seeds that are on the earth,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        yet when it is sown, grows up,
and becomes greater than all the herbs, and puts out great branches, so
that the birds of the sky can lodge under its shadow."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        With many such parables he spoke the word to them, as they
were able to hear it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        Without a parable he didn't speak to them;
but privately to his own disciples he explained all things.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        On that day, when evening had come, he said to them, "Let's
go over to the other side."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        Leaving the multitude, they took him
with them, even as he was, in the boat. Other small boats were also
with him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        There arose a great wind storm, and the waves beat
into the boat, so much that the boat was already filled.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        He
himself was in the stern, asleep on the cushion, and they woke him up,
and told him, "Teacher, don't you care that we are dying?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        He awoke, and rebuked the wind, and said to the sea, "Peace!
Be still!" The wind ceased, and there was a great calm.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        He said
to them, "Why are you so afraid? How is it that you have no faith?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        They were greatly afraid, and said to one another, "Who then
is this, that even the wind and the sea obey him?"
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="5">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        They came to the other side of the sea, into the country of
the Gadarenes.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        When he had come out of the boat, immediately
there met him out of the tombs a man with an unclean spirit,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        who
had his dwelling in the tombs. Nobody could bind him any more, not even
with chains,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        because he had been often bound with fetters and
chains, and the chains had been torn apart by him, and the fetters
broken in pieces. Nobody had the strength to tame him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Always,
night and day, in the tombs and in the mountains, he was crying out,
and cutting himself with stones.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        When he saw Jesus from afar, he
ran and bowed down to him,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        and crying out with a loud voice, he
said, "What have I to do with you, Jesus, you Son of the Most High God?
I adjure you by God, don't torment me."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        For he said to him, "Come
out of the man, you unclean spirit!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        He asked him, "What is your name?"

   He said to him, "My name is Legion, for we are many."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        He
begged him much that he would not send them away out of the country.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        Now there was on the mountainside a great herd of pigs feeding.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        All the demons begged him, saying, "Send us into the pigs, that
we may enter into them."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        At once Jesus gave them permission. The unclean spirits came
out and entered into the pigs. The herd of about two thousand rushed
down the steep bank into the sea, and they were drowned in the sea.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Those who fed them fled, and told it in the city and in the
country.

   The people came to see what it was that had happened.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        They
came to Jesus, and saw him who had been possessed by demons sitting,
clothed, and in his right mind, even him who had the legion; and they
were afraid.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        Those who saw it declared to them how it happened
to him who was possessed by demons, and about the pigs.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        They
began to beg him to depart from their region.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        As he was entering into the boat, he who had been possessed
by demons begged him that he might be with him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        He didn't allow
him, but said to him, "Go to your house, to your friends, and tell them
what great things the Lord has done for you, and how he had mercy on
you."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        He went his way, and began to proclaim in Decapolis how Jesus
had done great things for him, and everyone marveled.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        When Jesus had crossed back over in the boat to the other
side, a great multitude was gathered to him; and he was by the sea.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        Behold, one of the rulers of the synagogue, Jairus by name,
came; and seeing him, he fell at his feet,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        and begged him much,
saying, "My little daughter is at the point of death. Please come and
lay your hands on her, that she may be made healthy, and live."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        He went with him, and a great multitude followed him, and
they pressed upon him on all sides.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        A certain woman, who had an
issue of blood for twelve years,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        and had suffered many things by
many physicians, and had spent all that she had, and was no better, but
rather grew worse,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        having heard the things concerning Jesus,
came up behind him in the crowd, and touched his clothes.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        For
she said, "If I just touch his clothes, I will be made well."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        Immediately the flow of her blood was dried up, and she felt in her
body that she was healed of her affliction.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        Immediately Jesus, perceiving in himself that the power had
gone out from him, turned around in the crowd, and asked, "Who touched
my clothes?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        His disciples said to him, "You see the multitude pressing
against you, and you say, 'Who touched me?'"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        He looked around to see her who had done this thing.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        But the woman, fearing and trembling, knowing what had been done to
her, came and fell down before him, and told him all the truth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        He said to her, "Daughter, your faith has made you well. Go
in peace, and be cured of your disease."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        While he was still speaking, they came from the synagogue
ruler's house saying, "Your daughter is dead. Why bother the Teacher
any more?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        But Jesus, when he heard the message spoken, immediately said
to the ruler of the synagogue, "Don't be afraid, only believe."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        He allowed no one to follow him, except Peter, James, and John the
brother of James.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        He came to the synagogue ruler's house, and he
saw an uproar, weeping, and great wailing.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        When he had entered
in, he said to them, "Why do you make an uproar and weep? The child is
not dead, but is asleep."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        They laughed him to scorn. But he, having put them all out,
took the father of the child and her mother and those who were with
him, and went in where the child was lying.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        Taking the child by
the hand, he said to her, "Talitha cumi;" which means, being
interpreted, "Young lady, I tell you, get up."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="42"><p>
                        Immediately the
young lady rose up, and walked, for she was twelve years old. They were
amazed with great amazement.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="43"><p>
                        He strictly ordered them that no
one should know this, and commanded that something should be given to
her to eat.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="6">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        He went out from there. He came into his own country, and his
disciples followed him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        When the Sabbath had come, he began to
teach in the synagogue, and many hearing him were astonished, saying,
"Where did this man get these things?" and, "What is the wisdom that is
given to this man, that such mighty works come about by his hands?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        Isn't this the carpenter, the son of Mary, and brother of James,
Joses, Judas, and Simon? Aren't his sisters here with us?" They were
offended at him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        Jesus said to them, "A prophet is not without honor, except in
his own country, and among his own relatives, and in his own house."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        He could do no mighty work there, except that he laid his hands
on a few sick folk, and healed them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        He marveled because of their
unbelief.

   He went around the villages teaching.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        He called to himself the
twelve, and began to send them out two by two; and he gave them
authority over the unclean spirits.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        He charged them that they
should take nothing for their journey, except a staff only: no bread,
no wallet, no money in their purse,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        but to wear sandals, and not
put on two tunics.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        He said to them, "Wherever you enter into a
house, stay there until you depart from there.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        Whoever will not
receive you nor hear you, as you depart from there, shake off the dust
that is under your feet for a testimony against them. Assuredly, I tell
you, it will be more tolerable for Sodom and Gomorrah in the day of
judgment than for that city!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        They went out and preached that people should repent.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        They cast out many demons, and anointed many with oil who were sick,
and healed them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        King Herod heard this, for his name had become
known, and he said, "John the Baptizer has risen from the dead, and
therefore these powers are at work in him."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        But others said, "It
is Elijah." Others said, "It is the Prophet, or like one of the
prophets."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        But Herod, when he heard this, said, "This is John,
whom I beheaded. He has risen from the dead."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        For Herod himself
had sent out and arrested John, and bound him in prison for the sake of
Herodias, his brother Philip's wife, for he had married her.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        For
John said to Herod, "It is not lawful for you to have your brother's
wife."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        Herodias set herself against him, and desired to kill
him, but she couldn't,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        for Herod feared John, knowing that he
was a righteous and holy man, and kept him safe. When he heard him, he
did many things, and he heard him gladly.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        Then a convenient day came, that Herod on his birthday made a
supper for his nobles, the high officers, and the chief men of Galilee.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        When the daughter of Herodias herself came in and danced, she
pleased Herod and those sitting with him. The king said to the young
lady, "Ask me whatever you want, and I will give it to you."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        He
swore to her, "Whatever you shall ask of me, I will give you, up to
half of my kingdom."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        She went out, and said to her mother, "What shall I ask?"

   She said, "The head of John the Baptizer."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        She came in immediately with haste to the king, and asked, "I
want you to give me right now the head of John the Baptizer on a
platter."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        The king was exceedingly sorry, but for the sake of his
oaths, and of his dinner guests, he didn't wish to refuse her.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        Immediately the king sent out a soldier of his guard, and commanded to
bring John's head, and he went and beheaded him in the prison,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        and brought his head on a platter, and gave it to the young lady; and
the young lady gave it to her mother.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        When his disciples heard this, they came and took up his
corpse, and laid it in a tomb.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        The apostles gathered themselves together to Jesus, and they
told him all things, whatever they had done, and whatever they had
taught.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        He said to them, "You come apart into a deserted place,
and rest awhile." For there were many coming and going, and they had no
leisure so much as to eat.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        They went away in the boat to a
desert place by themselves.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        They saw them going, and many
recognized him and ran there on foot from all the cities. They arrived
before them and came together to him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        Jesus came out, saw a
great multitude, and he had compassion on them, because they were like
sheep without a shepherd, and he began to teach them many things.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        When it was late in the day, his disciples came to him, and
said, "This place is deserted, and it is late in the day.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        Send
them away, that they may go into the surrounding country and villages,
and buy themselves bread, for they have nothing to eat."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        But he answered them, "You give them something to eat."

   They asked him, "Shall we go and buy two hundred denarii worth of
bread, and give them something to eat?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        He said to them, "How many loaves do you have? Go see."

   When they knew, they said, "Five, and two fish."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        He commanded them that everyone should sit down in groups on
the green grass.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        They sat down in ranks, by hundreds and by
fifties.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        He took the five loaves and the two fish, and looking
up to heaven, he blessed and broke the loaves, and he gave to his
disciples to set before them, and he divided the two fish among them
all.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="42"><p>
                        They all ate, and were filled.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="43"><p>
                        They took up twelve
baskets full of broken pieces and also of the fish.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="44"><p>
                        Those who
ate the loaves were five thousand men.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="45"><p>
                        Immediately he made his disciples get into the boat, and to
go ahead to the other side, to Bethsaida, while he himself sent the
multitude away.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="46"><p>
                        After he had taken leave of them, he went up the
mountain to pray.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="47"><p>
                        When evening had come, the boat was in the midst of the sea,
and he was alone on the land.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="48"><p>
                        Seeing them distressed in rowing,
for the wind was contrary to them, about the fourth watch of the night
he came to them, walking on the sea, and he would have passed by them,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="49"><p>
                        but they, when they saw him walking on the sea, supposed that it
was a ghost, and cried out;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="50"><p>
                        for they all saw him, and were
troubled. But he immediately spoke with them, and said to them, "Cheer
up! It is I! Don't be afraid."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="51"><p>
                        He got into the boat with them;
and the wind ceased, and they were very amazed among themselves, and
marveled;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="52"><p>
                        for they hadn't understood about the loaves, but their
hearts were hardened.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="53"><p>
                        When they had crossed over, they came to land at Gennesaret,
and moored to the shore.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="54"><p>
                        When they had come out of the boat,
immediately the people recognized him,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="55"><p>
                        and ran around that whole
region, and began to bring those who were sick, on their mats, to where
they heard he was.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="56"><p>
                        Wherever he entered, into villages, or into
cities, or into the country, they laid the sick in the marketplaces,
and begged him that they might touch just the fringe of his garment;
and as many as touched him were made well.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="7">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        Then the Pharisees, and some of the scribes gathered together
to him, having come from Jerusalem.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Now when they saw some of his
disciples eating bread with defiled, that is, unwashed, hands, they
found fault.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        (For the Pharisees, and all the Jews, don't eat
unless they wash their hands and forearms, holding to the tradition of
the elders.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        They don't eat when they come from the marketplace,
unless they bathe themselves, and there are many other things, which
they have received to hold to: washings of cups, pitchers, bronze
vessels, and couches.)
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        The Pharisees and the scribes asked him,
"Why don't your disciples walk according to the tradition of the
elders, but eat their bread with unwashed hands?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        He answered them, "Well did Isaiah prophesy of you hypocrites,
as it is written,
'This people honors me with their lips,
   But their heart is far from me.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        But in vain do they worship me,
   Teaching as doctrines the commandments of men.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        "For you set aside the commandment of God, and hold tightly to
the tradition of men -- the washing of pitchers and cups, and you do
many other such things."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        He said to them, "Full well do you
reject the commandment of God, that you may keep your tradition.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        For Moses said, 'Honor your father and your mother;' and, 'He who
speaks evil of father or mother, let him be put to death.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        But
you say, 'If a man tells his father or his mother, "Whatever profit you
might have received from me is Corban, that is to say, given to God;"'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        then you no longer allow him to do anything for his father or
his mother,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        making void the word of God by your tradition, which
you have handed down. You do many things like this."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        He called all the multitude to himself, and said to them,
"Hear me, all of you, and understand.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        There is nothing from
outside of the man, that going into him can defile him; but the things
which proceed out of the man are those that defile the man.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        If
anyone has ears to hear, let him hear!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        When he had entered into a house away from the multitude, his
disciples asked him about the parable.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        He said to them, "Are you
thus without understanding also? Don't you perceive that whatever goes
into the man from outside can't defile him,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        because it doesn't
go into his heart, but into his stomach, then into the latrine, thus
making all foods clean?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        He said, "That which proceeds out of
the man, that defiles the man.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        For from within, out of the
hearts of men, proceed evil thoughts, adulteries, sexual sins, murders,
thefts,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        covetings, wickedness, deceit, lustful desires, an evil
eye, blasphemy, pride, and foolishness.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        All these evil things
come from within, and defile the man."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        From there he arose, and went away into the borders of Tyre
and Sidon. He entered into a house, and didn't want anyone to know it,
but he couldn't escape notice.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        For a woman, whose little
daughter had an unclean spirit, having heard of him, came and fell down
at his feet.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        Now the woman was a Greek, a Syrophoenician by
race. She begged him that he would cast the demon out of her daughter.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        But Jesus said to her, "Let the children be filled first, for it
is not appropriate to take the children's bread and throw it to the
dogs."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        But she answered him, "Yes, Lord. Yet even the dogs under the
table eat the children's crumbs."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        He said to her, "For this saying, go your way. The demon has
gone out of your daughter."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        She went away to her house, and found the child lying on the
bed, with the demon gone out.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        Again he departed from the borders of Tyre and Sidon, and
came to the sea of Galilee, through the midst of the region of
Decapolis.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        They brought to him one who was deaf and had an
impediment in his speech. They begged him to lay his hand on him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        He took him aside from the multitude, privately, and put his
fingers into his ears, and he spat, and touched his tongue.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        Looking up to heaven, he sighed, and said to him, "Ephphatha!" that is,
"Be opened!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        Immediately his ears were opened, and the
impediment of his tongue was loosed, and he spoke clearly.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        He
commanded them that they should tell no one, but the more he commanded
them, so much the more widely they proclaimed it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        They were
astonished beyond measure, saying, "He has done all things well. He
makes even the deaf hear, and the mute speak!"
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="8">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        In those days, when there was a very great multitude, and they
had nothing to eat, Jesus called his disciples to himself, and said to
them,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        "I have compassion on the multitude, because they have
stayed with me now three days, and have nothing to eat.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        If I send
them away fasting to their home, they will faint on the way, for some
of them have come a long way."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        His disciples answered him, "From where could one satisfy
these people with bread here in a deserted place?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        He asked them, "How many loaves do you have?"

   They said, "Seven."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        He commanded the multitude to sit down on the ground, and he
took the seven loaves. Having given thanks, he broke them, and gave
them to his disciples to serve, and they served the multitude.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        They had a few small fish. Having blessed them, he said to serve these
also.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        They ate, and were filled. They took up seven baskets of
broken pieces that were left over.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        Those who had eaten were about
four thousand. Then he sent them away.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        Immediately he entered into the boat with his disciples, and
came into the region of Dalmanutha.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        The Pharisees came out and
began to question him, seeking from him a sign from heaven, and testing
him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        He sighed deeply in his spirit, and said, "Why does this
generation seek a sign? Most assuredly I tell you, no sign will be
given to this generation."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        He left them, and again entering into the boat, departed to
the other side.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        They forgot to take bread; and they didn't have
more than one loaf in the boat with them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        He charged them,
saying, "Take heed: beware of the yeast of the Pharisees and the yeast
of Herod."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        They reasoned with one another, saying, "It's because we have
no bread."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        Jesus, perceiving it, said to them, "Why do you reason that
it's because you have no bread? Don't you perceive yet, neither
understand? Is your heart still hardened?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        Having eyes, don't you
see? Having ears, don't you hear? Don't you remember?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        When I
broke the five loaves among the five thousand, how many baskets full of
broken pieces did you take up?"

   They told him, "Twelve."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        "When the seven loaves fed the four thousand, how many
baskets full of broken pieces did you take up?"

   They told him, "Seven."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        He asked them, "Don't you understand, yet?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        He came to Bethsaida. They brought a blind man to him, and
begged him to touch him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        He took hold of the blind man by the
hand, and brought him out of the village. When he had spit on his eyes,
and laid his hands on him, he asked him if he saw anything.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        He looked up, and said, "I see men; for I see them like trees
walking."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        Then again he laid his hands on his eyes. He looked intently,
and was restored, and saw everyone clearly.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        He sent him away to
his house, saying, "Don't enter into the village, nor tell anyone in
the village."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        Jesus went out, with his disciples, into the villages of
Caesarea Philippi. On the way he asked his disciples, "Who do men say
that I am?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        They told him, "John the Baptizer, and others say Elijah, but
others: one of the prophets."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        He said to them, "But who do you say that I am?"

   Peter answered, "You are the Christ."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        He charged them that they should tell no one about him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        He began to teach them that the Son of Man must suffer many
things, and be rejected by the elders, the chief priests, and the
scribes, and be killed, and after three days rise again.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        He
spoke to them openly. Peter took him, and began to rebuke him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        But he, turning around, and seeing his disciples, rebuked Peter, and
said, "Get behind me, Satan! For you have in mind not the things of
God, but the things of men."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        He called the multitude to himself with his disciples, and
said to them, "Whoever wants to come after me, let him deny himself,
and take up his cross, and follow me.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        For whoever wants to save
his life will lose it; and whoever will lose his life for my sake and
the gospel's will save it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        For what does it profit a man, to
gain the whole world, and forfeit his life?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        For what will a man
give in exchange for his life?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        For whoever will be ashamed of me
and of my words in this adulterous and sinful generation, the Son of
Man also will be ashamed of him, when he comes in the glory of his
Father with the holy angels."
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="9">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        He said to them, "Most assuredly I tell you, there are some
standing here who will in no way taste death, until they see the
Kingdom of God come with power."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        After six days Jesus took with him Peter, James, and John, and
brought them up onto a high mountain privately by themselves, and he
was changed into another form in front of them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        His clothing
became glistening, exceedingly white, like snow, such as no launderer
on earth can whiten them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        Elijah and Moses appeared to them, and
they were talking with Jesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Peter answered Jesus, "Rabbi, it is good for us to be here.
Let's make three tents: one for you, one for Moses, and one for
Elijah."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        For he didn't know what to say, for they were very
afraid.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        A cloud came, overshadowing them, and a voice came out of the
cloud, "This is my beloved Son. Listen to him."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        Suddenly looking around, they saw no one with them any more,
except Jesus only.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        As they were coming down from the mountain, he charged them
that they should tell no one what things they had seen, until after the
Son of Man had risen from the dead.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        They kept the saying,
questioning among themselves what the rising from the dead should mean.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        They asked him, saying, "Why do the scribes say that Elijah
must come first?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        He said to them, "Elijah indeed comes first, and restores all
things. How is it written about the Son of Man, that he should suffer
many things and be despised?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        But I tell you that Elijah has
come, and they have also done to him whatever they wanted to, even as
it is written about him."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Coming to the disciples, he saw a great multitude around
them, and scribes questioning them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        Immediately all the
multitude, when they saw him, were greatly amazed, and running to him
greeted him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        He asked the scribes, "What are you asking them?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        One of the multitude answered, "Teacher, I brought to you my
son, who has a mute spirit;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        and wherever it seizes him, it
throws him down, and he foams at the mouth, and grinds his teeth, and
wastes away. I asked your disciples to cast it out, and they weren't
able."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        He answered him, "Unbelieving generation, how long shall I be
with you? How long shall I bear with you? Bring him to me."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        They brought him to him, and when he saw him, immediately the
spirit convulsed him, and he fell on the ground, wallowing and foaming
at the mouth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        He asked his father, "How long has it been since this has
come to him?"

   He said, "From childhood.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        Often it has cast him both into the
fire and into the water, to destroy him. But if you can do anything,
have compassion on us, and help us."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        Jesus said to him, "If you can believe, all things are
possible to him who believes."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        Immediately the father of the child cried out with tears, "I
believe. Help my unbelief!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        When Jesus saw that a multitude came running together, he
rebuked the unclean spirit, saying to him, "You mute and deaf spirit, I
command you, come out of him, and never enter him again!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        Having cried out, and convulsed greatly, it came out of him.
The boy became like one dead; so much that most of them said, "He is
dead."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        But Jesus took him by the hand, and raised him up; and he
arose.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        When he had come into the house, his disciples asked him
privately, "Why couldn't we cast it out?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        He said to them, "This
kind can come out by nothing, except by prayer and fasting."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        They went out from there, and passed through Galilee. He
didn't want anyone to know it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        For he was teaching his
disciples, and said to them, "The Son of Man is being handed over to
the hands of men, and they will kill him; and when he is killed, on the
third day he will rise again."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        But they didn't understand the saying, and were afraid to ask
him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        He came to Capernaum, and when he was in the house he asked
them, "What were you arguing among yourselves on the way?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        But they were silent, for they had disputed one with another
on the way about who was the greatest.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        He sat down, and called the twelve; and he said to them, "If
any man wants to be first, he shall be last of all, and servant of
all."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        He took a little child, and set him in the midst of them.
Taking him in his arms, he said to them,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        "Whoever receives one
such little child in my name, receives me, and whoever receives me,
doesn't receive me, but him who sent me."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        John said to him, "Teacher, we saw someone who doesn't follow
us casting out demons in your name; and we forbade him, because he
doesn't follow us."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        But Jesus said, "Don't forbid him, for there is no one who
will do a mighty work in my name, and be able quickly to speak evil of
me.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        For whoever is not against us is on our side.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        For
whoever will give you a cup of water to drink in my name, because you
are Christ's, most assuredly I tell you, he will in no way lose his
reward.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="42"><p>
                        Whoever will cause one of these little ones who believe
in me to stumble, it would be better for him if he was thrown into the
sea with a millstone hung around his neck.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="43"><p>
                        If your hand causes
you to stumble, cut it off. It is better for you to enter into life
maimed, rather than having your two hands to go into Gehenna, into the
unquenchable fire,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="44"><p>
                        'where their worm doesn't die, and the fire
is not quenched.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="45"><p>
                        If your foot causes you to stumble, cut it
off. It is better for you to enter into life lame, rather than having
your two feet to be cast into Gehenna, into the fire that will never be
quenched --
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="46"><p>
                        'where their worm doesn't die, and the fire is not
quenched.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="47"><p>
                        If your eye causes you to stumble, cast it out. It is
better for you to enter into the Kingdom of God with one eye, rather
than having two eyes to be cast into the Gehenna of fire,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="48"><p>
                        'where
their worm doesn't die, and the fire is not quenched.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="49"><p>
                        For
everyone will be salted with fire, and every sacrifice will be seasoned
with salt.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="50"><p>
                        Salt is good, but if the salt has lost its saltiness,
with what will you season it? Have salt in yourselves, and be at peace
with one another."
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="10">
                    

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        He arose from there and came into the borders of Judea and
beyond the Jordan. Multitudes came together to him again. As he usually
did, he was again teaching them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Pharisees came to him testing
him, and asked him, "Is it lawful for a man to divorce his wife?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        He answered, "What did Moses command you?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        They said, "Moses allowed a certificate of divorce to be
written, and to divorce her."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        But Jesus said to them, "For your hardness of heart, he wrote
you this commandment.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        But from the beginning of the creation,
'God made them male and female.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        For this cause a man will leave
his father and mother, and will join to his wife,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        and the two
will become one flesh,' so that they are no longer two, but one flesh.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        What therefore God has joined together, let no man separate."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        In the house, his disciples asked him again about the same
matter.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        He said to them, "Whoever divorces his wife, and
marries another, commits adultery against her.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        If a woman
herself divorces her husband, and marries another, she commits
adultery."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        They were bringing to him little children, that he should
touch them, but the disciples rebuked those who were bringing them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        But when Jesus saw it, he was moved with indignation, and said
to them, "Allow the little children to come to me! Don't forbid them,
for the Kingdom of God belongs to such as these.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        Most assuredly
I tell you, whoever will not receive the Kingdom of God like a little
child, he will in no way enter into it."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        He took them in his
arms, and blessed them, laying his hands on them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        As he was going out into the way, one ran to him, knelt
before him, and asked him, "Good Teacher, what shall I do that I may
inherit eternal life?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        Jesus said to him, "Why do you call me good? No one is good
except one -- God.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        You know the commandments: 'Do not murder,'
'Do not commit adultery,' 'Do not steal,' 'Do not give false
testimony,' 'Do not defraud,' 'Honor your father and mother.'"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        He said to him, "Teacher, I have observed all these things
from my youth."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        Jesus looking at him loved him, and said to him, "One thing
you lack. Go, sell whatever you have, and give to the poor, and you
will have treasure in heaven; and come, follow me, taking up the cross."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        But his face fell at that saying, and he went away
sorrowful, for he was one who had great possessions.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        Jesus
looked around, and said to his disciples, "How difficult it is for
those who have riches to enter into the Kingdom of God!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        The disciples were amazed at his words. But Jesus answered
again, "Children, how hard is it for those who trust in riches to enter
into the Kingdom of God!
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        It is easier for a camel to go through
a needle's eye than for a rich man to enter into the Kingdom of God."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        They were exceedingly astonished, saying to him, "Then who
can be saved?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        Jesus, looking at them, said, "With men it is impossible,
but not with God, for all things are possible with God."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        Peter began to tell him, "Behold, we have left all, and have
followed you."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        Jesus said, "Most assuredly I tell you, there is no one who
has left house, or brothers, or sisters, or father, or mother, or wife,
or children, or land, for my sake, and for the gospel's sake,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        but he will receive one hundred times more now in this time, houses,
brothers, sisters, mothers, children, and land, with persecutions; and
in the age to come eternal life.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        But many who are first will be
last; and the last first."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        They were on the way, going up to Jerusalem; and Jesus was
going in front of them, and they were amazed; and those who followed
were afraid. He again took the twelve, and began to tell them the
things that were going to happen to him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        "Behold, we are going
up to Jerusalem. The Son of Man will be delivered to the chief priests
and the scribes. They will condemn him to death, and will deliver him
to the Gentiles.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        They will mock him, spit on him, scourge him,
and kill him. On the third day he will rise again."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        James and John, the sons of Zebedee, came near to him,
saying, "Teacher, we want you to do for us whatever we will ask."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        He said to them, "What do you want me to do for you?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        They said to him, "Grant to us that we may sit, one at your
right hand, and one at your left hand, in your glory."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        But Jesus said to them, "You don't know what you are asking.
Are you able to drink the cup that I drink, and to be baptized with the
baptism that I am baptized with?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        They said to him, "We are able."

   Jesus said to them, "You shall indeed drink the cup that I drink,
and you shall be baptized with the baptism that I am baptized with;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        but to sit at my right hand and at my left hand is not mine to
give, but for whom it has been prepared."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        When the ten heard it, they began to be indignant towards
James and John.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="42"><p>
                        Jesus summoned them, and said to them, "You know that they
who are recognized as rulers over the Gentiles lord it over them, and
their great ones exercise authority over them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="43"><p>
                        But it shall not
be so among you, but whoever wants to become great among you shall be
your servant.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="44"><p>
                        Whoever of you wants to become first among you,
shall be servant of all.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="45"><p>
                        For the Son of Man also came not to be
served, but to serve, and to give his life as a ransom for many."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="46"><p>
                        They came to Jericho. As he went out from Jericho, with his
disciples and a great multitude, the son of Timaeus, Bartimaeus, a
blind beggar, was sitting by the road.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="47"><p>
                        When he heard that it
was Jesus the Nazarene, he began to cry out, and say, "Jesus, you son
of David, have mercy on me!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="48"><p>
                        Many rebuked him, that he should
be quiet, but he cried out much more, "You son of David, have mercy on
me!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="49"><p>
                        Jesus stood still, and said, "Call him."

   They called the blind man, saying to him, "Cheer up! Get up. He is
calling you!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="50"><p>
                        He, casting away his cloak, sprang up, and came to Jesus.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="51"><p>
                        Jesus asked him, "What do you want me to do for you?"

   The blind man said to him, "Rhabboni, that I may see again."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="52"><p>
                        Jesus said to him, "Go your way. Your faith has made you
well." Immediately he received his sight, and followed Jesus in the way.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="11">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        When they drew near to Jerusalem, to Bethsphage and Bethany,
at the Mount of Olives, he sent two of his disciples,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        and said
to them, "Go your way into the village that is opposite you.
Immediately as you enter into it, you will find a colt tied, on which
no one has sat. Untie him, and bring him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        If anyone asks you,
'Why are you doing this?' say, 'The Lord needs him;' and immediately he
will send him back here."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        They went away, and found a colt tied at the door outside in
the open street, and they untied him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Some of those who stood
there asked them, "What are you doing, untying the colt?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        They
said to them just as Jesus had said, and they let them go.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        They brought the colt to Jesus, and threw their garments on
it, and Jesus sat on it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        Many spread their garments on the way,
and others were cutting down branches from the trees, and spreading
them on the road.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        Those who went in front, and those who
followed, cried out, "Hosanna! Blessed is he who comes in the name of
the Lord!
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        Blessed is the kingdom of our father David that is
coming in the name of the Lord! Hosanna in the highest!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        Jesus entered into the temple in Jerusalem. When he had
looked around at everything, it being now evening, he went out to
Bethany with the twelve.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        The next day, when they had come out from Bethany, he was
hungry.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        Seeing a fig tree afar off having leaves, he came to
see if perhaps he might find anything on it. When he came to it, he
found nothing but leaves, for it was not the season for figs.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Jesus told it, "May no one ever eat fruit from you again!" and his
disciples heard it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        They came to Jerusalem, and Jesus entered into the temple,
and began to throw out those who sold and those who bought in the
temple, and overthrew the tables of the money-changers, and the seats
of those who sold the doves.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        He would not allow anyone to carry
a container through the temple.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        He taught, saying to them,
"Isn't it written, 'My house will be called a house of prayer for all
the nations?' But you have made it a den of robbers!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        The chief priests and the scribes heard it, and sought how
they might destroy him. For they feared him, for all the multitude was
astonished at his teaching.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        When evening came, he went out of the city.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        As they
passed by in the morning, they saw the fig tree withered away from the
roots.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        Peter, remembering, said to him, "Rabbi, look! The fig
tree which you cursed has withered away."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        Jesus answering said to them, "Have faith in God.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        For most assuredly I tell you, whoever may tell this mountain, 'Be
taken up and cast into the sea,' and doesn't doubt in his heart, but
believes that what he says is happening; he shall have whatever he
says.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        Therefore I tell you, all things whatever you pray and
ask for, believe that you receive them, and you shall have them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        Whenever you stand praying, forgive, if you have anything
against anyone; so that your Father, who is in heaven, may also forgive
you your transgressions.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        But if you do not forgive, neither
will your Father in heaven forgive your transgressions."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        They came again to Jerusalem, and as he was walking in the
temple, the chief priests, and the scribes, and the elders came to him,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        and they began saying to him, "By what authority do you do
these things? Or who gave you this authority to do these things?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        Jesus said to them, "I will ask you one question. Answer me,
and I will tell you by what authority I do these things.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        The
baptism of John -- was it from heaven, or from men? Answer me."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        They reasoned with themselves, saying, "If we should say,
'From heaven;' he will say, 'Why then did you not believe him?'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        If we should say, 'From men'"--they feared the people, for all held
John to really be a prophet.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        They answered Jesus, "We don't
know."

   Jesus said to them, "Neither do I tell you by what authority I do
these things."
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="12">
                    

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        He began to speak to them in parables. "A man planted a
vineyard, put a hedge around it, dug a pit for the winepress, built a
tower, rented it out to a farmer, and went into another country.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        When it was time, he sent a servant to the farmer to get from the
farmer his share of the fruit of the vineyard.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        They took him,
beat him, and sent him away empty.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        Again, he sent another
servant to them; and they threw stones at him, wounded him in the head,
and sent him away shamefully treated.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Again he sent another; and
they killed him; and many others, beating some, and killing some.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        Therefore still having one, his beloved son, he sent him last to
them, saying, 'They will respect my son.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        But those farmers said
among themselves, 'This is the heir. Come, let's kill him, and the
inheritance will be ours.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        They took him, killed him, and cast
him out of the vineyard.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        What therefore will the lord of the
vineyard do? He will come and destroy the farmers, and will give the
vineyard to others.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        Haven't you even read this Scripture:
'The stone which the builders rejected,
   The same was made the head of the corner.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        This was from the Lord,
   It is marvelous in our eyes'?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        They tried to seize him, but they feared the multitude; for
they perceived that he spoke the parable against them. They left him,
and went away.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        They sent some of the Pharisees and of the
Herodians to him, that they might trap him with words.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        When
they had come, they asked him, "Teacher, we know that you are honest,
and don't defer to anyone; for you aren't partial to anyone, but truly
teach the way of God. Is it lawful to pay taxes to Caesar, or not?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        Shall we give, or shall we not give?"

   But he, knowing their hypocrisy, said to them, "Why do you test me?
Bring me a denarius, that I may see it."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        They brought it.

   He said to them, "Whose is this image and inscription?"

   They said to him, "Caesar's."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        Jesus answered them, "Render to Caesar the things that are
Caesar's, and to God the things that are God's."

   They marveled greatly at him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        There came to him Sadducees, who say that there is no
resurrection. They asked him, saying,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        "Teacher, Moses wrote to
us, 'If a man's brother dies, and leaves a wife behind him, and leaves
no children, that his brother should take his wife, and raise up
offspring for his brother.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        There were seven brothers. The
first took a wife, and dying left no offspring.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        The second took
her, and died, leaving no children behind him. The third likewise;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        and the seven took her and left no children. Last of all the
woman also died.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        In the resurrection, when they rise, whose
wife will she be of them? For the seven had her as a wife."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        Jesus answered them, "Isn't this because you are mistaken,
not knowing the Scriptures, nor the power of God?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        For when they
will rise from the dead, they neither marry, nor are given in marriage,
but are like angels in heaven.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        But about the dead, that they
are raised; haven't you read in the book of Moses, about the Bush, how
God spoke to him, saying, 'I am the God of Abraham, the God of Isaac,
and the God of Jacob?'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        He is not the God of the dead, but of
the living. You are therefore badly mistaken."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        One of the scribes came, and heard them questioning
together. Knowing that he had answered them well, asked him, "Which
commandment is the greatest of all?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        Jesus answered, "The greatest is, 'Hear, Israel, the Lord
our God, the Lord is one:
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        you shall love the Lord your God with
all your heart, and with all your soul, and with all your mind, and
with all your strength.' This is the first commandment.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        The
second is like this, 'You shall love your neighbor as yourself.' There
is no other commandment greater than these."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        The scribe said to him, "Truly, teacher, you have said well
that he is one, and there is none other but he,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        and to love him
with all the heart, and with all the understanding, with all the soul,
and with all the strength, and to love his neighbor as himself, is more
important than all whole burnt offerings and sacrifices."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        When Jesus saw that he answered wisely, he said to him, "You
are not far from the Kingdom of God."

   No one dared ask him any question after that.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        Jesus
responded, as he taught in the temple, "How is it that the scribes say
that the Christ is the son of David?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        For David himself said in
the Holy Spirit,
'The Lord said to my Lord,
   Sit at my right hand,
   Until I make your enemies the footstool of your feet.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        Therefore David himself calls him Lord, so how can he be his
son?"

   The common people heard him gladly.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        In his teaching he said
to them, "Beware of the scribes, who like to walk in long robes, and to
get greetings in the marketplaces,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        and the best seats in the
synagogues, and the best places at feasts:
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        those who devour
widows' houses, and for a pretense make long prayers. These will
receive greater condemnation."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        Jesus sat down opposite the treasury, and saw how the
multitude cast money into the treasury. Many who were rich cast in
much.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="42"><p>
                        A poor widow came, and she cast in two small brass coins,
which make a quadrans.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="43"><p>
                        He called his disciples to himself, and
said to them, "Most assuredly I tell you, this poor widow gave more
than all those who are giving into the treasury,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="44"><p>
                        for they all
gave out of their abundance, but she, out of her poverty, gave all that
she had to live on."
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="13">
                    

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        As he went out out of the temple, one of his disciples said
to him, "Teacher, see what kind of stones and what kind of buildings!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Jesus said to him, "Do you see these great buildings? There
will not be left here one stone on another, which will not be thrown
down."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        As he sat on the Mount of Olives opposite the temple, Peter,
James, John, and Andrew asked him privately,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        "Tell us, when will
these things be? What is the sign that these things are all about to be
fulfilled?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Jesus, answering, began to tell them, "Be careful that no one
leads you astray.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        For many will come in my name, saying, 'I am
he!' and will lead many astray.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        "When you hear of wars and rumors of wars, don't be troubled.
For those must happen, but the end is not yet.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        For nation will
rise against nation, and kingdom against kingdom. There will be
earthquakes in various places. There will be famines and troubles.
These things are the beginning of birth pains.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        But watch
yourselves, for they will deliver you up to councils. You will be
beaten in synagogues. You will stand before rulers and kings for my
sake, for a testimony to them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        The gospel must first be
preached to all the nations.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        When they lead you away and
deliver you up, don't be anxious beforehand, or premeditate what you
will say, but say whatever will be given you in that hour. For it is
not you who speak, but the Holy Spirit.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        "Brother will deliver up brother to death, and the father
his child. Children will rise up against parents, and cause them to be
put to death.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        You will be hated by all men for my name's sake,
but he who endures to the end, the same will be saved.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        But when
you see the abomination of desolation, spoken of by Daniel the prophet,
standing where it ought not (let the reader understand), then let those
who are in Judea flee to the mountains,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        and let him who is on
the housetop not go down, nor enter in, to take anything out of his
house.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        Let him who is in the field not return back to take his
cloak.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        But woe to those who are with child and to those who
nurse babies in those days!
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        Pray that your flight won't be in
the winter.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        For in those days there will be oppression, such as
there has not been the like from the beginning of the creation which
God created until now, and never will be.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        Unless the Lord had
shortened the days, no flesh would have been saved; but for the elect's
sake, whom he chose, he shortened the days.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        Then if anyone
tells you, 'Look, here is the Christ!' or, 'Look, there!' don't believe
it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        For there will arise false christs and false prophets, and
will show signs and wonders, that they may lead astray, if possible,
even the chosen ones.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        But you watch.

   "Behold, I have told you all things beforehand.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        But in those
days, after that oppression, the sun will be darkened, the moon will
not give its light,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        the stars will be falling from the sky, and
the powers that are in the heavens will be shaken.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        Then they
will see the Son of Man coming in clouds with great power and glory.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        Then he will send out his angels, and will gather together his
elect from the four winds, from the ends of the earth to the ends of
the sky.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        "Now from the fig tree, learn this parable. When the branch
has now become tender, and puts forth its leaves, you know that the
summer is near;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        even so you also, when you see these things
coming to pass, know that it is near, at the doors.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        Most
assuredly I say to you, this generation will not pass away until all
these things happen.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        Heaven and earth will pass away, but my
words will not pass away.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        But of that day or that hour no one
knows, not even the angels in heaven, nor the Son, but only the Father.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        Watch, keep alert, and pray; for you don't know when the time
is.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        "It is like a man, traveling to another country, having left
his house, and given authority to his servants, and to each one his
work, and also commanded the doorkeeper to keep watch.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        Watch
therefore, for you don't know when the lord of the house is coming,
whether at evening, or at midnight, or when the rooster crows, or in
the morning;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        lest coming suddenly he might find you sleeping.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        What I tell you, I tell all: Watch."
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="14">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        It was now two days before the feast of the Passover and the
unleavened bread, and the chief priests and the scribes sought how they
might sieze him by deception, and kill him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        For they said, "Not
during the feast, because there might be a riot of the people."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        While he was at Bethany, in the house of Simon the leper, as
he sat at the table, a woman came having an alabaster jar of ointment
of pure nard -- very costly. She broke the jar, and poured it over his
head.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        But there were some who were indignant among themselves,
saying, "Why has this ointment been wasted?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        For this might have
been sold for more than three hundred denarii, and given to the poor."
They grumbled against her.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        But Jesus said, "Leave her alone. Why do you trouble her? She
has done a good work for me.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        For you always have the poor with
you, and whenever you want to, you can do them good; but you will not
always have me.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        She has done what she could. She has anointed my
body beforehand for the burying.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        Most assuredly I tell you,
wherever this gospel may be preached throughout the whole world, that
which this woman has done will also be spoken of for a memorial of her."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        Judas Iscariot, who was one of the twelve, went away to the
chief priests, that he might deliver him to them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        They, when
they heard it, were glad, and promised to give him money. He sought how
he might conveniently deliver him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        On the first day of
unleavened bread, when they sacrificed the Passover, his disciples
asked him, "Where do you want us to go and make ready that you may eat
the Passover?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        He sent two of his disciples, and said to them, "Go into the
city, and there you will meet a man carrying a pitcher of water. Follow
him,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        and wherever he enters in, tell the master of the house,
'The Teacher says, "Where is the guest room, where I may eat the
Passover with my disciples?"'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        He will himself show you a large
upper room furnished and ready. Make ready for us there."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        His disciples went out, and came into the city, and found
things as he had said to them, and they prepared the Passover.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        When it was evening he came with the twelve.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        As they
sat and were eating, Jesus said, "Most assuredly I tell you, one of you
will betray me -- he who eats with me."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        They began to be sorrowful, and to ask him one by one,
"Surely not I?" And another said, "Surely not I?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        He answered them, "It is one of the twelve, he who dips with
me in the dish.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        For the Son of Man goes, even as it is written
about him, but woe to that man by whom the Son of Man is betrayed! It
would be better for that man if he had not been born."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        As they were eating, Jesus took bread, and when he had
blessed, he broke it, and gave to them, and said, "Take, eat. This is
my body."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        He took the cup, and when he had given thanks, he gave to
them. They all drank of it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        He said to them, "This is my blood
of the new covenant, which is poured out for many.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        Most
assuredly I tell you, I will no more drink of the fruit of the vine,
until that day when I drink it anew in the Kingdom of God."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        When they had sung a hymn, they went out to the Mount of Olives.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        Jesus said to them, "All of you will be made to stumble
because of me tonight, for it is written, 'I will strike the shepherd,
and the sheep will be scattered.'
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        However, after I am raised
up, I will go before you to Galilee."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        But Peter said to him, "Although all will be offended, yet I
will not."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        Jesus said to him, "Most assuredly I tell you, that you
today, even this night, before the cock crows twice, you will deny me
three times."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        But he spoke all the more, "If I must die with you, I will
not deny you." They all said the same thing.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        They came to a place which was named Gethsemane. He said to
his disciples, "Sit here, while I pray."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        He took with him
Peter, James, and John, and began to be greatly troubled and
distressed.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        He said to them, "My soul is exceedingly sorrowful,
even to death. Stay here, and watch."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        He went forward a little, and fell on the ground, and prayed
that, if it were possible, the hour might pass away from him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        He said, "Abba, Father, all things are possible to you. Please remove
this cup from me. However, not what I desire, but what you desire."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        He came and found them sleeping, and said to Peter, "Simon,
are you sleeping? Couldn't you watch one hour?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        Watch and pray,
that you not enter into temptation. The spirit indeed is willing, but
the flesh is weak."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        Again he went away, and prayed, saying the same words.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        Again he returned, and found them sleeping, for their eyes were
very heavy, and they didn't know what to answer him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        He came
the third time, and said to them, "Sleep on now, and take your rest. It
is enough. The hour has come. Behold, the Son of Man is betrayed into
the hands of sinners.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="42"><p>
                        Arise, let us be going. Behold, he who
betrays me is at hand."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="43"><p>
                        Immediately, while he was still speaking, Judas, one of the
twelve, came -- and with him a multitude with swords and clubs, from
the chief priests, the scribes, and the elders.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="44"><p>
                        Now he who
betrayed him had given them a sign, saying, "Whoever I will kiss, that
is he. Seize him, and lead him away safely."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="45"><p>
                        When he had come,
immediately he came to him, and said, "Rabbi! Rabbi!" and kissed him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="46"><p>
                        They laid their hands on him, and seized him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="47"><p>
                        But a
certain one of those who stood by drew his sword, and struck the
servant of the high priest, and cut off his ear.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="48"><p>
                        Jesus answered them, "Have you come out, as against a
robber, with swords and clubs to seize me?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="49"><p>
                        I was daily with you
in the temple teaching, and you didn't arrest me. But this is so that
the Scriptures might be fulfilled."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="50"><p>
                        They all left him, and fled.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="51"><p>
                        A certain young man
followed him, having a linen cloth thrown around himself, over his
naked body. The young men grabbed him,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="52"><p>
                        but he left the linen
cloth, and fled from them naked.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="53"><p>
                        They led Jesus away to the
high priest. All the chief priests, the elders, and the scribes came
together with him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="54"><p>
                        Peter had followed him from a distance, until he came into
the court of the high priest. He was sitting with the officers, and
warming himself in the light of the fire.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="55"><p>
                        Now the chief priests
and the whole council sought witnesses against Jesus to put him to
death, and found none.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="56"><p>
                        For many gave false testimony against
him, and their testimony didn't agree with each other.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="57"><p>
                        Some
stood up, and gave false testimony against him, saying,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="58"><p>
                        "We
heard him say, 'I will destroy this temple that is made with hands, and
in three days I will build another made without hands.'"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="59"><p>
                        Even
so, their testimony did not agree.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="60"><p>
                        The high priest stood up in the midst, and asked Jesus,
"Have you no answer? What is it which these testify against you?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="61"><p>
                        But he stayed quiet, and answered nothing. Again the high
priest asked him, "Are you the Christ, the Son of the Blessed?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="62"><p>
                        Jesus said, "I AM. You will see the Son of Man sitting at
the right hand of Power, and coming with the clouds of the sky."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="63"><p>
                        The high priest tore his clothes, and said, "What further
need have we of witnesses?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="64"><p>
                        You have heard the blasphemy! What
do you think?" They all condemned him to be worthy of death.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="65"><p>
                        Some began to spit on him, and to cover his face, and to beat him with
fists, and to tell him, "Prophesy!" The officers struck him with the
palms of their hands.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="66"><p>
                        As Peter was in the courtyard below, one of the maids of the
high priest came,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="67"><p>
                        and seeing Peter warming himself, she looked
at him, and said, "You were also with the Nazarene, Jesus!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="68"><p>
                        But he denied it, saying, "I neither know, nor understand
what you are saying." He went out on the porch, and the cock crowed.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="69"><p>
                        The maid saw him, and began again to tell those who stood
by, "This is one of them."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="70"><p>
                        But he again denied it. After a
little while again those who stood by said to Peter, "You truly are one
of them, for you are a Galilean, and your speech shows it."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="71"><p>
                        But
he began to curse, and to swear, "I don't know this man of whom you
speak!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="72"><p>
                        The cock crowed the second time. Peter remembered the
word, how that Jesus said to him, "Before the cock crows twice, you
will deny me three times." When he thought about that, he wept.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="15">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        Immediately in the morning the chief priests, with the elders
and scribes, and the whole council, held a consultation, and bound
Jesus, and carried him away, and delivered him up to Pilate.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Pilate asked him, "Are you the King of the Jews?"

   He answered, "So you say."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        The chief priests accused him of many things.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        Pilate
again asked him, "Have you no answer? See how many things they testify
against you!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        But Jesus made no further answer, so that Pilate marveled.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        Now at the feast he used to release to them one prisoner,
whom they asked of him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        There was one called Barabbas, bound
with those who had made insurrection, men who in the insurrection had
committed murder.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        The multitude, crying aloud, began to ask him
to do as he always did for them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        Pilate answered them, saying,
"Do you you want me to release to you the King of the Jews?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        For he perceived that for envy the chief priests had delivered him up.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        But the chief priests stirred up the multitude, that he should
release Barabbas to them instead.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        Pilate again asked them,
"What then should I do to him whom you call the King of the Jews?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        They cried out again, "Crucify him!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Pilate said to them, "Why, what evil has he done?"

   But they cried out exceedingly, "Crucify him!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        Pilate, wishing to please the multitude, released Barabbas
to them, and handed over Jesus, when he had flogged him, to be
crucified.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        The soldiers led him away within the court, which is
the Praetorium; and they called together the whole cohort.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        They
clothed him with purple, and weaving a crown of thorns, they put it on
him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        They began to salute him, "Hail, King of the Jews!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        They struck his head with a reed, and spat on him, and bowing
their knees, did homage to him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        When they had mocked him, they
took the purple off of him, and put his own garments on him. They led
him out to crucify him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        They compelled one passing by, coming
from the country, Simon of Cyrene, the father of Alexander and Rufus,
to go with them, that he might bear his cross.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        They brought him
to the place called Golgotha, which is, being interpreted, "The place
of a skull."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="23"><p>
                        They offered him wine mixed with myrrh to drink,
but he didn't take it.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="24"><p>
                        Crucifying him, they parted his garments among them, casting
lots on them, what each should take.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="25"><p>
                        It was the third hour, and
they crucified him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="26"><p>
                        The superscription of his accusation was
written over him, "THE KING OF THE JEWS."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="27"><p>
                        With him they
crucified two robbers; one on his right hand, and one on his left.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="28"><p>
                        The Scripture was fulfilled, which says, "He was numbered with
transgressors."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="29"><p>
                        Those who passed by blasphemed him, wagging their heads, and
saying, "Ha! You who destroy the temple, and build it in three days,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="30"><p>
                        save yourself, and come down from the cross!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="31"><p>
                        Likewise, also the chief priests mocking among themselves
with the scribes said, "He saved others. He can't save himself.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="32"><p>
                        Let the Christ, the King of Israel, now come down from the cross, that
we may see and believe him." Those who were crucified with him insulted
him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="33"><p>
                        When the sixth hour had come, there was darkness over the
whole land until the ninth hour.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="34"><p>
                        At the ninth hour Jesus cried
with a loud voice, saying, "Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani?" which is,
being interpreted, "My God, my God, why have you forsaken me?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="35"><p>
                        Some of those who stood by, when they heard it, said,
"Behold, he is calling Elijah."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="36"><p>
                        One ran, and filling a sponge full of vinegar, put it on a
reed, and gave it to him to drink, saying, "Let him be. Let's see
whether Elijah comes to take him down."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="37"><p>
                        Jesus cried out with a loud voice, and gave up the spirit.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="38"><p>
                        The veil of the temple was torn in two from the top to the
bottom.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="39"><p>
                        When the centurion, who stood by opposite him, saw that
he cried out like this and breathed his last, he said, "Truly this man
was the Son of God!"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="40"><p>
                        There were also women watching from afar, among whom were
both Mary Magdalene, and Mary the mother of James the less and of
Joses, and Salome;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="41"><p>
                        who, when he was in Galilee, followed him,
and served him; and many other women who came up with him to Jerusalem.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="42"><p>
                        When evening had now come, because it was the Preparation
Day, that is, the day before the Sabbath,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="43"><p>
                        Joseph of Arimathaea,
a prominent council member who also himself was looking for the Kingdom
of God, came. He boldly went in to Pilate, and asked for Jesus' body.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="44"><p>
                        Pilate marveled if he were already dead; and summoning the
centurion, he asked him whether he had been dead long.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="45"><p>
                        When he
found out from the centurion, he granted the body to Joseph.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="46"><p>
                        He
bought a linen cloth, and taking him down, wound him in the linen
cloth, and laid him in a tomb which had been cut out of a rock. He
rolled a stone against the door of the tomb.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="47"><p>
                        Mary Magdalene and
Mary, the mother of Joses, saw where he was laid.
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="16">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                    
                        When the Sabbath was past, Mary Magdalene, and Mary the
mother of James, and Salome, bought spices, that they might come and
anoint him.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Very early on the first day of the week, they came
to the tomb when the sun had risen.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        They were saying among
themselves, "Who will roll away the stone from the door of the tomb for
us?"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        for it was very big. Looking up, they saw that the stone
was rolled back.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Entering into the tomb, they saw a young man sitting on the
right side, dressed in a white robe, and they were amazed.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        He
said to them, "Don't be amazed. You seek Jesus, the Nazarene, who has
been crucified. He has risen. He is not here. Behold, the place where
they laid him!
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        But go, tell his disciples and Peter, 'He goes
before you into Galilee. There you will see him, as he said to you.'"
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        They went out, and fled from the tomb, for trembling and
astonishment had come on them. They said nothing to anyone; for they
were afraid.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        Now when he had risen early on the first day of the
week, he appeared first to Mary Magdalene, from whom he had cast out
seven demons.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        She went and told those who had been with him, as
they mourned and wept.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        When they heard that he was alive, and
had been seen by her, they disbelieved.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        After these things he
was revealed in another form to two of them, as they walked, on their
way into the country.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        They went away and told it to the rest.
They didn't believe them, either.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Afterward he was revealed to the eleven themselves as they
sat at the table, and he rebuked them for their unbelief and hardness
of heart, because they didn't believe those who had seen him after he
had risen.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        He said to them, "Go into all the world, and preach
the gospel to the whole creation.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        He who believes and is
baptized will be saved; but he who disbelieves will be condemned.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        These signs will accompany those who believe: in my name they
will cast out demons; they will speak with new languages;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        they
will take up serpents; and if they drink any deadly thing, it will in
no way hurt them; they will lay hands on the sick, and they will
recover."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        So then the Lord Jesus, after he had spoken to them, was
received up into heaven, and sat down at the right hand of God.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        They went out, and preached everywhere, the Lord working with them, and
confirming the word by the signs that followed. Amen.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
