<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Apollodorus Against Stephanus 1</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by A. T. Murray, Ph.D.,
                            LL.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1939</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>

        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div type="section" n="1">
                <p>Having been overwhelmed by false testimony, men of Athens, and having been
                    outrageously and cruelly treated by Phormio, I have come to win in your court a
                    verdict against those responsible for the wrong. I beg and beseech and implore
                    you all, in the first place to give me a favorable hearing (for it is a great
                    thing for those who have met with misfortune, as I have done, to be able to tell
                    others of what they have suffered, and to find in you listeners who are kindly
                        disposed)<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl n="Aesch. PB 637"
                            >Aesch. PB 637-639</bibl> for an almost identical sentiment.</note>; and
                    in the second place, if I shall seem to you to be the victim of wrongdoing, to
                    render me the aid which is my due. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="2">
                <p>I shall prove to you that this man Stephanus has both given false testimony, and
                    has done this from a base desire for gain, and that he is convicted out of his
                    own lips; so transparent is the case from every point of view. And I shall
                    endeavor to relate to you in the fewest possible words all that has taken place
                    between Phormio and myself from the first; and after hearing this you will be
                    convinced both of the villainy of Phormio and that these men have borne false
                    testimony. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="3">
                <p>As for myself, men of the jury, a large property was left me by my father, and
                    this was in the possession of Phormio, who furthermore had married my mother
                    while I was out of the country on public business, serving as your trierarch.
                    (How he managed it, perhaps it is not proper for a son fully to explain about
                    his mother.) When I returned and learned of this and saw what had been done,
                    although I was greatly incensed and took it much to heart, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="4">
                <p>I was unable to bring a private action (for there were no actions at that time,
                    since you put off all such matters because of the war<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The reference is to the hostilities between Athens and
                        Thebes in the period between the battle of Leuctra (<date when="-0371"
                            >371</date> B.C.) and the battle of Mantinea (<date when="-0362"
                            >362</date> B.C.).</note>), but I indicted him before the
                        Thesmothetae<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note a on p. 202 of vol.
                        1.</note> on the charge of outrage.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The
                            <foreign xml:lang="grc">u(/brews grafh/</foreign> was a public
                        indictment for wanton outrage. It was a criminal charge, and involved the
                        penalty of a fine payable to the State, or, in extreme cases, even the
                        penalty of death. It was far more serious than a charge of common assault
                            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">ai)kei/as di/kh</foreign>). See <bibl
                            n="Dem. 54.1">Dem. 54.1</bibl></note> However, time passed and the
                    indictment was evaded (seeing that actions were not being held), and moreover
                    children were born by my mother to Phormio, and after this (for the whole truth
                    shall be told you, men of the jury), many kindly overtures were made on the part
                    of my mother, and pleas on behalf of this man Phormio, and many overtures on the
                    part of Phormio himself that were both moderate and humble in their terms. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="5">
                <p>However, to make the story brief, men of Athens, he would not do one of the
                    things to which he had agreed, and tried to withhold from me the money which he
                    held as capital in the bank; so then I was compelled to enter suit against him
                    at the earliest opportunity. Phormio on his part, seeing that everything would
                    be brought to light, and that he would be proved to have acted toward me as the
                    basest of humankind, contrived and concocted this plot in furtherance of which
                    the defendant Stephanus gave this false testimony against me. In the first
                    place, he entered a special plea in the suit in which he was defendant, claiming
                    that the suit was not admissible; and then he produced false witnesses who
                    stated that I had given him a release from my claims, and who deposed to a
                    forged lease and to a will which never existed. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="6">
                <p>He had the advantage over me in being the first speaker, because this was a
                    special plea and the case was not coming to trial upon the real issue, and by
                    reading these documents and making other false statements which he thought would
                    favor his case, he made such an impression on the jury that they refused to hear
                    a single word from me. I was fined one-sixth of the amount claimed,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See note a on p. 50 of vol. 1.</note> was denied
                    the right of a hearing, and was treated with such contumely as I doubt if any
                    other man ever was, and I went from the court, men of Athens, taking the matter
                    bitterly and grievously to heart. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="7">
                <p>Upon going over it in my own mind, however, I see that there was abundant excuse
                    for those who gave that verdict (for I do not know what other vote I could
                    myself have given, if I had known nothing of the facts and had heard the
                    testimony), but that our anger should fall upon these men who by giving false
                    testimony were responsible for this result. Of the others who have given
                    testimony I shall speak when I proceed against them, but regarding the testimony
                    of the defendant Stephanus I shall try to instruct you at once. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="8">
                <p>Take the deposition itself, and read it, please, that from its very language I
                    may prove my point.Read; and do you check the water.<quote n="Deposition"
                            ><title>Deposition</title><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Stephanus, son
                        of Menecles, of Acharnae, Endius, son of Epigenes, of Lamptrae, Scythes, son
                        of Harmateus, of Cydathenaeum<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Acharnae was
                            a deme of the tribe Oeneïs, Lamptrae of the tribe Erectheïs, and
                            Cydathenaeum of the tribe Pandionis.</note> depose that they were
                        present before the arbitrator Teisias, of Acharnae, when Phormio challenged
                        Apollodorus, if he declared that the document which Phormio put into the box
                        was not a copy of the will of Pasio, to open the will of Pasio, which
                        Amphias, brother-in-law of Cephisophon, submitted to the arbitrator; and
                        that Apollodorus refused to open it; and that the document in question was a
                        copy of the will of Pasio.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="9">
                <p>You have heard the deposition, men of the jury, and I think that even if you have
                    noticed nothing else, this at least must have seemed strange to you, that it
                    begins with a challenge and ends with a will. However, I on my part, count it
                    right, when I shall have shown what may be called the main substance of the
                    testimony to be false, then, and not till then, to say something also about
                    matters of that sort. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="10">
                <p>Well, then, it is deposed by them that Phormio challenged me to open the will
                    which Amphias, brother—in—law of Cephisophon, submitted to the arbitrator
                    Teisias; and that I refused to open it; and that the will to which they
                    themselves deposed was a copy of that original; and then follows a copy of the
                    will. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="11">
                <p>Now as to whether Phormio tendered me this challenge or not, and whether the will
                    is genuine or spurious I say nothing as yet; I will discuss these matters before
                    you presently; but I will take up the testimony they have given, that I refused
                    to open the document. I would have you look at the matter in this way—what
                    reason would anyone have had for refusing to open it? In order, one may say,
                    that the will might not be shown to the jury. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="12">
                <p>Well and good. If they had not deposed to the will as well as to the challenge,
                    there would have been some reason in my refusing to open the document; but since
                    they deposed to both, and the jurymen were going to hear the will in any case,
                    what advantage was there for me in refusing? None, assuredly. Quite the
                    contrary, men of Athens; even if these men had tendered no challenge, but had
                    merely talked of the matter, and someone had delivered a document to them as a
                    will, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="13">
                <p>it would have been my business to tender the challenge and to order them to open
                    it, in order that, if the contents differed from the statements which these men
                    had made in their deposition, I might have called a number of the bystanders as
                    witnesses, and have used this fact as a proof that the rest of their story too
                    was a fabrication; but, if the contents were the same, I might have required the
                    one presenting it to give evidence himself. If he consented, I should have had a
                    responsible witness, and, if he refused, this very fact again would have been a
                    convincing proof for me that the affair had been concocted. And in the former
                    case the result would have been that I had one person with whom to deal, whereas
                    according to the depositions of these men I have many. Is there anyone among you
                    who would have chosen the latter course? I think not one of you would have. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="14">
                <p>Well then, you ought not to believe it of anyone else either. For, men of Athens,
                    in all courses of action which involve anger or some getting of gain or
                    exasperation or a spirit of jealousy, different persons will act in different
                    ways in accordance with their several dispositions; but in all cases where none
                    of these things is involved, but merely a calm calculation of one's own
                    interest, who would be so senseless as to dismiss what would help him and do
                    what would make it more difficult for him to win his case? Yet a course of
                    action which is neither natural nor reasonable, which, in short, no human being
                    would have undertaken—this these witnesses have attributed to me. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="15">
                <p>Moreover, it is not only from what they have stated in their deposition regarding
                    my refusal to open the document that one can tell that they are lying, but also
                    from the fact that they have deposed at one and the same time both to a
                    challenge and to a will. For I think you are all aware that challenges were
                    devised for all transactions which it is impossible to bring before you;</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="16">
                <p>for instance, a man may not be put to torture in your presence—for this it is
                    necessary that there be a challenge; again, if anything has been transacted and
                    has taken place somewhere out of the country, it is necessary that for this too
                    there should be a challenge to go by sea or land to the place where the thing
                    was done; and so for other things of that sort. But in cases where it is
                    possible to produce the things themselves before your eyes, what could be
                    simpler than to produce them publicly? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="17">
                <p>Well, my father died at Athens, the arbitration took place in the Painted
                        Stoa,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The Painted Stoa was the largest and
                        finest of the porticoes surrounding the agora. It got its name from the
                        famous paintings with which its walls were adorned.</note> and these men
                    have deposed that Amphias produced the document before the arbitrator. Then, if
                    it was genuine, the document ought to have been put into the box,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 53.2">Aristot.
                            Ath. Pol. 53.2</bibl></note> and the one producing it should have so
                    testified, in order that the jurymen might have reached a decision in accordance
                    with the truth and after an inspection of the seals; and I, on my part, if
                    anyone was wronging me, might have proceeded against him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="18">
                <p>But, as it is, no one person has taken the whole matter upon himself or given
                    straightforward testimony, as one would do in testifying to the truth, but each
                    has deposed to a part of the story, fancying that he is very clever and that for
                    this reason he will escape punishment,—one of them deposing that he holds a
                    document on which is written “the will of Pasio”; another that, being sent by
                    the former person, he produced this document, but had no knowledge as to whether
                    it was genuine or spurious. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="19">
                <p>These men, who are here in court, using the challenge as a screen, deposed to a
                    will in such a way that the jurymen believed this will to be my father's, and I
                    was debarred from obtaining a hearing regarding my wrongs, but in such a way
                    also that they on their part would most clearly be convicted of having given
                    false testimony. And yet this was the very opposite of what they
                    intended.However, that you may know that I am speaking the truth in this, take
                    the deposition of Cephisophon.<quote type="Deposition"
                            ><title>Deposition</title><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Cephisophon,
                        son of Cephalion, of Aphidna,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Aphidna was a
                            deme of the tribe Aeantis.</note> deposes that a document was left him
                        by his father, on which was inscribed “the will of Pasio.”</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="20">
                <p>It was a simple thing, men of the jury, for the one who gave this testimony to
                    add “and this is the document which the deponent exhibits,” and to put the
                    document into the box. But, I presume, he thought that this falsehood would
                    deserve your indignation, and that you would punish him for it, whereas to
                    testify that a document had been bequeathed to him was a trifling matter and one
                    of no consequence. And yet it is this very thing that makes the whole matter
                    clear, and proves that they have concocted it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="21">
                <p>For if the inscription on the will had been “the property of Pasio and Phormio”
                    or “in the matter of Phormio,” or something of that sort, he would naturally
                    have kept it for him; but if, as he has testified, the inscription was “the will
                    of Pasio,” I should certainly have appropriated it, knowing that I was about to
                    go to law, and knowing further that, if its contents were as represented, it was
                    prejudicial to my interests; for I was the heir, and if the will was my
                    father's, it belonged to me, as did also all the rest of my father's estate.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="22">
                <p>Well then, by its having been produced to Phormio, by its having been inscribed
                    “the will of Pasio,” and yet ignored by me, it is proved that the will is a
                    forgery and that the testimony of Cephisophon is false. But no more of
                    Cephisophon; it is not with him that I have to do at present, and he has given
                    no testimony as to the contents of the will. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="23">
                <p>And yet, men of Athens, I would have you consider how strong a proof this also is
                    that these men have given false testimony. For when the witness who stated that
                    he had the document in his own possession did not dare to say that the one
                    produced by Phormio was a copy of the one in his own keeping; and when these men
                    cannot state that they were present in the first instance or that they saw the
                    document opened before the arbitrator, but have themselves actually deposed that
                    I refused to open it, to have testified now that the one is a copy of the other,
                    is not this to have accused themselves of falsifying? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="24">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>More than all this, men of Athens, any man by
                    examining the wording of the deposition can see that it is nothing but a
                    contrivance of theirs to the end that rightly or wrongly it may appear that my
                    father made this will.But take the deposition itself, and read, stopping
                    wherever I bid you, that from its own wording I may prove my point.<quote
                        n="Deposition"><title>Deposition</title><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>. . .
                        depose that they were present before the arbitrator Teisias, when Phormio
                        challenged Apollodorus, if he declared that the document was not a copy of
                        the will of Pasio . . .</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="25">
                <p>Stop reading. Bear in mind that the words are “of the will of Pasio.” Now persons
                    who wished to bear witness to the truth—assuming that it is absolutely
                    established that the challenge was tendered, which it was not—ought to have
                    given their testimony in the following way.Read the deposition again from the
                        beginning.<quote n="Deposition"><title>Deposition</title>. . . depose that
                        they were present before the arbitrator Teisias . . .</quote><milestone
                        ed="P" unit="para"/>We do depose; for we were present. Read on.<quote
                        type="continued">. . . when Phormio challenged Apollodorus . .
                    .</quote>This, too, they might properly have stated, assuming that he really
                    tendered the challenge.<quote n="continued">. . . if he declared that the
                        document was not a copy of the will of Pasio . . .</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="26">
                <p>Stop right there. There is not a person in the world, I presume, who would have
                    proceeded to give this testimony, unless he had been present when my father drew
                    up the will. Instead, he would have said at once, “How do we know if there is
                    any will of Pasio's?”—and he would have demanded that Phormio write, as in the
                    beginning of the challenge: “If I declared that the document was not a copy of
                    the will which Phormio stated that Pasio had left,”—not “of the will of Pasio.”
                    For this was to testify that there was a will (which was their intention), the
                    other that Phormio said that there was. And, I take it, there is a world of
                    difference between a thing's being so, and Phormio's saying that it is. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="27">
                <p>So, in order that you may know how many and how important objects were to be
                    secured by the fabrication of the will, listen for a moment. The first, men of
                    Athens, was this, that Phormio should escape paying the penalty for corrupting
                    one whom it is not proper for me to name, but whom you know of yourselves, even
                    if I do not name her<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This assumption of
                        reluctance to speak of his mother is in glaring contrast with the gross
                        accusation made against her later in the speech.</note>; next, that he might
                    get possession of my father's property which was in my mother's keeping; and in
                    addition to this, that he might become master of everything else which belonged
                    to us. That this is so, you will be convinced when you hear the will. For it
                    will be found, not like that of a father writing in the interest of his sons,
                    but like that of a slave who has shamefully misused what belonged to his master,
                    and who is seeking how he may escape punishment. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="28">
                <p>Read them the will itself, to which these men have deposed along with the
                    challenge; and do you mark well what I say.<quote n="Will"
                            ><title>Will</title><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This is the will of
                        Pasio of Acharnae. I give my wife Archippê to Phormio, and I give as dowry
                        to Archippê the talent due to me at Peparethus,<note resp="Loeb"
                            anchored="true">Peparethus is a small island north of Euboea, on which
                            was an Athenian colony. Its modern name is Skopelos.</note> the talent
                        due to me here in Athens, a lodging-house worth one hundred minae, the
                        female slaves and jewelry, and all else that she has in the house. All these
                        things I give to Archippê.</quote>You have heard, men of Athens, the large
                    amount of the dowry,—a talent from Peparethus, a talent from Athens, a
                    lodging-house worth a hundred minae, female slaves and jewelry, and all else
                    that she has in her possession—I give it all, says the will; and by this clause
                    he precludes us even from searching for any of the property that was left. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="29">
                <p>Now let me show you the lease under which Phormio had taken the bank from my
                    father; for from this also, spurious though it is, you will see that the will is
                    fabrication through and through. I will set forth for you, not a different
                    lease, but the one which Phormio produced, in which there is an added clause
                    setting down my father as owing Phorniio eleven talents on the deposits. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="30">
                <p>This had, I think, the following purpose. Of the effects in the house he made
                    himself master by the will, on the ground that they had been given as a dowry
                    with my mother, as you have just heard; but the money in the bank, about which
                    everybody knew, and which could not be hidden, he got into his hands by
                    representing that our father owed it, so that whatever sums he might be proved
                    to have in his possession he might claim to have received in payment. You have
                    perhaps imagined, because he solecizes<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true"
                            >“<foreign xml:lang="grc">so/loikos</foreign> is a word of narrower
                        meaning than <foreign xml:lang="grc">ba/rbaros</foreign>, and is applied
                        mainly to faults of pronunciation or mistakes in grammar, especially syntax,
                        due to foreign origin” (Sandys). It would, however, be quite futile to look
                        for a specific error in the, very probably spurious, lease inserted in the
                        oration.</note> in his speech, that he is a barbarian and a man readily to
                    be despised. The fellow is indeed a barbarian in that he hates those whom he
                    ought to honor; but in villainy and in bringing matters to ruin<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The metaphor is from house-breaking.</note> he is second to
                    none. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="31">
                <p>Take the lease and read it—the lease which they put in, as they did the will, by
                    means of a challenge.<quote n="Lease of The Bank"><title>Lease of The
                            Bank</title>On the following terms Pasio has let the bank to Phormio:
                        Phormio is to pay to the sons of Pasio as rental for the bank two talents
                        and forty minae each year above the daily expenditure, and it shall not be
                        lawful for Phormio to carry on a banking business independently unless he
                        first obtains the consent of the sons of Pasio. And Pasio owes the bank
                        eleven talents upon the deposits.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="32">
                <p>This, men of the jury, is the agreement which Phormio produced, alleging that he
                    had leased the bank upon these terms. You learn from hearing it read that
                    Phormio, over and above the daily expenditure, was to pay as rent two talents
                    and forty minae each year, and that it was not to be permitted him to carry on a
                    banking business, unless he obtained our consent; and there is added as a final
                    statement, “Pasio owes eleven talents upon the deposits.” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="33">
                <p>Now, is there any man who would have submitted to the payment of so large a
                    rental for the counter, the site, and the books? And is there any man who would
                    have entrusted the rest of the assets to a man thanks to whom the bank had
                    incurred so great a liability?<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Pasio is stated
                        by Phormio to have owed the bank eleven talents (<bibl n="Dem. 36.4">Dem.
                            36.4</bibl>). This debt may be assumed to have been properly secured, so
                        that it was in no sense a deficit. The present speaker, however, represents
                        it as such, and implies that the bank had been brought to insolvence through
                        Phormio's incompetence.</note> For, if there was a shortage of so large an
                    amount, it was incurred while Phormio was manager. For you all know that, while
                    my father was engaged in the banking business, Phormio sat at the counter and
                    was his manager; so that he ought rather to be in the mill<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">Slaves were often condemned to the heavy labor of turning
                        the millstone.</note> than to become master of the rest of the property.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="34">
                <p>However, I pass over this and all else that I might find to say about the eleven
                    talents, to show that my father did not owe them but that Phormio secretly
                    appropriated them.<milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>But let me remind you of the
                    purpose for which I read the lease, namely, to prove that the will is spurious.
                    For it stands written in the lease that it shall not be lawful for Phormio to
                    engage in banking business, unless he obtains our consent. This clause
                    absolutely proves the will to be spurious. For what man, who had taken
                    precautions that the profits which Phormio might make by banking should accrue
                    to his own children and not to Phormio himself, and to secure this end had
                    stipulated that it should not be permitted him to engage in banking for himself,
                    lest his interests might be separated from ours—what man, I ask, in these
                    circumstances would have provided that Phormio should get possession of what he
                    had himself won by his labor and left in his house? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="35">
                <p>And would he have begrudged him the banking business, in which he might have
                    given him a share without disgrace, and yet have given him his wife, a bequest
                    disgraceful above all others? Yes, after receiving from you the gift of
                    citizenship, he gave his wife (if indeed he gave her) as a slave giving to his
                    master, and not, on the contrary, as a master to a slave, and he added such a
                    dowry as no man in Athens was ever known to give.<note resp="Loeb"
                        anchored="true">The mother of Demosthenes brought to her husband a dowry of
                        only 80 minae (<bibl n="Dem. 27.5">Dem. 27.5</bibl>); the mother of
                        Mantitheus one of 60 minae (<bibl n="Dem. 40.6">Dem. 40.6</bibl>); and the
                        two daughters of Polyeuctus dowries of 40 minae each (<bibl n="Dem. 41.3"
                            >Dem. 41.3</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 41.27">Dem. 41.27</bibl>).</note>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="36">
                <p>And yet, to have been honored with the hand of his mistress was of itself enough
                    to make this fellow content, whereas in my father's case, even if he received as
                    much money as these people allege that he gave, it was not reasonable for him to
                    make this arrangement.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, it would not
                        have been reasonable for him to leave his wife to his former slave even if
                        he had received as a bribe the large sum which he is alleged to have given
                        as a marriage portion.</note> Nevertheless, to things which are proved to be
                    false by the probabilities, the dates and the facts, to these this man Stephanus
                    has not hesitated to depose. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="37">
                <p>Then he goes about, saying that Nicocles testified that he had served as guardian
                    under the will, and Pasicles that he had lived as ward under the will. But for
                    my part I hold that these very facts are proofs that neither these witnesses nor
                    those have testified to the truth. For a person who testifies that he served as
                    guardian under a will should certainly know what the nature of the will was, and
                    a person who testifies that he lived as ward under a will should certainly know
                    what the nature of the will was. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="38">
                <p>Why in the world, then, Stephanus, did you people depose to the will under the
                    form of a challenge, instead of leaving the matter to them? If they on their
                    part shall declare that they do not know the contents of the will, how is it
                    possible for you to know them, you who have never in any way been connected with
                    the matter? Why, pray, is it that one group of witnesses testified to these
                    facts, and another group to those? It is as I have already told you: they
                    divided the fraud. The one so testifying saw no danger in deposing that he
                    served as guardian under the will, or that he lived as ward under the will, </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="39">
                <p>each one of them omitting to state what had been written in the will by
                    Phormio,—no danger in deposing that one's father had left him a document with
                    the word “will” written on it, or anything of that sort. But to testify to the
                    existence of a will in which were involved the theft of such vast sums, the
                    corruption of a lady, the marriage of a mistress with her slave, matters which
                    entailed such shame and disgrace—nobody was ready to do this save these men who
                    got up the challenge; and from them it is right to exact the penalty for the
                    whole of this villainous fraud. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="40">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, men of Athens, that it may be made clear to
                    you that this fellow Stephanus has given false testimony—made clear not merely
                    by my accusations and proofs, but also by the acts of the person who brought him
                    forward as a witness—I wish to tell you what that person has done. As I said at
                    the beginning of my speech, I shall show that they are their own accusers. In
                    the suit in which this testimony was given, Phormio entered a special plea to
                    estop me on the ground that the suit was not admissible, alleging that I had
                    released him from all claims. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="41">
                <p>Now I myself know that this is false, and I shall prove it so when I proceed
                    against those who gave this testimony; but Stephanus is not at liberty to say it
                    is false. If, then, you should believe in the genuineness of the release, this,
                    more than anything else, would prove that the fellow has given false testimony,
                    and has deposed to a will that is forged. For who would be so senseless as to
                    give a release in the presence of witnesses, that his discharge might be
                    binding, and yet to suffer the articles of agreement, the will, and the other
                    documents regarding which he gave the release, to remain under seal as evidence
                    against himself? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="42">
                <p>The special plea, therefore, contradicts all the evidence, and the lease which I
                    just now read to you contradicts this will; not one of their acts is either
                    reasonable or straightforward or consistent with itself. In this manner their
                    whole story is shown to be a fiction and a fraud. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="43">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>That the statements in the deposition are true I
                    hold that neither Stephanus himself nor anyone else in his behalf will be able
                    to prove. I hear, however, that he is prepared to make some such statement as
                    this, that he is responsible for a challenge, not for a deposition, and that he
                    should be held to account, not for everything written in it, but for two things
                    only—whether Phormio tendered me this challenge or not, and whether I refused
                    it; these matters and no more, he will say, were included in his deposition; as
                    for the rest, Phormio covered them in his challenge, but whether they were true
                    or not it was not the business of the witness to inquire. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="44">
                <p>In answer to this argument and to the man's impudence it is better that I say a
                    few words to you in advance, that you be not taken at unawares and misled. In
                    the first place, when he tries to bring forward the argument that he is not
                    responsible for the entire content of the deposition, bear in mind that the
                    reason why the law requires people to give evidence in written form is that it
                    may not be open to them to strike out any part of what has been written, or add
                    anything to it. He should at the time have demanded the erasure of the
                    statements to which he will now deny having deposed, and not try now to brazen
                    it out, while they stand in the document. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="45">
                <p>Moreover, consider this too, whether you would suffer me in your presence to take
                    the document and add to it. Of course you would not. Well, then, neither is it
                    fitting to suffer him to strike out any of its contents. For who will ever be
                    convicted of giving false testimony, if he is to depose to what he pleases, and
                    be accountable only for what he pleases? No, the law does not thus make a
                    distinction in these matters, and you ought not to listen to such a thing
                    either. The straightforward and honest course is this: “What stands written? To
                    what have you deposed? Show that this is true. For you have written in your plea
                    in answer to the complaint these words, 'I have given true testiniony in
                    testifying to what is contained in the deposition'—not 'to this or that in the
                    deposition.'” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="46">
                <p>To prove that this is so, take, please, the plea itself. Read it.<quote
                        n="Complaint"><title>Complaint and Counter-Plea</title><milestone ed="P"
                            unit="para"/>Apollodorus, son of Pasio, of Acharnae, sues Stephanus, son
                        of Menecles, of Acharnae, for false testimony; damages one talent. Stephanus
                        gave false testimony against me in testifying to that which is contained in
                        the record.I gave true testimony in testifying to that which is contained in
                        the record.</quote><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>This is the plea which the
                    defendant himself has entered. You must keep it in mind, and not regard the
                    deceitful language which will soon be addressed to you as being more worthy of
                    credence than the laws and what the defendant has written in his own plea. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="47">
                <p>I learn that they are going to speak about my original suit and to denounce it as
                    baseless and malicious. But I on my part have already mentioned to you and
                    explained in detail the manner in which Phormio concocted the lease, in order to
                    get into his possession the banking-stock, and I should be unable to speak of
                    these other matters and at the same time convict these men of giving false
                    testimony; for the amount of water allotted me is not sufficient. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="48">
                <p>And that you yourselves could not in fairness be willing to listen to them in
                    regard to these matters you will see at once, if you reflect that it is no
                    difficult matter to speak now about subjects concerning which no charge is made,
                    just as it was no difficult matter for Phormio to get himself acquitted by
                    reading false depositions. However, no man would say that either of these
                    courses is right, but that course rather which I am about to propose. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="49">
                <p>Listen, and judge. I demand that they do not now seek for the proofs regarding my
                    charges, proofs which should have been mentioned at the former trial, but of
                    which they deprived me; but that they prove that the testimony by which they
                    deprived me of them was true. If, when I bring in my suit, they are to demand
                    that I refute their testimony, and, when I proceed against that, they are to bid
                    me speak regarding my original charges, what they propose will be neither right
                    nor in your interest. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="50">
                <p>For you have sworn to give a verdict, not in regard to matters upon which the
                    defendant asks your decision, but in regard to those only which are raised by
                    the prosecution. The cause of action must be made clear by the complaint of the
                    prosecutor, and this in my case is a suit against this man for false testimony.
                    Let him not, then, leave this and talk about matters regarding which I am not
                    suing him; and do you, if he is so shameless, refuse to permit it. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="51">
                <p>I imagine that, having no just argument to advance on any point, he will have
                    recourse to this defence also—that it is absurd for me, after having been
                    worsted in the case of the special plea, to sue those who gave evidence of a
                    will; and he will maintain that the jurymen in that trial were led to vote in
                    favor of Phormio, by the evidence of those who testified to the release rather
                    than by that of those who testified to the will. But, men of Athens, I think you
                    all know that it is your habit to examine the facts no less closely than the
                    pleas which men make regarding them; and these men, by giving false testimony
                    against me regarding the facts themselves, weakened my arguments on the special
                    plea. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="52">
                <p>However, besides this, it is absurd, when all have given false evidence, to
                    demonstrate who did the greatest amount of harm, instead of making each one
                    prove that he has himself testified to the truth. It is not by proving that
                    another has done more outrageous things than himself that a witness is to be let
                    off, but by showing that he has himself given testimony that is true. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="53">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>Now, men of Athens, let me show you the thing for
                    which more than anything else this fellow Stephanus deserves to be put to death.
                    It is an awful thing to bear false witness against anyone whomsoever, but it is
                    a thing more awful by far, and more deserving of indignation, to bear false
                    witness against those of your own blood; for a man of that stamp violates, not
                    the written laws alone, but also the ties of natural relationship. This, then,
                    Stephanus shall be proved to have done. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="54">
                <p>For his mother and the father of my wife are a brother and sister, so that my
                    wife is his first cousin, and the children born to her and to me are his
                    cousin's children. Do you think, then, that this man, if he saw his female
                    relatives driven by want to shameful actions, would give them in marriage and
                    add marriage portions out of his own resources—a thing which many a man has done
                    ere now—when he has chosen to give false testimony in order to prevent their
                    getting what belongs to them, and has counted the wealth of Phormio of higher
                    worth than the strong ties of kinship? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="55">
                <p><milestone ed="P" unit="para"/>However, to prove that I am telling the truth in
                    this, take the deposition of Deinias and read it; and call Deinias.<quote
                        n="Deposition"><title>Deposition</title>Deinias, son of Theomnestus, of
                            Athmonon,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Athmonon was a deme of the
                            tribe Cecropis.</note> deposes that he gave his daughter to Apollodorus
                        to live with him as his wife according to the laws, and that he was never
                        present when Apollodorus released Phormio from all claims, nor was ever
                        aware that he had done so.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="56">
                <p>Deinias, men of the jury, is very like Stephanus, is he not?—Deinias, who on
                    account of his relationship, refuses to testify against the defendant even to
                    what is true, and on behalf of his daughter and his daughter's children, and me,
                    his son-in-law!<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">We must assume that Deinias,
                        when called upon, refused to swear to the deposition which was read (whether
                        the deposition given in the text is authentic or not cannot be determined
                        with certainty). He must, therefore, have taken the oath of disclaimer
                            (<foreign xml:lang="grc">e)cwmosi/a</foreign>), although this is not
                        stated in the text. Apollodorus asserts that Deinias took this course for
                        fear that by swearing to the deposition he would work harm to his kinsman
                        Stephanus. We must be content to confess our ignorance of his
                        reasons.</note> Not so Stephanus here. He did not hesitate to give false
                    testimony against us; even respect for his own mother, if for no one else, did
                    not keep him from bringing the extremest poverty upon those who through her were
                    his relatives. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="57">
                <p>I wish now, men of the jury, to tell you of the most a outrageous thing which has
                    been done to me,—a thing which more than anything else overwhelmed me with
                    dismay in the course of the trial; for you will thus see even more clearly the
                    fellow's baseness, and I, by venting before you my grief for what has happened,
                    shall find, as it were, a sort of relief. The deposition, which I thought was
                    there, and which afforded the strongest evidence in support of my case, I did
                    not find in the box. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="58">
                <p>At the time, dismayed by this misfortune, I could imagine nothing else than that
                    the magistrate had wronged me and tampered with the box. Now, however, from what
                    I have since learned, I find that the defendant Stephanus had filched the
                    document away in the very presence of the arbitrator, when I had got up to put a
                    witness on his oath. And to prove that I am speaking the truth in this,
                    depositions shall first be offered you from those who were present at the time
                    and saw it; for I do not think they will choose to take an oath of disclaimer.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="59">
                <p>But if they are shameless enough to do this the clerk shall read you a challenge
                    by which you will catch them in the very act of perjury, and will know all the
                    same that this man did steal the deposition. And yet, men of Athens, a person
                    who would not shrink from being named as one who had stolen what was prejudicial
                    to another—what do you suppose he would do in his own interest? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="60">
                <p>Read the deposition, and then this challenge.<quote n="Deposition"
                            ><title>Deposition</title>The deponents testify that they are friends
                        and associates of Phormio, and that they were present hefore the arbitrator
                        Teisias when the announcement of the award was made in the suit between
                        Apollodorus and Phormio, and that they know that Stephanus filched away the
                        deposition which Apollodorus charges him, with having stolen.</quote>Either
                    depose, or take the oath of disclaimer.<quote n="Oath of Disclaimer">
                        <title>Oath of Disclaimer</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="61">
                <p>It was plain enough, men of the jury, that they would do this—take the oath of
                    disclaimer with eagerness. Well, then, that they may at once be convicted of
                    perjury, take, please, this deposition and challenge. Read.<quote
                        n="Deposition and Challenge"><title>Deposition and Challenge</title>The
                        deponents testify that they were present when Apollodorus challenged
                        Stephanus to give up his attendant slave to be put to the torture concerning
                        the theft of the document, and Apollodorus was ready to write out the
                        conditions on which the torture was to be administered; and that when
                        Apollodorus tendered this challenge, Stephanus refused to give up the slave,
                        but replied to Apollodorus that he might bring suit, if he chose, if he
                        maintained that he was being in any way wronged by him.</quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="62">
                <p>Who is there, men of the jury, who, on a charge like that, if he were sure of his
                    innocence, would not have accepted the torture? Then, by refusing the torture,
                    he is convicted of the theft. Now do you think that a man would be ashamed of
                    the reputation of having borne false witness, who did not shrink from being
                    proved a thief? Or that he would hesitate to give false witness at the request
                    of another, when, at no man's bidding, he voluntarily committed a fraud? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="63">
                <p>Now, men of the jury, while he might justly be made to pay the penalty for all
                    these things, he deserves even more to be punished in your court for the rest of
                    his conduct. Observe the kind of a life he has lived, and judge. For so long as
                    it was the lot of Aristolochus, the banker, to enjoy prosperity, this fellow
                    fawned upon him as he walked beside him, adapting his pace to his, and this is
                    well known to many of you who are present here. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="64">
                <p>But when Aristolochus was ruined and lost his property, chiefly through having
                    been plundered by this fellow and others of his stamp, Stephanus never stood by
                    the son of Aristolochus, who was overburdened with lawsuits, nor aided him, but
                    it was Apolexis<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Apolexis is a not unfamiliar
                        name (see e.g. <bibl n="Dem. 43.48">Dem. 43.48</bibl>), but of the Apolexis
                        or the Solon here mentioned nothing is known.</note> or Solon or anybody
                    else that helped him rather than he. Then he has courted Phormio and become
                    intimate with him, choosing him out of all the Athenians; and he sailed to
                        Byzantium<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Byzantium, the modern
                        Istanbul.</note> as agent in his interest, when the Byzantines detained
                    Phormio's vessels, and he pleaded his cause against the Calchedonians,<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Calchedon is a town on the east side of the
                        Bosporus, opposite Byzantium.</note> and he has thus flagrantly given false
                    witness against me. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="65">
                <p>A man, then, who is a flatterer of those in prosperity, and who betrays these
                    same men if they fall into adversity; who out of all the host of good and worthy
                    citizens of Athens deals with not a single one on the basis of equality, but
                    willingly fawns upon people like Phormio; who takes no thought whether he is
                    going to injure any of his kinsfolk by these actions, or whether he is going to
                    win an evil reputation in the minds of other men, but thinks only of one thing,
                    how he may enrich himself—ought you not to loathe this man as a common enemy of
                    the whole human race? I certainly think so. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="66">
                <p>This course of action, involving so great disgrace, he has adopted, men of
                    Athens, with a view to evading his duties to the state and to conceal his
                    wealth, that he may make secret profits by means of the bank, and never serve as
                    choregus or trierarch, or perform any other of the public duties which befit his
                    station. And he has accomplished this object. Here is a proof. Although he has
                    so large an estate that he gave his daughter a marriage portion of one hundred
                    minae, he has never been seen by you to perform any public service whatever,
                    even the very slightest. And yet how much more honorable it would have been to
                    be proved a man of public spirit and one zealous in the performance of his
                    duties to the state, than a flatterer and a bearer of false testimony! But the
                    fellow would do anything to get money. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="67">
                <p>Surely, men of Athens, you ought to feel indignation rather toward those who are
                    rascals in wealth than toward those who are such in poverty. In the case of the
                    latter the pressure of their needy state affords them some excuse in the eyes of
                    those who look on the matter with human sympathy, whereas those who, like this
                    fellow, are rascals while possessing abundance, could find no reasonable excuse
                    to offer, but will be shown to act as they do from a spirit of shameful greed
                    and covetousness and insolence, and a resolve to make their own plots stronger
                    than the laws. Not one of these things is to your interest, but rather that the
                    weak, if he suffers wrong, should be able to get redress from the wealthy. And
                    he will be able, if you punish those who are thus manifestly rascals while
                    possessing wealth. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="68">
                <p>Neither should the airs which the fellow puts on as he walks with sullen face
                    along the walls be properly considered as marks of sobriety, but rather as marks
                    of misanthropy. In my opinion a man whom no misfortune has befallen, and who is
                    in no lack of the necessaries of life, but who none the less habitually
                    maintains this demeanor,has reviewed the matter and reached the conclusion in
                    his own mind, that to those who walk in a simple and natural way and wear a
                    cheerful countenance, men draw near unhesitatingly with requests and proposals,
                    whereas they shrink from drawing near in the first place to affected and sullen
                    characters. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="69">
                <p>This demeanor, then, is nothing but a cloak to cover his real character, and he
                    shows therein the rudeness and malignity of his temper. Here is a proof. You
                    have been far better off than you deserved, yet to whom among the whole host of
                    Athenians have you ever made a contribution? To whom have you ever lent aid, or
                    to whom done a kindness? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="70">
                <p>You could not name a single one; but while lending money at interest and
                    regarding the misfortunes and necessities of others as your own good fortune,
                    you ejected your own uncle Nicias from the house of his fathers, you have taken
                    from your own mother-in-law the resources upon which she lived, and you have, in
                    so far as it depended upon you, rendered homeless the son of Archedemus. No one
                    ever exacted payment from a defaulter as rigorously as you exact interest from
                    your debtors. A man, then, whom you find to be so brutal and so savage on all
                    occasions, are you going to fail to punish him when you have caught him in the
                    very act of wrongdoing? In that case, men of the jury, you will do what is an
                    outrage and in no sense right. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="71">
                <p>It is fitting therefore, men of Athens, that you should wax indignant also
                    against Phormio, for bringing this man forward as a witness, when you see the
                    shamelessness of his character and his ingratitude. For I fancy you all know
                    that if, when the fellow was for sale, a cook or an artisan in any other trade
                    had bought him, he would have learned the trade of his master and been far
                    removed from the prosperity which now is his. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="72">
                <p>But since my father into whose possession he came, was a banker and taught him
                    letters and instructed him in his business and put him in control of large sums
                    of money, he has become wealthy, having found the good luck which brought him
                    into our family the foundation of all his present wealth. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="73">
                <p>It is outrageous, then, O Earth and the gods, and worse than outrageous, that he
                    should suffer those who made him a Greek instead of a barbarian and a man of
                    note instead of a slave, and who brought him to such great prosperity, to live
                    in dire want while he has means and is rich, and that he should have come to
                    such a pitch of shamelessness that he cannot bring himself to share with us the
                    good fortune which we shared with him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="74">
                <p>But for himself he has not scrupled to marry his mistress, and he dwells as
                    husband with her who scattered the sweatmeats over him when he was bought as a
                        slave,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">It was believed to be a good omen to
                        scatter sweetmeats, nuts, etc., over the head of a newly purchased slave.
                        See <bibl n="Aristoph. Pl. 768">Aristoph. Pl. 768</bibl></note> nor to write
                    a clause giving himself a marriage portion of five talents in addition to the
                    large sums of which he became master, inasmuch as they were in the custody of my
                    mother—for why do you suppose he wrote in the will the clause “and all else
                    which she has I give to Archippê”?—while he looks with indifference on my
                    daughters, who are doomed through poverty to grow old in maidenhood with none to
                    dower them. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="75">
                <p>If Phormio had been poor, and it had been our fortune to be wealthy, and if, in
                    the course of nature, anything had happened to me, this fellow's sons would have
                    claimed my daughters in marriage—the sons of the slave would have claimed the
                    daughters of the master! For they are their uncles, since the man married my
                    mother; but seeing that it is we who are poor, he will not help to portion them
                    off, but he talks and talks, and reckons up the amount of property which I
                    possess. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="76">
                <p>For this is the most absurd thing of all. Up to this day he has never seen fit to
                    render an account of the money of which he has defrauded me, but enters a
                    special plea that my action is not even admissible; yet he charges against me
                    what I have received from the estate of my fathers. Other slaves one may see
                    called to strict account by their masters, but here we see the very opposite:
                    the fellow, though a slave, calls his master to account, thinking thereby to
                    show him forth as a vile fellow and a prodigal. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="77">
                <p>For myself, men of Athens, in the matter of my outward appearance, my fast
                    walking, and my loud voice, I judge that I am not one of those favored by
                    nature; for in so far as I annoy others without benefiting myself, I am in many
                    respects at a disadvantage; but since I am moderate in all my personal expenses,
                    it will be seen that I live a much more orderly life than Phormio and others who
                    are like him. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="78">
                <p>Whatever concerns the state, however, and all that concerns you, I perform, as
                    you know, as lavishly as I can; for I am well aware that for you who are
                    citizens by birth it is sufficient to perform public services as the laws
                    require; we on the contrary who are created citizens ought to show that we
                    perform them as a grateful payment of a debt. Cease, then, to fling into my
                    teeth matters for which I should properly win commendation. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="79">
                <p>But, Phormio, whom of the citizens have I hired for prostitution, as you have
                    done? Show me. Whom have I deprived of the citizenship of which I was deemed
                    worthy, and of the right of free speech in the city, as you did in the case of
                    the man whom you dishonored? Whose wife have I debauched, as you have the wives
                    of many?—among them her to whom this god-detested fellow built the monument near
                    that of his mistress at a cost of more than two talents. And he did not see that
                    a structure, being of that sort, would be a monument, not of her tomb, but of
                    the wrong which because of him she had done to her husband. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="80">
                <p>Do you, then, who perform acts like these, and who have given such manifest
                    proofs of your outrageous conduct, dare to scrutinize the manner of life of
                    anyone else? By day you act soberly, but the whole night long you indulge in
                    actions for which death is the penalty. He is a knave, men of Athens, a knave
                    and a villain, and has been such from of old, ever since he left the temple of
                    Castor and Pollux.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">This was one of the places
                        where slaves were sold.</note> Here is the proof. If he had been honest, he
                    would have managed his master's business, and remained poor. But as it is,
                    having got control of so large an amount of money that he could steal from it
                    all that he now possesses without detection, he regards what he holds, not as a
                    debt, but as an inherited patrimony. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="81">
                <p>And yet, by the gods, if I had led you off to prison as a thief caught in the
                    act, piling upon your back—if this had been in any way possible—the wealth which
                    you now possess, and had then demanded of you, if you denied having got this
                    wealth by thievery, to refer me to the source from which you got it, to whom
                    would you have referred me? Your father did not give it to you; you did not find
                    it; you had not got it from some other source when you come into our family; for
                    you were a barbarian when you were purchased. Have you, then, a man who ought to
                    have been publicly put to death for what you have done, after saving your skin,
                    after securing for yourself a city with our money, and after being allowed to
                    beget children as brothers to your own masters—have you entered a special plea
                    that our action for the sums claimed from you is inadmissible? </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="82">
                <p>And, then, did you speak evil of me, and inquire what manner of man my father
                    was? Men of Athens, who would not have been indignant at this? For my part,
                    though it beseem me to have less of pride than any of you, yet I judge that I
                    may at least have more than Phormio, while as for him, though there be no one
                    else than whom he should have less, yet he should have less than I; for,
                    assuming that we are the sort of people your words made us out to be, you,
                    Phormio, were none the less our slave. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="83">
                <p>There is perhaps something else which one of them may say: that Pasicles,
                    although he is my brother, makes no charge against Phormio for these same
                    actions. Well, I will speak about Pasicles, too, men of Athens, though I beg and
                    implore you to pardon me, if I am so carried away by indignation at the outrages
                    I have received from my own slaves as to be unable to restrain myself; I will
                    not keep silent, but will declare what until now I pretended not to hear when
                    others said it;— </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="84">
                <p>I consider Pasicles to be my brother on my mother's side, but whether on my
                    father's side also, I do not know; but I am afraid that the wrongs which Phormio
                    has done us began with Pasicles. For when he joins in pleading the cause of the
                    slave and dishonors his brother, when he fawns upon those, and curries the favor
                    of those, who ought to seek his favor, to what suspicion does this naturally
                    give rise? Away, then, with Pasicles, and let him be called your son instead of
                    your master, and my adversary (since he so chooses) instead of my brother. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="85">
                <p>I bid adieu to this fellow and appeal to those to whom my father left me as my
                    helpers and friends—to you, men of the jury. And I beg and entreat and implore
                    you, do not suffer my daughters and myself through our poverty to become a
                    source of malicious joy to my own slaves and to his flatterers. My father gave
                    you a thousand shields and made himself serviceable to you in many ways, and
                    five times served as trierarch, voluntarily equipping the ships and manning them
                    at his own expense. I remind you of this, not because I consider that you are
                    under obligation to me—for it is I that am under obligation to you,—but in order
                    that I may not suffer unworthy treatment without your knowing it. For that would
                    not be a credit to you any more than to me. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="86">
                <p>I have much to say regarding the indignities which I have suffered, but I see
                    that I have not enough water left in the clock. I will tell you, therefore, how
                    I think you will all best come to know the enormity of the wrongs that have been
                    done me. You must each of you consider what slave he left at home, and then
                    imagine that you have suffered from him the same treatment that I have suffered
                    from Phormio. Do not take into consideration that they are severally Syrus or
                    Manes or what not, while this fellow is Phormio. The thing is the same—they are
                    slaves, and he was a slave; you are masters, and I was master. </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="87">
                <p>Believe, then, that it is fitting now for me to exact the penalty which each one
                    of you would claim; and in the interest of the laws and of the oaths which you
                    have taken as jurors punish the man who has robbed me of a verdict by giving
                    false testimony, and make him an example to others, remembering all that you
                    have heard from me and bearing it in mind, if they attempt to mislead you, and
                    meeting them at every point. If they deny that they have borne witness to all
                    the facts, ask them these questions, “What stands written in the deposition? Why
                    did you not strike it out at the time? What is the counter-plea in the custody
                    of the archons?” </p>
            </div>
            <div type="section" n="88">
                <p>If they declare that they have testified, one person that he lived as ward under
                    a will, another that he served as guardian, and another that he has the will in
                    his possession, demand of them, “What will? What were the provisions contained
                    in it?” For to the deposition to which these men bore witness no one of the
                    others has given corroborative testimony. But if they try whining tactics, you
                    should consider that the one wronged is more deserving of pity than those about
                    to be punished. If you act in this way, you will succor me, and you will
                    restrain these men from their excessive adulation; and to your own satisfaction
                    you will have rendered a righteous verdict.</p>
            </div>

        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
