<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" 
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
         	<title>On Monarchy, Democracy, and Oligrachy</title>
            <author>Plutarch</author>
            <editor role="translator">Harold North Fowler</editor>
         	<sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
         	<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
         	<respStmt>
         		<resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
         		<name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
         		<name>Rashmi Singhal</name>
         		<name>Bridget Almas</name>
         		<name>Angelia Hanhardt</name>
         		<name>Michael Konieczny</name>
         	</respStmt>
         	<funder n="org:NEH">The National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
         </titleStmt>
      	<publicationStmt>
      		<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
      		<pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
      		<authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      		<date type="release">2010-12-13</date>
      	</publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblStruct>
               <monogr>
                  <author>Plutarch</author>
                  <title xml:lang="lat">Moralia</title>
                  <respStmt>
                     <resp>with an English Translation by</resp>
                     <name>Harold North Fowler</name>
                  </respStmt>
                  <imprint>
                     <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
                     <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
                     <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                     <date type="printing">1936</date>
                  </imprint>
                  <biblScope unit="volume">10</biblScope>
               </monogr>
            	<ref target="https://archive.org/details/moraliainfifteen10plutuoft/page/300">The Internet Archive</ref>
            </biblStruct>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
         	<quotation marks="none"/>
            <correction status="high" method="silent">
               <p>optical character recognition</p>
            </correction>
         </editorialDecl>
      	<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
      	<p>The following text is encoded in accordance with EpiDoc standards and with the CTS/CITE Architecture</p>
      	<refsDecl n="CTS">
      		<cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)" n="section" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
      			<p>This pointer pattern extracts sections</p>
      		</cRefPattern>
           <!-- <state unit="section"/>-->
         </refsDecl><!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
				<state unit="stephpage" n="chunk"/>
				</refsDecl>-->
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">English</language>
            <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            <language ident="lat">Latin</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
      	<change who="RS" when="2010-05">tagged and parsed</change>
      	<change who="Karina Cooper" when="2019-07-19">EpiDoc and CTS conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
      	<div type="translation" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0007.tlg119.perseus-eng3">
         <pb xml:id="v.10.p.303"/>
      	<head>ON MONARCHY, DEMOCRACY, AND OLIGARCHY (<foreign xml:lang="lat">DE UNIUS IN REPUBLICA DOMINATIONE, POPULARI STATU, ET PAUCORUM IMPERIO</foreign>)</head>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="intro"> <head>INTRODUCTION</head> <p rend="indent"> This essay is evidently only a fragment, as Wyttenbach long ago pointed out. The opening words indicate that the author delivers it as an address before an audience to which he has spoken on the day before, but nothing further is known about the circumstances. Few scholars now believe that the author is Plutarch, though who the writer was is not known. The substance of the fragment is derived chiefly from the <title rend="italic">Republic</title> of Plato. </p> </div>
         <pb xml:id="v.10.p.305"/>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="1"><p rend="indent">Now as I was myself bringing before this company as a court of judgement the talk that I presented to you yesterday, I thought I heard, while wide awake, not in a dream,<note resp="editor" place="unspecified" anchored="true"> <foreign xml:lang="lat">Cf.</foreign> Homer, <title rend="italic">Od.</title> xix. 547.</note> Political Wisdom saying: <quote rend="blockquote">Golden foundation is wrought for canticles sacred,<note resp="editor" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Pindar, Frag. 194 (206), p. 465 ed. Schroeder.</note> </quote> so the speech, which exhorts and encourages you to enter political life has been laid as a basis. <q>Come, let us now build walls,</q><note resp="editor" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Pindar, <foreign xml:lang="lat">ibid.</foreign> </note> building upon the exhortation the teaching which is due. And it is due to anyone who has received the exhortation and the impulse to engage in public affairs that he next hear and receive precepts of statecraft by the use of which he will, so far as is humanly possible, be of service to the people and at the same time manage his own affairs with safety and rightful honour. But as a step towards that which follows and a consequence of that which has been said, we must consider what is the best form of government. For just as there are numerous modes of life for a man, so the <pb xml:id="v.10.p.307"/> government (<emph>politeia</emph>) is the life of a people, and therefore it is essential for us to take the best form of it; for of all forms the statesman will choose the best or, if he cannot obtain that, then the one of all the rest which is most like it. </p> </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="2"><p rend="indent">Now the word <emph>politeia</emph> (citizenship) is defined also as <q>having a share of the rights in a State,</q> as we say the Megarians voted Alexander the <emph>politeia</emph> (citizenship); and when he made fun of their eagerness, they told him that up to that time they had conferred citizenship upon Heracles only and now upon himself. Then Alexander was astonished and accepted the gift, thinking that its rarity gave it value. But the life of a statesman, a man who is occupied in public affairs, is also called <emph>politeia</emph> (statecraft); as, for example, we commend the <emph>politeia</emph> (statecraft) of Pericles and of Bias, but condemn that of Hyperbolus and Cleon. And some people even call a single brilliant act for the public benefit a <emph>politeia</emph> (politic act), such, for example, as a gift of money, the ending of a war, the introduction of a bill in parliament; and accordingly we say nowadays that so-and-so has performed a <emph>politeia</emph> if he happens to have put through some needed public measure. </p> </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="3"><p rend="indent">Besides all these, <emph>politeia</emph> is defined as an order and constitution of a State, which directs its affairs; and accordingly they say that there are three <emph>politeiae</emph> (forms of government), monarchy, oligarchy, and democracy, a comparison of which is given by Herodotus in his third book.<note resp="editor" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Herodotus, iii. 80-84.</note> They appear to be the most typical forms; for the others, as happens in musical scales when the strings of the primary notes are relaxed or tightened, turn out to be errors <pb xml:id="v.10.p.309"/> and corruptions through deficiency or excess. Of these forms of government, which have achieved the widest and greatest power in their periods of dominion, the Persians received as their lot royalty absolute and irresponsible, the Spartans oligarchy aristocratic and uncontrolled, the Athenians democracy self-governing and undiluted. When these forms are not hit exactly, their perversions and exaggerations are what are called (1) tyranny, (2) the predominance of great families,<note resp="editor" place="unspecified" anchored="true">See Aristotle, <title rend="italic">Politics</title>, iv. 4. 1 on <foreign xml:lang="grc">δυναστεία</foreign>.</note> (3) or mob-rule: that is, (1) when royalty breeds violence and irresponsible action; (2) oligarchy, arrogance and presumptuousness; (3) democracy breeds anarchy, equality, excess, and all of them folly. </p> </div>
         <div type="textpart" subtype="section" n="4"><p rend="indent">So, just as a real musician will make use of every instrument harmoniously, adapting it skilfully and striking each one with regard to its natural tunefulness, and yet, following Plato’s advice,<note resp="editor" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Plato, <title rend="italic">Republic</title>, 399 c, d.</note> will give up guitars, banjoes, psalteries with their many sounds, harps and string triangles and prefer the lyre and the cithara; in the same way the real statesman will manage successfully the oligarchy that Lycurgus established at Sparta, adapting to himself the colleagues who have equal power and honour and quietly forcing them to do his will; he will also get on well in a democracy with its many sounds and strings by loosening the strings in some matters of government and tightening them in others, relaxing at the proper time and then again holding fast mightily, knowing how to resist the masses and to hold his ground against them. But if he were given the choice among governments, <pb xml:id="v.10.p.311"/> like so many tools, he would follow Plato’s advice and choose no other than monarchy, the only one which is able to sustain that top note of virtue, high in the highest sense, and never let it be tuned down under compulsion or expediency. For the other forms of government in a certain sense, although controlled by the statesman, control him, and although carried along by him, carry him along, since he has no firmly established strength to oppose those from whom his strength is derived, but is often compelled to exclaim in the words of Aeschylus<note resp="editor" place="unspecified" anchored="true">Nauck, <title rend="italic" xml:lang="lat">Trag. Graec. Frag.</title> p. 107, no. 359; <title rend="italic">Life of Demetrius</title>, chap. xxxv.</note> which Demetrius the City-stormer employed against Fortune after he had lost his hegemony, <quote rend="blockquote">Thou fanst my flame, methinks thou burnst me up.</quote> </p> </div>
      	</div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>