<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">A True History.</title>
 <author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Emily James Smith</editor>
 <funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
 <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
 <respStmt>
  <persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
 </respStmt>
 </titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5.xml</idno>
<availability>
 <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date type="release">2023-08-01</date>
<publisher>Harvard College Library</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
 <biblStruct>
 <monogr>
<title xml:lang="eng">Selections from Lucian</title>
  <editor role="translator">Emily James Smith</editor>
  <author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
  <imprint>
   <publisher>Harper and Brothers</publisher>
	<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
	<date>1892</date>
  </imprint>
 </monogr>
  <ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/hvd.hw3j0n">The Hathi Trust</ref>
 </biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
 <p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
    <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
     replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts book and section</p>
    </cRefPattern>
    <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\w+)"
     replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
     <p>This pointer pattern extracts book</p>
    </cRefPattern>
   </refsDecl></encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="eng">
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5" xml:lang="eng">
<head>A TRUE HISTORY.</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="book" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5" n="1">
<head>Book 1.</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="1"><p>



Athletes and those who pay attention to bodily training do not bestow
all their care on securing a vigorous
condition or on active exercise. They
give some of it to the question of
seasonable relaxation; in fact, they conceive this
to be a very important part of their training. In
just the same way I believe it to be fitting for
those engaged with literature to relax their minds
after a prolonged reading of the more weighty
authors, and render them more vigorous for subsequent labor. </p>

</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="2"><p>
And this period of relaxation.
would be more profitable for such persons if they
should spend it over works which do not merely
furnish pastime by their wit and charm, but which
exhibit also some clever train of thought. This
is the ideal I propose to myself for the following
pages. For the novelty of the idea and the charm
of the subject will not be their only attraction,
nor yet the persuasive, consistent way in which
I set forth lies of all sorts, but the fact that each
of the events I record is a parody of some of the
poets and historians and philosophers of antiquity, who wrote such wonderful and fabulous histories.



<pb n="v.1.p.146"/>



I would even insert their names if they
were not going to disclose themselves to your
own mind as you read.</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="3">
<p>
Ktesias, the Knidian, son of Ktesiochos, wrote
an account of the countries of the Indians and
their manners and customs, which he never saw
himself or heard of from any one else. And Iambulus, too, wrote an astonishing account of things
in the Atlantic Ocean. It is patent to all that he
drew on his imagination, but he carried out his
design pleasantly enough. Many other writers,
too, have chosen the same subjects and written
on them, assuming to give an account of their
own wanderings and journeys, and the size of
the beasts they saw, and the savagery of the people and their strange ways of life. The founder
of the sect, the teacher of all this tomfoolery, was
Homer's Odysseus, who talked to Alkinous and
his people about the servitude of the winds; and
one-eyed people who eat raw flesh and live barbarously; yes, and of creatures with a plurality
of heads, and of transformations wrought on his
companions by drugs. Any amount of such marvels he described to the Phaeacians, as if they
were greenhorns.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="4">
<p>
Now, when I fell in with all these works, I did
not greatly blame the men for their lying, because
I saw at once that this was the habit of those
even who promise to write philosophy. But the


<pb n="v.1.p.147"/>


one thing that filled me with wonder at them was
that they believed their falsifications undetected.
Accordingly, I too, since my vanity made me
eager to leave something for posterity, was not
going to be the only one without a share in the
story-teller's license, and as I had nothing true to
relate for I have had no experiences worth telling-I turned myself to lying far more consistently than the others. For the one true statement I shall make is this: that everything I say
will be a lie. In this way I think I should even
escape the arraignment of others, since I admit
myself that there is not a true word in what I say.
Well, then, my book deals with things I neither
saw nor lived through myself, nor learned from
others things, moreover, which absolutely do not
exist, nor could possibly. Wherefore my readers
must put no manner of trust in them.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="5">
<p>
I once made a voyage, setting forth from the
Pillars of Hercules into the Western Ocean, with
a following wind. The cause of my journey and
my object in making it were the restless curiosity
of my mind, a yearning for novelties, and a desire
to learn what is the boundary of the ocean, and
what sort of people dwell on the other side. To
this end I stored a ship with a great quantity of
provisions, put plenty of water, too, aboard, secured fifty of my comrades who were of my way
of thinking, laid in, moreover, a good stock of


<pb n="v.1.p.148"/>



weapons, furnished myself with an excellent ship's
master at high wages, and had the vessel—she
was a light-built, fast-sailing craft — put in repair
as though for a long, hard voyage.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="6">
<p>
Well, we sailed for a day and a night with a
favorable wind, still in sight of land and making
no great progress. But as the sun rose on the
next day the wind increased, the sea rose, it grew
dark, and it became impossible even to take in
the sails. Accordingly, we surrendered ourselves
to the wind, and were storm-tossed for seventynine days; but on the eightieth the sun suddenly
shone out, and we perceived an island at no great
distance, high and wooded, with no fierce breakers
thundering about it, for the sea had already greatly subsided. So we brought the ship to land and
disembarked, and for some time we lay on the
ground, as was natural after our long distress.
But when we had got upon our feet we chose out
thirty of our number to stay and guard the ship,
and twenty to go inland with me and reconnoitre
the island.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="7">
<p>
When we had advanced as much as six hundred yards from the sea through the woods we
saw a pillar of wrought brass, bearing an inscription in Greek characters, blurred and rubbed
away, which read: "Herakles and Dionysos came
to this point." And there were two footprints in
the rock close by--one a hundred feet long, the


<pb n="v.1.p.149"/>


other smaller. I have no doubt that one of them,
the smaller, was left by Dionysos, the other by
Herakles. We paid our devotions and went forward. We had not gone far when we came to a
river flowing with wine-more like the wine of
Chios than any other.

The stream was full and
wide, so that in some places it was navigable.

So it came home to us more than ever that we
must believe the legend on the pillar when we
saw these signs of Dionysos's passage that way.

I made up my mind to explore the source of the
river and ascended along the stream; but I
found no spring, only a quantity of great vines
full of grapes, with a drop of translucent wine
trickling from the root of each, and from these
the river took its rise. There were also a quantity of fish to be seen in it, very like wine in color and taste. In fact we got drunk from eating
some of them that we caught, and we actually
found them full of lees when we cut them open.
Later, however, we bethought ourselves of the
other sort of fish that live in water, and by mixing
the two we mitigated the strength of our wine
food.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="9">
<p>We took some jars, and laid in a supply of
water and of wine, too, from the river, and having
encamped near it on the beach for the night, we
set sail at daybreak with a gentle breeze. But
about noonday, when we had lost sight of the
island, a whirlwind suddenly arose, spun the ship


<pb n="v.1.p.150"/>



around, lifted her four hundred miles in the air,
and did not set her back in the sea again; but as
she was hanging aloft in the air a wind struck the
sails, filled the canvas, and bore her on.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="10">
<p>
For
seven days and as many nights we coursed
through the air, and on the eighth we saw a great
earth in the air like an island, bright and round,
and shining with a great light. We made for it,
came to anchor, and went ashore. On examining
the country we found it inhabited and cultivated.
By day we could see nothing from it, but when
night came on many other islands appeared in
the neighborhood, some larger and some smaller,
of the color of fire, and a certain other earth below them with cities on it, and rivers and seas and
forests and mountains. This we judged was our
own.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="11">
<p>
We determined to go still farther into the interior, but we met some of the Hippogyps, as they
call themselves, and they arrested us. These
Hippogyps are men riding on great vultures,
using the birds like horses, for the vultures are
large and for the most part three-headed. You
may understand their size from this: each of their
feathers is longer and thicker than the mast of a
good-sized merchantman. Now it was the business of our Hippogyps to fly about the country,
and, if they found a stranger, bring him to the
king. Accordingly, they took us in charge and


<pb n="v.1.p.151"/>

brought us to him.
When he had looked at us,
he said: "I see, strangers, that you are Greeks.”
For he judged from our appearance and clothing.
Upon our replying that we were, he asked:
"How, then, have you come hither, traversing
such a waste of air?"
We told him our whole story, and then he began in turn and told us about himself: how he,
too, was a man, Endymion by name, and had
once been snatched up from our earth in his
sleep, and, arriving here, had become king of the
country. He said that this earth was what appeared to us below to be the moon. But he bade
us take heart and suspect no danger, for we should
have everything we wanted.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="12">
<p>
"If," said he, "I bring to a successful issue
the war I am now waging against the inhabitants
of the Sun, you will find this the pleasantest place
of residence in the universe."
We asked who the enemy were and what was
the matter in dispute.

"Phaeton," said he, "the king of the Sun-folk
-for the Sun is inhabited as well as the Moonhas been at war with us for a long time already.
It began from this cause: I had collected the
poorest of my subjects and planned to send them
off to colonize the Morning-star, which is a wilderness, uninhabited by any one. Now Phaeton,
in his jealousy, stopped the colonists, meeting


<pb n="v.1.p.152"/>



them half-way on their journey with his Antcavalry. On that occasion we were beaten—
for our numbers were not equal to theirs-and
we retired, but now I want to march out again
and convoy the colonists. So, if it be agreeable
to you, join my expedition. I will furnish you
with a vulture apiece from the royal stables and
the rest of your equipment. We shall set out tomorrow."
"We are at your service," said I.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="13">
<p>

He then invited us to supper, and we spent the night with
him.
[Here follows a detailed account of the extraordinary troops marshalled by Endymion and
Phaeton, and the manner in which the battle was
fought, the Moonites defeated, and the hero taken
prisoner with two of his companions. The victorious Sun-folk built a wall between their country
and the Moon, cutting off the sunlight, so that
Endymion's people were forced to sue for peace,
which was granted on easy terms, the chief stipulations being that the Moon should pay a yearly
tribute of a hundred thousand gallons of dew,
and that the Morning-star should be settled by
colonists from the Sun as well as the Moon, and
any one else who cared to join them.]

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="21">
<p>
Such were the terms of the peace. The wall
was forthwith torn down, and we prisoners-of-war
were surrendered. On our return to the Moon


<pb n="v.1.p.153"/>



our comrades and Endymion himself came out
to meet us, and embraced us with tears; and he
asked me to stay there and join his colony, promising to give me his own child in marriage. However, I by no means listened to him, but begged
him to convey me down into the sea again; and
when he saw it was impossible to move me he
sent us off after feasting us for seven days.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="27">
<p>
Then, after making our adieux to the king and
his people, we embarked and set sail. On me
Endymion also bestowed some gifts, two of their
crystal tunics, five bronze ones, and a suit of beanarmor-all of which I left in the whale. He sent
also a thousand Hippogyps to escort us fifty miles.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="28">
<p>
On our voyage we sailed past a number of
places, and put in at the Morning-star, which we
had just helped to colonize, and disembarked and
took in water. Going aboard again we made off
into the Zodiac on the left, all but touching the
Sun as we sailed past. We did not go ashore,
though many of my mates were eager to, for the
wind did not permit it. However, we saw the
country, which was blooming, rich, well-watered,
and full of all pleasant things. When the Cloud-centaurs, who are mercenaries of Phaeton, saw us,
they flew towards the ship; but, on learning that
we were allies, they withdrew.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="29">
<p>
The Hippogyps,
too, had already left us.


<pb n="v.1.p.154"/>



After sailing all the next night and day we arrived towards evening at what is called Lamptown, having already entered upon our downward
course. This city lies between the tracts of the
Pleiades and the Hyades, a good deal lower than
the Zodiac. Here we disembarked, but we found
no human being, only a multitude of lamps running about and transacting business in the market-place and on the wharves. Some were small,
the lower classes, as it were; but a few were large
and of high rank, and these were brilliant, and
could be seen afar. Each of them had his own
private residence or lantern, and a name, like a
man, and we heard them utter speech. They offered us no injury, but even invited us to be their
guests. Still we were afraid of them, and not one
of us dared either to sit at table or pass the night
with them. They have erected a palace in the
midst of the city, and there the ruler sits all night,
calling on each by name. If any one does not
respond, he is condemned to death as having deserted his post. Death with them is to be extinguished. We were present and saw what happened, and heard the lamps defending themselves
and explaining the reasons for their tardiness.
There I recognized also the lamp from our house,
and, addressing him, asked him how things were
going on at home, and he gave me a full account.
We spent that one night there, and the next




<pb n="v.1.p.155"/>



day we put out to sea again, being already nearer
the clouds. And there we saw Cloudcuckootown (to our amazement), but we did not put in,
as the wind was in the wrong direction. But
Crow, son of Blackbird, was said to be on the
throne, and I bethought me of Aristophanes the
poet, a grave man and truthful, and one whose
writings have been unworthily discredited.
On the third day thereafter we also got plain
sight of the ocean, but no land was anywhere to
be seen save those islands in the air, and they
had already taken on a fiery, dazzling look. On
the fourth day, about noon, the wind fell gently
and subsided, and we sank onto the sea.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="30">
<p>

When
we touched the water it was wonderful to see the
excesses of our joy and delight. We made what
cheer our means would allow, and sprang overboard and swam about, for there happened to be
a calm and the sea was quiet. But a change for
the better seems to be often the beginning of
greater evils, and so it was in our case. For two
days only we sailed with fine weather, and at daybreak, on the third, just before sunrise, we suddenly sighted a great number of sea-monsters
and whales, with one among them bigger than all
the rest, a hundred and seventy miles long. It
came on with its mouth yawning open, making
wide commotion in the sea, scattering foam in all
directions, and showing its great teeth. They


<pb n="v.1.p.156"/>



were all as sharp as pickets and white as ivory.
Well, we said our last farewells, embraced each
other, and waited. The creature was already
alongside, and swallowed us down at a gulp, ship
and all. However, it did not close its teeth in
time to crush us, but the ship slipped in through
the openings.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="31">
<p>
When we were within, all was dark at first,
and we saw nothing; but presently the creature
opened its mouth, and we beheld a great cavern,
so broad in all directions and so high that it
might have held a city of ten thousand souls. In
the midst lay the fragments of small fish and other animals, sails of ships, anchors, human bones,
and merchandise; and down the middle there
was dry land, with hills formed, I suppose, by the
settling of the mud the creature drank down. At
all events, there were woods on it, and plants of
all sorts grew there and vegetables had sprung
up, so that it was in all respects like tilled soil.
The circumference of the land was twenty-seven
miles. We could also see sea-fowl, gulls, and
halcyons building nests in the trees.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="32">
<p>
Well, at first we wept a long time, but by-andby I roused my comrades and we propped the
ship. Then we rubbed dry sticks together and
made a fire, and cooked a meal of anything we
could lay our hands on. There was an abundance
of fish at hand of all sorts, and we still had some



<pb n="v.1.p.157"/>


of the water we had laid in at the Morning-star.
Next morning when we arose, every time the
whale opened its mouth we saw now land, now
mountains, now sky alone, and often islands. By
this we perceived the creature was rushing swiftly
through all parts of the sea.
When we had already grown accustomed to this
manner of life, I took seven of my companions
and made my way into the forest, wishing to explore it thoroughly. I had not gone a thousand
yards before I came upon a temple dedicated to
Poseidon, as the inscription showed, and shortly
after a number of graves with headstones, and
near by a spring of clear water. Moreover, we
heard the barking of a dog, and perceived smoke
rising in the distance, so that we judged there
must be a habitation of some sort.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="33">
<p>Accordingly,
we hastened our steps, and came upon an old
man and a young one working very industriously
in a garden-plot, and watering it with water from
the spring. We halted, overjoyed, and at the
same time filled with fear, and they must have
had the same feeling towards us, for they stood
speechless.
But presently the old man said, "Who are you,
strangers? Are you," said he, "some of the gods
of the sea, or ill-fated mortals like ourselves?
For we are men, and we were reared on dry land;
but now we have become sea-dwellers, and we


<pb n="v.1.p.158"/>



swim about in company with this monster who
encloses us, not rightly knowing what condition
we are in; for reason tells us we are dead, and
yet we believe we are alive."
In answer to this I, too, spoke: "We, too, are
men, father-new-comers, at your service. We
were gulped down, the other day, ship and all.
We are making this expedition for the sake of
knowing what is in the forest, for it seemed large
and thickly wooded. Some god, I think, led us,
so that we might see you, and know that we are
not the only men penned up in this monster.
But come, tell us your story-who you are and
how you came hither."
But he said he would neither give nor seek information until he had offered us such hospitality
as was in his power; so he took possession of us
and led us to his dwelling, which was tolerably
made, with beds built in it and furnished with the
other necessaries. He set before us vegetables
and fruits and fish, and poured out wine for us,
too; and when we had eaten our fill, he inquired
what our adventures had been. I related them
all in order-the storm, our experiences on the
island, our voyage in the air, the war, everything
up to our engulfment by the whale.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="34">
<p>

He was
greatly astonished, and in turn gave us an account
of his own fortunes.
"By birth, friends, I am a Cypriote. Being engaged

<pb n="v.1.p.159"/>

in commerce, I set out from my
native land
with my boy, whom you see, and a number of
slaves as well, and sailed for Italy, carrying a
cargo of all sorts of wares in a large ship, which
you perhaps saw lying in fragments at the whale's
mouth. Well, as far as Sicily we had a favorable
voyage, but there a tempest fell upon us and drove
us three days out to sea, where we fell in with the
whale and were swallowed bodily. We two alone
were saved; all the others perished. We buried
our comrades and built the temple to Poseidon,
and then we fell into our present mode of life, tilling our kitchen-garden, and eating fish and fruits.
The forest, as you see, is extensive, and there are
actually quantities of grapes in it, which make the
sweetest wine. The spring, too, which perhaps
you know, gives very clear and cold water. We
make our bed of leaves; we have no lack of fire;
we capture the birds that fly in; we take alive the
fish that find their way into the monster's gills;
and there, too, we bathe when we wish. There is
a salt lake, also, not far off, more than two miles
in circumference, stocked with fish of all sorts.
There we swim and sail, too, in a small skiff that
I built myself. This is the twenty-seventh year
since we were swallowed.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="35">
<p>

As far as these
things go, our life was perhaps tolerable; but
our neighbors, the people who live near us,
are extremely rough and violent, for they are savages

<pb n="v.1.p.160"/>

who have never had commerce with civilization."
"What!" said I, "are there, then, still other
men in the whale ?"
"Numbers of them," said he, "inhospitable
and barbarous in their manners. The western territory towards the tail is inhabited by the Driedherring folk, an eel-eyed, lobster-faced race, warlike, fierce, and eaters of raw flesh. On the other
side, towards the right, are the Triton-weasels,
who are like men above but like weasels below.
However, they are less unruly than the others.
On the left are the Crabclaws and the Tunnyheads, who have made a friendly alliance between
themselves. The country between is inhabited by
the Crayfish and the Skaitfeet, a warlike race and
very swift in running. The eastern part towards
the mouth consists of waste deserts washed by
the sea. But this region I hold, paying the Skaitfeet a yearly tribute of five hundred oysters.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="36">
<p>

Such is the nature of the country; it is for you to
see to it that we may be able to hold our own
in war with so many tribes and get our living."
"What are their numbers in all ?" said I.
"More than a thousand," he replied.
"And what arms have they?"
"None," said he, "except fish-bones."
"Very well, then," I said; "it would be best to
engage them in battle, for they are unarmed and



<pb n="v.1.p.161"/>

we are armed. If we overcome them we shall
dwell without fear of molestation for the future."
This course was determined on, and we went
back to the ship and made ourselves ready. The
day for paying the tribute was at hand, and we
were going to make a refusal to pay it the ground
of war.
Sure enough, the savages sent messengers to demand the tribute, but our friends answered them scornfully and chased them away.
The Skaitfeet and the Crayfish were the first to
advance, furious with Skintharos-for that was
his name—and making a great noise.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="37">
<p>

But we had
suspected their attack, and awaited them fully
armed, having sent forward an ambuscade of
twenty-five men. The order given to the men in
ambush was that when they perceived the enemy
had passed by they should spring out, and this
is what they did. Springing out, they fell upon
them from the rear; and we ourselves, who were
also twenty-five in number (for Skintharos and his
son fought with us), met them in front and joined
battle, fighting desperately with might and main ;
and finally we put them to flight and chased
them to their caves. The enemy lost one hundred and seventy men; we lost one, and the pilot
was wounded in the back with the rib of a mullet.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="38">
<p>
That day and night we encamped on the battle-field, and raised a trophy by fixing the dried
spine of a dolphin upright. But the next day all



<pb n="v.1.p.162"/>



the others who had learned what was going on
presented themselves. The Dried-herrings were on
the right wing, with Pelamos in command, the Tunnyheads were on the left, and the Crab-claws occupied the centre. The Triton-weasels remained
neutral, not choosing to join either side. We took
the initiative, advanced to meet them, and engaged with a great shout close by the temple of
Poseidon. The hollow chamber echoed our cry
as if it had been a cavern. We routed them, unarmed as they were, and chasing them into the
depths of the forest, made ourselves masters of
the rest of the country.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="39">
<p>

Soon after they sent
messengers, who gathered up their dead and
discussed an alliance; but we decided not to
treat with them. On the contrary, we marched
against them next day, and literally cut them to
pieces, with the exception of the Triton-weasels.
These, when they saw what had happened, rushed
out through the gills and threw themselves into
the sea.
We marched into the country, stripped
already of enemies, and dwelt securely thereafter,
instituting exercises of various sorts and hunting; and we cultivated the vines, and gathered
the fruits from the trees, and were in every respect like well-fed prisoners left at large in a
great prison, from which escape was impossible.
We lived in this fashion for a year and eight
months;
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="40">
<p>
but on the fifth day of the ninth month


<pb n="v.1.p.163"/>


I rose at about the second yawning of the whale
-for he opened his mouth once in every hour,
so that we reckoned our time by it—well, about
the second yawning, as I said, a sudden great
uproar was heard, and what sounded like the
commands of officers and the rhythmic cry of
rowers. Startled, as you may suppose, we crept
up to the very mouth of the monster, and standing inside the teeth, we beheld the most amazing
sight I ever saw-namely, giants a hundred yards
tall, sailing towards one another on huge islands
as if they were triremes. Now I know that what
I am going to recount will seem highly incredible, nevertheless I shall tell it.
The islands were long, but not particularly
high, and each was as much as twelve miles in
circumference. About twenty-eight of the giants
sailed on each, part of them seated in order on
either side, and rowing with great pine-treesbranches, leaves and all—for oars. Aft, as if on
the poop, stood the pilot on a high hill, handling
a bronze rudder five hundred yards long. At the
prow stood as many as forty in armor, fighting.
They were like men in all respects save their
hair, but that was of flaming fire, so that they had
no need of helmets. They had no sails, but the
wind, striking against the trees, which grew in
forests on each, filled them, and drove the island
whithersoever the pilot wished. A boatswain


<pb n="v.1.p.164"/>



stood over the rowers to give them their time, and
the islands moved quickly at his order like so
many great ships.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="41">
<p>

At first we saw only two or three islands, but
afterwards as many as six hundred appeared,
ranged themselves in opposition, and began a
naval battle. Many dashed against each other's
prows, many were run into and sunk, but some
grappled and fought vigorously, and could not
easily be shaken off, for the warriors at the prow
showed the greatest spirit in boarding the other
vessel and killing her men, but no one took a
prisoner alive. Instead of grappling-irons they
threw great polyps, fastened one to another.
These entangled themselves in the trees and so
held the island itself. Their missiles and weapons were oysters large enough to fill a cart and
sponges thirty yards round.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:1" n="42">
<p>
 The commander on
one side was Fleet-foot, on the other Sea-Drinker.
The cause of the battle appeared to be a dispute
about plunder, for Sea-Drinker was said to have
driven off many herds of dolphins belonging to
Fleetfoot, as we could hear from what they shouted to one another, and in the same way we learned
the names of the kings.
Finally, Fleet-foot and his party were victorious, and they sank about a hundred and fifty
of the enemy's islands and captured three more
with their crews, but the others backed water and


<pb n="v.1.p.165"/>


fled. The victors gave chase for a while, but
when evening had fallen they returned to where
the débris floated, took possession of most of the
enemies' belongings and recovered their own;
for not less than eighty of their own islands had
sunk. They also raised a trophy in honor of the
victory on the whale's head, by setting one of the
enemy's islands on a post. That night they encamped round the whale, floating close by, having
fastened their hawsers and anchors to him, for
they had anchors, too-large ones made of glass
and very strong. The next day they sacrificed
on the whale, buried their comrades on him, and
sailed off rejoicing and apparently singing a song
of victory. Such are the details of the island
engagement.
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="book" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5" n="2">
<head>Book II.</head>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="1"><p>

From this time our life in the whale became
insupportable to me; I chafed against our imprisonment, and sought some device that would
make escape possible. My first idea was to dig
through the right side and make our way out, and
we began the excavation. But when we had advanced as much as a thousand yards and accomplished nothing, we gave over digging, and decided to set fire to the forest, for this would kill the


<pb n="v.1.p.166"/>



whale, and if he should die we could easily get
out. Accordingly, we set fire to it, beginning from
the tail, and for seven days and as many nights
he paid no attention to the burning. But on the
eighth and ninth days we saw he felt ill—at least
he opened his mouth more languidly, and when
he did open it, shut it again on the instant. On
the tenth and eleventh days he grew rigid, and
began to smell.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="2">
<p>
On the twelfth we perceived
just in time that, unless we propped his teeth
open when he yawned so that they could not
close again, we were in danger of being shut up
in the corpse and perishing with him. When we
had accordingly propped the mouth open with
great beams we got the ship ready, and put in as
much water as we could and the other provisions.
Skintharos was to be captain.
Next day the whale died. We dragged the ship
up, guided it through the openings between the
teeth, and lowering it by ropes attached to them,
sank gently into the sea. We disembarked on
the whale's back, sacrificed to Poseidon, and encamped there three days beside the trophy, for
there was no wind. On the third day we sailed
away. In the neighborhood we fell in with a
number of bodies from the sea-fight. We pushed
our way through them, and took their measure
with amazement.
For some days we sailed with a temperate wind;


<pb n="v.1.p.167"/>


but then it came on to blow violently from the
north, a great frost prevailed, and the whole sea
froze, not on the surface only, but to a depth of
four hundred fathoms, so that we could disembark
and run on the ice. But as the wind continued
and we were no longer able to endure it, we devised the following plan-Skintharos was the author of it: We dug a great cave in the ice, and
there we dwelt for thirty days, building a fire and
living on fish, which we found by digging. When
at last our food failed we came out, and hauled
the frozen ship out of the ice. Then we spread
the sails and swept along as if we were sailing,
gliding smoothly and gently over the ice. On the
fifth day it grew warm, the ice melted, and everything became water again.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="3">
<p>
After we had sailed
as much as thirty-four miles we touched at a small
uninhabited island, where we took in water-for
ours had already given out-and shot two wild
bulls, and set sail again. These bulls did not
have their horns on their foreheads but beneath
their eyes, as Momos thought they ought to be.
Shortly after we entered a sea, not of water, but
of milk, and we sighted a white island in it covered with vines. This island was an enormous
cheese, very compact, as we learned later by eating of it. It was three miles in circumference.
The vines were full of grapes; but it was milk, not
wine, that we squeezed from them and drank.


<pb n="v.1.p.168"/>



There was a temple in the middle of the island
erected to Galatea the Nereid, as we learned from
the inscription. As long as we stayed there
the earth supplied us with food, both substantial and light, and for drink we had the milk
from the grapes. Tyro, daughter of Salmoneus, was said to be queen of these parts, having been thus honored by Poseidon after her
death.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="4">
<p>
We stayed five days in the island, and set sail
on the sixth with a favorable wind and a smooth
sea. On the eighth day, when we had sailed out
of the milk and into salt, blue water, we perceived
a number of persons running on the sea, like ourselves in every detail of body and stature, except
only their feet, for these were of cork. I suppose
that is why they were called Corkfeet. We were
astonished when we saw they did not sink, but
skimmed over the waves and serenely pursued
their course. They approached us and even greeted us, and told us in Greek that they were hurrying to Cork, their native land. Accordingly, they
accompanied us some distance, running alongside; then they turned from our course and went
off, wishing us a fair voyage. Shortly after we
sighted a number of islands, among them Cork,
whither they were hastening. It was near us on
the left hand, and was a city set on a high round
cork. Farther on, and more to the right, were


<pb n="v.1.p.169"/>


five very large, high islands, with great fires blazing up from them.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="5">
<p>
But off our bow there lay a single island, broad
and low, not less than sixty miles in extent. As
soon as we came near it a wonderful air breathed
about us, sweet and fragrant, such an odor as the
historian Herodotus says comes from Araby the
Blest. It was like the fragrance of roses and
narcissus and hyacinths and lilies and violets,
with myrtle and laurel and grape-blossoms added, such a sweetness it was that fell upon us. As
this fragrance reached our senses and raised in
us hopes of the best of fortune after our long
distresses, we drew little by little nearer to the
island. Then we perceived that it was girt with
harbors where no waves broke, and that great,
clear rivers rolled quietly into the sea. We saw
meadows, too, and woods, and tuneful birds, some
singing on the beach and many more in the
branches. And the land was steeped in a light,
gentle-breathing air. Certain sweet breezes blew
softly through the wood and shook it, and even
the branches as they moved gave forth a pleasant, continuous sound like the strains of flutes
left hanging in the trees. There was a sound,
too, of many mingled voices, not discordant, but
such as you would hear at a banquet when the
flutes are heard and some of the guests speak
out their praise, and some applaud with their


<pb n="v.1.p.170"/>

hands, in accord with the flute or the cither.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="6">
<p>

Enchanted by all this we ran our ship in, anchored her, and went ashore, leaving Skintharos
and two of our comrades aboard.
As we were advancing through the flowery
meadows we came upon the sentinels and coastguards, who bound us with garlands of roses
for these are the heaviest bonds they use-and
led us before the ruler. On the road we learned
from them that this was called the Island of the
Blest, ruled by Rhadamanthos of Krete. When
we were brought into his presence our case was
the fourth in order for decision.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="7">
<p>

The first was
that of Telamonian Ajax, to decide whether or
not it was fitting for him to dwell with the heroes.
The charge against him was that he had slain
himself in frenzy. At last, after much debate,
Rhadamanthos decided thus: for the present he
was to be handed over to Hippokrates of Kos,
the doctor, to drink hellebore, and afterwards,
when he should have regained his senses, he
was to be admitted to the feasts of the heroes.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="8">
<p>
The second was a sentimental case, in which
Theseus and Menelaos disputed which had a
right to Helen. Rhadamanthos decided that she
belonged to Menelaos, because he had undergone
such toils and dangers on account of his marriage with her. And he pointed out that Theseus.



<pb n="v.1.p.171"/>


on the other hand, had other wives, the Amazon
and the daughters of Minos.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="9">
<p>
The third case was a question of precedence
between Alexander, son of Philip, and Hannibal
the Carthaginian. It was decided that the pas
belonged to Alexander, and a chair was set for
him beside Cyros the Elder, of Persia.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="10">
<p>
As the fourth case we were brought forward.
He asked what circumstances had brought us,
still living men, within sacred precincts, and we
told him the whole story in order. He then sent
us aside for some time and considered our case,
discussing it with his colleagues; for many others were on the bench with him, and among them
Aristides the Just, of Athens. He announced his
decision as follows: we were to pay, after death,
the penalty for our curiosity and our voyage; but
for the period fixed by him we might stay in the
island and dwell with the heroes, and then take
ourselves off. He set the day of our departure at
not more than seven months' distance.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="11">
<p>
Thereupon the garlands fell from us of their
own accord, leaving us free, and we were led into
the city, and to the banquet-hall of the blest.
The city itself is all of gold, but the wall around
it is of emerald. There were seven gates, each a
single piece of cinnamon. But the streets of the
city and the ground within the walls were ivory.
The temples of all the gods were built of beryll


<pb n="v.1.p.172"/>



stone, and the great altars in them, on which hecatombs are offered, are single amethysts. Around
the city flows a river of the sweetest unguents,
fifty yards broad and twenty-five deep, so that
one may swim in it pleasantly. The baths of
this country are great buildings of crystal filled
with the fragrance of burning cinnamon. But, instead of water, there is warm dew in the pools.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="12">
<p>
For garments the people wear delicate purple
spiders' webs. They themselves have no bodies;
they are impalpable and fleshless, and present to
the eye nothing but a shape, a contour. But although they are thus disembodied, they yet have
consistency, move, reason, and utter speech. In
fact, it is just as though their naked souls were
walking about, wearing the likeness of their bodies. At any rate, unless you should lay hold of
one of them, you would not detect that what your
eye rested on was incorporeal. They are like
shadows, except that they are upright and not
dark. No one grows old; each remains at the
age he had when he came. Nor is there any
night with them, or very bright day either, for the
light that pervades the land is like that white radiance of dawn before the sun has risen. Moreover, they know only one time of year, for it is
always spring there, and the south wind is the
only one that blows.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="13">
<p>

The country blooms with
all sorts of flowers and of green things, too, cultivated


<pb n="v.1.p.173"/>


 plants and shady forest-trees. The vines
bear twelve times a year, bringing forth their
fruit every month. But the pears and apples and
other fruits are said to come thirteen times yearly, for in one month, called there the month of
Minos, the trees bear twice. Instead of grain the
ears bear loaves, ready for eating, on their heads
like mushrooms. There are three hundred and
sixty-five springs of water about the city, as many
more of honey, and five hundred of perfumed oil;
but these are smaller. There are seven rivers of
milk and eight of wine.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="14">
<p>

The place of their banquets is outside the city,
in what is called the Elysian Field. It is a very
beautiful meadow surrounded by a dense wood
of all sorts of trees, which shade the guests as
they lie beneath them on beds of blossoms. The
winds wait upon the guests and serve them with
everything but wine. This they need not serve,
for surrounding the place are great trees of the
clearest crystal, and the fruits of these trees are
wine-cups of every sort of workmanship and size.
So that, when any one comes to table, he gathers
one or two of the cups and sets them beside him,
and they are straightway filled with wine. This,
then, is the manner of their drinking, and as for
garlands, they have none, but the nightingales
and other tuneful birds gather flowers from the
neighboring meadows in their beaks, and let them


<pb n="v.1.p.174"/>



fall like snow as they fly over the guests, singing the while. And I will tell you how they are
anointed with perfumes. Thick clouds draw up
perfume from the springs and the river; then
they station themselves above the banquet, and
when the winds gently press them they let fall a
light rain like dew.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="15">
<p>
At the feast they amuse themselves with music
and singing, and their favorites are the songs of
Homer; for he is there in person and feasts with
them, sitting next above Odysseus. The choruses
are composed of youths and maidens, and Eunomos of Lokris, Arion of Lesbos, Anakreon and
Stesichoros conduct them and sing with them.
For Stesichoros, too, I saw there, as Helen had
already made it up with him. When these cease
singing a second chorus comes forward, composed of swans and swallows and nightingales.
As soon as they begin to sing, the whole forest,
set going by the winds, accompanies them on the
flute.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="16">
<p>
But the greatest incentive they have to good
cheer is this: there are two springs near the
feasting-place, one of laughter and the other of
pleasure. Every one drinks from each of these
at the beginning of the merry-making, and the rest
of the time is spent with pleasure and laughter.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="17">
<p>
I wish to tell you, also, what famous persons I
saw there. There were all the demi-gods and the


<pb n="v.1.p.175"/>


heroes who went on the Trojan expedition, with
the exception of Lokrian Ajax; he, they said,
was being punished in the realm of the wicked.
Among the barbarians there were both the Cyruses, Anacharsis the Scythian, Zamolxis the
Thracian, and Numa the Italian. Sparta was
represented by Lykourgos, and Athens by Phokion, Tellos, and all the sages except Periander.
I also saw Sokrates, son of Sophroniskos, gossipping with Nestor and Palamedes. Round him
were Hyakinthos of Lacedaemon, Narkissos of
Thespiae, Hylas, and many other handsome lads,
and it seemed to me that he was fond of Hyakinthos. At all events, he often put him down in
argument. It was rumored that Rhadamanthos
was out of temper with Sokrates, and had often
threatened to banish him from the island if he
continued his nonsense and was not willing to
stop revelling in his irony. Plato only was not
there, and I was told that he was living himself
in the city he had fashioned, under the constitution and laws with which he endowed it in his
writings.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="18">
<p>
Aristippos, however, and Epicuros held the
greatest honors there, because they were charming and agreeable and most convivial. Aesop
the Phrygian was there, too, and held the office
of court-jester. Diogenes of Sinope had so altered his ways as to marry Lais, the courtesan,


<pb n="v.1.p.176"/>



and was given to getting up and dancing when
he was drunk, and playing other drunken tricks.
Not one of the Stoics was there, for they were
said to be still climbing the steep hill of "the
higher life." And I heard this of Chrysippos
himself, that it was not permitted to him to come
to the island until he had completed his fourth
course of hellebore-treatment. They said that
the Academics wished to come, but were still suspending their judgment and considering the matter, for they had not yet an apprehension even
of this, whether there be any such island or no.
I imagine they particularly dreaded the judgment
of Rhadamanthos, for by their principles they
deny any standard for forming judgments. They
asserted that many of their number set out to
follow these who actually arrived, but were so
deliberate that they were left behind, and turned
back when they had come half-way.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="19">
<p>

These, then,
were the most noteworthy people there. The
person most looked up to was Achilles, and next
after him Theseus.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="20">
<p>
Before more than two or three days had passed
I approached Homer, the poet, when we were
both at leisure, and asked him several questions;
among others, what his birthplace was, telling
him that this was a great subject of research
among us to this day. He said he was aware
already that some believe he was born in Chios,


<pb n="v.1.p.177"/>


some in Smyrna, and many in Colophon. He
was, however (he said), a Babylonian, and in his
own country was called not Homer, but Tigranes.
But when later he made his home in Greece as a
hostage he changed his name.
I also asked him about those verses in his
poems rejected by the critics, whether they were
written by him or not, and he declared they were
all his. As you will imagine, this filled me with
contempt for the callous criticism of the commentators Zenodotos and Aristarchos. When he
had satisfied me on these points, I asked what in
the world was his reason for beginning his poem
with the word "wrath." He said that was the
way it came into his head, and he took no pains
about it. I was eager to know this, too: whether
he wrote the Odyssey before the Iliad, as most
critics declare; but he said he did not. As to
that other story about him, that he was blind, I
very soon perceived that it was false, for he saw,
so that there was no need even to put the question. I repeated my action frequently when I saw
him unoccupied, going up to him and interrogating him. He answered me cordially, especially after he had won his lawsuit. An indictment for slander had been brought against him
by Thersites, on the ground of the scoffs against
him in Homer's poems. But Homer won the suit,
having Odysseus as counsel.



<pb n="v.1.p.178"/>



</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="21">
<p>
During this same time Pythagoras of Samos
also put in an appearance after his seventh transformation, his lives in the forms of as many animals, and his completion of the cycles of the soul.
His whole right thigh was of gold. He was
judged worthy to dwell with the others, but there
was doubt whether he ought to be called Pythagoras or Euphorbos. Empedokles also came,
done to a turn, with his whole body roasted. He,
however, was not admitted, though he begged hard.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="22">
<p>
Some time after this their games were held in
honor of the Festival of the Dead. Achilles presided for the fifth time and Theseus for the seventh. A full description would be too lengthy,
but I will narrate the most important events.
Karos, of the line of Hercules, won the wrestling
prize, although he had Odysseus for a competitor.
The boxing-match was a tie between Areion the
Egyptian, who is buried in Corinth, and Epeios,
who contended together. For the all-round contest they offer no prize there, and as for the footrace, I no longer remember who was the winner.
Among the poets Homer was easily the real victor, but nevertheless Hesiod won the prize. The
prize for all alike was a wreath woven of peacock's feathers.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="23">
<p>
Hardly were the games at an end when word
was brought that the criminals who were being
punished in the realm of the wicked had broken


<pb n="v.1.p.179"/>


their chains and overpowered the guard, and were
marching against the island. Phalaris of Agrigentum was in command, the report said, with
Busiris the Egyptian, the Thracian Diomede, and
Skeiron and the Pine-bender, with their followers.
When Rhadamanthos heard these tidings he marshalled the heroes on the beach, the commanders
being Theseus, Achilles, and Telamonian Ajax,
who had by this time recovered his wits. The
forces joined battle and the heroes were victorious, owing chiefly to the exploits of Achilles.
Sokrates, too, distinguished himself in the right
wing much more than at the battle of Delium,
while he was living. For when the enemy
advanced he kept his place with unflinching front.
As a reward for his bravery a prize was bestowed
on him later in the shape of a very large and
beautiful garden in the suburbs, where he assembled his followers and conversed with them, calling the place the Academy of the Dead.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="24">
<p>
The
vanquished were collected, of course, and sent
back again in irons to still greater punishments.
Homer wrote an account of this battle, too, and
presented me with a copy on my departure for
me to carry to men in this land, but I lost it afterwards, with my other belongings. The first line
of the poem was this:


<quote><l>Sing to me now, O Muse, the wars of the
shades of the heroes.</l></quote>


<pb n="v.1.p.180"/>



Their next proceeding was to cook some beans,
according to their custom after a successful war,
and hold a festival of victory with a great banquet. But Pythagoras alone would not partake.
He sat a distance fasting, and filled with loathing at the eating of beans.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="25">
<p>
Six months had already gone by and half of
the seventh when a disaster happened. Kinyras,
Skintharos's son, tall and handsome, had for some
time already been in love with Helen, who, on
her side, made no secret of her lively passion for
the youth. At any rate, they were constantly
making signs to one another at table and pledging each other as they drank their wine, and then
they would rise and wander off alone in the forest. Well, at last Kinyras, urged on by his passion and his helpless condition, conceived the
plan of stealing Helen and running off with her.
She, too, approved the idea of going off to one
of the neighboring islands, either Cork or Cheeseland. They had some time ago taken three of
my most valiant comrades into the conspiracy,
but Kinyras had not mentioned it to his father,
for he knew he would hinder him. They carried
out their preconcerted plan. The night came. I
was not at hand, for I happened to be asleep in
the banquet-hall. The conspirators eluded the
others, captured Helen, and set sail in haste.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="26">
<p>

About midnight Menelaus awoke, and, finding


<pb n="v.1.p.181"/>


his wife gone, he gave the alarm and went with
his brother to the king, Rhadamanthos. At daybreak the watchmen brought word that they could
make out the ship at a great distance. Accordingly Rhadamanthos ordered fifty of the heroes
into a vessel made of a single log of asphodel,
and bade them give chase. They rowed with a
will, and overtook the fugitives towards noon just
as they were entering the sea of milk in the neighborhood of Cheeseland; so near were they to
getting off! They made the ship fast to their
own with a chain of roses and sailed back, Helen
weeping for shame behind her veil. Kinyras
and his followers were first asked by Rhadamanthos whether they had any other accomplices,
and when they said they had not, he bound them,
flogged them with mallows, and sent them off to
the realm of the wicked.
</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="27">
<p>

They decided that we,
too, must be sent out of the island on short notice,
giving us only the following day. Thereupon I
burst into lamentations and wept at the thought
of leaving so many delights and setting forth on
my wanderings again. But the heroes heartened
me by saying that before many years I should
return to them, and they showed me a chair and
a couch made ready against that day near the
noblest. I went to Rhadamanthos and begged
and besought him to read the future for me and
map out my voyage, and he told me I should return

<pb n="v.1.p.182"/>

to my native land after many wanderings
and dangers, but he persisted in refusing to set
the time of my arrival. However, he pointed out
the neighboring islands, of which five were visible, with a sixth in the distance, and told me
these were the islands of the wicked, these nearer
ones, “from which," said he, "you see the great
fires flaming up, and the sixth, yonder, is the
City of Dreams. Beyond this is Kalypso's
island, but you cannot see it from here. When
you have sailed past these you will come to the
great continent which is opposite your own.
There you will have many adventures and pass
among all sorts of tribes, and visit barbarous people, and in time you will come to the other continent."

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="28">
<p>
So much he told me; and, plucking a mallow-root from the earth, he handed it to me, bidding
me call upon this in my greatest perils. He also
laid these injunctions on me in case I should ever
get back to this country: never to stir the fire
with my sword, never to eat beans, and never to
kiss a girl more than eighteen years old. If I
should keep these rules in mind I might confidently hope to return to the island.
After this I made ready for the voyage, and
when the time was come I feasted together with
them. The next morning I went to Homer, the
poet, to ask him to write me a distich for an inscription,

<pb n="v.1.p.183"/>


 and when he had composed it I erected
a pillar of beryll stone above the harbor, and inscribed it as follows:

<quote>
<l>Lucian, beloved of the gods who dwell in bliss everlasting,</l>
<l>Saw these realms, and then returned to the land of his
fathers.</l>
</quote>

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="29">
<p>
This was our last day; on the next we set forth,
escorted by the heroes. At this juncture Odysseus, too, came to me unbeknownst to Penelope,
and gave me a letter to carry to Kalypso in the
island of Ogygia.


[The first land made by Lucian on this voyage
was one of the Islands of the Wicked, where Timon of Athens was gate-keeper. Here he saw
Kinyras and others in torment, but the severest
punishments were reserved for liars and inaccurate historians, among whom he saw Ktesias the
Knidian and Herodotus. Thence he sailed to
the Island of Dreams, and so to Ogygia.]

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="35">
<p>
On the third day thereafter we made the island
of Ogygia and went ashore, but first I opened the
letter and read the contents. It ran as follows:</p>
<p>
ODYSSEUS GREETS KALYPSO.</p>
<p>Know that as soon as I sailed away from your
island on the raft I had built I suffered shipwreck,

<pb n="v.1.p.184"/>

and was only just saved by Leukothea and
brought to the country of the Phaeacians. They
conveyed me to my own land, where I found my
wife's numerous suitors revelling at my expense.
I killed them all, but was afterwards taken off by
Telegonos, my son by Circe. At present I am in
the Island of the Blest, repenting deeply that I
left your hospitality and the immortality you offered me, and as soon as I get a chance I will
make my escape and come to you."</p>
<p>
This was what the letter said, together with a
request that she would show us hospitality.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="36">
<p>

When I had advanced a short distance from
the sea I found a cave such as Homer described,
and the lady herself spinning wool. When she
had taken the letter and read it through she burst
into tears and wept a long time, but after a while
she invited us to dinner and feasted us nobly.
She asked questions about Odysseus and about
Penelope, what she was like to look at, and whether her good sense was so remarkable as Odysseus
used to boast it. We made such answers as we
thought would be agreeable to her. Then we
went off to the ship and bivouacked near by on
the beach.

</p>
</div>
<div type="textpart" subtype="section" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng5:2" n="47">
<p>

These, then, were my adventures on the sea,
during my voyage among the islands, in the air,


<pb n="v.1.p.185"/>


afterwards in the whale and when we had escaped thence, and among the heroes . . . until
I reached the opposite continent. What happened
to me on land I will describe in the following
books.

</p></div>
</div>
</div>






<pb n="v.1.p.189"/>

</body></text></TEI>
