<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">A True Story</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
    <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>
    <publisher>William Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
    <pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
    <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
<date>1913</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">1</biblScope>
</monogr>
    <series>
        <title>Loeb Classical Library</title>
    </series>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianha01luciuoft/page/248/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.b000604153?urlappend=%3Bseq=260">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="eng">English</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<pb n="v.1.p.249"/>
<head>A True Story<note xml:lang="eng">It is unfortunate that we cannot enjoy the full bouquet of
this good wine because so many of the works which Lucian
parodies here are lost. The little that remains of his
originals has been gathered by A. Stengel (De Luciani Veris
Historiis, Berlin 1911, from whom I cite as much as space
permits).</note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="book" n="1">
<head>I</head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

Men interested in athletics and in the care of
their bodies think not only of condition and exercise
but: also of relaxation in season; in fact, they
consider this the principal part of training. In like
manner students, I think, after much reading of
serious works may profitably relax their minds and
put them in better trim for future labour.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
It
would be appropriate recreation for them if they
were to take up the sort of reading that, instead of
affording just pure amusement based on wit and
humour, also boasts a little food for thought that the
Muses would not altogether spurn; and I think
they will consider the present work something
of the kind. They will find it enticing not only
for the novelty of its subject, for the humour of its
plan and because I tell all kinds of lies in a plausible
and specious way, but also because everything in my
story is a more or less comical parody of one or


<pb n="v.1.p.251"/>

another of the poets, historians and philosophers of
old, who have written much that smacks of miracles
and fables. I would cite them by name, were it
not that you yourself will recognise them from
your reading.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
One of them is Ctesias, son of
Ctesiochus, of Cnidos, who wrote a great deal about
India and its characteristics that he had never seen
himself nor heard from anyone else with a reputation
for truthfulness. Iambulus also wrote much that
was strange about the countries in the great sea: he
made up a falsehood that is patent to everybody, but
wrote a story that is not uninteresting for all that.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The writings of Ctesias and Iambulus are lost; also those
of Antonius Diogenes, whose story, On the Wonders beyond
Thule, was according to Photius (Bibb., cod. 166, 111 b) the
fountain-head of Lucian’s tale.</note>
Many others, with the same intent, have written about
imaginary travels and journeys of theirs, telling of
huge beasts, cruel men and strange ways of living.
Their guide and instructor in this sort of charlatanry
is Homer’s Odysseus, who tells Alcinous and his
court about winds in bondage, one-eyed men, carfnibals and savages; also about animals with many
heads, and transformations of his comrades wrought
with drugs. This stuff, and much more like it, is
what our friend humbugged the illiterate Phaeacians
with!

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

Well, on reading all these authors, I did
not find much fault with them for their lying, as I
saw that this was already a common practice even
among men who profess philosophy.<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">A slap at Plato’s Republic (x. 614 A seg.), as the scholiast
says.</note>
I did wonder,
though, that they thought that they could write untruths and not get caught at it. Therefore, as I myself,
thanks to my vanity, was eager to hand something




<pb n="v.1.p.253"/>

down to posterity, that I might not be the only one
excluded from the privileges of poetic licence, and
as I had nothing true to tell, not having had any
adventures of significance, I took to lying. But my
lying is far more honest than theirs, for though I
tell the truth in nothing else, I shall at least be
truthful in saying that I ama liar. I think I can
escape the censure of the world by my own admission that I am not telling a word of truth. Be it
understood, then, that I am writing about things
which I have neither seen nor had to do with nor
learned from others—which, in fact, do not exist at
all and, in the nature of things, cannot exist.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Compare the protestations of Ctesias and of Antonius
Diogenes (Phot. cod. 72, 49-50; 166, 109 b).</note>
Therefore my readers should on no account believe
in them.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>

Once upon a time, setting out from the Pillars
of Hercules and heading for the western ocean with
a fair wind, I went a-voyaging. The motive and
purpose of my journey lay in my intellectual activity
and desire for adventure, and in my wish to find
out what the end of the ocean was, and who the
people were that lived on the other side. On this
account I put aboard a good store of provisions,
stowed water enough, enlisted in the venture fifty of
my acquaintances who were like-minded with myself,
got together also a great quantity of arms, shipped
the best sailing-master to be had at a big inducement, and put my boat—she was a pinnace—in trim
for a long and difficult voyage.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

Well, for a day and
a night we sailed before the wind without making
very much offing, as land was still dimly in sight ; but
at sunrise on the second day the wind freshened, the -



<pb n="v.1.p.255"/>

sea rose, darkness came on, and before we knew it we
could no longer even get our canvas in. Committing
ourselves to the gale and giving up, we drove for
seventy-nine days. On the eightieth day, however,
the sun came out suddenly and at no great distance
we saw a high, wooded island ringed about with
sounding surf, which, however, was not rough, as
already the worst of the storm was abating.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">This paragraph is based on Iambulus (Diod. 2. 55).</note></p>

<p>Putting in and going ashore, we lay on the ground
for some time in consequence of our long misery, but
finally we arose and told off thirty of our number to
stay and guard the ship and twenty to go inland with
me and look over the island.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>

When we had gone
forward through the wood about three furlongs from
the sea, we saw a slab of bronze, inscribed with
Greek letters, faint and obliterated, which said : “To
this point came Hercules and Dionysus.” There
were also two footprints in the rock close by, one of
which was a hundred feet long, the other less—to
my thinking, the smaller one was left by Dionysus,
the other by Hercules.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">Cf. Herod. 4, 82; a footprint of Hercules, two cubits
long.</note>  We did obeisance and
went on, but had not gone far when we came upon a
river of wine, just as like as could be to Chian.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="3">Cf. Ctesias (Phot. cod. 72, 46 a).</note>

The
stream was large and full, so that in places it was
actually navigable. Thus we could not help having
much greater faith in.the inscription on the slab,
seeing the evidence of Dionysus’ visit. I resolved




<pb n="v.1.p.257"/>

to find out where the river took its rise, and
went up along the stream. What I found was
not a source, but a number of large grapevines,
full of clusters; beside the root of each flowed a
spring of clear wine, and the springs gave rise to the
river. There were many fish to be seen in it, very
similar to wine in colour and in taste. In fact, on
catching and eating some of them, we became drunk,
and when we cut into them we found them full
of lees, of course. Later on, we bethought ourselves
to mix with them the other kind of fish, those from
the water, and so temper the strength of our edible
wine.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>

Next, after crossing the river at a place where
it was fordable, we found something wonderful in
grapevines. The part which came out of the ground,
the trunk itself, was stout and well-grown, but the
upper part was in each case a woman, entirely perfect from the waist up. They were like our pictures
of Daphne turning into a tree when Apollo is just
catching her. Out of their finger-tips grew the
branches, and they were full of grapes. Actually,
the hair of their heads was tendrils and leaves and
clusters! When we came up, they welcomed and
greeted us, some of them speaking Lydian, some
Indian, but the most part Greek. They even kissed
us on the lips, and everyone that was kissed at once
became reeling drunk. They did not suffer us, however, to gather any of the fruit, but cried out in pain
when it was plucked. Some of them actually wanted
us to embrace them, and two of my comrades complied, but could not get away again. They were
‘held fast by the part which had touched them, for it


<pb n="v.1.p.259"/>

had grown in and struck root. Already branches
had grown from their fingers, tendrils entwined
them, and they were on the point of bearing fruit
like the others any minute.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

Leaving them in the
lurch, we made off to the boat, and on getting there,
told the men we had left behind about everything,
including the affair of our comrades with the vines.
Then, taking jars, we furnished ourselves not only
with water but with wine from. the river, encamped
for the night on the beach close by, and at daybreak
put to sea with a moderate breeze.</p>
<p>
About noon, when the island was no longer in
sight, a whirlwind suddenly arose, spun the boat
about, raised her into the air about three hundred
furlongs and did not let her down into the sea again ;
but while she was hung up aloft a wind struck her
sails and drove her ahead with bellying canvas.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>

For
seven days and seven nights we sailed the air, and on
the eighth day we saw a great country in it, resembling an island, bright and round and shining with
a great light. Running in there and anchoring, we
went ashore, and on investigating found that the land
was inhabited and cultivated. By day nothing was
in sight from the place, but as night came on we
began to see many other islands hard by, some
larger, some smaller, and they were like fire in
colour. We also saw another country below, with
cities in it and rivers and seas and forests and
mountains, This we inferred to be our own world.</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11">
<p>
We determined to go still further inland, but
we met what they call the Vulture Dragoons,
and were arrested. These are men riding on large


<pb n="v.1.p.261"/>

vultures and using the birds for horses. The
vultures are large and for the most part have
three heads : you can judge of their size from the
fact that the mast of a large merchantman is not
so long or so thick as the smallest of the quills they
have.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Cf. Odyss. 9, 322f.</note>
The Vulture Dragoons are commissioned to
fly about the country and bring before the king any
stranger they may find, so of course they arrested us
and brought us before him.



When he had looked us
over and drawn his conclusions from our clothes, he
said: “Then you are Greeks, are you, strangers?”
and when we assented, “Well, how did you get here,
with so much air to cross?" We told him all, and
he began and told us about himself: that he too was
a human being, Endymion by name, who had once
been ravished from our country in his sleep, and on
coming there had been made king of the land. He
said that his country was the moon that shines down
on us.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">The story of Antonius Diogenes included a description of
a trip to the moon (Phot. 1lla). Compare also Tucian’s
own Icaromenippus.</note>
He urged us to take heart, however, and
suspect no danger, for we should have everything
that we required.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
“And if I succeed,” said he,
“in the war which I am now making on the people
of the sun, you shall lead the happiest of lives with
me.” We asked whothe enemy were, and what the
quarrel was about. “Phaethon,’ said he, “the king
of the inhabitants of the sun—for it is inhabited,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="3">Cf. Lactantius 3, 23, 41: “Seneca says that there have
been Stoics who raised the question of ascribing to the sun
a population of its own."</note>

<pb n="v.1.p.263"/>

you know, as well as the moon—has been at war with
us for a long time now. It began in this way. Once
upon a time I gathered together the poorest people
in my kingdom and undertook to plant a colony on
the Morning Star, which was empty and uninhabited.
Phaethon out of jealousy thwarted the colonisation,
meeting us half-way at the head of his Ant Dragoons.
At that time we were beaten, for we were not a
match for them in strength, and we retreated:
now, however, I desire to make war again and plant.
the colony. If you wish, then, you may take part
with me in the expedition and I will give each of
you one of my royal vultures and a complete outfit.
We shall take the field to-morrow.” “Very well,”
said I, “since you think it best.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>


That night we stopped there as his guests, but
at daybreak we arose and took our posts, for the
scouts signalled that the enemy was near. The
number of our army was a hundred thousand, apart
from the porters, the engineers, the infantry and the
foreign allies ; of this total, eighty thousand were
Vulture Dragoons and twenty thousand Grassplumeriders, The Grassplume is also a very large bird, which
instead-of plumage is all shaggy with grass and has
wings very like lettuce-leaves. Next to these the
Millet-shooters and the Garlic-fighters were posted.
Endymion also had allies who came from the Great
Bear—thirty thousand Flea-archers and fifty thousand
Volplaneurs. The Flea-archers ride on great fleas,


<pb n="v.1.p.265"/>

from which they get their name; the fleas are as
large as twelve elephants. The Volplaneurs are
infantry, to be sure, but they fly in the air without
wings. As to the manner of their flight, they pull
their long tunics up through their girdles, let
the baggy folds fill with wind as if they were sails,
and are carried along like boats. For the most part
they serve as light infantry in battle. It was said, too,
that the stars over Cappadocia would send seventy
thousand Sparrowcorns and five thousand Crane
Dragoons. I did not get a look at them, as they did
not come, so I have not ventured to write about
their characteristics, for the stories about them were
wonderful and incredible.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Compare the reticence of Herodotus (1, 193), Thucydides
(3, 113, 6), and Tacitus (Germ. 46).</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>


These were the forces of Endymion. They all
had the same equipment—helmets of beans (their
beans are large and tough); scale-corselets of
lupines (they sew together the skins of lupines to
make the corselets, and in that country the skin of
the lupine is unbreakable, like horn); shields
and swords of the Greek pattern.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>
When the time
came, they took position thus; on the right wing,
the Vulture Dragoons and the king, with the bravest
about him (we were among them); on the left, the
Grassplumes; in the centre, the allies, in whatever
formation they liked. The infantry came to about
sixty million, and was deployed as follows. Spiders
in that country are numerous and large, all of them
far larger than the Cyclades islands. They were



<pb n="v.1.p.267"/>

commissioned by the king to span the air between
the Moon and the Morning Star with a web, and as
soon as they had finished and had made a plain, he
deployed his infantry on it. Their leaders were
Owlett son of Fairweather, and two others.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>


As to the enemy, on the left were the Ant
Dragoons, with whom was Phaethon. They are very
large beasts with wings, like the ants that we have,
except in size: the largest one was two hundred feet
long.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Herodotus (3, 102) tells of ants bigger than foxes.</note>
They themselves fought, as well as their
riders, and made especially good use of their feelers.
They were said to number about fifty thousand. On
their right were posted the Sky-mosquitoes,
numbering also about fifty thousand, all archers
riding on large mosquitoes. Next to them were the
Sky-dancers, a sort of light infantry, formidable
however, like all the rest, for they slung radishes at
long range, and any man that they hit could not hold
out a moment, but died, and his wound was
malodorous. They were said to anoint their missiles
with mallow poison. Beside them were posted the
Stalk-mushrooms, heavy infantry employed at close
quarters, ten thousand in number. They had the
name Stalk-mushrooms because they used mushrooms
for shields and stalks of asparagus for spears. Near
them stood the Puppycorns, who were sent him by
the inhabitants of the Dog-star, five thousand dogfaced men who fight on the back of winged acorns.

<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">Herodotus (4, 191) tells of dog-headed men and of
headless men with eyes in their breasts.</note>


<pb n="v.1.p.269"/>

It was said that there were tardy allies in Phaethon’s
tase, too—the slingers whom he had summoned from
the Milky Way, and the Cloud-centaurs. The latter
to be sure, arrived just after the battle was over
(if only they had not!); but the slingers did not put
in an appearance at all. On account of this, they
say, Phaethon was furious with them and afterwards
ravaged their country with fire.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>

This, then, was the array with which Phaethon
came on. Joining battle when the flags had been
flown and the donkeys on both sides had brayed (for
they had donkeys for trumpeters), they fought. The -
left wing of the Sunites fled at. once, without even
receiving the charge of the Vulture Horse, and we
pursued, cutting them down. But their right wing got
the better of the left on our side, and the Sky-mosquitoes advanced in pursuit right up to the infantry.
Then, when the infantry came to the rescue, they
broke and fled, especially as they saw that the forces
on their left had been defeated. It was a glorious
victory, in which many were taken alive and many
were slain; so much blood flowed on the clouds that
they were dyed and looked red, as they do in our
country when the sun is setting, and so much also
dripped down on the earth that I wonder whether
something of the sort did not take place in the sky
long ago, when Homer supposed that Zeus had sent
a rain of blood on account of the death of Sarpedon.1
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Il. 16, 459.</note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

When we had returned from.the pursuit we set up
two trophies, one on the spider-webs for the infantry
battle and the other, for the sky battle, on the clouds.



<pb n="v.1.p.271"/>

We were just doing this when the scouts reported
that the Cloud-centaurs, who should have come to
Phaethon’s aid before the battle, were advancing on
us. Before we knew it, they were coming on in
plain sight, a most unparalleled spectacle, being a
combination of winged horses and men. In size the
men were as large as the Colossus of Rhodes from
_ the waist up, and the horses were as large as a great
merchantman. Their number, however, I leave
unrecorded for fear that someone may think it
incredible, it was so great. Their leader was the
Archer from the Zodiac. When they saw that their
friends had been defeated, they sent word to
Phaethon to advance again, and then, on their own
account, in regular formation fell on the disordered
Moonites, who had broken ranks and scattered to
pursue and to plunder. They put them all to flight,
pursued the king himself to the city and killed most
of his birds; they plucked up the trophies and overran the whole plain woven by the spiders, and they
captured me with two of my comrades. By this
time Phaethon too was present, and other trophies
were being set up by their side.
As for us, we were taken off to the sun that day,
our hands tied behind our backs with a section of
spider-web.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>

The enemy decided not to lay siege
to the city, but on their way back they built a
wall through the air, so that the rays of the sun
should no longer reach the moon. The wall was
double, made of cloud, so that a genuine eclipse of the
moon took place, and she was completely enshrouded


<pb n="v.1.p.273"/>

in unbroken night. Hard pressed by this, Endymion
sent and begged them to pull down the construction
and not let them lead their lives in darkness. He
promised to pay tribute, to be an ally and not to
make war again, and volunteered to give hostages
for all this. Phaethon and his people held two
assemblies ; on the first day they did not lay aside a
particle of ‘their anger, but on the second day they
softened, and the peace was made on these terms:
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Compare the Athenian-Spartan treaty, Thuc. 5, 18.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>


On the following conditions the Sunites and their
allies make peace with the Moonites and Heir allies,
to wit:
That the Sunites tear down the dividing- wall and
do not invade the moon again, and that they make
over the prisoners of war, each at a set ransom ;
</p>

<p>That the Moonites permit the stars tu be autonomous, and do not make war on the Sunites ;</p>

<p>
That each country aid the other if it be attacked ;</p>

<p>
That in yearly tribute the King of the Moonites
pay the King of the Sunites ten thousand gallons of
dew, and that he give ten thousand of his people as
hostages ;</p>

<p>
That the colony on the Morning Star be planted
in common, and that anyone else who so desires may
take part in it;</p>

<p>
That the treaty be inseribed on a slab of electrum
and set up in mid-air, on the common confines.
Attested under hand and seal.</p>

<p>
(For the Sunites)</p>
<p>Firebrace</p>

<p>
Parcher</p>

<p>
Burns</p>


<p> (For the Moonites)</p>

<p>
Darkling</p>

<p>
Moony</p>

<p>
Allbright



<pb n="v.1.p.275"/>


</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
On those terms peace was made, and then the wall
was torn down at once and we prisoners were restored.
When we reached the moon we were met and tearfully
welcomed by our comrades and by Endymion himself. He wanted me to stay with him and join the
colony, promising to give me his own son in
marriage—there are no women in their country.
But I was not to be persuaded ; I asked him to let
me go down to the sea. When he perceived that he
could not prevail on me, he let us go after
entertaining us for seven days.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>

In the interval, while I was living on the moon,
I observed some strange and wonderful things
that I wish to speak of. In the first place there is
the fact that they are not born of women but of
men: they marry men and do not even know the
word woman at all! Up to the age of twenty-five
each is a wife, and thereafter a husband: They
carry their children in the calf of the leg instead of
the belly. When conception takes place the calf
begins to swell. In course of time they cut it open
and deliver the child dead, and then they bring it
to life by putting it in the wind with its mouth
open. It seems to me that the term “belly of the
leg"
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">i.e, calf of the leg. </note> came to us Greeks from there, since the leg
performs the function of a belly with them. But I
will tell you something else, still more wonderful.
They have a kind of men whom they call the
Arboreals, who are brought into the world as follows:
Exsecting a man’s right genital gland, they plant it
in the ground. From it grows a very large tree of



<pb n="v.1.p.277"/>

flesh, resembling the emblem of Priapus: it has
branches and leaves; and its fruit is acorns a cubit
thick. When these ripen, they harvest them and shell
out the men. Another thing, they have artificial
parts that are sometimes of ivory and sometimes,
with the poor, of wood, and make use of them in
their intercourse.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>

When a man grows old, he does
not die, but is dissolved like smoke and turns into
air. They all eat the same food; they light a fire
and cook frogs on the coals—they have quantities of
frogs, that fly about in the air—and while they are
cooking, they sit about them as if at table, snuff up
the rising smoke and gorge themselves.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Cf. Herod. 1, 202; 4, 75; Strabo 15, 1, 57.</note> This is
the food they eat, and their drink is air, which is
squeezed into a cup and yields a liquid like dew.
They are not subject to calls of nature, which, in
fact, they have no means of answering. Another
important function, too, is not provided for as one
would expect, but in the hollow of the knee.</p>


<p>
A man is thought beautiful in that country if
he is bald and hairless, and they quite detest long-haired people. It is different on the comets, where
they think long-haired people beautiful—there were
visitors in the moon who told us about them.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">The point of this is that κομήτης, whence our word comet,
means long-haired.</note>
Another point—they have beards that grow a little
above the knee, and they have no toe-nails, but are
all single-toed. Over each man’s rump grows a long
cabbage-leaf, like a tail, which is always green and




<pb n="v.1.p.279"/>

does not break if he falls on his back.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

Their noses
run honey of great pungency, and when they work
or take exercise, they sweat milk all over , their
bodies, of such quality that cheese can actually be
made from it by dripping in a little of the honey.
They make oil from onions, and it is very clear and
sweet-smelling, like myrrh. They have many watervines, the grapes. of which are like hailstones, and to
my thinking, the hail that falls down on.us is due
to the bursting. of the bunches when a wind strikes
and shakes, those vines. They use their bellies for
pockets, putting into them anything they have use
for,as they can open and shut them. These parts
do not seem to have any intestines in them or anything else, except that they are all shaggy and hairy
inside, so that the children enter them when it is
cold.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
The clothing of the rich is malleable glass
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Lucian’s glass clothing (ὑαλίνη) is a punning parody on
wooden clothing (ξυλίνη), i.e. cotton (Herod. 7, 65).</note>
and
that of the poor, spun bronze; for that region is
rich in bronze, which they work like wool by
wetting it with water. I am reluctant to tell you
what sort of eyes they have, for fear that you may
think me lying on account of the incredibility
of the story, but I will tell you, notwithstanding.
The eyes that they have are removable, and whenever they wish they take them out and put them
away until they want to see: then they put them in
and look. Many, on losing their own, borrow other
people’s to see with, and the rich folk keep a quantity



<pb n="v.1.p.281"/>

stored up.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Compare the story of the Graeae.</note>
For ears they have plane-leaves, except
only the acorn-men, who have wocden ones. In
the royal purlieus I saw another marvel.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
A large
looking-glass is fixed above a well, which is not very
deep. If a man goes down into the well, he hears
everything that is said among us on earth, and if he
looks into the looking-glass he sees every city and
every country just as if he were standing over it.
When I tried it I saw my family and my whole
native land, but I cannot go further and say for
certain whether they also saw me. Anyone who
does not believe ‘this is so will find, if ever he gets
there himself, that I am telling the truth.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>

To go back to my story, we embraced the king and
his friends, went aboard, and put off. Endymion even
gave me presents—two of the glass tunics, five of
bronze, and a suit of lupine armour—but I left them
all behind in the whale. He also sent a thousand
Vulture Dragoons with us to escort us for sixty miles.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>

On our way ‘we passed many countries and put
in at the Morning Star, which was just being
colonised. We landed there and procured water.
Going aboard and making for the zodiac, we passed
the sun to port, hugging the shore. We did not
land, though many of my comrades wanted to; for
the wind was unfavourable. But we saw that the
country was green and fertile and well-watered, and
full of untold good things. On seeing us, the Cloudcentaurs, who had entered the service of Phaethon,


<pb n="v.1.p.283"/>

flew up to the ship and then went away again when
they found out that the treaty protected us.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>

The
Vulture Dragoons had already left us.
Sailing the next night and day we reached Lamptown toward evening, already being on our downward way. This city lies in the air midway between
the Pleiades and the Hyades, though much lower
than the Zodiac. On landing, we did not find any
men at all, but a lot of lamps running about and
loitering in the public square and at the harbour.
Some of them were small and poor, so to speak; a
few, being great and powerful, were very splendid
and conspicuous. Each of them has his own house,
or sconce, they have names like men, and we heard -
them talking. They offered us no harm, but invited
us to be their guests. We were afraid, however,
and none of us ventured to eat a mouthful or close
an eye. They have a public building in the centre
of the city, where their magistrate sits all night and
" ealls each of them by name, and whoever does not
answer is sentenced to death for deserting. They
are executed by being put out. We were at court,
saw what went on, and heard the lamps defend
themselves and tell why they came late. There I
recognised our own lamp: I spoke to hm and
enquired how things were at home, and he told
me all about them.</p>

<p>
That night we stopped there, but on the next day
we set sail and continued our voyage. By this time


<pb n="v.1.p.285"/>

we were near the clouds. There we saw the city
of Cloudcuckootown,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The capital of Birdland in Aristophanes’ play, The Birds.</note>
and wondered at it, but did
not visit it, as the wind did not permit. The king,
however, was said to be Crow Dawson. It made me
think of Aristophanes the poet, a wise and truthful man whose writings are distrusted without
reason. On the next day but one, the ocean was
already in plain sight, but no land anywhere except
the countries in the air, and they began to appear
fiery and bright. Toward noon on the fourth day
the wind fell gently and gave out, and we were
set down on the sea.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>
When we touched the water
we were marvellously pleased and happy, made as
merry as.we could in every way, and went over the
side for a swim, for by good luck it was calm and the
sea was smooth.</p>

<p>It would seem, however, that a change for the
better often proves a prelude to greater ills. We
had sailed just two days in fair weather and the third
day was breaking when toward sunrise we suddenly
saw a number of sea-monsters, whales. One among
them, the largest of all, was fully one hundred and
fifty miles long. He came at us with open mouth,
dashing up the sea far in advance, foam-washed,
showing teeth much larger than the emblems of
Dionysus in our country,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">On the size of these, see Lucian’s Syrian Goddess, 28.</note> and all sharp as calthrops
and white as ivory. We said good-bye to one
another, embraced, and waited. He was there in an




<pb n="v.1.p.287"/>

instant, and with a gulp swallowed us down, ship
and all. He just missed crushing us with his teeth,
but the boat slipped through the gaps between
them into the interior.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p>

When we were inside, it
was dark at first, and we could not see anything,
but afterwards, when he opened his mouth, we saw
a great cavity, flat all over and high, and large
enough for the housing of a great city. In it
there were fish, large and small, and many other
creatures all mangled, ships’ rigging and anchors,
human bones, and merchandise. In the middle
there was land with hills on it, which to my thinking
was formed of the mud that he had swallowed.
Indeed, a forest of all kinds of trees had grown on
it, garden stuff had come up, and_ everything
appeared to be under cultivation. The coast of the
island was twenty-seven miles long. Sea-birds were
to be seen nesting on the trees, gulls and kingfishers.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">This story of the whale is no longer considered a parody
on Jonah’s adventure, as there were other versions of the
tale afloat in antiquity.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="32"><p>


At first we shed tears for a long time, and then
I roused my comrades and we provided for the ship
by shoring it up and for ourselves by rubbing sticks
together, lighting a fire and getting dinner as best
we could. We had at hand plenty of fish’ of all
kinds, and we still had the water from the Morning
Star. On rising the next day, whenever the whale
opened his mouth we saw mountains one moment,
nothing but sky the next, and islands frequently,
and we perceived by this that he was rushing swiftly
to all parts of the sea. When at Jength we became



<pb n="v.1.p.289"/>

wonted to our abiding-place, I took seven of my
comrades and went into the forest, wishing to have
a look at everything. I had not yet gone quite five
furlongs when I found a temple of Poseidon, as the
inscription indicated, and not far from it a number
of graves with stones on them. Near by was a
spring of clear water. We also heard the barking of
a dog, smoke appeared in the distance, and we made
out something like a farmhouse, too.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="33"><p>


Advancing eagerly, we came upon an old man
and a boy very busily at work in a garden which
they were irrigating with water from the spring.
Joyful and fearful at the same instant, we stopped
still, and they too, probably feeling the same as
we, stood there without a word. In course of time
the old man said: “Who are you, strangers? Are
you sea-gods, or only unlucky men like us? As for
ourselves, though we are men and were bred on land,
we have become sea-creatures and swim about with
this beast which encompasses us, not even knowing for certain what our condition is—we suppose
that we are dead, but trust that we are alive.”
To this I replied: “We too are men, my good
sir—newcomers, who were swallowed up yesterday,
ship and all: and we set out just now with the
notion of finding out how things were in the forest,
for it appeared to be very large and thick. But
some divinity, it seems, brought us to see you and
to discover that we are not the only people shut up
in this animal. Do tell us your adventures—who
you are and how you got in here.” But he said he
would neither tell us nor question us before giving.
us what entertainment he could command, and he


<pb n="v.1.p.291"/>

took us with him to the house. It was a commodious structure, had bunks built in it and was fully
furnished in other ways. He set before us vegetables,
fruit and fish and poured us out wine as well.
When we had had enough, he asked us what had
happened to us.” I told him about everything from
first to last—the storm, the island, the cruise in the
air, the war and all the rest of it up to our descent
into the whale.

</p>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="34">
<p>

He expressed huge wonder, and then told us his
own story, saying: “By birth, strangers, I am a
Cypriote. Setting out from my native land on a
trading venture with my boy whom you see and with
many servants besides, I began a voyage to Italy,
bringing various wares on a great ship, which you
no doubt saw wrecked in the mouth of the whale.
As far as Sicily we had a fortunate voyage, but
there we were caught by a violent wind and driven
out into the ocean for three days, where we fell in
with the whale, were swallowed up crew and all,
and only we two survived, the others being killed.
We buried our comrades, built a temple to Poseidon
and live this sort of life, raising vegetables and
eating fish and nuts. As you see, the forest is
extensive; and besides, it contains many grape-vines,
which yield the sweetest of wine. No doubt you
noticed the spring of beautiful cold water, too. g We
make our bed of leaves, burn all the wood we want,
snare the birds that fly in, and catch fresh fish by
going into the gills of the animal. We also bathe
there when we care to. Another thing, there is a


<pb n="v.1.p.293"/>

Jake not far off, twenty furlongs in circumference,
with all kinds of fish in it, where we swim and sail
in a little skiff that I made. It is now twenty-seven
years since we were swallowed.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="35"><p>

Everything else is
perhaps endurable, but our neighbours and fellowcountrymen are extremely quarrelsome and unpleas-_
ant, being unsociable and savage.” ‘ What!” said I,
“are there other people in the whale, too?” “Why,
yes, lots of them,” said he; “they are unfriendly
and are oddly’ built. In the western part of the
forest, the tail part, live the Broilers, an eel-eyed,
lobster-faced people that are warlike and bold, and
carnivorous. On one side, by the starboard wall,
live the Mergoats,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">According to Herodotus (2, 46), uévdns was Egyptian for
goat ; but there is nothing goatish in the Tritonomendetes as
Lucian describes them.</note>
like men above and catfish below :
they are not so wicked as the others. To port
there are the Crabclaws and the Codheads, who are
friends and allies with each other. The interior
is inhabited by Clan Crawfish and the Solefeet, good
fighters and swift runners. The eastern part, that
near the mouth, is mostly uninhabited, as it is
subject to inundations of the sea. I live in it,
however, paying the Solefeet a tribute of five
hundred oysters a year.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="36"><p>
Such being the nature
of the country, it is for you to see how we can fight
with all these tribes and how we are to get a living.”
“How many are there of them in all?” said I.
"More than a thousand,” said he. “What sort of
weapons have they?” “Nothing but fishbones,”



<pb n="v.1.p.295"/>

he said. “Then our best plan,” said I, “would be
to meet them in battle, as they are unarmed and
we have arms. If we defeat them, we shall live
here in peace the rest of our days.”</p>

<p>
This was resolved on, and we went to the boat and
made ready. The cause of war was to be the withholding of the tribute, since the date for it had
already arrived. They sent and demanded the tax,
and he gave the messengers a contemptuous answer
and drove them off. First the Solefeet and Clan
Crawfish, incensed at Scintharus—for that was his
name—came on with a great uproar.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="37"><p>

Anticipating their attack, we were waiting under arms,
having previously posted in our front a squad
of twenty-five men in ambush, who had been
dirécted to fall on the enemy when they saw that
they had gone by, and this they did. Falling on
them in the rear, they cut them down, while we
ourselves, twenty-five in number (for Scintharus and
his son were in our ranks), met them face to face
and, engaging them, ran our hazard with strength
and spirit. Finally we routed them and pursued
them clear to their dens. The slain on the side of
the enemy were one hundred and seventy ; on our
side, one—the sailing-master, who was run through
the midriff with a mullet-rib.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="38"><p>
That day and night
we bivouacked on the field and made a trophy
by setting up the dry spine of a dolphin. On the
following day the others, who had heard of it,
appeared, with the Broilers, led by Tom Cod, on the
right wing, the Codheads on the left, and the


<pb n="v.1.p.297"/>

Crabclaws in the centre. The Mergoats did not
take the field, choosing not to ally themselves with
either party. Going out to meet them, we engaged
them by the temple of Poseidon with great shouting,
and the hollow re-echoed like a cave. Routing them,
as they were light-armed, and pursuing them into the
forest, we were thenceforth masters of the land.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="39"><p>


Not long afterwards they sent heralds and were
for recovering their dead and conferring about
an alliance, but we did not think it best to make
terms with them. Indeed, on the following day we
marched against them and utterly exterminated
them, all but the Mergoats, and they, when they
saw what was doing, ran off through the gills and
threw themselves into the sea. Occupying the
country, which was now clear of the enemy, we
dwelt there in peace from that time on, constantly
engaging in sports, hunting, tending vines and
gathering the fruit of the trees. In short, we
resembled men leading a life of luxury and roaming
at large m a great prison that they cannot break
out of.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="40"><p>


For a year and eight months we lived in this way,
but on the fifth day of the ninth month, about the
second mouth-opening—for the whale did it once an
hour, so that we told time by the openings—about the
second opening, as I said, much shouting and commotion suddenly made itself heard, and what seemed
to be commands and oar-beats.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Compare the description of the sea-fight between Corinth
and Corcyra in Thucydides 1. 48.</note>
Excitedly we crept
up to the very mouth of the animal, and standing



<pb n="v.1.p.299"/>

inside the teeth we saw the most unparallelled of all
the sights that ever I saw—huge men, fully half
a furlong in stature, sailing on huge islands as
on galleys. Though I know that what I am going
to recount savours of the incredible, I shall say
it nevertheless. There were islands, long but not
very high, and fully a hundred. furlongs in circumference, on each of which about a hundred and
twenty of those men were cruising, some of whom,
sitting along each side of the island one behind the
other, were rowing with huge cypress trees for oars—
branches, leaves and all!
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Herodotus (2, 156) speaks of a floating island in Egypt.</note>
Aft at the stern, as I
suppose you would call it, stood the master on a high
hill, holding a bronze tiller five furlongs in length.
At the bow, about forty of them under arms were
fighting ; they were like men in all but their hair,
which was fire and blazed up, so that they had no
need of plumes.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">Cf. Il. 5,4; ‘ And tireless flames did burn on crest and
shield.”</note>  In lieu of sails, the wind struck the
forest, which was dense on each of the islands, filled
this and carried the island wherever the helmsman
would. There were boatswains in command, to keep
the oarsmen in time, and the islands moved swiftly
under the rowing, like war-galleys.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="41"><p>

At first we only saw two or three, but later on
about six hundred made their appearance. Taking
sides, they went to war and had a sea-fight. Many
collided with one another bows on, and miany



<pb n="v.1.p.301"/>

were rammed amidships and sunk. Some, grappling one another, put up a stout fight and were
slow to cast off, for those stationed at the bows
showed all zeal in boarding and slaying: no
quarter was given. Instead of iron grapnels they
threw aboard one another great devilfish with lines
belayed to them, and these gripped the woods and
held the island fast. They struck and wounded one
another with oysters that would fill a wagon and
with hundred-foot sponges.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="42"><p>

The leader of one
side was Aeolocentaur, of the other, Brinedrinker.
Their battle evidently came about on account of an
act of piracy: Brinedrinker was said to have driven
off many herds of dolphins belonging to Aeolocentaur.
We knew this because we could hear them abusing
one another and calling out the names of their kings.
Finally the side of Aeolocentaur won; they sank
about a hundred and fifty of the enemy’s islands;
and took three more, crews and all; the rest backed
water and fled. After pursuing them some distance,
they turned back to the wrecks at evening, making
prizes of most of them and picking up what belonged to
themselves; for on their own side not less than eighty
islands had gone down. They also made a trophy of
the isle-fight by setting up one of the enemy’s
islands on the head of the whale. That night they
slept on shipboard around the animal, making their:
shore lines fast to him and riding at anchor just off
him ; for they had anchors, large and strong, made
of glass.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Very likely a punning reference to some traveller’s
account of wooden (ξυλίναις) anchors.</note>
On the following day they performed



<pb n="v.1.p.303"/>

sacrifice on the whale, buried their. friends on
him, and sailed off rejoicing and apparently singing
hymns of victory. So much for the events of the
isle-fight.
</p></div>
</div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2:42" subtype="book" n="2">
<head>BOOK II</head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1">
<p>
From that time on, as I could no longer endure
the life in the whale and was discontented with the
delay, I sought a way of escape. First we determined to dig through the right side and make off,
and we made a beginning and tried to cut through.
-But when we had advanced some five furlongs without getting anywhere, we left off digging and decided to set the forest afire, thinking that in this way
the whale could be killed, and in that case our escape
would be easy. So we began at the tail end and set it
afire. For seven days and seven nights he was unaffected by the burning, but on the eighth and ninth
we gathered that he was in a bad way. For instance,
he yawned less frequently, and whenever he did
yawn he closed his mouth quickly. On the tenth
and eleventh day mortification at last set in and
he was noisome. On the twelfth we perceived just .
in time that if someone did not shore his jaws open
when he yawned, so that he could not close them
again, we stood a chance of being shut up in the
dead whale and dying there ourselves. At the last
moment, then, we propped the mouth open with
great beams and made our boat ready, putting aboard


<pb n="v.1.p.305"/>

all the water we could and the other provisions.
Our sailing-master was to be Scintharus.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

On the next day the whale was dead at last.
We dragged the boat up, took her through the gaps,
made her fast to the teeth and lowered her slowly
into the sea. Climbing on the back and sacrificing
to Poseidon there by the trophy, we camped for
three days, as it was calm. On the fourth day we
sailed off, and in so doing met and grounded on many
of the dead from the sea-fight, and measured their
bodies with amazement. For some days we sailed with
a moderate breeze, and then a strong norther blew up
and brought on great cold. The entire sea was frozen
by it, not just on the surface but to a depth of fully
six fathoms, so that we could leave the boat and run
on the ice. The wind held and we could not stand
it, so we devised an odd remedy—the proposer of the
idea was Scintharus. We dug a very large cave in
the water and stopped in it for thirty days, keeping
a fire burning and eating the fish that we found in
digging. When our provisions at last failed, we came
out, hauled up the boat, which had frozen in, spread
our canvas and slid, gliding on the ice smoothly and
easily, just as if we were sailing. On the fifth day
it was warm again, the ice broke up and everything
turned to water once more.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
After sailing about three hundred furlongs we


<pb n="v.1.p.307"/>

ran in at a small desert island, where we got water—
which had failed by this time—and shot two wild
bulls, and then sailed away. These bulls did not
have their horns on their head but under their eyes,
as Momus wanted.<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Momus suggested this in order that the animal might see
what he was doing with his horns.</note> Not long afterwards we entered
a sea of milk, not of water, and in it a white island,
full of grapevines, came in sight. The island was
a great solid cheese, as we afterwards learned by
tasting it. Itwastwenty-five furlongsin circumference.
The vines were full of grapes, but the liquid which
we squeezed from them and drank was milk instead
of wine. A temple had been constructed in the
middle of the island in honour of Galatea the .
Nereid, as its inscription indicated. All the time
that we stopped in the island the earth was our
bread and meat and the milk from the grapes our
drink. Theruler of that region was said to be Tyro,
daughter of Salmoneus, who after departure from
home received this guerdon from Poseidon.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">As gala is milk and tyros cheese, the goddess and the
queen of the island are fitly chosen.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
After stopping five days on the island we started
out on the sixth, with a bit of breeze propelling
us over a rippling sea. On the eighth day, by which
time we were no longer sailing through the milk
but in briny blue water, we came in sight of many men
running .over the sea, like us in every way, both in
shape and in size, except only their feet, which were
of cork: that is why they were called Corkfeet, if I




<pb n="v.1.p.309"/>

am not mistaken. We were amazed to see that they
did not go under, but stayed on the top of the waves
and went about fearlessly. Some of them came up
and greeted: us in the Greek language; they said
that they were on their way to Cork, their native
city. For some distance they travelled with us,
running alongside, and then they turned off and
went their way, wishing us luck on our voyage.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
In a little while many islands came in sight.
Near us, to port, was Cork, where the men were
going, a city built on a great round cork. Ata
distance and more to starboard were five islands,
very large and high, from which much fire was
blazing up. Dead ahead was one that was. flat
and low-lying, not less than five hundred furlongs
off. When at length we were near it, a wonderful
breeze blew about us, sweet and fragrant, like the
one that, on the word of the historian Herodotus,<note xml:lang="eng">3, 113.</note>
breathes perfume from Araby the blest. The sweetness that met us was as if it came from roses and
narcissi and hyacinths and lilies and violets, from
myrrh and laurel and vines in bloom. Delighted with
the fragrance and cherishing high hopes after our long
toils, we gradually drew near to the island at last.
Then we saw many harbours all about it, large and
unfretted by beating waves; transparent rivers emptying softly into the sea; meads, too, and woods and
songbirds, some of them singing on the shore and
many in the branches. A rare, pure atmosphere
enfolded the place, and sweet breezes with their



<pb n="v.1.p.311"/>

blowing stirred the woods gently, so that from the
moving branches came a whisper of delightful,
unbroken music, like the fluting of Pandean pipes in
desert places. Moreover, a confused sound could be
heard incessantly, which was not noisy but resembled
that made at a drinking-party, when some are
playing, others singing and others beating time to
the flute or the lyre.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>

Enchanted with all this,
we put in, anchored our boat and landed, leaving
Scintharus and two of my comrades on board.
Advancing through a flowery mead, we came upon
the guards and sentinels, who bound us with rosy
wreaths—the strongest fetter that they have—and
led us inland to their ruler. They told us on the
way that the island was the one that is called the
“Isle of the Blest, and that the ruler was the Cretan
Rhadamanthus. On being brought before him, we
were given fourth place among the people awaiting
trial.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>

The first case was that of Ajax,son of Telamon,
to decide whether he should be allowed to associate
with the heroes or not: he was accused of having
gone mad and killed himself. At last, when much
had been said, Rhadamanthus gave judgment that
for the present he should be given in charge of Hippocrates, the Coan physician, to take the hellebore
treatment,<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">A remedy for madness; Hor. Sat. 2. 3. 82.</note> and that later on, when he had recovered
his wits, he should have a place at the table of
the heroes.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>The second case was a love-affair—Theseus and Menelaus at law over Helen, to
determine which of the two she should live with.
Rhadamanthus pronounced that she should live with
Menelaus, because he had undergone so much toil,
and danger on account of his marriage: then too,



<pb n="v.1.p.313"/>

Theseus had other wives, the. Amazon<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Hippolyta.</note>
and the
daughters of Minos.<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">Ariadne and Phaedra.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

The third judgment was given
in a matter of precedence between Alexander,
son of Philip, and Hannibal of Carthage, and the
decision was that Alexander outranked Hannibal,
so his chair was placed next the elder Cyrus of
Persia.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="3">Cf. Dialogues of the Dead, 25.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>

We were brought up fourth; and he asked
us how it was that we trod on holy ground while still
alive, and we told him the whole story. Then he
had us removed, pondered for a long time, and
consulted with his associates about us, Among
many other associates he had Aristides the Just, of
Athens. When he had come to a conclusion,
sentence was given that for being inquisitive and
not staying at home we should be tried after death,
but that for the present we might stop a definite
time in the island and share the life of the heroes,
and then we must be off. They set the length of our
stay at not more than seven months.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>

Thereupon our garlands fell away of themselves,
and we were set free and taken into the city
and to the table of the blessed. The city itself is
all of gold and the wall around it of emerald.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="4">Lucian’s city is not necessarily a paredy on the New
Jerusalem, though the scholiast so understood it.</note> It
has seven gates, all of single planks of cinnamon.
The foundations of the city and the ground within
its walls are ivory. There are temples of all the
gods, built of beryl, and in them great monolithic
altars of amethyst, on which they make their great






<pb n="v.1.p.315"/>

burnt-offerings. Around the city runs a river of
the finest myrrh, a hundred royal cubits wide and
five deep, so that one can swim in it comfortably.
For baths they have large houses of glass, warmed
by burning cinnamon ; instead of water there is hot
dew in the tubs.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>

For clothing they use delicate
purple spider-webs. As for themselves, they have
no bodies, but are intangible and fleshless, with only
shape and figure. Incorporeal as they are, they
nevertheless live and move and think and talk. In
a word, it would appear that their naked souls go
about in the semblance of their bodies. Really, if
one did not touch them, he could not tell that what
he saw was not a body, for they are like upright
shadows, only not black. Nobody grows old, but
stays the same age as on coming there. Again, it is
neither night among them nor yet very bright day,
but the light which is on the country is. like the
gray morning toward dawn, when the sun has not
yet risen. Moreover, they are acquainted with only
one season of the year, for it is always spring there
and the only wind that blows there is Zephyr.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>

The country abounds in flowers and plants of all
kinds, -cultivated and otherwise.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Lucian makes a villainous pun here, contrasting hemeros (cultivated) with skieros (fond of darkness), as if the former
word meant-‘fond of daylight.’ (hemera)!</note> The grape-vines
yield twelve vintages a year, bearing every month;
the pomegranates, apples and other fruit-trees were
said to bear thirteen times a year, for in one month,
their Minoan, they bear twice. Instead of wheat-ears,
loaves of bread all baked grow on the tops of the



<pb n="v.1.p.317"/>

halms, so that they Jook like mushrooms. In the
neighbourhood of the city there are three handed
and sixty-five springs of water, as many of honey,
five hundred of myrrh—much smaller, however—seven rivers of milk and eight of wine.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
Their table is spread outside. the city in the Elysian
Fields, a very beautiful mead with thick woods of
all sorts round about it, overshadowing the feasters.
The couches they lie on are made of flowers, and they
are attended and served by the winds, who, however,
do not pour out their wine, for they do not need anyone to do this. There are great trees of the clearest
glass around the table, and instead of fruit they bear
cups of all shapes and sizes. When anyone comes to
table he picks one or two of the cups and puts them
at his place. These fill with wine at once, and
that is the way they get their drink. Instead of
garlands, the nightingales and the other song-birds
gather flowers in their bills from the fields hard by
and drop them down like snow, flying overhead and
singing. Furthermore, the way they are scented is
that thick clouds draw up myrrh from the springs
and the river, stand over the table and under the
gentle manipulation of the. winds rain down a
delicate dew.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>

At the board they pass their time
with poetry and song. For the most part they
sing the epics of Homer, who is there himself and
shares the revelry, lying at table in the place above
Odysseus. Their choruses are of boys and gnris, fed


<pb n="v.1.p.319"/>

and accompanied by Eunomus of Locris, Arion of
Lesbos, Anacreon and Stesichorus. There can be
no doubt about the latter, for I saw him there—by
that time Helen had forgiven him.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Stesichorus had said harsh words of Helen, and was
blinded by Castor and Pollux for his presumption. He
recanted in a famous Palinode, of which some lines are still
preserved (Plato, Phaedrus, 243), and so recovered his eyesight.</note> When they
stop singing another chorus appears, composed of
swans and swallows and nightingales, and as they
sing the whole wood renders the accompaniment,
with the winds leading.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>

But the greatest thing
that they have for ensuring a good time is that
two springs are by the table, one of laughter and
the other of enjoyment. They all drink from each
of these when the revels begin, and thenceforth enjoy
themselves and laugh all the while.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>

But I desire to mention the famous men whom
I saw there. There were all the demigods and
the veterans of Troy except Locrian Ajax, the only
one, they said, who was being punished in the
place of the wicked. Of the barbarians there were
both Cyruses, the Scythian Anacharsis, the Thracian
Zamolxis and Numa the Italian. In addition, there
were Lycurgus of Sparta, Phocion and Tellus of
Athens and the wise men, all but Periander. I
also saw Socrates, the son of Sophroniscus, chopping
logic with Nestor and Palamedes; about him were
Hyacinthus of Sparta, Narcissus of Thespiae, Hylas
and other handsome lads. It seemed to me that
Hyacinthus was his especial favourite, for at any rate
he refuted himi most. It was said that Rhadamanthus



<pb n="v.1.p.321"/>

was angry at Socrates and had often threatened to
banish him from the island if he kept up his nonsense
and would not quit his irony and be merry. Plato
alone was not there: it was said that he was living in
his imaginary city under the constitution and the laws
that he himself wrote.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

The followers of Aristippus and
Epicurus were in the highest favour among the heroes
because they are pleasant and agreeable and jolly
good fellows, Aesop the Phrygian was also there— —
they have him for a jester. Diogenes the Cynic had so
changed his ways that he not only married Lais the
courtesan, but often got up and danced and indulged
in tomfoolery when he had had too much. None of
the Stoics was there—they were said to be still on
the way up the steep hill of virtue. With regard to
Chrysippus, we heard tell that he is not permitted
to set foot on the island until he submits himself to
the hellebore treatment for the fourth time.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">See the Philosophers for Sale for another jest at Chrysippus’ insanity.</note>
They
said that the Academicians wanted to come but were
still holding off and debating, for they could not
arrive at a conclusion even on the question whether
such an island existed. Then too-I suppose they
feared to have Rhadamanthus judge them, as they
themselves had abolished standards of judgment.
It was said, however, that many of them had started
to follow people coming thither, but fell behind
through their slowness, being constitutionally unable
to arrive at anything, and so turned back half-way.
These were the most conspicuous of those present.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>

They render especial honours to Achilles and after
him to Theseus. About love-making their attitude



<pb n="v.1.p.323"/>

is such that they bill-and-coo openly, in plain sight
of everyone, without any discrimination, and think
no shame of it at all. Socrates, the only exception,
used to protest that he was above suspicion in
his relations with young persons, but everyone held
him guilty of perjury. In fact, Hyacinthus and
Narcissus often said that they knew better, but he
persisted in his denial. They all have their wives in
common and nobody is jealous of his neighbour ; in
this point they out-Plato Plato. Complaisance is the
universal rule.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
Hardly two or three days had passed before I
went up to Homer the poet when we were both at
leisure, and questioned him about everything.
“Above all,” said I, “where do you come from?
This point in particular is being investigated even
yet at home.” “Iam not unaware,” said he, “that
some think me a Chian, some a Smyrniote and many
a Colophonian. As a matter of fact, I am a Babylonian, and among my fellow-countrymen my name
was not Homer but Tigranes. Later on, when I was
a hostage ‘(homeros) among the Greeks, I changed my
name.” I went on to enquire whether the
bracketed lines had been written by him, and he
asserted that they were all his own: consequently I
held the grammarians Zenodotus and Aristarchus
guilty of pedantry in the highest degree. Since
he had answered satisfactorily on these points, I
next asked him why he began with the wrath of
Achilles; and he said that it just came into his
head that way, without any study. Moreover, I
wanted to know whether he wrote the Odyssey
before the Iliad, as most people say: he said no.
<pb n="v.1.p.325"/>

That he was not blind, as they say, I understood at
once—I saw it,and so had no need toask. Often again
at other times I would do this when I saw him at
leisure ; I would go and make enquiries of him and he
would give me a cordial answer to everything, particularly after the lawsuit that he won, for a charge of libel
had been brought against him by Thersites because
of the way he had ridiculed him in the poem, and
the case was won by Homer, with Odysseus for his
lawyer.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>


At about this time arrived Pythagoras of Samos
who had undergone seven transformations, had
lived in seven bodies and had now ended the migrations of his soul. All his right side was of gold.
Judgment was pronounced that he should become a
member of their community, but when I left
the point was still at issue whether he ought to be
called Pythagoras or Euphorbus. Empedocles came
too, all burned and his body completely cooked,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">From his leap into the crater of Aetna,</note> but
he was not received in spite of his many entreaties.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
As time went on their games came round, the
Games of the Dead. The referees were Achilles,
serving for the fifth time, and Theseus for the
seventh. The full details would make a long story,
but I shall tell the principal things that they did.
In wrestling the winner was Caranus, the descendant
of Heracles, who defeated Odysseus for the championship. The boxing was a draw between Areius
the Egyptian, who is buried at Corinth, and Epeius.
For combined boxing and wrestling they offer no



<pb n="v.1.p.327"/>

prizes. In the foot-race I do not remember who
won and in poetry, Homer was really far the best
man, but Hesiod won. The prize in each case was
a crown that was plaited of peacock feathers.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
Hardly had the games been concluded when
word came that those who were under punishment
in the place of the wicked had burst their bonds, had
overpowered their guard, and were advancing on the
island: that théy were under the leadership of
Phalaris of Acragas, Busiris the Egyptian, Diomed of
Thrace, and Sciron and Pityocamptes. When Rhadamanthus heard of this he mustered the heroes on the
shore. They were led by Theseus, Achilles and Ajax,
the son of Telamon, who by this time had recovered
his wits. They engaged and fought, and the heroes
won. Achilles contributed most to their success, but
Socrates, who was stationed on the right wing, was
brave, too—far more so than when’ he fought at -
Delium in his lifetime. When four of the enemy
came at him he did not run away or change countenance. For this they afterwards gave him a special
reward, a beautiful great park in the suburbs,
where he used to gather his comrades and dispute :
he named the place the Academy of the Dead.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>

Arresting the losers and putting them in irons,
they sent them off to be punished still more severely
than before. An account of this battle was written
by Homer, and as I was leaving he gave me the
book to take to the people at home, but later I lost
it along with everything else. The poem began:

<quote><l>This time sing me, O Muse, of the shades of the
heroes in battle !</l></quote>


<pb n="v.1.p.329"/>

But to return—they cooked beans,<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">An allusion to the Pyanepsia, the Athenian Beanfeast.</note>
as is their
custom when they are successful at war, hdd a feast
in honour of the victory and made a great holiday.
Pythagoras was the only one who did not take part
in it; he sat by himself and went dinnerless
because he detested beans.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
Six months had passed and it was about the
middle of the seventh when sedition arose. Cinyras,
the son of Scintharus, a tall and handsome lad, had
long been in love with Helen, and it was no secret
that she herself was madly enamoured of the boy. For
instance, they often winked to one another at table,
drank to each other and got up together and
wandered about the wood. Well, one fine day
through love and despair Cinyras determined to rape
Helen—she agreed to it—and go to one of the
islands in the offing, either Cork or Cheesie. As
accomplices they had long ago taken on three of the
most reckless of my comrades; but Cinyras did not
inform his father, for he knew that he would not let
him do it. When they had come to a decision, they
carried out their stratagem. It was at nightfall, and
I was not on hand, as I chanced to be taking a nap
under the table. Without the knowledge of the
rest they carried Helen off and put to sea in haste.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>

About midnight, when Menelaus woke up, and
found that his wife was not in bed, he made a
great stir and took his brother and went to King
Rhadamanthus. But as day began to break the
lookouts said that they saw the ship far out at sea.
Then Rhadamanthus put fifty of the heroes aboard a



<pb n="v.1.p.331"/>

ship made of a single log of asphodel and ordered
them to give chase. Rowing with a will, they overtook them about noon, just as they were entering
the milky place in the ocean near Cheesie—that is
all they lacked of escaping! Securing the ship with
a hawser of roses, they sailed home. -Helen cried
and hid her head for shame. As to Cinyras and the
rest, first Rhadamanthus asked them if they had any
other accomplices, and they said no; then he. had
them secured by the offending member and sent
them away to the place of the wicked, after they
had been first scourged with mallow.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>

The heroes
voted, too, that we be dismissed from the island
before our time was up, remaining only till the next
day.</p>

<p>
Thereupon I began to cry aloud and weep because
I had to leave such blessings behind me and resume
my wanderings. But they cheered me up, saying
that before many years I should come back to them
again, and they even pointed out to me my future
chair and couch, close to the best people. I went
to Rhadamanthus and earnestly besought him to tell
me what would happen and indicate my course. He
said that I should reach my native land in spite of
many wanderings and dangers, but refused to tell the
time of my return. However, pointing out the islands
near by—there were five in sight and a sixth in the
distance—, “These,” said he, “are the Isles of
the Wicked, here close at hand, from which you see
all the smoke arising: the sixth yonder is the City
of Dreams. Next comes the island of Calypso, but


<pb n="v.1.p.333"/>

you cannot see it yet. When you have sailed by
these, you will finally come to the great continent
opposite the one which your people inhabit. Then
at last, after you have had many adventures and
have travelled through all sorts of countries and lived
among unfriendly men, in course of time you will
reach the other continent.”

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>
With these words he plucked a root of mallow
from the ground and handed it to me, telling me to
pray to it in my greatest straits. And he advised me
if ever I reached this country, neither to stir the fire
with a sword-blade nor to eat lupines nor to make
love to anyone over eighteen,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The first is a real Pythagorean precept, or what passed
for such (Plut. Mor, 128) ; the other two are parodies.</note> saying that if I bore
these points in mind I might have good hopes of
getting back to the island.
</p><p>
Well, I made preparations for the voyage, and
when the time came, joined them at the feast. On
the next day I went to the poet Homer and begged
him to compose me a couplet to carve up, and when
he had done so, I set up a slab of beryl near the
harbour and had the couplet carved-onit. It was:

<l>One Lucian, whom the blessed gods befriend,</l>
<l>Beheld what’s here, and home again did wend.</l>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="29"><p>

I stayed that day, too, and put to sea on the
next, escorted by the heroes. At that juncture
Odysseus came to me without ‘the knowledge of
Penelope and gave me a letter to carry to Ogygia
Island, to Calypso. Rhadamanthus sent the pilot
Nauplius with me, so that if we touched at the



<pb n="v.1.p.335"/>

islands no one might arrest us, thinking we were
putting in on another errand.</p>

<p>Forging ahead, we had passed out of the fragrant
atmosphere when of a sudden a terrible odour
greeted us as of asphalt, sulphur, and pitch burning
together, and a vile, insufferable stench as of roasting
human flesh: the atmosphere was murky and foggy,
and a pitchy dew distilled from it. Likewise we
heard the noise of scourge$ and the wailing of many
men.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="30"><p>

The other islands’ we did not touch at,
but the one on which we landed was precipitous and
sheer on all sides ; it was roughened with rocks and
stony places, and there was neither tree nor water in
it. We crawled up the cliffs, however, and went
ahead in a path full of thorns and calthrops, finding
the country very ugly. On coming to the enclosure
and the place of punishment, first of all we wondered
at the nature of the region. The ground itself was
all sown with sword blades and calthrops, and around
it flowed three rivers, one of mud, the second of blood
and the inmost one of fire. The latter was very
large, and impossible to cross: it ran like water and
undulated like the sea, and it contained many fish,
some similar to torches, and some, a smaller variety,
to live coals. They called them candlefish.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="31"><p>

There was a single narrow way leading in, past all
the rivers, and the warder set there was Timon ot
Athens. We got through, however, and with
Nauplius for our conductor we saw many kings
undergoing punishment, and many commoners too.
Some of them we even recognized, and we saw Cinyras


<pb n="v.1.p.337"/>

triced up as aforesaid in the smoke of a slow fire.,
The guides told the life of each, and the crimes for
which they were being punished ; and the severest
punishment of all fell to those who told lies while
in life and those who had written what was not true,
among whom were Ctesias of Cnidos, Herodotus and
many more. On seeing them, I had good hopes for
the future, for I have never told a lie that I know
of.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="32"><p>

Well, I turned back to the ship quickly, for
I could not endure the sight, said good-bye to
Nauplius, and sailed away.</p>

<p>
After a short time the Isle of Dreams came
in sight close by, faint and uncertain to the eye. It
had itself some likeness to a dream, for as we
approached it receded and retired and retreated
to a greater distance. Overtaking it at length and
sailing into the harbour called Sleep, we landed near
the ivory gates, where the sanctuary of the Cock is,
about dusk, and on entering the city, we saw many
dreams of all sorts. But first I desire to speak of the
city itself, since no one else has written about it, and
Homer, the only one to mention it at all, was not
quite accurate in what he said.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Odyss. 19, 560 ff.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="33"><p>

On all sides of
it is a wood, in which the trees are tall poppies and
mandragoras, and they have a great number of bats
in them; for there is no other winged thing in the
island. A river flows near which they call Sleepwalker, and there are two springs by the gates,



<pb n="v.1.p.339"/>

named Soundly and Eight-hours. The wall of the
city is high and parti-coloured, very like a rainbow
in tint. The gates in it are not two, as Homer says,
but four. Two face Slowcoach Plain, one of which
is of iron and the other of earthenware; through
these, it is said, the fearful, murderous, revolting
dreams go out. The other two face the harbour
and the sea, one of which is of horn and the other,
through which we came in, of ivory. As one enters
the city, on the right is the temple of Night, for
the gods they worship most are Night and the Cock,
whose sanctuary is built near the harbour. On the left
is the palace of Sleep, who rules among them and has
appointed two satraps or lieutenants, Nightmare, son
of Causeless, and Rich, son of Fancy. In the centre
of the square is a spring which they call Drowsimere,
and close to it are two temples, that of Falsehood
and that of Truth. There too is their holy of holies
and their oracle, which Antiphon, the interpreter ot
dreams, presided over as prophet, having had this
office from Sleep.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="34"><p>

As to the dreams themselves,
they differ from one another both in nature and in
looks. Some were tall, handsome and well-proportioned, while others were small and ugly; and
some were rich, I thought, while others were
humble and beggarly. There were winged and
portentous dreams among them, and there were
others dressed up as if for a carnival, being clothed to
represent kings and gods and different characters of
the sort. We actually recognised many of them,
whom we had seen long ago at home. These came


<pb n="v.1.p.341"/>

up to us and greeted us like old acquaintances, took
us with them, put us to sleep and entertained us
very splendidly and hospitably. They treated us
like lords in every way, and even promised to make
us kings and nabobs, A few of them actually took
us off home, gave us a sight of our friends and
families and brought us back the same day.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="35"><p>

For
thirty days and thirty nights we stopped with them
and had a fine time—sleeping! Then of a ‘sudden a
great thunder-clap came; we woke up, sprang out of
bed and put to sea as soon as we had laid in
supplies.</p>

<p>On the third day out from there we touched at
the island of Ogygia and landed. But first I opened
the letter and read what was in it. It was:</p>

<p>Odysseus to Calypso, greeting.</p>
<p>“Soon after I built the raft and sailed away from
you I was shipwrecked, and with the help of Leucothea
managed to reach the land of the Phaeacians in
safety. They sent me home, and there I found that
my wife had a number of suitors who were living on
the fat of the land at our house. I killed them all,
and was afterwards slain by Telegonus, my son by
Circe. Now I am on the Isle of the Blest, thoroughly
sorry to have given up my life with you and the
immortality which you offered me. Therefore, if I
get a chance, I shall run away and come to you.”
In addition to this, the letter said. that she was to
entertain us.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="36"><p>

On going a short way from the
sea I found the cave, which was as Homer described
it,
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Odyss. 5, 55 ff.</note>
and found Calypso herself working wool. When



<pb n="v.1.p.343"/>

she had taken the letter and read it, she wept a long
time at first, and then she asked us in to enjoy her hospitality, gave us a splendid feast and enquired about
Odysseus and Penelope—how she looked and
whether she was prudent, as Odysseus used to boast
in old times.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Odyss. 5, 201 ff.</note> We made her such answers as we
thought would please her.</p>
<p>
After that, we went back to the ship and slept
beside it on the shore.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="37"><p>
Early in the morning
we put to sea in a rising wind. We were stormtossed for two days, and on the third we fell in with
the Pumpkin-pirates. They are savages from the
neighbouring islands who prey on passing sailors.
They have large boats.of pumpkin, sixty cubits long ;
for after drying a pumpkin they hollow it out, take
out the insides and go sailing in it, using reeds for
masts and a pumpkin-leaf for a sail. They attacked
us with two crews and gave us battle, wounding
many of us by hitting us with pumpkin-seeds instead
of stones. After fighting for a long time on even
terms, about noon we-saw the Nut-sailors coming up
astern of the Pumpkin-pirates. They were enemies
to one another, as they showed by their actions ; for
when the Pumpkin-pirates noticed them coming up,
they neglected us and faced about and fought with
them. But in the meantime we hoisted our canvas
and fled, leaving them fighting.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="38"><p>
It was evident that
the Nut-sailors would win, as they were in greater



<pb n="v.1.p.345"/>

numbers—they had five crews—and fought from
stouter ships. Their boats were the halves of empty
nutshells, each of which measured fifteen fathoms in
length.
When we had lost them from sight, we attended
to the wounded, and thereafter we kept under arms
most of the time, always looking for attacks. And we
did not look in vain.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="39"><p>

In fact, the sun had not yet
gone down when from a desert island there came out
against us about twenty men riding on huge dolphins,
who were pirates like the others. The dolphins
carried them securely and plunged and neighed like
horses. When they were close by, they separated
and threw at us from both sides with dry cuttle-fish
and crabs’ eyes. But when we let fly at them with
spears and arrows, they could not hold their ground,
but fled to the island, most of them wounded.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="40"><p>
About midnight, while it was calm, we unexpectedly ran aground on an enormous kingfisher’s
nest; really, it was sixty furlongs in circumference.
The female was sailing on it, keeping her eggs
warm, and she was not much smaller than the
nest—in fact, as she started up she almost sunk the
ship with the wind of her wings. She flew off, however, uttering a plaintive cry. We landed when day
began to break, and observed that the nest was like
a great raft, built of huge trees. There were five
hundred eggs in it, every one of them bigger than a
Chian wine-jar, and the chicks were already visible
inside them and were chirping. We cut open one


<pb n="v.1.p.347"/>

of the eggs with axes and took from the shell a
featherless chick fatter than twenty vultures.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="41"><p>

When we had sailed a distance of two hundred
furlongs from the nest, great and wonderful signs
manifested themselves to us. The gooseneck
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">In ancient ships the gooseneck was an ornament on the
stem, or (as here) on the stern, Nowadays it is a device for
fastening a spar to a mast.</note>
suddenly grew feathers and started cackling, the sailing-master, Scintharus, who was already bald, became
the owner of long hair, and what was strangest of all,
the ship’s mast budded, branched, and bore fruit at
the summit! The fruit consisted of figs and black
raisin-grapes, which were not yet ripe.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="2">A parody on the experience of the Pirates who carried
off Dionysus (Hymn. Hom. 7, 38).</note>
On seeing
this, we were disturbed, as well we might be, and
offered a prayer to the gods on account of the
strangeness of the manifestation.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="42"><p>

We had not
yet gone five hundred’ furlongs when we saw a very
large, thick forest of pines and cypresses. We
thought it was land, but in reality it was a
bottomless sea overgrown with rootless trees, in spite
of which the trees stood up motionless and straight,
as if they were floating. On drawing near and
forming an idea of the situation, we were in a
quandary what to do, for it was not possible to sail
between the trees, they being thick and close
together, nor did. it seem easy to turn back.
Climbing the tallest tree, I looked to see how things
were on the other side, and I saw that the forest
extended for fifty stades or a little more, and that
another ocean lay beyond. So we resolved to lift the




<pb n="v.1.p.349"/>

ship on to the tree-tops, which were thick, and cross
over, if we could, to the farther side ; and that is what
we did. We made her fast:to a large rope, climbed
" the trees and pulled her up with much ado. Setting
her on the branches and spreading our canvas, we
sailed just as if we were at sea, carried along by the
force of the wind. At that juncture a line of the
poet Antimachus came into my head; he says somewhere or other:

<quote>
<l>And unto them their forest cruise pursuing.</l>
</quote>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="43"><p>

We managed the wood in spite of everything
and reached the water. Lowering the ship again
in the same way we sailed through pure, clear
water, until we came to a great crevasse made by
the water dividing, like the cracks that one often
sees in the earth, made by earthquakes. Though
we got in the sails, the ship was slow to lose headway and so came near being engulfed. Peering over
the edge, we saw a precipice of fully a thousand
furlongs, most frightful and unnatural—the water
stood there as if cut apart! But as we looked about
us we saw on the right at no great distance a bridge
thrown across, which was of: water, joining the
surfaces of the two seas and flowing from one to the
other. Rowing up, therefore, we ran into the stream
and by great effort got across, though we thought
we should never do it.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="44"><p>

Then we came to a smooth sea and an island
of no great size that was easily accessible and was
inhabited. -It was peopled by savages, the Bullheads, who have horns in the style that the


<pb n="v.1.p.351"/>

Minotaur is represented at home. Landing, we
went up country to get water and food if we could,
for we no longer had any. Water we found close
by, but there was nothing else to be seen, though
we heard a great bellowing not far off. Thinking it
was a herd of cattle, we went ahead cautiously and
came upon the men of whom I spoke. On seeing
us, they gave chase, and captured three of my
comrades, but the rest of us made our escape to
the sea. Then, however, we all armed ourselves—
it did not seem right to let our friends go unavenged
—and fell on the Bullheads while they were portioning out the flesh of the men they had slain. We
put them all to flight and gave chase, killing about
fifty and taking two alive: then we turned back to
the ship with our prisoners. We found no food,
though. The rest therefore urged that the captives
be killed; I did not approve of this, however, but
put them in irons and kept them under guard until
ambassadors came from the Bullheads, asking for
them and offering a ransom. We understood them
because they made signs and bellowed plaintively as
if in entreaty. The ransom was a number of cheeses,
dried fish, onions, and four does, each of which had
only three feet, for while they had two behind, the
forefeet had grown together. In exchange for all
this we surrendered the captives, and after stopping
there a single day we put to sea.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="45"><p>

Already we began to see fish, birds flew by and
all the other signs that land was near made their
appearance. In a little while we saw men who were


<pb n="v.1.p.353"/>

following a novel mode of sailing, being at once
sailors and ships. Let me tell you how they did it:
they lay on their backs on the water, hoisted
their jury-masts, which are sizeable, spread sail on
them, held the clews in their hands, and were off
and away as soon as the wind struck them. Others
came next who sat on corks and had a pair of
dolphins hitched up, driving them and guiding them
with reins ; in moving ahead, the dolphins drew the
corks along. They neither offered us harm nor ran
away from us, but drove along fearlessly and peacefully, wondering at the shape of our boat and
examining her from all sides.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="46"><p>

In the evening we touched at another island of
no great size. It was inhabited by women—or so
we thought—who spoke Greek, and they came up
to us, welcomed and embraced us. They were got
up just like courtezans and were all beautiful and
young, with tunics that swept on the ground. The
island was called Witchery, and the city Watertown.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">Both names are uncertain in the Greck.</note>
Each of the women took one of us home with her
and made him her guest. But I excused myself for
a moment—I had misgivings—and on looking about
rather carefully, saw many human bones and skulls
lying there. To make an outcry, call my comrades
together and arm ourselves did not seem best to. me,
but I fetched out my mallow and prayed to it
earnestly that I might escape the ills that beset me.
After a little while, as my hostess was waiting on me,
I saw that her legs were not a woman’s but those of
an ass. Then I drew my sword, caught and bound



<pb n="v.1.p.355"/>

her and questioned her about the whole thing.
Against her will she told me that they were women
of the sea, called Asslegs and that they fed on the
strangers that visited them. ‘“When we have made’
them drunk,” said she, “we go to bed with them
and attack them in their sleep.” On hearing this, I
left her there tied up, and myself went up to the
housetop and cried out and called my comrades together. When they had come, I told them everything, showed them the bones and led them in to the
woman who was tied up, but she immediately turned
to water and disappeared. Nevertheless I thrust my
sword into the water as a test, and the water turned
to blood.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg012.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="47"><p>

With all speed we went back to the ship and
sailed away. When the light of day began to show,
we saw land and judged it to be the world opposite
the one which we inhabit. After doing homage and
offering prayer, we took thought for the future.
Some of us proposed just to land and then turn back
again, others to leave the boat there, go into the
interior and see what the inhabitants were like.
While we were debating this, a violent storm struck
the boat, dashed it ashore and wrecked it, and
we ourselves had much trouble in swimming out
with our arms and anything else that we could
catch up.</p>

<p>
Thus far I have told you what happened to me
until I reached the other world, first at sea, then


<pb n="v.1.p.357"/>

during my voyage among the islands and in the air, then
in the whale, and after we left it, among the heroes
and the dreams, and finally among the Bullheads
and the Asslegs. What happened in the other world
I shall tell you in the succeeding books.
<note xml:lang="eng" n="1">The biggest lie of all, as a disgruntled Greek scribe
remarks in the margin!</note>


</p></div></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>

