<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>  <?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>  
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>

        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Apollodorus Against Nicostratus</title>
                <author>Demosthenes</author>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Demosthenes</author>
                        <title>Demosthenes with an English translation by Norman W. DeWitt, Ph.D.,
                            and Norman J. DeWitt, Ph.D.</title>

                        <imprint>
                            <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William
                                Heinemann Ltd.</publisher>
                            <date>1949</date>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>

        <encodingDesc>

            <refsDecl>
                <refState unit="speech"/>
                <refState unit="section"/>
            </refsDecl>
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
                <language ident="grc">Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>

    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>

            <div n="1" type="section">
                <p>I have no desire to bring a baseless and malicious charge; but I have filed this
                    inventory of property because I have suffered wrong and indignity from these men
                    and therefore thought it my duty to avenge myself upon them. Of this you will
                    find convincing proof, men of the jury, in the amount of the valuation, and in
                    my having filed the information in my own name. For, I take it, if I had wished
                    to bring a malicious suit, I should not have listed slaves worth two minae and a
                    half, the sum at which the claimant himself has fixed their value, and myself
                    have run the risk of losing a thousand drachmae, and forfeiting the right ever
                    again to indict anyone on my own behalf. Nor, again, was I so lacking in
                    resources or in friends as to be unable to find some one to file the
                    information; </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
                <p>but I thought it the most outrageous thing ever seen among men, that I should
                    myself suffer the wrong, but that another should lend his name on behalf of me,
                    the one wronged; and that this would then serve as presumptive proof to my
                    adversaries that I am lying whenever I speak to you of our enmity; for they
                    would say that no other man would have filed the information, if I were myself
                    the one wronged. It was for this reason that I filed the information. And now
                    that I have done so, if I can prove that the slaves belong to Arethusius, to
                    whom they are stated in the information to belong, I relinquish to the state the
                    three fourths which under the law are given to the private citizen filing the
                    information; for myself it is enough to have taken vengeance. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
                <p>If, now, there were water enough in the water-clock to permit my telling you in
                    detail from the beginning all the benefits I have conferred on them and all the
                    acts they have committed toward me, I am sure that you would feel more lenient
                    toward me for my resentment against them, and would deem these men the most
                    wicked of humankind. As it is, however, even double the amount of water that I
                    now have would be insufficient. I shall therefore relate to you the greatest and
                    most flagrant of their wrongdoings, and those which gave rise to the filing of
                    the information; the bulk of them I shall pass over. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
                <p>Nicostratus, whom you see here in court, men of the jury, was a neighbor of mine
                    in the country, and a man of my own age. We had long known each other, but after
                    my father's death, when I went to live in the country, where I still live, we
                    had much more to do with one another, since we were neighbors and men of the
                    same age. As time went on we became very intimate; indeed I came to feel on such
                    intimate terms with him that he never failed to win any favor he asked of me;
                    and he, on his part, was useful to me in looking after my affairs and managing
                    them, and whenever I was abroad on public service as trierarch, or on any
                    private business of my own, I used to leave him in charge of everything on the
                    farm. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
                <p>It happened that I was sent as trierarch round the <placeName key="tgn,7017076"
                        >Peloponnesus</placeName>, and from thence I had to carry to <placeName
                        key="tgn,7003122">Sicily</placeName> the ambassadors whom the people had
                    elected. I was forced to set sail in haste, so I wrote to Nicostratus, telling
                    him that I had to put to sea, and that I should not be able to come home for
                    fear of delaying the ambassadors; and I charged him to look after the
                    administration of matters at home, as he had done before. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="section">
                <p>During my absence three household slaves of Nicostratus ran away from him from
                    his farm, two of those whom I had given him, and one of a number whom he had
                    purchased for himself. He pursued them, but was taken captive by a trireme and
                    brought to <placeName key="tgn,7011087">Aegina</placeName>, where he was sold.
                    When I had come home with the ship of which I was in command, Deinon, this man's
                    brother, came to me and told me of his misfortunes, stating that, although
                    Nicostratus had sent him letters, he had not gone in quest of him for want of
                    funds for the journey, and he told me also that he heard that his brother was in
                    a dreadful condition. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="section">
                <p>When I heard this I was touched with compassion for Nicostratus on account of his
                    ill-fortune, and at once sent his brother Deinon to fetch him, giving him three
                    hundred drachmae for his journey. When Nicostratus got home, he came at once to
                    me, embraced me, thanked me for giving his brother money for his journey,
                    bewailed his own unhappy lot, and, while complaining of his own relatives,
                    begged me to succor him, just as in time past I had been a true friend to him.
                    Then he wept, and told me that he had been ransomed for twenty-six minae, and
                    urged me to contribute something toward the cost of his redemption.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="section">
                <p>On hearing this story, I felt pity for him, and moreover I saw in what wretched
                    plight he was, and he showed me the wounds of the fetters on his calves (he has
                    the scars of them still, but, if you bid him show them to you, he will not wish
                    to do so); I therefore answered that in time past I had been a true friend to
                    him, and that now I would help him in his distress, that I forgave him the three
                    hundred drachmae which I had given his brother for the expenses of his journey
                    to fetch him, and that I would make a contribution of one thousand drachmae
                    toward his ransom. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="section">
                <p>Nor did I make this promise in words only and fail to perform it in act; but,
                    since I was not well provided with funds in consequence of my quarrel with
                    Phormion and of his depriving me of the estate which my father left me, I took
                    to Theocles, who at that time was carrying on a banking business, some cups and
                    a chaplet of gold, which I happened to have in my house as a part of my
                    ancestral inheritance, and bade him give Nicostratus a thousand drachmae; and
                    that sum I gave him outright as a gift, and I acknowledge that it was a gift.
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="section">
                <p>A few days afterwards he came up to me weeping, and told me that the strangers
                    who had lent him the ransom money were demanding payment of the balance, and
                    that it was stipulated in the agreement that he should pay it within thirty days
                    or be indebted for double the amount; that, moreover, no one would either buy or
                    take a mortgage on the farm adjoining mine, because his brother Arethusius, who
                    is the owner of the slaves mentioned in the information, would not suffer anyone
                    to buy it or take it on mortgage, alleging that money was owing him on it
                    already. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="section">
                <p>“Do you, therefore,” he said, “provide for me the amount which is lacking before
                    the thirty days have passed, in order that what I have already paid, the
                    thousand drachmae, may not be lost, and that I myself be not liable to seizure.
                    I shall make a collection from my friends,” he said, “and when I have got rid of
                    the strangers, I shall pay you in full whatever you shall have lent me. You
                    know,” he said, “that the laws enact that a person ransomed from the enemy shall
                    be the property of the ransomer, if he fail to pay the redemption money.” </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="section">
                <p>When I heard these words of Nicostratus, having no idea that he was lying, I
                    answered, as was natural for a young man who was an intimate friend, and who was
                    far from thinking that he would be defrauded, “Nicostratus, in time past I was a
                    true friend to you, and now in your misfortunes I have helped you to the full
                    extent of my power. But since at the moment you are unable to find the whole
                    amount due, I indeed have no funds on hand, nor have I money any more than
                    yourself, but I grant you a loan of whatever part of my property you choose, for
                    you to mortgage for the balance of your debt, and to use the money without
                    interest for a year, and to pay off the strangers. When you have made the
                    collection from your friends, pay off my mortgage, as you yourself propose.”
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="section">
                <p>Hearing this, Nicostratus thanked me, and bade me to proceed with the matter with
                    all speed before the expiration of the days in the course of which he said he
                    must pay the ransom. Accordingly I mortgaged my lodging-house for sixteen minae,
                    to Arcesas of Pambotadae,<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Pambotadae, a deme of
                        the tribe Erectheïs.</note> whom Nicostratus himself introduced to me, and
                    he lent me the money at the interest rate of eight obols a month for each
                        mina.<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">That is, at the rate of 16 per
                        cent.</note> But, when Nicostratus had got the money, so far from showing
                    any gratitude for what I had done for him, he immediately began to lay a plot
                    against me to rob me of my money and become my enemy, in order that I might be
                    at a loss how to deal with the matter, since I was young and without experience
                    in affairs, and might not exact from him the sum for which the lodging-house had
                    been mortgaged, but might forgive him the debt. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="section">
                <p>Accordingly he first conspired against me with some persons with whom I was at
                    law, and bound himself by an oath to support them; then, after my action against
                    them had commenced, he divulged to them my arguments, with which he was
                    acquainted, and he entered me as a debtor to the public treasury to the amount
                    of six hundred and ten drachmae, as a fine for non-production of property
                    (although no citation had been served upon me), having got the case brought on
                    through the agency of Lycidas the miller. As witnesses against me to attest the
                    citation, he entered the name of his own brother, this Arethusius to whom these
                    slaves belong, and another person; and they were prepared, in the event of my
                    bringing to a preliminary hearing the suits which I had entered against my
                        relatives<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The reference is to his law-suits
                        with Phormion and Stephanus; see <bibl n="Dem. 36">Dem. 36</bibl>, <bibl
                            n="Dem. 45">Dem. 45</bibl> and <bibl n="Dem. 46">Dem. 46</bibl>.</note>
                    who were wronging me, to lay an information against me, as being a debtor to the
                    treasury, and throw me into prison. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="section">
                <p>And more than all this, he who had secured a judgement against me for six hundred
                    and ten drachmae, when no citation had been served upon me, and had entered the
                    names of false witnesses to the citation, made a forcible entry into my house
                    and carried off all the furniture to the value of more than twenty minae; he did
                    not leave a thing. I thought it my duty to avenge myself, and after paying the
                    debt to the treasury on hearing of the fine, I was proceeding to indict the one
                    who admitted that he had cited me to appear (that is, Arethusius), on a charge
                    of false citation, as the law directs. He, however, came to my farm by night,
                    cut off all the choice fruit-grafts that were there, and the tree-vines as well,
                    and broke down the nursery-beds of olive trees set in rows round about, making
                    worse havoc than enemies in war would have done. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="section">
                <p>More than this, as they were neighbors and my farm adjoined theirs, they sent
                    into it in the daytime a young boy who was an Athenian, and put him up to
                    plucking off the flowers from my rose-bed, in order that, if I caught him and in
                    a fit of anger put him in bonds or struck him, assuming him to be a slave, they
                    might bring against me an indictment for assault.</p>
                <p>When they failed in this, and I merely called witnesses to observe the wrong done
                    me without committing any offence against them myself, they played against me
                    the most dastardly trick. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="section">
                <p>When I had now brought my indictment of him for false citation to the preliminary
                    examination and was about to bring the case into court, Nicostratus lay in wait
                    for me near the stone quarries, as I was coming back late from Peiraeus, and
                    struck me with his fist and seizing me around the waist was on the point of
                    throwing me into the quarries, had not some people come up and, hearing my
                    cries, run to my assistance. A few days later, I came into court on a day that
                    was divided up among a number of cases, and proving that he had falsely attested
                    the citation and was guilty of all the other crimes which I have mentioned, I
                    won a conviction. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="section">
                <p>When it came to fixing the penalty, the jurymen wished to impose a sentence of
                    death upon him, but I begged them to do nothing like that on a prosecution
                    brought by me, and I agreed to the fine of a talent which these men themselves
                    proposed,—not that I wished to save Arethusius from the death penalty (for he
                    deserved death on account of the wrongs which he had committed against me), but
                    that I, Pasion's son, made a citizen by a decree of the people, might not be
                    said to have caused the death of any Athenian.</p>
                <p>To prove that I have told you the truth, I shall call before you witnesses to all
                    these facts.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="section">
                <p>The wrongs done to me by these people, men of the jury, which led me to file the
                    information, I have made clear to you. That these slaves are the property of
                    Arethusius, and that I listed them in the inventory because they formed a part
                    of his estate, I shall proceed to show you. <placeName key="tgn,1032468"
                        >Cerdon</placeName> he reared from early childhood; and to prove that he
                    belonged to Arethusius, I shall bring before you witnesses who know the
                        fact.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="section">
                <p>I shall also bring before you witnesses to prove that Arethusius got the wages on
                    his account from all the persons with whom <placeName key="tgn,1032468"
                        >Cerdon</placeName> ever worked, and that he used, as being his master, to
                    receive compensation or give it, whenever <placeName key="tgn,1032468"
                        >Cerdon</placeName> wrought any damage.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote></p>
                <p>As for Manes: Arethusius lent some money to Archepolis of Peiraeus, and when
                    Archepolis was unable to pay either the interest or the principal in full, he
                    made over to him Manes in settlement.</p>
                <p>To prove that I am speaking the truth, I shall bring before you witnesses to
                    establish these statements.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="section">
                <p>Furthermore, from the following facts also you will see that the men belong to
                    Arethusius. For whenever they bought up the produce of an orchard, or hired
                    themselves out to reap a harvest, or undertook any other piece of farming work,
                    it was Arethusius who made the purchase or paid the wages on their behalf.</p>
                <p>To prove that I am speaking the truth, I shall bring before you witnesses to
                    establish these statements also.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="section">
                <p>All the evidence which I had to offer to prove that the slaves belong to
                    Arethusius, I have laid before you. I wish, however, to speak also about the
                    challenge which these men tendered me, and which I also tendered them. They
                    challenged me at the preliminary hearing, stating that they were ready to
                    deliver up the slaves, that I myself might put them to the torture, their wish
                    being that this offer should serve as a sort of evidence for their side. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="section">
                <p>I answered, however, in the presence of witnesses, that I was ready to go with
                    them to the senate, and in conjunction with the senate or the Eleven<note
                        resp="Loeb" anchored="true">The board of police commissioners at <placeName
                            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note> to receive the slaves
                    for the torture, telling them that, if my suit against them had been a private
                    one, I should have accepted the slaves for the torture, if they had offered
                    them, but that, as it was, both the slaves and the information belonged to the
                        state<note resp="Loeb" anchored="true">Since Arethusius was a
                        state-debtor.</note>; and therefore the examination by the torture should be
                    conducted by a public official. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="section">
                <p>I thought that it was not proper for me as a private individual to put public
                    slaves to the torture; for I was not empowered to conduct the torture, nor was
                    it proper that I should decide on the meaning of the answers given by the men. I
                    thought that the Eleven, or persons chosen by the senate, should have everything
                    written down, and then, having sealed up the evidence extorted by the
                    torture—the answers, that is, given by the men—should produce it in court, that
                    you might hear it, and in the light of this reach whatever verdict you might
                    think right. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="section">
                <p>For if the men had been put to the torture privately by me, everything would have
                    been disputed by these men; but, if publicly, we should have kept quiet, and the
                    officers or those chosen by the senate would have carried on the torture as far
                    as they saw fit. When I made this offer, they declared that they would not
                    deliver up the slaves to the officials, nor would they go with me to the
                    senate.</p>
                <p>To prove that I am speaking the truth, call, please, the witnesses to these
                        facts.<quote type="Witnesses">
                        <title>Witnesses</title>
                    </quote>
                </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="section">
                <p>Their shameless impudence in laying claim to what is yours appears to me manifest
                    on many grounds, but I shall make their character to appear most clearly by a
                    reference to your laws. For these men, when the jurors wished to impose a
                    sentence of death upon Arethusius, begged the jurors to impose a fine in money,
                    and begged me to give my assent to this; and they agreed to be jointly
                    responsible for the payment. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="section">
                <p>But so far are they from making payment according to their guarantee, that they
                    even lay claim to what is yours. And yet the laws enact that any man's estate
                    shall be confiscated who, after guaranteeing any sum due to the state, does not
                    make good his guarantee; so that, even if the slaves belonged to them, they
                    ought to be state-property, if the laws are of any use. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="section">
                <p>And before Arethusius became a debtor to the state, he was admitted to be the
                    richest of the brothers, but since the laws declare his property to be yours,
                    Arethusius is made out to be a poor man, and his mother lays claim to one part
                    of his property, and his brothers to another. If they had wished to act fairly
                    toward you, they should have disclosed the entire estate of Arethusius, and then
                    have filed a claim, if any of their own property had been included in the
                    inventory. </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="section">
                <p>If, then, you reflect that there will be no lack of persons to lay claim to what
                    is yours—for they will either suborn some orphans or heiresses and claim your
                    sympathy, or they will talk about old age and embarrassments and a mother's
                    maintenance, and by dwelling tearfully upon these matters by which they think
                    they can most easily deceive you, they will try to rob the state of what is due
                    her;—if, I say, you disregard all these tricks, and reach an adverse verdict,
                    you will decide aright.</p>

            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
