<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Areopagiticus from Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Isocrates</author>
        <editor role="editor">George Norlin</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl>
          <author>Isocrates</author>
          <title>Isocrates with an English Translation in three volumes, by George Norlin, Ph.D.,
            LL.D.</title>
          <publisher>Cambridge, MA, Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
            Ltd.</publisher>
          <date>1980</date>
        </bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl n="CTS">
        <cRefPattern n="section"
          matchPattern="(\\w+)"
          replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n=\'$1\'])">
          <p>This pointer pattern extracts section</p>
        </cRefPattern>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState n="chunk context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>
    
    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="eng">English </language>
        <language ident="grc">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.epideictic">
        <keywords>
          <term>Epideictic</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.estate.claim">
        <keywords>
          <term>Claim against an Estate</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>April 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files. Change markup in accordance with orator dtd</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>put speechs in numerical order and consolidated files</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>September-October 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed the notes, mostly citations</item>
      </change>
      <change><date>1 March 2000</date>
	<respStmt><name>David Smith</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: isoc.orat_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.3  2011-09-22 19:56:10  lcerrato
fixed bibl to Aesch. Seven 1

Revision 1.2  2010-06-16 15:52:16  lcerrato
fixed bibls for Plut. Mor. to correct work title

Revision 1.1  2009/11/24 20:08:29  rsingh04
moved more xml files around based on copyright status

Revision 1.18  2009/08/03 14:20:33  student
fixed Aristot. Nic. Eth. reference - zr

Revision 1.17  2009/07/23 20:24:35  student
fixed section numbers - zr

Revision 1.16  2009/06/26 17:51:34  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.15  2009/06/24 16:04:25  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.14  2009/06/19 19:06:52  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.13  2009/06/11 20:25:01  student
fixed bibl errors - zr

Revision 1.12  2009/06/11 19:55:46  rsingh04
fixed section error

Revision 1.11  2009/05/19 20:57:47  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.10  2009/04/29 02:29:49  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.9  2009/04/17 19:20:30  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.8  2009/04/03 20:20:43  lcerrato
fixing bad bibl refs

Revision 1.7  2009/03/02 19:01:28  rsingh04
fixed date, dateRange and dateStruct tags

Revision 1.6  2009/02/05 18:43:43  lcerrato
fixed bad bibls

Revision 1.5  2009/01/07 21:38:23  lcerrato
fixed bibl refs to Bacchylides

Revision 1.4  2008/12/18 20:25:05  lcerrato
fixing typos

Revision 1.3  2008/11/19 21:22:11  lcerrato
fixed bad refs to Aristot. Nic. Eth. and Solon

Revision 1.2  2006/02/10 21:10:25  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.1  2005/08/01 18:01:19  packel
split up letters and speeches

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:37:33  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:17:03  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2001/10/09 22:40:51  dasmith
Fixed instances of zero for capital O.

Revision 1.6  2000/03/04 20:34:39  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.5  2000/03/01 22:22:15  dasmith
Only look up speeches in the orat. subdoc.

Revision 1.4  2000/03/01 21:45:05  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.
Wrap letters in DIV1 so we can cite them as "L. 4.3" within document.


      </item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="eng">
    <body>
      <div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0010.tlg018.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
      <div n="1" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Many of you are wondering, I suppose, what in the world my purpose is<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Strictly, what my purpose was. The aorist tense reflects the
            fact that the Athenian orators had to give written notice, in advance, of any subject
            they proposed to discuss before the General Assembly. See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.15">Isoc.
              7.15</bibl>.</note> in coming forward to address you on <title>The Public
            Safety</title>, as if <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> were in danger
          or her affairs on an uncertain footing, when in fact she possesses more than two hundred
          ships-of-war, enjoys peace throughout her territory, maintains her empire on the sea,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The second Athenian Confederacy, organized in <date
              when="-0378">378 B.C.</date> See General Introduction p. xxxvii.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="2" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and has, furthermore, many allies who, in case of any need, will readily come to her
            aid,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">He refers here, probably, to allies by special
            treaty as distinguished from the allies next mentioned, who were members of the
            Confederacy and under the leadership of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName>. The latter paid their quotas into the Athenian treasury for the
            support of the Confederate navy.</note> and many more allies who are paying their
            contributions<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the second Confederacy the word <foreign
              xml:lang="grc">su/ntacis</foreign> (contribution) was used instead of <foreign
              xml:lang="grc">fo/ros</foreign> (tribute) which became an odious term in the
            Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>. Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.123">Isoc. 15.123</bibl>.</note> and obeying her commands. With these
          resources, one might argue that we have every reason to feel secure, as being far removed
          from danger, while our enemies may well be anxious and take thought for their own safety.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="3" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now you, I know, following this reasoning, disdain my coming forward, and are confident
          that with this power you will hold all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>
          under your control. But as for myself, it is because of these very things that I am
          anxious; for I observe that those cities which think they are in the best circumstances
          are wont to adopt the worst policies, and that those which feel the most secure are most
          often involved in danger. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="4" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The cause of this is that nothing of either good or of evil visits mankind unmixed, but
          that riches and power are attended and followed by folly, and folly in turn by
            licence;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introduction p. xxxiii.</note>
          whereas poverty and lowliness are attended by sobriety and great moderation; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="5" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>so that it is hard to decide which of these lots one should prefer to bequeath to one's
          own children. For we shall find that from a lot which seems to be inferior men's fortunes
          generally advance to a better condition,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 6.103">Isoc. 6.103 ff.</bibl></note> whereas from one which appears to be
          superior they are wont to change to a worse. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="6" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Of this truth I might cite examples without number from the lives of individual men,
          since these are subject to the most frequent vicissitudes; but instances which are more
          important and better known to my hearers may be drawn from the experiences of our city and
          of the Lacedaemonians. As for the Athenians, after our city had been laid waste by the
          barbarians, we became, because we were anxious about the future and gave attention to our
          affairs, the foremost of the Hellenes;<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, then a walled city, was temporarily abandoned
            by her people before the battle of <placeName key="tgn,7002340">Salamis</placeName>, and
            destroyed by the troops of Xerxes. After the Persian Wars, she became the head of the
            Confederacy of <placeName key="perseus,Delos">Delos</placeName>. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 6.42">Isoc. 6.42 ff.</bibl>, and <bibl n="Isoc. 4.71">Isoc.
            4.71-72</bibl>.</note> whereas, when we imagined that our power was invincible, we
          barely escaped being enslaved.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At the end of the
            Peloponnesian War, <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> was at the mercy
            of <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> and the Spartan allies. The latter
            proposed that <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> be utterly destroyed
            and her citizens sold into slavery, but the Spartans refused to allow the city “which
            had done a great service to <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>” to be
            reduced to slavery. <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 2.2.19">Xen. Hell. 2.2.19-20</bibl>. Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.78">Isoc. 8.78, 105</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 14.32">Isoc. 14.32</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.319">Isoc. 15.319</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="7" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Likewise the Lacedaemonians, after having set out in ancient times from obscure and
          humble cities, made themselves, because they lived temperately and under military
          discipline, masters of the <placeName key="tgn,7017076">Peloponnesus</placeName>;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.61">Isoc. 4.61</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.253">Isoc. 12.253 ff.</bibl></note> whereas later, when they grew
          overweening and seized the empire both of the sea and of the land, they fell into the same
          dangers as ourselves.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Spartan supremacy began with the
            triumph over <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in <date when="-0404"
              >404 B.C.</date> and ended with the defeat at Leuctra, <date when="-0371">371
              B.C.</date> See Vol I. p. 402, footnote. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 5.47">Isoc. 5.47</bibl>.
            After Leuctra, <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, in her turn, saved
              <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> from destruction. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 5.44">Isoc. 5.44</bibl> and note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="8" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Whoever, therefore, knowing that such great vicissitudes have taken place and that such
          mighty powers have been so quickly brought to naught, yet trusts in our present
          circumstances, is all too foolish,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the language cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. 6.48">Isoc. 6.48</bibl>.</note> especially since <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> is now in a much less favorable condition than
          she was at that time, while the hatred<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By the bitter
            “Social War.” See General Introduction p. xxxviii.</note> of us among the Hellenes and
          the enmity<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the course of the “Social War,” the Athenian
            general Chares had aided the satrap Artabazus in his revolt against Artaxerxes III. See
            Diodorus xvi. 22.</note> of the great King, which then brought disaster to our arms,
          have been again revived. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="9" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I am in doubt whether to suppose that you care nothing for the public welfare or that
          you are concerned about it, but have become so obtuse that you fail to see into what utter
          confusion our city has fallen. For you resemble men in that state of mind—you who have
          lost all the cities in <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName>,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Not all the cities on the northern coast of the <placeName
              key="tgn,7002675">Aegean</placeName> (<placeName key="tgn,7002756"
            >Thrace</placeName>), but those on the Chalcidian peninsula, notably Amphipolis Pydna,
              <placeName key="tgn,6004814">Potidaea</placeName>, and <placeName
              key="perseus,Olynthus">Olynthus</placeName>, which had fallen under the power or under
            the influence of Philip of <placeName key="tgn,7002715">Macedon</placeName>. See <bibl
              n="Dem. 4.4">Dem. 4.4</bibl>.</note> squandered to no purpose more than a thousand
          talents on mercenary troops,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Athenian forces were now
            largely made up of paid foreigners, recruited from everywhere. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.44"
              >Isoc. 8.44-47</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 4.20">Dem. 4.20</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="10" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>provoked the ill-will of the Hellenes and the hostility of the barbarians, and, as if
          this were not enough, have been compelled to save the friends of the Thebans<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Probably the Messenians, who had been made independent of
              <placeName key="perseus,Sparta">Sparta</placeName> by the Thebans. See Introduction to
              <bibl n="Isoc. 6.">Isoc. 6.</bibl>. Demosthenes, in his speech <title>For the
              Megalopolitans</title>, criticizes the Athenians for their folly in pledging
            themselves to aid the Messenians against Spartan aggression. See especially <bibl
              n="Dem. 16.9">Dem. 16.9</bibl>.</note> at the cost of losing our own allies<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Such powerful states as <placeName key="tgn,7002670"
              >Chios</placeName>, <placeName key="perseus,Byzantium">Byzantium</placeName>, and
              <placeName key="tgn,7011266">Rhodes</placeName> were lost to the Athenian Confederacy
            by the peace following the “Social War.” Of the seventy-five cities which belonged to
            the Confederacy the majority remained loyal. See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.2">Isoc.
            7.2</bibl>.</note>; and yet to celebrate the good news of such accomplishments we have
          twice now offered grateful sacrifices to the gods,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Diodorus
              (<bibl n="Diod. 16.22">Dio. Sic. 16.22</bibl>) records the celebration in <placeName
              key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> of the victory of Chares, supporting the
            rebellion of the Satrap Artabazus, over Artaxerxes III. See § 8, note. The occasion of
            the second celebration is not known.</note> and we deliberate about our affairs more
          complaisantly than men whose actions leave nothing to be desired! </p>
      </div>
      <div n="11" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> And it is to be expected that acting as we do we should fare as we do; for nothing can
          turn out well for those who neglect to adopt a sound policy for the conduct of their
          government as a whole. On the contrary, even if they do succeed in their enterprises now
          and then, either through chance or through the genius of some man,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">The reference is to the victorious campaigns of Conon and his son Timotheus.
            See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.142">Isoc. 4.142, 154</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 5.61">Isoc.
              5.61-64</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 15.107">Isoc. 15.107 ff.</bibl></note> they soon after
          find themselves in the same difficulties as before, as anyone may see from what happened
          in our own history. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="12" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For when all <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName> fell under the power of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, after the naval victory of Conon and
          the campaign of Timotheus, we were not able to hold our good fortune any time at all, but
          quickly dissipated and destroyed it.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In the disastrous
            “Social War.”</note> For we neither possess nor do we honestly seek to obtain a polity
          which can properly deal with our affairs. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="13" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet we all know that success does not visit and abide with those who have built
          around themselves the finest and the strongest walls,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
            Thucydides vii. 77: <foreign xml:lang="grc">a)/ndres ga\r po/lis, kai\ ou) tei/xh
              ou)de\ nh=es a)ndrw=n kenai/</foreign>. Also Alcaeus fr. 28, 29 L.C.L., and Sir
            William Jones, <title>What Constitutes a State</title>.</note> nor with those who have
          collected the greatest population in one place, but rather with those who most nobly and
          wisely govern their state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="14" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For the soul of a state is nothing else than its polity,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 12.138">Isoc. 12.138</bibl>; <bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 4.1295a.40"
              >Aristot. Pol. 1295a40</bibl>; <bibl n="Dem. 24.210">Dem. 24.210</bibl>.</note> having
          as much power over it as does the mind over the body; for it is this which deliberates
          upon all questions, seeking to preserve what is good and to ward off what is disastrous;
          and it is this which of necessity assimilates to its own nature the laws, the public
          orators and the private citizens; and all the members of the state must fare well or ill
          according to the kind of polity under which they live. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="15" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet we are quite indifferent to the fact that our polity has been corrupted, nor do
          we even consider how we may redeem it. It is true that we sit around in our shops<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In the market-place, especially the barber shops.</note>
          denouncing the present order and complaining that never under a democracy have we been
          worse governed, but in our actions and in the sentiments which we hold regarding it we
          show that we are better satisfied with our present democracy than with that which was
          handed down to us by our forefathers. It is in favor of the democracy of our forefathers
          that I intend to speak, and this is the subject on which I gave notice that I would
          address you. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="16" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I find that the one way—the only possible way—which can avert future perils from us
          and deliver us from our present ills is that we should be willing to restore that earlier
          democracy which was instituted by Solon, who proved himself above all others the friend of
          the people, and which was re-established by Cleisthenes, who drove out the tyrants and
          brought the people back into power— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="17" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>a government than which we could find none more favorable to the populace or more
          advantageous to the whole city.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For Solon and Cleisthenes
            as the authors of the restricted democracy of <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.232">Isoc. 15.232</bibl>. For Isocrates'
            political ideas see General Introduction p. xxxviii.</note> The strongest proof of this
          is that those who enjoyed this constitution wrought many noble deeds, won the admiration
          of all mankind, and took their place, by the common consent of the Hellenes, as the
          leading power of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>; whereas those who were
          enamored of the present constitution made themselves hated of all men, suffered many
          indignities, and barely escaped falling into the worst of all disasters.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 7.6">Isoc. 7.6</bibl> and note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="18" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And yet how can we praise or tolerate a government which has in the past been the cause
          of so many evils and which is now year by year ever drifting on from bad to worse? And how
          can we escape the fear that if we continue to progress after this fashion we may finally
          run aground on rocks more perilous than those which at that time loomed before us? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="19" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But in order that you may make a choice and come to a decision between the two
          constitutions, not from the summary statement you just heard, but from exact knowledge, it
          behoves you, for your part, to render yourselves attentive to what I say, while I, for my
          part, shall try to explain them both to you as briefly as I can. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="20" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> For those who directed the state in the time of Solon and Cleisthenes did not establish
          a polity which in name merely was hailed as the most impartial and the mildest of
          governments, while in practice showing itself the opposite to those who lived under it,
          nor one which trained the citizens in such fashion that they looked upon insolence as
          democracy, lawlessness as liberty, impudence of speech as equality, and licence to do what
          they pleased as happiness,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For similar caricatures of the
            later Athenian democracy see <bibl n="Thuc. 3.82.4">Thuc. 3.82.4 ff.</bibl>, and
            especially <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 560">Plat. Rep. 560-561</bibl>.</note> but rather a
          polity which detested and punished such men and by so doing made all the citizens better
          and wiser. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="21" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But what contributed most to their good government of the state was that of the two
          recognized kinds of equality—that which makes the same award to all alike and that which
          gives to each man his due<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For these two kinds of equality
            cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 3.14">Isoc. 3.14 ff.</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 2.14">Isoc. 2.14</bibl>;
              <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 558c">Plat. Rep. 558c</bibl>, and <bibl n="Plat. Laws 757b">Plat.
              Laws 757b</bibl>; <bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 5.1301a.26">Aristot. Pol. 1301a 26
            ff.</bibl></note>—they did not fail to grasp which was the more serviceable; but,
          rejecting as unjust that which holds that the good and the bad are worthy of the same
          honors, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="22" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and preferring rather that which rewards and punishes every man according to his deserts,
          they governed the city on this principle, not filling the offices by lot from all the
            citizens,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The method of electing the various magistrates
            changed from time to time, and is much less simple than Isocrates here represents it to
            be. For example, election of the chief magistrates, the archons, by lot (though from a
            previously selected group) is at least as old as Solon. On the other hand, in Isocrates'
            day officers who had supervision over military and financial affairs were elected by
            show of hands in the General Assembly. See Gilbert, <title>Greek Constitutional
              Antiquities</title>(English translation) pp. 216 ff. It seems clear, however, that
            after Cleisthenes all classes of citizens, the poor as well as the rich, became eligible
            to the offices (<bibl n="Plut. Arist. 22">Plut. Arist. 22</bibl>) and that election by
            lot became increasingly a device to further pure democracy.</note> but selecting the
          best and the ablest for each function of the state; for they believed that the rest of the
          people would reflect the character of those who were placed in charge of their affairs.
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="23" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Furthermore they considered that this way of appointing magistrates was also more
          democratic than the casting of lots, since under the plan of election by lot chance would
          decide the issue and the partizans of oligarchy would often get the offices; whereas under
          the plan of selecting the worthiest men, the people would have in their hands the power to
          choose those who were most attached to the existing constitution. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="24" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The reason why this plan was agreeable to the majority and why they did not fight over
          the offices was because they had been schooled to be industrious and frugal, and not to
          neglect their own possessions and conspire against the possessions of others, and not to
          repair their own fortunes out of the public funds,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">He is
            thinking of pay, not only for the magistrates, but for attendance at the sessions of the
            jury courts, of the General Assembly, etc. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.130">Isoc. 8.130</bibl>.
            Aristotle (<bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 24">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 24</bibl>) states that
            since the changes which were introduced by Aristides over twenty thousand Athenians
            earned their livelihood in public service of one sort or another. In the same work (62)
            he gives a brief sketch of the pay for such services.</note> but rather to help out the
          commonwealth, should the need arise, from their private resources,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For the public spirit of the old democracy see <bibl n="Isoc. 4.76">Isoc.
              4.76</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 8.42">Isoc. 8.42 ff.</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 12.145">Isoc.
              12.145 ff.</bibl></note> and not to know more accurately the incomes derived from the
          public offices than those which accrued to them from their own estates. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="25" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>So severely did they abstain from what belonged to the state that it was harder in those
          days to find men who were willing to hold office<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.146">Isoc. 12.146</bibl>; <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 347b">Plat. Rep.
            347b</bibl>, <bibl n="Plat. Rep. 520d">Plat. Rep. 520d</bibl>; <placeName
              key="tgn,2633991">Ruskin</placeName>, <title>Crown of Wild Olive</title>: “No one ever
            teaches well who wants to teach or governs well who wants to govern: it is an old saying
            (Plato's but I know not if his first) and as wise as old.”</note> than it is now to find
          men who are not begging for the privilege; for they did not regard a charge over public
          affairs as a chance for private gain but as a service to the state; neither did they from
          their first day in office seek to discover whether their predecessors had overlooked any
          source of profit, but much rather whether they had neglected any business of the state
          which pressed for settlement. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="26" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In a word, our forefathers had resolved that the people as the supreme master of the
          state, should appoint the magistrates, call to account those who failed in their duty, and
          judge in cases of dispute; while those citizens who could afford the time and possessed
          sufficient means<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Aristotle (<bibl
              n="Aristot. Pol. 2.1274a 15">Aristot. Pol. 1274a 15 ff.</bibl>) states that Solon gave
            to the populace the sovereign power of selecting their magistrates and of calling them
            to account, though the selection had to be made from “men of reputation and
            means.”</note> should devote themselves to the care of the commonwealth, as servants of
          the people, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="27" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>entitled to receive commendation if they proved faithful to their trust, and contenting
          themselves with this honor, but condemned, on the other hand, if they governed badly, to
          meet with no mercy, but to suffer the severest punishment.<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The same idea is developed in <bibl n="Isoc. 12.147">Isoc. 12.147</bibl>.</note> And
          how, pray, could one find a democracy more stable or more just than this, which appointed
          the most capable men to have charge of its affairs but gave to the people authority over
          their rulers? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="28" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Such was the constitution of their polity, and from this it is easy to see that also in
          their conduct day by day they never failed to act with propriety and justice; for when
          people have laid sound foundations for the conduct of the whole state it follows that in
          the details of their lives they must reflect the character of their government. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="29" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> First of all as to their conduct towards the gods—for it is right to begin with
            them<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This is almost poetic formula. Cf. Alcman fr. 3;
              <bibl n="Theoc. 17">Theocr. 17.1</bibl>; Aratus, <title>Phaenomena</title>
          1.</note>—they were not erratic or irregular in their worship of them or in the
          celebration of their rites; they did not, for example, drive three hundred oxen in
          procession to the altar,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The reference is, apparently, to
            special or occasional festivals such as those mentioned in <bibl n="Isoc. 7.10">Isoc.
              7.10</bibl>. He may have in mind here the festival held in honor of Chares' victory
            over Artaxerxes III, since that Athenian general was so generously paid by Artabazus
            that he could afford to contribute a drove of cattle for the celebration. See <bibl
              n="Diod. 16.22">Dio. Sic. 16.22</bibl>.</note> when it entered their heads to do
          so,while omitting, when the caprice seized them, the sacrifices instituted by their
            fathers;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 2.20">Isoc.
            2.20</bibl>.</note> neither did they observe on a grand scale the festivals imported
          from abroad, whenever these were attended by a feast, while contracting with the lowest
          bidder for the sacrifices demanded by the holiest rites of their religion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="30" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For their only care was not to destroy any institution of their fathers and to introduce
          nothing which was not approved by custom, believing that reverence consists, not in
          extravagant expenditures, but in disturbing none of the rites which their ancestors had
          handed on to them. And so also the gifts of the gods were visited upon them, not fitfully
          or capriciously, but seasonably both for the ploughing of the land and for the ingathering
          of its fruits. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="31" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> In the same manner also they governed their relations with each other. For not only were
          they of the same mind regarding public affairs, but in their private life as well they
          showed that degree of consideration for each other which is due from men who are
          rightminded and partners in a common fatherland. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="32" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>The less well-to-do among the citizens were so far from envying those of greater means
          that they were as solicitous for the great estates as for their own, considering that the
          prosperity of the rich was a guarantee of their own well-being. Those who possessed
          wealth, on the other hand, did not look down upon those in humbler circumstances, but,
          regarding poverty among their fellow-citizens as their own disgrace, came to the rescue of
          the distresses of the poor, handing over lands to some at moderate rentals, sending out
          some to engage in commerce, and furnishing means to others to enter upon various
          occupations; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="33" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for they had no fear that they might suffer one of two things—that they might lose their
          whole investment or recover, after much trouble, only a mere fraction of their venture; on
          the contrary, they felt as secure about the money which was lent out as about that which
          was stored in their own coffers. For they saw that in cases of contract the judges were
          not in the habit of indulging their sense of equity<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That
            is, their own sense of right and wrong (almost their sympathy) as distinguished from the
            legal sense. See Aristotle's distinction between equality and justice in <bibl
              n="Aristot. Rh. 1.13.19">Aristot. Rh. 1374b 21</bibl>. “The arbitrator,” he says,
            “looks to equity; the judge, to law.”</note> but were strictly faithful to the laws;
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="34" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>and that they did not in trying others seek to make it safe for themselves to disobey the
            law,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.142">Isoc. 15.142</bibl>,
            where he charges the Athenian juries with condoning depravity in others in order to make
            depravity safe for themselves.</note> but were indeed more severe on defaulters than
          were the injured themselves, since they believed that those who break down confidence in
          contracts do a greater injury to the poor than to the rich; for if the rich were to stop
          lending, they would be deprived of only a slight revenue, whereas if the poor should lack
          the help of their supporters they would be reduced to desperate straits. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="35" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And so because of this confidence no one tried to conceal his wealth<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">As now, from the sycophants. See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.8">Isoc. 15.8</bibl>, note.
            The present state of affairs is described in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.159">Isoc. 15.159
              ff.</bibl></note> nor hesitated to lend it out, but, on the contrary, the wealthy were
          better pleased to see men borrowing money than paying it back; for they thus experienced
          the double satisfaction—which should appeal to all right-minded men—of helping their
          fellow-citizens and at the same time making their own property productive for themselves.
          In fine, the result of their dealing honorably with each other was that the ownership of
          property was secured to those to whom it rightfully belonged, while the enjoyment of
          property was shared by all the citizens who needed it. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="36" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But perhaps some might object to what I have said on the ground that I praise the
          conditions of life as they were in those days, but neglect to explain the reasons why our
          forefathers managed so well both in their relations with each other and in their
          government of the state. Well, I have already touched upon that question,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In 20-27.</note> but in spite of that I shall now try to
          discuss it even more fully and more clearly. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="37" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> The Athenians of that day were not watched over by many preceptors<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">See Plato (<bibl n="Plat. Prot. 325c">Plat. Prot. 325c ff.</bibl>) for a
            picture of the education of Athenian boys.</note> during their boyhood only to be
          allowed to do what they liked when they attained to manhood;<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">In early times, the Council, according to Aristotle (<bibl
              n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 3">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 3</bibl>), not only had the duty of
            guarding the laws, but was the main factor in the government of the city, and punished
            at its discretion “all who misbehaved themselves.” It even selected the magistrates for
            the several offices (<bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 8">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 8</bibl>). Under
            Solon the Council kept its most important powers: it superintended the laws and guarded
            the constitution, exercised a censorship over the citizens “in the most important
            matters,” and corrected offenders, having plenary authority to inflict punishment (<bibl
              n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 8">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 8</bibl>). Under Cleisthenes its powers
            declined, but because of its wise and patriotic initiative in the Persian Wars it became
            again the supreme influence of the state (<bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 23">Aristot. Ath.
              Pol. 23</bibl>), and remained so until, under the leadership of Ephialtes, its
            important powers of supervision and censorship were taken from it and distributed to the
            Senate of the Five Hundred, the General Assembly, and the Heliastic juries (<bibl
              n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 25">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 25</bibl>).</note> on the contrary, they
          were subjected to greater supervision in the very prime of their vigor than when they were
          boys. For our forefathers placed such strong emphasis upon sobriety that they put the
          supervision of decorum in charge of the Council of the Areopagus—a body which was composed
          exclusively of men who were of noble birth<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Council was
            made up of ex-archons, who, after successfully passing an examination at the end of
            their terms of office to determine their fitness, became members of the Areopagus for
            life. The archons were at first “selected under qualifications of birth and of wealth.”
            See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 3">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 3</bibl>. After the “reforms” of
            Ephialtes, the property qualification was dropped, the only requirement being that of
            genuine citizenship. See <bibl n="Plut. Arist. 1">Plut. Arist.</bibl></note> and had
          exemplified in their lives exceptional virtue and sobriety, and which, therefore,
          naturally excelled all the other councils of <placeName key="tgn,1000074"
            >Hellas</placeName>. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="38" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And we may judge what this institution was at that time even by what happens at the
          present day; for even now, when everything connected with the election and the examination
          of magistrates<note anchored="true" resp="ed">With special reference to the archons, who
            became members of the Areopagus. He means that they were no longer taken necessarily
            from the best class of citizens. They did, however, have to undergo an examination (
              <foreign xml:lang="grc">eu)/quna</foreign>) on their conduct in office at the end of
            their term, and a further examination ( <foreign xml:lang="grc">dokimasi/a</foreign>)
            before the Council of the Areopagus to determine their worthiness to become members of
            that body. See Gilbert, <title>Greek Constitutional Antiquities</title> p. 282. What
            such an examination was like is described by <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 55">Aristot.
              Ath. Pol. 55</bibl>. Perhaps such examinations became largely perfunctory, and this
            may be the ground of Isocrates' complaint.</note> has fallen into neglect, we shall find
          that those who in all else that they do are insufferable, yet when they enter the
          Areopagus hesitate to indulge their true nature, being governed rather by its traditions
          than by their own evil instincts. So great was the fear which its members inspired in the
          depraved and such was the memorial of their own virtue and sobriety which they left behind
          them in the place of their assembly. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="39" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Such, then, as I have described, was the nature of the Council which our forefathers
          charged with the supervision of moral discipline—a council which considered that those who
          believed that the best citizens are produced in a state where the laws are prescribed with
          the greatest exactness<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 4.78">Isoc.
              4.78</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 12.144">Isoc. 12.144</bibl>.</note> were blind to the
          truth; for in that case there would be no reason why all of the Hellenes should not be on
          the same level, at any rate in so far as it is easy to borrow written codes from each
          other. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="40" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But in fact, they thought, virtue is not advanced by written laws but by the habits of
          every-day life; for the majority of men tend to assimilate the manners and morals amid
          which they have been reared. Furthermore, they held that where there is a multitude of
          specific laws, it is a sign that the state is badly governed;<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">For this idea that the multiplication of laws is a symptom of degeneracy see
              <bibl n="Tac. Ann. 3.27">Tacit. Ann. 3.27</bibl>: corruptissima republica plurimae
            leges.</note> for it is in the attempt to build up dikes against the spread of crime
          that men in such a state feel constrained to multiply the laws. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="41" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Those who are rightly governed, on the other hand, do not need to fill their
            porticoes<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Since Solon's time, Athenian laws were posted
            on pillars in the “King's Portico,” by the market-place. See <bibl
              n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 7">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 7</bibl>.</note> with written statutes,
          but only to cherish justice in their souls; for it is not by legislation, but by morals,
          that states are well directed, since men who are badly reared will venture to transgress
          even laws which are drawn up with minute exactness, whereas those who are well brought up
          will be willing to respect even a simple code.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Plat. Rep. 425a">Plat. Rep. 425a ff.</bibl></note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="42" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore, being of this mind, our forefathers did not seek to discover first how they
          should penalize men who were lawless, but how they should produce citizens who would
          refrain from any punishable act; for they thought that this was their duty, while it was
          proper for private enemies alone to be zealous in the avenging of crime.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The initiative in bringing criminals to justice was left
            largely to private citizens, any one of whom might bring charges before a court.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="43" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now our forefathers exercised care over all the citizens, but most of all over the
          young. They saw that at this age men are most unruly of temper and filled with a multitude
          of desires,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Plat. Laws 808d">Plat. Laws
              808d</bibl>.</note> and that their spirits are most in need of being curbed by
          devotion to noble pursuits and by congenial labor; for only such occupations can attract
          and hold men who have been educated liberally and trained in high-minded ways. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="44" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> However, since it was not possible to direct all into the same occupations, because of
          differences in their circumstances, they assigned to each one a vocation which was in
          keeping with his means; for they turned the needier towards farming and trade, knowing
          that poverty comes about through idleness, and evil-doing through poverty. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="45" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Accordingly, they believed that by removing the root of evil they would deliver the young
          from the sins which spring from it. On the other hand, they compelled those who possessed
          sufficient means to devote themselves to horsemanship,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">That
            is, in training for the races at the festivals.</note> athletics,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">There were three gymnasiums in <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName>: the Lyceum, the Academy, and the Cynosarges.</note> hunting,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">In <bibl n="Aristoph. Kn. 1382">Aristoph. Kn. 1382 ff.</bibl>,
            the reformed Demos declares that it will henceforth make all these demagogues take to
            hunting and give up concocting “decrees” for the Assembly.</note> and philosophy,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The cultivated life. See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.47">Isoc. 4.47
              ff.</bibl></note> observing that by these pursuits some are enabled to achieve
          excellence, others to abstain from many vices. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="46" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But when they had laid down these ordinances they were not negligent regarding what
          remained to be done, but, dividing the city into districts and the country into townships,
          they kept watch over the life of every citizen,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The
            supervision of the young through guardians appointed by districts survives in the later
            period. See <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 42">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 42</bibl>.</note> haling
          the disorderly before the Council, which now rebuked, now warned, and again punished them
          according to their deserts. For they understood that there are two ways both of
          encouraging men to do wrong and of checking them from evil-doing; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="47" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for where no watch is kept over such matters and the judgements are not strict, there
          even honest natures grow corrupt; but where, again, it is not easy for wrongdoers either
          to escape detection or, when detected, to obtain indulgence, there the impulse to do evil
          disappears. Understanding this, they restrained the people from wrongdoing in both
          ways—both by punishment and by watchfulness; for so far from failing to detect those who
          had gone astray, they actually saw in advance who were likely to commit some offence. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="48" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Therefore the young men did not waste their time in the gambling-dens or with the
          flute-girls or in the kind of company in which they now spend their days,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The same picture of degeneracy is found in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.287">Isoc. 15.287</bibl>. Cf. Theopompus in <bibl n="Ath. 532d">Athen.
              532d</bibl>.</note> but remained steadfastly in the pursuits to which they had been
          assigned, admiring and emulating those who excelled in these. And so strictly did they
          avoid the market-place that even when they were at times compelled to pass through it,
          they were seen to do this with great modesty and sobriety of manner.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Aristoph. Cl. 991">Aristoph. Cl. 991</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Plat. Theaet. 173c">Plat. Theaet. 173c-d</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="49" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>To contradict one's elders or to be impudent to them<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Aristoph. Cl. 998">Aristoph. Cl. 998</bibl>.</note> was then considered more
          reprehensible than it is nowadays to sin against one's parents; and to eat or drink in a
          tavern was something which no one, not even an honest slave, would venture to do;<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The same expression is used in <bibl n="Isoc. 15.286">Isoc.
              15.286</bibl>.</note> for they cultivated the manners of a gentleman, not those of a
          buffoon; and as for those who had a turn for jesting and playing the clown, whom we today
          speak of as clever wits, they were then looked upon as sorry fools.<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 15.284">Isoc. 15.284</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="50" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But let no one suppose that I am out of temper with the younger generation: I do not
          think that they are to blame for what goes on, and in fact I know that most of them are
          far from pleased with a state of affairs which permits them to waste their time in these
          excesses; so that I cannot in fairness censure them, when it is much more just to rest the
          blame upon those who directed the city a little before our time;<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">He is thinking of Ephialtes and those who, following in his footsteps, made
              <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> more “democratic.” Aristotle says
            that following the Archonship of Ephialtes “the administration of the state became more
            and more lax,” <bibl n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 26">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 26</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="51" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for it was they who led on our youth to this spirit of heedlessness and destroyed the
          power of the Areopagus. For while this Council maintained its authority, <placeName
            key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> was not rife with law-suits,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">It was not yet the “litigious <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName>,” ridiculed in Aristophanes' <title>Wasps</title>.</note> or
            accusations,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">By the sycophants especially. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.8">Isoc. 15.8</bibl>, note.</note> or tax-levies,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Special taxes levied for war purposes on the well-to-do citizens.</note> or
            poverty,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> was impoverished by her wars, <bibl n="Isoc. 8.19">Isoc.
              8.19</bibl>.</note> or war; on the contrary, her citizens lived in accord with each
          other and at peace with mankind, enjoying the good will of the Hellenes and inspiring fear
          in the barbarians; </p>
      </div>
      <div n="52" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>for they had saved the Hellenes from destruction and had punished the barbarians so
          severely that the latter were well content if only they might suffer no further
            injury.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 7.80">Isoc. 7.80</bibl> and
              <bibl n="Isoc. 4.117">Isoc. 4.117-118</bibl>.</note> And so, because of these things,
          our forefathers lived in such a degree of security that the houses and establishments in
          the country were finer and more costly than those within the city-walls,<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Demosthenes contrasts the magnificence of the temples and
            public buildings in <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> with the
            unpretentiousness of private houses in the “good old days” when the house of a Miltiades
            or of an Aristides was no finer than any other, <bibl n="Dem. 3.25">Dem. 3.25
            ff.</bibl></note> and many of the people never visited <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> even for the festivals, preferring to remain at home in the
          enjoyment of their own possessions rather than share in the pleasures dispensed by the
          state. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="53" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For even the public festivals, which might otherwise have drawn many to the city, were
          not conducted with extravagance or ostentation, but with sane moderation, since our people
          then measured their well-being, not by their processions or by their efforts to outdo each
          other in fitting out the choruses,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The training and fitting
            out of a chorus for a dramatic festival was one of the services (liturgies) rendered to
            the state by the more wealthy citizens. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.128">Isoc. 8.128</bibl>,
            note. Isocrates here complains of the expensive and ostentatious rivalry in such
            matters. See below: “garments spangled with gold.” The cost of such a service in some
            cases amounted to as much as five thousand drachmas.</note> or by any such empty shows,
          but by the sobriety of their government, by the manner of their daily life, and by the
          absence of want among all their citizens. These are the standards by which one should
          judge whether people are genuinely prosperous and not living in vulgar fashion. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="54" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For as things now are, who among intelligent men can fail to be chagrined at what goes
          on, when we see many of our fellow-citizens drawing lots in front of the law-courts to
          determine whether they themselves shall have the necessaries of life,<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Six thousand citizens were selected by lot each year to constitute the
            “Heliastic” Court. These were divided into ten sections of five hundred each, one
            thousand being held in reserve as substitutes. The number of jurymen required varied
            from day to day, and each morning the required number was picked by lot. Service on the
            jury was at first without pay, but now (and since Pericles) the pay was three obols a
            day—a paltry sum, but fought for by the populace, to many of whom this meant “bread and
            butter.” Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 8.130">Isoc. 8.130</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 15.152">Isoc.
              15.152</bibl>.</note> yet thinking it proper to support at their expense any of the
          Hellenes who will deign to row their ships;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">At the
            beginning of the Peloponnesian War, Athenian triremes (ships of war) were commanded by
            citizens, but the crews (rowers) were made up of hirelings recruited from everywhere—the
            scum of the earth, according to <bibl n="Isoc. 8.79">Isoc. 8.79</bibl>. At that time the
            soldiers were Athenian citizens. Later the reverse was true: the fleet was manned by
            citizens, while the land troops were mercenaries. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.48">Isoc.
              8.48</bibl>.</note> appearing in the public choruses in garments spangled with gold,
          yet living through the winter in clothing which I refuse to describe and showing other
          contradictions of the same kind in their conduct of affairs, which bring great shame upon
          the city? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="55" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Nothing of the sort happened when the Areopagus was in power; for it delivered the poor
          from want by providing them with work and with assistance from the wealthy, the young from
          excesses by engaging them in occupations and by watching over them, the men in public life
          from the temptations of greed by imposing punishments and by letting no wrong-doer escape
          detection, and the older men from despondency by securing to them public honors and the
          devotion of the young. How then could there be a polity of greater worth than this, which
          so excellently watched over all the interests of the state? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="56" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have now discussed most of the features of the constitution as it once was, and those
          which I have passed over may readily be judged from those which I have described, since
          they are of the same character. However, certain people who have heard me discuss this
          constitution, while praising it most unreservedly and agreeing that our forefathers were
          fortunate in having governed the state in this fashion, </p>
      </div>
      <div n="57" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>have nevertheless expressed the opinion that you could not be persuaded to adopt it, but
          that, because you have grown accustomed to the present order, you would prefer to continue
          a wretched existence under it rather than enjoy a better life under a stricter polity; and
          they warned me that I even ran the risk, although giving you the very best advice, of
          being thought an enemy of the people and of seeking to turn the state into an
            oligarchy.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The ready retort of demagogues to any critic
            of ochlocracy. See <bibl n="Isoc. 15.318">Isoc. 15.318</bibl> and note; <bibl
              n="Aristoph. Pl. 570">Aristoph. Pl. 570</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="58" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Well, if I were proposing a course which was unfamiliar and not generally known, and if
          I were urging you to appoint a committee or a commission<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >The very word (<foreign xml:lang="grc">suggrafei=s</foreign>) which was used of the
            board of twenty men appointed to make recommendations of a change in the constitution
            before the establishment of the oligarchy of the Four Hundred, <date when="-0411">411
              B.C.</date></note> to consider it, which was the means through which the democracy was
          done away with before, there might be some reason for this charge. I have, however,
          proposed nothing of the kind, but have been discussing a government whose character is
          hidden from no one, but evident to all— </p>
      </div>
      <div n="59" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>one which, as you all know, is a heritage from our fathers, which has been the source of
          numberless blessings both to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and to the
          other states of <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>, and which was, besides,
          ordained and established by men who would be acknowledged by all the world to have been
          the best friends of the people<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Those who did, not what the
            people liked, but what was for their good. So Solon is called <foreign xml:lang="grc"
              >dhmokw/tatos</foreign>, <bibl n="Isoc. 7.16">Isoc. 7.16</bibl>.</note> among the
          citizens of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>; so that it would be of all
          things most absurd if I, in seeking to introduce such a polity, should be suspected of
          favoring revolution. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="60" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Furthermore, it is easy to judge of my purpose from the fact that in most of the
            discourses<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See especially <bibl n="Isoc. 4.105">Isoc.
              4.105 ff.</bibl>; General Introduction p. xxxviii.</note> which I have written, you
          will find that I condemn oligarchies and special privileges, while I commend equal rights
          and democratic governments—not all of them, but those which are well-ordered, praising
          them not indiscriminately, but on just and reasonable grounds. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="61" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>For I know that under this constitution our ancestors were far superior to the rest of
          the world, and that the Lacedaemonians are the best governed of peoples because they are
          the most democratic;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Exclusive of the Perioeci and the
            Helots. See <bibl n="Aristot. Pol. 4.1294b 18">Aristot. Pol. 1294b 18 ff.</bibl></note>
          for in their selection of magistrates, in their daily life, and in their habits in
          general, we may see that the principles of equity and equality have greater influence than
          elsewhere in the world—principles to which oligarchies are hostile, while well-ordered
          democracies practise them continually. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="62" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Moreover, if we will examine into the history of the most illustrious and the greatest
          of the other states, we shall find that democratic forms of government are more
          advantageous for them than oligarchies. For if we compare our own government—which is
          criticized by everyone<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 7.15">Isoc.
              7.15</bibl>.</note>—not with the old democracy which I have described, but with the
          rule which was instituted by the Thirty,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The oligarchy of
            the thirty “Tyrants,” instituted with the help of the Spartans at the end of the
            Peloponnesian War, <date when="-0404">404 B.C.</date></note> there is no one who would
          not consider our present democracy a divine creation. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="63" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And I desire, even though some will complain that I am straying from my subject, to
          expound and to explain how much superior this government is to that of the Thirty, in
          order that I may not be accused of scrutinizing too minutely the mistakes of our
          democracy, while overlooking the many fine things which it has achieved. I promise,
          however, that the story will not be long or without profit to my hearers. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="64" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> When we lost our fleet in the <placeName key="tgn,7002638">Hellespont</placeName><note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">At the Battle of Arginusae, 406 B. C., the beginning of the
            end of the Peloponnesian War.</note> and our city was plunged into the disasters of that
          time, who of our older men does not know that the “people's party,”<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">Many of them had been exiled by the Thirty or had fled for their lives.
            Thrasybulus placed himself at their head, defeated the Thirty in battle, and restored
            the democracy. See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 2.4.10">Xen. Hell. 2.4.10 ff.</bibl></note> as
          they were called, were ready to go to any length of hardship to avoid doing what the enemy
          commanded, deeming it monstrous that anyone should see the city which had ruled over the
          Hellenes in subjection to another state, whereas the partisans of oligarchy were ready
          both to tear down the walls<note anchored="true" resp="ed">One of the terms insisted on by
            Lysander was that the “long walls” connecting <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
              >Athens</placeName> with the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName> be
            demolished.</note> and to submit to slavery? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="65" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Or that at the time when the people were in control of affairs, we placed our garrisons
          in the citadels of other states, whereas when the Thirty took over the government, the
          enemy occupied the Acropolis of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>?<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">Lysander kept a Spartan garrison on the Acropolis during the
            rule of the Thirty. See <bibl n="Isoc. 8.92">Isoc. 8.92</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 15.319"
              >Isoc. 15.319</bibl>.</note> Or, again, that during the rule of the Thirty the
          Lacedaemonians were our masters, but that when the exiles returned and dared to fight for
          freedom, and Conon won his naval victory,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The Battle of
              <placeName key="tgn,5003757">Cnidus</placeName>, <date when="-0394">394 B.C.</date>,
            re-established the power of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</note>
          ambassadors came from the Lacedaemonians and offered <placeName key="perseus,Athens"
            >Athens</placeName> the command of the sea?<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 9.68">Isoc. 9.68</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="66" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Yes, and who of my own generation does not remember that the democracy so adorned the
          city with temples and public buildings that even today visitors from other lands consider
          that she is worthy to rule not only over <placeName key="tgn,1000074">Hellas</placeName>
          but over all the world;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">In almost the same terms he praises
            Pericles for his adornment of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>, <bibl
              n="Isoc. 15.234">Isoc. 15.234</bibl>.</note> while the Thirty neglected the public
          buildings, plundered the temples, and sold for destruction for the sum of three talents
          the dockyards<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The bitterest denunciation of the misrule of
            the Thirty is in the oration <title>Against Eratosthenes</title>, by Lysias (<bibl
              n="Lys. 12">Lys. 12</bibl>). At its close, he speaks of the sacrilege of the Thirty,
            particularly in selling off the treasures stored in the temples, and of their tearing
            down the dockyards of the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>.</note>
          upon which the city had spent not less than a thousand talents? </p>
      </div>
      <div n="67" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And surely no one could find grounds to praise the mildness<note anchored="true"
            resp="ed">An example of irony (litotes), a figure sparingly used by Isocrates. Cf.
            “outworn” in <bibl n="Isoc. 4.92">Isoc. 4.92</bibl>.</note> of the Thirty as against
          that of the people's rule! For when the Thirty took over the city, by vote of the
            Assembly,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Under duress. See <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 2.3.2"
              >Xen. Hell. 2.3.2</bibl>.</note> they put to death fifteen hundred Athenians<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">The same number is given in <bibl n="Isoc. 20.11">Isoc.
              20.11</bibl>.</note> without a trial and compelled more than five thousand to leave
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> and take refuge in the <placeName
            key="perseus,Piraeus">Piraeus</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Only those
            enjoyed the franchise under the Thirty who were in the catalogue of the approved “three
            thousand.” See <bibl n="Isoc. 18.17">Isoc. 18.17</bibl>.</note> whereas when the exiles
          overcame them and returned to <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> under
          arms, these put to death only the chief perpetrators of their wrongs and dealt so
          generously and so justly by the rest<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Plat. Menex. 243e">Plat. Menex. 243e</bibl>.</note> that those who had driven the
          citizens from their homes fared no worse than those who had returned from exile. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="68" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the best and strongest proof of the fairness of the people is that, although those
          who had remained in the city had borrowed a hundred talents from the Lacedaemonians<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Lys. 12.59">Lys. 12.59</bibl>.</note> with which
          to prosecute the siege of those who occupied the <placeName key="perseus,Piraeus"
            >Piraeus</placeName>, yet later when an assembly of the people was held to consider the
          payment of the debt, and when many insisted that it was only fair that the claims of the
          Lacedaemonians should be settled, not by those who had suffered the siege, but by those
          who had borrowed the money, nevertheless the people voted to pay the debt out of the
          public treasury.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">This is attested to by Aristotle (<bibl
              n="Aristot. Ath. Pol. 40">Aristot. Ath. Pol. 40</bibl>) in a passage which pays a high
            compliment to the admirable spirit in which the feud between the two parties was wiped
            out.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="69" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And in truth it was because of this spirit that they brought us into such concord with
          each other and so far advanced the power of the city that the Lacedaemonians, who under
          the rule of the oligarchy laid their commands upon us almost every day, under the rule of
          the people came begging and supplicating us not to allow them to be driven from their
            homes.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">After the Battle of Leuctra. See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.105">Isoc. 8.105</bibl>; <bibl n="Xen. Hell. 6.5.33">Xen. Hell. 6.5.33
              ff.</bibl></note> In a word the spirit of the two parties was this: the oligarchies
          were minded to rule over their fellow-citizens and be subject to their enemies; the
          people, to rule over the world at large and share the power of the state on equal terms
          with their fellow-citizens. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="70" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> I have recounted these things for two reasons: because I wanted to show, in the first
          place, that I am not in favor of oligarchy or special privilege, but of a just and orderly
          government of the people, and, in the second place, that even badly constituted
          democracies are responsible for fewer disasters than are oligarchies, while those which
          are well-ordered are superior to oligarchies in that they are more just, more impartial,
          and more agreeable to those who live under them. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="71" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But perhaps some of you may wonder what my purpose is in trying to persuade you to
          exchange the polity which has achieved so many fine things for another, and why it is that
          after having just now eulogized democracy in such high terms, I veer about capriciously
          and criticize and condemn the present order. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="72" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Well, I reproach men in private life when they succeed in a few things and fail in many,
          and regard them as falling short of what they ought to be; and, more than that, when men
          are sprung from noble ancestors and yet are only a little better than those who are
          distinguished for depravity, and much worse than their fathers, I rebuke them and would
          counsel them to cease from being what they are. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="73" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>And I am of the same mind also regarding public affairs. For I think that we ought not to
          be proud or even satisfied should we have shown ourselves more law-regarding than men
          accursed by the gods and afflicted with madness,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">With
            particular reference to the Thirty.</note> but ought much rather to feel aggrieved and
          resentful should we prove to be worse than our ancestors; for it is their excellence and
          not the depravity of the Thirty which we should strive to emulate, especially since it
          behoves Athenians to be the best among mankind. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="74" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> This is not the first time that I have expressed this sentiment; I have done so many
          times and before many people. For I know that while other regions produce varieties of
          fruits and trees and animals, each peculiar to its locality and much better than those of
          other lands, our own country is able to bear and nurture men who are not only the most
          gifted in the world in the arts and in the powers of action and of speech, but are also
          above all others in valor and in virtue.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.33">Isoc. 4.33</bibl>; <bibl n="Isoc. 8.94">Isoc. 8.94</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="75" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> This conclusion we may justly draw from the ancient struggles which they carried on
          against the Amazons and the Thracians and all of the Peloponnesians, and also from the
          wars which they waged against the Persians, in which, both when they fought alone and when
          they were aided by the Peloponnesians, whether on land or on the sea, they were victorious
          over the barbarians and were adjudged the meed of valor;<note anchored="true" resp="ed"
            >This paragraph sums up Athenian achievements in war which are stated at length in <bibl
              n="Isoc. 4.51">Isoc. 4.51-98</bibl>. Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 6.42">Isoc. 6.42</bibl>; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.42">Isoc. 12.42 ff.</bibl></note> for they could not have achieved these
          things, had they not far surpassed other men in the endowments of nature. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="76" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But let no one think that this eulogy is appropriate to those who compose the present
          government—far from it; for such words are a tribute to those who show themselves worthy
          of the valor of their forefathers, but a reproach to those who disgrace their noble origin
          by their slackness and their cowardice. And this is just what we are doing; for you shall
          have the truth. For although we were blessed with such a nature at our birth, we have not
          cherished and preserved it, but have, on the contrary, fallen into folly and confusion and
          lust after evil ways. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="77" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But if I go on attacking the things which admit of criticism and of censure in our
          present order, I fear that I shall wander too far afield from my subject. In any case I
          have spoken about these things before,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl
              n="Isoc. 8.49">Isoc. 8.49 ff.</bibl></note> and I shall do so again if I do not
          succeed in persuading you to cease from such mistakes of policy. For the present, I shall
          speak but a few words on the theme which I proposed to discuss in the beginning and then
          yield the platform to any who desire to address you upon this question. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="78" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> If we continue to govern <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> as we are
          now doing, then we are doomed to go on deliberating and waging war and living and faring
          and acting in almost every respect just as we do at the present moment and have done in
          the past; but if we effect a change of polity, it is evident by the same reasoning that
          such conditions of life as our ancestors enjoyed will come about for us also; for from the
          same political institutions there must always spring like or similar ways of life. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="79" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> But we must take the most significant of these ways and, comparing one with the other,
          decide which is preferable for us. And first let us consider how the Hellenes and the
          barbarians felt towards the earlier polity as compared with how they are now disposed
          towards us; for other peoples contribute not the least part of our well-being when they
          are properly disposed towards us. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="80" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Well then, the Hellenes felt such confidence in those who governed the city in those
          times that most of them of their own accord placed themselves under the power of
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf.
              <bibl n="Isoc. 8.76">Isoc. 8.76</bibl>.</note> while the barbarians were so far from
          meddling in the affairs of the Hellenes that they neither sailed their ships-of-war this
          side of the Phaselis nor marched their armies beyond the <placeName key="tgn,6002441"
            >Halys River</placeName>, refraining, on the contrary, from all aggression.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">See <bibl n="Isoc. 4.118">Isoc. 4.118</bibl> and note; <bibl
              n="Isoc. 12.59">Isoc. 12.59</bibl>.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="81" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>Today, however, circumstances are so completely reversed that the Hellenes regard
            <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> with hatred and the barbarians hold
          us in contempt. As to the hatred of us among the Hellenes, you have heard the report of
          our generals<note anchored="true" resp="ed">He speaks as though addressing an actual
            assembly which had received reports from the generals and dispatches from the King of
              <placeName key="tgn,7000231">Persia</placeName>. See Introduction, close.</note>
          themselves, and what the King thinks of us, he has made plain in the letters which have
          been dispatched by him.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Threatening dispatches sent to the
            Athenians because Chares had supported the cause of the rebel satrap Artabazus. See 8,
            note.</note>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div n="82" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Furthermore, under the discipline of the old days the citizens were so schooled in
          virtue as not to injure each other, but to fight and conquer all who attempted to invade
          their territory.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Cf. <bibl n="Isoc. 8.76">Isoc.
            8.76</bibl>.</note> We, however, do the very opposite; for we never let a day go by
          without bringing trouble on each other, and we have so far neglected the business of war
          that we do not even deign to attend reviews unless we are paid money for doing so. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="83" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p>But the greatest difference lies in the fact that in that day no one of the citizens
          lacked the necessaries of life nor shamed the city by begging from passers-by, whereas
          today those who are destitute of means outnumber those who possess them.<note
            anchored="true" resp="ed">An exaggeration, but Isocrates dwells upon the poverty of
              <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> in the <bibl n="Isoc. 8.">Isoc.
              8.</bibl>also.</note> And we may well be patient with people in such circumstances if
          they care nothing for the public welfare, but consider only how they may live from day to
          day. </p>
      </div>
      <div n="84" subtype="section" type="textpart">
        <p> Now I have come before you and spoken this discourse, believing that if we will only
          imitate our ancestors we shall both deliver ourselves from our present ills and become the
          saviors, not of <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName> alone, but of all the
            Hellenes;<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See General Introduction p. xxxii.</note> but
          it is for you to weigh all that I have said and cast your votes according to your
          judgement of what is best for <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>.</p>
      </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
