<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader type="text">
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>The Third Tetralogy: Prosecution for Murder Of One Who Pleads Self-Defense from
          Speeches</title>
        <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
        <author>Antiphon</author>
        <editor role="translator">K. J. Maidment</editor>
        <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
        <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
        <respStmt>
          <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
          <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
          <name>William Merrill</name>
          <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
          <name>David Smith</name>
        </respStmt>
        <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>

      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
        <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
        <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
        <bibl><idno type="OCLC">5331826</idno><idno type="ISBN">0674993403</idno></bibl>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <encodingDesc>
      <refsDecl>
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=2">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=3">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
      <refsDecl n="speech=4">
        <refState delim="." unit="speech"/>
        <refState delim="." unit="tetralogy"/>
        <refState n="context" unit="section"/>
      </refsDecl>
    </encodingDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
        <language ident="en">English </language>
        <language ident="greek">Greek </language>
      </langUsage>

      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.prosecution">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Prosecution</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.defense">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Defense</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
      <textClass xml:id="gen.forensic.tetralogy">
        <keywords>
          <term>Forensic Tetralogy</term>
        </keywords>
      </textClass>
    </profileDesc>

    <revisionDesc>
      <!--
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Put bios and intros to speeches into separate files.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>May 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Change markup in accordance with orator dtd
      </item></change>
      <change><date>June 1992</date>
	<respStmt><name>W. Merrill</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Checkmark
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/7/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>Fixed tetralogy names and div2s again, prior to importing
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>made some corrections to the SGML
      </item></change>
      <change><date>9/8/92</date>
	<respStmt><name>EM</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>also fixed quoted text which had no content, just the attribute.
      </item></change>
      <change><date>15 October 1999</date>
	<respStmt><name>DAS</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
	<item>
$Log: antiph_eng.xml,v $
Revision 1.1  2009-10-07 21:00:37  rsingh04
began reorganizing texts module by collection.  created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files

Revision 1.6  2009/06/22 19:41:56  student
edited entity tags CEH

Revision 1.5  2008/11/21 21:38:13  lcerrato
fixing bad bibls

Revision 1.4  2008/02/13 19:32:23  lcerrato
fixed incorrect bibl tags

Revision 1.3  2006/02/10 21:10:04  packel
places/dates now actually tagged

Revision 1.2  2005/08/01 15:48:40  packel
removed stray item tags

Revision 1.1  2005/07/25 14:27:36  packel
Converted to XML
	
Revision 1.8  2003/07/01 22:14:27  yorkc
Updated texts to TEI P4 and Perseus P4 extensions; minor cleanup (esp. character encodings and typos.)

Revision 1.7  2000/03/04 20:33:52  dasmith
Added separate funder entity to TEI header.

Revision 1.6  2000/01/28 23:23:50  dasmith
Made ID numbers be the tag content.

Revision 1.5  1999/10/15 23:08:23  dasmith
Make sure we get three sections at a time.

Revision 1.4  1999/10/15 21:20:01  dasmith
Converted to TEI P3.


</item></change>
    <change><date>July 2014</date>
    <respStmt><name>Stella Dee</name><resp>ed.</resp></respStmt>
    <item>split speeches and converted to unicode</item>
      </change></change>-->
      <change when="2014-10-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text xml:lang="en">
    <body>
      <div type="tetralogy" n="1">
        <head>First speech for the Prosecution</head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p>It is very rightly laid down that in cases of murder prosecutors must take especial
            care to observe justice in making their charge and presenting their evidence: they must
            neither let the guilty escape nor bring the innocent to trial. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <p>For when God was minded to create the human race and brought the first of us into
            being, he gave us the earth and sea to sustain and serve us, in order that we might not
            die for want of the necessaries of life before old age brought us our end. Such being
            the value placed upon our life by God, whoever unlawfully slays his fellow both sins
            against the gods and confounds the ordinances of man. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="section">
          <p>For the victim, robbed of the gifts bestowed by God upon him, naturally leaves behind
            him the angry spirits of vengeance,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">For the <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">a)lith/rioi</foreign> see General Introduction, p. 39.</note> God's
            instruments of punishment, spirits which they who prosecute and testify without giving
            heed to justice bring into their own homes, defiling them with the defilement of
            another, because they share in the sin of him who did the deed. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="section">
          <p>And similarly, should we, the avengers of the dead, accuse innocent persons because of
            some private grudge, not only will our failure to avenge the murdered man cause us to be
            haunted by dread demons to whom the dead will turn for justice, but by wrongfully
            causing the death of the innocent we are liable to the penalties prescribed for murder,
            and because we have persuaded you to break the law, the responsibility for your mistake
            also becomes ours. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="section">
          <p>For my part, my fear of such consequences has led me to bring the true sinner before
            you, and thus the stain of none of the charges which I am making rests upon me; and if
            you yourselves give that attention to the trial which the considerations I have put
            before you demand, and inflict upon the criminal a punishment proportionate to the
            injury which he has done, you will cleanse the entire city of its defilement. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="section">
          <p>Had he killed his victim accidentally, he would have deserved some measure of mercy.
            But he wantonly committed a brutal assault upon an old man when in his cups; he struck
            him and throttled him until he robbed him of life. So for killing him he is liable to
            penalties prescribed for murder: and for violating every right to respect enjoyed by the
            aged he deserves to suffer in full the punishment usual in such cases. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="section">
          <p>Thus the law rightly hands him over to you for punishment; and you have listened to the
            witnesses who were present during his drunken assault. It is your duty to take vengeance
            for the injury which he so lawlessly inflicted: to punish such brutal violence as
            harshly as the harm which it has caused requires: to deprive him in his turn of a life
            which was used to plot another's death.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="tetralogy" n="2">
        <head>Reply to a Charge of Murder, Arguing that the Accused Killed in Self-Defense</head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p> The fact that their speech was brief does not surprise me: because for them the danger
            is, not that they may come to some harm, but that they may fail to gratify their
            animosity by sending me to a death which I do not deserve. On the other hand, that they
            should want to treat the present matter, in which the victim had himself to blame more
            than me, as a case of the greatest gravity, gives me, I think, some excuse for
            indignation. By resorting to violence as he did and making a drunken assault upon a man
            far more in control of himself than he, he was responsible not only for the disaster
            which befell himself, but for the accusation which has been brought against me. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <p>In my opinion, the prosecution are setting both God and man at defiance in accusing me.
            He was the aggressor; and even if I had used steel or stone or wood to beat him off, I
            was acting within my rights; an aggressor deserves to be answered with, not the same,
            but more and worse than he gave. Actually, when he struck me with his fists, I used my
            own to retaliate for the blows which I received. Was that unjustified? </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="section">
          <p>Well and good. “But,” he will object, “the law which forbids the taking of life whether
            justifiably or not shows you to be liable to the penalty prescribed for murder; for the
            man is dead.” I repeat for a second and a third time that I did not kill him. Had the
            man died on the spot from the blows which he received, his death would have been due to
            me, not but what I would have been justified—an aggressor deserves to be answered with
            not the same, but more and worse than he gave; </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="section">
          <p>—but in fact he died several days later, after being placed under an incompetent
            physician. His death was due to the incompetence of the physician, and not to the blows
            which he received. The other physicians warned him that though he was not beyond cure,
            he would die if he followed this particular treatment. Thanks to your advice, he did
            die, and thereby caused an outrageous charge to be brought against myself. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="section">
          <p>Further, the very law under which I am being accused attests my innocence; it lays down
            that the guilt of a murder shall rest upon that party which acted from design. Now what
            designs could I have on his life which he did not also have on mine? I resisted him with
            his own weapons, and returned blow for blow; so it is clear that I only had the designs
            upon his life which he had on mine. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="section">
          <p>Furthermore, if anyone thinks that his death was the result of the blows which he
            received and that therefore I am his murderer, let him set against that fact that it was
            the aggressor who was the cause of those blows, and that they therefore point to him,
            not to me, as the person responsible for his death; I would not have defended myself
            unless I had been struck by him</p>
          <p>Thus my innocence is attested both by the law and by the fact that my opponent was the
            aggressor; in no way am I his murderer. As to the dead man, if his death was due to
            mischance, he had himself to thank for that mischance: for it consisted in his taking
            the offensive.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">See note on <bibl n="Antiph. 4.3.4"
                >Antiph. 4.3.4</bibl>, ad fin.</note> Similarly, if his death was due to a loss of
            self-control it was through his own loss of self-control that he perished: for he was
            not in his right mind when he struck me. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="section">
          <p>I have now proved that I am unjustly accused. But I wish to prove also that my accusers
            are themselves exposed to all the charges which they are bringing against me. By
            accusing me of murder when I am free from guilt, and by robbing me of the life which God
            bestowed upon me, they are sinning against God by seeking to compass my death
            wrongfully, they are confounding the laws of man and becoming my murderers; and by
            urging you to commit the sin of taking my life, [;they are murdering your consciences
              also];.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">The text of the manuscript is clearly corrupt
              here. <foreign xml:lang="greek">au)toi\</foreign> cannot be right; and <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">fonh=s</foreign> is hardly tolerable after the <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">fonh=s</foreign> of the previous sentence. No satisfactory
              emendation has yet been proposed.</note>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="section">
          <p>May God visit them with the punishment which they deserve. You on your side must look
            to your own interests and be more disposed to acquit than to condemn me. If I am
            acquitted unjustly, if I escape because you have not been properly informed of the
            facts, then it is he who failed to inform you, not you, whom I shall cause to be visited
            by the spirit who is seeking vengeance for the dead. But if I am wrongfully condemned by
            you, then it is upon you, and not upon my accuser, that I shall turn the wrath of the
            avenging demons. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="section">
          <p>In this knowledge, make the prosecution bear the consequences of their sin; cleanse
            yourselves of guilt: and acquit me as righteousness and justice require you to do. Thus
            may all of us citizens best avoid defilement.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="tetralogy" n="3">
        <head>Second Speech for the Prosecution</head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p> I am not surprised that the defendant, who has committed so outrageous a crime, should
            speak as he has acted; just as I pardon you, who are desirous of discovering the facts
            exactly, for tolerating such utterances from his lips as deserve to be greeted with
            derision. Thus, he admits that he gave the man the blows which caused his death; yet he
            not only denies that he himself is the dead man's murderer, but asserts, alive and well
            though he is, that we, who are seeking vengeance for the victim, are his own murderers.
            And I wish to show that the remainder of his defense is of a similar character. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <p>To begin with, he said that even if the man did die as a result of the blows, he did
            not kill him: because it is the aggressor who is to blame for what happens: it is he
            whom the law condemns; and the aggressor was the dead man. First, let me tell you that
            young men are more likely to be the aggressors and make a drunken assault than old. The
            young are incited by their natural arrogance<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign
                xml:lang="greek">h( megalofrosu/nh tou= ge/nous</foreign> ought to mean “pride of
              birth”: but the speaker is not limiting his remarks to young aristocrats. <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">ge/nos</foreign> must be used in the sense of “class” or
              “type.”</note> their full vigor, and the unaccustomed effects of wine to give free
            play to anger: whereas old men are sobered by their experience of drunken excesses, by
            the weakness of age, and by their fear of the strength of the young. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="section">
          <p>Further, it was not with the same, but with vastly different weapons that the accused
            withstood him, as the facts themselves show. The one used hands which were in the
            fullness of their strength, and with them he slew; whereas the other defended himself
            but feebly against a stronger man, and died without leaving any mark of that defense
            behind him. Moreover, if it was with his hands and not with steel that the defendant
            slew, then the fact that his hands are more a part of himself than is steel makes him so
            much the more a murderer. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="section">
          <p>He further dared to assert that he who struck the first blow, even though he did not
            slay, is more truly the murderer than he who killed; for it is to the aggressor's wilful
            act that the death was due, he says. But I maintain the very opposite. If our hands
            carry out the intentions of each of us, he who struck without killing was the wilful
            author of the blow alone: the willfull author of the death was he who struck and killed:
            for it was as the result of an intentional act on the part of the defendant that the man
            was killed.</p>
          <p>Again, while the victim suffered the ill-effect of the mischance, it is the striker who
            suffered the mischance itself; for the one met his death as the result of the other's
            act, so that it was not through his own mistake, but through the mistake of the man who
            struck him, that he was killed; whereas the other did more than he meant to do, and he
            had only himself to blame for the mischance whereby he killed a man whom he did not mean
            to slay.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A reply to the arguments of the defense in <bibl
                n="Antiph. 4.2.6">Antiph. 4.2.6</bibl>. The terms <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >a)tuxi/a, a(marti/a</foreign>, and <foreign xml:lang="greek">sumfora/</foreign>
              represent the logically distinguishable elements which constitute an “unfortunate
              accident.” Owing to <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)tuxi/a</foreign> the agent commits an
              error (<foreign xml:lang="greek">a(marti/a</foreign>), i.e. performs an act which he
              either had no intention of performing at all or intended to perform differently, and
              the result is a <foreign xml:lang="greek">sumfora/</foreign>, which may fall either
              upon the agent himself or upon some second person. In the present paragraph it is
              assumed for the moment, as it had been assumed by the defense in <bibl
                n="Antiph. 4.2.6">Antiph. 4.2.6</bibl>, that death was purely accidental.
              Blood-guilt will still rest upon one of the two parties: but it will rest on the party
              guilty of <foreign xml:lang="greek">a(marti/a</foreign> (cf. <bibl n="Antiph. 3.1"
                >Antiph. 3</bibl>, <title>Tetralogy II</title>). Now the defense had argued in <bibl
                n="Antiph. 4.2.6">Antiph. 4.2.6</bibl> that X, the aggressor, had been responsible
              for the <foreign xml:lang="greek">a(marti/a</foreign>; it had consisted in his taking
              the offensive: and he was <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)tuxh/s</foreign> in doing so.
              The resultant <foreign xml:lang="greek">sumfora/</foreign> had fallen upon himself.
              The prosecution here replies that while the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >sumfora/</foreign> indeed fell on X, the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >a)tuxi/a</foreign> and the <foreign xml:lang="greek">a(marti/a</foreign> lay with
              Y, because Y had given a harder blow than he intended.</note>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="section">
          <p>I am surprised that, in alleging the man's death to have been due to the
              physician,<note anchored="true" resp="ed">If the <foreign xml:lang="greek"
                >ou)x</foreign> of the manuscripts is retained, we have a flat contradiction of
                <bibl n="Antiph. 4.2.4">Antiph. 4.2.4</bibl>, where the defense does in fact accuse
              the prosecution of having caused the man's death. Further, the argument of the present
              paragraph becomes exceedingly elliptical. It will presumably run thus: “The defendant
              accuses the physician; but he ought logically to accuse us instead. He would
              undoubtedly have accused us of having been responsible for the man's death through
              neglect, had we not sought medical aid at all; so he should similarly accuse us of
              murder, if we sent the patient to a bad physician instead of a good one.” If the
                <foreign xml:lang="greek">ou)x</foreign> is deleted, we get consistency with <bibl
                n="Antiph. 4.2.4">Antiph. 4.2.4</bibl>, and the argument is as in the text. <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">ou)x</foreign> was probably inserted by a reader who thought that
              the first sentence of 5 was self-contradictory. Note that this first sentence
                (<foreign xml:lang="greek">u(po\ de\ . . . diafqarh=nai</foreign>) does not imply
              merely that the defense have contradicted themselves by accusing first the physician
              and then the prosecution; this is clear from the <foreign xml:lang="greek">kai\ ga\r
                a)\n ktl.</foreign> which follows, giving the true reason for the speaker's
              surprise.</note> he should assign responsibility for it to us, upon whose advice it
            was that he received medical attention; for had we failed to place him under a
            physician, the defendant would assuredly have maintained that his death was due to
            neglect. But even if his death was due to the physician, which it was not, the physician
            is not his murderer, because the law absolves him from blame. On the other hand, as it
            was only owing to the blows given by the defendant that we placed the dead man under
            medical care at all, can the murderer be anyone save him who forced us to call in the
            physician? </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="section">
          <p>Although it has been proved so clearly and so completely that he killed the dead man,
            his impudence and shamelessness are such that he is not content with defending his own
            act of wickedness: he actually accuses us, who are seeking expiation of the defilement
            which rests upon him, of acting like unscrupulous scoundrels. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="section">
          <p>Assertions as outrageous as this, or even more so, befit one guilty of such a crime as
            he. We, on our side, have clearly established how the death took place: we have shown
            that there are no doubts about the blow which caused it: and we have proved that the law
            fixes the guilt of the murder upon him who gave that blow. So in the name of the victim
            we charge you to appease the wrath of the spirits of vengeance by putting the defendant
            to death, and thereby cleanse the whole city of its defilement.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div type="tetralogy" n="4">
        <head>Second Speech for the Defense</head>
        <div n="1" type="section">
          <p>The defendant, not because he has judged himself guilty, but because he was alarmed by
            the vehemence the prosecution, has withdrawn.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">A touch of
              realism. It was recognized that the defendant in a <foreign xml:lang="greek">di/kh
                fo/nou</foreign> had the right of withdrawing into exile half-way through the trial,
              if he saw no hope of an acquittal. Cf. <title>Herodes</title>, Introduction.</note> As
            to us, his friends, we are discharging our sacred duty to him more fitly by aiding him
            while he is alive than by aiding him after he is dead. Admittedly, he himself would have
            pleaded his own case best; but since the present course appeared the safer, it remains
            for us, to whom his loss would be a very bitter grief, to defend him. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="2" type="section">
          <p>To my mind, it is with the aggressor that the blame for the deed rests. Now the
            presumptions from which the prosecution argues that the defendant was the aggressor are
            unreasonable. If brutal violence on the part of the young and self-control on the part
            of the old were as natural as seeing with the eyes and hearing with the ears, then there
            would be no need for you to sit in judgement; the young would stand condemned by their
            mere age. In fact, however, many young men are self-controlled, and many old men are
            violent in their cups; and so the presumption which they furnish favors the defense no
            less than the prosecution. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="3" type="section">
          <p>As the presumption supports us as much as it does the dead man, the balance is in our
            favor; for according to the witnesses, it was he who was the aggressor. This being so,
            the defendant is cleared of all the other charges brought against him as well. For once
            it is argued that, because it was only the blow given by the striker which obliged you
            to seek medical attention at all, the murderer is the striker rather than the person
            immediately responsible for the man's death,<note anchored="true" resp="ed"><foreign
                xml:lang="greek">tou= a)poktei/nantos</foreign> is of course the physician.</note>
            it follows that the murderer was he who struck the very first blow of all: because it
            was he who compelled both his adversary to strike back in self-defense and the victim
            struck to go to the physician. It would be outrageous, were the defendant, who was
            neither slayer nor aggressor, to be held a murderer in place of the true slayer and the
            true aggressor. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="4" type="section">
          <p>Nor again is the intention to kill to be attributed to the accused rather than to his
            accuser. If it had been the case that, whereas he who struck the first blow had meant
            not to kill, but to strike, he who was defending himself had meant to kill, then it
            would have been this last who was guilty of the intention to kill. As it was, he who was
            defending himself likewise intended to strike, not to kill; but he committed an error,
            and struck where he did not mean to strike. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="5" type="section">
          <p>He was thus admittedly the wilful author of the blow; how can he have killed
            willfully,when he struck otherwise than he intended?</p>
          <p>Further, it is with the aggressor rather than with him who was defending himself that
            the responsibiIity for the error itself rests. The one was seeking to retaliate for the
            blows which he was receiving, when he committed his error: he was being forced to act by
            his attacker; whereas with the other, it was his own lack of self-control which caused
            him to give and receive the blows which he did: and so, since he is responsible both for
            his own error and for his victim's, he deserves the name of murderer. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="6" type="section">
          <p>Again, his defense was not more vigorous than the attack made upon him, but much less
            so: as I will show. The one was truculent, drunken, and violent; he took the offensive
            throughout, and was never on the defensive at all. The other was seeking to avoid blows
            and repel him; the blows which he received, he received from no choice of his own and
            the blows which he gave were given in defense of himself against the aggressor, and much
            less vigorously than that aggressor deserved, because his only object was to avoid the
            hurt which was being done to him; he did not take the offensive at all. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="7" type="section">
          <p>Even supposing that his defense was more vigorous than the attack made upon him,
            because there was more vigor in his hands, you cannot justly condemn him. Heavy
            penalties are invariably provided for the aggressor: whereas no penalty is ever
            prescribed for him who defends himself. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="8" type="section">
          <p>The objection that the taking of life, whether justifiably or not, is forbidden, has
            been answered; it was not to the blows, but to the physician, that the man's death was
            due, as the witnesses state in their evidence. Further, it is the aggressor, and not he
            who was defending himself, who was responsible for the accident. The one gave and
            received the blows which he did from no choice of his own, and therefore the accident in
            which he had a part was not of his own causing. The other did what he did of his own
            free will, and it was by his own actions that he brought the accident upon himself;
            hence he had himself to blame for the mischance whereby he committed his error. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="9" type="section">
          <p>It has been shown, then, that not one of the charges made concerns the defendant; and
            even if both parties are thought equally responsible alike for the actual crime and for
            the mischance which led to it, and it is decided from the arguments put forward that
            there is no more reason for acquitting the defendant than for condemning him, he still
            has a right to be acquitted rather than condemned. Not only is it unjust that his
            accuser should secure his conviction without clearly showing that he has been wronged:
            but it is a sin that the accused should be sentenced, if the charges made against him
            have not been proved conclusively. </p>
        </div>
        <div n="10" type="section">
          <p>As the defendant has been cleared so completely of the charges made, we lay upon you in
            his name a more righteous behest than did our opponents: in seeking to punish the
            murderer, do not put him who is blameless to death. If you do, [;the slayer no less than
            the slain will bring the wrath of heaven upon the guilty:];<note anchored="true"
              resp="ed">There is clearly some corruption here. Some reference is wanted to the the
              spirits of vengeance who will continue to haunt the guilty until due reparation has
              been made to the dead. See app. crit.</note> and if the defendant is put to death
            without scruple, he causes the defilement brought upon his slayers by the spirits of
            vengeance to become twofold.<note anchored="true" resp="ed">Briegleb's <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">mh/nima</foreign> is unnecessary. It is clear from <bibl
                n="Antiph. 4.1.3">Antiph. 4.1.3</bibl> sub fin. that the writer felt the <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">dusme/neia tw=n a)lithri/wn</foreign> and the <foreign
                xml:lang="greek">mi/asma fo/nou</foreign> to be complementary aspects of one and the
              some thing. The <foreign xml:lang="greek">a)lith/rioi</foreign> were the positive
              forces which gave effect to the <foreign xml:lang="greek">mi/asma</foreign>. Hence
              such a phrase as <foreign xml:lang="greek">mi/asma tw=n a)lithri/wn</foreign> in the
              present passage is perfectly orthodox; it is the “pollution to which the spirits of
              vengeance give expression.”</note>
          </p>
        </div>
        <div n="11" type="section">
          <p>Hold that defilement in fear: and consider your duty to absolve him who is guiltless.
            Him upon whom the stain of blood rests you may let time reveal, even as you may leave
            his punishment to his victim's kin. It is thus that you will best serve justice and the
            will of heaven.</p>
        </div>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
