<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">Toxaris, or Friendship</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor>Austin Morris Harmon, 1878-1950</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<resp>OCRd, tagged and added initial corrections to  the text</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg001.1st1K-eng1.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:1lg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1936</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">5</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/osu.32435024202111">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" xml:lang="eng">
<head>Toxaris, or Friendship<note><p>A conversation between Toxaris, a Scythian, and Mnesippus,
a Greek, on the subject of friendship. Toxaris explains that
the memory of Orestes and Pylades is honoured in Scythia
despite the havoc they wrought there because the Scythians
regard them as models of loyal friendship, which they hold in
the highest esteem. The Greeks, he thinks, are better nowadays at praising than at practising it. To settle the question
of superiority, Mnesippus tells five stories of Greek loyalty,
and Toxaris five of Scythian: all are declared on oath to be
authentic and recent happenings. The outcome, however,
can only be a draw because no umpire has been appointed,
and the two swear friendship with each other.</p>

<p>
The stories, then, are the thing, and the dialogue is just a
framing-tale in which to display them. Its time is present.
Toxaris, therefore, has nothing but the name in common with
the Toxaris whom Lucian in his Scythian (Vol. VI) represents
to have come to Athens before Anacharsis and to have
received worship there after death as the Hero-Physician.
Yet this Toxaris too has visited Athens and lived long among
the Greeks. The dialogue takes place somewhere in Hellas,
but the scene is not definitely fixed. The manner of the
allusion to Athens in § 21 seems to exclude that city. The
diction of the piece suggests a relatively early date. It
may have been written about a.d. 163 in Asia.</p>

<p>
The oaths of Toxaris and Mnesippus attest Lucian’s
mastery of the stock devices of a story-teller rather than the
authenticity of his tales. Most of his stories, both Scythian
and Greek, are probable enough to be founded on fact.
Several are notably romantic, and were probably either made
up by Lucian or borrowed from current romances, in which
the hero usually had a friend as well as a sweetheart (cf.
A. Calderini, Caritone di Afrodisia, pp. 104-106). In the
matter of Scythia his dependence on literary sources has
been indicated by Rostovtzeff (Skythien und der Bosporus,
pp. 96-99), who has pointed out that his background is
realistic and plausible in its general effect, but inaccurate in
historical and. geographic details, and argues that he drew
extensively upon Greek novels with a Scythian plot.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
What about it, Toxaris? Do you Scythians
sacrifice to Orestes and Pylades, and have you come
to believe that they are gods?
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
We sacrifice, Mnesippus, we sacrifice; not, however, because we think them gods, but good men.<note n="v.5.p.103.n.1"><p>The existence of a cult of Orestes and Pylades in Scythia is not otherwise attested, and is credible only in a limited sense, as a local development of Greek hero-worship; see below, on the Oresteum, § 6. </p></note>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Is it your custom to sacrifice to good men when
they are dead, as if they were gods?
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
Not only that, but we honour them with festivals
and pilgrimages.
</p>
<p><label>MNESIPPUS</label>
What do you crave from them? For surely it is
not to gain their grace that you sacrifice to them, in
view of the fact that they are dead.


<pb n="v.5.p.105"/>

<label>TOXARIS</label>
Well, we should be none the worse off, perhaps,
if even the dead should be gracious to us. However,
we think it will be better for the living if we do
not forget men of high achievement, and we honour
them after death because we consider that in this
way we can get many to wish to become like them.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="2"><p>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
In that matter, to be sure, your judgement is
sound. But as regards Orestes and Pylades, on
just what ground did you so admire them, that you
have put them on a parity with the gods, and that
too when they were trespassers upon your soil and—
what is most significant—enemies? Why, when the
Scythians of that day seized them after their shipwreck and dragged them off intending to sacrifice
them to Artemis, they set upon the keepers of their
prison, overpowered the watch, and not only slew
the king but carried off the priestess,<note n="v.5.p.105.n.1"><p>Both here and below in § 6 Lucian omits as self-understood the point that Orestes discovers the priestess to be his sister Iphigenia, previously thought to have perished at Aulis under the sacrificial knife. </p></note> nay even kidnapped Artemis herself, and then went. sailing
away, after having made a mock of the Scythian
commonwealth.<note n="v.5.p.105.n.2"><p>In the point that this version of the story makes the Greeks escape by overpowering the Scythians and killing Thoas, their king, it differs significantly both from Euripides in the Iphigenia among the Taurians and from Sophocles in the Chryses, in which Thoas was killed, to be sure, but only after they had somehow got away and he had overtaken them at “Sminthe,” whose ruler, Chryses, turning out to be the son of Agamemnon and Chryseis, and so the half-brother of Orestes and Iphigenia, aids them to kill their pursuer. Elsewhere in extant ancient literature the Lucianic version is found only in Servius and in accounts derived from him (Serv. in Aen., II, 216; cf. [Hyginus], 261, and Mythogr. Vat., II, 202). It may have been the accepted version of the cult of Diana at Aricia (Preller, Robert), but cannot be of Latin origin. It is surely the early version, effaced in the literary tradition by the influence of Euripides, but perpetuated (as early myths often were) in art through a painting by some famous Hellenistic master, later reflected not only in Graeco- Roman sarcophagus-reliefs but in the murals of some Graeco- Scythian Oresteum (§6). Lucian’s knowledge of it may safely be ascribed to an allusion to those murals in the literary source from which he derives the curious mixture of fact and fiction in § 6. </p></note> So if that is why you honour those




<pb n="v.5.p.107"/>

heroes, you will very soon produce many like them!
Draw the conclusion for yourselves in the light of
what happened of old whether it is desirable for you
that many an Orestes and Pylades should descend
upon Scythia. To me it seems that very soon, under
those conditions, you would become irreligious yourselves, yes, godless, after the remainder of your gods
had been similarly shipped out of the country to
foreign parts. And then, I suppose, in place of the
whole company of gods, you will deify the men who
came to obtain them for export and will sacrifice
to the robbers of your temples as gods!
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="3"><p>
If that is not why you honour Orestes and Pylades,
do tell me, Toxaris, what other benefit have they
done you to bring it about that although formerly
you deemed them anything but gods, now, on the
contrary, you have made them pass for gods by
sacrificing to them, and you now bring victims to
men who at that time very nearly became victims ?
This conduct, you know, might be thought ridiculous
and inconsistent with that of former times.
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
As a matter of fact, Mnesippus, even these actions
that you have described evince nobility in those
men. That two should dare so bold a deed; that
they should sail so far from their own country as to
cruise out into the Pontus (still unexplored by any
of the Greeks except the force that fared upon the
Argo to Colchis) undismayed either by the fables
regarding it or by its name through any terror
inspired by the fact that it was called ‘ Inhospitable” (I suppose because savage peoples dwelt

<pb n="v.5.p.109"/>

all about it);<note n="v.5.p.109.n.1"><p>According to Apollodorus (Strabo, VII, 298-299) the Pontus was at first called Azeinos (“Inhospitable”) because of its storminess and the ferocity of the tribes that surrounded it; later, after the Ionian settlements on its coast, it was called Huxeinos (“Hospitable”). Pindar knows both names (Pyth., IV, 203; Nem. IV, 49). </p></note> that after their capture they faced
the situation so courageously, and were not content
simply to make their escape but punished the king
for his insolence and took Artemis with them when
they sailed away—why is not all this admirable and
worthy of divine honour in some sort from all who
praise manhood? Yet that is not what we see in
Orestes and Pylades, to treat them as heroes.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="4"><p>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Please go on and say what else they did that
is imposing and godlike ; since as far as concerns their
voyage and their foreign travel I could point you
many who are more godlike than they—the merchant
traders, and particularly the Phoenicians among
them, who not only sail into the Pontus or as far as
Lake Maeotis and the Cimmerian Bosporus,<note n="v.5.p.109.n.2"><p>The Sea of Azov and the Straits of Kertsch. </p></note> but
cruise everywhere in Greek and foreign waters; for
these fellows comb every single shore and every strand,
you may say, each year before returning late in the
autumn to their own country. On the same principle,
you should account them gods, even though most of
them are pedlars and, it may be, fishmongers !

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
<label>TOXARIS</label>
Listen then, you amazing fellow, and learn how
much more generously than you Greeks we barbarians judge good men. In Argos and Mycenae
there is not even a respectable tomb of Orestes or



<pb n="v.5.p.111"/>

Pylades to be seen, but among us a temple has been
assigned them, to both together, as was reasonable
since they were comrades, and sacrifices are offered
them, and all sorts of honours besides. The fact
that they were not Scythians but foreigners is no
hindrance to their having been accounted good men
and their being cherished by the foremost Scythians ;
for we do not enquire what country proper men come
from, nor do we bear a grudge if men who are not
friendly have done noble deeds; we commend what
they have accomplished and count them our own in
virtue of their achievements.
What especially impressed us in these men and
gains our commendation is this: it seemed to us
that as friends they, surely, had proved themselves
the best in the world, and had established precedents
for everyone else in regard to the way in which
friends should share all their fortunes.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
All that the
went through in each other’s company or for eac
other’s sake our ancestors inscribed on a tablet of
bronze which they set up in the Oresteum;<note n="v.5.p.111.n.1"><p>Nothing could be more natural than for some Graeco- Scythian city in South Russia (Crimea?) to have had an Oresteum like this, with a set of murals commemorating the exploits of Orestes and Pylades. Indeed, the existence of the paintings is practically guaranteed by two considerations: they represent a version of the story of Orestes among the Taurians that is not known to us prior to Lucian except in art; and that version, involving as it does his killing of the king, is not likely to have been preferred to the Euripidean by Lucian for his present purpose, if the paintings were imaginary. Here there seems to be a core of fact which Lucian can have derived only from some previous writer; and we may perhaps also safely believe that the deified heroes obtained sufficient prestige among the native part of the population of the city and its environs to gain them a Scythian name (Korakoi: §7 end). Compare the Herodotean tale (IV, 103) of the worship of Iphigenia among the Taurians. This kernel of fact, however, has been enveloped in a hull of fiction by transporting the sanctuary to a mythical Scythian capital without a name and making it the focus of a great national cult of friendship—a happy conceit in view of the custom of swearing “blood-brotherhood” (§ 37), but sheer fiction none the less. It is perhaps possible that Lucian drew the fact from some Hellenistic AListorian and supplied the fiction himself; but it is more likely that he found both already combined in his source, and connected with one or more of the tales of Scythian friendship that he puts into the mouth of Toxaris (cf. especially p. 173, n. 2). </p></note> and they
made it the law that the first study and lesson for



<pb n="v.5.p.113"/>

their children should be this tablet and the memorising of all that had been written upon it. In point
of fact, every one of them would sooner forget the
name of his own father than fail to know the achievements of Orestes and Pylades.
But in the temple close, too, the very same matters
that are set forth on the tablet are to be seen represented in paintings by the ancients; Orestes voyaging with his friend, and then, after his ship had been
destroyed on the rocks, his arrest and preparation
for the sacrifice; Iphigenia is already consecrating
them. Opposite this, on the other wall, he is
depicted as just out of his fetters, slaying Thoas
and many more of the Scythians. Finally, they are
sailing off, with Iphigenia and the goddess; the
Scythians meanwhile are vainly laying hold of the
ship, which is already under way, hanging to the
rudders and trying to get aboard; then, unable to
accomplish anything, they swim back to land, some
of them because they are wounded, others for fear
of that. It is just there that one may see how much
good-will they displayed in each other’s interest;
I mean, in the engagement with the Scythians.
For the artist has portrayed each of them paying
no heed to the foemen opposite himself, but encountering those who are assailing the other, trying to meet
their missiles in his stead, and counting it nothing
to die if he saves his friend and intercepts with his
own body the stroke that is being directed at the
other.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
That great good-will of theirs, that common front
amid those perils, that faithfulness and comradely


<pb n="v.5.p.115"/>

love, that genuineness and solidity of their affection
for one another were not, we thought, of this world,
but marked a spirit too noble for these men about
us of the common sort, who, as long as the course of
their friends is with the wind, take it ill if they do
not give them an equal share in all their delights,
but if even a slight breath sets against them, they
bear away, entirely abandoning them to their perils.
For I would have you know this also—Scythians
think that there is nothing greater than friendship,
and there is not anything upon which a Scythian
will pride himself more than on aiding a friend and
sharing his dangers, just as there is no greater disgrace among us than to bear the name of having
played false to friendship. That is why we honour
Orestes and Pylades, because they practised best
what Scythians hold good, and excelled in friendship, an achievement which we admire before all
things else; in token whereof we have given them
the name of Korakoi to go by, which in our language
is as much as to say “guiding spirits of friendship.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Toxaris, it has turned out that Scythians are not
only good archers and better than all others in warfare, but the most convincing of all peoples at making
speeches. Anyhow, I, who formerly had a different
opinion, now myself think you do right in thus deifying
Orestes and Pylades. And I had failed, my accomplished friend, to grasp the fact that you are also a
good painter. Very animated indeed was the sketch


<pb n="v.5.p.117"/>

that you drew for us of the pictures in the Oresteum,
of the fighting of your heroes, and the wounds that
each bore for the other. However, I should not
have expected friendship to be so highly cherished
among the Scythians, for as they are inhospitable
and uncivilised I thought that they always were
well acquainted with hatred, anger, and bad humour
but did not enter into friendship even with their
closest kin, judging by all that we hear about them,
and especially the report that they eat their dead
fathers!<note n="v.5.p.117.n.1"><p>Alluded to also in Funerals, 21 (IV, p. 126). Cf. Herodotus, IV, 26 (of the Issedones), and I, 216 (of the Massagetae). </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="9"><p>
<label>TOXARIS</label>
Whether we are in general not only more just
than the Greeks towards our parents but more
reverential is a question which I would rather not
debate with you at present. But that Scythian
friends are far more faithful than Greek friends
and that friendship matters more with us than with
you is easily demonstrated; and in the name of your
Gods of Greece, do not listen to me with displeasure
if I mention one of the observations which I have
made after having lived with your people for a long
time now.
It seems to me that you Greeks can indeed say
all that is to be said about friendship better than
others, but not only fail to practise its works in a
manner that befits your words,—no, you are content
to have praised it and shown what a very good thing
it is, but in its times of need you play traitor to
your words about it and beat a hasty retreat, somehow or other, out of the press of deeds. And whenever your tragedians put friendships of this kind on


<pb n="v.5.p.119"/>

the stage and exhibit them to you, you bestow
praise and applause, yes, even tears upon them,
most of you, when they face danger for each other’s
sake; yet you yourselves dare not come out with
any praiseworthy deed for the sake of your friends.
On the contrary, if a friend happens to stand in need
of anything, those many tragic histories take wing
and vanish from your path on the instant, like
dreams, and leave you looking like those empty,
silent masks which, for all their open mouths, widely
agape, do not utter even the slightest sound. We
are your opposites; for we have as much the better
of you in practising friendship as we fall short of
you in talking about it.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="10"><p>
If you like, then, let us do this; let us leave the
friends of former times to rest in peace, whomsoever, I mean, of the ancients either we or you are
able to enumerate; for there, to be sure, you would
outdo us by citing many trustworthy witnesses,
your poets, who have rehearsed in the most beautiful
of epic lines and lyric verses the friendship of Achilles
and Patroclus and the comradeship of Theseus,
Peirithous, and all the rest. Instead, let us take up
just a few of our own contemporaries and recount
their deeds, I for the Scythian side, you for the
Greek; then whichever of us wins in this by bringing out better = of friendship shall not only
be adjudged victor himself but shall be allowed to
name his country in the proclamation, inasmuch as
he will have taken part in a right glorious and
noble contest. For my own part, I think I would


<pb n="v.5.p.121"/>

much rather be defeated in single combat and have
my right hand cut off, which is the penalty for defeat
in Scythia, than to be pronounced inferior to anyone
else in the matter of friendship, and above all to a
Greek, when I am myself a Scythian.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
It is no mean undertaking, Toxaris, to engage in
single combat with a man-at-arms like yourself,
equipped with very accurate and well-sharpened
shafts of speech. Nevertheless, I shall not so
ignobly betray of a sudden the whole Greek cause
as to yield you the field. It would be shocking if,
when they two defeated as many Scythians as are
indicated by the stories and by those ancient paintings in your country which you described with such
histrionic expressiveness a little while ago, all the
Greeks, including so many peoples and so many
cities, should lose by default to you alone. If
that should take place, it would be fitting for me
to be docked, not of my right hand, as your people
are, but of my tongue. But ought we to set ourselves a limit to the number of these exploits of
friendship, or should we hold that the more of
them a man can tell, the better off he is as regards
the victory ?
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
By no means; let us prescribe that the victory
does not in this case reside with the greater numbers.
No, if yours turn out to be better and more telling
‘than mine, though equal in number, they will
obviously inflict more serious wounds upon me and
I shall succumb to your blows more quickly.

<pb n="v.5.p.123"/>

<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
You are right, so let us settle how many will do.
Five, I should think, for each. .
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
I think so too; and you may speak first, after
taking oath that you will assuredly tell the truth.
Merely to make up such tales is not at all hard, and
there is no obvious means of disproof. But if you
should take your oath, it would not be right to
disbelieve you.
</p>
<p><label>MNESIPPUS</label>
We shall do so, if you really think an oath is
at all essential. But which of our gods will satisfy
you? Zeus Philios?
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
Yes indeed; and I will take the oath of my own
country for you when I myself speak.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Well then, as Zeus Philios is my witness, I solemnly
swear that whatever I shall tell you I will say either
from my own knowledge or from information obtained
of others with all the accuracy that was possible,
without contributing any dramaturgy on my own part.
And the first friendship of which I shall give you
an account is that of Agathocles and Deinias, which
has become far-famed among the Ionians.
Agathocles of Samos, to whom I refer, lived not
long ago, and was peerless in friendship, as he
proved, but otherwise not at all superior to the
general run of Samians qjther in family or in means.

<pb n="v.5.p.125"/>

He and Deinias, the son of Lyson, of Ephesus,
were friends from their boyhood. But Deinias
turned out to be enormously rich; and as was
natural in one whose wealth was new, he had many
others about him who were well enough as boon
companions and agreeable associates, but as far as
could be from friends.</p>

<p>
Well, for a time Agathocles was put to the test
among them, associating with them and drinking
with them, though he took little pleasure in that
kind of pastime; and Deinias held him in no higher
esteem than his toadies. But at length Agathocles
began to give offence by rebuking him frequently,
and. came to be considered a nuisance by reminding
him always of his ancestors and admonishing him
to keep what his father had acquired with much
labour and left to him. Consequently Deinias no
longer even took him along when he caroused about
the town, but used to go alone with those others,
trying to escape the eye of Agathocles.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="13"><p>
In course of time those flatterers persuaded the
poor fellow that Charicleia was in love with him.
She was the wife of Demonax, a distinguished man,
foremost among the Ephesians in public affairs.
Notes from the woman kept coming into his house ;
also, half-faded wreaths, apples with a piece bitten
out, and every other contrivance with which gobetweens lay siege to young men, gradually working up their love-affairs for them and inflaming them
at the start with the thought that they are adored
(for this is extremely seductive, especially to those
who think themselves handsome), until they fall
unawares into the net.</p>

<p>
Charicleia was a dainty piece of femininity, but

<pb n="v.5.p.127"/>

outrageously meretricious, giving herself to anyone
who happened to meet her, even if he should want
her at very little cost; if you but looked at her, she
nodded at once, and there was no fear that Charicleia
might perhaps be reluctant. She was clever too, in
every way, and an artist comparable with any
courtesan you please at alluring a lover, bringing
him into complete subjection when he was still of
two minds, and when at last he was in her toils
working him up and fanning his flame, now by anger,
now by flattery, soon by scorn and by pretending to
have an inclination for someone else. She was every
bit of her thoroughly sophisticated, that woman, and
plentifully armed with siege-engines to train upon
her lovers.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
This, then, was the ally whom Deinias’ toadies
at that time enlisted against the boy, and they constantly played up to rer lead, unitedly thrusting
him into the affair with Charicleia. And she, who
already had given many young fellows a bad fall,
* who, times without number, had played at being in
love, who had ruined vast estates, versatile and
thoroughly practised mischief-maker that she was—
once she got into her clutches a simple youngster who
had no experience of such enginery, she would not
let him out of her talons but encompassed him all
round about and pierced him through and through,
until, when at last she had him wholly in her power,
she not only lost her own life through her quarry
but caused poor Deinias misfortunes without end.</p>

<p>
From the very first she kept baiting him with
those notes, sending her maid continually, making
out that she had cried, that she had lain awake,


<pb n="v.5.p.129"/>

and at last that she would hang herself for love,
poor girl, until the blessed simpleton became convinced that he was handsome and adored by the
women of Ephesus, and of course made a rendezvous
after many entreaties.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="15"><p>

After that, naturally, it
was bound to be an easy matter for him to be captured by a beautiful woman, who knew how to
please him with her company, to weep on occasion,
to sigh piteously in the midst of her conversation, to
lay hold of him when he was at last going away,
to run up to him when he came in, to adorn herself
in the way that would best please him, and of course
to sing and to strum the lyre.</p>

<p>
All this she had brought into play against Deinias ;
and then, when she discerned that he was in a bad
way, having by that time become thoroughly permeated with love and pliable, she employed another
artifice to complete the poor boy’s undoing. She pretended to be with child by him (this too is an effective
way to fire a sluggish lover); moreover, she discontinued her visits to him, saying that she was
kept in by her husband, who had found out about
their affair.
</p>

<p>
Deinias was now unable to bear the situation and
could not endure not seeing her. He wept, he sent
his toadies, he called upon the name of Charicleia,
he embraced her statue (having had one of marble
made for him), he wailed; at last he flung himself
on the ground and rolled about, and his condition
was absolute insanity. Naturally, the gifts which
he exchanged for hers were not on a par with apples
and wreaths, but whole apartment-houses, farms,
and serving-women, gay clothing, and all the gold
that she wanted.


<pb n="v.5.p.131"/>

Why make a long story of it? In a trice the
estate of Lyson, which had been the most famous
in Ionia, was completely pumped out and exhausted.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
And then, when at last he was drained dry, she
left him, pursued another gilded youth from Crete,
and went over to him; now she loved him, and he
put faith in it.
Neglected not only by Charicleia but by the
toadies, for they too had now gone over to the
Cretan whom she loved, Deinias sought out Agathocles, who had long known that things were going
badly with him. Though overcome with shame at
first, nevertheless he told the whole story—his
passion, his desperate straits, the woman’s disregard, the Cretan rival—and in conclusion said
that he would not remain alive if he could not
have Charicleia. Agathocles thought it unseasonable at that moment to remind Deinias that he used
never to be glad to see him, and him only, of all
his friends, but used always to give preference to
his toadies in those days. So he sold all that he
had, the house that he had inherited in Samos,
and came back bringing him the price, three talents.
When Deinias received this, it was at once patent
to Charicleia that in some way he had once more
become handsome. Again the maid, and the notes,
and reproof because he had not come for a long
while; and the toadies came running up to dangle
a line for him, seeing that Deinias was still good for
a meal.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="17"><p>
But when he had promised to come to her,
had actually come, in the early hours of the night,
and was inside the house, Demonax, the husband
of Charicleia, whether through accidental detection
of him or through arrangement with his wife—both

<pb n="v.5.p.133"/>

stories are told—springing out upon him as if from
ambush, gave orders to lock the outer door and to
seize Deinias, threatening him with burning and
scourging and coming at him with drawn sword,
as an adulterer.</p>

<p>
Perceiving what a calamitous situation he was in,
Deinias seized a bar that lay near and killed not
only Demonax himself, striking him on the temple,
but also Charicleia, not with one blow in her case, but
by striking her first with the bar again and again
and afterwards with the sword of Demonax. The
servants stood speechless in the meantime, dazed
by the suddenness of the thing; then they tried to
seize him, but when he made at them too with the
sword, they fled, and Deinias made good his escape
in spite of his monstrous deed.</p>

<p>
The time that remained until dawn he spent with
Agathocles in going over all that had happened and
considering what would come of it in future. At
dawn the magistrates appeared, for by then the
thing had been noised abroad; they arrested
Deinias, who himself did not deny that he had
committed the murders, and brought him before the
Salariae’ who then administered Asia. He sent
im to the Emperor, and before long Deinias was
committed to the island of Gyaros, one of the
Cyclades, condemned by the Emperor to live there
in perpetual exile.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="18"><p>
Agathocles alone of all his friends kept with him,
sailed with him to Italy, went to the trial with him,
and failed him in nothing. Moreover, when at
length Deinias went into exile, he did not desert his
comrade even then, but of his own accord sentenced
himself to live in Gyaros and share his exile; and

<pb n="v.5.p.135"/>

when they were completely in want of necessities,
he joined the purple-fishers, dived with them, brought
home what he earned by this, and so supported
Deinias. Besides, when the latter fell ill, he took care
of him for a very long time, and when he died, did
not care to return again to his own country, but
remained there in the island, ashamed to desert his
friend even after his death.</p>

<p>
There you have the deed of a Greek friend which
took place not long ago; I hardly think five years
have passed since Agathocles died in Gyaros.
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
I do wish, Mnesippus, you had told this story
without taking an oath, so that I might have been
able to disbelieve it, for this Agathocles whom you
have described is very much of a Scythian friend.
However, I have no fear that you will be able to
name any other like him.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Listen then, Toxaris, to the tale of another,
Euthydicus of Chalcis. It was repeated to me
by Simylus, the sea-captain of Megara, who took his
solemn oath that he himself had seen the deed.
He said that he was making a voyage from Italy to
Athens at about the season of the setting of the
Pleiades, carrying a miscellaneous collection of
assengers, among whom was Euthydicus, and with
im Damon, also of Chalcis, his comrade. They were
of the same age, but Euthydicus was vigorous and
strong, while Damon was pale and sickly, just
convalescing, it seemed, from a prolonged illness.

<pb n="v.5.p.137"/>
</p>

<p>
As far as Sicily they had made a fortunate passage,
said Simylus; but when they had run through the
straits and in due time were sailing in the Adriatic
itself, a great tempest fell upon them. Why repeat
the many details of his story—huge seas, cyclones,
hail, and all the other evils of a storm? But when
they were at last abreast of Zacynthos,<note n="v.5.p.137.n.1"><p>Zante. </p></note>! sailing with
the yard bare, and also dragging hawsers in their
wake to check the fury of their driving, towards
midnight Damon became seasick, as was natural in
weather so rough, and began to vomit, leaning outboard. Then, I suppose because the ship was hove
down with greater force towards the side over which
he was leaning and the high sea contributed a send,
he fell overboard head-first ; and the poor fellow was
not even without his clothes, so as to have been able
to swim more easily. So he began at once to call for
help, choking and barely able to keep himself above
the water.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="20"><p>
When Euthydicus, who happened to be undressed
and in his bunk, heard him, he flung himself into the
sea, got to Damon, who was already giving out (all
this was visible at a long distance because the moon
was shining) and helped him by swimming beside him
and bearing him up. The rest of them, he said,
wanted to aid the men and deplored their misfortune,
but could not do it because the wind that drove them
was too strong; however, they did at least something,
for they threw them a number of pieces of cork
and some spars, on which they might swim if they
chanced upon any of them, and finally even the gang
plank, which was not small.


<pb n="v.5.p.139"/>

Think now, in the name of the gods! what firmer
proof of affection could a man display towards a
friend who had fallen overboard at night into a sea so
wild, than that of sharing his death? I beg you,
envisage the tumult of the seas, the roar of the breaking water, the boiling spume, the night, the despair ;
then one man strangling, barely keeping up his head,
holding his arms out to his friend, and the other
leaping after him at once, swimming with him, fearing
that Damon would perish first. In that way you can
appreciate that in the case of Euthydicus too it is no
common friend whom I have described.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="21"><p>
<label>TOXARIS</label>
Did the men lose their lives, Mnesippus, or were
they unaccountably saved, somehow? I am very
concerned about them.
</p>
<p><label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Never fear, Toxaris; they were saved and are now
at Athens, both of them, studying philosophy.
Simylus, to be sure, could only tell this tale about
what he had once seen in the night—the one falling
overboard, the other leaping after him, and both
swimming as long as he could distinguish them in the
darkness. But the sequel was told by Euthydicus
himself. In the beginning they came upon some
corks on which they supported themselves and kept
afloat uncomfortably, but afterwards, seeing the gang
plank at last, towards daybreak, they swam to it
and then, after climbing upon it, easily drifted to
Zacynthos.


<pb n="v.5.p.141"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
After these friends, who were by no means despicable, I should say, let me tell you now of a third who
was not a bit inferior to them.</p>

<p>
Eudamidas of Corinth had formed friendships with
Aretaeus of Corinth and Charixenus of Sicyon, who
were both rich, while he was extremely poor. When
he died, he left a will which very likely appeared
ridiculous to everyone else, but I hardly think it will
seem so to you, since you are a good man, a worshipper
of friendship, and a competitor for the first prize in it.
It was set down in the will: “I leave to Aretaeus my
mother to support and cherish in her old age, and to
Charixenus my daughter to bestow in marriage with
the largest dowry that he can give her out of his
own means” (besides an aged mother he had also
a daughter, already marriageable); “and if anything should befall either of these men in the
meantime, his interest is to go to the other.” When
this will was read, all who knew of the poverty of
Eudamidas but were unaware of the friendship which
he had with the men considered the thing a joke, and
every one of them went away laughing. ‘ What a
fine fortune Aretaeus and Charixenus, the lucky
fellows, are coming into,” said they, “if they must
pay out money to Eudamidas and have the dead
man inherit from them while they themselves are
still alive!”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
The heirs to whom these legacies had been left,
on hearing of it, came at once to administer the will.
Charixenus, to be sure, outlived his friend only five
days; but Aretaeus proved himself the best of
legatees. Assuming both his own interest and the

<pb n="v.5.p.143"/>

other’s, he supported Eudamidas’ mother and also
not long ago portioned his daughter off, giving, out
of five talents that he had, dowries of two talents to
his own daughter and two to his friend’s; moreover,
he thought fit that they should both be married on the
same day.
</p>

<p>
What is your opinion, Toxaris, of this man
Aretaeus? Has he set a bad example of friendship
in accepting such legacies and not playing false to his
his friend’s last will? Or shall we put him down
among those definitely elected as one of the five?
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
Yes, he too is noble; but to me Eudamidas is far
more wonderful for the confidence he had in his
friends. He made it plain that he himself would have
done likewise for them; indeed, he would not have
hung back if it had not been set down in a will, but
would have presented himself before all the rest as
an heir to such bequests by intestate succession.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="24"><p>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
You are quite right.—As the fourth I shall tell you
of Zenothemis, son of Charmolaus, of Massilia.</p>

<p>
He was pointed out to me in Italy when I was
there as an ambassador of my country, a handsome,
tall man, and a wealthy one, it seemed. His wife sat
beside him as he passed through the street on a
chariot ; not only was she repulsive in general, but
her right side was shrivelled and the eye wanting—
a hideously disfigured, unapproachable nightmare.
Then, when I expressed my surprise that he, a
handsome and attractive man, could endure to have
such a woman riding at his side, the person who

<pb n="v.5.p.145"/>

had pointed him out told me what had made the
marriage obligatory. He was accurately informed
about it all, for he too was a Massaliote.
</p>

<p>
“Menecrates,” he said, “the father of the misshapen woman yonder, had a friend, Zenothemis,
who, like himself, was wealthy and distinguished.
In course of time Menecrates had his property
confiscated by judicial sentence, when he was
disfranchised by the Six Hundred for presenting
an unconstitutional measure. That,’ said he, “is
the punishment we Massaliotes inflict whenever
anyone proposes an unconstitutional enactment.
Menecrates was distressed, of course, by the condemnation itself, since in a moment he had become
poor instead of rich and dishonoured instead of
honoured; but most of all he was worried about
this daughter, who was then marriageable, and
eighteen; but even with all the wealth which her
father had possessed before his condemnation, no
well-born man, though poor, would readily have
agreed to accept her, so unfortunate was she in
her appearance. It was said, too, that she had
attacks of the falling sickness when the moon was
waxing.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="25"><p>
“When he was lamenting these misfortunes to
Zenothemis, the latter said: ‘ Never fear, Menecrates; you shall not lack what you need, and your
daughter will find a husband worthy of her lineage.’
As he spoke, he grasped him by the hand, took him
home, and shared his great wealth with him. Also,
he ordered a dinner prepared and invited his friends,
including Menecrates, to a wedding-feast, pretending
to have persuaded one of his comrades to promise to
marry the girl. When their dinner was over and


<pb n="v.5.p.147"/>

they had poured the libation to the gods, at that
moment Zenothemis held out to him his cup, full of
wine, and said: ‘ Accept, Menecrates, the lovingcup from your son-in-law, for I shall this day wed
your daughter Cydimache; her dowry I received
long ago, amounting to twenty-five talents.’ The
other said: ‘No, no, Zenothemis, do not! May I
never be so mad as to suffer you, who are young and
handsome, to make a match with an ugly, disfigured
girl!’ But while he was saying this, Zenothemis
picked up the girl bodily and went into his chamber,
from which he returned presently, after having made
her his wife.</p>

<p>
“From that time on he has lived with her, cherishing her beyond measure and taking her about with him
everywhere, as you see.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="26"><p>
 Not only is he unashamed
of his marriage, but indeed seems to be proud of
it, offering it as proof that he thinks little of physical
beauty or ugliness and of wealth and glory, but has.
high regard for his friend, for Menecrates, and does
not believe that the latter’s worth, as regards
friendship, was lessened by the vote of the Six
Hundred.</p>

<p>
Already, however, Fortune has requited him for
this conduct. He has had a beautiful boy by this
ugly woman; and besides, only recently, when the
father took the child in his arms and brought him
into the Senate-house wreathed with leaves of olive
and dressed in black, in order that he might excite
greater pity on behalf of his grandfather, the baby
burst into laughter before the senators and clapped
his two hands, whereupon the senate, softened by
him, set the condemnation aside in favour of Menecrates, so that he is now in full possession of his rights

<pb n="v.5.p.149"/>

and privileges through employing so tiny an. advocate
to present his case to the members in session.”</p>

<p>
Such are the deeds which, according to the
Massaliote, Zenothemis performed for his friend ;
as you see, they are not trivial, or likely to have
been done by many Scythians, who even in the
matter of concubines are said to be careful to select
the most beautiful.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="27"><p>
We have the fifth remaining, and I do not purpose
to forget Demetrius of Sunium and tell of anyone
else.
Demetrius sailed to Egypt with Antiphilus of
Alopece, his friend from boyhood and comrade in their
military training. There they lived and studied
together; he himself followed the Cynic school of
philosophy under that sophist from Rhodes,<note n="v.5.p.149.n.1"><p>It has been suggested that this may have been Agathobulus (cf. p. 19, n. 3), but with little to go on except that Agathobulus must have been teaching Cynicism in Alexandria at about the time which this tale presupposes for the Rhodian sophist. It is hardly safe to assume that he cannot have had any rivals. </p></note> while
Antiphilus for his part studied medicine. Well, one
time Demetrius happened to have gone into Egypt
to see the pyramids and the statue of Memnon, for
he had heard that the pyramids, though high, cast
no shadow, and that Memnon utters a cry to the
rising sun. Eager, therefore, to see the pyramids
and tohear Memnon, Demetrius had cruised off up the
Nile six months before, leaving behind him Antiphilus,
who feared the journey and the heat.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="28"><p>
In the meantime the latter met with a calamity
which required a very staunch friend. His slave,
Syrus by name and Syrian by nationality, joined
certain temple-robbers, and entered the temple of


<pb n="v.5.p.151"/>

Anubis with them. They robbed the god of two
golden libation-bowls, a caduceus, also of gold, some
dog-headed figures of silver, and other such matters,
all of which they left in trust with Syrus. Then,
after their imprisonment (for they were taken when
they tried to sell something), they at once told everything when they were broken on the wheel, came
under escort to the house of Antiphilus, and fetched
out the stolen goods, which were lying under a bed
in a dark corner. Consequently Syrus was confined
at once, and with him his master, Antiphilus, who was
actually seized while he listened to a lecture by his
teacher. Nobody came to his assistance; on the
contrary, even his erstwhile friends turned their backs
upon him on the ground that he had robbed the
Anubideum and considered it an act of impiety on
their own part if they had ever drunk or eaten with
him. Moreover, the two remaining servants bundled
up everything in the house and made off.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="29"><p>
Poor Antiphilus therefore remained in confinement
for a long time, regarded as the most villainous of all
the malefactors that there were in the prison, and the
Egyptian keeper, a superstitious fellow, thought to
gratify and avenge his god by exercising his authority
over Antiphilus with a heavy hand. Whenever he
defended himself, saying that he had not done anything of the sort, he was thought brazen-faced, and
was detested much more for it. Consequently, he
sickened at length and was ill, as might be expected
in view of the fact that he slept on the ground and at
night could not even stretch out his legs, which were
confined in the stocks. By day, to be sure, the collar
was sufficient, together with manacles upon one hand ;
but for the night he had to be fully secured by his

<pb n="v.5.p.153"/>

bonds. Moreover, the stench of the room and its
stifling air (since many were confined in the same
place, cramped for room, and scarcely able to draw
breath), the clash of iron, the scanty sleep—all these
conditions were difficult and intolerable for such a
man, unwonted to them and unschooled to a life so
rigorous.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="30"><p>
He was giving up the struggle and refusing even
to take food when Demetrius came back, knowing
nothing of what had happened until then. As soon
as he found out, he set off, just as he was, straight for
the prison at arun. At that time, however, he was
not admitted, for it was evening and the keeper had
long ago locked the door and gone to sleep, after
directing his servants to keep watch; but in the
morning he obtained admission by vehement entreaty.
After entering he made a long search for Antiphilus,
who had become unrecognisable through his miseries.
He went about examining each of the prisoners just
as people do who seek out their own dead amon
the altered bodies on battle-fields. Indeed, had he
not called his name aloud, ‘ Antiphilus, son of
Deinomenes,” he would not for a long time have
known which was he, so greatly had he been changed
by his dire straits. But Antiphilus, hearing his
voice, cried out; and, as Demetrius approached,
he parted his long hair, all unkempt and matted,
drew it away from his face, and so disclosed his
identity. At once both fell in a faint at the
unexpected sight.</p>

<p>
After a time Demetrius brought both himself and
Antiphilus to their senses, and ascertained from him
definitely how everything stood. Then he bade him
have no fear, and tearing his short cloak in two, put

<pb n="v.5.p.155"/>

on one of the halves himself and gave the remainder
to Antiphilus, after stripping from him the filthy,
worn-out rags that he was wearing.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="31"><p>
From that time
forth, too, he shared his life in every way, attending
and cherishing him; for by hiring himself out to the
shipmen in the harbour from early morning until
noon, he earned a good deal of money as a stevedore.
Then, on returning from his work, he would give part
of his pay to the keeper, thus rendering him tractable
and peaceful, and the rest sufficed well enough for
the maintenance of his friend. Each afternoon he
remained with Antiphilus, keeping him in heart;
and when night overtook him, he ‘sept just in front
of the prison door, where he had made a place to lie
and had put down some leaves.</p>

<p>
For some time they carried on in this way, Demetrius coming in without hindrance and Antiphilus
bearing his misfortune more lightly.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="32"><p>
But later, after
a certain brigand had died in the prison (by poison,
it was thought) a close guard was instituted, and not
one of those who sought admission could enter the
gaol any longer. Perplexed and distressed over this
situation, as he had no other way to be with his
comrade, he went to the governor and incriminated
himself, alleging that he had been an accomplice in
the attempt upon Anubis.</p>

<p>
When he had made that statement, he was haled
straight to prison, and on being brought in with
Antiphilus, he managed with difficulty, by dint of
urgent entreaties addressed to the warden, to obtain
from him one concession, at least—that of being
confined near Antiphilus and in the same set of irons.
Then indeed, more than any other time, he displayed
the affection which he had for him, neglecting his own

<pb n="v.5.p.157"/>

adversities (though he himself had fallen ill) but
taking care that Antiphilus should sleep as well as
possible and should suffer less distress. So they bore
their discomforts more easily by sharing them with
each other.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="33"><p>
In time an accident occurred which relieved them
from further misfortune. One of the men in irons,
having somehow obtained possession of a file and
enlisted many of the prisoners in a plot, cut the chain
to which they were all attached in a row, with their
fetters strung upon it, and so set them allfree ; whereupon they easily killed the guards, who were few, and
escaped together. Well, those others scattered at
once, going wherever each one of them could, and
afterwards were arrested, most of them. Demetrius
and Antiphilus, however, remained where they were,
and seized Syrus just as he was about to go. When
daylight came, as soon as the prefect of Egypt
learned what had happened, hesent men tohunt down
the others, but summoned Demetrius and his friend
and freed them from imprisonment, praising them
because they alone did not run away.</p>

<p>
They were not the men, however, to be content
with being released in that way. Demetrius cried
out and made a great stir, saying that grave injustice
was being done them, since it would be thought that
they were criminals, and were being released by way
of mercy or commendation because they had not run
away; and at length they forced the magistrate to
undertake an accurate investigation of the affair.
When he discovered that they were not guilty, he
commended them, expressing very great admiration
for Demetrius, and in dismissing them condoled with
them over the punishment which they had undergone

<pb n="v.5.p.159"/>

through their unjust imprisonment and presented
each of them with a gift out of his own pocket,
Antiphilus with ten thousand drachmas and Demetrius with twice as much.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="34"><p>
Antiphilus is still in Egypt, but Demetrius left his
own twenty thousand to his friend and went away to
India, to join the Brahmans, merely saying to Antiphilus that he might fairly be held excusable for
leaving him now; for he himself would not want the
money as long as he remained what he was, able to
content himself with little, and Antiphilus would not
need a friend any longer, since his circumstances had
become easy.</p>

<p>
That, Toxaris, is what Greek friends are like. If
you had not previously calumniated us as priding
ourselves greatly upon words, I should have repeated
for you the very speech, a long one and a good one,
that Demetrius made in the court-room, not defending himself at all but only Antiphilus; weeping,
moreover, and imploring, and taking the whole thing
upon himself until Syrus under the lash exonerated
both of them.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="35"><p>
I have told you these few instances out of a greater
number (the first that my memory supplied), of
friends that were good and true; and now, dismounting from my steed, I yield the word henceforth to
you. How you are to make out that your Scythians
are not worse, but much better than these men, will
be your own look-out, if you are at all concerned
about your right hand, for fear of having it cut off.
But you must show yourself a man of prowess, for
you would put yourself in a laughable position if,
after your very expert laudation of Orestes and

<pb n="v.5.p.161"/>

Pylades, you should reveal yourself a poor spokesman
on behalf of Scythia.
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
Well done, Mnesippus! You are giving me
- encouragement for my speech, as if it did not matter
at all to you whether you get the worst of it in our
dispute and have your tongue docked. However, I
shall begin at once, without any display of fine words
such as you have made; for that is not a Scythian
habit, especially when the deeds speak louder than
the words. And do not expect from us anything like
what you told of when you commended a man if he
married an ugly wife without a dowry, or if he gave
money to the amount of two talents to the daughter
of 'a friend on her marriage, or even, by Zeus, if he
allowed himself to be imprisoned when it was obvious
that he would soon be released; for those are very
paltry matters, and there is nothing of greatness or
bravery in them.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="36"><p>
I shall tell you of many deeds of
blood and battles and deaths for the sake of friends,
that you may know the achievements of your people
to be child’s play in comparison with those of the
Scythians.</p>

<p>
Yet it is not unaccountable that this is so with you
Greeks, but natural for you to praise these trivial
matters; for you lack, you entirely lack momentous
occasions for the display, of friendship, living as you do
in profound peace. Just so in calm weather a
man cannot tell whether his sailing-master is good ;
hé will need a storm to determine that. With us,
however, wars are continuous, and we are always
either invading the territory of others, or withdrawing before invaders, or meeting in battle over


<pb n="v.5.p.163"/>

pasturage or stolen cattle, where need for good
friends is greatest; and for that reason we cement
our friendships as strongly as we can, thinking this
to be the only irresistible and unconquerable weapon
of war.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="37"><p>
First of all, I wish to tell you how we make our
friends. Not through boon-companionship, as you
do, nor because a man has been a comrade of ours
in military training or a neighbour. No, when we
see a brave man, capable of great achievements, we
all make after him, and we think fit to behave in
forming friendships as you do in seeking brides, paying them protracted court and doing everything in
their company to the end that we may not fall short
of attaining their friendship or be thought to deserve
rejection. And whena man has been singled out and
is at last a friend, there ensue formal compacts and the
most solemn of oaths that we will not only live with
one another but die, if need be, for each other; and
we do just that. For, once we have cut our fingers,
let the blood drip into a cup, dipped our sword-points
into it, and then, both at once, have set it to our
lips and drunk, there is nothing thereafter that can
dissolve the bond between us.<note n="v.5.p.163.n.1"><p>Cf. Herodotus, IV, 70, who, however, makes no reference to the point that both drink from the same cup at the same time, which is proved by a gold plaque from the tomb of Kul-Oba near Kertch (often reproduced; e.g., Minns, Scythians and Greeks, p. 203), where a drinking horn is used. </p></note>_ We are permitted
at most to enter into three such compacts, since a
man of many friends resembles, we think, promiscuous women with their lovers, and we consider
that his friendship is no longer of the same strength
when it has been split up into a multitude of
loyalties.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="38"><p>
I shall begin with the affair of Dandamis, which



<pb n="v.5.p.165"/>

happened recently. In our engagement with the
Sauromatae, when Amizoces had been taken
prisoner, his friend Dandamis—but stay! first let
me take my oath for you in our way, since that also
was part of the agreement that I made with you in
the beginning. I swear by Wind and Glaive that I
shall tell you no falsehood, Mnesippus, about Scythian
friends.
</p>
<p><label>MNESIPPUS</label>
I scarcely felt the need of your swearing, but you
did well to avoid taking oath by any god!
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
What is that you say? Do you not think Wind
and Glaive are gods? Were you really so unaware
that there is nothing more important to mankind
than life and death? Well then, when we swear by
Wind and Glaive, we do so because the wind is the
source of life, and the glaive the cause of death.<note n="v.5.p.165.n.1"><p>Herodotus alludes to Scythian sword-worship (IV, 62), but says nothing of their worshipping the wind, which Rostovtzeff takes to be an invention of Lucian’s. </p></note>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Well, really, if that is the reason, you could have
many other such gods as Glaive is—Arrow, Spear,
Poison, Halter, and the like; for this god Death takes
many shapes and puts at our disposal an infinite
number of roads that lead to him.
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
Don’t you see how it smacks of sophists bickering
and lawyers in court for you to act this way, interrupting and spoiling my story? I kept still while you
were talking.


<pb n="v.5.p.167"/>

<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
I won’t do it again, anyhow, Toxaris, for you were
quite right in your reproof. Therefore, you may
proceed confidently, as if I were not even here while
you are talking, so silent shall I be for you.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="39"><p>
<label>TOXARIS</label>
The friendship of Dandamis and Amizoces was three
days old, counting from the time when they drank
each other’s blood, when the Sauromatae descended
upon our country with ten thousand horse ; and the
foot came over the border, it was said, in thrice that
number. As our people had not foreseen their
attack, they not only routed us completely when they
fell upon us, but slew many of the fighting men and
took the rest prisoners, except one or another who
succeeded in swimming over to the other side of the
river, where we had half our encampment and part
of the wagons; for that was the way in which we
had pitched our tents at the time, since for some
reason unknown to me it had seemed good to the
leaders of our horde—on both banks of the Tanais.<note n="v.5.p.167.n.1"><p>This dates the tale’s origin at a time when the Scythians and the Sauromatae, or Sarmatians, faced each other on opposite’sides of the Don, as Rostovtzeff has pointed out. </p></note></p>

<p>
At once they began to round up the cattle, secure
the prisoners, plunder the tents, and seize the
wagons, taking most of them with all their occupants
and offering violence to our concubines and wives
before our very eyes; and we were distressed over
the situation.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="40"><p>
But as Amizoces was being dragged
away—for he had been taken—he called upon his
friend by name because of his disgraceful captivity


<pb n="v.5.p.169"/>

and reminded him of the cup and the blood. When
Dandamis heard that, without an instant’s hesitation,
under the eyes of everyone he swam over to the
enemy. The Sauromatae rushed at him with
brandished javelins, intending to spear him to death,
but he called out “Zirin.”” If anyone says that, he is
not killed by them, but is received as coming to offer
ransom.<note n="v.5.p.169.n.1"><p>It is clear from the use of the word Zirin below that it does not mean “ransom” or “‘ransomer,” and cannot be connected with late Persian Zer, “gold,” as Vasmer suggests (Iranier in Siidrussland, p. 39). It must denote something like “brother,” “friend,” “envoy.” </p></note>
On being brought up to the leader, he demanded
his friend back, but the man asked for ransom;
he would not let him go, he said, unless he got a great
deal for him. Dandamis replied: “All that I had
has been carried off by your people; but if in any way
I can make payment as I stand, I am ready to proffer
it to you. Lay on me whatever command you will;
if you like, take me in his place and use me as you
please.” The Sauromatian answered: “There is
no need for you to put yourself completely in our
power, especially when you come as Zirin; pay part
of what you possess, and take away your friend.”
Dandamis asked what he would have; whereupon
the other demanded his eyes, and at once he allowed
them to be put out. When that had been done
and the Sauromatae had their ransom, taking Amizoces, he set off for home leaning upon him, and
by. swimming across together they got back to us in
safety.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="41"><p>
This occurrence heartened all the Scythians, and
they no longer thought themselves beaten, seeing


<pb n="v.5.p.171"/>

that the greatest of all our treasures had not been
carried off by the enemy, but we still had among us
staunch resolution and loyalty to friends. Furthermore, the Sauromatae were daunted more than a
little by that same thing, when they considered what
manner of men they were about to face in pitched
battle, even though in the surprise attack for the
moment they had obtained the upper hand. So
when night had fallen, abandoning most of the flocks
and herds and firing the wagons, they vanished in
flight. Amizoces, however, could not bear to have
‘his own sight when Dandamis was blind, but put out
his eyes with his own hands; and now both of them
sit idle, maintained with every show of honour at
public expense by the Scythian folk.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="42"><p>
What similar deed, Mnesippus, could you mention,
even if you were allowed to enumerate ten more
instances over and above your five, unsupported
by oath, if you liked, so that you might adorn them
with plenty of fiction? Then too, I have told you the
naked facts; but if you were describing anyone
like that, I know very well how many embellishments you would intersperse in the story, telling
how Dandamis pleaded, how he was blinded, what he
said, how he returned, how he was received with
laudation by the Scythians, and other matters such as
you Greeks are in the habit of manufacturing to
gratify your hearers.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="43"><p>
But let me tell you about another man equally
honoured, Belitta, cousin of that same Amizoces.
He saw that his friend Basthes had been dragged
off his horse by a lion (it chanced that they were
hunting together), and already the lion, lying upon
him, had fastened upon his throat and was tearing him

<pb n="v.5.p.173"/>

with his claws. Springing to the ground, he attacked
the animal from behind and tried to draw him away,
provoking him, diverting his attention, inserting
his fingers between his teeth, and endeavouring in
every possible way to extract Basthes from the grip
of his jaws, until at last the lion left Basthes halfdead and turning upon Belitta, seized and killed him.
In dying, however, he at least succeeded in stabbing
the lion in the breast with his sword, so that they all
died together, and in burying them we made two
barrows in close proximity, one for the friends and
one facing it for the lion.<note n="v.5.p.173.n.1"><p>This tale, with its lion (in South Russia, about a.d. 150!) and the poetic justice of the animal’s entombment, distinctly suggests a literary source, perhaps an epigram. </p></note>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="44"><p>
The third friendship of which I shall tell you,
Mnesippus, is that of Macentes, Lonchates, and
Arsacomas. This Arsacomas fell in love with
Mazaea, the daughter of Leucanor, who had become
king in Bosporus,<note n="v.5.p.173.n.2"><p>History knows no king of Bosporus named Leucanor, nor any Eubiotus, set down below as his illegitimate brother and successor (§ 51). In a fragment of a Greek romance, however, of which the plot is laid in Scythia (Papiri della Societa Italiana, VIII, 981) there is a character, evidently a ruler, named Eubiotus, and Rostovtzeff points to this as evidence that Lucian’s tale, itself a miniature romance, is drawn. from some historical novel (Skythien und der Bosporus, p. 98). I have noted in it several passages which seem to be abridgements of a more detailed story. </p></note> when he was there on a mission
regarding the tribute which is regularly paid us by
the people of Bosporus but at that time was more
than two months overdue. Well, at the banquet
he caught sight of Mazaea, a tall and beautiful
girl, instantly fell in love with her and was hard hit.
The matter of the contributions had been settled



<pb n="v.5.p.175"/>

already, and the king was giving him audience and
entertaining him in connection with his dismissal.
It is customary, however, in Bosporus for suitors to
bespeak brides at dinner and tell who they are that
they should think themselves worthy of acceptance,
and at this time it chanced that many of them were
at the banquet, kings and the sons of kings; Tigrapates the dynast of the Lazi was there, and Adyrmachus, the ruler of Machlyene, and many others.
Each of the suitors, after announcing that he has
come to propose, must then take dinner, lying in his
place among the others, in silence; but when they
have finished dinner, he must call for a goblet of
wine, pour a drink-offering upon the table, and sue
for the girl’s hand, commending himself freely
according to his standing in family or wealth or
power.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="45"><p>
Many, therefore, in accordance with this usage
had poured their libation, made their request, and
enumerated their kingdoms and treasures. Then,
last of all, Arsacomas asked for the cup. He did not
make libation, for it is not our custom to pour out our
wine; on the contrary, we hold that to be an offence
to the god. Instead, he drank it out at a single
draught, and said: “O King, give me your daughter
Mazaea for my wife, since I am a much better match
than these men, at least in point of wealth and
property.”” Leucanor was surprised, for he knew that
Arsacomas was poor and just an ordinary Scythian,
and he asked: “How many cattle and how many
wagons have you, Arsacomas, since they constitute
the wealth of your people?” “Why,’ said he,
“I own no wagons or herds, but I have two noble
friends, such as no other Scythian has.”

<pb n="v.5.p.177"/>
</p>

<p>
Well, at the time they laughed at him on account
of this remark and ignored him, thinking that he
was drunk; Adyrmachus was preferred, and in the
morning was to take away his bride along Lake
Maeotis to the Machlyans.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="46"><p>
But Arsacomas returned
home and informed his friends how he had been dishonoured by the king and laughed at in the banquet
because he was considered poor. “And yet,” said
he, “I told him what riches I possess in you two,
Lonchates and Macentes, and that your devotion
was better and more lasting than sovereignty over
the people of Bosporus. But in spite of my saying
this, he ridiculed and contemned us, and gave the
maiden to Adyrmachus the Machlyan to take away,
because he was said to own ten golden goblets,
eighty four-bunk wagons, and many sheep and
cattle. So far above brave men did he value great
flocks and herds, artistic drinking-cups, and heavy
wagons.</p>

<p>
“Now for my part, my friends, I am doubly distressed, for not only do I love Mazaea but this
insult in the presence of so many men has affected
me deeply. And I think that you also have been
equally injured, for a third of the disgrace belonged
to each of us, since we live in the understanding
that from the time when we came together we have
been but as one man, distressed by the same things,
pleased by the same things.” “Not only that,”
Lonchates added, “but each of us is completely
disgraced in your suffering such treatment.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="47"><p>
“How, then, shall we handle the situation?”
said Macentes. “Let us divide the task between


<pb n="v.5.p.179"/>

us,” Lonchates replied; “I engage to bring Arsacomas the head of Leucanor, and you must fetch
his bride home to him.” “Very well,” said the
other; “and in the meantime, Arsacomas, as it is
likely that we shall presently need to take the field
and go to war, you, awaiting us here, should collect
and make ready arms, horses, and a very large force.
You might very easily enlist many, since you yourself are brave and we have plenty of relatives, and
it would be especially easy if you should sit on the
ox-hide.” Those plans were approved, and Lonchates, just as he was, made straight for Bosporus,
while Macentes headed for the Machlyans, both of
them mounted. Arsacomas, remaining at home,
held conferences with his comrades and armed a
force recruited from his relatives; then at last he
sat upon the hide.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="48"><p>
Our custom in the matter of the hide is as follows.
When a man who has been wronged by another wishes
to avenge himself but sees that by himself he is not
strong enough, he sacrifices a bull, cuts up and cooks
the meat, spreads the hide out on the ground, and
sits on it, with his hands held behind his back like a
man bound by the elbows. That is our strongest
appeal for aid. The meat of the bull is served up,
and as the man’s kinsmen and all else who wish
approach, each takes a portion of it, and then, setting his right foot upon the hide, makes a pledge
according to his ability, one that he will furnish five
horsemen to serve without rations or pay, another
ten, another still more, another foot-soldiers, heavy-


<pb n="v.5.p.181"/>

armed or light-armed, as many as he can, and another
simply himself, if he is very poor. So a very large
force is sometimes raised on the hide, and such an
army is especially dependable as regards holding
together and very hard for the enemy to conquer,
since it is under oath; for setting foot on the hide
is an oath.<note n="v.5.p.181.n.1"><p>Lucian is our only authority for this curious custom; the allusions to it in Suidas and the paroemiographi (Gaisford, Bodl. 355, Coisl. 207; Leutech, Append. II, 80, Apostol. VII, 75) are mere quotations from Lucian, and Gilbert Cognatus’ mysterious reference to “Zenodotus” and “the ox of the Homolotti” derives (by way of Erasmus, Adagia: “Bos Homolottorum”) from Zenobius, II, 83: βοῦς ὁ Μολοτ- τῶν! That the Molossian custom of cutting up (but not eating) an ox in connection with making treaties has nothing to do with the Scythian usage is clear from the more detailed explanation of it in Coisl. 57 (Gaisford, p. 126). </p></note>
</p>

<p>
Arsacomas, then, was thus engaged; and he raised
some five thousand horse and twenty thousand foot,
heavy-armed and light-armed together.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="49"><p>

Lonchates
in the meantime entered Bosporus unrecognised,
approached the king while he was attending to a
matter of government, and said that he came with
a message from the Scythian commonwealth, but
also in his private capacity brought him important
news. When he was bidden to speak, he said:
‘The Scythians make one of their ordinary, every-da’
requests, that your herdsmen shall not encroac
upon the plain but shall graze only as far as the stony
ground; and they say that the cattle-lifters whom
you charge with overrunning your country are not
sent out by order of the state but steal for profit,
each on his own account; if any one of them should
be captured, you have full authority to punish
him. That is their message.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="50"><p>
 But on my own part, I
give you notice that a great attack upon you is
about to be made by Arsacomas, the son of



<pb n="v.5.p.183"/>

Mariantes, who came to you recently on a mission,
and—no doubt because he asked you for your
daughter and did not obtain his request from you—
is incensed; he has been sitting on the hide for six
days now,<note n="v.5.p.183.n.1"><p>It should not be inferred that it has taken Lonchates all this time to reach the city and its king. As the king has heard of the Scythian mustering before Lonchates sees him, it is evident that there was some delay, whether accidental or deliberate, </p></note> and has collected a great host.”</p>

<p>
“I myself,” said Leucanor, “had heard that a
force was being raised on the hide, but did not know
that it is being formed against us or that Arsacomas
is the organiser of it.” “Why,” said Lonchates,
“the preparations are directed at youin person. But
Arsacomas is no friend of mine, bearing a grudge
against me because I am held in higher regard by
our dignitaries and considered in all respects a
better man. If you will promise me your other
daughter, Barcetis, since even on other grounds I am
not unworthy of alliance with you, before lon
I will come and bring you his head.” “I promise,”
said the king, who had become thoroughly alarmed
because he recognised the just ground for the anger
of Arsacomas in connection with his proposal of
marriage; and besides, he stood in perpetual dread
of the Scythians.</p>

<p>
Lonchates replied: “Swear that you will keep the
agreement, and will not go back on your word then,
when the thing is done.”” When the king lifted his
hands toward Heaven and was in purpose to swear,
the other said: “Not here, for fear that some
onlooker may suspect the reason of our oath. No,
let us enter the sanctuary of Ares yonder and lock
the doors before we swear; and let nobody hear us!


<pb n="v.5.p.185"/>

If Arsacomas should get any knowledge of this,
I am afraid that he may initiate the war by making
a victim of me, as he is already surrounded by a
large band.” “Let us enter,’ responded the
king. ‘Gentlemen, withdraw as far as possible,
and let no one present himself in the temple who
is not summoned by me.”</p>

<p>
When they had entered and the guardsmen had
withdrawn, Lonchates drew his sword, clapped one
hand over the king’s mouth, that he might not
cry out, and stabbed him in the breast. Then
he cut off his head and carried it out (ith him under
his cloak, keeping up, as he did so, a pretended
conversation with him and saying that he would
return speedily, as if he had been sent by the king
to fetch something. Getting in this way to the place
where he had left his horse tied, he mounted and
rode off to Scythia. There was no pursuit of him,
since the Bosporans remained long in ignorance of
what had happened, and when they did find out
about it, they fell to squabbling over the throne.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="51"><p>
That, then, is what Lonchates did, and so fulfilled his promise to Arsacomas by giving him the
head of Leucanor. As for Macentes, while on his
way he had heard what had happened in Bosporus,
and. when he reached the Machlyans was the first
to report to them the tidings of the king’s death,<note n="v.5.p.185.n.1"><p>It should not be inferred that it has taken Lonchates all this time to reach the city and its king. As the king has heard of the Scythian mustering before Lonchates sees him, it is evident that there was some delay, whether accidental or deliberate, week or more (p. 183 and note) has elapsed before Macentes reaches the Machlyans, yet he returns in less than forty-eight hours, riding night and day, to be sure, but with the horse earrying double and therefore obliged to rest frequently. </p></note>
adding: “And the city, Adyrmachus, calls you to
the throne, as his son-in-law; so you yourself must
ride on ahead and take over the government, appear-



<pb n="v.5.p.187"/>

ing suddenly in the midst of things while they are
unsettled; but the girl must follow you in your wagontrain, for in that way it will be easier for you to win
over the common people in Bosporus, after they have
seen the daughter of Leucanor. For myself, I am
an Alan, and also related to the girl through her
mother, since Masteira, whom Leucanor married,
was of our people; and I come to you now on the
part of Masteira’s brothers in the country of the
Alans, who urge you to ride with all speed to Bosporus
and not to let the government go over to Eubiotus,
who being the illegitimate brother of Leucanor, is
always friendly to the Scythians and detests the
Alans.”<note n="v.5.p.187.n.1"><p>Abridgement seems to enter here; for the fact that Eubiotus is the illegitimate brother of Leucanor does not in itself adequately account for his attitude toward the Scythians and the Alans. Was his mother a Scythian, or perhaps a Sarmatian? At this time he is living among the Sarmatians (§ 54). </p></note></p>

<p>
Macentes was able to say this because he wore the
same dress and spoke the same tongue as the Alans.
These characteristics are common to Alans and
Scythians, except that the Alans do not wear their
hair very long, as the Scythians do. Macentes, however, had made himself resemble them in this also,
and had docked his hair by as much as an Alan’s
would probably be shorter than a Scythian’s.
Therefore he was believed, and was thought to be a
relative of Masteira and Mazaea.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="52"><p>
“Now then, Adyrmachus,” said he, “I am ready
to ride with you to Bosporus, if you wish, or to remain,
if necessary, and conduct the girl.” “That,” said
Adyrmachus, “is what I should like better—that
as you are of her blood, you should conduct Mazaea.
For if you go with us to Bosporus, we should gain



<pb n="v.5.p.189"/>

but a single horseman; but if you should conduct
my wife, you would be as good as many.”
</p>

<p>
That was put into effect, and he rode off, leaving
it to Macentes to conduct Mazaea, who was still a
maid. And he did indeed escort her upon her
wagon during the day; but when night overtook
them, he set her upon his horse—he had seen to it
that only one other horseman should attend them<note n="v.5.p.189.n.1"><p>Macentes comes alone; this single horseman is therefore presumably a Machlyan, and hostile. What, then, becomes of him? Only implications enlighten us. For some reason Macentes does not do the obvious thing—kill him at night and take his horse. Either he eludes them, or they elude him; and instead of following them, he posts ahead to overtake Adyrmachus with the news (§ 54). </p></note>—
himself leaped to his seat, and instead of continuing
to ride along the shore of Lake Maecotis, turned off
into the interior, taking on his right the mountains
of the Mitraeans. Stopping only at intervals to
allow the girl to rest, on the third day he succeeded
in reaching Scythia from Machlyene; his horse,
on ceasing to run, stood still for a moment and fell
dead,
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="53"><p>
while Macentes, delivering Mazaea to Arsacomas, said: “Accept from me also the fulfilment
of my promise!”</p>

<p>
Arsacomas was amazed at the unexpectedness
of that sight, and tried to express his gratitude,
but Macentes said: “Stop making me a different
person from yourself! To express gratitude to me
for what I have done in this is just as if my left hand
should be grateful to my right for ministering to it
when it had been wounded and taking care of it
fondly while it was weak. So with us—it would be
ridiculous if, after having fused ourselves together
long ago and united, as far as we could, into a
single person, we should continue to think it a
great thing if this or that part of us has done something useful in behalf of the whole body; for it



<pb n="v.5.p.191"/>

was working in its own behalf as a part of the whole
organism to which the good was being done.”</p>

<p>
This, then, was the reply of Macentes to Arsacomas
when he expressed his gratitude.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="54"><p>
But when Adyrmachus heard of the stratagem, instead of going on to
Bosporus, inasmuch as Eubiotus had been summoned from the Sauromatae, with whom he was
living, and was already on the throne, he returned
to his own country, and after assembling a great
army, advanced through the hill-country into
Scythia. Eubiotus, too, presently made an incursion
with his Greeks in full force and allied levies of
Alans and Sauromatae numbering twenty thousand
from each. After Eubiotus and Adyrmachus had
combined their armies, they amounted in all to
ninety thousand, a third of them mounted archers.</p>

<p>
For our part (and I say our, because I myself took
part in their expedition, having offered on the hide
at that time a hundred self-supporting horsemen)
we had raised not much less than thirty thousand,
including the horsemen, and were awaiting their
onset; our commander was Arsacomas. When we
saw them coming on, we marched forward to meet
them, sending our horsemen out in advance. After
a long and hard-fought battle, our side in time began
to give ground, the phalanx began to break, and at
last the entire Scythian force was cut in two. One
part began to withdraw, but it was not at all certain
that they were beaten; indeed, their flight was
considered a retreat, for even the Alans did not
venture to pursue them any distance. The other,
smaller part was surrounded by the Alans and
Machlyans, who were hammering it from all sides,
loosing arrows and javelins without stint; so that

<pb n="v.5.p.193"/>

those of us who had been surrounded were suffering
severely, and the rank and file were already throwing
away their arms.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="55"><p>
Lonchates and Macentes happened to be in this
part, and had already received wounds from fighting
in the front ranks, Lonchates in the thigh with the
spike of a spear-butt, Macentes on the head with an
axe and on the shoulder with a javelin. When
Arsacomas, who was with us others, perceived that,
thinking it would be dreadful if he should go away
and abandon his friends, he put spurs to his horse,
gave a great shout, and charged among the enemy
with uplifted battle-axe, so that the Machlyans
could not even face the fury of his wrath but separated and allowed him to go through.</p>

<p>
He encouraged his friends and rallied all the others,
then rushed at Adyrmachus, struck him at the base
of the neck with his axe, and clove him to the belt.
Upon his fall they gave way—the whole Machlyan
force first, the Alans not long afterwards, and the
Greeks next. So we had the upper hand once
more, and might have pursued them for a long
distance, killing them, if night had not ended the
business.</p>

<p>
On the next day men came to us as suppliants
from the enemy and asked us to make friends; the
Bosporans promised to pay us twice as much tribute,
the Machlyans said that they would give hostages,
and the Alans to make up for that attack undertook
to help us by subduing the Sindians, who had revolted some time previously. On those terms we
assented, but only after the approval of Arsacomas


<pb n="v.5.p.195"/>

and Lonchates had been given ;<note n="v.5.p.195.n.1"><p>Macentes would seem to have died of his wounds, though Lucian does not say so. It may be noted, too, that although the Sauromatians contributed 20,000 men to the invading force, we hear nothing of their part either in the battle or in the settlement. </p></note> and when the treaty
of peace was made, they negotiated the details.
Such are the deeds, Mnesippus, that Scythians
dare to do for their friends.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="56"><p>
<label>MNESIPPUS</label>
They are very dramatic, Toxaris, and quite like
fables. May Glaive and Wind, by whom you swore,
be good to me, but really, if one were to disbelieve
them, one would not seem very open to criticism.
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
But see to it, my gallant adversary, that your
disbelief is not jealousy! Nevertheless, I am not
the man to let your disbelieving me deter me from
telling you other such deeds that I know to have
been done by Scythians.
</p>
<p><label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Only don’t let them be too protracted, my
excellent friend, and don’t use such an unembarrassed
flow of speech; for as it is, by running hither and
thither through Scythia and Machlyene, and by
going off to Bosporus and then coming back again,
you have taken very liberal advantage of my silence.
</p>
<p><label>TOXARIS</label>
In this too I must obey your dictates; I must
speak briefly so that I shall not have you getting
completely tired out by following me all about with
your attention.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="57"><p>
No, rather let me tell you how I
myself was assisted by a friend named Sisinnes.



<pb n="v.5.p.197"/>
</p>

<p>
When I was going away from home to Athens by
reason of my desire for Greek culture, I put in at
Amastris, on the Black Sea; the city is a port of call
for those sailing this way from Scythia, not far distant
from Carambis. I was accompanied by Sisinnes,
who had been my companion from childhood.
After looking out a lodging near the port and transferring our effects to it from the vessel, we went
shopping, without suspecting any mischief. In
the meantime thieves pried the door open and
carried off everything, so as not to leave even enough
to suffice for that day.
</p>

<p>When we returned home and found out what had
happened, we did not think it best to proceed against
the neighbours, who were numerous, or against our
host, fearing that we should be accounted blackmailers in public opinion if we said that someone
had robbed us of four hundred darics, a great deal
of clothing, some rugs, and all the other things
that we had.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="58"><p>
So we discussed the situation to see
what we should do, now that we had become
absolutely penniless in a strange country. My
own thought was to plunge my sword into my side
forthwith, and make my exit from life before enduring any unseemly experience under the pressure of
hunger or thirst, but Sisinnes encouraged me and
begged me not to do anything of that sort, for he
himself would discover a means of our having enough
to live on.</p>

<p>
That day, therefore, he carried lumber in from the
port and came back with supplies for us which he
had procured with his wages. But the next morning, while going about in the market-place he saw a
sort of procession, as he put it, of high-spirited,

<pb n="v.5.p.199"/>

handsome young men. These had been enrolled
to fight duels for hire and were to settle their combats
on the next day but one. Well, he found out all
about them, and then came to me, saying:

“Toxaris, you need not call yourself a poor man any
longer; on the day after to-morrow I shall make
you rich.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="59"><p>
Those were his words; accordingly, we eked out a
wretched existence during the interval, and when
at length the spectacle began we were there looking
on, for taking me with him on the pretext of going
to see a Greek show that would be enjoyable and
novel, he had brought me to the theatre. We
took our seats, and first we saw wild beasts brought
down with javelins, hunted with dogs, and loosed
upon men in chains—criminals, we conjectured.
Then the gladiators entered, and the herald, bringing
in a tall youth, said that whoever wanted to fight
with that man should come forward, and would
receive ten thousand drachmas in payment for the
encounter. Thereupon Sisinnes arose, and, leaping
down, undertook to fight and requested arms. On
receiving his pay, the ten thousand drachmas, he
promptly put it in my hands, saying: “If I win,
Toxaris, we shall go away together, with all that we
need; but if I fall, bury me and go back to Scythia.”
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="60"><p>
While I was lamenting over this, he was given
his armour and fastened it on, except that he did
not put on the helmet but took position bareheaded
and fought that way. He himself received the first
wound, an under-cut in the back of the thigh, dealt
with a curved sword, so that blood flowed copiously.
For my part, I was already as good as dead in my
fright. But he waited until his opponent rushed

<pb n="v.5.p.201"/>

upon him too confidently; then he stabbed him in
the breast and ran him through, so that on the instant
he fell at his feet. Himself labouring under his
wound, he sat down upon the body and his life
almost left him, but I, running up, revived and inspirited him. When at length he was dismissed
as victor, I picked him up and carried him to our
lodgings. After long treatment he survived and still
lives in Scythia, with my sister as his wife; he is
lame, however, from his wound.</p>

<p>
That, Mnesippus, did not happen either in
Machlyene or among the Alans, so as to be unattested and possible to disbelieve; there are
many Amastrians here who remember the fight of
Sisinnes.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="61"><p>
As the fifth, I shall tell you the deed of Abauchas,
and then I shall stop. Once upon a time this man
Abauchas came to the city of the Borysthenites,<note n="v.5.p.201.n.1"><p>Olbia. </p></note>
bringing his wife, of whom he was exceptionally
fond, and two children, one of whom, a boy, was a
child in arms, while the other, a girl, was seven
years old. There came with him also a companion
of his, Gyndanes, who was ill of a wound which he
had received on the way from robbers who had
attacked them. In fighting with them he had got a
thrust in the thigh, so that he could not even stand
for the pain of it. During the night, as they slept—
they chanced to be living in an upper story—a great
fire broke out, every avenue of escape was being
cut off, and the flames were encompassing the house
on all sides. At that juncture Abauchas woke up;
abandoning his crying children, shaking off his wife


<pb n="v.5.p.203"/>

as she hung upon him and urging her to save herself,
he carried his comrade down and managed to burst
through at a place which the fire had not yet completely burned away. His wife, carrying the baby,
followed, telling the girl too to come along. Halfburned, she let the child fall from her arms and
barely leaped through the flames, and with her the
little girl, who also came very near losing her life.
When someone afterwards rebuked Abauchas for
abandoning his wife and children but bringing out
Gyndanes, he said: “Why, I can easily have other
children, and it was uncertain whether these would
be good for anything but I could not in a long time
find another friend like Gyndanes, who has given
me abundant proof of his devotion.”<note n="v.5.p.203.n.1"><p>The reasoning of Abauchas on this point is suspiciously like that ascribed to Seleucus Nicator by Lucian in the Goddess of Syria (18: Vol. IV, p. 364), to Antigone by Sophocles (Antig. 905-912), and to the wife of Intaphernes by Herodotus (III, 119). We cannot, however, be entirely certain in the case of Abauchas that it derives from the Herodotean story. There are parallels from India (in the Ramayana and in the Jatakas: Hermes, XXVIII, 465) and from Persia: sbid., XXIX, 155); cf. also, for modern Syria, A. Goodrich-Freer, Arabs in Tent and Town, p. 25. . </p></note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="62"><p>
I have finished, Mnesippus, the story of these five,
whom I have selected out of many. And now it is
perhaps time to decide which of us is to have either
his tongue or his right hand cut off, as the case may
be. Who, then, will be our judge?
</p>
<p><label>MNESIPPUS</label>
No one at all; for we did not appoint any judge
of the debate. “But do you know what we ought to
do? Since this time we have shot into the void, let
us some other day choose an umpire and in his
presence tell of other friends; then, whichever of us



<pb n="v.5.p.205"/>

gets beaten shall at that time have his tongue cut off
if it be I, or his right hand if it be you. Or, if that
is crude, inasmuch as you have resolved to extol
friendship and I myself think that men have no
other possession better or nobler than this, why
should not we ourselves make an agreement with
each other to be friends from this instant and remain
so for ever, content that both have won and thereby
have obtained magnificent prizes, since instead of a
single tongue or a single right hand each of us will
get two, and what is more, two pairs of eyes and of
feet; in a word, everything multiplied by two?
For the union of two or three friends is like the
pictures of Geryon that artists exhibit—a man with
six hands and three heads. Indeed, to my mind
Geryon was three persons acting together in all
things, as is right if they are really friends.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg044.perseus-eng1" subtype="section" n="63"><p>
<label>TOXARIS</label>
Good! let us do so.
</p>
<p><label>MNESIPPUS</label>
But let us not feel the need of blood, Toxaris, or
any sword to confirm our friendship. This conversation of ours just now and the similarity of our ideals
are far more dependable sureties than that cup which
your people drink, since achievements like these
require resolution rather than compulsion, it seems
to me.

<pb n="v.5.p.207"/>

<label>TOXARIS</label>
I approve all this; so let us now be friends and
each the other’s host, you mine here in Hellas and I
yours if ever you should come to Scythia.
</p>
<p><label>MNESIPPUS</label>
Truly you may be very sure that I shall not hesitate
to go even farther if I am to meet such friends as
you, Toxaris, have clearly shown me that you are,
by what you have said.

<pb n="v.5.p.211"/>
</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>
