<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>On the Articulations</title>
				<author>Hippocrates</author>
				<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
				<funder>National Library of Medicine History of Medicine Division</funder>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Cultural Heritage Langauge Technologies</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Kansas City Missouri</pubPlace>
				<date>February 20, 2003</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<monogr>
						<title>The Genuine Works of Hippocrates</title>
						<author>Hippocrates</author>
						<editor role="translator">Francis Adams</editor>
						<imprint>
							<pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
							<publisher>William Wood &amp; Company</publisher>
							<date>1886</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<correction status="high">
					<p>Data Entry</p>
				</correction>
			</editorialDecl>

			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Aph.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl n="text=Epid.">
				<refState unit="text"/>
				<refState unit="book"/>
				<refState unit="chapter"/>
				<refState unit="section" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
			<refsDecl>
				<refState unit="page" n="chunk"/>
			</refsDecl>
		</encodingDesc>

		<profileDesc>
			<langUsage>
				<language ident="en">English</language>
			</langUsage>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
			<pb n="p.210"/>
			<div type="section" n="1">
				<head>Part 1</head>
				<p> I am acquainted with one form in which the shoulder-joint is dislocated, namely,
					that into the armpit; I have never seen it take place upward nor outward; and
					yet I do not positively affirm whether it might be dislocated in these
					directions or not, although I have something which I might say on this subject.
					But neither have I ever seen what I considered to be a dislocation forward.
					Physicians, indeed, fancy that dislocation is very apt to occur forward, and
					they are more particularly deceived in those persons who have the fleshy parts
					about the joint and arm much emaciated; for, in all such cases, the head of the
					arm appears to protrude forward. And I in one case of this kind having said that
					there was no dislocation, exposed myself to censure from certain physicians and
					common people on that account, for they fancied that I alone was ignorant of
					what everybody else was acquainted with, and I could not convince them but with
					difficulty, that the matter was so. But if one will strip the point of the
					shoulder of the fleshy parts, and where the muscle (<hi rend="ital"
						>deltoid?</hi>) extends, and also lay bare the tendon that goes from the
					armpit and clavicle to the breast (<hi rend="ital">pectoral muscle?</hi>), the
					head of the humerus will appear to protrude strongly forward, although not
					dislocated, for the head of the humerus naturally inclines forward, but the rest
					of the bone is turned outward. The humerus is connected obliquely with the
					cavity of the scapula, when the arm is stretched along the sides; but when the
					whole arm is stretched forward, then the head of the humerus is in a line with
					the cavity of the humerus, and no longer appears to protrude forward. And with
					regard to the variety we are now treating of, I have never seen a case of
					dislocation forward; <pb n="p.211"/>and yet I do not speak decidedly respecting
					it, whether such a dislocation may take place or not. When, then, a dislocation
					into the armpit takes place, seeing it is of frequent occurrence, many persons
					know how to reduce it, for it is an easy thing to teach all the methods by which
					physicians effect the reductions, and the best manner of applying them. The
					strongest of those methods should be used when the difficulty of reduction is
					particularly great. The strongest is the method to be last described.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="2">
				<head>Part 2</head>
				<p> Those who are subject to frequent dislocations at the shoulder-joint, are for
					the most part competent to effect the reduction themselves; for, having
					introduced the knuckles of the other hand into the armpit, they force the joint
					upward, and bring the elbow toward the breast. The physician might reduce it in
					the same manner, if having introduced his fingers into the armpit on the inside
					of the dislocated joint, he would force it from the ribs, pushing his own head
					against the acromion, in order to make counter-pressure, and with his knees
					applied to the patient's elbow pushing the arm to the sides. It will be of
					advantage if the operator has strong hands, or the physician may do as directed
					with his head and hands, while another person brings the elbow toward the
					breast. Reduction of the shoulder may also be effected by carrying the fore-arm
					backward to the spine, and then with the one hand grasping it at the elbow, to
					bend the arm upward, and with the other to support it behind at the
					articulation. This mode of reduction, and the one formerly described, are not
					natural, and yet by rotating the bone of the joint, they force it to return.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="3">
				<head>Part 3</head>
				<p> Those who attempt to perform reduction with the heel, operate in a manner which
					is an approach to the natural. The patient must lie on the ground upon his back,
					while the person who is to effect the reduction is seated on the ground upon the
					side of the dislocation; then the operator, seizing with his hand the affected
					arm, is to pull it, while with his heel in the armpit he pushes in the contrary
					direction, the right heel being placed in the right armpit, and the left heel in
					the left armpit. But a round ball of a suitable size must be placed in the
					hollow of the armpit; the most convenient are very small and hard balls, formed
					from <pb n="p.212"/>several pieces of leather sewed together. For without
					something of the kind the heel cannot reach to the head of the humerus, since,
					when the arm is stretched, the armpit becomes hollow, the tendons on both sides
					of the armpit making counter-contraction so as to oppose the reduction. But
					another person should be seated on the other side of the patient to hold the
					sound shoulder, so that the body may not be dragged along when the arm of the
					affected side is pulled; and then, when the ball is placed in the armpit, a
					supple piece of thong sufficiently broad is to be placed round it, and some
					person taking hold of its two ends is to seat himself above the patient's head
					to made counter-extension, while at the same time he pushes with his foot
					against the bone at the top of the shoulder. The ball should be placed as much
					on the inside as possible, upon the ribs, and not upon the head of the
					humerus.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="4">
				<head>Part 4</head>
				<p> There is another method of reduction performed by the shoulder of a person
					standing. The person operating in this way, who should be taller than the
					patient, is to take hold of his arm and place the sharp point of his own
					shoulder in the patient's armpit, and push it in so that it may lodge there, and
					having for his object that the patient may be suspended at his back by the
					armpit, he must raise himself higher on this shoulder than the other; and he
					must bring the arm of the suspended patient as quickly as possible to his own
					breast. In this position he should shake the patient when he raises him up, in
					order that the rest of the body may be a counterpoise to the arm which is thus
					held. But if the patient be very light, a light child should be suspended behind
					along with him. These methods of reduction are all of easy application in the
					palestra, as they can all be performed without instruments, but they may also be
					used elsewhere.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="5">
				<head>Part 5</head>
				<p> Those who accomplish the reduction by forcibly bending it round a pestle,
					operate in a manner which is nearly natural. But the pestle should be wrapped in
					a soft shawl (for thus it will be less slippery), and it should be forced
					between the ribs and the head of the humerus. And if the pestle be short, the
					patient should be seated upon something, that his arm can with difficulty pass
					above the pestle. But for the most part the pestle<pb n="p.213"/> should be
					longer, so that the patient when standing may be almost suspended upon the piece
					of wood. And then the arm and forearm should be stretched along the pestle,
					whilst some person secures the opposite side of the body by throwing his arms
					round the neck, near the clavicle.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="6">
				<head>Part 6</head>
				<p> But the method with a ladder is another of the same kind, and still better,
					since by it the body can be more safely counterpoised on this side; and that,
					while in the method which the piece of wood resembling a pestle, there is danger
					of the body tumbling to either side. But some round thing should be tied upon
					the step of the ladder which may be fitted to the armpit, whereby the head of
					the bone may be forced into its natural place.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="7">
				<head>Part 7</head>
				<p> The following, however, is the strongest of all the methods of reduction. We
					must get a piece of wood, five, or at least four inches broad, two inches in
					thickness, or still thinner, and two cubits in length, or a little less; and its
					extremity at one end should be rounded, and made very narrow and very slender
					there, and it should have a slightly projecting edge (<hi rend="ital">ambe</hi>)
					on its round extremity, not on the part that is to be applied to the side, but
					to the head of the humerus, so that it may be adjusted in the armpit at the
					sides under the head of the humerus; and a piece of soft shawl or cloth should
					be glued to the end of the piece of wood, so as to give the less pain upon
					pressure. Then having pushed the head of this piece of wood as far inward as
					possible between the ribs and the head of the humerus, the whole arm is to be
					stretched along this piece of wood, and is to be bound round at the arm, the
					fore-arm, and the wrist, so that it may be particularly well secured; but great
					pains should be taken that the extremity of this piece of wood should be
					introduced as far as possible into the armpit, and that it is carried past the
					head of the humerus. Then a cross-beam is to be securely fastened between two
					pillars, and afterward the arm with the piece of wood attached to it is to be
					brought over this cross-beam, so that the arm may be on the one side of it and
					the body on the other, and the cross-beam in the armpit; and then the arm with
					the piece of wood is to be forced down on the one side of the cross-beam, and
					the rest of the body on the other. The cross-beam is to be bound so high that
					the <pb n="p.214"/>rest of the body may be raised upon tip-toes. This is by far
					the most powerful method of effecting reduction of the shoulder; for one thus
					operates with the lever upon the most correct principles, provided only the
					piece of wood be placed as much as possible within the head of the humerus, and
					thus also the counter-balancing weights will be most properly adjusted, and
					safely applied to the bone of the arm. Wherefore recent cases in this way may be
					reduced more quickly than could be believed, before even extension would appear
					to be applied; and this is the only mode of reduction capable of replacing old
					dislocations, and this it will effect, unless flesh has already filled up the
					(glenoid) cavity, and the head of the humerus has formed a socket for itself in
					the place to which it has been displaced; and even in such an old case of
					dislocation, it appears to me that we could effect reduction (for what object
					would a lever power properly applied not it move?), but it would not remain in
					its place, but would be again displaced as formerly. The same thing may be
					effected by means of the ladder, by preparing it in the same manner. If the
					dislocation be recent, a large Thessalian chair may be sufficient to accomplish
					this purpose; the wood, however, should be dressed up as described before; but
					the patient should be seated sideways on the chair, and then the arm, with the
					piece of wood attached to it, is to be brought over the back of the chair, and
					force is to be applied to the arm, with the wood on the one side, and the body
					on the other side. The same means may be applied with a double door. One should
					always use what happens to be at hand.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="8">
				<head>Part 8</head>
				<p> Wherefore it should be known that one constitution differs much from another as
					to the facility with which dislocations in them may be reduced, and one
					articular cavity differs much from another, the one being so constructed that
					the bone readily leaps out and another less so; but the greatest difference
					regards the binding together of the parts by the nerves (<hi rend="ital"
						>ligaments?</hi>) which are slack in some and tight in others. For the
					humidity in the joints of men is connected with the state of the ligaments, when
					they are slack and yielding; for you may see many people who are so humid (<hi
						rend="ital">flabby?</hi>) that when they choose they can disarticulate their
					joints without pain, and reduce them in like manner. The<pb n="p.215"/> habit of
					the body also occasions a certain difference, for in those who are in a state of
					embonpoint and fleshy the joint is rarely dislocated, but is more difficult to
					reduce; but when they are more attenuated and leaner than usual, then they are
					subject to dislocations which are more easily reduced. And the following
					observation is a proof that matters are so; for in cattle the thighs are most
					apt to be dislocated at the hip-joint, when they are most particularly lean,
					which they are at the end of winter, at which time then they are particularly
					subject to dislocations (if I may be allowed to make such an observation while
					treating of a medical subject); and therefore Homer has well remarked, that of
					all beasts oxen suffer the most at that season, and especially those employed at
					the plow as being worked in the winter season. In them, therefore, dislocations
					happen most frequently, as being at that time most particularly reduced in
					flesh. And other cattle can crop the grass when it is short, but the ox cannot
					do so until it becomes long; for, in the others, the projection of the lip is
					slender, and so is the upper lip, but in the ox the projection of the lip is
					thick, and the upper jaw is thick and obtuse, and therefore they are incapable
					of seizing short herbs. But the <hi rend="ital">solidungula</hi> as having
					prominent teeth in both their front jaws, can crop the grass and grasp it with
					their teeth while short, and delight more in short grass than in rank; for, in
					general, short grass is better and more substantial than rank, as having not yet
					given out its fructification. Wherefore the poet has the following line: "As
					when to horned cattle dear the vernal season comes,"<note>It is certain that
						there is no such line in the works of Homer as they have come down to us,
						and it is singular that Galen takes no notice of it, so that it is
						impossible to explain how our author came to use it.</note> because rank
					grass appears to be most sought after by them. But otherwise in the ox, this
					joint is slacker than in other animals, and, therefore, this animal drags his
					foot in walking more than any other, and especially when lank and old. For all
					these reasons the ox is most particularly subject to dislocations; and I have
					made the more observations respecting him, as they confirm <pb n="p.216"/>all
					that was said before on this subject. With regard, then, to the matter on hand,
					I say that dislocations occur more readily, and are more speedily reduced in
					those who are lean than in those who are fleshy; and in those who are humid and
					lank there is less inflammation than in such as are dry and fleshy, and they are
					less compactly knit hereafter, and there is more mucosity than usual in cases
					not attended with inflammation, and hence the joints are more liable to
					luxations; for, in the main, the articulations are more subject to mucosities in
					those who are lean than in those who are fleshy; and the flesh of lean persons
					who have not been reduced by a proper course of discipline abounds more with
					mucosity than that of fat persons. But in those cases in which the mucosity is
					accompanied with inflammation, the inflammation binds (<hi rend="ital"
						>braces?</hi>) the joint, and hence those who have small collections of
					mucosities are not very subject to dislocations, which they would be if the
					mucosity had not been accompanied with more or less inflammation.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="9">
				<head>Part 9</head>
				<p> In cases of dislocation those persons who are not attacked with inflammation of
					the surrounding parts, can use the shoulder immediately without pain, and do not
					think it necessary to take any precautions with themselves; it is therefore the
					business of the physician to warn them beforehand that dislocation is more
					likely to return in such cases than when the tendons have been inflamed. This
					remark applies to all the articulations, but particularly to those of the
					shoulder and knee, for these are the joints most subject to luxations. But those
					who have inflammation of the ligaments cannot use the shoulder, for the pain and
					the tension induced by the inflammation prevent them. Such cases are to be
					treated with cerate, compresses, and plenty of bandages; but a ball of soft
					clean wool is to be introduced into the armpit, to fill up the hollow of it,
					that it may be a support to the bandaging, and maintain the joint <hi
						rend="ital">in situ</hi>. The arm, in general, should be inclined upward as
					much as possible, for thus it will be kept at the greatest possible distance
					from the place at which the head of the humerus escaped. And when you bandage
					the shoulder you must fasten the arms to the sides with a band, which is to be
					carried round the body. The shoulder should be <pb n="p.217"/>rubbed gently and
					softly. The physician ought to be acquainted with many things, and among others
					with friction; for from the same name the same results are not always obtained;
					for friction could brace a joint when unseasonably relaxed, and relax it when
					unseasonably hard; but we will define what we know respecting friction in
					another place. The shoulder, then, in such a state, should be rubbed with soft
					hands; and, moreover, in a gentle manner, and the joint should be moved about,
					but not roughly, so as to excite pain. Things get restored sometimes in a
					greater space of time, and sometimes in a smaller.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="10">
				<head>Part 10</head>
				<p> A dislocation may be recognized by the following symptoms:-Since the parts of a
					man's body are proportionate to one another, as the arms and the legs, the sound
					should always be compared with the unsound, and the unsound with the sound, not
					paying regard to the joints of other individuals (for one person's joints are
					more prominent than another's), but looking to those of the patient, to
					ascertain whether the sound joint be unlike the unsound. This is a proper rule,
					and yet it may lead to much error; and on this account it is not sufficient to
					know this art in theory, but also by actual practice; for many persons from
					pain, or from any other cause, when their joints are not dislocated, cannot put
					the parts into the same positions as the sound body can be put into; one ought
					therefore to know and be acquainted beforehand with such an attitude. But in a
					dislocated joint the head of the humerus appears lying much more in the armpit
					than it is in the sound joint; and also, above, at the top of the shoulder, the
					part appears hollow, and the acromion is prominent, owing to the bone of the
					joint having sunk into the part below; there is a source of error in this case
					also, as will be described afterward, for it deserves to be described; and also,
					the elbow of the dislocated arm is farther removed from the ribs than that of
					the other; but by using force it may be approximated, though with considerable
					pain; and also they cannot, with the elbow extended, raise the arm to the ear,
					as they can the sound arm, nor move it about as formerly in this direction and
					that. These, then, are the symptoms of dislocation at the shoulder. The methods
					of reduction and the treatment are as described.<pb n="p.218"/>
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="11">
				<head>Part 11</head>
				<p>It deserves to be known how a shoulder which is subject to frequent dislocations
					should be treated. For many persons owing to this accident have been obliged to
					abandon gymnastic exercises, though otherwise well qualified for them; and from
					the same misfortune have become inept in warlike practices, and have thus
					perished. And this subject deserves to be noticed, because I have never known
					any physician treat the case properly; some abandon the attempt altogether, and
					others hold opinions and practice the very what is proper. For physicians have
					burned the shoulders subject to dislocation, at the top of the shoulder, at the
					anterior part where the head of the humerus protrudes, and a little behind the
					top of the shoulder; these burnings, if the dislocation of the arm were upward,
					or forward, or backward, would have been properly performed; but now, when the
					dislocation is downward, they rather promote than prevent dislocations, for they
					shut out the head of the humerus from the free space above. The cautery should
					be applied thus: taking hold with the hands of the skin at the armpit, it is to
					be drawn into the line, in which the head of the humerus is dislocated; and then
					the skin thus drawn aside is to be burnt to the opposite side. The burnings
					should be performed with irons, which are not thick nor much rounded, but of an
					oblong form (for thus they pass the more readily through), and they are to be
					pushed forward with the hand; the cauteries should be red-hot, that they may
					pass through as quickly as possible; for such as are thick pass through slowly,
					and occasion eschars of a greater breadth than convenient, and there is danger
					that the cicatrices may break into one another; which, although nothing very
					bad, is most unseemly, or awkward. When you have burnt through, it will be
					sufficient, in most cases, to make eschars only in the lower part; but if there
					is no danger of the ulcers passing into one another, and there is a considerable
					piece of skin between them, a thin spatula is to be pushed through these holes
					which have been burned, while, at the same time, the skin is stretched, for
					otherwise the instrument could not pass through; but when you have passed it
					through you must let go the skin, and then between the two eschars you should
					form another eschar with a <pb n="p.219"/>slender iron, and burn through until
					you come in contact with the spatula. The following directions enable you to
					determine how much of the skin of the armpit should be grasped; all men have
					glands in the armpit greater or smaller, and also in many other parts of the
					body. But I will treat in another work of the whole constitution of the glands,
					and explain what they are, what they signify, and what are their offices. The
					glands, then, are not to be taken hold of, nor the parts internal to the glands;
					for this would be attended with great danger, as they are adjacent to the most
					important nerves. But the greater part of the substances external to the glands
					are to be grasped, for there is no danger from them. And this, also, it is
					proper to know, that if you raise the arm much, you will not be able to grasp
					any quantity of skin worth mentioning, for it is all taken up with the
					stretching; and also the nerves, which by all means you must avoid wounding,
					become exposed and stretched in this position; but if you only raise the arm a
					little, you can grasp a large quantity of skin, and the nerves which you ought
					to guard against are left within, and at a distance from the operation. Should
					not, then, the utmost pains be taken in the whole practice of the art to find
					out the proper attitude in every case? So much regarding the armpit, and these
					contractions will be sufficient, provided the eschars be properly placed.
					Without the armpit there are only two places where one might place the eschars
					to obviate this affection; the one before and between the head of the humerus
					and the tendon at the armpit; and then the skin may be fairly burned through,
					but not to any great depth, for there is a large vein adjacent, and also nerves,
					neither of which must be touched with the heat. But externally, one may form
					another eschar considerably above the tendon at the armpit, but a little below
					the head of the humerus; and the skin must be burned fairly through, but it must
					not be made very deep, for fire is inimical to the nerves. Through the whole
					treatment the sores are to be so treated, as to avoid all strong extension of
					the arm, and this is to be done moderately, and only as far as the dressing
					requires; for thus they will be less cooled (for it is of importance to cover up
					all sorts of burns if one would treat them mildly), and then the<pb n="p.220"/>
					lips of them will be less turned aside; there will be less hemorrhage and fear
					of convulsions. But when the sores have become clean, and are going on to
					cicatrization, then by all means the arm is to be bound to the side night and
					day; and even when the ulcers are completely healed, the arm must still be bound
					to the side for a long time; for thus more especially will cicatrization take
					place, and the wide space into which the humerus used to escape will become
					contracted. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="12">
				<head>Part 12</head>
				<p> When attempts to reduce a dislocated shoulder have failed, if the patient be
					still growing, the bone of the affected arm will not increase like the sound
					one, for although it does increase in so far it becomes shorter than the other;
					and those persons called <hi rend="ital">weasel-armed</hi>, become so from two
					accidents, either from having met with this dislocation <hi rend="ital">in
						utero</hi>, or from another accident, which will be described afterward. But
					those who while they were children have had deep-seated suppurations about the
					head of the bone, all become weasel-armed; and this, it should be well known,
					will be the issue, whether the abscess be opened by an incision or cautery, or
					whether it break spontaneously. Those who are thus affected from birth are quite
					able to use the arm yet neither can they raise the arm to the ear, by extending
					the elbow, but they do this much less efficiently than with the sound arm. But
					in those who have had the shoulder dislocated after they were grown up, and when
					it has not been reduced, the top of the shoulder becomes much less fleshy, and
					the habit of body at that part is attenuated; but when they cease to have pain,
					whatever they attempt to perform by raising the elbow from the sides obliquely,
					they can no longer accomplish as formerly; but whatever acts are performed by
					carrying the arm around by the sides, either backward or forward, all those they
					can perform; for they can work with an auger or a saw, or with a hatchet, and
					can dig, by not raising the elbow too much, and do all other kinds of work which
					are done in similar attitudes. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="13">
				<head>Part 13</head>
				<p> In those cases where the acromion has been torn off, the bone which is thus
					separated appears prominent. The bone is the bond of connection between the
					clavicle and scapula, for in this respect the constitution of man is different
					from that of<pb n="p.221"/> other animals; physicians are particularly liable to
					be deceived in this accident (for as the separated bone protrudes, the top of
					the shoulder appears low and hollow), so that they make preparations as if for
					dislocation of the shoulder; for I have known many physicians, otherwise not
					inexpert at the art, who have done much mischief by attempting to reduce such
					shoulders, thus supposing it a case of dislocation; and they did not desist
					until they gave over mistake of supposing that they had reduced the shoulder.
					The treatment, in these cases, is similar to that which is applicable in others
					of a like kind, namely, cerate, compresses, and suitable bandaging with linen
					cloths. The projecting part must be pushed down, and the greater number of
					compresses are to be placed on it, and most compression is to be applied at that
					part, and the arm being fastened to the side is to be kept elevated; for thus
					the parts which had been torn asunder are brought into closest proximity with
					one another. All this should be well known, and if you choose you may
					prognosticate safely that no impediment, small or great, will result from such
					an injury at the shoulder, only there will be a deformity in the place, for the
					bone cannot be properly restored to its natural situation, but there must
					necessarily be more or less tumefaction in the upper part. For neither can any
					other bone be made exactly as it was, which having become incorporated with
					another bone, and having grown to it as an apophysis, has been torn from its
					natural situation. If properly bandaged, the acromion becomes free of pain in a
					few days. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="14">
				<head>Part 14</head>
				<p> When a fractured clavicle is fairly broken across it is more easily treated, but
					when broken obliquely it is more difficult to manage. Matters are different in
					these cases from what one would have supposed; for a bone fairly broken across
					can be more easily restored to its natural state, and with proper care the upper
					part may be brought down by means of suitable position and proper bandaging, and
					even if not properly set, the projecting part of the bone is not very sharp. But
					in oblique fractures the case is similar to that of bones which have been torn
					away, as formerly described; for they do not admit of being<pb n="p.222"/>
					restored to their place, and the prominence of the bone is very sharp. For the
					most part, then, it should be known, no harm results to the shoulder or to the
					rest of the body from fracture of the clavicle, unless it sphacelate, and this
					rarely happens. A deformity, however, may arise from fracture of the clavicle,
					and in these cases it is very great at first, but by and by it becomes less. A
					fractured clavicle, like all other spongy bones, gets speedily united; for all
					such bones form callus in a short time. When, then, a fracture has recently
					taken place, the patients attach much importance to it, as supposing the
					mischief greater than it really is, and the physicians bestow great pains in
					order that it may be properly bandaged; but in a little time the patients,
					having no pain, nor finding any impediment to their walking or eating, become
					negligent; and the physicians finding they cannot make the parts look well, take
					themselves off, and are not sorry at the neglect of the patients, and in the
					meantime the callus is quickly formed.<note>See the Plate at the end of the
						volume.</note> The method of dressing which is most appropriate, is similar
					to that used in ordinary cases, consisting of cerate, compresses, and bandages;
					and it should be most especially known in this operation, that most compresses
					should be placed on the projecting bone, and that the greatest pressure should
					be made there. There are certain physicians who make a show of superior skill by
					binding a heavy piece of lead on the part in order to depress the projecting
					bone; but this mode of treatment does not apply to the clavicle, for it is
					impossible to depress the projecting part to any extent worth mentioning. There
					are others who, knowing the fact that the bandages are apt to slip off, and that
					they do not keep the projecting parts in their place, apply compresses and
					bandages like the others, and then having girt the patient with a girdle, where
					it is usually applied with most effect, they make a heap of the compresses upon
					the projecting bone when they apply them, and having fastened the head of the
					bandage to the girdle in front, they apply it so as to bring the turns of it
					into the line of the clavicle, carrying them to the back, and then bringing them
					around the girdle they <pb n="p.223"/>carry them to the fore part and again
					backward. There are others who do not apply the bandage round the girdle, but
					carry the rounds of it by the perineum and anus, and along the spine, so as to
					compress the fracture. To an inexperienced person these methods will appear not
					far from natural, but when tied, they will be found of no service; for they do
					not remain firm any length of time, even if the patient keep his bed, although
					in this position they answer best; and yet even when lying in bed, should he
					bend his leg, or should his trunk be bent, all the will be displaced; and,
					moreover, the bandaging is inconvenient, in as much as the anus is comprehended
					by it, and many turns of the bandage are crowded there in a narrow space. And in
					the method with the girdle, the girdle cannot be so firmly girt around, but that
					the turns of the bandage force the girdle to ascend, and hence of necessity all
					the other bandages must be slackened. He would seem to me to come nearest his
					purpose, although after all he effects but little, who would take a few turns
					round the girdle, but would use the bandage principally to secure the former
					bandaging; for in this manner the bandages would be most secure, and would
					mutually assist one another. Every thing now almost has been said which applies
					to fracture of the clavicle. But this also should be known, that in fractures of
					the clavicle, it is the part attached to the breast which is uppermost, and that
					the piece attached to the acromion is the lowermost. The cause of this is, that
					for the most part the breast can neither be depressed nor raised, there being
					but a slight movement of the joint at the breast, for the sternum is connected
					together on both sides with the spine. The clavicle admits of most motion at the
					joint of the shoulder, and this arises from its connection with the acromion.
					And, moreover, when broken, the part which is connected with the sternum flies
					upward, and is not easily forced downward; for it is naturally light, and there
					is more room for it above than below. But the shoulder, the arm, and the parts
					connected with them, are easily moved from the sides and breast, and, on that
					account, they admit of being considerably elevated and depressed. When,
					therefore, the clavicle is broken, the fragment attached to the shoulder
					inclines downward, for it inclines much more readily <pb n="p.224"/>with the
					shoulder and arm downward than upward. Matters being as I have stated, they act
					imprudently who think to depress the projecting end of the bone. But it is clear
					that the under part ought to be brought to the upper, for the former is the
					movable part, and that which has been displaced from its natural position. It is
					obvious, therefore, that there is no other way of applying force to it (for the
					bandages no more force it to than they force it from); but if one will push the
					arm when at the sides as much as possible upward, so that the shoulder may
					appear as sharp as possible, it is clear that in this way it will be adjusted to
					the fragment of the bone connected with the breast from which it was torn. If
					one then will apply a bandage, <hi rend="ital">secundum artem</hi>, for the
					purpose of promoting a speedy cure, and will reckon everything else of no value,
					except the position as described, he will form a correct opinion of the case,
					and will effect a cure in the speediest and most appropriate manner. It is of
					great importance, however, that the patient should lie in a recumbent posture.
					Fourteen days will be sufficient if he keep quiet, and twenty at most. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="15">
				<head>Part 15</head>
				<p> But if the clavicle be fractured in the opposite manner (which does not readily
					happen), so that the fragment of bone connected with the breast is depressed,
					while the piece connected with the acromion is raised up and rides over other,
					this case does not require much management, for if the shoulder and arm be let
					go, the fragments of the bone will be adjusted to one another, and an ordinary
					bandage will suffice, and the callus will be formed in the course of a few days.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="16">
				<head>Part 16</head>
				<p> If the fracture be not thus, but if it incline either forward or backward, it
					may be restored to its natural position, by raising the shoulder with the arm as
					formerly described, and brought back to its natural place, when the cure will be
					speedily accomplished. Most of the varieties of displacement may be rectified by
					raising the arm upward. When the upper bone is displaced laterally or downward,
					it would favor the adaptation of the parts if the patient would lie on his back,
					and if some elevated substance were placed between the shoulder-blades, so that
					the breast may be depressed as much as possible upon the two sides; and if,
						while<pb n="p.225"/> another person raised the arm extended along the sides,
					the physician, applying the palm of the one hand to the head of the bone, would
					push it away, and with the other would adjust the broken bones, he would thus
					reduce the parts most readily to their natural position. But, as formerly
					stated, the upper bone (<hi rend="ital">sternal fragment?</hi>) is rarely
					depressed downward. In most cases, after the bandages have been applied, that
					position is beneficial in which the elbow is fixed to the same side, and the
					shoulder is kept elevated; but in certain cases, the shoulder is to be raised,
					as has been directed, and the elbow is to be brought forward to the breast, and
					the hand laid on the acromion of the sound side. If the patient has the
					resolution to lie in bed, something should be placed so as to support the
					shoulder, and keep it as much elevated as possible. But if he walk about, the
					arm should be slung in a shawl, which embraces the point of the elbow, and is
					passed round the neck. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="17">
				<head>Part 17</head>
				<p> When the elbow-joint is displaced or dislocated to the side or outward, while
					its sharp point (<hi rend="ital">olecranon?</hi>) remains in the cavity of the
					humerus, extension is to be made in a straight line, and the projecting part is
					to be pushed backward and to the side. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="18">
				<head>Part 18</head>
				<p> In complete dislocations toward either side, extension is to be made as in
					bandaging fracture of the arm; for thus the rounded part of the elbow will not
					form an obstacle to it. Dislocation, for the most part, takes place toward the
					sides (<hi rend="ital">inwardly?</hi>). Reduction is to be effected by
					separating (the bones) as much as possible, so that the end (of the humerus) may
					not come in contact with the olecranon, and it is to be carried up, and turned
					round, and not forced in a straight line, and, at the same time, the opposite
					sides are to be pushed together, and propelled into their proper place. It will
					further assist if rotation of the fore-arm be made at the elbow, sometimes
					turning it into a supine position, and sometimes into a prone. The position for
					the treatment consists in keeping the hand a little higher than the elbow, and
					the arm at the sides; then it may either be suspended or laid at rest, for
					either position will answer; and nature and the usage of common means will
					accomplish the cure, if the callus does not form improperly: it is formed
					quickly. The treatment<pb n="p.226"/> is to be conducted with bandages according
					to the rule for bandaging articulations, and the point of the elbow is to be
					included in the bandage. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="19">
				<head>Part 19</head>
				<p> Dislocations at the elbow give rise to the most serious consequences, such as
					fevers, pain, nausea, vomitings of pure bile, and more especially when the
					humerus is displaced backward from pressure on the nerve, which occasions
					numbness; next to it is the dislocation forward; the treatment is the same;
					reduction in dislocation backward is by extension and adaptation; the symptom of
					this variety-loss of the power of extension; of dislocation forward-loss of the
					power of flexion, and in this case reduction is to be accomplished by placing a
					hard ball (in the bend of the elbow), and bending the fore-arm about it, along
					with sudden extension. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="20">
				<head>Part 20</head>
				<p> Diastasis of the bones may be recognized by examining the part where the vein
					that runs along the arm divides. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="21">
				<head>Part 21</head>
				<p> In those cases callus is quickly formed. In congenital dislocations the bones
					below the seat of the injury are shorter than natural, and, mostly, those
					nearest to the place; namely, the bones of the fore-arm, next those of the hand;
					and, third, those of the fingers. The arm and shoulder are stronger, owing to
					the nourishment which they receive, and the other arm, from the additional work
					which it has to perform, is still more strong. Wasting of the flesh takes place
					on the inside if the dislocation be on the outside; or otherwise, on the side
					opposite the dislocation. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="22">
				<head>Part 22</head>
				<p> When the elbow is dislocated either inward or outward, extension is to be made
					with the fore-arm at a right angle to the arm; the arm, suspended by means of a
					shawl passed through the armpit, and a weight attached to the extremity of the
					elbow; or force may be applied with the hands; when the articular extremity has
					been cleared, the displaced parts are to be rectified with the palms of the
					hand, as in dislocations of the hands. It is to be bandaged, suspended in a
					sling, and placed while in this attitude. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="23">
				<head>Part 23</head>
				<p> Dislocations backward are to be rectified by the palms of the hands, along with
					sudden extension; the two acts are to be performed together, as in other cases
					of the kind. But in dislocation<pb n="p.227"/> forward the arm is to be bent
					around a ball of cloth of proper size, and at the same time replaced. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="24">
				<head>Part 24</head>
				<p> But if the displacement be on the other side, both these operations are to be
					performed in effecting the adjustment. For conducting the treatment, the
					position and bandaging are the same as in the other cases. But all these cases
					may be reduced by ordinary distention. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="25">
				<head>Part 25</head>
				<p> Of the methods of reduction, some operate by raising up the part, some by
					extension, and some by rotation: the last consists in rapidly turning the
					fore-arm to this side and that. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="26">
				<head>Part 26</head>
				<p> The joint of the hand is dislocated either inward or outward, most frequently
					inward. The symptoms are easily recognized: if inward, the patient cannot at all
					bend his fingers; and if outward, he cannot extend them. With regard to the
					reduction,-by placing the fingers above a table, extension and counter-extension
					are to be made by other persons, while with the palm or heel of the hand on the
					projecting bone one pushes forward, and another from behind on the other bone;
					some soft substance is to be applied to it, and the arm is to be turned to the
					prone position if the dislocation was forward, but to the supine, if backward.
					The treatment is to be conducted with bandages. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="27">
				<head>Part 27</head>
				<p> The whole hand is dislocated either inward or outward, or to this side or that,
					but more especially inward; and sometimes the epiphysis is displaced, and
					sometimes the other of these bones is separated. In these cases strong extension
					is to be applied, and pressure is to be made on the projecting bone, and
					counter-pressure on the opposite side, both at the same time, behind and at the
					side, with the hands upon a table, or with the heel. These accidents give rise
					to serious consequences and deformities; but in the course of time the part gets
					strong, and admits of being used. The cure is with bandages, which ought to
					embrace both the hand and fore-arm; and splints are to be applied as far as the
					fingers; and when they are used they should be more frequently unloosed than
					infractures, and more copious affusions of water should be used. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="28">
				<head>Part 28</head>
				<p> In congenital dislocations (at the wrist) the hand becomes <pb n="p.228"
					/>shortened, and the atrophy of the flesh occurs, for the most part, on the side
					opposite to the dislocation. In an adult the bones remain of their natural size.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="29">
				<head>Part 29</head>
				<p> Dislocation at the joint of a finger is easily recognized. Reduction is to be
					effected by making extension in a straight line, and applying pressure on the
					projecting bone, and counter-pressure on the opposite side of the other. The
					treatment is with bandages. When not reduced, callus is formed outside of the
					joint. When the dislocation takes place at birth, during adolescence the bones
					below the dislocation are shortened, and the flesh is wasted rather on the
					opposite than on the same side with the dislocation. When it occurs in an adult
					the bones remain of their proper size. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="30">
				<head>Part 30</head>
				<p> The jaw-bone, in few cases, is completely dislocated, for the zygomatic process
					formed from the upper jaw-bone (<hi rend="ital">malar?</hi>) and the bone behind
					the ear (<hi rend="ital">temporal?</hi>) shuts up the heads of the under jaw,
					being above the one (<hi rend="ital">condyloid process?</hi>), and below the
					other (<hi rend="ital">coronoid process?</hi>). Of these extremities of the
					lower jaw, the one, from its length, is not much exposed to accidents, while the
					other, the coronoid, is more prominent than the zygoma, and from both these
					heads nervous tendons arise, with which the muscles called temporal and masseter
					are connected; they have got these names from their actions and connections; for
					in eating, speaking, and the other functional uses of the mouth, the upper jaw
					is at rest, as being connected with the head by synarthrosis, and not by
					diarthrosis (<hi rend="ital">enarthrosis?</hi>): but the lower jaw has motion,
					for it is connected with the upper jaw and the head by enarthrosis. Wherefore,
					in convulsions and tetanus, the first symptom manifested is rigidity of the
					lower jaw; and the reason why wounds in the temporal region are fatal and induce
					coma, will be stated in another place. These are the reasons why complete
					dislocation does not readily take place, and this is another reason, because
					there is seldom a necessity for swallowing so large pieces of food as would make
					a man gape more than he easily can, and dislocation could not take place in any
					other position than in great gaping, by which the jaw is displaced to either
					side. This circumstance, however, contributes <pb n="p.229"/>to dislocation
					there; of nerves (<hi rend="ital">ligaments?</hi>) and muscles around joints, or
					connected with joints, such as are frequently moved in using the member are the
					most yielding to extension, in the same manner as well-dressed hides yield the
					most. With regard, then, to the matter on hand, the jaw-bone is rarely
					dislocated, but is frequently slackened (<hi rend="ital">partially
						displaced?</hi>) in gaping, in the same manner as many other derangements of
					muscles and tendons arise. Dislocation is particularly recognized by these
					symptoms: the lower jaw protrudes forward, there is displacement to the opposite
					side, the coronoid process appears more prominent than natural on the upper jaw,
					and the patient cannot shut his lower jaw but with difficulty. The mode of
					reduction which will apply in such cases is obvious: one person must secure the
					patient's head, and another, taking hold of the lower jaw with his fingers
					within and without at the chin, while the patient gapes as much as he can, first
					moves the lower jaw about for a time, pushing it to this side and that with the
					hand, and directing the patient himself to relax the jaw, to move it about, and
					yield as much as possible; then all of a sudden the operator must open the
					mouth, while he attends at the same time to three positions: for the lower jaw
					is to be moved from the place to which it is dislocated to its natural position;
					it is to be pushed backward, and along with these the jaws are to be brought
					together and kept shut. This is the method of reduction, and it cannot be
					performed in any other way. A short treatment suffices, a waxed compress is to
					be laid on, and bound with a loose bandage. It is safer to operate with the
					patient laid on his back, and his head supported on a leather cushion well
					filled, so that it may yield as little as possible, but some person must hold
					the patient's head.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="31">
				<head>Part 31</head>
				<p> When the jaw is dislocated on both sides, the treatment is the same. The
					patients are less able to shut the mouth than in the former variety; and the jaw
					protrudes farther in this case, but is not distorted; the absence of distortion
					may be recognized by comparing the corresponding rows of the teeth in the upper
					and lower jaws. In such cases reduction should be performed as quickly as
					possible; the method of reduction has been described<pb n="p.230"/> above. If
					not reduced, the patient's life will be in danger from continual fevers, coma
					attended with stupor (for these muscles, when disordered and stretched
					preternaturally, induce coma); and there is usually diarrhea attended with
					billous, unmixed, and scanty dejections; and the vomitings, if any, consist of
					pure bile, and the patients commonly die on the tenth day. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="32">
				<head>Part 32</head>
				<p> In fracture of the lower jaw, when the bone is not fairly broken across, and is
					still partially retained, but displaced, it should be adjusted by introducing
					the fingers at the side of the tongue, and making suitable counter-pressure on
					the outside; and if the teeth at the wound be distorted and loosened, when the
					bone is adjusted, they should be connected together, not only two, but more of
					them, with a gold thread, if possible, but otherwise, with a linen thread, until
					the bone be consolidated, and then the part is to be dressed with cerate, a few
					compresses, and a few bandages, which should not be very tight, but rather
					loose. For it should be well known that in fracture of the jaw, dressing with
					bandages, if properly performed, is of little advantage, but occasions great
					mischief if improperly done. Frequent examinations should be made about the
					tongue, and prolonged pressure should be applied with the fingers, in order to
					rectify the displaced bone. It would be best if one could do so constantly, but
					that is impossible. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="33">
				<head>Part 33</head>
				<p> But if the bone be fairly broken across (this, however, rarely happens), it is
					to be set in the manner now described. When adjusted, the teeth are to be
					fastened together as formerly described, for this will contribute much toward
					keeping the parts at rest, especially if properly fastened, and the ends of the
					thread secured with knots. But it is not easy to describe exactly in writing the
					whole manipulation of the case; but the reader must figure the thing to himself
					from the description given. Then one must take a piece of Carthaginian leather;
					if the patient be a younger person, it will be sufficient to use the outer skin,
					but if an adult the whole thickness of the hide will be required; it is to be
					cut to the breadth of about three inches, or as much as will be required, and
					having smeared the jaw with a little gum (for thus it sticks more pleasantly),
					the end of the skin is to be<pb n="p.231"/> fastened with the glue near the
					fractured part of the jaw, at the distance of an inch or a little more, from the
					wound. This piece is to be applied below the jaw; but the thong should have a
					cut in it, in the direction of the chin, so that it may go over the sharp point
					of the chin. Another piece of thong like this, or somewhat broader, is to be
					glued to the upper part of the jaw, at about the same distance from the wound as
					the other thong; this thong should be so cut as to encircle the ear. The thongs
					should be sharp-pointed at the part where they unite, and in gluing them, the
					flesh of the thong should be turned to the patient's skin, for in this way it
					will be more tenacious; then we must stretch this thong, but still more so the
					one at the chin, in order to prevent the fragments of the jaw from riding over
					each other, and the thongs are to be fastened at the vertex, and then a bandage
					is to be bound round the forehead, and a proper apparatus is to be put over all,
					to prevent the bandages from being displaced. The patient should lie upon the
					sound side of the jaw, not resting upon the jaw, but upon the head. He is to be
					kept on a spare diet for ten days, and then nourished without delay. If there be
					no inflammation during the first days, the jaw is consolidated in twenty days;
					for callus quickly forms in this, as in all the other porous bones, provided
					there be no sphacelus (<hi rend="ital">exfoliation?</hi>). But much remains to
					be said on the sphacelus of bones in another place. This method of distention
					with glued substances is mild, of easy application, and is useful for many
					dislocations in many parts of the body. Those physicians who have not judgment
					combined with their dexterity, expose themselves in fractures of the jaws, as in
					other cases, for they apply a variety of bandages to a fractured jaw-bone,
					sometimes properly, and sometimes improperly. For all such bandaging of a
					fractured jawbone has a tendency rather to derange the bones connected with the
					fracture, than to bring them into their natural position. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="34">
				<head>Part 34</head>
				<p> But if the lower jaw be disjointed at its symphysis in the chin (there is but
					one symphysis in the lower jaw, but there are several in the upper; but I am
					unwilling to digress from the subject, as these matters will have to be touched
					upon in other kinds of disease)-if, then, the symphysis be separated at the
					chin, it<pb n="p.232"/> is the work which anybody can perform, to rectify it;
					for the part which protrudes is to be pushed inward by pressure with the
					fingers, and the part that inclines inward is to forced outward by pushing with
					the fingers from within. It is after having applied extension to separate the
					fragments that this is to be done, for they will thus be more easily restored to
					their natural position, than if one should bring them together by using force.
					This is proper to be known as applying to all such cases. When you have set the
					parts, you must fasten the teeth on both sides to one another, as formerly
					directed. The treatment is to be accomplished with cerate, a few compresses, and
					bandages. This part, in particular, requires a short but complex (?) bandaging,
					for it is nearly cylindrical, though not exactly so; but the turn of the bandage
					is to be made, if the right jaw was dislocated, to the right hand (that is said
					to be to the right hand when the right hand conducts the bandaging); but if the
					other jaw be the seat of the dislocation, the bandaging is to be made in the
					other direction. And if matters be properly adjusted, and the patient keep
					quiet, there will be a speedy recovery, and the teeth will be uninjured; but if
					not, the recovery will be more protracted, the teeth will be distorted, will
					give trouble, and become useless. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="35">
				<head>Part 35</head>
				<p> Of fractures of the nose there are more than one variety, but those who, without
					judgment, delight in fine bandagings, do much mischief, most especially in
					injuries about the nose. For this is the most complex of all the forms of
					bandaging, having most of the turns of the bandage called "ascia," and
					rhomboidal intervals and uncovered spaces of the skin. As has been said, those
					who practice manipulation without judgment are fond of meeting with a case of
					fractured nose, that they may apply the bandage. For a day or two, then, the
					physician glories in his performance, and the patient who has been bandaged is
					well pleased, but speedily the patient complains of the incumbrance of the
					bandage, and the physician is satisfied, because he has had an opportunity of
					showing his skill in applying a complex bandage to the nose. Such a bandaging
					does everything the very reverse of what is proper; for, in the first place,
					those who have their nose flattened by the fracture, will clearly have the part
					rendered <pb n="p.233"/>still more flat, if pressure above be applied to it; and
					further, those cases in which the nose is distorted to either side, whether at
					the cartilage or higher up, will evidently derive no benefit from bandaging
					above it, but will rather be injured; for it will not admit of having compresses
					properly arranged on either side of the nose, and indeed, persons applying this
					bandage do not seek to do this.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="36">
				<head>Part 36</head>
				<p> This bandaging would appear to me to answer best when the skin surrounding the
					bone is contused on its ridge near the middle, or if the bone itself have
					sustained some injury, but not a great one, in such cases, redundant callus
					forms in the nose, and the part becomes a little too prominent; and yet, even in
					these cases, the bandaging need not require much trouble, if, indeed, any
					bandage be applied at all; for it is enough if one lay a waxed compress on the
					contusion, and then apply the double-headed bandage, thus taking one turn with
					it. The best application to such accidents is a small cataplasm of wheaten
					flour, washed, and mixed up into a viscid mass. If the flour be made from good
					wheat, and if it be glutinous, it should be used alone for all such cases, but
					if it be not very glutinous, a little of the manna of frankincense, well
					pulverized, is to be moistened with water, and the flour is to be mixed up with
					it, or a very little gum may be mixed in like manner. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="37">
				<head>Part 37</head>
				<p> In those cases in which the fractured portions are depressed and flattened, if
					it is depressed in front at the cartilage, something may be introduced into the
					nostrils to rectify the parts. If not, all such deformities may be restored by
					introducing the fingers into the nostrils, if this can be managed, but if not, a
					thick spatula is to be introduced with the fingers, not to the fore part of the
					nose, but to the depressed portion, and the physician is to take hold of the
					nose externally on both sides, and at the same time raise it up. And if the
					fracture be much in the fore part one may introduce into the nostrils as already
					stated, either caddis scraped from a linen towel, or something such wrapped up
					in a piece of cloth, or rather stitched in Carthaginian leather, and moulded
					into a shape suitable to the place into which it is to be introduced. But if the
					fracture be at a greater distance, it is<pb n="p.234"/> not possible to
					introduce anything within, for if it was irksome to bear anything of the kind in
					the fore part, how is it not to be so when introduced farther in? At first,
					then, by rectifying the parts from within, and sparing no pains upon them from
					without, they are to be brought to their natural position, and set. A fractured
					nose may be readily restored to shape, especially on the day of the accident, or
					even a little later, but the physicians act irresolutely, and touch it more
					delicately at first than they should; for the fingers should be applied on both
					sides along the natural line of the nose, and it is to be pushed downward, and
					thus, with pressure from within, the displacement is to be rectified. But for
					these purposes no physician is equal to the index-fingers of the patient
					himself, if he will pay attention and has resolution, for they are the most
					natural means. Either of the fingers is to be placed firmly along the whole
					nose, and thus it is to be gently held, and steadily, if possible until it
					become firm, but if not, he himself is to hold it for as long a time as
					possible, or if he cannot, a child or woman should do it, for the hands ought to
					be soft. Thus may a fracture of the nose, attended with depression, and not with
					displacement to the side, but in a straight line, be most properly treated. I
					have never seen a case of fractured nose which could not be rectified when
					attempted, before callus is formed, provided the treatment be properly applied.
					But although men would give a great price to escape being deformed, yet at the
					same time they do not know how to take care, nor have resolution, if they do not
					experience pain, nor fear death, although the formation of callus in the nose
					speedily place, for the most part is consolidated in ten days, provided
					sphacelus do not take place. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="38">
				<head>Part 38</head>
				<p> When the fractured bone is displaced laterally, the treatment is the same, but
					it is obvious that the reduction is to be made, not by applying equal force on
					both sides, but by pushing the displaced portion into its natural position, and
					pressing on it from without, and introducing something into the nostrils, and
					boldly rectifying the fragments which incline inward, until the whole be
					properly adjusted, well knowing that if you do not restore the parts at once, it
					is impossible but that the nose must<pb n="p.235"/> be distorted. But when you
					restore the parts to their natural position, either the patient himself, or some
					other person, is to apply one finger or more to the part which protrudes, and
					keep it in position until the fracture be consolidated; but the little finger
					is, from time to time, to be pushed into the nostril, to rectify the parts which
					incline inward. When any inflammation supervenes, dough must be used, but
					attention must still be equally paid to the application of the fingers, although
					the dough be on the part. But if the fracture be in the cartilage, with lateral
					displacement, the end of the nose must necessarily be distorted. In such cases
					some of the aforementioned means of reduction, or whatever suits, is to be
					introduced into the nostril; but there are many convenient things to be found
					which have no smell, and are appropriate in other respects; thus, on one
					occasion, I introduced a slice of sheep's lung, as it happened to be at hand;
					for sponges, if introduced, imbibe humidities. Then the outer skin of
					Carthaginian leather is to be taken, and a piece of the size of the thumb, or
					what will answer, is to be cut off and glued to the outside of the nostril which
					is turned aside, and then this piece of thong is to be stretched to the proper
					degree, or rather a little more than what will be sufficient to make the nose
					straight and regular. Then (for the thong must be long) it is to be brought
					below the ear and round the head, and the end of the thong may either be glued
					to the forehead, or a still longer one may be carried all round the head, and
					secured. This is a natural mode of setting the nose, is of easy application, and
					is calculated to enable the counter-extension on the nose to be made greater or
					less, as you may incline. In a case where the fractured nose is turned to the
					side, the treatment is to be conducted otherwise, as already described; and in
					most of them the thong ought to be glued to the end of the nose, in order to
					make extension in the opposite direction. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="39">
				<head>Part 39</head>
				<p> When the fracture is complicated with a wound, one need not be troubled on that
					account, but pitch-cerate or any of the applications for fresh wounds is to be
					applied to the sores; for, in general, they admit of easy cure, even when there
					is reason to apprehend that pieces of bone will come out. The parts, at first,
						<pb n="p.236"/>are to be adjusted fearlessly, taking care that nothing is
					omitted, and, subsequently, they are also to be adjusted with the fingers; more
					softly, indeed, but still it must be done; and of all parts of the body the nose
					is modeled with the greatest ease. And there is nothing to prevent us from
					having recourse to the practice of gluing on the thongs, and drawing the nose to
					the opposite side, even if there be a wound or the parts be inflamed, for these
					thongs give no pain. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="40">
				<head>Part 40</head>
				<p> In fractures of the ear all sorts of bandages do harm. For one would not think
					of applying it quite loose, and if applied more tightly, it only does the more
					harm, for even the sound ear, when confined with a bandage, becomes painful,
					throbs, and gets into a febrile state. With regard to cataplasms, the heaviest,
					on the whole, are the worst; but almost all kinds are bad, form abscesses,
					occasion an increase of humors, and afterward troublesome suppurations; and a
					fractured ear stands in less need of such applications than any other part; the
					most ready, if required, is the paste of meal, but neither should it have
					weight. It should touch as little as possible; for it is a good sometimes to
					apply nothing at all, both to the ear and to many other cases. Attention must be
					paid to the patient's position during sleep. And the body must be reduced, more
					especially if there be danger lest the ear suppurate; it will also be better to
					open the bowels, and if the patient can be readily made to vomit, this may be
					accomplished by means of the <hi rend="ital">syrmaism</hi>. If the part come to
					suppuration, it should not be hastily opened; for often when matter appears to
					be formed it is absorbed again, even when no cataplasm is applied. But if forced
					to open it, the part will get soonest well if transfixed with a cautery, and yet
					it should be well understood that the ear gets maimed, and is less than the
					other if burned through. If not burned through, an incision, and not a very
					small one, should be made on the upper side; for the pus is found to be
					surrounded with a thicker covering than one would have supposed; and it may be
					said, in general, that all parts of a mucous nature and which form mucus, as
					being all viscid, when touched, slip from below the fingers to either side; and
					on that account the physician, in such cases, finds that he has to pass his<pb
						n="p.237"/> instrument through a thicker substance than he supposed; and in
					certain ganglionic cases, when the skin is flabby and mucous, many physicians
					open them, expecting to find a collection in them; here the physician forms a
					wrong judgment, but by such a procedure no great harm results to the patient
					from having had the part opened. But with regard to watery parts, and such as
					are filled with mucus, and which are situated in regions where every one of the
					parts, if opened, will occasion death or some other injury, these will be
					treated of in another work. When, therefore, incision is made in the ear, all
					sorts of cataplasms and pledges should be avoided, and it is to be treated
					either with applications for recent wounds, or anything else which is neither
					heavy nor will occasion pain, for if the cartilage be laid bare and abscesses
					form, the case will be troublesome; this happens from such modes of treatment.
					In all aggravated cases, the most effectual remedy is the transfixing of the
					part with a hot iron. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="41">
				<head>Part 41</head>
				<p> The vertebrae of the spine when contracted into a hump behind from disease, for
					the most part cannot be remedied, more especially when the gibbosity is above
					the attachment of the diaphragm to the spine. Certain of those below the
					diaphragm are carried off by varices in the legs, more especially by such as
					occur in the vein at the ham; and in those cases where the gibbosities are
					removed, the varices take place also in the groin; and some have been carried
					off by a dysentery when it becomes chronic. And when the gibbosity occurs in
					youth before the body has attained its full growth, in these cases the body does
					not usually grow along the spine, but the legs and the arms are fully developed,
					whilst the parts (about the back) are arrested in their development. And in
					those cases where the gibbosity is above the diaphragm, the ribs do not usually
					expand properly in width, but forward, and the chest becomes sharp-pointed and
					not broad, and they become affected with difficulty of breathing and hoarseness;
					for the cavities which inspire and expire the breath do not attain their proper
					capacity. And they are under the necessity of keeping the neck bent forward at
					the great vertebra, in order that their head may not hang downward; this,
					therefore, occasions great contraction of the pharynx by its <pb n="p.238"
					/>inclination inward; for, even in those who are erect in stature, dyspnoea is
					induced by this bone inclining inward, until it be restored to its place. From
					this frame of body, such persons appear to have more prominent necks than
					persons in good health, and they generally have hard and unconcocted tubercles
					in the lungs, for the gibbosity and the distension are produced mostly by such
					tubercles, with which the neighboring nerves communicate. When the gibbosity is
					below the diaphragm, in some of these cases nephritic diseases and affections of
					the bladder supervene, but abscesses of a chronic nature, and difficult to cure,
					occur in the loins and groins, and neither of these carries off the gibbosity;
					and in these cases the hips are more emaciated than when the gibbosity is seated
					higher up; but the whole spine is more elongated in them than in those who have
					the gibbosity seated higher up, the hair of the pubes and chin is of slower
					growth and less developed, and they are less capable of generation than those
					who have the gibbosity higher up. When the gibbosity seizes persons who have
					already attained their full growth, it usually occasions a crisis of the then
					existing disease, but in the course of time some of them attack, as in the case
					of younger persons, to a greater or less degree; but, not withstanding, for the
					most part, all these diseases are less malignant. And yet many have borne the
					affection well, and have enjoyed good health until old age, more especially
					those persons whose body is inclined to be plump and fat; and a few of them have
					lived to beyond sixty years of age, but the most of them are more short-lived.
					In some cases the curvature of the spine is lateral, that is to say, either to
					the one side or the other; the most of such cases are connected with tubercles
						(<hi rend="ital">abscesses?</hi>) within the spine; and in some, the
					positions in which they have been accustomed to lie cooperate with the disease.
					But these will be treated of among the chronic affections of the lungs; for
					these the most suitable prognostics of what will happen in these cases are
					given. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="42">
				<head>Part 42</head>
				<p> When the spine protrudes backward, in consequence of a fall, it seldom happens
					that one succeeds in straightening it. Wherefore succussion on a ladder has
					never straightened anybody, as far as I know, but it is principally practiced by
					those <pb n="p.239"/>physicians who seek to astonish the mob-for to such persons
					these things appear wonderful, for example, if they see a man suspended or
					thrown down, or the like; and they always extol such practices, and never give
					themselves any concern whatever may result from the experiment, whether bad or
					good. But the physicians who follow such practices, as far as I have known them,
					are all stupid. The device, however, is an old one, and I give great praise to
					him who first invented this, and any other mechanical contrivance which is
					according to nature. For neither would I despair, but that if succussion were
					properly gone about, the spine, in certain cases, might be thereby rectified.
					But, indeed, for my own part, I have been ashamed to treat all such cases in
					this way, because such modes of procedure are generally practiced by charlatans.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="43">
				<head>Part 43</head>
				<p> Those cases in which the gibbosity is near the neck, are less likely to be
					benefited by these succussions with the head downward, for the weight of the
					head, and tops of the shoulders, when allowed to hang down, is but small; and
					such cases are more likely to be made straight by succussion applied with the
					feet hanging down, since the inclination downward is greater in this way. When
					the hump is lower down, it is more likely in this case that succussion with the
					head downward should do good. If one, then, should think of trying succussion,
					it may be applied in the following manner:-The ladder is to be padded with
					leather lined cushions, laid across, and well secured to one another, to a
					somewhat greater extent, both in length and breadth, than the space which the
					man's body will occupy; he is then to be laid on the ladder upon his back, and
					the feet, at the ankles, are to be fastened, at no great distance from one
					another, to the ladder, with some firm but soft band; and he is further to be
					secured, in like manner, both above and below the knee, and also at the nates;
					and at the groins and chest loose shawls are to be put round in such a fashion
					as not to interfere with the effect of the succussion; and his arms are to be
					fastened along his sides to his own body, and not to the ladder. When you have
					arranged these matters thus, you must hoist up the ladder, either to a high
					tower or to the gable-end of a house; but the place where you make the <pb
						n="p.240"/>succussion should be firm, and those who perform the extension
					should be well instructed, so that they may let go their hold equally to the
					same extent, and suddenly, and that the ladder may neither tumble to the ground
					on either side, nor they themselves fall forward. But, if the ladder be let go
					from a tower, or the mast of a ship, fastened into the ground with its cordage,
					it will be better, so that the ropes run upon a pulley or axle-tree. But it is
					disagreeable even to enlarge upon these matters; and yet, by the contrivances
					now described, the proper succussion may be made. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="44">
				<head>Part 44</head>
				<p> But if the hump be situated very high up, and if succussion be by all means to
					be used, it will be better to do it with the feet downward, as has been said,
					for the force downward will be the greater in this case. The patient is to be
					well fastened to the ladder by cords at the breast, at the neck by means of a
					very loose shawl so as merely to keep the part properly on the ladder, and the
					head is to be fastened to the ladder at the forehead, the arms are to be
					stretched along and attached to the patient's body, and not to the ladder, and
					the rest of the body is not to be bound, except so as to keep it in place by
					means of a loose shawl wrapped round it and the ladder; attention, moreover,
					should be paid that these ligatures do not interfere with the force of the
					succussion, and the legs are not to be fastened to the ladder, but should be
					placed near one another, so as to be in line with the spine. These matters
					should be thus arranged, if recourse is to be had at all to succussion on a
					ladder; for it is disgraceful in every art, and more especially in medicine,
					after much trouble, much display, and much talk, to do no good after all. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="45">
				<head>Part 45</head>
				<p> In the first place, the structure of the spine should be known, for this
					knowledge is requisite in many diseases. Wherefore, on the side turned to the
					belly (<hi rend="ital">the anterior?</hi>) the vertebrae are in a regular line,
					and are united together by a pulpy and nervous band of connection, originating
					from the cartilages, and extending to the spinal marrow. There are certain other
					nervous cords which decussate, are attached (<hi rend="ital">to the
						vertebrae?</hi>), and are extended from both sides of them. But we will
					describe in another work the connections of the veins and arteries, their<pb
						n="p.241"/> numbers, their qualities, their origin, their functional offices
					in particular parts, in what sort of sheaths the spinal marrow is inclosed,
					where they arise, where they terminate, how they communicate, and what their
					uses. On the opposite side (<hi rend="ital">behind?</hi>) the vertebrae are
					connected together by a ginglymoid articulation. Common cords (<hi rend="ital"
						>nerves?</hi>) are extended to all parts, both those within and without.
					There is an osseous process from the posterior part of all and each of the
					vertebra, whether greater or smaller; and upon these processes there are
					cartilaginous epiphyses, and from them arise nervous productions (<hi
						rend="ital">ligaments?</hi>), akin to the external nerves (<hi rend="ital"
						>tonoi</hi>). The ribs are united to them, having their heads inclined
					rather to the inside than the out, and every one of them is articulated with the
					vertebrae; and the ribs in man are very curved, and, as it were, arched. The
					space between the ribs and the processes of the vertebrae is filled on both
					sides by muscles, which arise from the neck and extend to the loins (<hi
						rend="ital">?</hi>). The spine, longitudinally, is a straight line slightly
					curved; from the os sacrum to the great vertebra which is connected with the
					articulation of the femur, the spine inclines backward, for the bladder, the
					organs of generation, and the loose portion of the rectum, are situated there.
					From this, to the attachment of the diaphragm, the spine inclines inward, and
					this portion alone, from the internal parts, gives origin to muscles, which are
					called <hi rend="ital">psoae</hi>. From this to the great vertebra (<hi
						rend="ital">seventh cervical?</hi>) which is above the tops of the
					shoulders, it is convex behind lengthways; but it is more in appearance than it
					really is, for the spinous processes are highest in the middle, and less so
					above and below. The region of the neck is convex before. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="46">
				<head>Part 46</head>
				<p> In cases of displacement backward along the vertebrae, it does not often happen,
					in fact, it is very rare, that one or more vertebrae are torn from one another
					and displaced. For such injuries do not readily occur, as the spine could not
					easily be displaced backward but by a severe injury on the fore part through the
					belly (which would prove fatal), or if a person falling from a height should
					pitch on the nates, or shoulders (and even in this case he would die, but not
					immediately); and it also would not readily happen that such a displacement
					could take place <pb n="p.242"/>forward, unless some very heavy weight should
					fall upon it behind; for each of the posterior spinal processes is so
					constructed, that it would sooner be broken than undergo any great inclination
					forward from a force which would have to overcome the ligaments and the
					articulations mutually connecting them. And the spinal marrow would suffer, if
					from the displacement of a vertebra it were to be bent even to a small extent;
					for the displaced vertebra would compress the spinal marrow, if it did not break
					it; and if compressed and strangled, it would induce insensibility of many great
					and important parts, so that the physician need not give himself any concern
					about rectifying the displacement of the vertebra, accompanied, as it is, by
					many other ill consequences of a serious nature. It is evident, then, that such
					a case could not be reduced either by succussion or by any other method, unless
					one were to cut open the patient, and then, having introduced the hand into one
					of the great cavities, were to push outward from within, which one might do on
					the dead body, but not at all on the living. Wherefore, then, do I write all
					this? Because certain persons fancy that they have cured patients in whom the
					vertebra had undergone complete dislocation forward. Some, indeed, suppose that
					this is the easiest of all these dislocations to be recovered from, and that
					such cases do not stand in need of reduction, but get well spontaneously. Many
					are ignorant, and profit by their ignorance, for they obtain credit from those
					about them. These are deceived in this way, for they suppose the spinous
					processes to be the vertebrae themselves, because every one of them appears
					round to the touch, not knowing that these bones are processes from the
					vertebrae, as formerly stated; but the vertebrae are at a considerable distance
					before them; for of all animals, man, in proportion to his bulk, has the belly
						(<hi rend="ital">internal cavity?</hi>) the narrowest from behind to before,
					especially at the breast. When, therefore, any of these processes are severely
					fractured, whether one or more, the part there appears lower than on either
					side, and for that reason they are deceived, supposing that the vertebrae are
					displaced inward. And the attitudes of the patient contribute also to deceive
					them; for if they attempt to put themselves into a bent position, they <pb
						n="p.243"/>are pained, from the skin being stretched at the seat of the
					injury, and at the same time the fragments of the bones wound the skin still
					more; but if they bend forward, they feel easier, for the skin at the wound is
					thus relaxed, and the bones are less disposed to hurt them; and if touched, they
					shrink and bend forward, and the part which is touched appears empty and soft.
					All the circumstances now mentioned contribute to deceive the physician. Such
					patients speedily get well without any bad effects, for callus readily forms in
					all such bones as are porous. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="47">
				<head>Part 47</head>
				<p> There are many varieties of curvature of the spine even in persons who are in
					good health; for it takes place from natural conformation and from habit, and
					the spine is liable to be bent from old age, and from pains. Gibbosities (<hi
						rend="ital">or</hi> projections backward) from falls generally take place
					when one pitches on the nates, or falls on the shoulders. In this case some one
					of the vertebrae must necessarily appear higher than natural, and those on
					either side to a less degree; but yet no one generally has started out of the
					line of the others, but every one has yielded a little, so that a considerable
					extent of them is curved. On this account the spinal marrow easily bears such
					distortions, because they are of a circular shape, and not angular. The
					apparatus for the reduction in this case must be managed in the following
					manner: a strong and broad board, having an oblong furrow in it, is to be
					fastened in the ground, or, in place of the board, we may scoop out an oblong
					furrow in the wall, about a cubit above the floor, or at any suitable height,
					and then something like an oaken bench, of a quadrangular shape, is to be laid
					along (the wall?) at a distance from the wall, which will admit of persons to
					pass round if necessary, and the bench is to be covered with robes, or anything
					else which is soft, but does not yield much; and the patient is to be stoved
					with vapor, if necessary, or bathed with much hot water, and then he is to be
					stretched along the board on his face, with his arms laid along and bound to his
					body; the middle, then, of a thong which is soft, sufficiently broad and long,
					and composed of two cross straps of leather, is to be twice carried along the
					middle of the patient's breast, as near the armpits as possible, then what is
					over of the thongs at the armpits is <pb n="p.244"/>to be carried round the
					shoulders, and afterward the ends of the thong are to be fastened to a piece of
					wood resembling a pestle; they are to be adapted to the length of the bench laid
					below the patient, and so that the pestle-like piece of wood resting against
					this bench may make extension. Another such band is to be applied above the
					knees and the ankles, and the ends of the thongs fastened to a similar piece of
					wood; and another thong, broad, soft, and strong, in the form of a swathe,
					having breadth and length sufficient, is to be bound tightly round the loins, as
					near the hips as possible; and then what remains of this swathelike thong, with
					the ends of the thongs, must be fastened to the piece of wood placed at the
					patient's feet, and extension in this fashion is to be made upward and downward,
					equally and at the same time, in a straight line. For extension thus made could
					do no harm, if properly performed, unless one sought to do mischief purposely.
					But the physicians, or some person who is strong, and not uninstructed, should
					apply the palm of one hand to the hump, and then, having laid the other hand
					upon the former, he should make pressure, attending whether this force should be
					applied directly downward, or toward the head, or toward the hips. This method
					of applying force is particularly safe; and it is also safe for a person to sit
					upon the hump while extension is made, and raising himself up, to let himself
					fall again upon the patient. And there is nothing to prevent a person from
					placing a foot on the hump, and supporting his weight on it, and making gentle
					pressure; one of the men who is practiced in the palestra would be a proper
					person for doing this in a suitable manner. But the most powerful of the
					mechanical means is this: if the hole in the wall, or in the piece of wood
					fastened into the ground, be made as much below the man's back as may be judged
					proper, and if a board, made of limetree, or any other wood, and not too narrow,
					be put into the hole, then a rag, folded several times or a small leather
					cushion, should be laid on the hump; nothing large, however, should be laid on
					the back, but just as much as may prevent the board from giving unnecessary pain
					by its hardness; but the hump should be as much as possible on a line with the
					hole made in the wall, so that the board introduced into it may <pb n="p.245"
					/>make pressure more especially at that spot. When matters are thus adjusted,
					one person, or two if necessary, must press down the end of the board, whilst
					others at the same time make extension and counter-extension as along the body,
					as formerly described. Extension may also be made with axles, which may either
					be fastened in the ground beside the bench, or the post of the axles may be
					attached to the bench itself, if you will make them perpendicular and
					overtopping (<hi rend="ital">the bench?</hi>) a little at both ends, or at
					either end of the bench. These powers are easily regulated, so as to be made
					stronger or weaker, and they are of such force, that if one were to have
					recourse to them for a mischievous purpose, and not as a remedy, they would
					operate strongly in this way also; for by making merely extension and
					counter-extension longitudinally, without any additional force, one might make
					sufficient extension; and if, without making extension at all, one were only to
					press down properly with the board, sufficient force might be applied in this
					way. Such powers, then, are excellent which admit of being so regulated, that
					they can be made weaker and stronger as required. And the forces are applied in
					the natural way; for the pressure above forces the displaced parts into their
					place. Natural extension restores parts which have come too near one another to
					their natural position. I, then, am acquainted with no powers which are better
					or more appropriate than these; for extension along the spine downward has no
					proper hold at the bone called the os sacrum; and extension upward, along the
					neck and head, has indeed a hold; but extension thus made is unseemly to behold,
					and, besides, if increased, may occasion much mischief otherwise. I once made
					trial of the following plan. Having placed the patient on his back, I put below
					the hump a bladder, not inflated, and afterward introduced air into the bladder
					by means of a brass pipe connected with it. But the experiment did not succeed;
					for, when the man was fairly extended, the bladder yielded, and the air could
					not be forced into it; and, besides, the hump of the patient was apt to slip off
					the distended bladder when they were pressed together. But when I did not extend
					the man strongly, the bladder was swelled up by the air, and the man became more
					bent forward <pb n="p.246"/> than proper. I have written this expressly; for it
					is a valuable piece of knowledge to learn what things have been tried and have
					proved ineffectual, and wherefore they did not succeed.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="48">
				<head>Part 48</head>
				<p> In curvatures forward of the vertebrae from a fall, or from some heavy body
					falling upon them, in general no one of them is displaced far beyond the others,
					but if one or more be so displaced, the case proves fatal; but, not
					withstanding, as formerly stated, the displacement is circular, and not angular.
					In such cases, then, the urine and faeces are more apt to be retained than in
					displacement outward, the feet and the whole inferior extremities are colder,
					and the symptoms are more fatal than in the former case; and if they do survive,
					they are more subject to retention of the urine, and to loss of strength, and to
					torpor in their legs. But if the displacement be in the upper part, they
					experience loss of strength and torpor of the whole body. I know no mechanical
					contrivance by which such a displacement could be reduced, unless that one might
					be benefited by succussion on a bladder, or any other similar plan of treatment,
					such as extension, as formerly described. I am not aware of any mode of pressure
					which might be applied along with the extension, like that of the board in
					displacement backward; for how could one apply pressure from before through the
					belly? (<hi rend="ital">internal cavity?</hi>) The thing is impossible. But
					neither coughing nor sneezing has any power so as to cooperate with the
					extension, nor would the injection of air into the bowels have any effect. And
					to apply large cupping instruments with the view of drawing back the vertebrae
					which have protruded forward, shows a great error of judgment; for they rather
					propel than attract, and those who apply them are not aware even of this fact,
					for the greater will be the inclination forward the greater the instrument
					applied, the skin being forcibly drawn into the cupping-instrument. I could tell
					of other modes of succussion than those formerly described, which one might
					fancy would be more applicable in such an affection; but I have no great
					confidence in them, and therefore I do not describe them. On the main, it should
					be known, respecting the accidents which I have briefly described, that
					displacements forward are of a fatal and injurious nature; but that
					displacements backward, <pb n="p.247"/>for the most part, do not prove fatal,
					nor occasion retention of urine nor torpor of the limbs, for they do not stretch
					the ducts leading toward the intestines, nor occasion obstruction of the same;
					but displacements forward produce both these bad effects, and many others in
					addition. And truly they are more apt to lose the power of their legs and arms,
					to have torpor of the body, and retention of urine, who experience no
					displacement either forward or backward, but merely a violent concussion along
					the spine, while those who have displacement backward are least subject to these
					symptoms. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="49">
				<head>Part 49</head>
				<p> And one might observe many other instances in medicine, of considerable injuries
					not proving serious, but producing a crisis in some affection, while less
					considerable injuries prove more serious, give rise to chronic diseases, and
					extend their effects to the whole system. Now something similar may happen in
					fracture of the ribs; for in fracture of one or more ribs, in general, if the
					fractured bones are not driven inward, nor are laid bare, fever rarely
					supervenes, neither does it often happen that there is haemoptysis, empyema, and
					suppurating sores, which require treatment with pledgets, nor necrosis of the
					bones; and in these cases the ordinary regimen is sufficient. For, unless they
					be seized with continual fever, a strict diet does more harm than good, by
					inducing inanition, and increasing the pain, fever, and cough; for moderate
					fullness of the intestines has a tendency to replace the ribs, while evacuation
					leads to suspension of the ribs, and suspension induces pain. Ordinary
					bandaging, externally, is sufficient in such cases; the bandages should be
					applied moderately tight, along with cerate and compresses, or a pad of wool may
					be applied. The rib is consolidated in twenty days, for callus soon forms in
					such bones. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="50">
				<head>Part 50</head>
				<p> But when there is contusion of the flesh about the ribs, either from a blow, or
					a fall, or a bruise, or any like cause, there is often copious vomiting of
					blood, for there are canals stretched along the vacuity of each rib (<hi
						rend="ital">intercostal space?</hi>), and nerves proceeding from the most
					important parts of the body have their origin there. Many of these, therefore,
					are troubled with coughs, tubercles, empyema, external suppurations, and
					sphacelus of the <pb n="p.248"/>ribs. And even when no such symptoms supervene
					from contusion of the skin about the ribs, still in such cases there is,
					generally, more combined pain than in fractures of the ribs, and relapses of
					pain in the seat of the injury are more apt to occur. Wherefore some physicians
					pay much less attention to such injuries, than where the rib is fractured,
					whereas, if they were wise, they would treat such cases with far greater care
					than the other; for it is proper that the diet should be restricted, that the
					patients should remain at rest as much as possible, and abstain from venery,
					from fat articles of food, from such as excite cough, and from everything
					strong; they should be bled in the arm, speak as little as possible, should have
					the contused part bound round with folded compresses, plenty of bandages,
					broader than the contusion, and which should be smeared with cerate; in applying
					the bandages, broad and soft shawls should be used, and they should be put on
					moderately firm, so that the patient will say that they are neither too tight
					nor loose, and the bandaging should commence at the seat of the injury, and be
					made more particularly tight there, and the bandaging should be conducted as is
					done with a double-headed roller, so that the skin about the ribs may not be
					ruffled, but may lie smooth, and the bandaging should be renewed every day, or
					every alternate day. It is better also to open the bowels with some gentle
					medicine, so as just to produce an evacuation of the food, and the diet is to be
					restricted for ten days, and then the body is to be recruited and filled up;
					while you are upon the reducing system, the bandaging should be tighter, but
					when you are making him up again, it must be looser; and, if he spit blood from
					the commencement, the treatment and bandaging should be continued for forty
					days; but if there be no haemoptysis, treatment for twenty days will generally
					be sufficient; but the length of time must be regulated by the magnitude of the
					injury. When such contusions are neglected, if no greater mischief result there
					from, at all events the bruised part has its flesh more pulpy than it had
					formerly. When, therefore, any such thing is left behind, and is not properly
					dissipated by the treatment, it will be worse if the mucosity be lodged near the
					bone, for the flesh no longer adheres to the bone <pb n="p.249"/>as formerly,
					the bone becomes diseased, and chronic sloughings of the bone in many cases
					arise from such causes. But if the mischief be not upon the bone, but it is the
					flesh itself which is pulpy, relapses and pains will return from time to time,
					if there happen to be any disorder in the body; wherefore proper bandaging, and
					for a considerable time, must be had recourse to, until the extravasated blood
					forming in the bruise be dried up and absorbed, and the part be made up with
					sound flesh, and the flesh adhere to the bone. The best cure is the cautery in
					those cases which, from neglect, have become chronic, and the place turns
					painful, and the flesh is pulpy. And when the flesh itself is pulpy, the burning
					should be carried as far as the bone, but the bone itself should not be heated;
					but if it be in the intercostal space, you need not make the burning so
					superficial, only you must take care not to burn quite through. But if the
					contusion appear to be at the bone, if it be still recent, and the bone has not
					yet become necrosed, if it be very small, it is to be burned as has been
					described; but if the rising along the bone be oblong, several eschars are to be
					burned over it. Necrosis of the rib will be described along with the treatment
					of suppurating sores.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="51">
				<head>Part 51</head>
				<p> There are four modes of dislocation at the hip-joint: of which modes,
					dislocation inward takes place most frequently, outward, the most frequently of
					all the other modes; and it sometimes takes place backward and forward, but
					seldom. When, therefore, dislocation takes place inward, the leg appears longer
					than natural, when compared with the other leg, for two reasons truly; for the
					bone which articulates with the hip-joint is carried from above down to the
					ischium where it rises up to the pubes, upon it, then, the head of the femur
					rests, and the neck of the femur is lodged in the cotyloid foramen (<hi
						rend="ital">foramen thyroideum?</hi>). The buttock appears hollow
					externally, from the head of the thighbone having shifted inward, and the
					extremity of the femur at the knee is turned outward, and the leg and foot in
					like manner. The foot then being turned outward, physicians, from ignorance,
					bring the sound leg to it and not it to the sound leg; on this account, the
					injured limb appears to be much longer than the sound one, and in many other
					cases similar circumstances <pb n="p.250"/>lead to error in judgment. Neither
					does the limb at the groin admit of flexion as in the sound limb, and the head
					of the bone is felt at the perineum too prominent. These, then, are the symptoms
					attending dislocation of the thigh inward. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="52">
				<head>Part 52</head>
				<p> When, then, a dislocation has not been reduced, but has been misunderstood or
					neglected, the leg, in walking, is rolled about as is the case with oxen, and
					the weight of the body is mostly supported on the sound leg, and the limb at the
					flank, and the joint where the dislocation has occurred is necessarily hollow
					and bent, while on the sound side the buttock is necessarily rounded. For if one
					should walk with the foot of the sound leg turned outward, the weight of the
					body would be thrown upon the injured limb, but the injured limb could not carry
					it, for how could it? One, then, is forced in walking to turn the leg inward,
					and not outward, for thus the sound leg best supports its own half of the body,
					and also that of the injured side. But being hollow at the flank and the
					hip-joint, they appear small in stature, and are forced to rest on a staff at
					the side of the sound leg. For they require the support of a staff there, since
					the nates inclines to this side, and the weight of the body is carried to it.
					They are forced also to stoop, for they are obliged to rest the hand on the side
					of the thigh against the affected limb; for the limb which is injured cannot
					support the body in changing the legs, unless it be held when it is applied to
					the ground. They who have got an unreduced dislocation inward are forced to put
					themselves into these attitudes, and this from no premeditation on their part
					how they should assume the easiest position, but the impediment itself teaches
					them to choose that which is most conformable to their present circumstances.
					For persons who have a sore on the foot, or leg, and cannot rest upon the limb,
					all, even children, walk in this way; for they turn the injured limb outward in
					walking, and they derive two advantages therefrom, to supply two wants; the
					weight of the body is not equally thrown upon the limb turned outward, as upon
					the one turned inward, for neither is the weight in a line with it, but is much
					more thrown upon the one under the body; for the weight is in a straight line
					with it, both in walking and in the shifting of the legs. In this <pb n="p.251"
					/>position one can most quickly turn the sound limb under the body, by walking
					with the unsound limb outward, and the sound inward. In the case we are now
					treating of, it is well that the body finds out the attitudes which are the
					easiest for itself. Those persons, then, who have not attained their growth at
					the time when they met with a dislocation which is not reduced, become maimed in
					the thigh, the leg, and the foot, for neither do the bones grow properly, but
					become shortened, and especially the bone of the thigh; and the whole limb is
					emaciated, loses its muscularity, and becomes enervated and thinner, both from
					the impediment at the joint, and because the patient cannot use the limb, as it
					does not lie in its natural position, for a certain amount of exercise will
					relieve excessive enervation, and it will remedy in so far the deficiency of
					growth in length. Those persons, then, are most maimed who have experienced the
					dislocation <hi rend="ital">in utero</hi>, next those who have met with it in
					infancy, and least of all, those who are full grown. The mode of walking adopted
					by adults has been already described; but those who are children when this
					accident befalls them, generally lose the erect position of the body, and crawl
					about miserably on the sound leg, supporting themselves with the hand of the
					sound side resting on the ground. Some, also, who had attained manhood before
					they met with this accident, have also lost the faculty of walking erect. Those
					who were children when they met with the accident, and have been properly
					instructed, stand erect upon the sound leg, but carry about a staff, which they
					apply under the armpit of the sound side, and some use a staff in both arms; the
					unsound limb they bear up, and the smaller the unsound limb, the greater
					facility have they in walking, and their sound leg is no less strong than when
					both are sound. The fleshy parts of the limb are enervated in all such cases,
					but those who have dislocation inward are more subject to this loss of strength
					than, for the most part, those who have it outward. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="53">
				<head>Part 53</head>
				<p> Some tell a story how the Amazonian women dislocate the joints of their male
					children while mere infants, some at the knee, and others at the hip-joint, that
					they may be maimed, and that the male sex may not conspire against the female,
					and that <pb n="p.252"/>they use them as artisans to perform any sedentary work,
					such as that of a shoemaker or brazier. Whether these things be true or not I do
					not know, but this I know, that matters would be such as is represented,
					provided their children, while infants, were to have their joints dislocated.
					The consequences of dislocation inward at the hip-joint are much greater than of
					dislocation outward at the hip-joint, but at the knee, although there be some
					difference, it is less; but the mode of either impediment is peculiar, their
					legs are more bandied when the dislocation is outward, but those who have
					dislocation inward stand erect on their feet with less freedom. In like manner,
					when the dislocation is at the anklejoint, if outward they become <hi
						rend="ital">vari</hi> (<hi rend="ital">their toes are turned inward?</hi>),
					but they can stand; but if the dislocation be inward they become <hi rend="ital"
						>valgi</hi> (<hi rend="ital">their toes are turned outward?</hi>), but they
					have less freedom of standing. The proportional growth of their bones is as
					follows: in those cases in which the bone of the leg is dislocated, the bones of
					the feet grow very little, as being very near the injury, but the bones of the
					leg increase in size, and with very little defect, but the fleshy parts (<hi
						rend="ital">muscles?</hi>) are wasted. But when the ankle-joint is in its
					natural state, but the knee is dislocated, in these cases the bones of the leg
					do not grow in like manner, but become shortened, as being nearest the seat of
					the injury, and the bones of the feet also are atrophied, but not in the same
					proportion; because, as was said a little while ago, the ankle-joint is safe,
					and if they could use it, as in the case of club-foot, the bones of the foot
					would be still less atrophied. When the dislocation takes place at the
					hip-joint, the bone of the thigh, in this case, does not generally grow in like
					manner, as being the one nearest the seat of the injury, but becomes shorter
					than the sound one; but the growth of the bones of the leg is not arrested in
					like manner; nor of those of the feet, for this reason, that there is no
					displacement between the bones of the thigh and leg, nor between those of the
					leg and foot; in those cases, however, the fleshy parts of the whole limb are
					atrophied; but if they could make use of the limb, the growth of the bones would
					be still more developed, as formerly stated, only the thigh, although its flesh
					would be much less wasted, would <pb n="p.253"/>still be by no means so fleshy
					as the sound limb. The following observations are a proof of this: those persons
					who are weasel-armed (<hi rend="ital">galiancones</hi>) from birth, owing to
					dislocation of the humerus, or when the accident has happened to them before
					they have attained their full growth, such persons have the bone of the arm
					shortened, but those of the fore-arm and hand are little inferior in size to the
					sound, for the reasons which have been stated, because the humerus is the bone
					nearest to the joint affected, and, on that account, it is shorter than natural;
					but the fore-arm is not equally affected by the accident, because the joint at
					which the bones of the arm and forearm are articulated remains in its natural
					condition, and the hand is still further distant than the fore-arm from the seat
					of the injury. Such are the reasons why certain of the bones in this case
					increase in growth, and certain do not. The laborious office of the hand
					contributes much to the development of the flesh in the fore-arm and hand, for
					whatever work is done by the hand, these weasel-armed persons strive to do no
					less effectually with the other hand than with the sound; for the arms do not
					support the weight of the body like the legs, and the work performed by them is
					light. From exercise, then, the fleshy parts on the hand and fore-arm are not
					atrophied in weasel-armed persons, and by these means the arm, too, gains flesh.
					But in dislocation inward at the hip-joint, whether from birth or from
					childhood, the fleshy parts, on that account, are much more atrophied than those
					of the hand, because the patients cannot exercise the leg. Another proof will be
					given in the observations which will be presently stated, that these things are
					such as I things are such as I have represented. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="54">
				<head>Part 54</head>
				<p> When the head of the femur is dislocated outward, the limb in these cases, when
					compared with the other, appears shortened, and this is natural, for the head of
					the femur no longer rests on a bone as in dislocation inward, but along the side
					of a bone which naturally inclines to the side, and it is lodged in flesh of a
					pulpy and yielding nature, and on that account it appears more shortened.
					Inwardly, the thigh about the perineum appears more hollow and flabby, but
					externally the buttock is more rounded, from the head of the thigh having
					slipped outward, but <pb n="p.254"/>the nates appear to be raised up, owing to
					the flesh there having yielded to the head of the thigh-bone; but the extremity
					of the thigh-bone, at the knee, appears to be turned inward, and the leg and
					foot in like manner, neither does it admit of flexion like the sound limb.
					These, then, are the symptoms of dislocation outward. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="55">
				<head>Part 55</head>
				<p> When such a dislocation is not reduced in adults, the whole limb appears to be
					shortened, and in walking they cannot reach the ground with the heel, but they
					walk with the ball of the foot on the ground, and the points of their toes
					incline a little inward. But the injured limb, in this case, can support the
					body much better than in dislocation inward, both because the head of the femur
					and the neck of its articular extremity, being naturally oblique, have formed a
					bed under a considerable portion of the hip, and because the extremity of the
					foot is not forcibly turned outward, but is nearly in a line with the body, and
					is even inclined more inwardly. When, then, the articular extremity of the femur
					has worn out a socket for itself in the flesh where it was lodged, and the flesh
					is lubricated, it ceases to be painful in the course of time, and when it
					becomes free from pain, they can walk without a staff, if so inclined, and they
					can support the body on the injured limb. From usage then, in such cases, the
					fleshy parts are less enervated than in those which have been mentioned a little
					before, still, however, they lose their strength more or less; but in general
					there is more enervation when the dislocation is inward than when it is outward.
					Some of them, then, cannot wear their shoes, owing to the unbending state of
					their leg, and some of them can. But when this dislocation takes place <hi
						rend="ital">in utero</hi>, and when the dislocation having occurred at any
					time before manhood, from violence, has not been replaced, or when from disease
					the articular extremity has started from its socket, and is displaced (for many
					such cases occur, and from some of them, if the femur become necrosed, obstinate
					suppurations requiring the use of tents are formed, and in certain of them the
					bone is laid bare), whether the bone become necrosed or not, the bone of the
					thigh is much shortened, and does not usually grow like the sound one, the
					bones, too, of the leg, become shorter than those <pb n="p.255"/>of the other,
					but in a small degree, for the same reasons that were formerly stated; such
					persons can walk, some of them in the same fashion as adults having an unreduced
					dislocation, and some of them walk with the whole foot on the ground, but limp
					in walking, being obliged to do so by the shortness of the limb. Such is the
					result, even though they be carefully and properly trained in the attitudes
					before they have strength for walking, and in like manner also, after they have
					acquired the necessary strength; but those persons require the most care who
					were very young when they met with the accident, for, if neglected while
					children, the limb becomes entirely useless and atrophied. The fleshy parts of
					the entire limb are more wasted than those of the sound limb, but this is much
					less apt to happen in their case than in dislocation inward, owing to usage and
					exercise, as they are speedily able to make use of the limb, as was stated a
					little before with regard to the weasel-armed (<hi rend="ital"
					>galiancones</hi>).</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="56">
				<head>Part 56</head>
				<p> There are persons who, from birth or from disease, have dislocations outward of
					both the thighs; in them, then, the bones are affected in like manner, but the
					fleshy parts in their case lose their strength less; the legs, too, are plump
					and fleshy, except that there is some little deficiency at the inside, and they
					are plump because they have the equal use of both their legs, for in walking
					they totter equally to this side that. Their nates appear very prominent, from
					the displacement of the bones of the joint. But if in their case the bones do
					not sphacelate (<hi rend="ital">become carious?</hi>) and if they do not become
					bent above the hip-joint, if nothing of this kind happen to them, they become
					otherwise sufficiently healthy, but the growth of all the rest of the body, with
					the exception of the head, is arrested. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="57">
				<head>Part 57</head>
				<p> In dislocations of the head of the femur backward, which rarely occur, the
					patient cannot extend the leg, either at the dislocated joint, or at the ham, to
					any extent, and of all the dislocations, this is the variety in which the
					patients have the least power of making extension at the groin and the ham. But,
					moreover, this also should be known (for it is a valuable piece of knowledge,
					and of much importance, and yet most yet most people are ignorant of it), that
					persons in health cannot extend the joint <pb n="p.256"/>at the ham, if they do
					not extend the joint at the groin at the same time, unless they raise the foot
					very high, for in this way they could do it; neither also could they bend the
					joint at the ham, but with much greater difficulty, if they do not bend the
					joint at the groin at the same time. There are many other things in the body
					which have similar connections, both with regard to the contractions of nerves
						(<hi rend="ital">ligaments?</hi>), and the positions of muscles, and many of
					them more worthy of being known than is generally supposed, and with regard to
					the nature of the intestine and that of the whole internal cavity, and with
					regard to the displacements and contractions of the uterus; but all these things
					will be treated of elsewhere, in a work akin to the present one. But with regard
					to the matter on hand, they cannot make extension, as has been already stated;
					and the limb appears shortened, for two reasons-first, because it cannot be
					extended, and also because the bone has slipped into the flesh of the nates; for
					the head and neck of the femur, in this dislocation, are carried downward from
					their natural situation, to the outside of the nates. But yet they can bend the
					limb, unless prevented by pain, and the leg and foot appear pretty straight, and
					not much inclined toward either side, but at the groin the flesh, when felt,
					appears looser, from the bone of the joint having slipped to the other side, but
					at the nates the head of the femur may be felt to be more prominent than
					natural. Such are the symptoms accompanying dislocation of the thigh backward.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="58">
				<head>Part 58</head>
				<p> When this dislocation occurs in an adult, and is not reduced, he can walk,
					indeed, after a time, and when the pain has abated, and when he has been
					accustomed to rotate the articular bone in the flesh; he finds it necessary,
					however, to make strong flexion at the groin in walking, for two reasons, both
					because the limb, for the causes already stated, becomes much shorter, and he is
					far from touching the ground with his heel, and he can barely reach it with the
					ball of his foot, and not even thus, unless he bend himself at the groins, and
					also bend with the other leg at the ham. And in this case, he is under the
					necessity of supporting the upper part of the thigh with his hand at each step:
					this also contributes, in a certain degree, to make him bend the body <pb
						n="p.257"/>at the groins; for, during the shifting of the feet in walking,
					the body cannot be supported on the unsound be supported on the unsound limb,
					unless it be pressed to the ground by the hand,-the end of the femur not being
					placed properly under the body, but having slipped backward to the nates; and if
					he should try to rest the weight of his body for a little, upon the foot,
					without any other support, he would fall backward, for there would be a great
					inclination in this direction, from the hips having protruded backward far
					beyond the line of the foot, and the spine inclining toward the hips. Such
					persons can walk, indeed, without a staff, if so accustomed, for because the
					sole of the foot is in its old line, and is not inclined outward, they do not
					require anything to balance them. Such, however, as, instead of grasping the
					thigh, prefer resting their weight upon a staff introduced into the armpit of
					the affected side, these, if they use a longer staff, will walk, indeed, more
					erect, but will not be able to reach the ground with the foot, or if they wish
					to rest upon the foot, they must take a shorter staff, and will require to bend
					the body at the groins. The wasting of the fleshy parts is analogous to what
					happens in the cases formerly described, for the wasting is greatest in those
					cases in which the patients keep the limb up, and do not exercise it, whilst
					those who practice walking, have the least atrophy. The sound leg, however, is
					not benefited, but is rather rendered more deformed, if the injured limb be
					applied to the ground, for it is forced to cooperate with the other, being
					protruded at the hip, and bent at the ham. But if the patient does not use the
					injured limb by applying it to the ground, but carries it up, and rests upon a
					staff, the sound leg thereby gains strength, for it is employed in its natural
					position, and further, the exercise gives it strength. But it may be said, these
					things are foreign to medicine; for what is the use of enlarging upon cases
					which are already past remedy? This is far from being the case, for it belongs
					to the knowledge of medicine to be acquainted also with these, and they cannot
					possibly be separated from one another; for to such as are curable, means are to
					be used to prevent them from becoming incurable, studying how they may best be
					prevented from getting into an incurable state. And incurable cases should be
					known, that they <pb n="p.258"/>may not be aggravated by useless applications,
					and splendid and creditable prognostics are made by knowing where, how, and when
					every case will terminate, and whether it will be converted into a curable or an
					incurable disease. When then, from birth, or during one's youth, this
					dislocation backward occurs, and is not reduced, whether it be connected with
					violence or disease (for many such dislocations occur in diseases, but the
					nature of the diseases in which dislocations take place, will be described
					afterward); if, then, the dislocated limb be not reduced, the bone of the thigh
					becomes shortened, the whole limb is impaired, is arrested in its growth, and
					loses its flesh from want of use; the articulation at the ham is also impaired,
					for the nerves (<hi rend="ital">ligaments?</hi>) become stretched, from cases
					formerly stated, wherefore those who have this dislocation, cannot make
					extension at the knee-joint. In a word, all parts of the body which were made
					for active use, if moderately used and exercised at the labor to which they are
					habituated, become healthy, increase in bulk, and bear their age well, but when
					not used, and when left without exercise, they become diseased, their growth is
					arrested, and they soon become old. Among these parts the joints and nerves (<hi
						rend="ital">ligaments?</hi>), if not used, are not the least liable to be so
					affected; they are impaired, then, for the reasons we have stated, more in this
					variety of dislocation than in the others, for the whole limb is wasted, both in
					its bones and in its fleshy parts. Such persons, then, when they attain their
					full growth, keep the limb raised and flexed, rest the weight of the body on the
					other leg, and support themselves with a staff, some with one, and others with
					two.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="59">
				<head>Part 59</head>
				<p> In dislocations of the head of the thigh-bone forward (they are of rare
					occurrence), the patients cannot extend the leg completely, but least of all can
					they bend it at the groin; they are pained, also, if forced to bend the limb at
					the ham. The length of the leg, if compared at the heel, is the same as that of
					the other; but the extremity of the foot inclines less to project forward. But
					the whole limb has its natural direction, and inclines neither to this side nor
					to that. These cases are particularly attended with severe pain, and they are
					more apt to be accompanied with retention of urine at first than any of the
					other <pb n="p.259"/>dislocations; for the head of the thigh-bone is lodged very
					near to important nerves. And the region of the groin appears swelled out and
					stretched, while that of the nates is more wrinkled and flabby. The symptoms now
					stated are those which attend this dislocation of the thigh-bone.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="60">
				<head>Part 60</head>
				<p> When persons have attained their full growth before meeting with this
					dislocation, and when it has not been reduced, upon the subsidence of the pain,
					and when the bone of the joint has been accustomed to be rotated in the place
					where it is lodged, these persons can walk almost erect without a staff, and
					with the injured leg almost quite straight, as it does not admit of easy flexion
					at the groin and the ham; owing, then, to this want of flexion at the groin,
					they keep the limb more straight in walking than they do the sound one. And
					sometimes they drag the foot along the ground, as not being able to bend the
					upper part of the limb, and they walk with the whole foot on the ground; for in
					walking they rest no less on the heel than on the fore part of the foot; and if
					they could take great steps, they would rest entirely on the heel in walking;
					for persons whose limbs are sound, the greater the steps they take in walking,
					rest so much the more on the heel, while they are putting down the one foot and
					raising the opposite. In this form of dislocation, persons rest their weight
					more on the heel than on the anterior part of the foot, for the fore part of the
					foot cannot be bent forward equally well when the rest of the limb is extended
					as when it is in a state of flexion; neither, again, can the foot be arched to
					the same degree the limb is bent as when it is extended. The natural state of
					matters is such as has been now described; and in an unreduced dislocation,
					persons walk in the manner described, for the reasons which have been stated.
					The limb, moreover, is less fleshy than the other, at the nates, the calf of the
					leg, and the whole of its posterior part. When this dislocation occurs in
					infancy, and is not reduced, or when it is congenital, in these cases the bone
					of the thigh is more atrophied than those of the leg and foot; but the atrophy
					of the thigh-bone is least of all in this form of dislocation. The fleshy parts,
					however, are everywhere attenuated, more especially behind, as has been stated
					above. If properly trained, <pb n="p.260"/>such persons, when they grow up, can
					use the limb, which is only a little shorter than the other, and yet they
					support themselves on a staff at the affected side. For, not being able to use
					properly the ball of the foot without the heel, nor to put it down as some can
					in the other varieties of dislocation (the cause of which has been just now
					stated), on this account they require a staff. But those who are neglected, and
					are not in the practice of putting their foot to the ground, but keep the limb
					up, have the bones more atrophied than those who use the limb; and, at the
					articulations, the limb is more maimed in the direct line than in the other
					forms of dislocation. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="61">
				<head>Part 61</head>
				<p> In a word, luxations and subluxations take place in different degrees, being
					sometimes greater and sometimes less; and those cases in which the bone has
					slipped or been displaced to a much greater extent, are in general more
					difficult to rectify than otherwise; and if not reduced, such cases have greater
					and more striking impairment and lesion of the bones, fleshy parts, and
					attitudes; but when the bone has slipped, or been displaced to a less extent, it
					is easier to reduce such cases than the other; and if the attempts at reduction
					have failed, or have been neglected, the impairment in such cases is less, and
					proves less injurious than in the cases just mentioned. The other joints present
					great differences as to the extent of the displacements which they are subject
					to. But the heads of the femur and humerus are very similar to one another as to
					their dislocations. For the heads of the bones are rounded and smooth, and the
					sockets which receive the heads are also circular, and adapted to the heads;
					they do not admit then of being dislocated in any intermediate degree, but, not
					withstanding, from their rounded shape, the bones slip either outward or inward.
					In the case we are now treating of, then, there is either a complete dislocation
					or none at all, and yet these bones admit of being displaced to a greater or
					less extent; and the thigh is more subject to these differences than the arm.
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="62">
				<head>Part 62</head>
				<p> Wherefore, then, some of these congenital displacements, if to a small extent,
					may be reduced to their natural condition, and especially those at the
					ankle-joint. Most cases of congenital club-foot are remediable, unless the
					declination be very great, <pb n="p.261"/>or when the affection occurs at an
					advanced period of youth. The best plan, then, is to treat such cases at as
					early a period as possible, before the deficiency of the bones of the foot is
					very great, and before there is any great wasting of the flesh of the leg. There
					is more than one variety of club-foot, the most of them being not complete
					dislocations, but impairments connected with the habitual maintenance of the
					limb in a certain position. In conducting the treatment, attention must be paid
					to the following points: to push back and rectify the bone of the leg at the
					ankle from without inward, and to make counter-pressure on the bone of the heel
					in an outward direction, so as to bring it bring it into line, in order that the
					displaced bones may meet at the middle and side of the foot; and the mass of the
					toes, with the great toe, are to be inclined inward, and retained so; and the
					parts are to be secured, with cerate containing a full proportion of resin, with
					compresses, and soft bandages insufficient quantity, but not applied too tight;
					and the turns of the bandages should be in the same direction as the rectifying
					of the foot with the hand, so that the foot may appear to incline a little
					outward. And a sole made of leather not very hard, or of lead, is to be bound
					on, and it is not to be applied to the skin but when you are about to make the
					last turns of the bandages. And when it is all bandaged, you must attach the end
					of one of the bandages that are used to the bandages applied to the inferior
					part of the foot on the line of the little toe; and then this bandage is to be
					rolled upward in what is considered to be a sufficient degree, to above the calf
					of the leg, so that it may remain firm when thus arranged. In a word, as if
					moulding a wax model, you must bring to their natural position the parts which
					were abnormally displaced and contracted together, so rectifying them with your
					hands, and with the bandaging in like manner, as to bring them into their
					position, not by force, but gently; and the bandages are to be stitched so as to
					suit the position in which the limb is to be placed, for different modes of the
					deformity require different positions. And a small shoe made of lead is to be
					bound on externally to the bandaging, having the same shape as the Chian
					slippers had. But there is no necessity for it if the parts be properly adjusted
						<pb n="p.262"/>with the hands, properly secured with the bandages, and
					properly disposed of afterward. This, then, is the mode of cure, and it neither
					requires cutting, burning, nor any other complex means, for such cases yield
					sooner to treatment than one would believe. However, they are to be fairly
					mastered only by time, and not until the body has grown up in the natural shape;
					when recourse is had to a shoe, the most suitable are the buskins, which derive
					their name from being used in traveling through mud; for this sort of shoe does
					not yield to the foot, but the foot yields to it. A shoe shaped like the Cretan
					is also suitable. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="63">
				<head>Part 63</head>
				<p> In cases of complete dislocation at the ankle-joint, complicated with an
					external wound, whether the displacement be inward or outward, you are not to
					reduce the parts, but let any other physician reduce them if he choose. For this
					you should know for certain, that the patient will die if the parts are allowed
					to remain reduced, and that he will not survive more than a few days, for few of
					them pass the seventh day, being cut off by convulsions, and sometimes the leg
					and foot are seized with gangrene. It should be well known that such will be the
					results; and it does not appear to me that hellebore will do any good, though
					administered the same day, and the draught repeated, and yet it is the most
					likely means, if any such there be; but I am of opinion that not even it will be
					of service. But if not reduced, nor any attempts at first made to reduce them,
					most of such cases recover. The leg and foot are to be arranged as the patient
					wishes, only they must not be put in a dependent position, nor moved about; and
					they are to be treated with pitched cerate, a few compresses dipped in wine, and
					not very cold, for cold in such cases induces convulsions; the leaves also of
					beet, or of colt's foot, of any such, when boiled in dark-colored austere wine,
					form a suitable application to the wound and the surrounding parts; and the
					wound may further be anointed with cerate in a tepid state. But if it be the
					winter season, the part is to be covered with unscoured wool, which is to be
					sprinkled from above with tepid wine and oil, but on no account is either
					bandage or compress to be applied; for this should be known most especially,
					that whatever compresses, or is heavy, does mischief in such cases. And certain
					of <pb n="p.263"/>the dressings used to recent wounds are suitable in such
					cases; and wool may be laid upon the sore, and sprinkled with wine, and allowed
					to remain for a considerable time; but those dressings for recent wounds which
					only last for a few days, and into which resin enters as an ingredient, do not
					agree with them; for the cleansing of the sores is a slow process, and the sore
					has a copious discharge for a long time. Certain of these cases it may be
					advantageous to bandage. It ought also to be well understood, that the patient
					must necessarily be much maimed and deformed, for the foot is retracted outward,
					and the bones which have been displaced outward protrude: these bones, in fact,
					not being generally laid bare, unless to a small extent; neither do they
					exfoliate, but they heal by thin and feeble cicatrices, provided the patient
					keeps quiet for a length of time; but otherwise there is danger that a small
					ulcer may remain incurable. And yet in the case we are treating of, those who
					are thus treated are saved; whereas, when the parts are reduced and allowed to
					remain in place, the patients die. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="64">
				<head>Part 64</head>
				<p> The same rule applies to dislocations at the wrist, attended with a wound and
					projection of the bone, whether the bones of the arm be displaced inward or
					outward. For this should be well understood, that the patient will die in the
					course of a few days, by the same mode of death as formerly described, if the
					bone be reduced, and allowed to remain so. But in those cases in which they are
					not reduced, nor any attempt made to reduce them, the patients, for the most
					part, recover; and the same mode of treatment as has been described will be
					applicable; but the deformity and impediment of the limb must necessarily be
					great, and the fingers of the hand will be weak and useless; for if the bones
					have slipped inward, they cannot bend the fingers, or if outward, they cannot
					extend them. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="65">
				<head>Part 65</head>
				<p> When the os tibiae, having made a wound at the knee, has protruded through the
					skin, whether the dislocation be outward or inward, in such a case, if the bone
					be reduced, death will be even more speedy than in the other cases, although
					speedy also in them. But the only hope of recovery is if you treat them without
					reduction. These cases are more dangerous than the others, <pb n="p.264"/>as
					being so much higher up, as being so much stronger joints, and displaced from
					bones which are so much stronger. But if the os femoris form a wound at the
					knee, and slip through it, provided it be reduced and left so, it will occasion
					a still more violent and speedy death than in the cases formerly described; but
					if not reduced, it will be much more dangerous than those cases mentioned
					before, and yet this is the only hope of recovery. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="66">
				<head>Part 66</head>
				<p> The same rule applies to the elbow-joint, and with regard to the bones of the
					fore-arm and arm. For when these bones protrude through a wound which they have
					made in the skin, all cases in which they are reduced prove fatal; but if not
					reduced, there is a chance of recovery; but to those that survive there is
					certain impediment. And if in any instance the bones of the upper articulations
						(<hi rend="ital">shoulder-joint?</hi>), should be dislocated, and project
					through a wound which they have made in the skin, these, if reduced, are
					followed by more speedy death; and if not reduced, they are more dangerous than
					the others. But the mode of treatment which appears to me most suitable has been
					already described. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="67">
				<head>Part 67</head>
				<p> When the joints of the toes or hands are dislocated, and the bones protrude
					through a wound which they have made, and when there is no fracture of the bone,
					but merely displacement of the joint, in these cases, if the reduction be made
					and allowed to remain, there is some danger of spasms (<hi rend="ital"
						>tetanus?</hi>) if not properly treated, and yet it may be worth while to
					reduce them, having warned the patient beforehand that much caution and care
					will be required. The easiest, the most efficient method, and the one most
					conformable to art, is that by the lever, as formerly described when treating of
					bones which have been fractured and protruded; then the patient must be as quiet
					as possible, lie in a recumbent position, and observe a restricted regimen. And
					it will be better also that he should get some gentle emetics. The sore is to be
					treated with dressings for fresh wounds, which permit of allusions, or with the
					leaves of camomile, or with the applications for fractured bones of the head,
					but nothing very cold must be applied. The first (<hi rend="ital">most
						distant?</hi>) joints are least dangerous, but those still higher, are more
					so. <pb n="p.265"/>Reduction should be made the same day, or the next, but by no
					means on the third or fourth, for it is on the fourth day that exacerbations
					especially attack. In those cases, then, where immediate reduction cannot be
					accomplished, we must wait until after the aforesaid days; for whatever you
					reduce within ten days, may be expected to induce spasm. But if the spasm
					supervene on its being reduced, the joint should be quickly displaced, and
					bathed frequently with warm water, and the whole body should be kept in a warm,
					soft, and easy condition, and more especially about the joints, for the whole
					body should rather be in a bent than in an extended state. Moreover, it is to be
					expected, that the articular extremities of the bones of the fingers will for
					this generally happens, if even the least degree of inflammation take place, so
					that if it were not that the physician would be exposed to censure, owing to the
					ignorance of the common people, no reduction should be made at all. The
					reduction of the bones of joints which have protruded through the skin, is
					attended with the dangers which have been described. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="68">
				<head>Part 68</head>
				<p> When the articular bones of the fingers are fairly chopped off, these cases are
					mostly unattended with danger, unless deliquium come on in consequence of the
					injury, and ordinary treatment will be sufficient to such sores. But when
					resection is made, not at the articulations, but at some other point in the
					bones, these cases also are free from danger, and are still more easily cured
					than the others; and the fractured bones of the fingers which protrude otherwise
					than at the joint admit of reduction without danger. Complete resections of
					bones at the joints, whether the foot, the hand, the leg, the ankle, the
					forearm, the wrist, for the most part, are not unattended with danger, unless
					one be cut off at once by deliquium animi, or if continual fever supervene on
					the fourth day. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="69">
				<head>Part 69</head>
				<p> With regard to the sphacelus of fleshy parts, it takes place in wounds where
					there are large blood-vessels, which have been strongly compressed, and in
					fractures of bones which have been bound too tight, and in other cases of
					immoderate constriction, when the parts which have been strangulated generally
					drop off; and the most of such patients recover, even when a portion of the <pb
						n="p.266"/>thigh comes away, or of the arm, both bones and flesh, but less
					so in this case; and when the fore-arm and leg drop off, the patients readily
					recover. In cases then, of fracture of the bones, when strangulation and
					blackening of the parts take place at first, the separation of the dead and
					living parts quickly occurs, and the parts speedily drop off, as the bones have
					already given way; but when the blackening (<hi rend="ital">mortification</hi>)
					takes place while the bones are entire, the fleshy parts, in this case, also
					quickly die, but the bones are slow in separating at the boundary of the
					blackening, and where the bones are laid bare. Those parts of the body which are
					below the boundaries of the blackening are to be removed at the joint, as soon
					as they are fairly dead and have lost their sensibility; care being taken not to
					wound any living part; for if the part which is cut off give pain, and if it
					prove not to be quite dead, there is great danger lest the patient may swoon
					away from the pain, and such swoonings often are immediately fatal. I have known
					the thigh-bones, when denuded in this manner, drop off on the eightieth day; but
					in the case of this patient, the parts below were separated at the knee on the
					twentieth day, and, as I thought, too early, for it appeared to me that this
					should be done more guardedly. In a case which I had of such blackening in the
					leg, the bones of the leg, as far as they were denuded, separated at its middle
					on the sixtieth day. But the separation of denuded bones is quicker or slower,
					according to the mode of treatment; something, too, depends upon whether the
					compression be stronger or weaker, and whether the nerves, flesh, arteries, and
					veins are quicker or slower in becoming blackened and in dying; since, when the
					parts are not strongly compressed, the separation is more superficial, and does
					not go the length of laying the bones bare, and in some cases it is still more
					superficial, so as not even to expose the nerves. For the reasons now stated, it
					is impossible to define accurately the time at which each of these cases will
					terminate. The treatment of such cases, however, is to be readily undertaken,
					for they are more formidable to look at than to treat; and a mild treatment is
					sufficient in all such cases, for they come to a crisis of themselves; only the
					diet must be attended to, so that it may be as little <pb n="p.267"/>calculated
					to create fever as possible, and the body is to be placed in the proper
					positions: these are, neither raised very high up, nor inclined much downward,
					but rather upward, until the separation be completed; for at that time there is
					most danger of hemorrhage; on this account, wounds should not be laid in a
					declining position, but the contrary. But after a while, and when the sores have
					become clean, the same positions will no longer be appropriate; but a straight
					position, and one inclining downward, may be proper; and in the course of time,
					in some of these cases, abscesses form, and require bandages. One may also
					expect that such patients will be attacked with dysentery; for dysentery usually
					supervenes in cases of mortification and of hemorrhage from wounds; it comes on
					generally when the blackening and hemorrhage have arrived at a crisis, and is
					profuse and intense, but does not last many days; neither is it of a fatal
					nature, for such patients do not usually lose their appetite, nor is it proper
					to put them on a restricted diet. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="70">
				<head>Part 70</head>
				<p> Dislocation inward at the hip-joint is to be reduced in the following manner:
					(it is a good, proper, and natural mode of reduction, and has something of
					display in it, if any one takes delight in such ostentatious modes of
					procedure). The patient is to be suspended by the feet from a cross-beam with a
					strong, soft, and broad cord; the feet are to be about four inches or less from
					one another; and a broad and soft leather collar connected with the cross-beam
					is to be put on above the knees; and the affected leg should be so extended as
					to moved be two inches longer than the other; the head should be about two
					cubits from the ground, or a little more or less; and the arms should be
					stretched along the sides, and bound with something soft; all these preparations
					should be made while he is lying on his back, so that he may be suspended for as
					short a time as possible. But when the patient is suspended, a person properly
					instructed and not weak, having introduced his arm between his thighs, is to
					place his fore-arm between the perineum and the dislocated head of the os
					femoris; and then, having joined the other hand to the one thus passed through
					the thighs, he is to stand by the side of the suspended patient, and suddenly
					suspend and swing himself in the air as <pb n="p.268"/>perpendicularly as
					possible. This method comprises all the conditions which are natural; for the
					body being suspended by its weight, produces extension, and the person suspended
					from him, along with the extension, forces the head of the thigh-bone to rise up
					above the acetabulum; and at the same time he uses the bone of the fore-arm as a
					lever, and forces the os femoris to slip into its old seat. The cords should be
					properly prepared, and care should be taken that the person suspended along with
					the patient have a sufficiently strong hold. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="71">
				<head>Part 71</head>
				<p> Wherefore, as formerly stated, men's constitutions differ much from one another
					as to the facility or difficulty with which dislocations are reduced; and the
					cause of this was also stated formerly in treating of the shoulder. In some the
					thigh is reduced with no preparation, with slight extension, directed by the
					hands, and with slight movement; and in some the reduction is effected by
					bending the limb at the joint, and making rotation. But much more frequently it
					does not yield to any ordinary apparatus, and therefore one should be acquainted
					with the most powerful means which can be applied in each case, and use whatever
					maybe judged most proper under all circumstances. The modes of extension have
					been described in the former parts of the work, so that one may make use of
					whatever may happen to be at hand. For, extension and counter-extension are to
					be made in the direction of the limb and the body; and if this be properly
					effected, the head of the thigh-bone will be raised above its ancient seat; and
					if thus raised, it will not be easy to prevent it from settling in its place, so
					that any ordinary impulse with the lever and adjustment will be quite
					sufficient; but some apply insufficient extension, and hence the reduction gives
					much trouble. The bands then should be fastened, not only at the foot, but also
					above the knee, so that the force of the extension may not be expended on the
					knee-joint more than upon the hip-joint. The extension in the direction of the
					foot is to be thus contrived. But the counter-extension is not only to be
					managed by means of something carried round the chest and armpits, but also by a
					long, double, strong, and supple thong applied to the perineum, and carried
					behind along the spine, and in front along the collar-bone <pb n="p.269"/>and
					fixed to the point from which counter-extension is made; and then force is to be
					so applied, by means of this extension and counter-extension, that the thong at
					the perineum may not pass over the head of the thigh-bone, but between it and
					the perineum; and during the extension one should strike the head of the femur
					with the fist, so as to drive it outward. And when the patient is raised up by
					the stretching, you should pass a hand through (<hi rend="ital">between the
						legs?</hi>) and grasp it with the other hand, so as at the same time to make
					extension, and force the dislocated limb outward; while some other person
					sitting by the knee quietly directs it inward. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="72">
				<head>Part 72</head>
				<p> It has been formerly stated by us that it will be of importance for any person
					who practices medicine in a populous city to get prepared a quadrangular board,
					about six cubits or a little more in length, and about two cubits in breadth; a
					fathom will be sufficient thickness for it; and then along it from the one end
					to the other, an excavation must be made, so that the working of the levers may
					not be higher than is proper; then at both sides we are to raise short, strong,
					and strongly-fixed posts, having axles; and in the middle of the bench five or
					six long grooves are to be scooped out about four inches distant from one
					another, three inches will be a sufficient breadth for them, and the depth in
					like manner; and although the number of grooves I have mentioned will be
					sufficient, there is nothing to prevent their being made all over the bench. And
					the bench should have in its middle a pretty deep hole, of a square shape, and
					of about three inches in size; and into this hole, when judged necessary, is to
					be adjusted a corresponding piece of wood, rounded above, which, at the proper
					time, is to be adjusted between the perineum and the head of the thigh-bone.
					This upright piece of wood prevents the body from yielding to the force dragging
					downward by the feet; for sometimes this piece of wood serves the purpose of
					counter-extension upward; and sometimes, too, when extension and
					counter-extension are made, this piece of wood, if susceptible of some motion to
					this side or that, will serve the purpose of a lever for pushing the head of the
					thigh-bone outward. It is on this account that several grooves are scooped out
					on the bench, <pb n="p.270"/>so that this piece of wood, being erected at the
					one which answers, may act as a lever, either on the sides of the articular
					heads of bones, or may make pressure direct on the heads along with the
					extension, according as it may suit to push inward or outward with the lever;
					and the lever may be either of a round or broad form, as may be judged proper;
					for sometimes the one form and sometimes the other suits with the articulation.
					This mode of applying the lever along with extension is applicable in the
					reduction of all dislocations of the thigh. In the case now on hand, a round
					lever is proper; but in dislocations outward a flat lever will be the suitable
					one. By means of such machines and of such powers, it appears to me that we need
					never fail in reducing any dislocation at a joint. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="73">
				<head>Part 73</head>
				<p> And one might find out other modes of reduction for this joint. If the large
					bench were to have raised on it two posts about a foot (<hi rend="ital">in
						diameter?</hi>), and of a suitable height, on each side near its middle, and
					if a transverse piece of wood like the step of a ladder, were inserted in the
					posts, then if the sound leg were carried through between the posts, and the
					injured limb were brought over the transverse piece of wood, which should be
					exactly adapted in height to the joint which is dislocated (and it is an easy
					matter so to adjust it, for the step of the ladder should be made a little
					higher than required, and a convenient robe, folded several times, is to be laid
					below the patient's body), then a piece of wood, of suitable breadth and length,
					is to be laid below the limb, and it should reach from the ankle to beyond the
					head of the thigh-bone, and should be bound moderately tight to the limb. Then
					the limb being extended, either by means of the pestle-like piece of wood
					(formerly described), or by any of the other methods of extension, the limb
					which is carried over the step with the piece of wood attached to it, is to be
					forced downward, while somebody grasps the patient above the hip-joint. In this
					manner the extension will carry the head of the thighbone above the acetabulum,
					while the lever power that is exercised will push the head of the thigh-bone
					into its natural seat. All the above-mentioned powers are strong, and more than
					sufficient to rectify the accident, if properly and skill-<pb n="p.271"/>fully
					applied. For, as formerly stated, in most cases reduction may be effected by
					much weaker extension, and an inferior apparatus. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="74">
				<head>Part 74</head>
				<p> If the head of the bone slip outward, extension and counter-extension must be
					made as described, or in a similar manner. But along with the extension a broad
					lever is to be used to force the bone from without inward, the lever being
					placed at the nates or a little farther up, and some person is to steady the
					patient's body, so that it may not yield, either by grasping him at the buttocks
					with his hands, or this may be effected by means of another similar lever,
					adjusted to one of the grooves, while the patient has something laid below him,
					and he is secured, and the dislocated thigh is to be turned gently from within
					outward at the knee. Suspension will not answer in this form of dislocation,
					for, in this instance, the arm of the person suspended from him, would push the
					head of the thigh-bone from the acetabulum. But one might use the piece of wood
					placed below him as a lever, in such a manner as might suit with this mode of
					dislocation; it must work from without. But what use is there for more words?
					For if the extension be well and properly done, and if the lever be properly
					used, what dislocation of the joint could occur, that might not be thus reduced?
				</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="75">
				<head>Part 75</head>
				<p> In dislocation of the thigh, backward, extension and counter-extension should be
					made as has been described; and having laid on the bench a cloth which has been
					folded several times, so that the patient may lie soft, he is to be laid on his
					face, and extension thus made, and, along with the extension, pressure is to be
					made with a board, as in the case of humpback, the board being placed on the
					region of the nates, and rather below than above the hip-joint; and the hole
					made in the wall for the board should not be direct over, but should be inclined
					a little downward, toward the feet. This mode of reduction is particularly
					appropriate to this variety of dislocation, and at the same time is very strong.
					But perhaps, instead of the board, it might be sufficient to have a person
					sitting (<hi rend="ital">on the seat of luxation?</hi>), or pressing with his
					hands, or with his foot, and suddenly raising himself up, along with the
					extension. None of the other afore-<pb n="p.272"/>mentioned modes of reduction
					are natural in this form of dislocation. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="76">
				<head>Part 76</head>
				<p> In dislocation forward, the same mode of extension should be made; but a person
					who has very strong hands, and is well trained, should place the palm of the one
					hand on the groin, and taking hold of this hand with the other, is at the same
					time to push the dislocated part downward, and at the same time to the fore part
					of the knee. This method of reduction is most especially conformable to this
					mode of dislocation. And the mode of suspension is also not far removed from
					being natural, but the person suspended should be well trained, so that his arm
					may not act as a lever upon the joint, but that the force of the suspension may
					act about the middle of the perineum, and at the os sacrum. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="77">
				<head>Part 77</head>
				<p> Reduction by the bladder is also celebrated in dislocations at this joint, and I
					have seen certain persons who, from ignorance, attempted to reduce both
					dislocations outward and backward therewith, not knowing that they were rather
					displacing than replacing the parts; it is clear, however, that he who first
					invented this method intended it for dislocation inward. It is proper, then, to
					know how the bladder should be used, if it is to be used, and it should be
					understood that many other methods are more powerful than it. The bladder should
					be placed between the thighs uninflated, so that it may be carried as far up the
					perineum as possible, and the thighs beginning at the patella are to be bound
					together with a swathe, as far up as the middle of the thigh, and then a brass
					pipe is to be introduced into one of the loose feet of the bladder, and air
					forced into it, the patient is to lie on his side with the injured limb
					uppermost. This, then, is the preparation; some, however, do the thing worse
					than as I have described, for they do not bind the thighs together to any
					extent, but only at the knees, neither do they make extension, whereas extension
					should be made, and yet some people by having the good fortune to meet with a
					favorable case, have succeeded in making reduction. But it is not a convenient
					method of applying force, for the bladder, when inflated, does not present its
					most prominent part to the articular extremity of the femur, which is the place
						<pb n="p.273"/>that ought to be more especially pressed outward, but its
					middle, which probably corresponds with the middle of the thigh, or still lower
					down, for the thighs are naturally curved, being fleshy, and in contact above,
					and becoming smaller downward, so that the natural configuration of the parts
					forces the bladder from the most proper place. And if a small bladder be
					introduced, its power will be small, and unable to overcome the resistance of
					the articular bone. But if the bladder must be used, the thighs are to be bound
					together to a considerable extent, and the bladder is to be inflated along with
					the extension of the body, and in this method of reduction both legs are to be
					bound together at their extremity. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="78">
				<head>Part 78</head>
				<p> The prime object of the physician in the whole art of medicine should be to cure
					that which is diseased; and if this can be accomplished in various ways, the
					least troublesome should be selected; for this is more becoming a good man, and
					one well skilled in the art, who does not covet popular coin of base alloy. With
					regard to the subject now on hand, the following are domestic means of making
					extension of the body, so that it is easy to choose from among the things at
					hand:-In the first place, when soft and supple thongs are not at hand for
					ligatures, either iron chains, or cords, or cables of ships, are to be wrapped
					round with scarfs or pieces of woolen rags, especially at the parts of them
					which are to be applied, and in this state they are to be used as bands. In the
					second place, the patient is to be comfortably laid on the strongest and largest
					couch that is at hand, and the feet of the couch, either those at the (<hi
						rend="ital">patient's?</hi>) head, or those at the feet, are to be fastened
					to the threshold, either within or without, as is most suitable; and a square
					piece of wood is to be laid across, and extending from the one foot to the
					other; and if this piece of wood be slender, it should be bound to the feet of
					the couch, but, not withstanding, if it be thick, there will be no necessity for
					this; then the heads of the ligatures, both of those at the head and those at
					the feet, are to be fastened to a pestle, or some such piece of wood, difficult
					to reduce at either end; the ligatures should run along the line of the body, or
					be a little elevated above it, and it should be stretched proportionally to the
					pestles, so that, standing erect, the one may be <pb n="p.274"/>fastened to the
					threshold, and the other to the transverse piece of wood. Extension is then to
					be made by bending back the ends of the pestles. A ladder, having strong steps,
					if laid below the bed, will serve the purpose of the threshold and the piece of
					wood laid along (<hi rend="ital">the foot of the couch?</hi>), as the pestles
					can be fastened to the steps at either end, and when drawn back they thus make
					extension of the ligatures. Dislocation, inward or forward, may be reduced in
					the following manner: a ladder is to be fastened in the ground, and the man is
					to be seated upon it, and then the sound leg is to be gently stretched along and
					bound to it, wherever it is found convenient; and water is to be poured into an
					earthen vessel, or stones put into a hamper and slung from the injured leg, so
					as to effect the reduction. Another mode of reduction: a cross-beam is to be
					fastened between two pillars of moderate height; and at one part of the
					cross-beam there should be a protuberance proportionate to the size of the
					nates; and having bound a coverlet round the patient's breast, he is to be
					seated on the protuberant part of the cross-beam, and afterward the breast is to
					be fastened to the pillar by some broad ligature; then some one is to hold the
					sound leg so that he may not fall off, and from the injured limb is to be
					suspended some convenient weight, as formerly described. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="79">
				<head>Part 79</head>
				<p> It should be particularly known that the union of all bones is, for the most
					part, by a head and socket (<hi rend="ital">cotyle</hi>); in some of these the
					place (<hi rend="ital">socket?</hi>) is cotyloid and oblong, and in some the
					socket is glenoid (<hi rend="ital">shallow?</hi>). In all dislocations reduction
					is to be effected, if possible, immediately, while still warm, but otherwise, as
					quickly as it can be done; for reduction will be a much easier and quicker
					process to the operator, and a much less painful one to the patient, if effected
					before swelling comes on. But all the joints when about to be reduced should be
					first softened, and gently moved about; for, thus they are more easily reduced.
					And, in all cases of reduction at joints, the patient must be put on a spare
					diet, but more especially in the case of the greatest joints, and those most
					difficult to reduce, and less so in those which are very small and easily
					reduced. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="80">
				<head>Part 80</head>
				<p> If any joint of the fingers is dislocated, whether the first, <pb n="p.275"
					/>second, or the third, the same method of reduction is to be applied, but the
					largest joints are the most difficult to reduce. There are four modes of
					displacement-either upward, downward, or to either side; most commonly upward,
					and most rarely laterally, and in consequence of violent motion. On both sides
					of its articular cavity there is a sort of raised border. When the dislocation
					is upward or downward, owing to the articular cavity having smoother edges there
					than at the sides, if the joint of it be dislocated, it is more easily reduced.
					This is the mode of reduction:-The end of the finger is to be wrapped round with
					a fillet, or something such, that, when you lay hold of it and make extension,
					it will not slip; and when this is done, some person is to grasp the arm at the
					wrist, and another is to take hold of the finger which is wrapped in the fillet,
					and then each is to make considerable extension toward himself, and at the same
					time the projecting bone is to be pushed into its place. But, if the dislocation
					be lateral, the same mode of reduction is to be used; but when you think that
					the extremity of the bone has cleared the rim, at the same time that extension
					is made, the bone is to be pushed direct into its place, while another person on
					the other side of the finger is to take care and make counter-pressure, so that
					it may not again slip out there. The twisted nooses formed from palm-shoots are
					convenient for effecting reduction, if you will make extension and
					counter-extension by holding the twisted string in the one hand and the wrist in
					the other. When reduced, you must bind the part as quickly as possible with
					bandages; these are to be very slender and waxed with cerate, neither very soft
					nor very hard, but of middle consistence; for that which is hard drops off from
					the finger, while that which is soft and liquid is melted and lost by the
					increased heat of the finger. The bandage is to be loosed on the third or fourth
					day; but on the whole, if inflamed, it is to be the more frequently loosed, and
					if otherwise, more rarely; this I say respecting all the joints. The
					articulation of a finger is restored in fourteen days. The treatment of the
					fingers and of the toes is the same. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="81">
				<head>Part 81</head>
				<p> After all reductions of joints the patient should be confined to a restricted
					diet and abstinence until the seventh day; <pb n="p.276"/>and if there be
					inflammation, the bandages are to be the more frequently loosed, but otherwise,
					less frequently, and the pained joint is to be kept constantly in a state of
					rest, and is to be laid in the most convenient position possible. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="82">
				<head>Part 82</head>
				<p> Accidents at the knee are more mild than at the elbow, from its being compact,
					regular, and elegant in its construction; and, therefore, it is more readily
					dislocated and reduced. It is most frequently dislocated inward, but also
					outward and backward. The modes of reduction are these: by flexion at the knee,
					or by sudden calcitration, or having rolled a swathe into a ball, and fixed it
					in the ham, the patient's body is to be suddenly dropped on its bended knees.
					Dislocation backward, also, as in the case of the elbow, may be reduced by
					moderate extension, and to either side, either by flexion or calcitration, but
					also by moderate extension. The adjustment is the same in all cases. In
					dislocations backward which are not reduced, the patient cannot bend the joint,
					but neither can he, to any great extent, in the other varieties; the thigh and
					leg are wasted in front; but if inward the patients become bow-legged, and the
					external parts are wasted; but if outward they become more bandy-legged, but the
					impediment is less, for the body is supported on the larger of the bones, and
					the inner parts are wasted. When these accidents happen at birth or during
					adolescence, they follow the rule formerly stated.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="83">
				<head>Part 83</head>
				<p> Dislocations at the ankle-joints require strong extension, either with the hands
					or some such means; and adjustment, which at the same time effects both
					purposes, as is common in all cases. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="84">
				<head>Part 84</head>
				<p> Injuries of the foot are to be remedied like those of the hand.</p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="85">
				<head>Part 85</head>
				<p> The bones connected with the leg, and which are dislocated, either at birth or
					during adolescence, follow the same course as those in the hand. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="86">
				<head>Part 86</head>
				<p> When persons jumping from a height pitch on the heel, so as to occasion
					separation (<hi rend="ital">diastasis</hi>) of the bones, ecchymosis of the
					veins, and contusion of the nerves; when these symptoms are very violent there
					is danger of sphacelus, and that the case may give trouble during life, for the
					bones are so constructed as <pb n="p.277"/>to slip from one another, and the
					nerves communicate together. And, indeed, in cases of fracture, either from an
					injury in the leg or thigh, or in paralysis of the nerves (<hi rend="ital"
						>tendons?</hi>) connected with these parts, or from neglect during
					confinement to bed, when the heel gets blackened the most serious consequences
					result therefrom. Sometimes, in addition to the sphacelus, there come on acute
					fevers accompanied with hiccup, aberration of intellect, and speedy death, with
					lividities of the large blood-vessels. With regard to the symptoms attending
					exacerbations, if the ecchymosed and blackened parts and those around be
					somewhat hard and red, and if along with the hardness there be lividity,
					mortification is to be apprehended; but if the parts be slightly livid, or even
					very livid, and the swelling diffused, or if greenish and soft, these
					appearances, in such cases, are all favorable. The treatment, if no fever be
					present, consists in the administration of hellebore, but otherwise (it is not
					to be given, but <hi rend="ital">oxyglyky</hi> (<hi rend="ital">decoction of
						honeycombs and vinegar</hi>) is to be given for drink, if required.
					Bandaging as in the other articulations: above all, more especially in
					contusions, the bandages should be numerous and softer than usual, but the
					compression should be less; most turns should be made around the heel. Position,
					like the bandaging, should be so regulated as not to determine to the heel.
					Splints are not to be used. </p>
			</div>
			<div type="section" n="87">
				<head>Part 87</head>
				<p> When the foot is dislocated, either alone or along with its epiphysis, the
					displacement is, for the most part, to the inside. If not reduced, in the course
					of time, the hip, the thigh, and the side of the leg opposite the dislocation,
					become atrophied. Reduction is the same as in the wrist, but the extension
					requires to be very powerful. Treatment, agreeably to the general rule for
					joints. Exacerbations do occur, but less frequently than in dislocations at the
					wrist, provided the parts get rest. While they remain at rest the diet should be
					restricted. Those which occur at birth, or during adolescence, follow the rule
					formerly stated.<pb n="p.278"/></p>
			</div>

		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>
