<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://epidoc.stoa.org/schema/latest/tei-epidoc.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader xml:lang="eng">
<fileDesc>
<titleStmt>
<title xml:lang="eng">The Downward Journey, or the Tyrant</title>
<author>Lucian of Samosata</author>
<editor role="translator">Austin Morris Harmon</editor>
<funder>National Endowment for the Humanities</funder>
<principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
<respStmt>
<persName>Gregory Crane</persName>
<orgName>Tufts University</orgName>
<resp>Digital conversion and editing</resp>
</respStmt>
</titleStmt>
<publicationStmt>
<authority>Perseus Digital Library</authority>
<idno type="filename">tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2.xml</idno>
<availability>
<licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/4.0/">Available under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 4.0 International License</licence>
</availability>
<date>2023</date>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>United States</pubPlace>
</publicationStmt>
<sourceDesc>
<listBibl>
<biblStruct>
<monogr>
<title>Lucian</title>
<editor>
<persName>
<name>Austin Morris Harmon</name>
</persName>
</editor>
<author ref="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062">Lucian of Samosata</author>
<imprint>
<publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
<pubPlace>Cambridge, MA</pubPlace>
<date>1915</date>
</imprint>
<biblScope unit="volume">2</biblScope>
</monogr>
<ref target="https://archive.org/details/lucianhar02luciuoft/page/4/mode/2up">Internet Archive</ref>
<ref target="https://hdl.handle.net/2027/uc1.b000604154?urlappend=%3Bseq=18">The Hathi Trust</ref>
</biblStruct>
</listBibl>
</sourceDesc>
</fileDesc>
<encodingDesc>
<p>Text encoded in accordance with the latest EpiDoc standards</p>
<refsDecl n="CTS">
<cRefPattern n="section" matchPattern="(\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
<p>This pointer pattern extracts section.</p>
</cRefPattern>
</refsDecl>
</encodingDesc>
<profileDesc>
<langUsage>
<language ident="grc">Greek</language>
<language ident="lat">Latin</language>
</langUsage>
</profileDesc>
<revisionDesc>
<change/>
</revisionDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text>
<body>
<div type="translation" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" xml:lang="eng">
<head>The Downward Journey, or the Tyrant<note xml:lang="eng"><p>A scene in the realm of Hades, showing that cobblers fare
better there than kings. The lower world is depicted also in
the Menippus and in the Dialogues of the Dead. All these
pleces were deeply influenced by Cynic satire and in particular by the Necyia of Menippus. Helm maintains that the
Downward Journey is based on a couple of scenes in the
Necyia which Lucian left unused in writing his Menippus
and subsequently worked up into a separate dialogue, prefixing an introduction of his own; but there is hardly
enough evidence to make this theory plausible, lect alone
incontestable.</p>
<p>The part played by the Fates is unusual. Instead of
Spinning destinies up aloft as in the Charon, two of them are
given a share in the convoying of souls to the underworld,Atropos turning them over to Hermes and C lotho presiding
over their reception at the ferry. Clotho’s function thus in
great measure duplicates that assigned to Aeacus.</p></note></head>
<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="1"><p>

<label>CHARON</label>
Well, Clotho, we have had this boat all ship-shape
and thoroughly ready to sail for some time. The
water is baled out, the mast is set up, the sail is
hoisted in stops and each of the oars has a lanyard to
it, so that as far as I am concerned there is nothing
to hinder our getting up anchor and sailing. But
Hermes is behind hand; he should have been here
long ago. There is not a passenger aboard the ferryboat, as you see, when she might have made three
trips to-day by this time, and here it is almost dusk
and I haven’t earned even an obol yet. Besides,
Pluto will surely think I am taking it easy all this
time, when really someone else is to blame. Our
honourable guide of souls<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.3.n.1">Hermes.</note> has had a drink of Lethewater up there if ever a man did, and so has forgotten
to come back to us: he is either wrestling a fall with
the boys or playing a tune on the lyre or making
speeches to show off his command of piflle, or maybe
the gentleman is even playing sneak-thief, for that is
one of his accomplishments also. Anyhow, he takes

<pb n="v.2.p.5"/>

liberties with us as if he were free, when really
he is half ours.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.5.n.1">Like a slave in the upper world, Charon identifies himself with his master Pluto.</note>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="2"><p>

<label>CLOTHO</label>
But, Charon, how do you know that he hasn’t
found something to keep him busy? Zeus may have
wanted to make more use of him than usual in
affairs up above. He too is his master.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Yes, Clotho, but he has no right to go too far in
playing the master over joint property, for we
on our part have never kept Hermes back when
he had to go. No, I know the reason: here with
us there is nothing but asphodel and libations and
funeral-cakes and offerings to the dead, and all else
is misty, murky darkness ; in heaven, however, it is
all bright, and there is ambrosia in plenty and nectar
without stint, so it is likely that he finds it more
pleasant to tarry there. And when he leaves us he
flies up as if he were escaping from jail, but when it
is time to come down he comes with reluctance, at
the last moment, slowly and afoot.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="3"><p>

<label>CLOTHO</label>
Don’t be angry any longer, Charon; here he is
close by, you see, bringing us a lot of people, or I
should say waving them along with his wand, all in
a huddle, like a herd of goats. But what’s this?
There is a man in fetters among them and another
who is laughing, I see, and one fellow with a wallet
over his shoulder and a club in his hand, who has a
piercing eye and hurries the others along. Don’t
you see, too, that Hermes himself is dripping with
sweat and dusty-footed and panting? In fact, he is

<pb n="v.2.p.7"/>

gasping for breath. What’s all this, Hermes?
What’s the excitement? You seem to be in a stew,
you know.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Why, Clotho, this miserable sinner ran away and I
chased him, and so almost failed to make your boat
to-day, that’s all!
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Who is he, and what was his object in trying to
run away?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
That’s easy to see—he preferred to live! He isa
king or a tyrant, to judge from his lamentations and
the wailing that he makes, in which he makes out
that he has had great happiness taken away from
him.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
So the poor fool tried to run away, thinking that
he could live longer, when the thread of life apportioned to him had already run short?
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="4"><p>

<label>HERMES</label>
Tried to run away, do you say? Why, if this
splendid fellow, the one with the stick, had not
helped me and we had not caught and bound him, he
would have got clean away from us. You see, from
the moment Atropos turned him over to me he kept
straining and pulling back every inch of the way,
and as he braced his feet on the ground he was by
no means easy to lead; sometimes, too, he would
beg and entreat, wanting to be let go for a little
while and promising a heavy bribe. Of course I did
not let him go, for I saw that what he was after
was impossible. But when we were right by the

<pb n="v.2.p.9"/>

entrance, while I was counting the dead for Aeacus<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.9.n.1">Aeacus is the “collector of customs” (Charon 2). The idea was probably suggested by the Froys of Aristophanes, in which he figures as Pluto’s janitor (464).</note>
as usual and he was comparing them with the tally
sent him by your sister, he gave us the slip somehow
or other, curse him, and made off. Consequently we
were one dead man short in the reckoning, and
Aeacus raised his eyebrows and said : “Don’t be too
promiscuous, Hermes, in plying your thievery; be
content with your pranks in Heaven. The accounts
of the dead are carefully kept and cannot be falsified.
The tally has a thousand and four marked on it, as
you see, and you come to me with one less. You
aren’t going to say that Atropos cheated you in the
reckoning ?” What he said made me blush, but I
speedily recalled what had happened on the way,
and when, after glancing about me, I did not see
this fellow anywhere, I perceived that he had escaped
and pursued with all the speed I could muster along
the road leading toward the light. My good friend
here followed me of his own free will, and by running
as if in a match we caught him just at Taenarus:<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.9.n.2">A promontory in Laconia where the ancients located one of the entrances to Hades ; now Cape Matapan.</note>
that was all he lacked of escaping.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="5"><p>
<label>CLOTHO</label>
And we, Charon, were condemning Hermes for
neglecting his duty, indeed !
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Well, why do we keep dilly-dallying as though we
had not had delay enough already.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Right ; let them get aboard. I will hold the book
and sit by the gangway as usual, and as each of them

<pb n="v.2.p.11"/>

comes aboard I will see who he is, where he comes
from, and how he met his death ; you receive them,
and as you do so, pack and stow them. LTlermes,
heave these babies aboard first, for what in the world
can they have to say to me?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Here you are, ferryman, three hundred of them,
including those that were abandoned.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
I say, what a rich haul! It’s green-grape dead
you have brought us.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Clotho, do you want us to get the unmourned
aboard next ?
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
You mean the old people? Yes, for why should I
bother now to investigate what happened before the
food?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.11.n.1">Literally, "before Euclid,” the Athenian archon of 403 B.C., the year in which the democracy was restored and the misdeeds of the oligarchy obliterated by a general amnesty.</note> All of you who are over sixty go in now.
What’s this? They don’t heed me, for their ears are
stopped with years. You will probably have to pick
them up and carry them in, too.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Here you are again, three hundred and _ninetyeight, all tender and ripe and harvested in season.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Good Lord, yes! They’re all raisins now !
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="6"><p>
<label>CLOTHO</label>
Bring in the wounded next, Hermes. (To the
DEAD) First tell me what deaths brought you

<pb n="v.2.p.13"/>


here—but no, I myself will refer to my papers and
pass you. Eighty-four should have died in battle
yesterday in Media, among them Gobares, the son of
Oxyartas.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Here they are!
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Seven committed suicide for love, among them the
philosopher Theagenes for the courtesan from
Megara.<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.13.n.1">This man can hardly be other than the Cynic of Patras mentioned in The Passing of Peregrinus, who died in the teign of Marcus Aurelius. To be sure, Galen says he was killed by his doctor (x, p. 909), but he may well have been alive when Lucian wrote this.</note>
<label>HERMES</label>
Right here beside you.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Where are the men who killed each other fighting
for the throne?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Here they stand.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
And the man who was murdered by his wife and
her lover ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
There beside you.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Now bring in the output of the courts, I mean
those who died by the scourge and the cross. And
where are the sixteen who were killed by pirates,
Hermes ?

<pb n="v.2.p.15"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
Here they are, these wounded men whom you see.
Do you want me to bring in all the women
together ?
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
By all means, and also those lost at sea, for they
died in the same way. And those who died of the
fever, bring them in together, too, and their doctor
Agathocles along with them.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="7"><p>
Where is the philosopher Cyniscus, who was to die from eating the
dinner of Hecate and the lustral eggs and a raw
squid besides ?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.15.n.1">The dinner of Hecate (mentioned also in Dialogues of the Dead, 1) was a purificatory offering made at cross-roads and,to judge from Aristophanes (Plutus 594), very well received by the poor. For the use of eggs in purification see Ovid, Ars Amat. ii. 329; Juv. vi. 517. The raw squid is mentioned because Diogenes is said to have died from eating one (Diog. Laert. 156 ap; cf. Philosophers for Sale, 10).</note>
<label>CYNISCUS</label>
Ihave been standing at your elbow a long time,
kind Clotho. What have I done that you should leave
me on earth so long? Why, you nearly ran off your
whole spindle for me! In spite of that, I have often
tried to cut the thread and come, but somehow or
other it could not be broken.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
I left you behind to observe and prescribe for
the sins of man. But get aboard, and good luck to
you. :
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
No, by Heaven, not till we have put this man in
fetters aboard. I am afraid he may come it over you
with his entreaties.

<pb n="v.2.p.17"/>
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="8"><p>
<label>CLOTHO</label>
Come, let’s see who he is.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Megapenthes,<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.17.n.1">“Great woe.”</note> son of Lacydes, a tyrant.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Aboard with you !
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Oh no, good lady Clotho! Do let me go back to
earth for a little while. Then [ll come of my own
accord, you will find, without being summoned by
anyone.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Why is it that you want to go back ?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Let me finish my house first, for the building has
been left half-done.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Nonsense! Come, get aboard.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
It’s not much time that I ask for, Lady of Destiny ;
let me stay just this one day, till I can give my wife
directions about my money—the place where I kept
my great treasure buried.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
It is settled ; you can’t be permitted.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Then is all that gold to be lost?
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
No, it will not be lost. Be easy on that score
your cousin Megacles will get it.
<pb n="v.2.p.19"/>

<label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
What an outrage! My enemy, whom I was too
easy-going to put to death before I died ?
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
The very man ; and he will outlive you forty years
and a little more, taking over your concubines and
your clothing and all your plate.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
You are unjust, Clotho, to bestow my property on
my worst enemies.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Why, did not it formerly belong to Cydimachus,
and did not you take it over after killing him and
slaughtering his children upon him while the breath
was still in his body ?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
But it was mine now.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Well, the term of your ownership has now expired.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="9"><p>

<label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Listen, Clotho, to something that I have to say to
you in private, with nobody else listening. (Yo the
others.) You people stand aside a moment. (Yo ctoruo)
If you let me run away, I promise to give you a
thousand talents of coined gold to-day.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
What, you ridiculous creature, have you gold and
talents still on the brain ?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
And I'll give you also, if you wish, the two winebowls that I got when I put Cleocritus to death ;
they are of refined gold and weigh a hundred talents
each.

<pb n="v.2.p.21"/>


<label>CLOTHO</label>
Hale him off: it seems that he won’t go aboard
willingly.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
I call you all to witness, the town wall and the
docks remain unfinished. I could have finished them
if I had lived only five days longer.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Never mind ; someone else will build the wall.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
But this request at all events is reasonable.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
What request ?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
To live only long enough to subdue the Pisidians
and subject the Lydians to tribute, and to build
myself a huge mausoleum and inscribe on it all the
great military exploits of my life.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Why, man, you are no longer asking for this one
day, but for a stay of nearly twenty years !

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="10"><p>

<label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
But I tell you I am ready to give bail for my
speedy return. If you wish, I’ll even surrender you
my beloved as a substitute for myself.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Vile wretch! Have not you often prayed that he
night outlast you on earth?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
That was long ago, but now I perceive whawi is for
the best.

<pb n="v.2.p.23"/>

<label>CLOTHO</label>
He too will soon be here, you'll find, slain by the
new ruler.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="11"><p>
<label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Well, at all events don't refuse me this, Lady of
Destiny. ,
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
What ?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
I want to know how things will turn out after my
death.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Listen, for it will vex you all the more to know.
Midas, your slave, will have your wife ; indeed, he
has been her lover a long time.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Curse him, I set him free at her request !
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Your daughter will be enrolled among the concubines of the present tyrant, and the busts and
statues which the city long ago set up in your
honour will all be pulled down and will make everyone who looks at them laugh.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Tell meé, will none of my friends get angry at these
doings ?
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Why, what friend did you have, and how did you
make him? Don’t you know that all those who
bowed the knee and praised your every word and
deed did so either from hope or from fear, being

<pb n="v.2.p.25"/>

friends of your power, not of you, and keeping their
eyes on the main chance?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
But as they poured their libations at our drinking
parties they used to pray at the top of their voices
that many blessings might descend upon me, saying
every one of them that he was ready to die for me if
so might be ; in a word, they swore by me.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Consequently, you died after dining with one of
them yesterday : it was that last drink he gave you
that sent you down here.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Then that is why I noticed a bitter taste. But
what was his object in doing it?
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
You are asking me many questions when you ought
to get aboard.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="12"><p>
<label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
There is one thing that sticks in my throat above
all, Clotho, and on account of it I longed to slip
back again to the light of day, if only for a
moment.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
What is that? It must be something tremendous.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
As soon as Cario, my valet, saw that I was dead,
toward evening he came into the room where I lay,
having nothing to do, for nobody was doing anything,
not even guarding me, and brought in my mistress
Glycerium; they had been on good terms a long time,

<pb n="v.2.p.27"/>

Isuppose. Shutting the door, he began to make free
with her as though nobody was in the room, and
then, when he had enough of it, he gazed at me and
said: “You wretched little shrimp, you often gave
me beatings when I was not at fault.” With that he
pulled my hair and hit me in the face, and finally,
after clearing his throat raucously and spitting on
me, went away saying: “Off with you to the place
of the wicked!” I was aflame with rage, but could
not do a thing to him, for I was already stiff and
cold. And as for the wretched wench, when she
heard people approaching she smeared her eyes with
spittle as if she had been crying over me and
went away weeping and calling my name. If I
should catch them—

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="13"><p>

<label>CLOTHO</label>
Stop threatening and get aboard; it is already
time for you to make your appearance in court.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
And who will dare to pass judgement on a tyrant?
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
On a tyrant, no one, but on a dead man,
Rhadamanthus. You shall soon see him impose on
every one of you the sentence that is just and fits the
case. No more delay now!
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Make me even a common man, Lady of Destiny,
one of the poor people; make me evenaslave instead
of the king that once I was. Only let me come to
life again!

<pb n="v.2.p.29"/>

<label>CLOTHO</label>
Where is the man with the club? You take hold
of him too, Hermes, and pull him in by the leg, for
he won’t go aboard willingly.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Come along now, runaway. (Zo cuanon.) Take
this fellow, ferryman, and see here—mind you make
sure—
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
No fear! he shall be lashed to the mast.
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
But I ought to sit on the quarter-deck !
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
For what reason ?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
Because I was a tyrant, God knows, and had a
regiment of guardsmen.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Then wasn’t Cario justified in pulling your hair, if
you were such a lout? But you'll get small joy of
your tyranny if I give you a taste of my club!
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
What, will a Cyniscus make bold to shake his staff
at me? Did I not come within an ace of tricing you
up to a cross the other day because you were too
free-spoken and sharp-tongued and censorious?
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
That is why you yourself will stay triced up to
the mast.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="14"><p>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Tell me, Clotho, do you people take no account at
all of me? Is it because I am poor that I have to
get aboard last?

<pb n="v.2.p.31"/>

<label>CLOTHO</label>
And who are you ?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
The cobbler Micyllus.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
So you are aggrieved at having to wait? Don’t
you see how much the tyrant promises to give us
if we will let him go for a little while? Indeed,
it surprises me that you are not equally glad of the
delay.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Listen, kind. Lady of Destiny; I have no great
liking for such gifts as the famous one of the
Cyclops,—to be promised “T’]l eat Noman last of all.”<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.31.n.1">Odyssey 9, 369.</note>
In truth, be it first, be it last, the same teeth are in
waiting. Besides, my position is not like that of the
rich; our lives are poles apart, as the saying goes.
Take the tyrant, considered fortunate his whole life
long, feared and admired by everybody ; when he
came to leave all his gold and silver and clothing and
horses and dinners and handsome favourites and
beautiful women, no wonder he was distressed and
took it hard to be dragged away from them. Somehow or other the soul is limed, as it were, to things
like these and will not come away readily because
it has been cleaving to them long; indeed, the ties
with which such men have the misfortune to be
bound are like unbreakable fetters. Even if they
are haled away by force, they lament and entreat,
you may be sure, and although they are bold in
everything else, they prove to be cowardly in
the face of this journey to Hades. At any rate,
they turn back and, like unsuccessful lovers, want to

<pb n="v.2.p.33"/>

gaze, even from afar, at things in the world of light.
That is what yonder poor fool did, who not only ran
away on the road but heaped you with entreaties
when he got here.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="15"><p>

But as for me, having nothing at
stake in life, neither farm nor tenement nor gold
nor gear nor reputation nor statues, of course I was
in marching order, and when Atropos did but sign to
me I gladly flung away my knife and my leather (I
was working on a sandal) and sprang up at once and
followed her, barefooted as I was and without even
washing off the blacking. In fact, I led the way,
with my eyes to the fore, since there was nothing in
the rear to turn me about and call me back. And
by Heaven I see already that everything is splendid
here with you, for that all should have equal rank
and nobody be any better than his neighbour is
more than pleasant, to me at least. And I infer that
there is no dunning of debtors here and no paying of
taxes, and above all no freezing in winter or falling
ill or being thrashed by men of greater consequence.
All are at peace, and the tables are turned, for we
paupers laugh while the rich are distressed and
lament.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="16"><p>
<label>CLOTHO</label>
Indeed, I noticed some time ago that you were
laughing, Micyllus. What was it in particular that
made you laugh ?
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Listen, goddess whom I honour most. As I lived
next door to Sir Tyrant on earth, I used to see quite
distinctly what went on at his house, and I then
thought him a very god; for I held him happy when
I saw the splendour of his purple, the number of his

<pb n="v.2.p.35"/>

attendants, his plate, his jewelled goblets, and his
couches with legs of silver; besides, the savour
of the dishes prepared for his dinner drove me to
distraction. Therefore he appeared to me a superman, thrice-blessed, better looking and a full royal
eubit taller than almost anyone else; for he
was uplifted by his good fortune, walked with a
majestic gait, carried his head high and dazzled all
he met. But when he was dead, not only did he cut
an utterly ridiculous figure in my eyes on being
stripped of his pomp, but I laughed at myself even
more than at him because I had marvelled at such a
worthless creature, inferring his happiness from the
savour of his kitchen and counting him lucky because
of his purple derived from the blood of mussels in
the Laconian Sea.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="17"><p>

And he was not the only one
that I laughed at. When I saw the usurer Gnipho
groaning and regretting that he had not enjoyed his
money but had died without sampling it, abandoning
his property to that wastrel Rhodochares, who was
nextof kin to him and had the first claim on the estate
according to law, I could not control my laughter,
: especially when I called to mind how pale and
unkempt he always was, with a forehead full of
worries, feeling his riches only with the fingers with
which he reckoned up thousands and tens of thousands ashe gathered in, little by little, what was soon
to be poured out by that lucky dog Rhodochares.
But why not gonow? We can finish our laughing
during: the sail as we see them crying.

<pb n="v.2.p.37"/>

<label>CLOTHO</label>
Get aboard, so that the ferryman can haul the
anchor up.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="18"><p>

<label>CHARON</label>
Hi, fellow! Where are you going so fast? The
boat is fullalready. Wait there till to-morrow ; we'll
set you across first thing in the morning.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
You are committing a misdemeanour, Charon, in
leaving behind you a dead man who is already high.
No fear, I'll have you up before Rhadamanthus for
breaking the law. Oh, Lord! What hard luck!
They are sailing already, “and I'll be left behind
here all alone.”<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.37.n.1">The words form a trimeter in the Greek, perhaps a line of comedy.</note> But why not swim across in their
wake? I’m not afraid of giving out and drowning,
seeing that I’m already dead! Besides, I haven’t an
obol to pay my passage.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
What’s this? Wait, Micyllus; you mustn’t cross
that way.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
See here, perhaps I'll beat you to the shore.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
No, no! Come, let’s row up and take him in.
Hermes, lend a hand to pull him in.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="19"><p>
<label>CHARON</label>
Where shall he sit? The boat’s full, as you see.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
On the shoulders of the tyrant, if you like.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
A happy thought, that of Hermes !

<pb n="v.2.p.39"/>

<label>CHARON</label>
Climb up, then, and set your feet on the sinner's
neck. Let’s go on while the wind is fair.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Charon, I may as well tell you the truth here and
now. I shan’t be able to pay you your obol when
we come to land, for I have nothing more than the
wallet which you see, and this club here. However,
I am ready either to bale, if you like, or to row; you
will have no fault to find if you only give me a stout,
well-balanced oar. ,
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Pull an oar ; that will be enough to exact of you.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Shall I strike up a song, too?
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
Yes, by all means, if you know any of the sailors’
chanties,
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
I know plenty of them, Charon; but as you see,
these people are competing with our music by crying, so that we shall be put out of tune in our song.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="20"><p>


<label>THE DEAD</label>
(one) Alas, my wealth! (anoTuer) Alas, my
farms! (aNoTHER) Alackaday, what a house I left
behind me! (anotuer) To think of all the thousands
my heir will come into and squander! (aNoruer)
Ah, my new-born babes! (anorner) Who will get
the vintage of the vines I set out last year ?

<pb n="v.2.p.41"/>

<label>HERMES</label>
Micyllus, you are not lamenting at all, are you?
Nobody may cross without a tear.
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Get out with you! I have no reason to lament
while the wind is fair.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Do cry, however, even if only a little, for custom’s
sake,
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Well, I'll lament, then, since you wish it, Hermes.
—Alas, my scraps of leather! Alas, my old shoes !
Alackaday, my rotten sandals! Unlucky man that
I am, never again will I go hungry from morning to
night or wander about in winter barefooted and halfnaked, with my teeth chattering for cold! Who
is to get my knife and my awl ?
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Enough weeping ; we are almost in now.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="21"><p>

<label>CHARON</label>
Come, now, pay us your fares, all of you, the first
thing you do. (Yo micytius) You there, pay yours
too; I have it from everybody now. I say, Micyllus,
pay your obol too. °
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
You’re joking, Charon, or if not, you might as well
write in water as look for an obol from Micyllus. I
haven’t the slightest idea whether an obol is round
or square.
</p>
<p><label>CHARON</label>
What a fine, profitable cruise this has been to-day !

<pb n="v.2.p.43"/>

Ashore with you, all the same. I am going after
horses and cattle and dogs and the rest of the animals,
for they have to cross now.
</p>
<p><label>CLOTHO</label>
Take them in charge, Hermes, and lead them off.
I myself will go back to the other side to bring
over the Chinamen Indopates and Heramithras, for
they have just died fighting with one another over
boundaries.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Let’s move on, good people—or better, all follow
me in order.

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="22"><p>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Heracles, how dark it is! Where now is handsome
Megillus, and who can tell here that Simiche is not
more beautiful than Phryne? All things are alike
and of the same colour, and nothing is either beautiful
or more beautiful; indeed, even my short cloak,
which till now I thought ugly, is as good as the
purple mantle of the king, for both are invisible and
submerged in the same darkness. Cyniscus, where
in the world are you?
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Here I am, talking to you, Micyllus. Come, let’s
walk together, if you like. :
</p>
<p><label>MICYLLUS</label>
Good! Give me your hand. Tell me—for of
course you have been through the Eleusinian
Mysteries, Cyniscus—don’t you think this is like
them ?
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Right you are; indeed, here comes a woman with

<pb n="v.2.p.45"/>

a torch, who looks very fierce and threatening. Do
you suppose it is an Erinys ?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.45.n.1">The Erinyes, or Furies, were Alecto, Megaera, and Tisiphone. The torch of Tisiphone enhances the resemblance to the Mysteries, which were carried on by torch-light.</note>
<label>MICYLLUS</label>
Probably, to judge from her appearance.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="23"><p>
<label>HERMES</label>
Take these people in charge, Tisiphone, a thousand
and four.
</p>
<p><label>TISIPHONE</label>
Indeed, Rhadamanthus here has been awaiting
you this long time.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Bring them before me, Erinys. Be crier, Hermes,
and summon them by name.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Rhadamanthus, in the name of Zeus your father
I beseech you to have me up first and judge me.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
For what reason ?
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Come what may, I wish to prosecute a certain tyrant
for the wicked deeds that I know him to have done
in life, and I cannot expect to be believed when I
speak unless I first make it plain what sort of man I
am. and what sort of life I led.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Who are you?
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Cyniscus, your worship, by profession a philosopher.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Come here and be tried first. Call the plaintiffs.


<pb n="v.2.p.47"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="24"><p>


<label>HERMES</label>
If any one has charges to prefer against this man
Cyniscus, let him come this way.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
No one comes.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
But that is not enough, Cyniscus: strip yourself,
so that I can judge you from the marks on your
back.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Why, how did I ever come to be a marked man?<note xml:lang="eng" n="v.2.p.47.n.1">As orvypyartas (branded man) was applied to rogues in general, there is a slight word-play in the Greek also.</note>
<label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
For every wicked deed that each of you has done
in his life he bears an invisible mark on his soul.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Here I am naked, so seek out the marks you
mention.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
The man is altogether free from marks, except for
these three or four, very faint and uncertain. But
what is this? There are many traces and indications
of brandings, but somehow or other they have been
erased, or rather, effaced. How is that, Cyniscus,
and how is it that you looked free from them at
first ?
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
I will tell you. For a long time I was a wicked
man through ignorance and earned many marks
thereby ; but no sooner had I begun to be a philosopher than I gradually washed away all the scars
from my soul.

<pb n="v.2.p.49"/>

<label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
At any rate he made use of a cure that is sound
and very efficacious. Well, go your way to the Isles
of the Blest to live with the good, but first prosecute
the tyrant you spoke of. Hermes, summon others.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="25"><p>

<label>MICYLLUS</label>
My case also is a trifling one and needs but a short
investigation. In fact, I have been stripped and
waiting for you a long time, so inspect me.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Who are you?
</p>
<p><label>MICVLLUS</label>
The cobbler Micyllus.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Good, Micyllus, you are quite clean and unmarked.
Be off and join Cyniscus there. Call the tyrant now.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Let Megapenthes, son of Lacydes, come this way.
Where are you turning to? Come here! It is you I
am calling, tyrant. Thrust him in among us, Tisiphone, with a push on the neck.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Cyniscus, open your prosecution and state your
case now, for here is the man.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="26"><p>

<label>CYNISCUS</label>
On the whole, there is no need of words; you
will at once discover what sort of man he is from
his marks. But in spite of that I will myself unveil
the man to you and show him up more plainly. All


<pb n="v.2.p.51"/>

that the cursed scoundrel did while he was a private
citizen I intend to pass over; but when he had
leagued himself with the boldest men and had got
together a bodyguard, and so had set himself over the
city and had become tyrant, he not only put to
death more than ten thousand people without a
hearing but confiscated their properties in each case ;
and after he had made himself extremely rich, he
did not leave a single form of excess untried,
but practised every sort of savagery and high-handedness upon his miserable fellow-citizens, ravishing
maids, corrupting boys, and running amuck in every
way among his subjects. And for his superciliousness,
his pride, and his haughtiness toward all he met you
never could exact from him a fitting penalty. It
would have been less dangerous to look steadily at
the sun than at this man. Then, too, in the matter
of punishments who could describe his cruel inventiveness? Why, he did not even let his closest kin
alone! And that all this is not mere empty calumny
against him you will soon find out if you summon
up the men he murdered—but no, they are here
unsummoned, as you see, and press about him and
throttle him. All these men, Rhadamanthus, have
met their death at the scoundrel’s hands, some of
them entrapped in plots because of pretty wives,
others because they were angry on account of sons
outrageously kidnapped, others because they were
rich, and others because they were honest and decent
ind did not like his actions in the least.

<pb n="v.2.p.53"/>

</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="27"><p>
<label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
What have you to say to this, you villain ?
</p>
<p><label>MEGAPENTHES</label>
The murders which he speaks of I did commit,
but in all the rest of it—the intrigues, the outrages
against boys and the injuries to girls—in all that
Cyniscus has maligned me.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Then for that too, Rhadamanthus, I shall produce
you witnesses.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Whom do you mean?
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Hermes, please summon up his lamp and his bed,
for they will appear in person and testify to the
things that they know he has done.
</p>
<p><label>HERMES</label>
Bed and Lamp of Megapenthes, appear.
They have been so good as to comply.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Now then, tell us what you know this man
Megapenthes to have done. You speak first, Bed.
</p>
<p><label>BED</label>
All that Cyniscus has charged is true. But I am
ashamed, Rhadamanthus, my lord, to speak of these
matters, such were the deeds he did upon me.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Well, you give the clearest of testimony against
him by your very reluctance to speak of the facts.
Now, Lamp, it is your turn to testify.

<pb n="v.2.p.55"/>

<label>LAMP</label>
I did not see what happened by day, for I was
not there, and what went on at night I am loth to
say; I witnessed many things, however, that were
unspeakable and overleaped the bounds of all
outrageousness. In fact, I often tried of my own
accord to keep my wick from drinking the oil, for I
wanted to go out ; but he for his part even put me
closer to the scene and polluted my light in every
way.
</p></div>

<div type="textpart" xml:base="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0062.tlg016.perseus-eng2" subtype="section" n="28"><p>

<label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Enough witnesses ! Come, strip off your purple robe
that we may see the number of your marks. Well,
well! The fellow isall livid and crisscrossed ; indeed,
he is black and blue with marks. How can he be
punished? Shall he be thrown into the River of
Burning Fire or turned over to Cerberus ?
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
No, no! If you like, I will suggest you a punishment that is new and fits his crime.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Speak out; I shall be most grateful to you for
it.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
It is customary, I believe, for all the dead to drink
the water of Lethe?
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Certainly.
</p>
<p><label>CYNISCUS</label>
Then let this man be the only one not to drink
it.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Why, pray?

<pb n="v.2.p.57"/>

<label>CYNISCUS</label>
He will pay a bitter penalty in that way, by
remembering what he was and how much power
he had in the upper world, and reviewing his life
of luxury.
</p>
<p><label>RHADAMANTHUS</label>
Good ! Let sentence stand in that form, and let
the fellow be taken off and put in fetters near
Tantalus, to remember what he did in life.

</p></div></div>

</body></text></TEI>

