<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.stoa.org/epidoc/schema/8.19/tei-epidoc.rng"
schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title n="English Bible" type="work">World English Bible - 2 Peter</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <editor role="editor">Rainbow Missions, Inc.</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:FIPSE">Fund for the Improvement of Postsecondary Education</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <biblStruct>
                    <monogr>
                        <author>Rainbow Missions, Inc.</author>
                        <title>World English Bible</title>
                        <editor role="editor">
                            Rainbow Missions, Inc.;  revision of the American Standard Version of 1901
                        </editor>
                        <imprint>
                            <pubPlace>http://ebible.org/bible/web</pubPlace>
                        </imprint>
                    </monogr>
                </biblStruct>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc>
            <refsDecl n="CTS">
                <cRefPattern n="verse"
                    matchPattern="(\w+).(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1']/tei:div[@n='$2'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter and verse</p>
                </cRefPattern>
                <cRefPattern n="chapter"
                    matchPattern="(\w+)"
                    replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div/tei:div[@n='$1'])">
                    <p>This pointer pattern extracts chapter</p>
                </cRefPattern>
            </refsDecl>
            
            <refsDecl>
                <!--<refState delim=" " unit="book"/>-->
                <refState delim=":" unit="chapter"/>
                <refState unit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>
            
            <!--<refsDecl>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV1 N %1)" refunit="book" delim=" "/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 DIV2 N %2)" refunit="chapter" delim="."/>
                <step to="DITTO" from="DESCENDANT (1 MILESTONE N %3)" refunit="verse"/>
            </refsDecl>-->
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language ident="eng">English</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change when="2016-10-27" who="Lisa Cerrato">EpiDoc and CTS conversion</change>
            <change when="2014-08-01" who="Stella Dee">edited markup</change>
            <change when="2010-06-29" who="student">fixing place tags AD</change>
            <change when="2009-10-08" who="rsingh04">began reorganizing texts module by collection.created separate work directory in texts module to keep hopper files separate from in progress files</change>
            <change when="2009-05-27" who="rsingh04">added/fixed cvs log keyword</change>
            <change when="1999-10-14" who="Anne Mahoney">Initial markup from flat ASCII text</change>
</revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="eng">
        <body>
            <div type="edition" xml:lang="eng" n="urn:cts:greekLit:tlg0031.tlg022.perseus-eng2">
                <head>Peter's Second Letter</head>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="1">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                   
                        Simon Peter, a servant and apostle of Jesus Christ, to those
who have obtained a like precious faith with us in the righteousness of
our God and Savior, Jesus Christ:
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Grace to you and peace be
multiplied in the knowledge of God and of Jesus our Lord,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        seeing that his divine power has granted to us all things that pertain to life
and godliness, through the knowledge of him who called us by his own
glory and virtue;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        by which he has granted to us his precious and
exceedingly great promises; that through these you may become partakers
of the divine nature, having escaped from the corruption that is in the
world by lust.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        Yes, and for this very cause adding on your part
all diligence, in your faith supply moral excellence; and in moral
excellence, knowledge;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        and in knowledge, self-control; and in
self-control patience; and in patience godliness;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        and in
godliness brotherly affection; and in brotherly affection, love.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        For if these things are yours and abound, they make you to be not idle
nor unfruitful to the knowledge of our Lord Jesus Christ.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        For he
who lacks these things is blind, seeing only what is near, having
forgotten the cleansing from his old sins.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        Therefore, brothers,
be more diligent to make your calling and election sure. For if you do
these things, you will never stumble.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        For thus will be richly
supplied to you the entrance into the eternal Kingdom of our Lord and
Savior, Jesus Christ.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        Therefore I will not be negligent to remind you of these
things, though you know them, and are established in the present truth.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        I think it right, as long as I am in this tent, to stir you up
by reminding you;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        knowing that the putting off of my tent comes
swiftly, even as our Lord Jesus Christ made clear to me.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        Yes, I
will make every effort that you may always be able to remember these
things even after my departure.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        For we did not follow cunningly
devised fables, when we made known to you the power and coming of our
Lord Jesus Christ, but we were eyewitnesses of his majesty.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        For
he received from God the Father honor and glory, when the voice came to
him from the Majestic Glory, "This is my beloved Son, in whom I am well
pleased."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        This voice we heard come out of heaven when we were
with him in the holy mountain.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        We have the more sure word of prophecy; whereunto you do well
that you take heed, as to a lamp shining in a dark place, until the day
dawns, and the day star arises in your hearts:
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        knowing this
first, that no prophecy of Scripture is of private interpretation.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        For no prophecy ever came by the will of man: but holy men of
God spoke, being moved by the Holy Spirit.</p>
                    
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="2">
                

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                   
                        But there also arose false prophets among the people, as among
you also there will be false teachers, who will secretly bring in
destructive heresies, denying even the Master who bought them, bringing
on themselves swift destruction.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        Many will follow their
destructive ways, and as a result, the way of the truth will be
maligned.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        In covetousness they will exploit you with deceptive
words: whose sentence now from of old doesn't linger, and their
destruction will not slumber.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        For if God didn't spare angels when
they sinned, but cast them down to Tartarus, and committed them to pits
of darkness, to be reserved to judgment;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        and didn't spare the
ancient world, but preserved Noah with seven others, a preacher of
righteousness, when he brought a flood on the world of the ungodly;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        and turning the cities of Sodom and Gomorrah into ashes,
condemned them to destruction, having made them an example to those who
would live ungodly;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        and delivered righteous Lot, who was very
distressed by the lustful life of the wicked
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        (for that righteous
man dwelling among them, was tormented in his righteous soul from day
to day with seeing and hearing lawless deeds):
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        the Lord knows how
to deliver the godly out of temptation and to keep the unrighteous
under punishment for the day of judgment;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        but chiefly those who
walk after the flesh in the lust of defilement, and despise authority.
Daring, self-willed, they are not afraid to speak evil of dignitaries;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        whereas angels, though greater in might and power, don't bring a
railing judgment against them before the Lord.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        But these, as
unreasoning creatures, born natural animals to be taken and destroyed,
speaking evil in matters about which they are ignorant, will in their
destroying surely be destroyed,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        receiving the wages of
unrighteousness; people who count it pleasure to revel in the day-time,
spots and blemishes, reveling in their deceit while they feast with
you;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        having eyes full of adultery, and who can't cease from sin;
enticing unsettled souls; having a heart trained in greed; children of
cursing;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        forsaking the right way, they went astray, having
followed the way of Balaam the son of Beor, who loved the wages of
wrong-doing;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        but he was rebuked for his own disobedience. A mute
donkey spoke with man's voice and stopped the madness of the prophet.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        These are wells without water, clouds driven by a storm; for
whom the blackness of darkness has been reserved forever.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        For,
uttering great swelling words of emptiness, they entice in the lusts of
the flesh, by licentiousness, those who are indeed escaping from those
who live in error;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="19"><p>
                        promising them liberty, while they themselves
are bondservants of corruption; for by whom a man is overcome, by the
same is he also brought into bondage.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="20"><p>
                        For if, after they have escaped the defilement of the world
through the knowledge of the Lord and Savior Jesus Christ, they are
again entangled therein and overcome, the last state has become worse
with them than the first.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="21"><p>
                        For it would be better for them not to
have known the way of righteousness, than, after knowing it, to turn
back from the holy commandment delivered to them.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="22"><p>
                        But it has
happened to them according to the true proverb, "The dog turns to his
own vomit again," and "the sow that had washed to wallowing in the
mire."
                    </p>
                </div></div>
                <div type="textpart" subtype="chapter" n="3">
                   

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="1"><p>
                   
                        This is now, beloved, the second letter that I have written to
you; and in both of them I stir up your sincere mind by reminding you;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="2"><p>
                        that you should remember the words which were spoken before by
the holy prophets, and the commandments of us, the apostles of the Lord
and Savior:
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="3"><p>
                        knowing this first, that in the last days mockers
will come, walking after their own lusts,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="4"><p>
                        and saying, "Where is
the promise of his coming? For, from the day that the fathers fell
asleep, all things continue as they were from the beginning of the
creation."
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="5"><p>
                        For this they willfully forget, that there were
heavens from of old, and an earth formed out of water and amid water,
by the word of God;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="6"><p>
                        by which means the world that then was, being
overflowed with water, perished.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="7"><p>
                        But the heavens that now are,
and the earth, by the same word have been stored up for fire, being
reserved against the day of judgment and destruction of ungodly men.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="8"><p>
                        But don't forget this one thing, beloved, that one day is with
the Lord as a thousand years, and a thousand years as one day.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="9"><p>
                        The Lord is not slow concerning his promise, as some count slowness;
but is patient with us, not wishing that any should perish, but that
all should come to repentance.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="10"><p>
                        But the day of the Lord will come
as a thief in the night; in which the heavens will pass away with a
great noise, and the elements will be dissolved with fervent heat, and
the earth and the works that are in it will be burned up.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="11"><p>
                        Therefore since all these things are thus to be destroyed, what manner
of persons ought you to be in holy living and godliness,
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="12"><p>
                        looking
for and earnestly desiring the coming of the day of God, by reason of
which the heavens being on fire will be dissolved, and the elements
will melt with fervent heat?
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="13"><p>
                        But, according to his promise, we
look for new heavens and a new earth, in which dwells righteousness.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="14"><p>
                        Therefore, beloved, seeing that you look for these things, be
diligent to be found in peace, without blemish and blameless in his
sight.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="15"><p>
                        Regard the patience of our Lord as salvation; even as our
beloved brother Paul also, according to the wisdom given to him, wrote
to you;
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="16"><p>
                        as also in all of his letters, speaking in them of these
things. In those are some things hard to be understood, which the
ignorant and unsettled twist, as they also do to the other Scriptures,
to their own destruction.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="17"><p>
                        You therefore, beloved, knowing these
things beforehand, beware lest, being carried away with the error of
the wicked, you fall from your own steadfastness.
                        </p></div>

<div type="textpart" subtype="verse" n="18"><p>
                        But grow in
the grace and knowledge of our Lord and Savior Jesus Christ. To him be
the glory both now and forever. Amen.
                    </p>
                </div>
            </div></div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
