<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><TEI.2>
    <teiHeader type="text" status="new">
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Homeric Hymn 7 to Dionysus</title>
                <title type="sub">Machine readable text</title>
                <editor role="translator">Hugh G. Evelyn-White</editor>
                <sponsor>Perseus Project, Tufts University</sponsor>
                <principal>Gregory Crane</principal>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Prepared under the supervision of</resp>
                    <name>Lisa Cerrato</name>
                    <name>William Merrill</name>
                    <name>Elli Mylonas</name>
                    <name>David Smith</name>
                </respStmt>
                <funder n="org:AnnCPB">The Annenberg CPB/Project</funder>
            </titleStmt>
            <extent>about 159Kb</extent>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Trustees of Tufts University</publisher>
                <pubPlace>Medford, MA</pubPlace>
                <authority>Perseus Project</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <bibl>
                    <author>Anonymous</author>
                    <title>The Homeric Hymns and Homerica with an English Translation by Hugh G.
                        Evelyn-White. Homeric Hymns</title>
                    <publisher>Cambridge, MA.,Harvard University Press; London, William Heinemann
                        Ltd.</publisher>
                    <date>1914</date>
                </bibl>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
        <encodingDesc><refsDecl id="CTS">
            <cRefPattern matchPattern="(\\w+)" replacementPattern="#xpath(/tei:TEI.2/tei:text/tei:body/tei:div1[@n=\'$1\'])">
                <p>This pointer pattern extracts card</p>
            </cRefPattern>
        </refsDecl>
            <refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
                <state delim="." n="chunk" unit="hymn"/>
                <state unit="line"/>
            </refsDecl>
            <!--<refsDecl doctype="TEI.2">
	<state n="chunk" unit="card"/>
      </refsDecl>-->
        </encodingDesc>
        <profileDesc>
            <langUsage>
                <language id="en">English</language>
                <language id="greek">Greek</language>
                <language id="xgreek">Transliterated Greek</language>
            </langUsage>
        </profileDesc>
        <revisionDesc>
            <change>
                <date>1988</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>tagging</resp>
                    <name>Bill Merrill</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Text keyboarded in the Philippines. Basic SGML tagging by Bill Merrill</item>
            </change>
            <change>
                <date>8/93</date>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>ed.</resp>
                    <name>EM</name>
                </respStmt>
                <item>Go over text, check cardbreaks, and change tags to be more TEI
                    conformant.</item>
            </change>
        </revisionDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <head>To Dionysus</head>
            <div1 type="card" n="1">
                <p>
                    <milestone ed="P" n="1" unit="line"/>I will tell of Dionysus, the son of
            glorious Semele, how he appeared on a jutting headland by the shore of the
            fruitless sea, seeming like a stripling in the first flush of manhood: his
            rich, dark hair was waving about him, <milestone ed="P" n="5" unit="line"/>and on his strong shoulders he wore a purple robe. Presently there came
            swiftly over the sparkling sea Tyrsenian<note anchored="yes" resp="ed">Probably not Etruscans, but the non-Hellenic peoples of <placeName key="tgn,7002756">Thrace</placeName> and (according to
                Thucydides) of <placeName key="tgn,7011173">Lemnos</placeName> and
                <placeName key="perseus,Athens">Athens</placeName>. Cp. Herodotus i.
                57; Thucydides iv. 109.</note> pirates on a well-decked ship —a
            miserable doom led them on. When they saw him they made signs to one another
            and sprang out quickly, and seizing him straightway <milestone ed="P" n="10" unit="line"/>put him on board their ship exultingly; for they thought
            him the son of heaven-nurtured kings. They sought to bind him with rude
            bonds, but the bonds would not hold him, and the withes fell far away from
            his hands and feet: and he sat with a smile <milestone ed="P" n="15" unit="line"/>in his dark eyes. Then the helmsman understood all and
            cried out at once to his fellows and said:</p>
                <p>“Madmen! what god is this whom you have taken and bind, strong that he
            is? Not even the well-built ship can carry him. Surely this is either Zeus
            or Apollo who has the silver bow, <milestone ed="P" n="20" unit="line"/>or
            Poseidon, for he looks not like mortal men but like the gods who dwell on
            <placeName key="tgn,7011019">Olympus</placeName>. Come, then, let us set
            him free upon the dark shore at once: do not lay hands on him, lest he grow
            angry and stir up dangerous winds and heavy squalls.”</p>
                <p>
                    <milestone ed="P" n="25" unit="line"/>So said he: but the master chid him
            with taunting words: “Madman, mark the wind and help hoist sail on the
            ship: catch all the sheets. As for this fellow we men will see to him: I
            reckon he is bound for <placeName key="tgn,7016833">Egypt</placeName> or for
            <placeName key="tgn,1000112">Cyprus</placeName> or to the Hyperboreans
            or further still. But in the end <milestone ed="P" n="30" unit="line"/>he
            will speak out and tell us his friends and all his wealth and his brothers,
            now that providence has thrown him in our way.” </p>
            </div1>
            <div1 type="card" n="32">
                <p>When he had said this, he had mast and sail hoisted on the ship, and the wind
            filled the sail and the crew hauled taut the sheets on either side. But soon
            strange things were seen among them. <milestone ed="P" n="35" unit="line"/>First of all sweet, fragrant wine ran streaming throughout all the black
            ship and a heavenly smell arose, so that all the seamen were seized with
            amazement when they saw it. And all at once a vine spread out both ways
            along the top of the sail with many clusters hanging down from it,
            <milestone ed="P" n="40" unit="line"/>and a dark ivy-plant twined about
            the mast, blossoming with flowers, and with rich berries growing on it; and
            all the thole-pins were covered with garlands. When the pirates saw all
            this, then at last they bade the helmsman to put the ship to land. But the
            god changed into a dreadful lion there on the ship, <milestone ed="P" n="45" unit="line"/>in the bows, and roared loudly: amidships also he showed
            his wonders and created a shaggy bear which stood up ravening, while on the
            forepeak was the lion glaring fiercely with scowling brows. And so the
            sailors fled into the stern and crowded bemused about the right-minded
            helmsman, until suddenly the lion sprang upon the master <milestone ed="P" n="50" unit="line"/>and seized him; and when the sailors saw it they
            leapt out overboard one and all into the bright sea, escaping from a
            miserable fate, and were changed into dolphins. But on the helmsman Dionysus
            had mercy and held him back and made him altogether happy, saying to
            him:</p>
                <p>
                    <milestone ed="P" n="55" unit="line"/>“Take courage, good...; you have
            found favour with my heart. I am loud-crying Dionysus whom Cadmus' daughter
            Semele bare of union with Zeus.”</p>
                <p>Hail, child of fair-faced Semele! He who forgets you can in no wise order
            sweet song.</p>
            </div1>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI.2>